<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364872">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000982718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigation of alpha-lipoic acid supplementation in patients with schizophrenia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigation of alpha-lipoic acid supplementation on oxidative stress parameters in patients with schizophrenia </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic sindrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will evaluate the effect of alpha lipoic acid (LA) in patients with schizophrenia treated with antipsychotics drugs. In this open label, interventional study we will investigate LA effects (capsule with 500 mg LA, once day 30 min before meals for 90 days) on oxidative stress markers and antioxidative defence in patients with schizophrenia and compared to healthy controls.  We hypothesize that LA will effects on increased oxidative stress in schizophrenia, as well as improve some metabolic risk factors, that are resulting in side effects of antipsychotic use. Compliance measured through the number of returned capsules.</interventions>
    <comparator>The active healthy control group underwent
the exact same treatment (500 mg LA, once day 30 min before meals for 90 days) as the intervention group.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effects of alpha-lipoic acid supplementation on oxidative stress (plasma superoxide anion levels, serum thiobarbituric acid-reacting substances concentrations, plasma advanced oxidation protein products levels, serum total oxidative status levels, serum proxidative-antioxidative balance levels) and antioxidative defence markers : plasma (superoxide dismutase) and erythrocyte antioxidant enzyme acitivities ( superoxide dismutase, glutathione peroxidase, catalase), total glutathione concentrations in  erythrocytes, plasma total sulfhydryl groups, serum total antioxidant status, plasma PON1 actiivity</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements were done at the point of the study start, after 45 days of supplementation with LA, and after 90 days of supplementation. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effects of alpha-lipoic acid supplementation on metabolic risk factors
Anthropometric measurements: weight and height were measured  using a calibrated stadiometer and a balance beam scale , % body fat (bioimpedance analysis), waist and hip circumference were measured with a flexible tape.
Systolic and diastolic blood pressures were measured with a standard mercury sphygmomanometer
Laboratory analysis: plasma fasting glucose level and serum lipid status parameters [total cholesterol (t-C), LDL cholesterol (LDL-C), HDL cholesterol (HDL-C), triglycerides (TG)]</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements were done at the point of the study start, after 45 days of supplementation with LA, and after 90 days of supplementation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A ICD 10 diagnosis of schizophrenia
Ability to give assent
All patients on stable dose of antipsychotic drugs 
Otherwise medically stable

Inclusion criteria for healthy controls were absence of any psychiatric and somatic disease. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of substance abuse or dependence 
Several medical disorders: severe head injury, seizure disorders diabetes, cancer, renal or liver diseases, pregnancy 
Oral contraceptives, hormone replacement therapy, hypolipidemic drugs, any food supplements at least 30 days before and during the study.
Patients clinically unstable on current medication regimen
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Combination single group and parallel design study:
different groups of participants receive same interventions during the three months period</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/04/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/05/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>12/04/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Serbia and Montenegro</country>
      <state>Belgrade</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Belgrade, Faculty of Pharmacy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Vojvode Stepe 450 
11 000 Belgrade</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Serbia and Montenegro</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Belgrade
Faculty of Pharmacy
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Vojvode Stepe 450 
11 000 Belgrade</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Serbia and Montenegro</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Increasing evidence suggested that oxidative stress exists in schizophrenia. Oxidative stress also has been indicate to contribute to metabolic syndrome and related disorders, including diabetes and cardiovascular disease, which are higher prevalence in schizophrenia compared to general population. Alpha-lipoic acid is a naturally occurring compound that is synthesized in small amounts by humans. It is found in spinach, potatoes, broccoli, red meats and liver. Orally supply alpha-lipoic acid has potent antioxidant activity. Beside, quenching free radicals, there is evidence that alpha-lipoic acid lead to regeneration endogenous antioxidants such as vitamins C and E, and GSH. Alpha-lipoic acid  has been reported to has beneficial effect in many disease associated with increased oxidative stress, which could be a consequence of either increased production of free radicals or reduced antioxidant defenses.We hypothesized that LA would effects on increased oxidative stress in schizophrenia, as well as improved some metabolic risk factors, that are resulting in side effects of antipsychotic use. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethical Committee of the Clinical Centre of Serbia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Clinical Centre of Serbia,
Pasterova 2
11000 Belgrade</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/11/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Serbia and Montenegro</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bojana Vidovic</name>
      <address>University of Belgrade
Faculty of Pharmacy
Department of Bromatology
Vojvode Stepe 450, 
11221 Belgrade</address>
      <phone> +381 11 3951-395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bojana@pharmacy.bg.ac.rs</email>
      <country>Serbia and Montenegro</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bojana Vidovic</name>
      <address>University of Belgrade
Faculty of Pharmacy
Department of Bromatology
Vojvode Stepe 450, 
11221 Belgrade</address>
      <phone> +381 11 3951-395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bojana@pharmacy.bg.ac.rs</email>
      <country>Serbia and Montenegro</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bojana Vidovic</name>
      <address>University of Belgrade
Faculty of Pharmacy
Department of Bromatology
Vojvode Stepe 450, 
11221 Belgrade</address>
      <phone> +381 11 3951-395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bojana@pharmacy.bg.ac.rs</email>
      <country>Serbia and Montenegro</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bojana Vidovic</name>
      <address>University of Belgrade
Faculty of Pharmacy
Department of Bromatology
Vojvode Stepe 450, 
11221 Belgrade</address>
      <phone> +381 11 3951-395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bojana@pharmacy.bg.ac.rs</email>
      <country>Serbia and Montenegro</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>