<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82438">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000051246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimisating corticosteroid injection for lateral epicondylalgia with the addition of physiotherapy: A randomised control trial with placebo comparison.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of combining physiotherapy and corticosteroid injection in the treatment of tennis elbow: a randomised control trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PINTe</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tennis Elbow</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lateral Epicondylalgia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants in the study will be warned that pain-provoking activities should be avoided, especially if the provoked pain persists for longer than several minutes. They will also be advised that complete rest is extremely detrimental to musculoskeletal disorders and that activity that does not create pain in the elbow should be encouraged.

There will be four groups: (a) corticosteroid injection only, (b) corticosteroid injection plus physiotherapy, (c) saline injection, and (d) saline injection and physiotherapy.
 
The corticosteroid injection and physiotherapy are described here and saline below in the comparator condition.

Corticosteroid injection: This involves the placement of the corticosteroid injection into the most-tender palpable point(s) of the lateral elbow in the region of the lateral humeral epicondyle. The single injection consists of a 1 ml quantity of 1% lignocaine with 10mg of triaminolone acetonide in 1 ml. Participants will be advised to gradually return to normal activities and not to aggressively pursue return of normal activities even if they were pain free. Prior to the injection the practitioner will perform a routine clinical examination as would be regarded best clinical practice. The protocol has been previously followed in Bisset et al (2006, BMJ 333(7575): 939-41).

Physiotherapy:  Physiotherapy will be as recently evaluated by Bisset et al (2006, BMJ 333(7575): 939-41), which consists of specific elbow manipulation know as mobilisation with movement and a customized therapeutic exercise program (Vicenzino 2003 Manual Therapy 8(2): 66-79) under the guidance of a physiotherapist over 8 thirty minute sessions in 8 weeks (Vicenzino and Bisset 2007, EBM 12: 37-8). Participants are required to perform a home program of exercises and self manipulation twice daily, each session lasting approximately 20 minutes for the duration of the study.  The program will be taught by the therapist and progressed at the physiotherapy treatment sessions, as per a standardised protocol, which is based on the status of the condition and its response to the previously prescribed exercise and self manipulation. Program adherence will be facilitated by attendance at the regular therapist sessions, as well as the provision of exercise equipment (e.g., elasticised resistance exercise band(s)) and an exercise booklet.

Timing of measures:
The injection will be performed within 10 days of randomisation.  Participants receiving physiotherapy will commence their first session prior to injection and second session one week following injection, with the remaining 6 sessions completed by 8 weeks post randomisation.  Hence participants receiving injection alone will complete their treatment with 10 days, while those receiving injection with physiotherapy will complete treatment by 8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>A placebo injection comprising 0.5ml of isotonic saline (0.9%) will be injected in a similar manner to the corticosteroid injection.  The syringe will be drawn up and injected such that the patient is unable to view its contents and standardised advice will be provided as per the corticosteroid injection advice outlined above. As the therapeutically active constituent of the corticosteroid injection is unknown, it could be argued that it is ethically responsible from a community healthcare perspective to include such an injection arm in a high quality randomised clinical trial.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General improvement (6-point scale: completely recovered, much improved, improved, no change, worse, much worse)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain-free Grip Force</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-rated tennis elbow evaluation questionnaire (PRTEE)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of resting pain and worst pain and functional capacity measured on an 10cm pain visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure Pain Threshold will be measured using a Somedic algometer with 1cm2 probe size applied at a rate of 40kPa/s immediately anterior to the lateral epicondyle.  The end point of this test is when the participant willl press a button when the sensation of pressure changes to one of pressure and pain.  Triplicate measures will be performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thermal (heat and cold) Pain Threshold will be measured using a Somedic Thermotest system which will adjust the temperature of the probe applied to the lateral epicondyle region at a rate of 1-2degrees/second.  The end point of this test is when the participant first notes the sensation of pain by pressing a button.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tampa Scale of Kinesiophobia (TSK): will be administered at baseline to assess the degree of kinesiophobia, also known as fear of movement or (re)injury.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Elbow Flexion and Extension Isometric Strength will be measured in standing with the elbow positioned in 90 degrees flexion and neutral shoulder and forearm pronation/supination.  A dynamometer attached to a frame will allow measurement of force applied at the wrist during either flexion or extension (in kilograms).  Participants will be instructed to maintain upright position (no formal fixation of posture will occur).  As gripping is pain provoking in participants with lateral epicondylalgia, participants will be instructed to avoid making a fist during the test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>European Quality of Life Measurement (EuroQol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 4, 8, 12, 26 and 52 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Costs will be measured from a societal perspective by a standardised telephone interview requesting information about expenses incurred over the preceding month. Data will include including a) direct health care costs, such as visits to doctors, therapists, investigations and prescribed medication; b) direct non-health care costs, such as costs of over-the-counter medication, hours of paid and unpaid household help, transportation and other out-of-pocket expenses; c) indirect costs, such as absence from work, housekeeping and other daily activities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be contacted every three months, totaling four interviews over the 12 month period.  The first interview will be randomly allocated by computerised number generation to either 1,2 or 3 months following randomisation and subsequent interviews conducted at three monthly intervals.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Contingent valuation will be performed at baseline using a willingness to pay questionnaire and structured interview to elicit a participants' monetary valuation of a healthcare intervention, standardised by use of a hypothetical scenario.  Starting bids will be randomised according to a computerised number generation to minimise bias.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Lateral elbow pain of greater than 6 weeks duration and satisfying widely accepted
diagnostic criteria for tennis elbow: (a) pain over the lateral humeral epicondylar region, (b) pain that is provoked by gripping activities, (c) reduced grip strength, and (d) increased sensitivity to manual palpation over the lateral epicondylar region. Reproduction of pain with stretching of the forearm extensor muscles or with specific resisted static contraction of extensor carpi radialis brevis is also usually present.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i.	Bilateral elbow symptoms
ii.	Received an injection for lateral epicondylalgia (LE) within the preceding 6 months
iii.	Received a course of physiotherapy, acupuncture or massage for their LE, within the preceding 3 months  
iv.	Concomitant neck or arm pain, other than LE, that has prevented participation in usual work or recreational activities or necessitated treatment within the last 6 months. 
v.	Evidence of other primary sources of lateral elbow pain including: pain over the radiohumeral joint; exacerbation of elbow pain with neck movements or manual examination; or sensory disturbance in the affected hand
vi.	History of other specific elbow pathology including: fractures within the preceding 10years; surgery; malignancy or inflammatory or arthritic disorder 
vii.	Any medical condition which may contraindicate injection or exercise prescription
viii.	Pregnant or breastfeeding</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealed allocation by a computerised randomisation schedule developed by a central trial unit (Queensland Clinical Trial Centre).</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation schedule with stratification by baseline pain severity on Visual Analogue Scale.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A 2x2 factorial design will be used, such that the two main effects of injection and physiotherapy are combined to constitute four treatment groups.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>132</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4000 - 4170</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Bill Vicenzino</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Therapies building 84A
Therapies Rd
University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Leanne Bisset</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus 
QLD 4222</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Peter Brooks</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Executive Dean of Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Prof Luke Connelly</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Medicine, Conrod Building, The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A recent systematic review has identified an urgent need to study the long-term effects of corticosteroid injection, especially the possible deleterious ones. We have recently completed a high quality RCT with long term follow up that found poor long-term effects and very high recurrence rates following corticosteroid injection;which clearly highlights the problem to be addressed by this project. The solution to the problem, which we propose to test, is the addition to the injection treatment of a specific physiotherapy program that we have recently shown to have merit for this purpose. As well as evaluating the impact on clinical efficacy and recurrence rates of adding physiotherapy to injection we will also evaluate the economic value of adding the two treatments.  In addition the project will help provide insight into the role of medication and non-medication injection related factors (eg placebo) in treatment of tennis elbow.  The hypotheses to be tested in this study are:
I Addition of physiotherapy to an injection when compared to injection alone will: (a) improve long term efficacy, and (b) reduce the recurrence rate.
II The benefits gained by adding physiotherapy to injection outweighs the cost associated with injection alone.
III The combined corticosteroid and local anaesthetic medication are superior to that of saline.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Office of Research and Postgraduate Studies
Cumbrae-Stewart Bldg (72)
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND 
St Lucia QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007001703</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/07/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>Therapies building 84A
Therapies Rd
University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+617 3365 2275</phone>
      <fax>+617 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>Therapies building 84A
Therapies Rd
University of Queensland
St Lucia 
QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+617 3365 2275</phone>
      <fax>+617 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>Therapies building 84A
Therapies Rd
University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+617 3365 2275</phone>
      <fax>+617 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>