<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367997">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000469516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of obstetric gels on the labor process and duration in pregnant women</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of obstetric gels on the labor process and duration in pregnant women</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>vaginal birth</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All women included to the study received standard routine antepartum care in delivery room. In this context, obstetric residency trainer (medical doctor) or obstetrician (specialist) attended all the vaginal exams, all the application of the obstetric gel, all the deliveries, and episiotomy (selectively) in our institution as an educational university clinic. All the pregnant women examined vaginally at least every hour until to the end of the first stage, and than examination frequency changed depend on the labor progress in the second stage of the labor. Continue fetal monitorization was performed with tococardiograph until to the delivery. Maternal and fetal parameters were recorded on partograph during labor. All the pregnant women included and received standard antepartum care randomly assigned to either two groups at the first stage of the labor. 
Pregnant women in group A underwent a standard antepartum care plus vaginal application of the obstetric gel according to the study protocol. A specially designed sterile obstetric gel which has properties of high mucoadhesive activity, high viscosity, electric conductivity and non-allergenic was used for the study (Gynotal Obstetric  Registered Trademark). The obstetric gel is based on cross-linked polyacrylic acid, hydroxyethylcellulose and propylene glycol and is free of preservatives. The obstetric gel was intermittently applied into the vaginal canal with special applicator beginning early first stage of labor (prior to 4 cm cervical dilation) and ended with the delivery of the baby. 3-5 ml of gel were administered and evenly distributed in the vagina every two hours at examination using a sterile glove by obstetric residency trainer (medical doctor) or obstetrician (specialist). Only one box containing 2 pieces syringes (12ml) labeled as Stage A and 1 piece syringe (12ml) labeled as Stage B was used for during delivery and limited for each patient. Syringes labeled as Stage A and syringe labeled as Stage B were performed for the active phase of first stage, and the second stage of labor, respectively. No perineal massage was performed. </interventions>
    <comparator>All women included to the study received standard routine antepartum care in delivery room. In this context, obstetric residency trainer (medical doctor) or obstetrician (specialist) attended all the vaginal exams, all the application of the obstetric gel, all the deliveries, and episiotomy (selectively) in our institution as an educational university clinic. All the pregnant women examined vaginally at least every hour until to the end of the first stage, and than examination frequency changed depend on the labor progress in the second stage of the labor. Continue fetal monitorization was performed with tococardiograph until to the delivery. Maternal and fetal parameters were recorded on partograph during labor. All the pregnant women included and received standard antepartum care randomly assigned to either two groups at the first stage of the labor. 
Pregnant women in group B, which is control group for the study underwent standard antepartum care without use of any obstetric gel. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of the active phase of first stage of labor assessed by recording the period from the beginning to end of the active phase of first stage of labor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During first stage of labor</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of the second stage of labor assessed by recording the period from the beginning to end of the second stage of labor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During second stage of labor</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number and types of Perineal lacerations by performing physical-pelvic examination, no any specific laboratory test or tool. This is a composite outcome. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During The Labor </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Singleton baby in vertex presentation
* Low risk pregnancy
* Normoweight fetus (clinically or by sonography)
* Term pregnancy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Indication for cesarean delivery 
* Macrosomia
* Contraindication for vaginal delivery</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Turkuaz Saglik Hizmetleri, Medikal, Temizlik, Kimyasal Urunler San. ve Tic. Ltd. St.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Saadetdere Mah. 27 sokak No:3 34100 Esenyurt Istanbul Turkey</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Turkuaz Saglik Hizmetleri, Medikal, Temizlik, Kimyasal Urunler San. ve Tic. Ltd. St.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Saadetdere Mah. 27 sokak No:3 34100 Esenyurt Istanbul Turkey</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We aimed to investigate the effects of the obstetric gels on the labor process, and perineum after vaginal birth in this study. 
A total of 200 women with singleton low-risk pregnancies in vertex position at term were recruited for the randomized controlled study. All the pregnant women included and received standard antepartum care randomly assigned to either two groups at the first stage of the labor. Pregnant women in group A underwent a standard antepartum care plus vaginal application of the obstetric gel according to the study protocol. Pregnant women in group B, which is control group for the study underwent standard antepartum care without use of any obstetric gel. The obstetric gel was intermittently applied into the vaginal canal with special applicator beginning early first stage of labor (prior to 4 cm cervical dilation) and ended with the delivery of the baby. 3-5 ml of gel were administered and evenly distributed in the vagina every two hours at examination using a sterile glove by obstetric residency trainer (medical doctor) or obstetrician (specialist). </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ankara University Medical Faculty Instituonal ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ankara Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Dekanligi
Klinik Arastirmalar Etik Kurulu 06100 Sihhiye ANKARA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11-425-13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mehmet Murat Seval</name>
      <address>Ankara University Medical Faculty 
Department of Obststrics and Gynecology
Cebeci Hospital, 06620, Mamak, 
Ankara</address>
      <phone>+90 312 595 68 58</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>seval@ankara.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nizamettin Uzunkol</name>
      <address>Ankara University Medical Faculty, cebeci Hospital, 06620, Mamak, Ankara</address>
      <phone>+90 312 595 64 05</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nizdil@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sabri Cavkaytar</name>
      <address>Zekai Tahir Burak Women' Health Research and Education Hospital, Gurpinar sokak 4/8, 06260, Cebeci, Ankara</address>
      <phone>+90 312 306 55 52</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sabri.cavkaytar@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>