<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336843">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000435987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Observational Study Of The Correlation Between Intra-Abscess Pressures And The Severity Of Infection.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>STUPP = The Pus Project - An Observational Study Of The Correlation Between Intra-Abscess Pressures And The Severity Of Infection.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-8706</utrn>
    <trialacronym>STUPP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Isolated and uniloculated subcutaneous abscesses</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Description of condition 
The condition is an isolated and uniloculated subcutaneous abscess. 

Research aims and questions
The project is designed to:
1. Establish the feasibility of measuring the pressure of abscesses
2. To explore the possible correlation between intra-abscess pressure and clinical signs of the severity of local and systemic infection
3. This will add new scientific knowledge to abscess formation
4. This may lead to the useful clinical investigation to determine the timing of surgical intervention in the future  

The project will use a descriptive questionnaire to record abscess pressures; abscess volumes; and, clinical, systemic and microbiological manifestations of the abscess. 

Setting
The entire project will be conducted at the Royal Darwin Hospital (RDH), at the Division of Surgery. The pressure measurements will be taken in theatre when the patients are under general anaesthesia.  

Procedure 
This project will be an observational study. Initially there will be a pilot study of the first 20 cases to statistically validate the outcomes and make adjustments to the methods, or other aspects of the study if required. 

To determine the best method of intra-abscess pressure measurement half (10 cases) will have their abscess pressure measured with the intra-compartmental pressure monitoring system and half (10 cases) with the intra-arterial (arterial line) system. This will establish the most accurate device for the measurement of intra-abscess pressure. 

The project will use a descriptive perioperative questionnaire to be completed prior to and post abscess drainage by the operating surgeon. RDH surgeons will be informed of the project and questionnaire protocol as well as encouraged to complete the necessary documentation. The investigators will follow up completed questionnaires daily and complete additional documentation. 

All patients will be provided with an information sheet about the project. Informed consent will be obtained from patients aged 16 years or above with the legal capacity to consent to confirm their participation in the project. The information sheet and consent form outline the procedure used to measure the abscess pressure and requests access to patient records for the purposes of the project. This will be explained comprehensively to the patient. The Northern Territory Interpreter Service will be utilised for Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander persons as well as persons of other countries. The procedure for measuring abscess pressure will not affect patient management. Hence, the RDH consent for procedures/treatment form will be completed for incision and drainage of the abscess. 

The patient observation time will be for the duration of hospital admission.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome 1: To establish the feasibility of measuring the pressure of abscesses
Measurement: 
Intra-compartmental pressure monitoring system
Intra-arterial (arterial line) system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon surgical drainage of the abscess in the operating theatre at Royal Darwin Hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome 2: The correlation between intra-abscess pressure and clinical signs of the severity of local and systemic infection
Measurement:
Extent of skin necrosis and presence of necrotising fasciitis
Pulse rate - pulse oximeter
Mean arterial pressure - blood pressure cuff
Temperature - thermometer
C-reactive protein - biochemistry 
White cell count - biochemistry
Blood cultures - microbiology</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission to the Royal Darwin Hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients with an isolated and uniloculated subcutaneous abscess presenting to the Royal Darwin Hospital, Emergency Department who are aged 16 years or above with the legal capacity to consent. The abscess must require surgical drainage in the operating theatre. Patients must be otherwise healthy (see exclusion criteria).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All patients with: 
- A multiloculated abscess,
- Other potential sources of infection, for example pneumonia, 
- Increased mortality risk, and
- Major immune compromise, for example chronic renal failure, heart failure, or diabetes.
Patients who are pregnant as well as children (aged less than 16 years) or those without the legal capacity to consent will also be excluded from the project.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Philip Carson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>P.O. Box 41326,
Casuarina, Northern Territory, 0811</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lovelace Osei-Tutu</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4/10-14 Omeo Street,
Brinkin, Northern Territory, 0810</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Darwin Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rocklands Drive, 
Casuarina, Northern Territory, 0810</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>An abscess is a localised collection of bacteria, dead tissue, and pus. There are no human studies demonstrating a link between increasing abscess pressures and the spread of infection. The current management is surgical incision and drainage of the abscess cavity. Once the abscess spreads it is associated with a prolonged stay in hospital and a longer recovery time. We propose to measure the abscess pressure in patients presenting to the Royal Darwin Hospital Emergency Department, and correlate the pressure with clinical indices of local and systemic inflammatory reaction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NT Department of Health and Menzies School of Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Menzies School of Health Research
PO Box 41096
CASUARINA NT 0811</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011-1570</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Philip Carson</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 41326,
Casuarina, Northern Territory, 0811</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8922 8249</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8922 8601</fax>
      <email>phillip.carson@nt.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Lovelace Osei-Tutu</name>
      <address>4/10-14 Omeo Street,
Brinkin, Northern Territory, 0810</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8922 8888</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8922 8286</fax>
      <email>boltsnadd@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Eliza Theodore</name>
      <address>c/o NT Clinical School
P.O. Box 41326,
Casuarina, Northern Territory, 0811</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8922 8888</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8922 8286</fax>
      <email>jane.theodore@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>