<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371987">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000027314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing The Effects Of A Low Fat Diet Versus A Ketogenic Diet On The Motor And Non-Motor Symptoms Of Parkinson's Disease: A Randomized Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing The Effects Of A Low Fat Diet Versus A Ketogenic Diet On The Motor And Non-Motor Symptoms Of Parkinson's Disease: A Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1185-9688</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This will be a randomized controlled study with 10-40 patients in each of two groups (20-80 patients total). The study will last for ten weeks, although the actual dietary intervention will only be for eight weeks.

(1)	Diets.

Patients will be given a four-week meal plan containing information about their diet, grocery shopping lists for each week, standard meal plan recipes, optional calorie booster recipes, and a cheat diary.

Two different diets will be compared. The first diet will be low fat (1758 calories, 42 g fat, 75 g protein, 246 g net carbohydrate per day); by weight, the percentages will be 11% fat versus 62% net carbohydrate. The second diet will be high fat ketogenic (1758 calories, 152 g fat, 75 g protein, 16 g net carbohydrate per day - in other words, a 1.5:1 modified ketogenic diet); by weight, the percentages will be 60% fat versus 6% net carbohydrate. Notably, calorie and protein intake per day will be the same in both diets.

The 1758 calories per day and macronutrient ratios given above will be the baseline diet that all participants will be expected to be able to consume. However, some participants will clearly require a higher caloric intake than this. We will provide simple recipes that substantially increase caloric intake but minimally affect protein intake for each group. For the low fat diet several low fat, high net carbohydrate supplemental options (such as fruit shakes) will be provided to the participants. For the ketogenic diet several high fat, low net carbohydrate supplemental options (such as fat shakes) will be provided to the participants. These options will allow for more calories to be consumed while maintaining the relevant fat to net carbohydrate ratio, without significantly increasing protein consumption.

We will not ask the patient to maintain a detailed food diary as proof of their sticking to the diet, as previous studies have shown these to be burdensome from the patient perspective. However, we will prescribe a cheat diary to each patient such that if they do deviate from the meal plan, they write down the details of the food they ate that was not part of the meal plan.

Dietary education and counselling will be provided throughout the study to assist patients with the practical aspects of their diet. We will endeavour to represent both diets as potentially providing health benefits.


(2)	Assessments.

There will be one screening visit one month before the study starts for the following:

(1) 0-60 minutes - Lead investigator presentation including explanation of Participant Information Sheet and signing of Consent Form.
(2) 60-90 minutes - Parkinsons nurse assessment on demographics, home situation, comorbidities, Parkinsons diagnosis, Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) score, constipation including Bowel Function Index (BFI) score, and medications/medication allergies.
(3) 90-150 minutes - Nutrition specialist assessment regarding meal preparation abilities, food preferences/food allergies, and physical status.

Information required to calculate body mass index and recommended daily calorie intake will be gathered at the screening visit, but these variables will be calculated after the visit.

There will be four clinical visits at Weeks 1, 2, 6, and 10 for the following:

(1) 0-15 minutes - Document weight and body mass index, lying and standing blood pressure, and explain and record glucose/ketone monitor.
(2) 15-30 minutes - Movement Disorder Society Unified Parkinsons Disease Rating Scale (MDS-UPDRS) questionnaire.
(3) 30-60 minutes - MDS-UPDRS blinded neurologist assessment (non-motor aspects of daily living, motor aspects of daily living, motor examination, motor complications).
(4) 60-75 minutes - Bloods (CBC, EUC, lipids, uric acid, CRP).


(3)	Procedure.

Months Before	
Ads in local and nation-wide Parkinsons newsletters.
Presentations to enhance awareness of study.

Month Before	
Screening visit.

Week 1	
First clinical visit.
Hand out and explain how to use glucose/ketone monitor. 
Week 2	
Second clinical visit.
Randomize and hand out meal plans, including cheat diaries.

Week 3	
Participants commence individual meal plans.
Week 4	
Continue.
Week 5	
Continue.
Week 6	
Third clinical visit.
Immediately after the visits are completed, MDS-UPDRS scores will be analyzed to see if one meal plan is superior (participants on one meal plan have significantly improved scores compared to their aggregate baseline scores, or participants on the other meal plan have significantly worse scores compared to their aggregate baseline scores).
-	If one meal plan is superior, all participants go on the superior meal plan. 
-	Otherwise, all participants stay on their current meal plan.

Week 7	
Participants commence superior meal plan, or stay on current meal plan.
Week 8	
Continue.
Week 9	
Continue.
Week 10	
Fourth clinical visit.

Month After	
Results relayed to group.

*Patients will have 24-hour access to a neurologist and a Parkinsons nurse throughout the study.
*Patients will also be contacted by phone or email every week to see how they are going.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be low fat (1758 calories, 42 g fat, 75 g protein, 246 g net carbohydrate per day); by weight, the percentages will be 11% fat and 62% net carbohydrate. Carbohydrates will be primarily derived from vegetables, fruits, and multigrain breads.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of Parkinson's Disease motor and non-motor symptoms using the MDS-UPDRS score. This will be undertaken by a neurologist, blinded to the meal plan that the patient is currently taking.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index assessed by BMI calculator</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lying and standing blood pressure assessed with electronic blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipid profile assessed by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Uric acid assessed by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>C-reactive protein assessed by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood glucose assessed by Freestyle Precision NeoMonitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood ketones assessed by Freestyle Precision NeoMonitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycosylated hemoglobin assessed by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessments Weeks 1 and 2. Assessment end of Week 6 (four weeks post commencing meal plan). Assessment end of Week 10 (four weeks post commencing superior or current meal plan). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 40-75 years.
Body mass index &gt;18.5.
Montreal cognitive assessment (MoCA) &gt;20.
Parkinsons diagnosis fulfilling UK Brain Bank criteria.
Sufficient motivation and ability to follow either meal plan.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to provide informed consent or speak and understand English.
A substance abuse, mental health, or medical condition that in the opinion of the investigators would make it difficult for the patient to take part in the study.
Parkinsons Disease extremely mild or extremely severe (Hoehn and Yahr Stages 0 and 5).
Current use of weight-loss medications.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>7/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>47</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>18/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>18/08/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Waikato Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Selwyn and Pembroke Street, Hamilton 3204</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Waikato Hospital Neurology Department</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Selwyn and Pembroke Street, Hamilton 3204</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Parkinsons disease may result from mitochondrial dysfunction and chronic cell energy failure (1,2). If so, a high fat, low carbohydrate ketogenic diet may alleviate this chronic energy failure as ketones compensate for deteriorating brain glucose metabolism (3,4), bypass deficient Complex I activity (5,6), and provide more ATP per unit oxygen than glucose (7). Previous studies have shown that physiological ketosis is beneficial in epilepsy (8) and Alzheimers disease (9,10). To date, one study has examined the ketogenic diet in Parkinsons (11); it lacked a control arm.

Objectives:
In mid-2017, the Waikato Hospital neurology department will run a randomized controlled study with two objectives - first, to show it is feasible to institute a ketogenic diet in patients with Parkinsons, second, to compare the effects of a low fat diet versus a ketogenic diet on motor and non-motor symptoms of Parkinsons.

Methods:
Randomized controlled study over ten weeks. Baseline assessments in week 1 and 2. In week 3, participants randomized to either low fat or ketogenic diet followed by blinded clinical assessment at end of week 6. In week 7, all participants go on superior or current diet followed by blinded clinical assessment at end of week 10.

(1) Bose and Beal. 2016. Mitochondrial dysfunction in Parkinsons disease. Journal of Neurochemistry 139(Suppl 1), 216-231.
(2) Perier and Vila. 2012. Mitochondrial biology and Parkinsons Disease. Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Medicine 4:a009332, 1-19.
(3)	Roy et al. 2012. The ketogenic diet increases brain glucose and ketone uptake in aged rats: a dual tracer PET and volumetric MRI study. Brain Research 1-10.
(4)	Cunnane et al. 2011. Brain fuel metabolism, aging, and Alzheimers disease. Nutrition 27(1), 1-41.
(5) Tieu et al. 2003. D-ß-Hydroxybutyrate rescues mitochondrial respiration and mitigates features of Parkinson disease. The Journal of Clinical Investigation 112(6), 892-901. 
(6)	Gasior et al. 2006. Neuroprotective and disease-modifying effects of the ketogenic diet. Behavioural Pharmacology 17(5-6), 431-439.
(7)	Veech. 2004. The therapeutic implications of ketone bodies: the effects of ketone bodies in pathological conditions: ketosis, ketogenic diet, redox states, insulin resistance, and mitochondrial metabolism. Prostaglandins, Leukotrienes, and Essential Fatty Acids 70(3), 309-319.
(8) Neal et al. 2008. The ketogenic diet for the treatment of childhood epilepsy: a randomized controlled trial. Lancet Neurology 7(6), 700-706.
(9) Reger et al. 2004. Effects of beta-hydroxybutyrate on cognition in memory-impaired adults. Neurobiology of Aging 25, 311-314.
(10) Henderson et al. 2009. Study of theketogenic agent AC-1202 in mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicenter trial. Nutrition and Metabolism 6(31), 1-25.
(11) VanItallie et al. 2005. Treatment of Parkinson disease with diet-induced hyperketonemia; A feasibility study. Neurology 64, 728-730.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/STH/133</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew CL Phillips</name>
      <address>Neurology Department, Waikato Hospital
Selwyn and Pembroke Street
Hamilton 3204</address>
      <phone>+64274057415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Matthew.Phillips@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew CL Phillips</name>
      <address>Neurology Department, Waikato Hospital
Selwyn and Pembroke Street
Hamilton 3204</address>
      <phone>+64274057415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Matthew.Phillips@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew CL Phillips</name>
      <address>Neurology Department, Waikato Hospital
Selwyn and Pembroke Street
Hamilton 3204</address>
      <phone>+64274057415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Matthew.Phillips@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew CL Phillips</name>
      <address>Neurology Department, Waikato Hospital Selwyn and Pembroke Street Hamilton 3204 </address>
      <phone>+64274057415 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Matthew.Phillips@waikatodhb.health.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>