<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371655">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001454460p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Significance of the Suprarenal Aortic Diameter and Surgical Complications  in Patients who have undergone Endovascular Aortic Aneurysm Repair.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Significance of the Suprarenal Aortic Diameter in the Occurrence of Late Proximal Neck Complications Following Endovascular Aortic Aneurysm Repair.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-6736</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Endoleaks and other complications, and their association with suprarenal aortic diameter following endovascular aneurysm repair.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>CT scans for the 6 month follow up after endovascular repair will be examined to assess the diameter or the suprarenal aorta. This will be the only observational point for each participant in this study.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no control group. We are looking at the association of aortic diameter with complications.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the association between endoleaks following endovascular abdominal aortic aneurysm repair and suprarenal aortic calibres. The occurrence of endoleaks will be determined by a review of the patient's medical records, and the suprarenal aortic calibres will be assessed by CT scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 6 month follow-up for endovascular aneurysm repair (EVAR).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Our first secondary objective is to determine whether there is an association between aortic calibres and  re-intervention after endovascular aneurysm repair as determined by the patient's medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 6 month follow- up post EVAR.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Our second secondary objective is to determine whether there is an association between aortic calibres and aneurysm related mortality as assessed by patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 6 month follow up post EVAR.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Our third secondary objective is to determine whether there is an association between aortic calibres and all cause mortality, as assessed by patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 6 month follow up post EVAR</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Our fourth secondary objective is to determine whether there is an association between aortic calibres and aneurysmal sac growth as determined by patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 6 month follow up post EVAR.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with infrarenal abdominal aortic aneurysms who have undergone endovascular aneurysm repair( EVAR)  at Dunedin Public Hospital, as identified through unit audit databases and hospital coding data.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who have not undergone EVAR at Dunedin Public Hospital, and who have not had a 6 month follow-up CT scan.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods> If there is evidence of a difference in mean aortic diameters between the complications and no complications groups (using a two-sample t-test if model assumptions hold and a Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon test should assumptions not hold and not be otherwise correctable), logistic regression will be used to investigate associations between aortic diameter and complication status while adjusting for prognostic variables which could confound the association.  Given the possibility of 30 or fewer cases, Peduzzi et al. (1996) would suggest only one or two potential confounders could be simultaneously included in the models alongside aortic diameter and so the effect of adding age, gender, height, weight, type of graft, and pre-EVAR co-morbidities individually will be examined to see if this alters any association between aortic diameter and complication status.  The Hosmer-Lemeshow test and a specification test will be used to assess issues with model fit, including non-linearities with respect to continuous predictors.  Statistical analyses will be performed using Stata 14.1 or R 3.3.1 (or later versions) and two-sided p&lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>134</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago, Surgical Sciences</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The infrarenal aorta is the site most commonly affected by aneurysm formation, but the cause of aneurysms is still not well understood. Our group have data that suggests the presence of aneurysmal disease is more likely in patients with suprarenal aortic calibres over than 25mm, whereas the presence of  ischaemic heart disease is more likely in those with suprarenal aortic calibres less than 25mm. 

This is of particular interest in the setting of endovascular abdominal aortic aneurysm repair (EVAR). Complications following EVAR, such as stent-graft migration, endoleaks, and aneurysmal sac growth, are correlated with aneurysm-related mortality.  We hypothesise that larger aortic diameters would be more likely to be associated with complications in patients following EVAR.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Krysa</name>
      <address>Department of Surgical Sciences
Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 3 470 9850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jo.krysa@southerndhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kari Clifford</name>
      <address>Department of Surgical Sciences
Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64210668369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kari.clifford@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kari Clifford</name>
      <address>Department of Surgical Sciences
Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 2 1066 8369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kari.clifford@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kari Clifford</name>
      <address>Department of Surgical Sciences
Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 2 1066 8369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kari.clifford@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>