<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369215">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000945527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An investigation of sleep monitoring techniques and the impact of the clinical environment on Intensive Care patients sleep. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation of the application of actigraphy to assess sleep disturbance compared to polysomnography and subjective sleep assessments within the Intensive Care Unit. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-1192.</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sleep disturbance 
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sleep fragmentation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sleep monitoring</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Clinical environment </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Concurrent sleep monitoring techniques applied  to patients admitted to the intensive care environment, including polysomnography, actigraphy, patient self-reports and clinician based observations.

Sleep monitoring procedure:

Actigraphy: Participants will be fitted an omidirectional accelerometer wrist actigraphy watch, which detects movement used to identify activity/rest cycles. This device will monitoring rest/activity cycles for a 24 hour period. 

Polysomnography: 24 hour polysomnography will be conducted, and requires the application of 9 small electrodes on the head and face to record the biophysiological features of the sleep cycle.  

Patient self-assessment:Patients will be requested to  complete the Richards-Campbell Sleep Questionnaire (RCSQ)  and the Karolinska Sleepiness Scale (univariant scale). The RCQS is a 6 item scale that will be completed by the patient the following morning after the night recording, whilst the Karolinska Sleepiness Scale will be completed at three intervals with minimum of 6 hours between assessments to evaluate subjective sleepiness 

Nurses subjective assessment of sleep:  Nursing staff  will be required to complete an hourly sleep assessment, contained within the MetaVision electronic information system (iMDSoft). This assessment will require nursing staff to subjectively assess if the participant has been awake, asleep for less than 15 minutes, asleep for approximately 30 minutes, asleep for 45 minutes, asleep approximately 60 minutes of each hour of the monitoring period, or could not assess (e.g. due to sedation). This monitoring will conducted over the 24 hour monitoring period. 



Monitoring of environmental factors considered to be the etiological cause of sleep disturbance; light, noise and clinical interactions.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Concurrent 24 hour sleep monitoring applied to participants admitted to Intensive Care, with polysomnography (the gold standard of sleep monitoring) acting as the control. Comparative sleep monitoring techniques being investigated will include actigraphy, observational recording of sleep duration, and participant self-reporting of sleep quality  (Karolinska Sleepiness Scale and  Richards-Campbell Sleep Questionnaire). Sleep monitoring techniques will be time synchronised to the monitoring of the clinical environment: light, noise and clinical intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1:To determine the accuracy of actigraphy compared to polysomnography in monitoring total sleep time and sleep fragmentation.
 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at the completion of 24 hours of continuous monitoring.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: To evaluate the accuracy of subjective assessments (patient reports and clinical observations) of sleep compared to biophysiological sleep monitoring: polysomnography. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at the completion of 24 hours of continuous monitoring.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 3: To report the composite impact of the noise levels greater than 70dB(A) and nocturnal exposure to artificial light on sleep.

Noise level will monitored an recorded in the decibel A weighted by a sound meter positioned at the head end of the patient's bed.

Light levels will monitored using a light meter to record luminance (Lux) and is the standard unit of measure in photometry, representative of the intensity of light perceived by the human eye. This device will positioned a head end of the patients bed. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at the completion of 24 hours of continuous monitoring.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1: To quanitfy the percentage of time spent in the stages of the sleep cycle (stage 1, 2, 3 and rapid eye movement) determined by polysomnography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: Over a 24 hour period of sleep monitoring</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 2: Report the total sleep time acquired determine by polysomnography by Intensive care patients. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: Over a 24 hour period of sleep monitoring</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Over 18 years of age.
Admission to intensive care anticipated to be greater than 24 hours.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be ineligible for the study if the treating ICU consultant determines the patient to:
1. Have significant neurological injury (Intra-cranial pressure &gt;20mmHg in the past 24 hours, neurosurgical intervention in the past 3 days),  
2. If patients are not suspected to survive for more than 24 hours, 
3. Admissions with a confirmed or suspected drug overdose,
4. Patients who have been administered administered paralyzing agents within the past 24 hours,
5. Patients requiring a barbiturate infusion, 
6. Patients admitted with a primary seizure disorder or assessed has having seizure activity,
7. Patients who are receiving palliative care or treatment withdrawal,
8. Patients with a known past medical history of Parkinsons or Alzheimers Disease,
9. Inadequate English language skills, 
10. Facial injuries that prohibit the placement of the PSG electrodes,
11. Injuries that preclude the application of actigraphy, 
12. Patients with known spinal cord injury or neuromuscular dege nerative conditions such as Guillain Barrre Syndrome, and  
13. Clinically suspected encephalopathies: septic encephalopathy, hepatic encephalopathy or uremic encephalopathy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sixty-seven (67) participants are needed to determine the strength and direction of correlations between PSG and actigraphy measurements of sleep quality and quantity, and the ability of actigraphy to correctly distinguish between sleep and wakeful state with 80% power, 95% significance and to detect a medium effect size (correlation co-efficient Rho, p = 0.3). 

Descriptive statistics including means and standard deviations will be used to describe the patient cohort, with medians and interquartile ranges reported for non-parametric data.  Data will be analysed using Statistical Packages for Social Sciences (version 20.) 

Actigraphy and behavioural assessment data will be compared with PSG data using the Wilcoxon nonparametric tests, paired t-tests and Pearson correlations. All p values &gt; 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. 

Multiple regression analysis will be conducted to explore the relationship between the variables being investigated. In addition, a Blandt-Altman plot will used to investigate the agreement between PSG and actigraphy for arousal and sleep, and the Cohen-Kappa test will be used to test agreement between nominal data. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>67</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assistant Professor Lori Delaney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Disciplines of Nursing and Midwifery 
University Drive 
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canberra Hospital Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Canberra Hospital
Yamba Drive
Garran ACT 2605</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mortara Instrument Aust. Pty. Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> Unit 28, 9 Hoyle Avenue CASTLE HILL NSW 2154.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associated Professor Dr Frank Van Haren </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Intensive Care Unit
The Canberra Hospital
Yambe Drive 
Garran ACT 2605 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sleep is an essential biological function which is required by all animal. The Intensive Care Unit (ICU) environment fails to be propitious for sleep, which has been attributed to immediate and long term physiological and psychological morbidities. It is widely acknowledge that sleep is critical for ICU patients recovery, however the ability to monitor and evaluate sleep amongst this patient cohort has eluded clinicians. Bio-physiological monitoring of sleep undertaken via polysomnography is not viable for widespread implementation into intensive care as it is cumbersome, expensive, technically difficult, and requires expertise in data analysis. However, identifying alternative sleep monitoring methods that are both accurate and feasible have eluded clinicians. The role of sleep is an aspect of clinical care that is imperative to address in order to improve patient health, support physiological homeostasis, and to implement strategies that mitigate the short and long term adverse effects associated with sleep disturbance that complicates patients recovery. This study is investigating whether sleep monitoring conducted by actigraphy will provide an accurate objective assessment of total sleep time and sleep fragmentation compared to polysomnography. 

Objectives: 
1.To determine the total sleep time of patients admitted to ICU. 
2.Evaluate the sleep architecture of patients admitted to an Australian Intensive Care Unit
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Capital Territory Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 11,Woden, ACT 2606.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress>ACT Health 
Research Ethics and Governance Office 
Human Research  Ethics Committee
PO Box 11 
Woden ACT 2606</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.5.16.071</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lori Delaney</name>
      <address>Disciplines of Nursing and Midwifery 
University Drive 
University of Canberra 
Bruce ACT 2601 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 2108</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6201 5128</fax>
      <email>lori.delaney@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lori Delaney</name>
      <address>Disciplines of Nursing and Midwifery 
University Drive 
University of Canberra 
Bruce ACT 2601 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 2108</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6201 5128</fax>
      <email>lori.delaney@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lori Delaney</name>
      <address>Disciplines of Nursing and Midwifery 
University Drive 
University of Canberra 
Bruce ACT 2601 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 2108</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6201 5128</fax>
      <email>lori.delaney@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lori Delaney</name>
      <address>Disciplines of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of Canberra 
Bruce ACT 2601 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 2108</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6201 5128</fax>
      <email>lori.delaney@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>