<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367063">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000990628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparative assessment of the absorption of a single oral dose of beclomethasone dipropionate in healthy male and female volunteers with and without concurrent oral charcoal blockade.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single dose, randomized, open label, crossover comparative bioavailability study of beclomethasone dipropionate in healthy male and female volunteers under fasting conditions with and without concurrent oral charcoal blockade.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1160-5894</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bioavailability study conducted in healthy volunteers comparing beclomethasone dipropionate administered with and without concurrent charcoal dosing with no health condition or problem studied. 

Although this study is being conducted in healthy volunteers who are not being treated for the condition to which the medicine is used, beclomethasone dipropionate belongs to a class of medicines called synthetic corticosteroids. It is used for the treatment of symptoms of seasonal allergic rhinitis including hay fever.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single dose, crossover study design whereby each participant receives the formulation of beclomethasone dipropionate (1 x 2000 mcg) on one occasion with oral charcoal administered pre-dose and at specified times up to 4 hours post dosing and on one occasion without oral charcoal with each dose separated by a one week washout period. The intervention for this trial is beclomethasone dipropionate with and without charcoal.

No water is allowed for 1 hour prior to dosing until 1 hour after dosing (except for the water consumed with the dose). 
Participants are required not to eat for 10 hours before receiving each dose and to fast for approximately 4 hours after receiving each dose.

Bathroom visits will be supervised to ensure no unauthorised water or food intake and for personal safety. Participants will be confined at the Clinical Site for 10 hours prior to dosing to ensure compliance and will be monitored and for 24 hours after dosing.

Standard meals will be consumed at the Clinical Site with no additional food intake allowed.

Vital sign examination, assessment of well-being, a throat examination, alcohol breath testing, drug testing and pregnancy testing will be performed upon each participant reporting to the Clinical Site 10 hours prior to dosing.

Pre and post study laboratory tests will be completed to assess the healthy of participants along with HIV, Hepatitis and drugs of abuse testing. 

The volunteer's randomsied to receive 50 ml of activated charcoal suspension will be given the charcoal suspension 2 minutes prior to dosing, immediately with dosing and also at 1, 2 and 4 hours post dosing.

Each dose (1 x 2000 mcg) will be taken orally as 2 ml of beclomethasone dipropionate nasal spray suspension in 18 ml of water. Medication will be administered via a 30 ml syringe and a mouth check will be conducted to ensure the medication has been taken as directed.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Single dose, crossover study design whereby each participant receives beclomethasone dipropionate (1 x 2000 mcg) with concurrent oral charcoal on one occasion and beclomethasone dipropionate (1 x 2000 mcg) on one occasion without oral charcoal with each dose separated by a one week washout period. The comparator/control for this trial is beclomethasone dipropionate with and without charcoal.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the bioavailability of beclomethasone dipropionate and 17-BMP (as summarised by Cmax and AUC) with and without concurrent oral charcoal. All plasma samples will be assayed for beclomethasone dipropionate using one fully validated LC/MS/MS method. Validation will be conducted to comply with EU and FDA guidelines. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 0.08, 0.025, 0.50, 0.75, 1, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 20 and 24 hours </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to maximum peak concentration (Tmax) will be determined by plasma sample analysis. Tmax will be the time where the maximum concentration occurred in the sample points. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 0.08, 0.025, 0.50, 0.75, 1, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 20 and 24 hours </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy male and non-pregnant females
Aged between 18 and 45
Non-smoker
BMI between 18.5 and 30 inclusive
Normal, healthy individuals as determined by medical history, physical examination, ECG, blood pressure, pulse, heart rate, temperature, well-being assessment and laboratory tests
Able to provide written informed consent 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any history of COPD, chronic bronchitis, emphysema,  asthma , or any other lung disease, recent upper or lower respiratory tract infection,  migraine headaches
Concomitant drug therapy of any kind
Who have taken any drug that induces/inhibits the hepatic microsomal enzymes within 30 days prior to dosing
Who have received an investigational compound or drug known to induce or inhibit liver enzymes within 60 days of the start of the study
Sensitivity to beclomethasone dipropionate any other similar class medicines or the excipients of beclomethasone dipropionate
Any history of recent recurrent attacks of bronchitis, asthma, migraine headaches
Concomitant drug therapy of any kind
History of any conditions that might interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of the drug
Females who are pregnant and/or are breastfeeding
Who are planning to start a family within 60 days of receiving the final dose.
Smoker (anyone who has smoked in the last 6 months)
History of alcohol or drug abuse or dependency
Participation in a drug study within 60 days of the start of the study or donated blood in the 60 days preceding the study.
Volunteers for whom the Clinical Investigator believes, for any reason, that participation would not be an acceptable risk </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All formulations will be labelled as Formulation A and B. The identification of each treatment will only be known to the Managing Director and the Section Head - Trials and Regulatory Affairs. 

Each participant will be identified by a 3 digit screening number and a 2 digit subject number. The screening number will be issued once the participant has given written consent to participate in the study and the two digit subject number (randomisation number) after acceptance into the study 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation list will be prepared using a computer program for a balanced two-way crossover design. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/09/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cipla Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cipla House
Peninsula Business Park
Ganpatrao Kadam Marg
Lower Parel
Mumbai 400013</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>India</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this study is to evaluate the bioavailability of beclomethasone dipropionate in healthy male and female volunteers under fasting conditions with and without concurrent oral charcoal.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>No presentations or citations available. Final CSR provided to sponsor company for registration purposes.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health and Disability Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
1 the Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTB/130</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Noelyn Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited 156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777) Dunedin 9016 </address>
      <phone>+6434779669 </phone>
      <fax>+6434779605 </fax>
      <email>noelyn.hung@otago.ac.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Linda Folland</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited 156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777) Dunedin 9016 </address>
      <phone>+6434779669 </phone>
      <fax>+6434779605 </fax>
      <email>linda.folland@zenithtechnology.co.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cheung Tak Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited 156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777) Dunedin 9016 </address>
      <phone>+6434779669 </phone>
      <fax>+6434779605 </fax>
      <email>tak.hung@zenithtechnology.co.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>