<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362993">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000956808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of protein on gastric emptying and hormones, and appetite and energy intake in undernourished compared with healthy older individuals</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of oral protein on energy intake, appetite, antral area, gastric emptying, amino acids, hormones and glucose in undernourished compared with healthy older individuals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ageing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participant receives a single 450mL preload per study visit (separated by at least 3 days) in a randomised, crossover fashion of: i) 30 grams Whey Protein Isolate with diet lime cordial flavouring or ii) Water control with diet lime cordial flavouring. Both preloads contain 100uL of 13C Octanoic acid to enable measurement of gastric emptying via 13CO2 in the breath.

Gastric emptying rate and intragastric meal distribution are determined using 3D ultrasound.

Appetite sensation questionnaires in the form of a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) are measured and blood samples are collected for concentrations of gut hormones, amino acids and glucose.

A standard buffet meal is provided at 180 minutes following the preload and the participant has 30 minutes to eat until comfortably full. The buffet meal consists of 300ml orange juice, 600ml water, 375ml iced coffee, 4 slices white bread, 4 slices brown bread, 100g deli leg ham, 100g virginian chicken, 4 slices cheese, 100g tomato, 100g cucumber, 100g lettuce, 2 portions mayonnaise, 2 portions margarine, 1 medium apple, 1 medium banana, 200g chocolate custard, 150g fruit salad, 200g strawberry yoghurt, and a 14g milky way bar.

Each volunteer receives one of each of the 2 treatments on each of the 2 study days. Each study visit is separated by no less than 3 days. Each visit lasts approximately 4 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: a single 450mL water and diet lime cordial preload.

Undernourished older people will be compared to 'healthy' older people.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Macronutrient and total energy intake of a standard buffet meal are quantified using Foodworks software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Buffet meal is presented at 180 minutes following the last ultrasound measurement and the subject is allowed to freely consume food until comfortably full for 30 minutes (until t= 210 minutes)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentrations of gut hormones (cholecyctokinin (CKK), glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1), peptide YY (PYY), gastric inhibitory polypeptide (GIP), ghrelin, glucagon and insulin), glucose and amino acids.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples are taken at t= -15, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150 and 180 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastric emptying rate assessed by three-dimensional (3D) ultrasonography and 13C Octanoic Acid Breath Test.

3D ultrasound defines the fraction of the meal emptied from the stomach, including 50% emptying time (T1/2), during the study.

The 13C Octanoic Acid breath test assesses gastric emptying of the protein drink through measurement of 13CO2 in the breath via mass spectrometry. Half-emptying time and gastric emptying coefficient will also be calculated and compared to those obtained using 3D ultrasonography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ultrasound measurements for assessment of gastric emptying will be taken at -15, 0, and every 15 minutes thereafter until 180 minutes.

Breath samples are collected for assessment of 13CO2 immediately before meal ingestion, and every 5 minutes for the 30 minutes following meal ingestion. Breath samples are then collected every 15 minutes until 180 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite sensations using a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) (nausea, hunger, fullness, desire to eat, thirst).</outcome>
      <timepoint>VAS is administered at time points: -15 minutes, 0 minutes and every fifteen minutes thereafter until 180 minutes. The final VAS is administered at 210 minutes after the buffet meal has been consumed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure and heart rate are determined using an automatic sphygmomanometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood pressure and heart rate are measured at -15 minutes, 0 minutes and every fifteen minutes thereafter until 180 minutes. The final measurement is at 210 minutes after the buffet meal has been consumed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Undernourished older people:

at risk of malnourishment + malnourishment defined by a well validated, widely used, screening tool that is associated with poor outcomes in older people: the Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA) with a score &lt;24 out of 30

and, at least one of: self-reported weight loss in the previous 3 months, or a Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt;22 kg/m2

'Healthy' older people:

BMI: 20-30 kg/m2

Weight stable (&lt;5% fluctuation in body weight in previous 3 months).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant gastrointestinal symptoms, disease, or surgery.

Current gallbladder or pancreatic disease; diabetes mellitus; epilepsy; cardiovasculr or respiratory diseases; any other illnesses as assessed by the investigator (including chronic illnesses not explicitly listed above).

Impaired cognitive function.

Depression.

Use of prescribed or non-prescribed medications (including vitamins and herbal supplements) which may effect gastrointestinal function or appetite.

Lactose intolerant or other food allergies; intolerance or allergy to paracetomol.

Individuals with low ferritin levels or who have donated blood in the 12 weeks prior to taking part in the study.

Current intake of &gt;2 standard drinks on &gt;5 days per week.

Current smokers of cigarettes/cigars/marijuana.

Current intake of any illicit substance.

Experience claustrophobia in confined spaces.

Unable to comprehend study protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers are asked to visit the clinic for a screening visit. A series of screening questionnaires are answered by the volunteer, and a blood sample is taken for determination of ferritin levels. Eligibility is determined based on the inclusion/exclusion criteria. A signed informed consent form is obtained and study dates are established. Eligible volunteers are assigned a subject number and randomised into a treatment for each study visit using a randomisation table. Randomisation involves contacting the holder of the randomisation table (study assistant) to inform them of the subjects details and study dates. The unblinded study assistant is therefore responsible for allocating a random treatment to the subject and preparing the preload on each study day.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation table was created using http://www.randomization.com/</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Stijn Soenen</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building,
Frome Road,
Adelaide, SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Adelaide</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5005</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5005</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ageing is associated with a physiological reduction of appetite and energy intake, which has been called the anorexia of ageing. Dietary supplementation with liquid protein preparations is now used frequently to increase energy and protein intake in older adults in both institutionalized and community-dwelling populations. Although the latter would appear a logical approach, evidence for success of increased energy intake in older individuals is limited. It is well established that the ingestion of nutrients induce a number of changes in gastrointestinal (GI) function, which are associated with the modulation of appetite and energy intake. These changes include the slowing of gastric emptying, which sustains gastric distension and is associated with proximal gastric relaxation. In addition to the effects of healthy ageing, there is evidence of differences between undernourished and well-nourished older people, which may potentially result from being undernourished and/or contribute to the undernourished state. Urgent investigation is warranted to determine the effects of oral protein intake, so that protein can be incorporated into their diet to assist in sparing muscle mass without reducing their appetite.

The study aims to characterise in older individuals, the effect of undernutrition on energy intake, appetite, antral area, gastric emptying, plasma concentrations of amino acids, hormones (i.e. CCK, PYY, ghrelin, GLP-1, GIP, glucagon and insulin) and glucose.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute, North Terrace
Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>120602</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Stijn Soenen</name>
      <address>Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building,
Frome Road,
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5073</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>stijn.soenen@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Stijn Soenen</name>
      <address>Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building,
Frome Road,
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5073</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>stijn.soenen@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>