<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343424">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001080910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Supporting Childrens Outcomes using Rewards, Exercise and Skills study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a school-based physical activity program in disadvantaged primary schools: The Supporting Childrens Outcomes using Rewards, Exercise and Skills study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SCORES</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Fundamental Movement Skills</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical Inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this group randomised control trial is to develop, implement and evaluate a school-based intervention to promote physical activity and improve fundamental movement skill (FMS) proficiency in children from disadvantaged primary schools. The 12-month intervention will include professional development workshops for teachers and students, school policy review and recommendations, community and parental engagement in the intervention process, student-led recess and lunchtime activities, and physical activity equipment packs. Physical activity behaviour, FMS competency, self esteem, physiological outcomes and potential mediators of behaviour change will be assessed. Assessments will be conducted at baseline 6- and 12-months.
 
The intervention is based on Harters Competence Motivation Theory and will be implemented using a socio-ecological framework. The intervention will be delivered in two stages and includes the following components: 

Stage 1

i)	Professional development for teachers  The research team will deliver professional development workshops for teachers. Workshops will focus on effective teaching methods for the development of FMS, strategies for assessing FMS, increasing active learning time (ALT) and promoting physical activity in PE and school sport. 
a. School champion workshop: will be held at the university.  
b. Whole-school workshops: will be delivered in the study schools during one of their scheduled professional development days.

ii)	Student leadership  Students will be provided with an opportunity to achieve SCORES leadership accreditation. This will provide students with formal acknowledgment (i.e. certificates) and rewards (i.e. water bottles, stickers and balls) for their participation. SCORES leaders will be encouraged to help organise and deliver lunch and recess activities at school. Workshops will be delivered at the study schools during PE/school sport by the research team.

Stage 2

i)	Community links  Community organisations (e.g. local football clubs) will be invited to the visit the study schools during PE/school sport. This will help to promote community sporting links. 

ii)	Policy and environment  2 strategies will be used:
a. Policy review and recommendations: The research team will conduct a review of physical activity policy in the schools. The research team will work with Principals to revise policy to support the physical activity promotion.
b. Equipment and resources: Each school will be provided with physical activity equipment (e.g. bats, balls etc) and resources (e.g. activity cards) to support the implementation of the intervention based on their individual school needs (approx. $1,000).

iii)	Parental engagement  3 strategies will be used to involve parents:
a. Newsletters - Parents of study participants will be provided with newsletters to educate and encourage them to support their childrens physical activity behaviors. Newsletters will also provide updates and feedback on the project. 
b. FMS Homework  Students will be encouraged to complete practical homework tasks focused on FMS development with their parents/guardians.
c. Parent evening  Parents will be invited to attend an information session on how to promote and increase physical activity and FMS in the home setting.</interventions>
    <comparator>To prevent compensatory rivalry and resentful demoralisation the control schools will be provided with an equipment pack and a condensed version of the program following the 12-month assessments.

The condensed version of the intervention will include the professional development workshops for schools and students. University of Newcastle undergraduate teachers will assist in the delivery of school sport for one school term. Strategies to engage parents and a review of school physical activity policy will be conducted.  The equipment pack will include a variety of sports equipment (e.g. bats, balls, cones, goals) based on individual school requirements (Approx. $1,000 AUD).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity - Students will wear accelerometers for 7 consecutive days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6- and 12-months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardio-respiratory fitness - Students will be assessed using a 20m shuttle test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6- and 12-months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fundamental movement skill  competency -  Students will complete a standard test (TGMD II) including six locomotor and six object control skills, which will be video-taped for assessment (Ulrich 2000).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6- and 12-months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index (BMI) - Height and weight calculations will be measured using a portable scale and stadiometer.
Age and gender adjusted BMI z-scores will also be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary behaviour - Students will complete selected items from the Australian Child and Adolescent Eating Survey (Watson, Collins et al. 2009).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-concept - Students will complete Harter's Self-Perception Profile (Harter 1985).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resilience - Students will complete the Child and Youth Resilience Measure (Ungar and Liebenberg, 2011).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Enjoyment - Students will complete the Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale (PACES) (Motl, Dishman, Saunders, Dowda, Felton, &amp; Pate, 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social support - Students will complete the Physical Activity Social Support scale (Prochaska, Rodgers, and Sallis, 2002), and the Social support in PE and school sport scale (Lubans, Morgan, &amp; McCormack, 2011).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical education / sport effectiveness - PE / sport lessons will be assessed using the System for Observing Fitness Instruction Time (SOFIT) (McKenzie, 2009).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will be students in grades 3 and 4 attending one of the recruited study schools (government primary schools located in the Hunter Region with a Socio-Economic Indexes for Areas (SEIFA) index of less than 5).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>10</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>SEIFA index greater than 5, non-government schools</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will not be concealed. Eligible low-SES schools include those with a SEIFA index of less than 5. We will recruit 6 of the schools that have been identified as eligible. Voluntary, informed and written personal consent will be obtained from all participating principals, teachers and parents. Voluntary, informed and written parental consent will be obtained for all child participants and parents will be encouraged to discuss the project details with their child before giving consent. Participants will be recruited through their school. An oral presentation will provide students and teachers with information about the study and detailed Participant Information Sheets and Consent Forms will be available for students to take home and discuss further with their parents their potential involvement in the study. In order to participate, students will need to return signed Parent Consent Forms indicating consent to participate. Parent Consent Forms ask students to return signed forms to their roll-class teacher or to the school’s front office. Once written consent is obtained, the participants will be invited to baseline assessments. Once baseline assessments have been conducted schools will be randomised to one of the two study arms.</concealment>
    <sequence>The project will use a group randomised controlled trial design with schools randomly allocated to intervention or wait-list control groups for the duration of the study. 

Schools will be match-paired based on size and location, then randomly allocated to the intervention or control group using a computer-based random number producing algorithm. This method ensures an equal chance of allocation to each group.

(i)The study program recipient group: student participants will receive a 12-month physical activity and fundamental movement skills program. 

(ii)The wait-list control group: student participants will not receive the physical activity and fundamental movement skills program during the study period.  However, program materials will be made available following the study’s completion.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Wait list control design. Participants assigned to the control group will receive a condensed version of the intervention at the completion of the study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/03/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>234</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>HMRI Clinical Research Centre
Level 3 John Hunter Hospital 
Lookout Road, New Lambton Heights
NSW 2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>HMRI Clinical Research Centre
Level 3 John Hunter Hospital 
Lookout Road, New Lambton Heights
NSW 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this group randomised control trial is to develop, implement and evaluate a school-based intervention to promote physical activity and improve fundamental movement skill (FMS) proficiency in children from disadvantaged primary schools. The 12-month intervention will include professional development workshops for teachers and students, school policy review and recommendations, community and parental engagement in the intervention process, student-led recess and lunchtime activities, and physical activity equipment packs. Physical activity behaviour, FMS competency, self esteem, physiological outcomes and potential mediators of behaviour change will be assessed. Assessments will be conducted at baseline 6- and 12-months.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Published articles: Lubans, D. R., Morgan, P. J., Weaver, K., Callister, R., Dewar, D. L., Costigan, S. A., Plotnikoff, R. C. (2012). Rationale and study protocol for the Supporting Children's Outcomes using Rewards, Exercise and Skills (SCORES) group randomized controlled trial: A physical activity and fundamental movement skills intervention for primary schools in low-income communities. BMC Public Health. 
Cohen, K.E., Morgan, P.J., Plotnikoff, R.C., Callister, R., and Lubans, D.R. (2014). Fundamental movement skills and physical activity among children living in low-income communities: a cross-sectional study. International Journal of Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity. 11(49) . 
The paper has been accepted as a poster presentation at the International Congress on Physical Activity and Public Health: Weaver, K., Lubans, D. R., Morgan, P. J., Callister, R., Dewar, D. L., Costigan, S. A., Plotnikoff, R. C. (2012). Rationale and intervention description of the Supporting Childrens Outcomes using Rewards, Exercise and Skills physical activity intervention. International Congress on Physical Activity and Public Health, October 31 - November 3, Sydney, Australia. 

The following abstracts were presented at the AIESEP World Congress Conference held in Auckland in February 2014: 
Cohen, K.E., Morgan, P.J., Plotnikoff, R.E., Callister, R., &amp; Lubans, D.R. (under revision) Fundamental movement skill competency and objectively measured physical activity amongst children living in low-income communities. 
Morgan, P.J., Barnett, L.M., Cliff, D.P., Okely, A, D.,, Scott, H.A., Weaver, K., &amp; Lubans, D. R. (2013). Effectiveness of interventions to improve fundamental movement skill proficiency in youth: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Pediatrics, 132(5), 1361-1383. 
Cohen, K.E., Morgan, P.J., Plotnikoff, R.C., Callister, R., &amp; Lubans, D.R. Physical Activity and Movement Skills Intervention: The SCORES Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial. 
Under revision: 
Cohen, K.E., Morgan, P.J., Plotnikoff, R.C., Callister, R., and Lubans, D.R. (under revision). Physical Activity and Skills Intervention: SCORES Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial. Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive
Callaghan 
NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>H-2011-0214</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Education and Training</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2011200</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Lubans</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 2049</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 2084</fax>
      <email>David.Lubans@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Lubans</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 2049</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 2084</fax>
      <email>David.Lubans@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Lubans</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 2049</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 2084</fax>
      <email>David.Lubans@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Lubans</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 2049</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Lubans@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>