<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1434">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/06/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000067471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of the Practitioner Asthma Communication and Education (PACE) Australia Program</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to measure the impact of the Practitioner Asthma Communication and Education (PACE) Australia program on the process and outcomes of general practioners' management of children with asthma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PACE Australia Phase 3</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Childhood asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The PACE Australia intervention for General Practitioners (GPs) comprised two structured 3-hour interactive sessions one week apart. Eight PACE workshops were held from February 2007 to April 2008 for intervention group GPs. Attendance was set at a maximum of 15 GPs per workshop. The specific aims of the PACE workshops were to improve GP practice in the following key areas: appropriate use of medications, writing an asthma action plan, communication between patient and doctor to improve adherence and patient education and giving instructions on the correct use of aerosol delivery devices.</interventions>
    <comparator>General practitioners (GPs) were randomly allocated to be wait listed to receive the PACE Australia workshops after patients have had 12 months follow up.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of paediatric asthma patients having a written Asthma Action Plan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 12 months follow up post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Process outcomes were assessed at baseline and at 12 months follow up using validated questionnaires: (1) GP communication and teaching behaviour ; (2) GP adherence to National Asthma Council paediatric asthma management guidelines ; (3) Proportion of children who have completed the Asthma Cycle of Care item numbers;</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 12 months follow up post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children's outcomes were collected over 12 months by telephone interviews: (1) Medication use ; (2) Number of unscheduled and scheduled consultations ; (3) Days missed from school or child care ; (4) Satisfaction with care provided by the GP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 12 months follow up post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>GPs:All interested GPs in the Western &amp; Central Sydney Area. The inclusion criteria for families were a child between the ages of 2 and 14 years with a diagnosis of asthma; only one child per family was eligible to participate and a level of English fluency was necessary to enable participation in telephone-administered questionnaires.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: only one child per family; parents who aren't fluent in English for interviewing purpose.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Use of an independent body to generate the randomisation sequence by using minimisation to balance participant numbers over three levels (gender; Division of General Practice; FRACGP membership).</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated random number sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Double blinded: Family (patient) participants, data analyst</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/07/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Primary Health Care Education &amp; Research Unit, Faculty of Medicine, University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Westmead Hospital, PO Box 533, Westmead NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Chronic Disease Programs Section, Chronic Disease Branch, Mental Health and Chronic Disease Division, Australian Government Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848 MDP4
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Practitioner Asthma Communication and Education (PACE) Australia study is a collaborative project of the University of Sydney, The Woolcock Institute of Medical Research, The Royal Childrens Hospital, Melbourne and the University of Michigan, funded by the Australian Government Department of Health and Ageing. 
The aim of the study was to assess the impact of an evidencebased paediatric asthma program for GPs on GP practice and family health outcomes.
We recruited a total of 150 GPs and 221 patients from western and central Sydney. We performed a randomised controlled trial with intervention GPs randomly allocated to receive the PACE workshops. Comparison GPs did not receive the PACE workshops until the end of the study.
The PACE workshops comprised two 3-hour interactive sessions led by asthma experts. These sessions focussed on best practice approaches to paediatric asthma management and communication strategies with parents. 
Outcome measures for both GPs and patients were determined at baseline and 12 months.
Following the PACE Australia workshops:
1.	GPs reported increased use of the recommended communication strategies with their patients; increased use of the Asthma Cycle of Care item numbers and more frequent provision of written asthma action plans.
2.	Families of intervention GPs reported increased receipt of asthma action plans and spacer devices, as well as more appropriate medication use. 
The program resulted in significant improvements in the way in which GPs manage asthma consultations, particularly with regard to doctor-patient communication and adherence to asthma management guidelines with a resultant improvement in key patient outcomes. 
The PACE Australia workshops were highly rated by all participating GPs. Heres what some GPs said:
Improved my communication with patients and my knowledge and use of asthma devices. 
I have been able to provide more useful education to the patients by using the models provided at the workshop.
I have been more interactive with parents &amp; child, involving child more in treatment planning.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>The PACE Australia workshop educator’s and train the trainer’s manual will be available online through the Asthma Foundation of Victoria website http://www.asthma.org.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>2010
	Shah S, SM Sawyer, CM Mellis, BG Toelle, JK Peat, JK Roydhouse, M Lagleva, P Edwards, T Usherwood, CR Jenkins&amp; Clark NM (accepted for oral presentation).  Improving Paediatric Asthma Management Through Provider Education: A Randomised Controlled Trial, 2010 Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand Annual Scientific Meeting, March 2010, Brisbane &amp; 2010 American Thoracic Society Annual Meeting, May 2010, New Orleans

o	To be submitted to the British Medical Journal: ?Authors A randomised controlled trial to test the effectiveness of the Practitioner Asthma Communication and Education (PACE) Australia program. 
	Roydhouse JK, Shah S, Toelle BG, Sawyer SM, Peat JK, Jenkins CR on behalf of PACE Australia (submitted for oral presentation). Paediatric asthma education and communication in general practice: what do doctors and parents say? 2010 Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand Annual Scientific Meeting, March 2010, Brisbane &amp; 2010 American Thoracic Society Annual Meeting, May 2010, New Orleans

2009
	Smita Shah, Jessica K. Roydhouse, Craig Mellis, Brett Toelle, Susan M Sawyer, Christine Jenkins for PACE Australia (accepted for poster presentation), Evaluation of asthma education and communication skills workshops for general practitioners, 2009 General Practitioner &amp; Primary Health Care Research Conference, 15 - 17 July 2009, Melbourne

	Smita Shah, Jessica K. Roydhouse, Brett Toelle, Susan M Sawyer, Christine Jenkins for PACE Australia (accepted for oral presentation), The status of paediatric asthma management in Australian general practice, 2009 General Practitioner &amp; Primary Health Care Research Conference, 15 - 17 July 2009, Melbourne

o	To be submitted to the Primary Care Respiratory Journal: Roydhouse JK, Shah S, Toelle B, Sawyer SM, CR Jenkins. Australian GPs attitudes, levels of confidence and self-reported practice regarding paediatric asthma management


	Smita Shah, Jessica K. Roydhouse, Craig Mellis, Brett Toelle, Susan M Sawyer, Christine Jenkins for PACE Australia (accepted for poster presentation), Evaluation of asthma education and communication skills workshops for general practitioners, 2009 American Thoracic Society Annual Scientific Meeting, San Diego 

	Jessica K. Roydhouse, Smita Shah, Brett Toelle, Susan M Sawyer, Christine Jenkins for PACE Australia (accepted for oral presentation), The status of paediatric asthma management in Australian general practice, 2009 American Thoracic Society Annual Meeting, San Diego

	Smita Shah, Jessica K. Roydhouse, Craig Mellis, Brett Toelle, Susan M Sawyer, Christine Jenkins for PACE Australia (oral presentation), Evaluation of asthma education and communication skills workshops for general practitioners, 2009 Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand Annual Scientific Meeting, Darwin
o	Published as: S Shah, JK Roydhouse, B Toelle, SM Sawyer, C Jenkins. Evaluation of asthma education and communication skills workshops for general practitioners, Respirology 2009 14, (Suppl 1) A 30 

	Jessica K. Roydhouse, Smita Shah, Brett Toelle, Susan M Sawyer, Christine Jenkins for PACE Australia (poster presentation), The status of paediatric asthma management in NSW general practice, 2009 Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand Annual Scientific Meeting, Darwin
o	Published as: Jessica K Roydhouse, Smita Shah, Brett Toelle, Susan M Sawyer, Christine Jenkins, for PACE Australia. The status of paediatric asthma management in NSW general practice, Respirology 2009 14, (Suppl 1) A 80 

2008
	Smita Shah, Jessica K. Roydhouse, Brett Toelle, Susan Sawyer, Christine Jenkins, for the PACE Australia Management Committee (poster presentation), Recruitment For A RCT In Primary Care: What works best? 27  29 August 2008, Westmead Hospital Research Week, Sydney

	Smita Shah, Jessica K. Roydhouse, Brett Toelle, Susan Sawyer, Christine Jenkins, for the PACE Australia Management Committee, Recruitment For A RCT In Primary Care: What works best? 28  31 May 2008, International Primary Care Respiratory Group 4th World Conference, Seville (oral presentation)

	Roydhouse JK, Shah S, Toelle B, Sawyer S, Mellis C, Jenkins C, for the PACE Australia Management Committee, Strategies used in Recruitment for a Randomised Controlled Trial in Primary Care, 16  21 May 2008, American Thoracic Society Annual Meeting, Toronto (poster presentation) 
o	Published as: Roydhouse JK, Shah S, Toelle B, Sawyer S, Jenkins C. Strategies used in Recruitment for a RCT in Primary Care, Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2008 April; 177 (Abstracts Issue), A576.

	Smita Shah, Jessica K. Roydhouse, Brett Toelle, Susan Sawyer, Christine Jenkins, for the PACE Australia Management Committee, Strategies Used In Recruitment For A RCT In Primary Care, 29 March  3 April 2008, Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand Annual Meeting, Melbourne (poster presentation).
o	Published as: Shah S, Roydhouse JK, Toelle B, Sawyer S, Jenkins C. Strategies used in Recruitment for a RCT in Primary Care, Respirology 2008 13, (2) A 68 

2007
	Shah S, Toelle B, Roydhouse J, Sawyer S &amp; Jenkins C, Partnerships and challenges in recruitment for a RCT in primary care, 29 November 2007, 4th Biennial NSW Primary Health Care Research &amp; Evaluation Conference, Sydney (oral presentation)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney West Area Health Service-Westmead Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/06/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/4/4/11(2334)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/07/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>9379</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service-Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>New ethics address. Please modify.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X07-0024</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Smita Shah</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care Education and Research Unit, University of Sydney, Westmead Hospital PO Box 533 Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98456505</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98455310</fax>
      <email>smita_shah@wsahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Smita Shah</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care Education and Research Unit, University of Sydney, Westmead Hospital PO Box 533 Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98456505</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98455310</fax>
      <email>smita_shah@wsahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Smita Shah</name>
      <address>Primary Health Care Education and Research Unit, University of Sydney, Westmead Hospital PO Box 533 Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98456505</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98455310</fax>
      <email>smita_shah@wsahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>