<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83829">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000332224</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Do wheeled walkers increase physical activity in people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), does the use of a wheeled walker in the home and community change daily physical activity?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Not applicable</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>On completion of a pulmonary rehabilitation program, participants will be randomised to either Group 1 or 2 using a computer-generated random number sequence. Following randomisation, a Research Assistant will visit the homes of all participants. Those participants randomised to Group 1 will receive a wheeled walker during the first home visit and a Research Assistant will provide standardised instructions regarding its use and encourage daily ambulation with the device. Those participants randomised to Group 2 will receive encouragement regarding daily ambulation, but no wheeled walker. Four weeks after the first home visit, participants will be provided with two devices that measure physical activity and instructed to wear the devices for 5 days. At the end of these 5 days, a Research Assistant will perform a second home visit to collect the devices and other outcome measures.  Those participants randomised Group 1 will have their wheeled walker removed and those participants randomised Group 2 will have a wheeled walker issued and be provided with standardised instructions regarding its use. During this home visit, all participants will receive the same encouragement from a Research Assistant to perform daily ambulation. Four weeks later, participants will again be provided with the devices that measure physical activity and instructed to wear them for 5 days. At the end of this 5 day period, a Research Assistant will perform a third and final home visit to collect the devices and other outcome measures. The four week period of time without the wheeled walker represents the 'wash-out' period.</interventions>
    <comparator>At the beginning of the control period, participants will receive encouragement to ambulate during daily life. They will continue to receive usual medical care. That is, they will continue with their usual medications and see their doctor as required. This will be the same for all participants during the control period. The control period will be 5 weeks in duration (four weeks "wash-out" and one week of assessment).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily physical activity will be measured during the waking hours of five consecutive days using the ActivPAL and Stepwatch activity monitors. Participants will also be asked to estimate how the average amount of time they spent walking during the preceding week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4-5 weeks and 9-10 weeks after enrollment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life will be measured using the Chronic Respiratory Disease Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Health-related quality of life will be measured once 4-5 weeks weeks after enrollment and once 9-10 weeks after enrollment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of falling will be measured using a standardised questionnaire called the Survey of Activities and Fear of falling in the Eldery (SAFE).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fear of falling will be measured once 4-5 weeks after enrollment and once 9-10 weeks after enrollment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wheeled walker use will be measured using a magnetic odemeter on the front wheel of the walker.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The number of wheel revolutions (i.e. wheeled walker use) made during the time the participant has the device will be recorded. That is, wheeled walker use will be recorded once 4-5 weeks after enrollment or once 9-10 weeks after enrollment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preference (with vs. without wheeled walker) will be measured using standardised questions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of COPD
Six-minute walk distance &lt; 450 m prior to pulmonary rehabilitation 
Deemed approp for a wheeled walker by a physiotherapist</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>use of a wheeled walker for more than 2 weeks prior to commencing pulmonary rehabilitation
any co-morbid condition that limits mobility</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified during participation in a pulmonary rehabilitation program. Once consent is obtained, subjects will be randomly allocated to one of two groups. The randomisation sequence will be concealed using opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random number sequence, blocked for groups of 4, stratified according to oxygen use.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/12/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Bentley Health Service - Bentley</hospital>
    <hospital>Swan Districts Hospital - Middle Swan</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Sue Jenkins</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Kylie Hill</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Peter Eastwood</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nola Cecins</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Curtin University of Technology</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA, 6845</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will determine: (i) to what extent people with COPD choose to use a wheeled walker in day-to-day life; (ii) whether providing a wheeled walker for use in their home and community increases their level of daily physical activity and; (iii) whether use of a wheeled walker improves quality of life or increases an individuals confidence to walk (i.e. they feel less fearful of falling). 

A total of 30 patients with COPD will participate in the study. On the completion of a pulmonary rehabilitation program, people with COPD that are considered appropriate for a wheeled walker will complete two consecutive four week periods.  During one of these periods, but not the other, they will have a wheeled walker provided for use during daily life. Measurements of wheeled walker usage, daily physical activity, quality of life and fear of falling will be collected on completion of each four-week period and compared in order to determine the effect of a wheeled walker on these outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>C Ng, S Jenkins, N Cecins, P Eastwood &amp; K Hill (2010) Measurement of Physical Activity in People with COPD Who Use a Wheeled Walker. Poster presentation at SCGH Research week, September 2010, Perth, Western Australia 

C Ng, S Jenkins, N Cecins, P Eastwood &amp; K Hill (2010) Evaluation and Optimisation of Physical Activity in Individuals with COPD: The use of wheeled walkers. Oral presentation at LIWA 12th August 2010, Perth, Western Australia

C Ng, S Jenkins, N Cecins, P Eastwood &amp; K Hill (2011) Measurement Properties of Two Accelerometers in People with COPD: Effect of Walk Speed and 4-Wheeled Walker Use. Poster presentation at TSANZ, 4th Apr 2011, Perth, Western Australia
 
C Ng, S Jenkins, N Cecins, P Eastwood &amp; K Hill (2011) Measurement Properties of Two Accelerometers in People with COPD: Effect of Walk Speed and 4-Wheeled Walker Use. Poster presentation on 28th Nov 2011 at SCGH Physiotherapy Department, Perth, Western Australia

Li Whye Cindy Ng, Sue Jenkins &amp; Kylie Hill (2011) Accuracy and Responsiveness of the Stepwatch Activity Monitor and ActivPAL in Patients with COPD when Walking with and without a Rollator, Disability and Rehabilitation, 2012, 34:1317-1322

 

C Ng, S Jenkins, N Cecins, P Eastwood &amp; K Hill (2012) A Wheeled Walker on Physical Activity in People with COPD: Preliminary Data. Poster presentation at TSANZ, 1st Apr 2012, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/o Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Area Health Service Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/o Fremantle Hospital and Health Service
Alma Street Fremantle
Western Australia 6160</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>S/10/192</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Perth Hospital
Room 5105 level 5 , Colonial House
197 Wellington St, 
Perth CBD 
Western Australia 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA-10/007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/03/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swan Kalamunda Health Service Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Swan Kalamunda Health Service
Executive Office
PO Box 195
Midland
Western Australia 6936</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Ref no: 032</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Hill</name>
      <address>c/o Physiotherapy Dept,
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital,
Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 4408</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 9346 3037</fax>
      <email>K.Hill@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Hill</name>
      <address>c/o Physiotherapy Dept,
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital,
Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 4408</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 9346 3037</fax>
      <email>K.Hill@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Hill</name>
      <address>c/o Physiotherapy Dept,
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital,
Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 4408</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 9346 3037</fax>
      <email>K.Hill@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Hill</name>
      <address>c/o Physiotherapy Dept, Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, Hospital Ave, Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 4408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>K.Hill@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>