<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347965">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000105842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Follow-up study on participants who participated in Institute for Eye Research Protocol (IERP2007-009) - Myopia progression in children: multifocal soft contact lenses versus single vision soft contact lenses</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Follow-up study on participants who previously participated in IERP2007-009 ("Myopia progression in children: multifocal soft contact lenses versus single vision soft contact lenses") to determine their current ocular refractive status and collect questionnaire data.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>IERP2007-009 was registered with ANZCTR. Registration number: ACTRN12611001148965</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cycloplegic refraction and ocular axial length.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Myopia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cycloplegic refractive error will be measured both objectively and subjectively; ocular axial length will be measured using a Zeiss IOL master. Cycloplegia will be achieved using diagnostic eye drops (1% tropicamide and 0.4% oxybuprocaine).</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable as study is observational</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the rate of myopia progression, as assessed by cycloplegic autorefraction, in children and adolescents who participated in IERP2007-009.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This study involves only 1 visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the characteristics of the peripheral refraction profiles in children and adolescents following participation in IERP2007-009. Peripheral refraction will be measured using a Shin Nippon open-field autorefractor or eyemapper instrument.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This study involves only 1 visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To obtain a history of the refractive correction chosen by the participants since they completed IERP2007-009 and their lifestyle variables. This outcome will be assessed using questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This study involves only 1 visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>have successfully enrolled in study IERP2007-009 
be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent (or their parent(s)/legal guardian);
if under 18 years of age, be accompanied by their parent(s)/legal guardian when signing the informed consent form;
be willing to comply with the clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the investigator;
have ocular health findings considered to be normal;</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>21</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude the use of diagnostic eye drops (1% tropicamide and 0.4% oxybuprocaine).
a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication up to 12 weeks prior to and during the trial;
any systemic disease that may affect ocular health. Conditions such as systemic hypertension do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
any systemic or topical medications up to 12 weeks prior to and during the trial that will affect ocular physiology; 
had eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>26</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Brien Holden Vision Institute (previously known as the Institute for Eye Research) conducted a clinical trial to test commercially-available multifocal contact lenses for their potential to control the progression of myopia in children(IERP2007-009, ACTRN12611001148965). The trial was completed in 2008. Approximately half of the 40 children who participated in trial IERP2007-009 were enrolled in a subsequent myopia control trial at the Brien Holden Vision Institute (IER2008-001, ACTRN12611001141932) in which all participants wore the test product of trial IERP2007-009. This research is based on the hypothesis that the peripheral retina plays a role in controlling the refractive development of the eye as shown in animal experiments (Smith et al. 2007).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road, Dulwich, South Australia, 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fabian Conrad</name>
      <address>Level 5 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+612 93857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.conrad@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fabian Conrad</name>
      <address>Level 5 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+612 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+612 93857401</fax>
      <email>f.conrad@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>