<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364164">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000511730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ILLUMENATE Global (ProspectIve, SingLe-Arm, Global MuLti-Center Study to EvalUate TreatMent of Obstructive SupErficial Femoral Artery or Popliteal LesioNs With A Novel PacliTaxel-CoatEd Percutaneous Angioplasty Balloon)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>ILLUMENATE Global: Prospective, single-arm, global multi-center study to evaluate the safety and performance of the CVI paclitaxel-coated percutaneous angioplasty balloon catheter in the treatment of de novo or restenotic lesions (excluding in-stent lesions) in the superficial and/or popliteal arteries to establish blood flow and to maintain vessel patency.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Percutaneous Transluminal Angioplasty will be completed using a 2.0  micrograms per square millimeter. Paclitaxel-Coated Balloon.  Balloon will be inflated to a size appropriate for the target vessel, as determined by the physician.  Total balloon inflation time is determined by the physician, but no less than one minute.  </interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Safety Endpoint: Freedom from device and procedure-related death through 30 days post-procedure and freedom from target limb major amputation and clinical driven target lesion revascularization through 12 months post-procedure. Primary Efficacy Endpoint: Primary patency at 12 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 12 months post-procedure.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major Adverse Event (MAE) rate through discharge and at 1, 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure, defined as a composite rate of cardiovascular death, major unplanned index limb amputation, and clinical driven target lesion revascularization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of adverse events through discharge, and at 1, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months post-procedure, defined as any untoward medical occurrence, unintended disease or injury, or untoward clinical signs in subjects. This definition includes all events related to the investigational medical device and to the procedures involved.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of clinically-driven target lesion revascularization at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of clinically-driven target vessel revascularization (TVR) at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of major amputation of the target limb at 6, 12, 24 and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24 and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause mortality rate at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of occurrence of arterial thrombosis of the treated segment at 1, 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of ipsilateral embolic events of the study limb within 30 days post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary patency rate at 6, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.  Primary patency is defined as the absence of target lesion restenosis per duplex ultrasound (peak systolic velocity ratio [PSVR] = 2.5) and freedom from clinically-driven target limb revascularization.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lesion success, defined as achievement of a final in-lesion residual diameter stenosis of = 50% (per angiographic core lab), after using the investigational device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After using the investigational device</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Technical success, defined as achievement of a final in-lesion residual diameter stenosis of less than or equal to 50% (per angiographic core lab), using the CVI paclitaxel-coated PTA balloon catheter without a device malfunction.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>After using the investigation device.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical success (per subject) defined as technical success without the occurrence of major adverse events during procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural success (per subject) defined as lesion success without the occurrence of major adverse events during procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Ankle-Brachial Index (ABI) from baseline to 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure in subjects with compressible arteries and baseline ABI &lt; 0.9. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Walking Impairment Questionnaire (WIQ) score from baseline to 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Rutherford Clinical Category (RCC) from baseline to 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in EQ-5D from baseline to 6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12, 24, and 36 months post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>General Inclusion Criteria 1. Has clinically significant symptomatic leg ischemia, requiring treatment of the SFA and/or popliteal artery. 2. Has a Rutherford Clinical Category of 2 - 4. Note: Rutherford Clinical Category 2-3 subjects should be entered into the study if conservative treatment and/or medicinal therapy have been unsuccessful. 3. Is at least 18 years old. 4. Has life expectancy &gt; 1 year. 5. Is able and willing to provide written informed consent prior to study-specific procedures. 6. Is willing and capable of complying with the required follow-up visits, testing schedule and medication regimen. Angiographic Inclusion Criteria 1. Has evidence at the target lesion(s) of clinically and hemodynamically significant de novo stenosis or restenosis, or occlusion, in the SFA (1 cm distal to the ostium of the profunda) and/or popliteal artery, confirmed by angiography. 2. Has target limb with at least one patent (&lt;50% stenosis) tibio-peroneal run-off vessel to the foot confirmed by baseline angiography or magnetic resonance angiography (MRA) or computed tomography angiography (CTA). Note: Treatment of outflow disease is NOT permitted. 3. Has 1 or 2 target lesion(s) with a cumulative length of no more than 20 cm. 4. Has target lesion(s) located &gt;2 cm from any stent if the target vessel was previously stented. 5. Has a reference vessel diameter of 4 - 6 mm. 6. Has a successful exchangeable guidewire crossing of the lesion(s).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>General Exclusion Criteria 1. Is pregnant, of childbearing potential not taking adequate contraceptive measures, or nursing. 2. Has significant gastrointestinal bleeding or any coagulopathy that would contraindicate the use of anti-platelet therapy 3. Has known intolerance to study medications, paclitaxel or contrast agents that in the opinion of the investigator cannot be adequately pre-treated. 4. Is currently participating in another investigational device or drug study that would interfere with study endpoints. 5. Has history of hemorrhagic stroke within 3 months. 6. Has surgical or endovascular procedure of the target limb within 14 days prior to the index procedure. 7. Has any planned surgical intervention (requiring hospitalization) or endovascular procedure within 30 days after the index procedure. 8. Has had a previous peripheral bypass affecting the target limb. 9. Has unstable angina pectoris, myocardial infarction, liver failure, renal failure or chronic kidney disease within 30 days of the index procedure. Angiographic Exclusion Criteria 1. Has significant stenosis (greater than or equal to 50%) or occlusion of inflow tract that is not successfully revascularized (&lt; 30% residual stenosis without death or major vascular complication) prior to treatment of the target lesion(s). Treatment of target lesion(s) is acceptable after successful treatment of inflow artery lesion(s). 2. Has an acute or sub-acute intraluminal thrombus within the target vessel. 3. Has in-stent restenosis or restenosis of the target lesion following previous treatment with a drug-coated balloon. 4. Has an aneurysmal target vessel. 5. Has perforation, dissection or other injury of the access or target vessel requiring stenting or surgical intervention prior to enrollment. 6. Has no normal arterial segment proximal to the target lesion in which duplex ultrasound velocity ratios can be measured. 7. Requires use of adjunctive therapies (i.e., laser, atherectomy, cryoplasty, scoring/cutting balloons, brachytherapy). 8. Has severe calcification that precludes adequate PTA treatment. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The subject is enrolled in the study after he/she has signed the subject informed consent, it has been determined that he/she meets all of the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria, and the pre-dilatation has been completed.  The point of enrollment is defined as the moment the investigational device enters the vasculature.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>370</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Enrolling by invitation</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Covidien</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>3033 Campus Drive N550
Plymouth, MN 55441</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Covidien</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>3033 Campus Drive N550
Plymouth, MN 55441</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Single-Arm Multicenter Study to continue to assess the safety and performance of the CVI Paclitaxel-Coated PTA Balloon Catheter in the treatment of de novo or restenotic lesions in the superficial femoral and/or popliteal arteries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disabiltities Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/NTA/84</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Holden</name>
      <address>Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road
Grafton, Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>64 9 3797 440</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrewh@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Charis Sugden</name>
      <address>Covidien
3033 Campus Drive N550
Plymouth, MN 55441</address>
      <phone>1 763-398-7713</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>charis.sugden@covidien.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Charis Sugden</name>
      <address>Covidien
3033 Campus Drive N550
Plymouth, MN 55441</address>
      <phone>1 763-398-7713</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>charis.sugden@covidien.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kirsten Overby</name>
      <address>Covidien 3033 Campus Drive N550 Plymouth, MN 55441  </address>
      <phone>+1 763 398 7320</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kirsten.Overby@covidien.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>