<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367416">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001255673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>High intensity interval training for smoking cessation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>HIIT to Quit: A pilot study to evaluate the effect of high intensity interval training versus lifestyle physical activity on smoking cessation in women currently smoking at least 10 cigarettes per day</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HIIT to Quit</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>High intensity interval training
12 weeks duration
2 supervised (one-on-one supervision by an exercise physiologist) session per week, The 35 minute protocol consists of: warm-up at 65% HRmax (5 min); 4 x 4 minute intervals at 85-90% HRmax, interspersed with 3 minutes recovery at 65% HRmax; and cool down (5 min). 
the mode of exercise will be treadmill or cycle ergometer, determined by participant preference.
1 unsupervised session using Borg Scale for intensity, using participants own equipment or environment. Borg scale intensity will correspond to the  intensity indicated at the baseline measure corresponding to 85-90% HRmax.
Adherence monitored by supervised sessions attended and self report of unsupervised sessions
Participants also receive Quitline quit packs and quit apps, both the quit pack and app (available from Quitline) covers planning and preparing to quit, strategies for quit success, and coping with cravings and relapse. The quit pack and app provides two options for participants to receive this support. </interventions>
    <comparator>Lifestyle physical activity
12 week duration
Using pedometers with the aim of increasing daily steps to 10,000
A weekly phone call and sms will be provided to monitor progress and barriers. There will be no face to face supervised sessions.
Adherence monitored by log book and 10,000 steps website
Participants also receive Quitline quit packs and quit apps, both the quit pack and app (available from Quitline) covers planning and preparing to quit, strategies for quit success, and coping with cravings and relapse. The quit pack and app provides two options for participants to receive this support. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of participants who have ceased smoking 

Identified using the Russell standard, self-reported abstinence (previous 2 weeks) and carbon monoxide concentration of less than 10ppm.</outcome>
      <timepoint>13 and 26 weeks after randomisation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of cigarettes smoked on a daily basis.

Self report</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Withdrawal symptoms and cravings

Assessed using the Moods and Physical Symptoms Scale (MPSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 3, 6, 9, 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking dependency

Assessed using the Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependance (FTND) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 6, 13 and 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective stress

Assessed using the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 3, 6, 9 ,12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Well-being

Assessed using the SF36</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motivation

Assessed using the Behavioural Regulation in Exercise Questionnaire (BREQ-2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiorespiratory fitness (VO2max) 

The fitness test will be the Modified Bruce Protocol Stress Test. The treadmill is started at 2.74 km/hr (1.7 mph) and at a gradient (or incline) of 0%. The incline and speed of the treadmill increases every three minutes.The participant must breathe through a tube while exercising, for analysis of oxygen and carbon dioxide concentrations (metabolic cart). They must wear a nose-peg to ensure complete breathing through the mouth. The participant will rate their perceived exertion (Rating of Perceived Exertion  Borg scale) every 3 minutes during the test. The test will stop when they want it to, which will be communicated to the researcher using a hand signal. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function

forced vital capacity [FVC], forced expiratory volume in 1 second [FEV1], FEV1/ FVC ratio, and peak expiratory flow rate [PEFR]) will be assessed using a Vitalograph</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition

BMI (height, weight), waist circumference and waist to hip ratio</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity and sedentary behaviour

Measured using a wrist-worn GENEActiv tri-axial accelerometer for a 7-day period at each time-point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Demographic information

A self-report questionnaire designed for the study will include questions related to age, education, occupation, income, health history, smoking history
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 13 and 26 weeks with relevant repeated questions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Currently smoking at least 10 cigarettes per day 
Want to quit
Willing to exercise (able to attend the gym twice weekly)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Already using pharmacological quit smoking aids
Medical problems that increase risk of exercise adverse events (including unstable angina, pulmonary disease, uncontrolled hypertension, cardiomyopathty, orthepedic or neurological limitations)
Planned operation during research period
Current or planned pregnancy
Drug or alcohol abuse
Reluctance to sign consent form
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who meet the eligibility criteria will be randomised into one of 2 groups: 1) HITT or 2) 10,000 steps. The randomisation will be conducted at UQ by a statistician not associated with the trial. The allocation will be provided to us via email</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer program will be used to generate the random sequence</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This pilot study aims to assess the feasibility of conducting an RCT to compare the efficacy of two exercise interventions for smoking cessation. We will use the results to inform the sample size for a larger trial, and to evaluate the potential utility of using each of the measures in women who smoke.  Funding allows for 80 participants (40 per group). Descriptive statistics will be used to summarize characteristics of participants in each group, and to describe those who successfully quit. Analysis of the primary outcome will be by Yates corrected Chi-squared test for differences in the proportions who quit in each group. Changes in categorical (eg smoking abstinence) and continuous (eg number of cigarettes smoked) variables will be assessed using general linear modeling.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4000 - Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brisbane St Lucia, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Heart Foundation, Level 12, 500 Collins Street, Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of this project are: (1) compare the effects of two exercise interventions (High Intensity Interval Training [HIIT] and 10,000 steps) combined with usual care smoking cessation support, on the cessation rates of female smokers wishing to quit; (2) assess the effects of HIIT and 10,000 steps for weight management during quit attempts; and (3) assess whether improvements in fitness, vitality and intrinsic motivation are mediators of the relationship between HITT and smoking cessation. We hypothesise that HIIT will provide higher smoking cessation rates than 10,000 steps.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cumbrae-Stewart Building, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014001266</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Toby Pavey</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies, Blair Drive, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia Campus, Brisbane, Australia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 9898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.pavey@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Toby Pavey</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies, Blair Drive, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia Campus, Brisbane, Australia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 9898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.pavey@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Toby Pavey</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies, Blair Drive, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia Campus, Brisbane, Australia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 9898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.pavey@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Toby Pavey</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies, Blair Drive, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia Campus, Brisbane, Australia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 9898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.pavey@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>