<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372863">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000864325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A clinical registry to monitor outcomes of shoulder and elbow pathology</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A clinical quality registry to monitor outcomes of shoulder and elbow pathology among private patients referred to an orthopaedic clinic</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1196-2935</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CROSEP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>MSEC - CROSEP</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Shoulder arthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Elbow arthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Shoulder dislocation/recurrent instability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Shoulder rotator cuff pathology</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Clavicle/humerus/scapula fracture</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acromioclavicular dislocation/instability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Elbow trauma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Shoulder arthroplasty complication/revision/failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Elbow tendon pathology</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients presenting with pathologies of the shoulder or elbow and referred to specialist orthopaedic review. 

1. Patients diagnosed with either a recent shoulder dislocation or clinically defined glenohumeral instability: Treated with non-operative management or surgical stabilisation. Followed for a duration of 2 years.

2. Patients diagnosed with rotator cuff pathology (subacromial impingement; tendinopathy; tear): Treated with non-operative management or surgical repair. Followed for a duration of 2 years.

3. Patients diagnosed with acromioclavicular instability of any aetiology: Treated with non-operative management or surgical stabilisation. Followed for a duration of 2 years.

4. Patients diagnosed with glenohumeral arthritis of any aetiology: Treated with non-operative management, arthroscopic surgery or total shoulder arthroplasty. Followed for a duration of 5 years.

5.  Patients diagnosed with acute fracture of the scapula, clavicle or humerus (including associated glenohumeral dislocation): Treated with non-operative management, internal fixation or total shoulder arthroplasty. Followed for a duration of 2 years.

6. Patients presenting with a symptomatic issue related to an in-situ arthroplasty prosthesis: Managed non-operatively or treated surgically with reoperation, minor or major device revision. Followed for a duration of 2 years.

7. Patients diagnosed with frozen shoulder, prominent hardware of the shoulder, extrinsic tendon injury or neuological injury affecting the shoulder: Managed non-operatively or treated surgically (arthroscopic or open repair). Followed for a duration of 2 years.

8. Patients diagnosed with elbow arthritis of any aetiology: Managed non-operatively or treated surgically (arthroscopically or joint arthroplasty). Followed for a duration of 5 years.

9. Patients diagnosed with fracture, ligament injury or instability event about the elbow: Managed non-operatively or treated surgically (stabilisation, repair or internal fixation). Followed for a duration of 2 years.

10. Patients diagnosed with tendon injury about the elbow (rupture, tear or tendinopathy); Managed non-operatively or repaired surgically. Followed for a duration of 2 years.

11. Patients presenting with a primary diagnosis of the elbow not matching other cohorts: Managed non-operatively or treated surgically. Followed for a duration of 2 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of patients that are deemed a "failure to cure" following definitive treatment 

Insufficient improvement in patient reported outcome measures (function or pain); adverse findings on post-treatment medical imaging; positive signs of instability, weakness or other primary pathology during clinical follow-up; failure to improve shoulder or elbow range of motion

</outcome>
      <timepoint>6months, 12months, 2years and 5years after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the specific pathology.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General health assessed by Veterans Rand - 12 (VR-12)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, and 12months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the specific pathology.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical imaging - radiographs (XR), computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), ultrasound (US) appropriate to the diagnosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 6weeks, 3months, 6months, 12months, 2years and 5years after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the diagnosis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Joint range of motion assessed by goniometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the specific pathology.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications and adverse events: any deviation from the ideal postoperative course that is not inherent in the procedure and does not comprise a failure to cure. E.g. surgical site infection as per the criteria described in Parvizi et al 2011 (CORR, 469). </outcome>
      <timepoint>intraoperatively, 2 weeks, 6weeks, 3months following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shoulder strength in forward elevation, internal rotation, and external rotation, measured using manual muscle testing and graded using the British Medical Research Council (MRC) system. </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the specific pathology.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-reported shoulder function assessed by the American Shoulder and Elbow Score (ASES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months and 24months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the specific pathology.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported shoulder function assessed by Oxford Shoulder Score (OSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months and 24months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the specific pathology.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported shoulder function assessed by the Simple Shoulder Test (SST)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months and 24months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical), depending on the specific pathology.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported shoulder function and instability assessed by the Oxford Shoulder Instability Score (OSIS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months and 24months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported shoulder function and instability assessed by the Western Ontario Should Instability score (WOSI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months and 24months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported shoulder function and rotator cuff pathology symptoms assessed by the Western Ontario Rotator Cuff index (WORC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months and 24months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient reported elbow function assessed by the Patient Rated Elbow Evaluation (PREE)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, 3months, 6months, 12months and 24months after clinical diagnosis within the specialist orthopaedic practice or following definitive treatment (non-operative OR surgical).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients presenting for diagnosis and treatment to one of the participating orthopaedic surgeons as a private patient (private insured, public uninsured as a private patient)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Elects to opt-out of the registry
- Suffers from a neurological, psychological pathology that precludes them from providing patient feedback on treatment outcomes
- unable to provide informed consent to treatment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation; The registry has been designed to capture &gt;80% of patients presenting to the participating clinic as per the inclusion criteria to provide adequate internal validity of the results and generalisability to patients presenting to a private clinic in a major city of Australia.

The registry will routinely report data quality with respect to the core dataset. This will incorporate data completeness, consistency and validity. Registry primary and secondary outcomes will be reported annually.

Analyses relevant to each patient cohort will be pre-planned specific to the prospective questions identified for each.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>5</followup>
    <followuptype>Years</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2027</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/07/2032</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Cabrini Brighton - Brighton</hospital>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital - Bendigo - Bendigo</hospital>
    <hospital>Linacre Private Hospital - Hampton</hospital>
    <postcode>3186 - Brighton</postcode>
    <postcode>3550 - Bendigo</postcode>
    <postcode>3188 - Hampton</postcode>
    <postcode>3186 - Brighton North</postcode>
    <postcode>3550 - Bendigo South</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mr Harry Clitherow</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>31 NORMANBY ST BRIGHTON 3186 VIC - Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mr Harry Clitherow</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>31 NORMANBY ST BRIGHTON 3186 VIC</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mr Brendan Soo</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>31 NORMANBY ST BRIGHTON 3186 VIC - Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>EBM Analytics</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>27/8 Buller Road, Artarmon NSW 2064</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed registry is necessary to monitor the natural history of shoulder pathologies occurring in the general population and to monitor short-term and long-term patient outcomes associated with the condition and contemporary treatment options. The aim of the registry is to objectively assess patient-centred outcomes of definitive management for shoulder and elbow pathologies. 

Patients will be enrolled in an opt-out clinical registry (longitudinal observational design) hosted by the clinic providing diagnosis and treatment of their condition. Patient outcomes, clinical imaging, joint function, as well as treatment and clinical information will be collected as part of standard of care and collated into an electronic registry maintained at the clinic. Patients will be monitored for up to 5years after definitive treatment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cabrini Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>243 New Street Brighton VIC 3186</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CHREC 06-15-05-17</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Harry Clitherow</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre - 31 NORMANBY ST BRIGHTON, VIC 3186</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9592 3388</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>harry@harryclitherow.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mac Cowley</name>
      <address>EBM Analytics - 27/8 Buller Road, Artarmon, NSW 2064</address>
      <phone>+61 43829080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mcowley@ebma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Corey Scholes</name>
      <address>EBM Analytics - 27/8 Buller Road, Artarmon, NSW, 2064</address>
      <phone>+61 411032987</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cscholes@ebma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mac Cowley</name>
      <address>EBM Analytics - 27/8 Buller Road, Artarmon, NSW, 2064</address>
      <phone>+61 434829080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mcowley@ebma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>