<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343022">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000596909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Understanding anaemia among young children of rural Karnataka, India</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The socioeconomic, biochemical, and nutritional determinants of anaemia and micronutrient status among 12-23 month old children living in two districts of rural Karntaka, South India</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-9655</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anaemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Iron Deficiency</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vitamin B12 deficiency</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Folate deficiency</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vitamin A deficiency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To be measured at a single point in time in the home village of the child, during a field survey which was undertaken from August to October 2008:
Laboratory indices: Iron status, Folate status, Vitamin B12 status, Inflammation, Hemoglobinopathy, Hookworm infestation status, Malaria infection status
Nutritional intake: Low iron intake, Continued breastfeeding,
Food insecurity, 
Maternal nutrition: Maternal haemoglobin and anaemia, maternal body mass index. 
Child growth: Stunting, Underweight, Wasting status.
Demographics: wealth, religion, caste</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anaemia in children (haemoglobin &lt;11g/dL)
Measured by automated complete blood count (Sysmex XT-2000i [Sysmex Inc, Kobe, Japan], using an adaption of the cyanmethaemoglobin technique.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cross sectional study, measurements taken at a single point in time, during field survey conducted August-October 2008.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children's Haemoglobin concentrations, measured by automated complete blood count (Sysmex XT-2000i [Sysmex Inc, Kobe, Japan], using an adaption of the cyanmethaemoglobin technique.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cross sectional study, measurements taken at a single point in time, during field survey conducted August-October 2008.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ferritin concentration, electrochemiluminescent immunoassay, ELECSYS 2010 [ELECSYS, Hi- tachi High Technologies Corporation, Tokyo, Japan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cross sectional study, measurements taken at a single point in time, during field survey conducted August-October 2008.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Folate, electrochemiluminescent immunoassay, ELECSYS 2010 [ELECSYS, Hi- tachi High Technologies Corporation, Tokyo, Japan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cross sectional study, measurements taken at a single point in time , during field survey conducted August-October 2008.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>vitamin B12, electrochemiluminescent immunoassay, ELECSYS 2010 [ELECSYS, Hi- tachi High Technologies Corporation, Tokyo, Japan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cross sectional study, measurements taken at a single point in time, during field survey conducted August-October 2008.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>vitamin A (retinol binding protein): nephelometry, Siemens BM Prospec Nephelometer, Marburg, Germany.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cross sectional study, measurements taken at a single point in time, during field survey conducted August-October 2008.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Child born between 12 and 23 months 30/31 days prior to the date of sampling, living in selected villages served by randomly selected subcentres of the study Primary Health Centres. 
Where birth records are unavailable or carers are unaware of the specific birth date, local calendars will be used to identify important dates (eg festivals), and we will ask whether children were born before/ after these dates. We will accept ages and birth dates to within the month.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>23</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:
Any child without a primary carer (mother, father, relative or responsible adult defined as older than 18 years). Where the mother is the primary carer but is younger than 18 years old, the father will be asked to provide additional consent for the childs involvement in the study if he is older than 18 years old. Where both parents are younger than 18 years, consent attained from the mother will be confirmed by a responsible senior member of the village.  

Any child living with a carer whom is unwilling or unable to give informed consent for participation in the study.
Any child currently suffering from an acute medical illness, defined as:
a.	Fever  temperature &gt;38.0 degrees Celsius
b.	Tachypnoea  respiratory rate &gt;45 resps/ minute
c.	Diarrhoea &gt; 4 soft/ watery stools per day, or bloody diarrhoea.
d.	Dehydration  signs of moderate  severe dehydration, including sunken eyes, dry mucous membranes, fewer than 4 wet nappies per day, raised skin turgor, or acidotic breathing. 
e.	Drowsiness, excessive fatigue, lethargy.
f.	Any previous blood transfusion.
g.	Any other acute illness requiring immediate medical attention.
All children will be screened by a medical officer prior to enrolment. Children meeting the above criteria will be transported to the Primary Health Centre for immediate treatment. 

Child refusing cooperation with the study team despite 15 minutes comforting by carer and study team  such children may be visited again later if the carer agrees. 

The total number of children eligible, the number found to be unwell, the number whose carers are not willing to participate, and the total number finally enrolled in the study will be reported.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Random sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>420</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Karnataka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Haematology Research Unit, St John's Research Institute, St Johns National Academy of Health Sciences, Bangalore, India</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St. John's Research Institute,
St. John's National Academy of Health Sciences,
Bangalore 560 034
Karnataka; India</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>India</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Allen Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Allen Foundation Inc.
Post Office Box 1606
Midland, Michigan 48641-1606</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Allen Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Post Office Box 1606
Midland, Michigan 48641-1606</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nossal Institute for Global Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nossal Institute for Global Health
Level 4, Alan Gilbert Building
Corner of Barry and Grattan Streets (161 Barry Street)
The University of Melbourne
Carlton Victoria 3010 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Karuna Trust</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>#686, 16th Main, 4th T - Block Jayanagar
Bangalore - 560011 
Karnataka</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>India</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Anaemia (low haemoglobin) is highly prevalent in India. A recent national study identified that up to 80% of children and 60% of women were anaemic. Anaemia has been associated with impaired growth and development in children, and increased morbidity and maternal mortality in women. Anaemia can be due to numerous causes, particularly iron deficiency, but other causes that may contribute include folate and B12 deficiency, malaria and hookworm infection, and haemoglobinopathy. Delayed growth (stunting and wasting) are also commonly seen amongst rural Indian children. Karnataka is a large state of Southern India, where the prevalence of anaemia amongst children aged 1-2 years has been estimated at 86%.

Key questions: What what are the causes and biological types of anaemia amongst young (1-2 year) children of rural Karnataka and how could this problem best be addressed? How do poverty, food insecurity, diet and parasitic infection interact to produce anaemia? 

Research design/approach: A sample of children and their mothers living in a typical rural district of Karnataka with evaluation of nutritional aspects, socioeconomic conditions, hookworm infection status and blood haemoglobin and iron status. 

The participants in the study: All children aged 1-2 years of age living in villages served by the selected primary health care subcentres will be invited to participate. Mothers or carers of children will be informed about the study and invited to participate along with their child. We will conduct a questionnaire, perform anthropometry on the child and mother, and collect blood samples by venipuncture from the child, and finger prick from the mother. We will collect stool from the child. 

Relevance: We seek to identify the reasons for anaemia and under-nutrition in this population to facilitate implementation of a relevant, effective prevention strategy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Publications
Pasricha S-R, Black JF, Biggs BA, Shet AS et al. Determinants of anemia among children in rural India. Pediatrics. 2010 Jul;126(1):e140-e149

Pasricha S-R, Vijaykumar V, Prashanth N, Sudarshan H, Biggs BA, Black J, et al. A community based field research project investigating anaemia amongst young children living in rural Karnataka, India: a cross sectional study. BMC Public Health. 2009 Feb 17;9(1):59 

Presentations:

Pasricha S-R, Black J, Biggs B-A, Prashanth NS, Moodie R,  Sudarshan H, Shet A. Delivery of iron supplementation in rural Karnataka, India. Proceedings of the National Conference on Blood Disorders in Public Health, Atlanta, USA 2010.

Pasricha S-R, Black J, Shet A, Bhat V, Biggs B-A, Prashanth NS et al. Anaemia among young children in rural India: a cross sectional study. Proceedings of the National Conference on Blood Disorders in Public Health, Atlanta, USA 2010. 

Pasricha S-R, Black J, Shet A, Bhat V, Biggs B-A, Selvaraj S, et al. An explanatory model for haemoglobin among young children in rural Karnataka, India. Physicians Week, Royal Australasian College of Physicians, Sydney, Australia 2009. 

Pasricha S-R, Black J, Shet A, Bhat V, Biggs B-A, Selvaraj S, et al. The etiology of anemia in young children aged 12-23 months. Proceedings of PHOCON 2008 Annual Conference of Pediatric Hematology Oncology Chapter Indian Academy of Pediatrics. New Delhi, India; 2008</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne Research
The Univerity of Melbourne
Level 5, Alan Gilbert Building
VIC 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0825639</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St John's National Academy of Health Sciences Institutional Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St John's National Academy of Health Sciences
Bengaluru, Karnataka 
560034, India</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>India</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sant-Rayn Pasricha</name>
      <address>Nossal Institute for Global Health
Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and Health Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Carlton Victoria 3010 Australia

Co affiliation:
Haematology Research Unit,
St. John's Research Institute,
St. John's National Academy of Health Sciences,
Bangalore-560 034
Karnataka; India</address>
      <phone>+61 431709123</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6872</fax>
      <email>santapasricha@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sant-Rayn Pasricha</name>
      <address>Nossal Institute for Global Health
Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and Health Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Carlton Victoria 3010 Australia

Co affiliation:
Haematology Research Unit,
St. John's Research Institute,
St. John's National Academy of Health Sciences,
Bangalore-560 034
Karnataka; India</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 9299</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6872</fax>
      <email>santapasricha@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sant-Rayn Pasricha</name>
      <address>Nossal Institute for Global Health
Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and Health Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Carlton Victoria 3010 Australia

Co affiliation:
Haematology Research Unit,
St. John's Research Institute,
St. John's National Academy of Health Sciences,
Bangalore-560 034
Karnataka; India</address>
      <phone>+61 431709123</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6872</fax>
      <email>santapasricha@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>