<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308452">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/11/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000044022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intensive versus Conventional Renal Support in Acute Renal Failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In critically ill patients with acute renal failure does a strategy of intensive renal replacement therapy as compared to a strategy of less-intensive renal replacement therapy decrease all-cause mortality at 60 days</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ATN Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov NCT00076219</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Renal Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intensive renal replacement therapy defined as: Daily (except Sunday) intermittent hemodialysis when hemodynamically stable and
Continuous venovenous hemodiafiltration at 35 mL/kg per hour or daily (except Sunday) sustained low-efficiency dialysis when hemodynamically unstable 
Duration of intervention: Up to 28 days or until recovery of kidney function, withdrawal of life support, death or discharge from acute care</interventions>
    <comparator>Less-intensive renal replacement therapy defined as: Evenry-other day (except Sunday) intermittent hemodialysis when hemodynamically stable and
Continuous venovenous hemodiafiltration at 20 mL/kg per hour or every-other day (except Sunday) sustained low-efficiency dialysis when hemodynamically unstable</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause mortality as assessed from medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 days following randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery of renal function defined as a measured creatinine clearance of &gt; 20 mL/min</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause in-hosptial mortality assessed from hospital medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 days following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause mortality assessed from follow-up telephone interview and/or vital status registry</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year following randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Acute renal failure (ARF) clinically consistent with a diagnosis of acute tubular necrosis (ATN), defined as: clinical setting of acute ischemic or nephrotoxic injury; and oliguria (average urine output &lt; 20 mL/hr) for &gt; 24 hours or an increase in serum creatinine of at least 2.0 mg/dL (men)/1.5 mg/dL (women) over a period of no more than 4 days

2. Plan for renal replacement therapy

3. Receiving care in critical care unit

4. At least one non-renal organ failure (Sequential Organ Function Assessment organ system score of at least 2) or the presence of sepsis

5. Age of at least 18 years

6. Informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Baseline chronic kidney disease (CKD) defined by serum creatinine &gt; 2 mg/dL (men) / 1.5 mg/dL (women)

2. Acute renal failure (ARF) due to an etiology other than acute tubular necrosis (ATN)

3. More than 72 hours since meeting BOTH of the following: Definition of ARF as specified in the inclusion criteria and a blood urea nitrogen (BUN) &gt; 100 mg/dL

4. More than 1 hemodialysis treatment or more than 24 hours of continuous renal replacement therapy (CRRT)

5. History of kidney transplantation

6. Weight &gt; 128.5 kg

7. Pregnancy

8. Prisoner

9. Non-candidacy for renal replacement therapy (RRT)

10. Not expected to survive 28-days due to underlying chronic medical condition

11. Moribund sate or comfert measures only (CMO) status

12. Participation in a concurrent interventional trial

13. Patient refusal

14. Physician refusal</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/11/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1164</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>US Department of Veterans Affairs Cooperative Studies Program</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1722 I St., NW
Washington, DC 20006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>US Department of Veterans Affairs</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1722 I St., NW
Washington, DC 20006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Institutes of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6707 Democracy Boulevard
Bethesda, MD 20892</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Institutes of Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>6707 Democracy Boulevard
Bethesda, MD 20892</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Acute Renal Failure Trial Network (ATN) Study is a clinical research study that is jointly sponsored by the Department of Veterans Affairs and the National Institutes of Health in order to determine if an increased dose of dialysis will decrease mortality rates in patients with acute renal failure (ARF).

The ATN Study is being conducted using a network of VA and non-VA medical centers across the United States. The study is comparing two strategies for the management of renal replacement therapy in critically ill patients with ARF. Both treatment strategies employ both conventional intermittent hemodialysis in patients whose blood pressure is stable and either sustained low-efficiency dialysis (SLED) or continuous renal replacement therapy (CRRT) in patients who are hemodynamically unstable. In one strategy, intermittent hemodialysis and SLED are provided three-times per week and CRRT is dosed to provide a clearance of approximately 20 mL/kg/hour. In the other treatment arm, intermittent hemodialysis and SLED are provided six-times per week and CRRT is dosed to provide a clearance of approximately 35 mL/kg/hour.

The ATN study began enrolling patients in November 2003 and closed after 44 months on July 2, 2007. The total enrollment was 1124 subjects. All-cause mortality was 53.6% with intensive therapy and 51.5% with less-intensive therapy (odds ratio, 1.09; 95% confidence interval, 0.86 to 1.40; P = 0.47). There was no significant difference between the two groups in the duration of renal replacement therapy or the rate of recovery of kidney function or nonrenal organ failure.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.ATNStudy.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication>1. Palevsky PM, O'Connor T, Zhang JH, Star RA, Smith MW for the VA/NIH Acute Renal Failure Trial Network. Design of the VA/NIH Acute Renal Failure Trial Network (ATN) study: Intensive versus conventional renal support in acute renal failure.  Clinical Trials 2005; 2:423-435.
2. Palevsky PM, Zhang JH, OConnor TZ, Chertow GM, Crowley ST, Choudhury D, Finkel K, Kellum JA, Paganini E, Schein RMH, Smith MW, Swanson KM, Thompson BT, Vijayan A, Watnick S, Star RA, Peduzzi P for the VA/NIH Acute Renal Failure Trial Network. Intensity of renal support critically ill patients with acute kidney injury. New England Journal of Medicine 2008; 359:7-20.
3. Palevsky PM, OConnor TZ, Chertow GM, Crowley ST, Zhang JH, Kellum JA for the VA/NIH Acute Renal Failure Trial Network.  Intensity of renal replacement therapy in acute kidney injury: Prospective from within the Acute Renal Failure Trial Network Study. Critical Care 2009; 13:310.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cooperative Studies Program Human Rights Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cooperative Studies Program Coordinating Center
VA Connecticut Healthcare System
950 Campbell Avenue
West Haven, CT  06516</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Paul Palevsky</name>
      <address>Chief, Renal Section, Medical Service, VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System, University Drive, Pittsburgh, PA 15240, USA</address>
      <phone>+1 412 360-3932</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>palevsky@pitt.edu</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr, Paul Palevsky</name>
      <address>Chief, Renal Section, Medical Service, VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System, University Drive, Pittsburgh, PA 15240, USA</address>
      <phone>+1 412 360-3932</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>palevsky@pitt.edu</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Paul Palevsky</name>
      <address>Chief, Renal Section, Medical Service, VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System, University Drive, Pittsburgh, PA 15240, USA</address>
      <phone>+1 412 360-3932</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>palevsky@pitt.edu</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>