<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368350">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000404527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise for Mental Health in Medical Students: The UNSW MedEx Project</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of structured exercise on psychological distress among undergraduate medical students</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MedEx</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mental health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Supervised high intensity aerobic interval training
participants randomized to the aerobic interval group will attend the CSEP labs 2 x per week for 15 minutes for 8 weeks. Participants in this group will complete an aerobic training session on the stationary bike incorporating 5 x 1 minute maximum effort (rate of perceived exertion 15- 18/20) cycling bouts, with one minute active low intensity (RPE 8-9) recovery between each bout. Each session will be preceded by a warm up and followed by a cool down. Sessions will be supervised an Accredited Exercise Physiologist (AEP). Sessions will be one-on-one.

Arm 2: Progressive resistance training (PRT)
Participants randomised to the PRT group will attend the university training laboratory located on Ground Floor of the Wallace Wurth Building, University of NSW. Participants will exercise 2 times per week for approximately 15 minutes each visit for 8 weeks. Training will be fully supervised by an AEP to maintain proper intensity and progression, as well as to ensure correct technique. All PRT participants will receive weight lifting exercises of 5 major muscle groups using resistance equipment located in the CSEP lab. Exercises chosen include the large muscle groups of the chest, upper back and upper leg and include the cable chest press, standing cable row and leg press. These are symmetrical exercises and functionally relevant to activities of daily living (ADLs). Participants will perform 3 sets of 8 repetitions of each exercise, with controlled concentric and eccentric phases. The initial intensity for this treatment group will be set at 50% of the participants peak strength determined at baseline (1 repetition maximum or 1RM). Intensity will then be increased by 10% each session over 4 sessions until 80% 1RM has been reached, as we have done in previous trials of adults. Repetition maximum testing will be repeated at 2-week intervals to ascertain progress and intensity will be adjusted accordingly (usually 3% per session) and fine-tuned by a rating of between 15-18 on the BORG Rating of Perceived Exertion Scale. This will ensure maintenance of an intensity of 80% of the subjects current 1RM on a continuous basis throughout the 8 week training program. Sessions will be one-on-one.

Arm 3: Active control
Participants who are randomised to the active control will be given the current National Physical Activity guidelines of completing 10,000 steps per day. Steps will be measured by a Jawbone or similar physical activity device and recorded/synced at a twice weekly visit with an AEP located in the Clinical Skills Exercise Physiology (CSEP) Lab. This will ensure equal contact exposure to the supervised intervention groups. Face-to-face contact will be one-on-one.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants who are randomised to the active control will be given the current National Physical Activity guidelines of completing 10,000 steps per day. Steps will be measured by a Jawbone or similar physical activity device and recorded/synced at a twice weekly visit with an AEP located in the Clinical Skills Exercise Physiology (CSEP) Lab. This will ensure equal contact exposure to the supervised intervention groups.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress (Kessler-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active Australia Physical Activity Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight (kg)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference (cm)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum muscle strength (repetition maximum assessment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak aerobic capacity ( Volume Oxygen consumption)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart rate (Electrocardiograph)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks post</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be ambulatory
Participants must be willing to provide written informed consent Participants must be willing to participate in the study and comply with the study requirements over 10 weeks</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those with current alcohol or substance abuse; Persons unable to comply with study requirements over the course of 10 weeks (including baseline and final assessments); Persons currently undertaking a resistance training or other regular (at least 3 days per week) moderate to high intensity exercise of any kind; Persons with specific contraindications to resistance or high intensity aerobic training exercise such as unstable cardiovascular disease, aortic aneurysm, symptomatic hernias, proliferative diabetic retinopathy, retinal laser surgery within 6 weeks, uncontrolled hypertension or rapidly progressive or terminal illness; Persons on psychotropic drugs or currently undertaking psychological interventions to control stress, anxiety and/or depression.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study will be advertised via advertisements located in and around the Wallace Wurth and Biomedical building on the UNSW Kensington campus, as well as via announcements to students at the end of lectures and via word of mouth from medical students at UNSW. The MedEx Project advertisements will be displayed around the UNSW Faculty of Medicine buildings as a poster, and promoted by the President of the UNSW Medical Society. Advertisements will invite students to participate and be sure to let students know that participation is entirely voluntary and their relationship with the University and Academic staff will not be affected in anyway should they choose not to participate. If students are interested in taking part in the study, they will be asked to contact Dr Belinda Parmenter via email: b.parmenter@unsw.edu.au. The student will be asked to provide their contact details to a researcher who will then contact them to discuss the study, perform an initial telephone screen (script attached) and arrange a time for the initial assessment. Upon completing the telephone screen and showing initial eligibility, participants will be emailed a Participant Information Statement and Informed Consent (attached) which will outline the study in detail. Participants will be asked to read through this and to bring it along with them to their initial appointment to have any questions they may have answered and to sign consent prior to providing any further information, including completing the MedEx screening tool.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be done by an independent researcher via a computer-generated randomisation scheme using randomly permuted blocks (www.randomization.com) after completion of baseline testing. Stratification by gender will be planned, due to the likely gender imbalance favouring men and their physiological adaptations to exercise training. Allocation will be concealed via placement of sequential group assignments into opaque sealed envelopes prepared by an independent researcher.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All key outcomes will be measured at baseline and 9 weeks, after completion of 8 week exercise program. Data will be entered into a password secure SPSS software database (PASW Statistics 20, IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY, USA) on the UNSW Exercise Physiology server. Data will be analysed via intention to treat with missing follow up data imputed via the expectation maximization algorithm. Data will be inspected for normality visually and statistically (skewness -1 to greater than or equal to 1) and expressed as mean and standard deviation. Baseline comparisons between the three groups will be made via analysis of variance (ANOVA) or chi square test as appropriate. Relationships between stress and physical activity levels in each group will be determined by simple, stepwise and multiple linear regression models as appropriate. Differences in outcomes between groups will be analysed by repeated analysis of variance models, adjusting for relevant covariates with group by time interaction as the primary outcome of interest. Covariates will be chosen as appropriate via a priori hypothesised confounders as well as observed differences between groups at baseline within the cohort. Relationships between variables of interest at baseline and between change scores will be determined by simple and stepwise regression models. Statistical significance will be initially set at 0.05. Relative effect size and 95% CIs will be calculated for all outcomes.
Sample size calculations were based on a 2010 Cochrane review on Exercise for Depression, where exercise produced a moderate improvement in symptoms of depression post treatment (effect size -0.67 [-0.90 to -0.43]). Setting alpha at 0.05, and beta at 0.2, gives the study an actual power of 80% to detect a significant moderate (ES=-0.67) improvement in symptoms of depression using the Kessler-10 Scale of Psychological Distress. Setting n1=n2=n3, a sample size of n=108 (36 per group) was therefore calculated. If we then conservatively estimate a drop out of 10%, a sample size of approximately 120 participants (40 per group) will be needed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Exercise Physiology
School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
Wallace Wurth Building
University of New South Wales
New South Wales
Sydney 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to determine the feasibility and acceptability of a brief, individualized and supervised exercise intervention to improve symptoms of depression, anxiety and stress among medical students. The project will also evaluate the effect of the intervention on key measures of physical health including weight, waist circumference, aerobic exercise capacity (fitness), muscle strength and sleep behavior. The project will randomly allocate participants to either one of three experimental groups aerobic exercise, resistance exercise or an active control condition where participants will receive a Jawbone or similar physical activity monitor for a period of eight weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Belinda Parmenter</name>
      <address>Department of Exercise Physiology
School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
Wallace Wurth Building
University of New South Wales
Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 8313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.parmenter@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Rosenbaum</name>
      <address>The Bondi Centre, South Eastern Sydney Local Health District
26 Llandaff St
Bondi Junction
NSW 2022</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9366 8669</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rosenbaum@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Rosenbaum</name>
      <address>The Bondi Centre, South Eastern Sydney Local Health District
26 Llandaff St
Bondi Junction
NSW 2022</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9366 8669</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rosenbaum@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>