<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372057">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000241336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Measuring the mesh position after a successful urinary incontinence surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>May the length of the surgical midurethra be longer than anatomical midurethra? An analysis of the mesh position with translabial ultrasonography in successful cases after transobturator tape operation. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1191-0755</utrn>
    <trialacronym>AML</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stress urinary incontinence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Between September 2011 and April 2016 a total of 82 successful transobturator tape (TOT)  surgeries were performed at the Department of Urology, Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University.  In this study, all cases with favorable results will be phone called prospectively for a translabial ultrasonographic examination to evaluate the mesh location after surgery. The ultrasonography will be performed by an experienced radiologist.  The ultrasonographic examinations will be conducted at Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University.  
After measuring the length of the urethra, the distance from the bladder neck and external urethral meatus to the edges of the mesh will be measured.  The anatomic mid-urethra is accepted as the mid one-third of the urethral length.  Patients with successful surgical results will be examined whether all the meshes are in the boundaries of the anatomic mid-urethra or not.

The width of the mesh, the distance from the urethral mucosa and from vaginal mucosa to the mesh will also be measured.  All measurements will be made in mm.  The posterior urethrovesical angle is going to be measured as the angle between the line parallel to the urethra and parallel to the bladder trigone during resting and valsalva.  These angles will be measured for two times.  The average of the degree of these angles after two different measurements will be calculated.  The difference of the angles between resting and valsalva will be recorded.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The bounds of the anatomic and surgical midurethra will be compared after translabial ultrasonographic measurements.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of ultrasound examination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The posterior urethrovesical angle will be measured with translabial ultrasonography</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of ultrasound examination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who have had transobturatory tape operation at the Department Urology, Ahi Evran University  between September 2011 and April 2016 with a successful surgical outcome will be included in this study.  Patients without stress urinary incontinence, emptying problem, extrusion of the mesh or erosion of the urethra will be accepted as surgical success.  Patients who had had the surgery for at least two months ago will be admitted to work.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>26</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>81</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who had another urogynecological surgery simultaneously or with unsuccessful surgical outcome will be excluded from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The patients with surgical success will be involved this study.  Kolmogorov-Smirnov test will be used to assess the normality of distribution.  Pearsons Chi-square test will be used for the categorical variables and independent t-test will be used for continuous variables.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>82</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>75</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>6/03/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Kirsehir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ahi Evran University Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Radiology and Department of Urology, Ahi Evran University, Kirsehir, Turkey Postcode:40200</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ahi Evran University Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Radiology and Department of Urology, Ahi Evran University, Kirsehir, Turkey. Postcode:40200</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The surgical treatment of stress urinary incontinence is successfully maintained by transobturator midurethral sling (MUS) surgeries over a decade.  The short and medium-term results are well understood after many clinical trials. ,   The mesh is being motivated to localize just under the mid part of the urethra during MUS.  After understanding the  integral theory, this concept has become more important.   
The location of the mesh under the midurethra is crucial for the success and complication rates of MUS.  Anatomically the midurethra is the mid one-third of the urethra.  This part is the high-pressure region of the urethra.    The aim of this study is to evaluate the exact location of the mesh under the urethra with translabial ultrasonography and to compare the mesh position to the anatomic midurethra in MUS patients with favorable results,  and find out if there is a difference in lengths of surgical and anatomic midurethra.
Between September 2011 and April 2016 a total of 82 successful transobturator tape (TOT)  surgeries were performed at the Department of Urology, Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University.  In this study, all cases with successful results will be prospectively phone called for a translabial ultrasonographic examination to evaluate the relationship of the mesh to the surrounding structures after surgery.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics committee of medicine faculty, Ahi Evran University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University, Bagbasi Campus, Kirsehir.
Postcode:40200</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-01/02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sahin Bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University, Kirsehir, Turkey  Postcode:40200</address>
      <phone>+903862134517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahin.bagbanci@ahievran.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>sahin bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University, Kirsehir, Turkey  Postcode:40200</address>
      <phone>+903862134517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahin.bagbanci@ahievran.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sahin Bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University, Kirsehir, Turkey  Postcode:40200</address>
      <phone>+903862134517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahin.bagbanci@ahievran.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sahin Bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Medicine Faculty of Ahi Evran University, Kirsehir, Turkey  Postcode:40200</address>
      <phone>+903862134517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahin.bagbanci@ahievran.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>