<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366644">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000786695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot randomised controlled trial to determine the effect of a physiological (step) versus a standard action (slope) labour progress lines on the rate of spontaneous vaginal birth amongst low risk women in labour for the first time</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For women in labour for the first time does a partograph with a graduated dystocia line compared to a standard sloping action line increase the likelihood of a spontaneous vaginal birth</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Normal Labour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The 'physiological' partogram is a visual tool that uses a graduated (stepped) line to indicate whether cervical dilatation, determined by vaginal assessment at regular intervals, is slower than a mean of 0.5cm per hour.</interventions>
    <comparator>The standard partogram is a visual tool that uses a sloping line to indicate whether cervical dilatation, determined by vaginal assessment at regular intervals, is slower than a mean of 1cm per hour.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of women recruited, proportion of potentially eligible women recruited and reasons women are not recruited</outcome>
      <timepoint>completion of the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with the trial interventions and reasons for non-compliance assessed using chart audit and a tool specifically designed for the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>completion of the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Completeness of data collection for secondary outcomes and proportion lost to follow-up</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of women receiving an artificial rupture of membranes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proprtion of women requiring oxytocic augmentation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of women having an operative birth (forceps, vacuum extraction or Caesarean Section) and primary indication</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of women having a primary postpartum haemorrhage (&gt; 1500mL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>clinician compliance with partogram use assessed through chart audit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composite of serious adverse outcomes for the infant defined as: Infant death (any fetal death after study entry or death of a live born infant within 7 days of age; or serious infant morbidity defined as, one or more of the following: active resuscitation, which includes intubation/cardiac massage and/or the need to ventilate; Hypoxic Ischemic Encephalopathy (HIE) 2 or 3 and /or seizures under 48 hours; Apgar score equals 4 at 5 minutes; cord pH less than 7.18 and /or base deficit greater than -10 (arterial cord blood taken in scenarios where cord blood sampling would normally be collected); admission to special care or neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) greater than 4 days; need for inspired oxygen greater than 30% and/or  the need for Continuous Positive Airways Pressure (CPAP) or  invasive ventilation; proven systemic infection in first 48 hours of life (treated with antibiotics) (excluding lethal congenital anomalies). </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of women having a Spontaneous Vaginal Birth (SVB)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Nulliparous women in spontaneous labour who are:
* At term (between 37  and 41 weeks plus 6 days gestation) with a singleton pregnancy, a cephalic (head down) presentation and cervical dilatation of 4cm or greater 
* Equal to or greater than 18 years of age and able to provide informed consent
* Defined as low risk i.e. no history of: stillbirth or neonatal death, three or more consecutive miscarriages, previous fetal death in utero, previous preterm birth (less than 32 weeks), previous mid-trimester loss/cervical incompetence/cone biopsy/known uterine anomaly, previous early onset of pre-eclampsia (less than 32 weeks gestation), or rhesus iso-immunisation; no complications during the current pregnancy (such as multiple pregnancy or fetal abnormality); and no precluding medical conditions (such as cardiac disease, essential hypertension, renal disease, pre-existing diabetes, previous gestational diabetes, epilepsy, severe asthma, substance use, significant psychiatric disorders, age greater than 40 years, body mass indexless than 17 or greater than 35).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Private insurance status (this refers to women who utilise their health insurance to access maternity care from an obstetrician of their choice)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be consented to the trial during the antenatal period. Upon assessment of active labour that attending midwife will obtain an opaque study envelope containing either an experimental or standard partogram labelled with a unique study code.</concealment>
    <sequence>Opaque envelopes containing partograms with pre printed stepped (intervention) or sloping (standard care) lines will be prepared by the Mater Research Institute using block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/05/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>99</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mater Mother's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Sue Kildea</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mater Research Institute / University of Queensland
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland
Australia
4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mater Health Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland
Australia
4101</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to test the feasbility of a trial into a new type of partograph for measuring progress in labour with the goal of increasing rates of spontaneous vaginal birth (SVB), improving maternal and infant health outcomes and reducing maternity costs.  The partograph is a paper based tool recommended by the World Health Organisation (WHO), and universally used to measure progress in labour and to assist in the diagnosis and management of prolonged labour. Research suggests that a newly designed partograph could be more appropriate to the high resource setting and may result in increased SVB rates without harmful effects on mother or baby. We hypothesise that such a partograph will result in fewer women requiring augmentation (medical acceleration of labour) and increase the rate of SVBs. This trial will also determine the effect of the new partograph on analgesic use, operative birth (caesarean section and instrumental), maternal and infant outcomes. Appropriate management in labour is critical to achieving optimal SVB rates</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Health Services HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mater Health Services
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland
4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00332</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nigel Lee</name>
      <address>Midwifery Research Unit
Mater Research Institute
Level 2 Aubigny Place
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>61 7 31636118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nigel.lee@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nigel Lee</name>
      <address>Midwifery Research Unit
Mater Research Institute
Level 2 Aubigny Place
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>61 7 31636118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nigel.lee@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nigel Lee</name>
      <address>Midwifery Research Unit
Mater Research Institute
Level 2 Aubigny Place
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>61 7 31636118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nigel.lee@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nigel Lee</name>
      <address>Midwifery Research Unit
Mater Research Institute
Level 2 Aubigny Place
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>61 7 31636118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nigel.lee@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>