<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368721">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000005459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An evaluation of user acceptance and performance of a mobile real-time continuous glucose monitoring system in people with type 1 and type 2 diabetes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An evaluation of user acceptance and performance of a mobile real-time continuous glucose monitoring system in people with type 1 diabetes (T1D) and with type 2 diabetes treated with multiple daily injections (MDI) of insulin.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-0698 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 Diabetes.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes treated with multiple daily injections of insulin.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study aims to evaluate the user acceptance of a real time continuous glucose monitoring (RT-CGM) system in people with T1D and T2D treated with MDI of insulin. This study also intends to evaluate the performance of the system and the the impact it has on glycaemia. 

The RT-CGM system consists of a glucose sensor and transmitter and a linked study iPod displaying glucose information. The glucose sensor is inserted subcutaneously, in the abdomen region, and measures glucose in the interstitial fluid (IF) through a glucose oxidase reaction.

This study is a randomized crossover study involving 20 participants (10 with T1D and 10 with T2D using MDI of insulin). Participants will undertake one week of unmasked RT-CGM system (where there will be able to see their CGM information) linked to a study iPod , and one week of masked RT-CGM system (where they will not be able to see their CGM information) linked to a glucose senor recorder (GSR), in random order.

Following baseline clinical assessment, researchers will provide participants  with education about  study devices. Initial venous blood sampling for HbA1c and 1,5 AG will be taken. 1 hour following sensor insertion, participants will undergo frequent venous blood samples (FST) to measure plasma glucose at 20 minute intervals for a duration of 3 hours. .  For the 2 week study period participants will be instructed to undertake reference capillary blood glucose measurements (a minimum of 4 times a day) and to wear the RT-CGM system continuously.  

For the study duration participants will be instructed to keep a diary documenting activity, diet, capillary glucose reading, insulin, and symptomatic hypoglycaemia episodes.

Participants will attend a study visit on Day 8. Participants assigned to the unmasked RT-CGM arm will complete a user evaluation questionnaire. 

A standard meal will be provided to both groups and venous bloods for glucose will be collected from the start of the meal at 20 minute intervals for a duration of 5 hours. Two hours post-meal a second sensor will be inserted to allow for crossover of the study, where the sensor will be linked to the alternative GSR or iPod. The sensor inserted on Day 1 will be removed and collected for review of the data prior to the participants departure.

On Day 15 participants will attend their final study visit. Participants assigned to the unmasked RT-CGM for the second half of the study will complete a user evaluation questionnaire. An intravenous cannula will be inserted to the cubital fossa and venous blood for HbA1c and 1,5 anhydroglucitol (1,5 AG) will be taken. Participants will then be provided a meal and have venous blood collected at this time at 20 minute intervals over the following 3 hours for plasma glucose measurements. </interventions>
    <comparator>masked RT-CGM as a comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant acceptance regarding comfort and utility of the RT-CGM system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed via a questionnaire designed specifically for the study after  6 weeks of use.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance of the RT-CGM system measured by proportion of time
the glucose sensor is displayed and the mean absolute relative
difference relative to YSI and study meter glucose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously over the 6 weeks of wear</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance of the RT-CGM system measured by proportion of time the glucose sensor is displayed and the mean absolute relative difference relative to YSI and study meter glucose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously during the 6 weeks of wear</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of percentage time in CGM target range (4-8mmol/L) in RT-CGM system versus ""usual care"" study group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously over the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of percentage time above target CGM range (&gt;10mmol/L) in in RT-CGM system versus ""usual care"" study group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously over the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of percentage time below target CGM range (&lt;4mmol/L) in the RT-CGM system versus ""usual care"" study group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously over  the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in overall glycaemia as measured by laboratory assays for 1,5 AG.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood samples obtained on Day 1, 32, 42, 54, 64</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-T1D, or T2D of &gt;10 years duration treated with MDI of insulin
-Participant willing to comply with study protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Pregnant or planned pregnancy during the study period
-Life-threatening illness
-Major psychiatric illness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical comparison for this study will be performed using a two tailed paired t-test (p&lt;0.05). This study is a hypothesis generating study, therefore no statistical assumptions were used when deciding the number of participants needed to achieve study objectives. It will be used to inform larger studies incorporating clinical interventions.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincents hospital Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy 3065 VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic Diabetes</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>18000 Devonshire Street Northridge CA 91325

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Until recently, insulin administration has been based upon finger-prick measurements of capillary glucose readings. RT-CGM involves using a subcutaneous sensor to measure interstitial fluid glucose levels continuously and provides the patient with the glucose level in real-time, as well as the rate and direction of change in the glucose. While there is an increasing body of evidence indicating that RT-CGM in combination with an insulin pump results in an improvement in glycaemia and reduces hypoglycaemia, compared with self monitoring of blood glucose (SMBG) and MDI in people with T1D, data is limited regarding the use of RT-CGM in conjunction with MDI. The study aims to evaluate the user acceptance of the RT-CGM device in patients with T1D, and T2D on MDI, as well as to evaluate its' impact on glycaemic control.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincents Hospital Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Unit
Level 5, Mary Aikenhead Building
27 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David O'Neal</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 41 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92312211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dno@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sybil McAuley</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 41 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92312211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sybil.mcauley@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sybil McAuley</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 41 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92312211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sybil.mcauley@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dilshani Jayawardene</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne, 41 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92312211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dilshani_jay@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>