<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372302">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000463370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does drinking water and applying heat increase vein size?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of hydration and heat on upper extremity vein diameter and distance of vein from skin surface in healthy volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>patients requiring intravenous treatments</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>patients requiring venepuncture</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A three arm parallel randomised controlled trial will be undertaken to determine the effect of hydration and heat on vein diameter and distance of vein from skin surface. 39 participants (13 each group) will be recruited from staff and students of the University of South Australia. Participants will be invited to register their interest by emailing the researchers. Once registered, participants will be emailed an information sheet and consent form. The participants will be asked to email a signed consent form to the researchers prior to study commencement. Registration details will be entered into a spreadsheet and used to randomise participants to one of three groups control, heat or hydration. This will be an unblinded RCT due to the nature of the interventions.
All participants will be asked to fast (food and fluid) from 2400 the previous night to when the measurements occur. The researchers will undertake baseline measurement vein measurements using a portable ultrasound early the next day. Two veins on the left arm commonly used for venepuncture and PIVC insertion will be identified using ultrasound. A mark will be applied to the measurement site with nonpermanent pen. Both the diameter and depth of these veins will be determined using the inbuilt callipers of a portable SonoSite SSeries ultrasound machine. Participants will be given a short questionnaire to determine age, BMI, gender, medical history (diagnosed by medical practitioner) tobacco and medication use. Additionally, level of physical activity will be measured (Godin LeisureTime Exercise Questionnaire).
Participants allocated to the fluid arm will be given 1 litre of room bottled water temperature (approx. 22 degrees Celsius) and asked to consume this over 30 minutes. Those in the arm receiving heat intervention will have a wheat bag (warmed in a domestic microwave on high power for 2 minutes) applied directly over the veins of interest in the cubital fossa/forearm area for 15 minutes. Participants in the heat arm will have the second vein measurement after 15 minutes of heat application. The fluid and control group will have the second measurements undertaken 1 hour after the baseline measurements.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control arm will not receive fluid or heat and will be asked to sit quietly until the second vein diameter and depth measurements (1 hour after baseline measurement). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A portable SonoSite S-Series ultrasound machine (SonoSite, Bothell, WA) with a 13-6 MHz linear probe and vascular pre-set will be used to identify and measure vein diameter 
Two veins (median cubital and cephalic vein) on the left arm of participants will be measured. The median cubital vein will be measured at the cubital fossa. The cephalic vein measured at the most distal point that the vein is identified on the forearm in a pre-determined section (between 30mm distal from the antecubital fossa and 120mm proximal to the radial styloid). The distance from these anatomical landmarks will be measured and recorded. A mark will be made at both sites with non-permanent ink. The transducer will be manoeuvred along the mark and angled from left to right to obtain the clearest image of the vein and reduce artefacts in the image. Light transducer pressure will be used to avoid vein compression and gain/depth will be optimized for each image. The inbuilt callipers of the ultrasound will be used to measure the anterior posterior diameter of the vein </outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants in the heat arm will have the second vein measurement after 15 minutes of heat application. The fluid and control groups will have the second measurements undertaken 1 hour after the baseline measurements.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A portable SonoSite S-Series ultrasound machine (SonoSite, Bothell, WA) with a 13-6 MHz linear probe and vascular pre-set will be used to measure the distance of the vein from the skin surface. 
Two veins (median cubital and cephalic vein) on the left arm of participants will be measured. The median cubital vein will be measured at the cubital fossa. The cephalic vein measured at the most distal point that the vein is identified on the forearm in a pre-determined section (between 30mm distal from the antecubital fossa and 120mm proximal to the radial styloid). The distance from these anatomical landmarks will be measured and recorded. A mark will be made at both sites with non-permanent ink. The transducer will be manoeuvred along the mark and angled from left to right to obtain the clearest image of the vein and reduce artefacts in the image. Light transducer pressure will be used to avoid vein compression and gain/depth will be optimized for each image. The inbuilt callipers of the ultrasound will be used to measure the distance between the uppermost vein wall and skin surface.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants in the heat arm will have the second measurement after 15 minutes of heat application. The fluid and control groups will have the second measurements undertaken 1 hour after the baseline measurements.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Staff and students at the University of South Australia City East campus will be invited to take part.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant women, insulin dependent diabetics and participants who have any other serious health conditions that may be effected by fasting will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>There was a paucity of data to inform this power analysis. We have used the effect demonstrated in Zhu et al. (2015) to guide our calculation. They demonstrated a 2mm increase in subclavian vein diameter after rehydration with one litre of intravenous fluid. It was expected that there would be an increase in vein diameter of 2mm after intervention and no change in the control group (SD 1.5mm). A two group t- test found that this would require 13 per group to achieve 80% power with a 0.025 significance level. Descriptive statistics will be used to present participant variables such as age, gender and activity levels. Differences in mean vein diameter and distance of vein from skin surface will be analysed using paired t-tests to determine the effect of localized heat and oral hydration on vein diameter and depth.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>39</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>4/04/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5001 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Rebecca Sharp</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of South Australia,
GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001



</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of South Australia,
GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Jessie Childs</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia,
GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Adrian Esterman</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of South Australia,
GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The insertion of peripheral intravenous catheters (PIVC) or cannulas for intravenous treatment and venepuncture for blood sampling are common in modern health care. However, difficulty in obtaining successful access is common and patients may undergo repeated attempts. This difficulty results in high costs for health care organisations and distress for patients (Sharp et al. 2014; Robinson Reilly 2015). 
Successful attempts may be influenced by both the size and the depth of the vein (Witting 2010; Kimori 2016). Clinicians often apply heat to the area and encourage fluid intake to increase vein diameter and make veins more superficial so as to improve venepuncture success (Fink 2009). However, these interventions are based on limited evidence. Existing research about the effect of hydration on the size of veins used for venepuncture and PIVC insertion is scant. No existing research could be identified that has investigated the effect of heat or hydration on the distance of the vein from skin surface.
Hypotheses: 
- Heat and hydration will increase vein diameter
- Heat and hydration will decrease vein depth
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of South Australia,
North Terrace,
Adelaide, South Australia, 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000035866</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Sharp</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of South Australia,
 GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2663</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.sharp@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Sharp</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of South Australia,
 GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2663</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.sharp@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Sharp</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of South Australia,
 GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2663</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.sharp@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Sharp</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
University of South Australia,
 GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2663</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.sharp@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>