<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363806">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000765729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing to see if picosalax in combination with low residue diet is as good for bowel cleanliness and better tolerated than current bowel preparations used for morning colonoscopies. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single-blind, randomised non inferiority study of the effectiveness and tolerability of picosalax and low residue diet compared to standard bowel preparation prior to morning colonoscopy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>effectiveness of bowel preparation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>tolerability of bowel preparation </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Picosalax bowel preparation in combination to low residue diet

Picosalax Two sachets, each to be mixed in 250ml of water 
*One to be taken 9pm the day prior to the colonoscopy 
*One to be taken 4am on the day of the colonoscopy

The low residue diet is to start 2 days prior to the colonoscopy and cease when bowel preparation starts 
* Examples include : *Milk (regular, low fat, skim), water, lemonade, soda or mineral water, clear (not coloured) Gatorade or other sports drinks
*Regular white bread/toast, rice bubbles, white rice, regular pasta, potatoes (peeled), rice noodles, plain rice crackers, white flour, sugar
*Eggs, Chicken breast (no skin), white fish fillet (no skin)
*Plain cream cheese, cheddar cheese, ricotta, fetta, cottage, parmesan or mozzarella cheese, white sauce
*White coloured yoghurt (no added fruit or inulin), mayonnaise, cream, sour cream, butter and margarine, oil for cooking
*White chocolate, vanilla ice cream, lemonade icypole, clear jelly, custard, milk bottles(confectionery

Adherence will be assessed through a food diary that the patient fills up during the two days prior to the colonoscopy</interventions>
    <comparator>Current standard bowel preparation ie. clear fluids diet with PrepKit C

Day before the procedure, the patient is only to have clear fluids after a light breakfast. Examples include :
*Water 
* Clear broth or Bonox
Clear fruit juice without pulp or seeds (eg Apple juice)
* Coffee or tea without milk
* Gatorade, Sportsplus, Lucozade, or Gastrolyte
* Soft drinks
* Fruit flavoured cordials
* Plain jelly without added fruits or toppings
(avoid red and purple coloured drinks/jellies)

PrepKitC contains two sachets of picoprep and one sachet of glycoprep 
5pm - Picoprep one sachet with 250ml of water 
6pm One sachet of Glycoprep in 1L of water 
7pm One sachet of Picoprep with 250ml of water 

Patients are then to fast from midnight </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of bowel cleanliness- this is assessed via the Ottawa bowel cleanliness scale which has 2 components:
1. Three sections of the colon - the degree of washing and suctioning required to obtained a clear mucosa with a score allocated 
2. The total amount of fluid present in the entire bowel

The 2 components are then added to determine the final score 
A score of 5 or less is deemed successful. 
A score of 6 or more is deemed unsuccessful. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During the Colonoscopy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient tolerance, acceptance and compliance with the study bowel preparation in comparison to current bowel preparations used- assessed via a questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>By the scheduled colonoscopy date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caecal and terminal ileal intubation rates </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the colonoscopy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time taken to complete the procedure </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of the colonoscopy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Polyp to adenoma detection rate ratios. 
The total polyp numbers for each patient is determined by the end of the procedure. 
The removed polyps are then examined and proportion of adenomatous polyps are then determined by the pathologist. 
A ratio is then calculated from both these values. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>When histology available- generally 2 to 4 weeks from the procedure date </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A history of constipation, laxative use or opoid analgesia usage affects the quality of bowel preparation- this is determined through a patient questionnaire completed and handed over on the day of the colonoscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day of the colonoscopy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Consenting adult patients (aged 18 years and greater) undergoing outpatient colonoscopy for clinically accepted indications.

Clinically accepted indications generally include but are not restricted to iron deficiency anaemia, surveillance of bowel polyps, colorectal cancer screening, assessment of symptoms such as abdominal pain, diarrhoea and constipation, assessment or investigation of inflammatory bowel disease. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>99</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria are conditions generally considered as exclusions to colonoscopy in normal clinical practice.  

They are suspected bowel perforation, gastric outlet obstruction, toxic megacolon, severe colitis, and pregnancy or lactation.  

For additional safety, will also exclude patients with the relative contraindications of significant renal failure (eGFR&lt;30) significant heart failure (New York Heart Association Class III or IV).  

Prep-Kit C is contraindicated in individuals with phenylketonuria, due to the presence of aspartame and patients with Glucose-6-Phosphate Dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency given it contains ascorbic acid (vitamin C) which is an oxidant.  Any person with a known hypersensitivity to a constituent of Picoprep, Glycoprep or Picosalax will also be excluded. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed

Patients will be invited to participate in this study from outpatient gastroenterology clinics at the Alfred Hospital and inpatient wards of the Alfred hospital.  We will only be recruiting people to this study who have been advised to have a colonoscopy for clinically accepted reasons. We may also contact patients who have already been booked for elective outpatient colonoscopy at the Alfred Hospital but are awaiting their procedure. 

Given that patients may wait for a period of weeks to many months for their colonoscopy after the time of booking (depending on the urgency of the indication), a number of potential participants will already exist on the waiting list at the Alfred Hospital when recruitment begins. We will recruit patients already waiting for elective outpatient colonoscopy who have not yet been invited to participate in the trial and have not received the standard Alfred instructions regarding bowel preparation for their colonoscopy.  The research nurse or an investigator may contact the patient by phone to invite them to participate, provide a verbal explanation of the trial, the benefits and risks of involvement and then if they are interested, mail them the study information sheet and consent form should they wish to participate. They will be informed that a decision not to be involved in the study will not influence their treatment 
or the timing of their procedure
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation

Patients will be randomly allocated to one of the dietary regimens on a 1:1 basis.  
Randomisation will occur at the time a colonoscopy is booked to a specific date allocated to a morning list.  The sealed envelope will be mailed along with other standard instructions about the time of their procedure.  The bookings clerk will record the patient’s hospital ‘UR’ number with their study reference number on a password protected database at that time. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculated assuming a 75% success rate with clear fluids based on prior research and a non inferiority margin of 15%. 
Approximately 104 patients are required in each group. Adding 20% to account for drop outs, 125 will be studied in each group (250 in total) 

An intent-to-treat analysis will be used to assess the primary outcome.  The percentage of success will be assessed in each treatment group and the 95% confidence interval for the difference in success rates will be determined.  Non-inferiority of the low-residue diet with Picosalax regimen will be established if the lower confidence limit for the difference in effect turns out to lie above -15%.  An interim analysis will be performed looking at the primary end-point after 50% of recruitment.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>9/02/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>55 Commercial Road Prahran Vic 3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alfred Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>55 Commercial Road Prahran Vic 3181</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Primary purpose of the study is to examine if a low volume bowel preparation in conjunction with a white diet will have the same cleansing effect as current bowel preparations. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital  Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 COmmercial Road Melbourne Prahran Vic 3181 PO BOx 315</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>107/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gregor Brown </name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital
Level 4 Department of Gastroenterology 
55 Commercial Road Prahran Vic 3181</address>
      <phone>+61390763000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>G.brown@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jonathan Yong Chiang TAN</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital
Level 4 Department of Gastroenterology 
55 Commercial Road Prahran Vic 3181</address>
      <phone>+61390765739</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jonathan.TAN@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jonathan Yong Chiang TAN</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital 
Level 4 Department of Gastroenterology 
55 Commercial Road Prahran Vic 3181</address>
      <phone>+61390765739</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jonathan.TAN@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>