<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362676">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000710820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Novel Interventions in Heart Failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction using ivabradine</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Novel Interventions in Heart Failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction -a single centre, randomised double blinded placebo cross-over pilot study using IVABRADINE, to assess the effect on 6 minute walk test, peak oxygen consumption and New York heart association Class of symptoms, from the Flinders Clinical Research group, Flinders University.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-0432</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NIHEF-2012i(Novel Interventions in Heart Failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction using ivabradine)
20 refres to the number of patients, 2012 refres the year of study, i- refers to first letter in ivabradine</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Effect of Ivabradine in Heart failure with preserved ejection fraction
Ivabradine 5-7.5 mg oral tablets twice daily depending on heart rate at the time of randomisation for 8 weeks followed by a 2 week wash out period and cross over to microcelullose placebo for 8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo- microcellulose oral capsule twice daily</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in 6 minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 and 18 weeks after randomistaion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak VO2 as assessed by cardio-pulmonary exercise testing. The Vo2 is calculated using the difference between the heart rate at rest and at peak exercise. The heart rate blood pressure and concentaration of inspired oxygen will be monitored regularlr by monitors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 and 18 weeks after randomistaion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>RV volume as assessed on cardiac magnetic resonance imaging</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 and 18 weeks after randomistaion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diastolic parametres of E/E', E/A ratio on echocardiogram</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 and 18 weeks after randomistaion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age greater than or equal to 18 years
	HF-PEF (LVEF greater than or equal to 50% within 6m of randomisation)
	NYHA II-III
	Diastolic dysfunction on echo
E/A equal to 1, E/E equal to or greater than 15, deceleration time less than or equal to 140ms
	Heart rate over 70/min 
	Stable disease, confirmed by no hospital admissions or HF medication changes within 3m prior to randomisation
	Informed consent
	No other causes for exertional dyspnoea</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Atrial Fibrillation
	Contraindications to MRI
	Significant valvular or coronary disease as primary cause of HF
	Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, cardiac amyloidosis, sarcoidosis
	GFR equal to or greater than 45 ml/min</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>20 patients recruited for the study will be randomised to receive Ivabradine or placebo twice daily for 8 weeks in addition to their usual medications. They will then be crossed over to the other treatment for 8 weeks after a 2 week wash-out period.
Allocation is by numberedcontainers, which is done by the randomisation company.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation to study drug or placebo is based on a block randomisation. Blocking is used to ensure that comparison groups will be generated according to a predetermined ratio, usually 1:1 or groups of approximately the same size.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Box 15, lEVEL 1B
Mark Oliphant Building
Laffer Drive, Science Park
Bedford Park, SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background.
It is estimated that over 300,000 Australians have heart failure (HF) at any given time and the incidence increases with increase in life expectancy. The point prevalence of chronic heart failure (CHF) has been about 1% in people aged 5059 years, 10% in people aged over 65 years, and over 50% in people aged above 85 years. Despite therapeutic advances, HF remains a disease with unacceptably high mortality rates, poor quality of life and massive socioeconomic cost. Heart failure with preserved ejection fraction (HF-PEF) previously known as diastolic heart failure accounts for about 50% of patients with heart failure. HF-PEF refers to a clinical syndrome of symptoms and clinical signs of HF, normal or near normal left ventricular (LV) systolic function (EF&gt; 50%) and evidence of diastolic dysfunction in the form of abnormal LV filling and elevated filling pressures. This can be objectively confirmed on echocardiogram.
There is no difference in morbidity between patients with heart failure with reduced ejection fraction and those with preserved ejection fraction and some studies have shown similar mortality in the two conditions. The efficacy for beta blockers, angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACE-I), angiotensin receptor blockers (ARB) and aldosterone antagonists is well established in the treatment of HF with reduced EF. The efficacy for these drugs in HF-PEF is not well established. The I-PRESERVE trial studied the effects of Irbesartan (ARB) in symptomatic patients with HF-PEF. 4128 patients were enrolled and followed up for 4 years. There was no improvement in outcomes in patients on Irbesartan. The CHARM preserved trial studied Candesartan in 3000 patients with HF-PEF for a period of 3 years. There was only a small reduction in hospital admissions for heart failure in the Candesartan group. The PEP-CHF trial assessed the efficacy of Perindopril (ACE-I) in 850 patients over the age of 70 with HF-PEF. At one year there were fewer unexpected hospital admissions for heart failure in the perindopril group although the trial when completed showed no difference in its primary end point. Although therapies have proven effective in reducing morbidity and mortality from heart failure with reduced ejection fraction, mortality from HF-PEF remains unchanged. No therapies thus far have been proven to correct the abnormalities seen in HF-PEF, halt its progression, reduce its mortality or conclusively reduce its morbidity.
Rationale.
 Reducing heart rate with Ivabradine will improve symptoms, exercise tolerance and LV relaxation in patients with HF-PEF
Objectives.
The primary objective of the study is to trial a novel agent in the treatment of HF-PEF as patients continue to be symptomatic on currently available medications.
We propose to use Ivabradine which is a selective heart rate lowering agent in patients with HF-PEF and assess the effect on symptoms, exercise tolerance, echocardiographic and Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance (CMR) imaging parameters of heart failure.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre,The Flats G5, Room 3 and 4,Flinders Drive, Bedford Park, SA-5042, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>207.12a</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Govindarajan Srinivasan</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine
Flinders Medical Centre, 1, Flinders Drive
Bedford Park, SA, 5042</address>
      <phone>+61-08-82017916</phone>
      <fax>+61-08-82017701</fax>
      <email>Govindarajan.Srinivasan@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Govindarajan Srinivasan</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine
Flinders Medical Centre, 1,Flinders Drive
Bedford Park, SA, 5042</address>
      <phone>+61-08-82017916</phone>
      <fax>+61-08-82017701</fax>
      <email>Govindarajan.Srinivasan@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Govindarajan Srinivasan</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine
Flinders Medical Centre, 1 Flinders Drive
Bedford Park, SA, 5042</address>
      <phone>+61-08-82017916</phone>
      <fax>+61-08-82017701</fax>
      <email>Govindarajan.Srinivasan@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>