<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370817">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000768493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Provision of positive pressure ventilation to term and late-preterm infants: Does a novel suction device reduce face mask leak compared with a conventional mask? </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Provision of positive pressure ventilation to term and late-preterm infants: Does a novel suction device reduce face mask leak compared with a conventional mask? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SEAL: Suction mask in early aeration of the infant lung</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breathing support in the delivery room for term and nearterm infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mask ventilation will be performed using the suction mask (60 mm). Either CPAP or intermittent positive pressure ventilation will be performed by a neonatal resident, fellow or consultant. 

The suction mask called Resusi-sure (LSR Health care, NSW, Australia) uses suction to create a seal between the mask and the infants face. This mask has a vacuum chamber between the inner and the outer rim and has a side port to connect to standard tubing used by suction apparatus on the resuscitation trolley. The mask has Australian Therapeutic Goods Administration approval (June 2015). A negative pressure of -75 mmHg will be used to form a seal and used for the duration of mask use. 

All other devices are set up as per standard hospital guideline for a resuscitation of a term baby. The initial setups are flow 10 l/min, Pip 30, Peep 5, no humidity, FiO2 0.21 and are escalated according to the physicians discretion and the infants response to rescucitation. </interventions>
    <comparator>Mask ventilation will be performed using the conventional mask (standard size mask for these infants is 65 mm), this is the current standard of care at the Royal Womens Hospital. Either CPAP or intermittent positive pressure ventilation will be performed by a neonatal resident, fellow or consultant.

The conventional mask is a Laerdal Silicone mask (Laerdal, Stavanger, Norway, size 0/1) which the standard mask use in this hospital for nearterm and term infants. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Face mask leak 

The sensor of a neonatal respiratory monitor (NewLifeBox Neo-RSD, Advanced Life Diagnostics UG, Weener, Germany) will be placed between the T-piece and the mask to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. Expiratory leak will be calculated from the volume of gas that does not return back through the flow sensor on expiration, expressed as a percentage of the inspired volume. 
Leak (%) = (inspired tidal volume - expired tidal volume)  x   100 / inspired tidal volume
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continous monitoring within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Expiratory tidal volumes (VTe)

The sensor of a neonatal respiratory monitor (NewLifeBox Neo-RSD, Advanced Life Diagnostics UG, Weener, Germany) will be placed between the T-piece and the mask to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. The flow sensor is able to detect volume. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continous monitoring within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Positive inspiratory pressure (PIP)

The sensor of a neonatal respiratory monitor (NewLifeBox Neo-RSD, Advanced Life Diagnostics UG, Weener, Germany) will be placed between the T-piece and the mask to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. The flow sensor is able to detect PIP. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continous monitoring within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP)

The sensor of a neonatal respiratory monitor (NewLifeBox Neo-RSD, Advanced Life Diagnostics UG, Weener, Germany) will be placed between the T-piece and the mask to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. The flow sensor is able to detect PEEP. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continous monitoring within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen saturation (SpO2)

An oximetry sensor (LNOP Neo sensor; Masimo, Irvine, California, USA) will be placed around the infants right wrist and connected to the pulse oximeter (Radical7 V5; Masimo) to measure peripheral oxygen saturation (SpO2) and heart rate (HR). Continuous data will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continous monitoring within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate (HR)

Oximetry: An oximetry sensor (LNOP Neo sensor; Masimo, Irvine, California, USA) will be placed around the infants right wrist and connected to the pulse oximeter (Radical7 V5; Masimo) to measure peripheral oxygen saturation (SpO2) and heart rate (HR). Continuous data will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continous monitoring within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inspired oxygen (FiO2) 

Oxygen analyser: The concentration of inspired oxygen (FiO2) will be measured with a Teledyne oxygen analyser (Teledyne Analytical Instruments, California, USA). The analyser will be inserted into the inspiratory limb Neopuff circuit. Continuous data will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continous monitoring within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of mask ventilation

The duration of mask ventilation is beeing assessed by the researcher who is present at birth as well as by a webcam which is integrated into the monitor using the respiratory fuction monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endotracheal intubation in the delivery room

The researcher who is present at birth will document if the baby needed to be intubated in the delivery room. In addition a webcam which is integrated into the monitor using the respiratory fuction monitor will document this as well. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spontaneous breathing patterns

a.	To identify and define spontaneous breathing patterns (expiratory hold, slow expiration, crying, grunting, unbraked expiration patterns) we will use criteria defined in our previous work on breathing patterns. The most accurate method to analyse these patterns are by viewing the flow and volume curves recorded with the respiratory monitor.

(NewLifeBox Neo-RSD, Advanced Life Diagnostics UG, Weener, Germany) will be placed between the T-piece and the mask to measure inflating pressures and gas flow.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of attempts of repositioning of the mask

The researcher who is present at birth will document the number of attempts of repositioning the mask.  In addition a webcam which is integrated into the monitor using the respiratory fuction monitor will document this as well. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trauma (skin, ocular - if any) according to a self-designed scoring system
Grade 0: no mark visible
Grade 1: red mark on an infants face that replicates the shape of the face mask
Grade 2: bruising
Grade 3: broken skin
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular trauma: Any ocular trauma (bruising, broken skin, subconjunctival haemorrhage)? (YES/NO)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within first 10 min of life during positive pressure ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time for red mark (if any) to resolve

The researcher who is present at birth will document the time for the red mark to resolve. In addition a webcam which is integrated into the monitor using the respiratory fuction monitor will document this as well. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Until red mark resolution (hourly assessments if necessary). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Admission to the neonatal intensive care unit (YES/NO)

The researcher who is present at birth will document if the baby needed to be admitted to the NISC. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After birth until being discharged. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pneumothoraces (needing treatment  (YES/NO)
          (either needle or intercostal catheter)

This outcome is assesssed by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intubation  (YES/NO) /time of intubation in the NISC

This outcome is assesssed by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of mechanical ventilation. 

This outcome is assesssed by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of non-invasive support (CPAP/HF)

This outcome is assesssed by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of additional oxygen requirement

This outcome is assesssed by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surfactant administration  (YES/NO)

This outcome is assesssed by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inotropes administered  (YES/NO)

This outcome is assesssed by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death  (YES/NO)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After admission until hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>term and late preterm appropriately grown infants with gestational age (GA) at birth greater than or equal to 34 weeks AND who require either CPAP (continuous positive airway pressure) or IPPV (intermittent positive pressure ventilation) in the delivery room/ operating theatre within the first 10 minutes after birth.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* congenital anomaly of the face, which may affect the ability of a mask to create a seal.
* inability of research team to attend
* not eligible for Medicare
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is 1:1. variable block randomisation will be used to ensure balance is achieved over the recruiting period. Sealed consecutively numbered opaque envelopes will be used. </concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation is 1:1. variable block randomisation will be used to ensure balance is achieved over the recruiting period. There will be no stratification. 
The sequence of randomisation will be generated by an independent statistician. Sealed consecutively numbered opaque envelopes will be used.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>It is not possible to blind the operator to mask allocation. However, it possible to blind clinicians to the respiratory function measurements (leak and tidal volume). The monitor is designed so that researchers can black out the screen whilst continuing to collect data.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We used human studies to inform the sample size calculation. There are several published studies including one RWH study published in 2010, that have reported the percentage face mask leak during resuscitation of preterm infants in the delivery room. Most recently Cheung et al. reported a mean of 30% (SD 17) which is comparable to earlier studies. To achieve a 50% reduction in leak and reduce the leak from 30% (using the conventional mask) to 15% (using the suction mask) we will need 44 infants (22 in each group) with 80% power and a two-tailed alpha error of 0.05.

We predict that approximately 1/3 of term infants who have their delivery expedited by an obstetric intervention will transition relatively smoothly and either require very few positive pressure inflations (&lt; 5) or only continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP). Face mask leak is difficult to assess by conventional physiological measures during the application of CPAP alone and assessing superiority of one device over another with five or less inflations could be potentially inaccurate. These infants will be excluded from the analysis of the primary outcome leak but will be included in the analysis of the secondary outcomes, such as oxygen saturation (SpO2), inspired oxygen (FiO2), heart rate (HR), differences in the rates of intubation, number of attempts of repositioning of the mask, duration that mask is applied to the infants face, and documentation of any local trauma. 
Since the sample size is based on the primary outcome of face mask leak, we are planning to recruit 44 infants who receive more than five inflations of intermittent positive pressure ventilation. We anticipate that we will randomise approximately 14 additional patients who will subsequently be excluded from the primary analysis because they received either CPAP alone, or less than five inflations.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>20 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Women's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Around 3-6% of newborn infants require positive pressure ventilation (PPV) in the delivery room (DR). However, delivering effective mask ventilation can be challenging, because of large leak around the mask. The presence of a large leak may lead to ineffective ventilation and an unsuccessful resuscitation. A new face mask called Resusi-sure (LSR Health care, NSW, Australia) uses suction to create a seal between the mask and the infants face. 
Primary objective is to test (in a randomised trial) the hypothesis that there will be less leak during intermittent positive pressure ventilation of term and near term infants (newly born infants greater than or equal to 34 weeks) in the delivery room if performed with the suction mask compared with the conventional mask. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research &amp; Ethics Secretariat
Arthur Hui
20 Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Project 16/08-SEAL Trial</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laila Lorenz</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Department 
The Royal Women's Hospital 
20 Flemington Road
Parkville Melbourne, 3052 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61-477799274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laila.lorenz@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laila Lorenz</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Department 
The Royal Women's Hospital 
20 Flemington Road
Parkville Melbourne, 3052 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61-477799274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laila.lorenz@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laila Lorenz</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Department 
The Royal Women's Hospital 
20 Flemington Road
Parkville Melbourne, 3052 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61-477799274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laila.lorenz@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laila Lorenz</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Department 
The Royal Women's Hospital 
20 Flemington Road
Parkville Melbourne, 3052 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61-477799274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laila.lorenz@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>