<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362652">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000664842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Breaking up prolonged sitting with intermittent standing: acute effects in overweight inactive adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The acute effect of breaking up prolonged sitting with intermittent bouts of short-duration standing on postprandial glucose metabolism, lipid metabolism and vascular function in overweight/obese adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The STOMP (Standing To Offset the Metabolic derangement of Prolonged sitting) study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight and obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The experimental condition involves a single day of prolonged sitting (total duration= 7hrs) with intermittent bouts of short-duration standing.  Participants will remain seated for the initial 140min (steady state) period, after which they will consume a standardised mixed meal (50g fat, 75g carbohydrate) and will complete a 2min bout of standing every 20mins for the remaining 5 hours (total standing duration:28mins). All activities will take place in a controlled laboratory environment under the supervision of trained clinical research staff. During the condition, participants will be permitted to watch television, DVDs or read. 
In this trial, participants will complete each condition (experimental and control) in random order, with a minimum 7 day washout period between conditions.</interventions>
    <comparator>In a controlled laboratory environment, participants will complete one day (total duration=7hr) of prolonged sitting without standing breaks. Participants will sit quietly in a comfortable chair and will consume a standardised mixed meal (50g fat, 75g carbohydrate) after an intial 140min steady state period. Participants will be permitted to watch television programs, DVDs or read during the condition, and all activities will be supervised and recorded by clinical research staff.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial plasma glucose levels (mean area under the curve [AUC]). Plasma glucose concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at an outsourced medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood glucose levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean AUC. The mean AUC will be determined at day 7 and day 14 following study enrolment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial plasma insulin levels (mean AUC). Plasma insulin concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at an outsourced medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood insulin levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean AUC. The mean AUC will be determined at day 7 and day 14 following study enrolment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial serum triglycerides (mean AUC). Plasma triglyceride concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at an outsourced medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serum triglyceride levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean AUC. The mean AUC will be determined at day 7 and day 14 following study enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial plasma fatty acid levels (mean AUC). Plasma free fatty acid concentrations will be assessed using standard testing equipment at an outsourced medical laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Plasma free fatty acid levels will be measured every hour for determination of the mean AUC. The mean AUC will be determined at day 7 and day 14 following study enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial reactive oxygen metabolites (hydroperoxides).  Postprandial reactive oxygen metabolites will be measured in-house using a commercially available kit (dROMs kit).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serum levels of reactive oxygen species will be measured every hour for determination of the mean AUC. The mean AUC will be determined at day 7 and day 14 following study enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of endothelial function using non-invasive peripheral arterial tonometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Endothelial function will be measured at 2 hours (completion of steady state period), 4 hours and 7 hours during each condition (days 7 and 14).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria includes: overweight or obesity (body mass index greater than or equal to 25kg/m2 but less than or equal to 45kg/m2) and English speaking</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion is based on: of pregnancy; employment in a non-sedentary occupation (&lt; 5 hours total sitting during the typical workday); currently watching &lt; 3 hours of total screen (including television, computer or electronic games) time per day; regularly engaged in moderate-vigorous physical activity greater than or equal to 150min/week &gt; 3 months; use of carbohydrate or lipid-lowering medication; greater than or equal to 5 previous vasovagal syncope episodes or epilepsy; known physical activity contraindications; major illness/injury (acute or chronic), smokers; orthostatic intolerance, and the use of aspirin or other anticoagulants.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Interested volunteers will receive written information about the study in lay terms and a full description of the inclusion/exclusion criteria. After obtaining informed consent and background information, the potential participants will be screened to confirm eligibility. Once a potential subject has been deemed eligible, the subject will be randomised to the order of experimental conditions. The method for allocation concealment is closed envelopes. The allocation information will be placed in numbered envelopes (1 allocation per envelope) by an independent researcher. After a subject has been enrolled in the study, the study co-ordinators will contact an independent staff member to ask for the sequence of experimental conditions. The independent staff member will keep a log of the date and time the envelope was opened, the envelope number, the initials and gender of the participant and the order of experimental conditions. The study co-ordinator will also keep a record of this information</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation allocation sequence will be generated using computer –generated random numbers in a balanced orthogonal design</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/06/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/07/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>75 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004 (Postal address: PO Box 6492, St Kilda Road Central, Victoria 8008)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 20 Allara Street, Canberra ACT 2601 (Postal address: GPO Box 1421 Canberra ACT 2601)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is well known that being physically active is important for maintaining good health. However, new evidence has emerged showing that being sedentary (sitting for prolonged periods) is adversely associated with indicators of poor health, such as elevated blood glucose and blood fats. Recent experimental evidence suggests that breaking up sitting time throughout the day with light-intensity activity (ie. walking) results in lower blood glucose and blood fat levels than sitting for prolonged periods without activity breaks. However, it is not known whether short-duration bouts of standing, of comparable frequency, can elicit similar metabolic benefits to those observed with treadmill walking. Consequently, this study aims to test the acute (7-hour) effect of prolonged sitting on glucose metabolism and vascular function with and without intermittent breaks of standing.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Ethics Office, Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/10/0199</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Alicia Thorp</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4, 99 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1854</phone>
      <fax>+613 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>alicia.thorp@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Robyn Larsen</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4, 99 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1859</phone>
      <fax>+613 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>robyn.larsen@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Robyn Larsen</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4, 99 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1859</phone>
      <fax>+613 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>robyn.larsen@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Dunstan</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4, 99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 8532 1873</phone>
      <fax>+613 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>david.dunstan@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>