<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365559">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000077662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Noninvasive ventilation improves the cardiovascular response and fatigability during resistance exercise in patients with heart failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>effects of noninvasive ventilation on cardiovascular response and quadriceps fatigability during isokinetic resistance exercise in patients with heart failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1151-7534</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>heart failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>cardiovascular diseases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants attended the isokinetic strength testing laboratory on three different days, with a minimum interval of 72 hours between each visit. On the first day, the study participants were familiarized with noninvasive ventilation (BIPAP Sycnrony II, Respironics Inc, Murrysville, PA, USA) and the isokinetic dynamometer. To select the bi-level positive airway pressure intervention (BV) pressures during exercise, the best inspiratory and expiratory positive airway pressure (inspiratory positive airway pressure (IPAP) and expiratory positive airway pressure (EPAP) respectively) were evaluated. The IPAP was initially set at 10 cmH2O and increased gradually by 2 cmH2O every minute to a maximum of 14 cmH2O. The EPAP was set at 4 cmH2O and increased gradually by 1 cmH2O every minute to a maximum of 8 cmH2O. The pressure level was set to individual subject tolerance for all study participants. The sham intervention (SV) was applied with minimal pressure support (IPAP 4 cmH2O and EPAP 2cmH2O). All participants received noninvasive ventilation via a facial mask interface (Comfort full 2 Mask, Respironics Inc, Murrysville, PA, USA) during both BV and SV.	
On the second and third days, all subjects underwent a quadriceps isokineitc resistance exercise protocol utilizing both conditions of noninvasive ventilation (BV and SV). Subjects were randomly allocated to the BV or SV intervention before starting each procedure. First, all participants underwent 20 minutes of the allocated intervention (BV and SV) while at rest. During this initial period, the subjects sat on the isokinetic dynamometer (Biodex Medical System 2, Shirley, New York, USA). 
The resistance maneuver for this study was concentric knee extension, on the dominant side, at a speed of 60 degress per second. Five sets of 10 repetitions were performed during the two exercise bouts and each set was separated by two minutes of rest. Positioning and stabilization of each participant was standardized. Correction for the effect of gravity was made. Change in peak torque (PT, expressed in Nm), total work (TW, expressed in J) and Power (Pw, expressed in W) between the fifth and first sets were also measured to evaluate quadriceps fatigability by isokinetic dynamometer. Verbal encouragement and visual feedback using the computer screen were given in an attempt to achieve a maximum level of effort. All procedures were performed by the same investigator. The validity and reliability of this testing procedure have been previously described.   
	At rest, during the resistance exercise protocol as well as during the recovery period, HR was continuously monitored (Polar model RS 800, Polar Electro Inc., Kempele, Finland). Systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) were also measured using a calibrated oscilometric automatic device (OMROM MIT elite plus, OMROM Health Care Inc, Illinois, USA). 
</interventions>
    <comparator>On the second and third days, all subjects underwent a quadriceps isokineitc resistance exercise protocol utilizing both conditions of noninvasive ventilation (BV and SV). Subjects were randomly allocated to the BV or SV intervention before starting each procedure. First, all participants underwent 20 minutes of the allocated intervention (BV and SV) while at rest. During this initial period, the subjects sat on the isokinetic dynamometer (Biodex Medical System 2, Shirley, New York, USA). </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cardiovascular response - At rest, during the resistance exercise protocol as well as during the recovery period, HR was continuously monitored (Polar model RS 800, Polar Electro Inc., Kempele, Finland). Systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) were also measured using a calibrated oscilometric automatic device (OMROM MIT elite plus, OMROM Health Care Inc, Illinois, USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>at rest, peak exercise and recovery ( 5 minutos after exercise protocol)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quadriceps fatigability - the subjects sat on the isokinetic dynamometer (Biodex Medical System 2, Shirley, New York, USA). 
The resistance maneuver for this study was concentric knee extension, on the dominant side, at a speed of 60 degrees per second. Five sets of 10 repetitions were performed during the two exercise bouts and each set was separated by two minutes of rest. Positioning and stabilization of each participant was standardized. Correction for the effect of gravity was made. Change in peak torque (PT, expressed in Nm), total work (TW, expressed in J) and Power (Pw, expressed in W) between the fifth and first sets were also measured by the isokinetic dynamometer. Verbal encouragement and visual feedback using the computer screen were given in an attempt to achieve a maximum level of effort . All procedures were performed by the same investigator. The validity and reliability of this testing procedure have been previously described. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in peak torque, total work and power between fifth and first sets</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The recruited subjects satisfied the following inclusion criteria: 1) a diagnosis of HF 9 documented for at least 6 months, 2) echocardiography showing left ventricular systolic dysfunction &lt; 35%, 3) New York Heart Association classification class II-III, and 4) No participation in either a resistance or aerobic training program for at least 3 months prior to study initiation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any subject with a previous diagnosis of moderate to severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease  or who were unable to perform the resistance isokinetic exercise protocol were excluded from this study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>he patients were randomly allocated to two groups by drawing lots, by placing blue and red ribbons inside opaque envelopes. Patients that chose an envelope containing a blue ribbon were allocated in the BV group, and those that chose the envelopes containing the red ribbon were allocated in the Sham group.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An a-prior analysis for this study revealed 9 subjects were needed to achieve 80% power (a = 0,05 and beta = 0.20). All analyses were carried out using a statistical software package (Graphpad Prism version 5 software, Graphpad software, Inc., La Jolla, CA, USA). Values for continuous variables were represented as mean and standard deviation. A two way analysis of variance (ANOVA) assessed differences in continuous variables between study subjects. Post-hoc analysis was performed by the Tukey test. Isokinetic measurements were evaluated by unpaired t- test. A p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant for all tests</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Distrito Federal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Brasilia Brazil</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centro Metropolitano
Conjunto A
Lote 01
Ceilandia
Brasilia - DF
ZIP: 72220-900</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Brasilia Brazil</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Centro Metropolitano
Conjunto A
Lote 01
Ceilandia
Brasilia - DF
ZIP: 72220-900</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Centro Nacional de Desenvolvimento de Pesquisa CNPQ</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>SHIS QI 1 Conjunto B - Blocos A, B, C e D
Lago Sul - Brasilia.DF - ZIP: 71605-001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>previous studies have demonstrated that respiratory muscle unloading probably results in a better balance between oxygen supply and demand, with beneficial effects on dyspnea and reduced exertional leg discomfort during high intensity exercise in heart failure patients. However, the application of noninvasive ventilation during resistance exercise has not been evaluated in this population.  
The aim of the current study was to evaluate: 1) the effects of noninvasive ventilation on knee extensor isokinetic resistance exercise performance in a heart failure cohort. We hypothesize that the use of noninvasive ventilation during this resistance exercise protocol would improve muscular performance and reduce leg fatigue
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Instituo de Cardiologia do Distrito Federal</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Instituto de Cardiologia do Distrito Federal
Estrada Parque Contorno do Bosque, s/n
Bairro: Cruzeiro Novo
Cidade: Brasilia - DF
ZIP: 70.658-700
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>none</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/01/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Vinicius Zacarias Maldaner da Silva</name>
      <address>Vinicius Zacarias Maldaner da Silva
SQSW 105 bloco F apto 413
Sudoeste Brasilia DF 
ZIP 70670426</address>
      <phone>+55 61 35422490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>viniciusmaldaner@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gerson Cirpiano Jr</name>
      <address>Gerson Cipriano Jr
Centro Metropolitano
Conjunto A
Lote 01
Ceilandia
Brasilia - DF
CEP: 72220-900</address>
      <phone>+55 61 81907111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ciprianeft@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gerson Cirpiano Jr</name>
      <address>Gerson Cipriano Jr
Centro Metropolitano
Conjunto A
Lote 01
Ceilandia
Brasilia - DF
CEP: 72220-900</address>
      <phone>+ 55 61 81907111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ciprianeft@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Vinicius Zacarias Maldaner da Silva</name>
      <address>SQSW 105 bloco F apto 413
Sudoeste Brasilia DF 
ZIP 70670426</address>
      <phone>+55 61 35422490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>viniciusmaldaner@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>