<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370222">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000296437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial investigating the efficacy of online continuing education for health professionals to improve the management of Chronic Fatigue Syndrome (CFS).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of online continuing education for health professionals to improve the management of CFS.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>UN1111-1180-1073</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Myalgic encephalomyelitis </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is an eLearning program that will be accessed online for a duration of four weeks. The eLearning program contains an introduction to CFS and seven learning modules (1: Psychoeducation; 2. Activity pacing and graded exercise therapy; 3. Interventions for sleep-wake cycle disturbance; 4. Interventions of neurocognitive functioning in CFS; 5. Interventions for mood disturbance; 6. Interventions for anxiety; 7. Interventions for coping). Learning activities (e.g., concept maps, free text response questions, fill in the blanks) with feedback regarding responses are embedded within each module to facilitate learning. Each module take approximately 30- to 60-mins to complete. The program has been designed so participants can complete the modules within a time frame of their own choosing (e.g., over multiple sittings if they wish) and are able to revisit completed sections at will. The eLearning software will monitor adherence, time to complete, frequency of visits to the program and participant progress.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will consist of health professionals that have been randomly allocated to the waiting list and do not have access to the intervention (i.e., eLearning program). They will receive access to the intervention after post-intervention data has been collected, that is, 4 weeks after the intervention group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants knowledge about CFS and CFS interventions measured at post intervention compared with baseline. Multiple choice and short answer questions, integrated with case vignettes, will test participants knowledge about CFS symptoms, differential diagnosis, CFS management strategies and interventions (CBT and GET), and interventions for conditions that commonly arise secondary to fatigue (reduced mood and anxiety). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome data will be collected at three time points. Both groups will complete the outcome measure at baseline (week 0) and post-intervention (week 4-5), while the follow-up measures will be completed in week 12 for the education group and week 16 for the wait-list control group. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants self-reported confidence in their knowledge of CFS and confidence in their clinical skills to implement evidence-based CFS interventions. This part of the questionnaire requires participants to rate their confidence in their knowledge and clinical skills related to CFS using a 5-point Likert scale anchored at one end with not at all confident and at the other end with very confident.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at three time points. Both groups will complete the outcome measures at baseline (week 0) and post-intervention (week 4-5), while the follow-up measures will be completed in week 12 for the education group and week 16 for the wait-list control group. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants self-reported success in treating people with CFS or medically unexplained fatigue. This part of the questionnaire requires participants to rate their level of success in treating people with CFS or medically unexplained fatigue using a 5-point Likert scale, anchored at one end with completely unsuccessful and at the other end with completely successful.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected at the at the 8- week follow-up, i.e., week 12 for the education group and week 16 for the wait list control group.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data on adherence to and satisfaction with the education activity will be collected for the education group only. Intervention adherence will be tracked using in-built features of the online education platform, which will monitor: time spent in total on the activity, time spent on each module of the activity and engagement in integrated formative assessment tasks. Participants will be asked to rate their agreement with a number of statements related to their satisfaction with the online education activity. This will be done using a 5-point Likert scale anchored at one end with strongly disagree and at the other end with strongly agree. Open-ended responses will also be collected. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected after completing the intervention at weeks 4-5 in the Education group only.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants self-reported portion of clinical practice devoted to people with CFS or medically unexplained fatigue. This part of the questionnaire requires the participant to indicate the percentage of their clinical practice that is devoted to people with CFS or medically unexplained fatigue.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected at the at the 8- week follow-up, i.e., week 12 for the education group and week 16 for the wait list control group.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measure will be the retention of knowledge about CFS and CFS interventions at follow-up, and participants self-reported confidence in their clinical skills, at follow-up. As with the primary outcome measures, multiple choice and short answer questions, integrated with case vignettes, will test participants knowledge about CFS symptoms, differential diagnosis, CFS management strategies and interventions (CBT and GET), and interventions for conditions that commonly arise secondary to fatigue (reduced mood and anxiety). Similarly, participants self-reported confidence in their knowledge of CFS and confidence in their clinical skills to implement evidence-based CFS interventions will be assessed by a questionnaire requiring them to rate their confidence in their knowledge and clinical skills related to CFS using a 5-point Likert scale anchored at one end with not at all confident and at the other end with very confident.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected at the at the 8- week follow-up, i.e., week 12 for the education group and week 16 for the wait list control group.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Fully registered member of relevant allied health professional body (e.g., Australian Psychological Society, Exercise and Sports Science Association), currently practicing.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Studying to be a health professional but without having completed the relevant degree.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through advertisements placed in e-bulletins released by relevant professional associations. A technical support officer will program the eLearning platform to automatically deliver the intervention at week0 (the intervention group) or at week12 (wait list control group) depending on group allocation. The experimenters will not be aware of when individual participants receive the intervention ensuring allocation concealment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly allocated using an electronically generated number sequence. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A total sample of 128 participants is required to detect a moderate effect size of improvement in clinician knowledge and confidence, with a power of 80% and a 2-tailed alpha of 0.05. However, 180 participants will be recruited to account for a potential 30% attrition rate.

Change scores (from Baseline to post-intervention) of the knowledge assessment and self-reported confidence for the intervention and control group will be compared using t-tests to determine improved CFS knowledge/skills. Self reported success in treating people and portion of clinical practice devoted to people with CFS will be compared at baseline and follow-up using t-tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>219</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>3/10/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNSW Australia
High St
Kensington, NSW 2052
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Judith Jan Mason &amp; Harold Stannett Williams Memorial Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4/100 Queen Street
Melbourne VICTORIA 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) is a serious and debilitating illness that affects between 0.2-2.6% of the worlds population (Prins et al, 2006). There is Level One evidence indicating that graded exercise therapy (GET) and cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) is currently the most effective means to manage CFS (for review see Larun et al, 2015; Prince et al, 2008). Despite GET and CBT being widely acknowledged as best-practice interventions for CFS, the great majority of patients in Australia are not receiving these appropriate evidence-based interventions. Recent studies have demonstrated that the reason for this documented gap between research and practice is largely due to practicing health professionals lacking the knowledge and skills to provide appropriate care. 
In order to address this lack of knowledge, our group has developed a CFS Treatment Manual and accompanying DVD aimed at providing clinicians with the knowledge and skills required to effectively manage CFS. However, recent studies have documented that seeking to train clinicians simply by providing a manual is ineffective (Wiborg et al, 2014). Other barriers to continuing education of practicing clinicians include the financial expense of courses and the geographical constraints of attending training (McHugh &amp; Barlow, 2010). The proposed study aims to conduct a randomised controlled trial (RCT) to evaluate the efficacy of the eLearning activity in improving clinician knowledge of CFS and their confidence and skills in implementing evidence-based CFS interventions. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW Human research ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC16419</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sophie Huk Lahn Li</name>
      <address>UNSW Australia
High Street
Kensington, NSW, 2052
</address>
      <phone>+61 (2) 9385 8657</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.h.li@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sophie Huk Lahn Li</name>
      <address>UNSW Australia
High Street
Kensington, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (2) 9385 8709</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.h.li@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sophie Huk Lahn Li</name>
      <address>UNSW Australia
High Street
Kensington, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (2) 9385 8709</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.h.li@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sophie Huk Lahn Li</name>
      <address>UNSW Australia
High Street
Kensington, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (2) 9385 8709</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.h.li@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>