<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372898">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000785303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The role of continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) systems as a self-monitoring tool to optimise blood glucose control in individuals with type 2 diabetes (T2D) - Pilot</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The role of continuous glucose monitoring as a self-monitoring behaviour change tool to enhance glycemic control in individuals with type 2 diabetes - Pilot Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1196-4069 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>CGMCONTT2D</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Glycaemic Control </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight/Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A pilot feasibility study, to determine the effectiveness of real-time continuous glucose monitoring (RT-CGMS) compared with standard care self-management blood glucose (SMBG) approach for improving glycaemic control, reducing cardiovascular disease risk markers and enhancing quality of life in response to the prescription of a lifestyle modification program in overweight and obese individuals with type 2 diabetes (T2D).
Both groups will also perform usual self-monitoring blood glucose readings before each meal and at bedtime as per standard practice with morning fasting recordings to be provided to the study dietitian and Endocrinologist for review and support.
At study commencement (Week 0), participants will be counselled by a research dietitian for 1 hrs and receive a prescriptive low carbohydrate (50g or 14% of total energy) higher protein (28% of total energy) higher fat (58% of total energy) dietary plan and supporting materials (Meal plans, recipes, food lists), individualised for energy level using the Schofields energy equation. To facilitate dietary adherence, the dietary prescription will be structured to include a specific daily eating plan with foods listed in a quantitative food record that participants will be required to complete as a measure of overall dietary adherence, whilst dietitian for the trial will be entering the food data into a food database to ensure macronutrient adherence.

At week 3, participants will be provided face to face education on how to adapt the diet and add food exchanges into their day whilst remaining compliant to the intervention.  Participants will be counselled by an accredited practising dietitian for up to 45 minutes and will be provided comprehensive materials including dietary plans, recipes, shopping lists to assist them to make appropriate energy and food exchanges to maintain the prescribed energy level and macronutrient profile. Participants will also receive a home-based exercise plan incorporating moderate intensity aerobic (walking)/resistance exercises (Theraband), consistent with diabetes Australia exercise recommendations. Materials provided will be visual guides and instructions on specific exercises and how to complete the activity journal.  Intensity recommended will be 60-70% of max heart rate. Exercise session will be of at 30 mins a session every day (210mins minimum target a week) as per the diabetes Australia recommendations. 
The activity journal will be provided to participants who will be asked to document their exercise type and time, this will be provided to the identify adherence to physical activity. 
Apart from the introductory counselling session, participants will receive no further formal counselling regarding the components of the diet or exercise, but will have a contact number for the clinical trial manager for any queries. Queries of a lifestyle or medical nature will be directed to the respective researchers for follow-up.
Participants will attend 3 weekly follow-up clinic visits to return and collect glucose sensors, to document any adverse events and to have any questions regarding sensor management answered. At these visits, participants will be required to return activity journals and food records for compliance assessment. 
These visits will be face to face with the trial manager for 30 minutes and a trial manager or PhD student will also measure weight, body composition and blood pressure and review blood glucose data for assessment of medication change requirements. It is likely that participants may be taking hypoglycaemic, antihypertensive and lipid-lowering medications and changes to oral hypoglycaemic medication will be required. The participants health will be monitored and periodically assessed by project clinician (Prof. Thompson) who will conduct a medication review when necessary .

For the intervention group, the Real Time CGM sensor will be inserted by a nurse into the lower abdominal, subcutaneous tissue, instructions on insertion will be provided.
** CGM sensor wear will be monitored by the clinical research nurse and returning of used sensors will be taken as a measure of compliance. The real time CGM instructions for participants is an attachment to this ANZCTR Trial record.

Duration: 12-week randomized controlled study

Participant: 20 overweight/obese individuals (BMI:26-45 kg/m2, age:20-75 yrs) with T2D will be randomly allocated to undertake 1 of 2 interventions:

Group 1 (N=10)  Prescription of a low carbohydrate, high protein and unsaturated fat diet (LC diet) combined with the use of a real-time continuous glucose monitor (worn continuously for 12 weeks).

Group 2 (N=10) - Prescription of a LC diet combined with the use of a non-display, masked continuous glucose monitor (worn continuously for 12 weeks).
</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2 (N=10) - Will be provided a prescribed LC diet combined with a home exercise plan (as per intervention). The difference will be the use of a non-display, masked continuous glucose monitor (worn continuously for 12 weeks). Inclusion of the use of this masked monitor will ensure high-level scientific rigour of the study design is maintained by achieving a comparable level of interaction to Group 1. Participants will also be required to continue with their standard SMBGL, fasting daily. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycated Haemaglobin (A1C%)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted blood sampling (MBA 20, Insulin and Lipids) will be obtained from consenting participants 0700-1100 in the mornings of their baseline visit (Wk 0) final visit, week 12 after trial  commencement measured at a certified clinical laboratory using standard assay kits.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24hr Blood Glucose Profile measured by continuous blood glucose monitoring device - Medtronic  Guardian Connect (Commercially Available in Australia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood Glucose is obtained every  5 minutes over 7 day intervals for 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes-related medication changes assessed by the validated an anti-glycemic medication effect score (MES) based on Medication changes documented by medication type and dosage changes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 and 12 after trial commencement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Composition using InBody 270 bioimpendance scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 3, 6, 9, 12 after trial commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure using an automated sphygmomanometer (SureSigns Vs3, Phillips Medical Systems, MA, USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 and 12 after trial commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quality using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI); </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 and 12 post trial commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity measured using 7-day accelerometery and the international physical activity questionnaire (Ipaq)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 and 12 post trial commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Food intake using a 3 day weighed food records and diet histories</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 3, 6, 9 and 12 post trial commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Food Craving Eating Style using the food Craving Inventory (FCI); </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks  0 and 12 post trial commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stress Survey using Perceived Stress Scale (PSS);</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 and 12 post study commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Mental wellbeing using a series of validated assessment questionnaires, including - Diabetes Distress - Problem Areas in Diabetes Questionnaire (PAID); Diabetes Quality of life questionnaire: Diabetes 39  Quality of Life Questionnaire,</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 and 12 post study commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptance and Tolerance of CGM Wear and Lifestyle plan  ( 5 Subjective likert questions)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 6 and 12 post trial commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria
*Adults aged 20-75yrs (Male and Female)
 *BMI 26-45kg/m2
* Diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes
*With a HbA1c between 5.9-6.9% and ARE taking oral medications or insulin
* With a HbA1c between 7-12% with or without medications
* Must be willing to comply with the study procedures
 *Have signed informed consent
 *Able to attend appointments and live within the Adelaide Metropolitan area
 *If female, not pregnant or breast feeding
 *No history of heart disease or other heart abnormalities
 *Do not strictly control or restrict the food and drinks that you have daily (i.e. *restrained eater questionnaire score greater than 10)
 *Being weight stable (+/- 3kg) in the past 3 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria
*Type 1 Diabetes 
*Taking short acting insulin (i.e. Actrapid)  Fitted with any electronic medical device / implant i.e. pacemaker
* Abnormality of clinical significance on medical history (including; current cancer, chronic lung disease, Depression, significant hormone problems (other than stable treated thyroid disease), kidney, respiratory, brain or gastrointestinal disease including gastrointestinal disease which may affect study outcomes)
* Any identified abnormality of specific blood or urine tests such as for liver function tests ((including ALT, AST or GGT greater than or equal to 2.5X upper limit of normal), Protein in the urine or HIV infection
 *HBA1c greater than 12%
 *BMI less than 26kg/m2 or greater than 45kg/m2
 *Taking glucocorticoids such as prednisone [oral/inhaled or topical] within last 3   months.
* Use of illicit drugs
 *Psychotropics other than a stable dose of an antidepressant
 *Musculoskeletal problems that prevent physical activity
 *History of heavy alcohol consumption (more than 2 standard drink on &gt; 4 days per week)
 *History of or current eating disorder
 *Not willing to cease alcohol consumption for study duration
 *Not willing to comply with study protocols
 *Inability to prepare meals or meet dietary requirements
 *Extended absences due to travel or other commitments
 *Active/Current Gastro-Intestinal Disorders
 *Past history of gastrointestinal surgery which may affect study outcomes (ie stomach surgery due to cancer)
 *Diagnosed food intolerances (i.e. lactose intolerance)
 *Medications which affect bowel movement or hunger /appetite (e.g.metoclopramide, domperidone and cisapride, anticholinergic drugs (eg atropine), erythromycin)
 *Unable to comprehend the requirements of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The proposed study is to be a feasibility pilot study. The benefits of a feasibility pilot study is that it is a small-scale investigation that is conducted prior to an adequately powered randomized control trial, that provides researchers an opportunity to identify  important parameters that are needed to design the main study. The purpose of this feasibility pilot is to look at the standard deviation of the primary outcome measures to estimate adequate sample size, willingness  of participants to actively wear a CGM device and sensor and the tolerance of wear in time and location of sensor and the usefulness and limitations of the secondary outcome measures. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>19/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CSIRO </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gate 13, Kinotre Avenue Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetes Australia Research Trust  (DART)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Diabetes Australia Research Trust
GPO Box 3156
Canberra ACT 2600
Australia </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic Australisia Pty.Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Medtronic Australasia Pty Ltd
 5 Alma Road
 Macquarie Park NSW 2113
 PO Box 945
 North Ryde NSW 1670
* provision of CGM Devices and Sensors</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Medtronic Australisia Pty.Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Medtronic Australasia Pty Ltd
 5 Alma Road
 Macquarie Park NSW 2113
 PO Box 945
 North Ryde NSW 1670
* provision of CGM Devices and Sensors</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Adelaide </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Tce,  
City of Adelaide
SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to determine how effective real-time continuous glucose monitoring (RT-CGMS) compared with standard care self-management blood glucose (SMBG) is for improving glycaemic control, and enhancing quality of life in response to the prescription of a lifestyle modification program in overweight and obese individuals with type 2 diabetes (T2D)

If shown to be effective, this innovative public health, clinical service delivery model can be used in a cost effective manner to enhance current self-management approaches for diabetes and be incorporated by health professionals as part of mainstream diabetes management practice that will improve cardiovascular health on a wide-scale community level.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Of Adelaide Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Tce,
Adelaide City,
SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2016-259</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/o Dr Anneliese Spinks
CSIRO Human Research Ethics Committee
Ecosciences Precinct,
41 Boggo Road, Dutton Park QLD 4102

*Reciprocal Ethics Approval</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RR 4-2017</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372898-CGM Insertion Instructions HREC 2017-259.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372898-RR 4_2017 endorsement 240317.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Grant Brinkworth</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Health
Riverside Corporate Park
11 Julius Avenue, North Ryde NSW 2113.</address>
      <phone>  +61294905665</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>grant.brinkworth@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Pennie Taylor (PhD Candidate)</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Health 
PO Box 10041, Adelaide, South Australia, 5000 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038954</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pennie.taylor@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Campbell Thompson </name>
      <address>University of Adelaide
Discipline of Medicine
North Terrace
Adelaide, South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038954</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>campbell.thompson@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Pennie Taylor</name>
      <address>CSIRO Food and Health 
PO Box 10041, Adelaide, South Australia, 5000 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038954</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pennie.taylor@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>