<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373665">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001360303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using e-learning and the theory of planned behaviour to predict behavioural intention in Chronic Kidney Disease screening practices in Australian primary health care nurses: A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Using e-learning and the theory of planned behaviour to predict behavioural intention in Chronic Kidney Disease screening practices in Australian primary health care nurses: A randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1202-2557 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will use a single blinded pre-post interventional randomised controlled trial design to evaluate the effectiveness of an asynchronous internet based e-learning module on Australian primary health care nurses knowledge and behavioural intentions in relation to opportunistic screening practices in people at risk of Chronic Kidney Disease (CKD). Participants will be randomised to either an active control (e-learning module focused on CKD screening knowledge only) or intervention arm (interactive e-learning module focused on barriers to opportunistic CKD screening and information related to potential solutions. 9 challenges related to CKD risk identification and screening were identified in a previous study that informed the intervention. Practical solutions to these challenges were developed and delivered by a team of primary health care nurses using a variety of multimedia and other resources in the intervention. The participant identifies which challenges are relevant to them and follows a pathway that presents potential solutions that are specific to their needs). Given that the intervention is an online asynchronous e-learning program it can be completed by participants at any time or any place that is convenient to them as long as they have access to the internet.  The intervention was designed in collaboration with primary health care nurses and peer reviewed by nurse educators, nurse practitioners, academics and other key stakeholders in kidney health in Australia. Participants undertaking the active control are expected to complete the module in 60 minutes. Participants undertaking the intervention are expected to complete the intervention within 90 - 150 minutes depending on their level of knowledge on CKD screening (determined by an online survey (i.e. knowledge quiz) prior to starting intervention module. Intervention adherence or fidelity will not be directly assessed as part of this study due to the independent and interactive nature of the intervention which is pragmatic and allows participants to identify challenges that are exclusive and tailored to their personal needs. Participants will not be able complete post intervention surveys unless they have completed the entire e-learning module assigned to them.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control arm will be exposed to a case study focused internet based e-learning module that focuses on two learning outcomes: 
1. Identify the major risk factors for developing CKD
2. Describe the best practice screening method for CKD</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioural intention as assessed by the Theory of Planned Behaviour Chronic Kidney Disease Identification and Screening Questionnaire  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within one week of completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary health care nurses perceived satisfaction with an asynchronous web based e-learning module evaluated using the Learner Satisfaction with asynchronous e-Learning tool</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon completion of module/s</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary health care nurses knowledge about CKD risk factors and screening practices using a CKD knowledge evaluation tool</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon completion of module</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be eligible for the study if they are currently working as a nursing aligned health care professional (i.e. practice nurse) in a primary health care in Australia </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Anyone who is not currently working as a nursing aligned health care professional (i.e. practice nurse) in a primary health care in Australia </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer program</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation with blocks of randomly varying size (4 or 6), stratified by rurality and years of experience (&lt; 10 years or 10+ years). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation was performed using Stata version 14 (Statacorp, College Station, TX). Based on a power of 0.80 with a two sided a of 0.05 and assuming a mean standardised effect size of (Cohens d) 0.3  the study will require a total of 110 participants per group (220 in total). This calculation assumes a baseline/follow-up correlation of 0.6. Assuming attrition up to 20%, we need to recruit 140 per group (280 in total).  A sample of this size is achievable as there are currently 4000 practice nurses registered with the APNA. Assuming a consent rate of 20% this means this means a sample of 800 participants could be achieved.

Data analysis will be conducted using the statistical software package JMP version 11.2 for Windows (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). A p value of =0.05 will be considered to be statistically significant.
Demographic data including age, gender, geographic location, job title, nursing history  and previous exposure to kidney health related continuing professional development opportunities will be analysed using the chi-square test and independent t-tests. These tests will be used to examine the comparability of the two cohorts and determine whether there are any significant differences in their demographic characteristics and/or pre-test knowledge scores (Merrill, 2013). 
Primary Hypothesis: Effectiveness of the intervention on the primary outcome within 1 week follow-up assessed by comparing those who receive the intervention against the active control group. The analysis will be done using Analysis of Covariance (ANCOVA). The treatment group and baseline value of the outcome will be included in the model as covariates. The intervention will be considered statistically significantly better than control if the p-value for the treatment group comparison is &lt;0.05. An intention-to-treat analysis will be performed by including all available data from all participants randomised into the study. 
Secondary hypothesis: The relationship between behavioural intent and the theoretical constructs of the Theory of Planned Behaviour (attitude, subjective norm and perceived behavioural control) will be assessed through linear regression. The outcome in the model will be behavioural intent, and independent variables will include treatment arm, the constructs of the Theory of Planned Behaviour. Potentially confounding variables such as age, years of experience and rurality will also be included in the model.


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>280</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>3/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Newcastle
Faculty of Health &amp; Medicine
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Newcastle
Faculty of Health &amp; Medicine
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Opportunistic screening for chronic kidney disease in the primary care health setting plays an integral role in early detection and subsequent management. However, there are significant deficits in current screening practices despite early identification being a national kidney health priority. Consequently, there is a need to identify strategies to improve screening practices. One potential way is through the education of practice nurses. However equitable access to professional development opportunities, particularly for nurses from rural and remote communities, can be challenging. E-learning provides a potential solution to this challenge. 
This study will use a single blinded randomised controlled trial to evaluate the effectiveness of an asynchronous e-learning module on learner satisfaction, knowledge acquisition and changes in behavioural intentions related to the primary health care nurses intentions to perform a kidney health check. The primary hypothesis of the study is that participants randomised to an asynchronous e-learning group will have an increase in behavioural intention of at least 0.3 standard deviation within one week follow-up, measured using the theory of planned behaviour, compared with participants randomised to an active control group. Behaviour intention will be evaluated using a an instrument constructed with reference to the Theory of Planned Behaviour and will be the major focus of this study. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Newcastle
Faculty of Health &amp; Medicine
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2016-0394</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373665-HREC Expedited Approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ashley Kable</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery
Faculty of Health &amp; Medicine
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 6334</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashley.kable@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Sinclair</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery
Faculty of Health &amp; Medicine
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 7436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.sinclair@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Sinclair</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery
Faculty of Health &amp; Medicine
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 7436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.sinclair@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Sinclair</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery
Faculty of Health &amp; Medicine
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 7436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.sinclair@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>