<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368771">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000935538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>12 weeks of single-leg cycling in individuals with coronary artery disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In individuals with stable coronary artery disease, does single-leg cycling improve functional capacity greater than double-leg cycling?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary artery disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants with stable heart disease will be randomised to one of two exercise groups involving 12 weeks of different forms of cycling. One group will undertake single-leg high intensity interval cycle training and the second group will undertake double-leg high intensity interval cycle training. 

All exercise intensities will be prescribed according to a predetermined level of perceived exertion, using the Borg 6-20 rating of perceived exertion (RPE) scale, which is associated with a desired percent of aerobic capacity (VO2peak). Each session will begin and end with a 5 minute double-leg cycling based warm-up (intensity; RPE 11-13, 40-60% VO2peak) and cool down (intensity; RPE 8-10, 20-40% VO2peak), followed by a 20 minute resistance circuit, as is standard practice in cardiac rehabilitation programs. During the double-leg high intensity interval sessions, the participant will complete ten 30 second double-leg efforts at an RPE 15-17 (60-85% VO2peak) with each effort separated by 60 seconds of passive rest (RPE 6; &lt;20% VO2peak). During the single-leg high intensity interval sessions, participants will complete ten 30 second single-leg efforts at an RPE of 15-17 with each effort separated by 60 seconds of passive rest (RPE 6). At the completion of the first ten efforts, a short break will be provided (~5 minutes) prior to the participant completing another ten efforts with the opposite leg.

3 sessions per week will be prescribed and monitored by Miss Nicole Gordon, an ESSA Accredited Exercise Physiologist. Program adherence will be monitored through exercise logs.</interventions>
    <comparator>The double-leg high intensity group will be used as the control group upon which the focus of the study, single-leg high intensity cycling, will be compared against.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional capacity will be assessed during a graded exercise test to volitional exhaustion on a cycle ergometer for determine of maximal aerobic capacity.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activities of daily living will be assessed by the five times sit-to-stand, 30 seconds sit-to-stand and the timed up and go tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial function will be assessed by noninvasive ultrasound of an artery in the arm (brachial artery) to evaluate flow-mediated dilation and glyceryl trinitrate-mediated dilation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart structure will be assessed by cardiac MRI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition will be assessed by waist and hip circumference as well as a dual energy xray absorptiometry (DEXA) scan for determination of body fat, muscle and bone mineral content.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leg strength will be assessed by a series of isokinetic and isometric tests of the quadriceps muscle on a HumacNorm Dynamometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular risk factor status will be assessed as a composite outcome by a single fasting blood sample analysing cholesterol profile, insulin sensitivity and markers of inflammation (CRP and fibrinogen).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General quality of life will be assessed by the Short Form 12 questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart function will be assessed by impedance cardiography (PhysioFlow) during the graded exercise test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels will be assessed by the International Physical Activity Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychosocial status will be assessed by the Cardiac Depression Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life will be assessed by the MacNew Health-related Quality of Life questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed at baseline and following the 12 week exercise intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals with established coronary artery disease assessed by angiography, a history of an acute coronary syndrome, or elective percutaneous coronary intervention or coronary artery bypass grafting surgery.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals less than 6 months after an acute cardiac event or surgery, signs or symptoms of myocardial ischaemia at rest, or in response to maximal exercise testing, left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; /= 45%, moderate to severe aortic stenosis, a history of complex ventricular arrhythmias, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus or hypertension, recent medication change (&lt;2 weeks), or orthopaedic or neurological disorders.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation by computer, and then placed into sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The power analysis (a = 0.05, power = 0.8, calculated total sample size = 58) was completed using a difference in peak aerobic capacity of 2.5 +/- 3.3 mL/kg/min following 8 weeks of single-leg high intensity cycling in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease [Bjorgen 2009]. An additional 2 participants will be recruited to account for dropouts, giving a total target sample size of 60 participants.

All analyses will be conducted on an intention-to-treat basis. Linear mixed modelling will be used to assess differences between interventions for physiological, functional and psychosocial outcomes. Significant main effects or interactions will be analysed using Tukeys post hoc analysis. Statistical analysis will be performed using SPSS v21.0 data analysis software (SPSS, Chicago, IL) with significance set at p &lt; 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/04/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychology and Exercise Science, Murdoch University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fiona Stanley Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>102-118 Murdoch Dr
Murdoch WA 6150</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Perth Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>197 Wellington St
Perth WA 6000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Curtin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Kent St
Bentley WA 6102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>60 participants will be recruited to complete 12 weeks of either single-leg high intensity interval cycling or double-leg high intensity interval cycling. This study aims to determine the functional, psychosocial and physiological effects of cycle exercise training using either one or two legs. This will be a parallel randomised group design recruiting individuals 18-80 years of age with established coronary artery disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Southern Integrated Research Organisation (SIRO) 
Level 2, Southern Research Facility (Perkins South Building)
102  118 Murdoch Drive 
Murdoch WA 6150
Locked Bag 100 Palmyra DC WA 6961</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REG 14-159</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicole Gordon</name>
      <address>REF3.001, Refectory building, Murdoch University, 90 South Street, Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 448 098 227</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Gordon@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicole Gordon</name>
      <address>REF3.001, Refectory building, Murdoch University, 90 South Street, Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 448 098 227</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Gordon@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicole Gordon</name>
      <address>REF3.001, Refectory building, Murdoch University, 90 South Street, Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 448 098 227</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Gordon@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>