<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82777">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000354381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does the addition of inpatient aquatic physiotherapy hasten recovery after total joint replacement surgery?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does a specific inpatient aquatic physiotherapy program after joint replacement surgery improve strength more than additional ward physiotherapy or water exercise?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>hip and knee arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants received standard post-operative ward physiotherapy as clinically determined by the treating physiotherapist for the first three days post-operatively. Throughout the intervention stage of the trial, from Day 4 to discharge, all participants continued to receive one ward physiotherapy treatment each day, following the standard orthopaedic clinical pathway used at the hospital. The experimental treatment was in addition to usual care. From Day 4 after surgery, participants completed one of the two aquatic treatment programs each day until discharge. All treatments were one-on-one individual physiotherapy treatment sessions to standardise intervention between the groups and also to allow close monitoring of the physiological response to immersion in the early days after surgery. The aquatic physiotherapy intervention consisted of exercises in 30% weight-bearing (chest deep water) focusing on strength using speed of movement as well as functional activities such as step ups and squats, walking forwards, backwards and sideways, balance exercises and open-chain strengthening exercises using equipment for increased resistance eg flippers. The water exercise program was undertaken in 10% weight-bearing (neck-deep water) at a slow speed and involved exercises such as marching and single-leg standing on the non-operated leg, walking forwards and general upper limb strengthening exercises. The number of additional physiotherapy treatments was recorded for all participants and on average, participants received 3.5 additional treatments while in hospital. Each treatment session lasted 40 minutes and the average length of stay was 7.5 days. The primary end-point of the trial was Day 14. After discharge home from the acute hospital and having completed the Day 14 assessments, participants were free to undertake whatever, if any, post-operative physiotherapy they chose.</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants received standard post-operative ward physiotherapy as clinically determined by the treating physiotherapist for the first three days post-operatively. Throughout the intervention stage of the trial, from Day 4 to discharge, all participants continued to receive one ward physiotherapy treatment each day, following the standard orthopaedic clinical pathway used at the hospital. The control group received a second ward physiotherapy treatment each day from Day 4 until discharge. All treatments in the ward were one-on-one individual physiotherapy treatment sessions to standardise intervention between the groups.The additional ward treatment was a second session of the same exercises and included strength and range of motion exercises in supine and standing as well as mobility/gait re-education. The number of additional physiotherapy treatments was recorded for all participants and on average, participants received 3.5 additional treatments while in hospital. Each treatment session lasted 40 minutes and the average length of stay was 7 days. The primary end-point of the trial was Day 14. After discharge home from the acute hospital and having completed the Day 14 assessments, participants were free to undertake whatever, if any, post-operative physiotherapy they chose.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip abductor strength of operated limb, measured by hand-held dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and then Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 after surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional recovery measured by Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) LK 3.1 (V3 Australia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and than Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 post-operatively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in walking speed measured by the 10m walk test, timed with a stopwatch from a standing start</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and then Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 post-operatively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery of quadriceps and hamstrings strength of operated limb, measured with hand-held dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and then Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>resolution of post-operative swelling measured with a tape measure at mid-patella level and recovery of active range of motion measured using a goniometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and then Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>recovery of functional mobility by using the time taken to complete the timed Up and Go test, timed with a stopwatch</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and then Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to participation in usual activities measured using the Patient-Specific Functional Measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and then Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy measured using two sub-scales of the Arthritis Self Efficacy Scale: self-efficacy to achieve outcomes and self-efficacy to manage symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-operatively, and then Day 14, Day 90 and Day 180 post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>all people from one orthopaedic surgery practice undergoing primary knee or hip replacement surgery for osteoarthritis in The Wesley Hospital who were able to be assessed at home before admission and lived within the Brisbane metropolitan area for follow-up after surgery</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>medically unwell day 4 post-operatively
any diagnosed neurological disorder, 
had another major musculoskeletal problem that altered mobility other than the specified joint (eg low back pain, severe osteoarthritis (OA) in another lower limb joint), 
cognitive dysfunction 
were undergoing revision joint surgery or bilateral knee replacements.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>simple randomisation using sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>envelopes were prepared, shuffled and numbered consecutively prior to commencement of study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ann Rahmann</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department
Building 84A
Services Road
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Wesley Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level B2, Moorlands Wing
The Wesley Hospital
451 Coronation Drive 
Auchenflower Qld 4066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Jennifer Nitz</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Physiotherapy Department
Building 84A
Services Road
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Sandra Brauer</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Physiotherapy Department
Building 84A
Services Road
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>No studies to our knowledge have been published on the use of aquatic physiotherapy from Day 4 post-operatively after THR or TKR surgery. This randomised controlled trial was therefore undertaken to investigate whether inpatient aquatic physiotherapy from Day 4 in addition to usual ward physiotherapy improved early functional recovery more than non-specific water exercise or additional ward physiotherapy. The primary endpoint of the trial was Day 14. Considering the usual level of activity in healthy older people, rehabilitation to optimal function after joint replacement is usually the aim of physiotherapy. Reduced strength and gait dysfunction can persist for many months after joint replacement. If return to normal function and activity is the goal of physiotherapy intervention after joint replacement surgery, follow-up beyond the early post-acute phase is important to understand the longer term impact of early rehabilitation. Participants were therefore followed up for six months after surgery to more thoroughly gauge functional recovery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presented in part at the Australasian Centre on Ageings Emerging Researchers in Ageing Conference, December 2004, Brisbane, Australia and the Australian Physiotherapy Associations National Aquatic Physiotherapy Symposium, August 2005, Sydney, Australia.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Office of Research and Postgraduate Studies
Cumbrae-Stewart Bldg (72)
Building 72,
Hawken Drive
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/11/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2002000723</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Wesley Hospital Multidisciplinary Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Wesley Hospital
451 Coronation Drive
Auchenflower, Qld 4066</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2002/29</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Ann Rahmann</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Building 84A,
Services Road,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
the University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2275</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>a.rahmann@shrs.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Ann Rahmann</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Building 84A,
Services Road,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
the University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2275</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>a.rahmann@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Ann Rahmann</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Building 84A,
Services Road,
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
the University of Queensland
St Lucia, Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2275</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>a.rahmann@shrs.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>