<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369267">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001115527p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Transdermal dihydrotestosterone Gel to Improve In Vitro Fertilization Outcomes In Women With Poor Ovarian Response
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Transdermal DHT Gel to Improve IVF Outcomes In Women With Poor Ovarian Response
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Women with poor ovarian response undergoing IVF</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>DHT gel 5mg daily transdermal application for 21 days prior to controlled ovarian stimulation: The DHT or placebo gel will be similar and packed into capped 1 ml tuberculin-type syringes without needles and labelled with study and participant IDs. Each syringe has sufficient gel for 5 daily doses. Participating women will be given a supply of 5 syringes at the enrollment visit.. They will return the syringes at the end of the DHT treatment period (Day 21 of this study).

Compliance:
Compliance will be determined by counting returned syringes on day 21. 

In addition women will provide at least one finger prick dried blood sample (DBS) at home to evaluate serum DHT during treatment. This uses our established DBS technology using a finger prick, similar to home blood glucose motoring, at home. Using a standard lancet, whole blood is dropped or smeared onto Guthrie-type filter paper and air dried. The filter paper with DBS can be kept in a dry place (plastic bag) at home without any special handling procedures unlike serum from venepuncture (i.e. no requirement for blood clotting, separation or refrigeration). The filter papers are returned with the used syringes for subsequently measurement of serum DHT. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo gel- Glycerin and purified water</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of clinical pregnancies - review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of IVF treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of follicles on hCG day - review of medical records
</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of IVF treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of oocytes retrieved- Review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of IVF treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of oocytes fertilised- review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of IVF treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of embryos- review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of IVF treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cycle cancellation rate - review of medical reocrds</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of IVF treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total dose &amp; duration of FSH - review of medical  records</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of IVF treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sexual function (modified FSFI scale) - review of the answers to the questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of IVF treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Steroid profiles in the serum and follicular fluid and correlation of these with the standard IVF outcomes - review of medical notes</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of IVF treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>evaluate mRNA expression for AR splice variants and noncoding RNA regulatory FSH receptor - review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of IVF treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Miscarriage rate - review of medical notes</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of IVF treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse effects - At the day 21 visit, participants will be asked to if they have experienced any unusual, unexpected or unwanted effects (symptoms, signs, conditions or an observation) since they started treatment. Any reports of undesirable or unwelcome effects will be documented as adverse events (AE). The investigators will also judge whether the AE is definitely, likely, possible or unrelated to the study medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of IVF treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Age &gt;18 years
*Modified Bologna criteria stratified by age
-For women &gt;40 years, no additional inclusion criteria  
-For women &lt;40 years, at least one additional inclusion criterion either previous IVF cycle with POR (&lt;3 oocytes with conventional stimulation) and/or impaired ovarian reserve (ultrasonic antral follicle count &lt;7 follicles or serum AMH &lt;1.1 ng/ml) 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Use of androgens or pro-androgens in previous 2 months
*Perimenopausal (no regular cycle, high serum FSH)
*Major uterine abnormalities 
*History of untreated systemic medical disease or organ failure (eg impaired cardiac, respiratory, hepatic, or renal function)
*Extensive skin disease that would interfere with use of the transdermal gel
*Participation in other clinical trials of medical therapy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients attending RPAH IVF clinics will be invited to participate subject to providing written informed consent and meeting eligibility criteria. Patient recruitment will be undertaken by the gynaecologist co-investigators Dr Marren and Associate Professor Bowman, together with their fellow clinicians and clinic nurses.

Eligible, consenting participants will receive a consecutive, unique study enrolment number which will be documented in the participant’s medical record and all study documents. The participants will be randomized at the enrolment visit according to their unique study ID number to receive either DHT or placebo gel. All study staff and participants will remain blinded to treatment throughout the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Eligible, consenting participants will receive a consecutive, unique study enrolment number which will be documented in the participant’s medical record and all study documents. The participants will be randomized at the enrolment visit according to their unique study ID number to receive either DHT or placebo gel. All study staff and participants will remain blinded to treatment throughout the study.

Randomization is according to a computer-generated random list, prepared by a person not directly involved with the study participants. The randomisation allocations will be provided in sealed opaque envelopes marked with the study ID number on the outside to allow for concealed allocation in a 1:1 ratio to either the DHT or placebo treatment groups. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is an investigator-initiated, proof-of-concept study as a randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel group clinical trial of DHT (5mg vs placebo) gel used daily for 21 days immediately prior to an IVF hyperstimulation cycle with the goal of improving ovarian response in women with prior poor ovarian response to IVF. 

Eligible, consenting participants will, on enrolment, receive a unique study number which will be documented in the participants case record forms and all study documents. Participants will be randomly assigned to treatment (DHT or placebo) in a 1:1 ratio by means of receiving an opaque envelope numbered with her study ID on the outside and containing on the inside the drug allocation code. The randomization is created by a computer-generated randomization list of drug allocation codes so as to assure concealment of allocation from study staff and participants. 
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary and secondary endpoints will be analysed on an intention-to-treat basis for efficacy endpoints and for per protocol for safety endpoints using paired t-tests or mixed model analysis of variance to incorporate covariables based on known risk factors for poor IVF outcomes. 

Sample size and power:
Power calculation (PASS software) assuming two-sided alpha=0.05, beta=0.2 (80% power) and a background pregnancy rate in women with POR of 15% indicates that 121 women/group are required to reliably detect a significant benefit of DHT pre-treatment as defined as a doubling of the pregnancy rates to 30%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 0</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>8/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>242</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof.David Handelsman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The ANZAC Research Institute
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Gate 3, Hospital Road
Concord NSW 2139, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Local Health District, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Missenden Road
Camperdown 
NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite the advances in assisted reproduction techniques, suboptimal In Vitro Fertilization(IVF) outcomes in women with Poor Ovarian Response(POR) still remains a challenge. Older women seeking IVF have suboptimal utcomes, at least partly due to inadequate number of eggs on conventional stimulation. This suboptimal response relates
mainly to inadequate ovarian response but there is often also reduced live birth rates, increased risk cycle cancellation and a need larger doses of gonadotrophins, which increases both cost and risk of ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (OHSS) risk.

There is now growing evidence that androgens (or male hormones) may improve egg quality and numbers in women with POR. So far the androgens used in women with POR include testosterone and the pro-androgen hormone Dehydroepiandrosterone(DHEA) as well as aromatase inhibitor drugs, which increase the bodys own testosterone levels by blocking its conversion to estradiol. For each of these drugs, their multiple levels of action mean that it is not clear whether they produce any benefits by acting as an androgen (or male hormone). For this reason, this study is using dihydrotestosterone (DHT), the natural product of testosterone in the body of men and women, and which acts only as a pure androgen in the body. As a result, the study will determine for the first time whether these drugs do work as androgens or not and may refine and improve the treatment for POR. In this study we will temporarily increase the circulating levels of DHT during the time when oocyte (egg) development and maturation is occurring. This will be achieved by applying the DHT gel onto the skin once a day for 21 days prior to the start of IVF ovarian stimulation.

Aims: 
To investigate the efficacy of DHT gel treatment applied onto the skin before an IVF stimulation cycle in women with poor ovarian response.

Research Hypothesis
DHT pre-treatment prior to an IVF cycle will improve the number of healthy, fertilisable eggs retrieved.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District - RPAH</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden road
Camperdown
NSW  2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Handelsman</name>
      <address>ANZAC Research Institute,
Gate 3, Concord Repatriation General Hospital, Hospital Road,
Concord  NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 97679100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>djh@anzac.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nandini Shankara Narayana</name>
      <address>ANZAC Research Institute,
Gate 3, Concord Repatriation General Hospital, Hospital Road,
Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 97676026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nsha7690@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nandini Shankara Narayana</name>
      <address>ANZAC Research Institute,
Gate 3, Concord Repatriation General Hospital, Hospital Road,
Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 97676026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nsha7690@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nandini Shankara Narayana</name>
      <address>ANZAC Research Institute,
Gate 3, Concord Repatriation General Hospital, Hospital Road,
Concord 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 97676026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nsha7690@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>