<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335349">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000286044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Simplified Regimens for Management of Possible Serious Bacterial Infections in Neonates and Young Infants for Use in Outpatient and Community Settings: A multi-centre Randomized Controlled Trial in Africa</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of treatment failure rate between three simplified regimens and a reference regimen for management of possible serious bacterial infections in neonates and young infants.: A multi-centre randomized controlled trial in Africa</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1114-6362</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Possible serious bacterial infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Stratum I (severe infection) 
To test the efficacy of the following three simpler regimens, compared to the reference regimen, in children who have 'severe infection'
- Treatment regimen B: injection gentamicin once daily (4-6.5 mg/kg/day) and oral amoxicillin (75-100 mg/kg/day) twice daily for 7 days (7 injections in total)
- Treatment regimen C: injection gentamicin (4-6.5 mg/kg/day) once daily and injection procaine penicillin (40,000-60,000 units/kg/day) once daily for 2 days, thereafter oral amoxicillin (75-100 mg/kg/day) for 5 days (4 injections in total)
- Treatment regimen D: injection gentamicin (4-6.5 mg/kg/day) once daily and oral amoxicillin (75-100 mg/kg/day) for 5 days twice daily for 2 days, thereafter oral amoxicillin (75-100 mg/kg/day) twice daily for 5 days (2 injections in total)

Stratum II (fast breathing only)
To test the efficacy of the following simpler regimen, compared to the reference regimen, in children who have fast breathing:
- Treatment regimen E: Oral amoxicillin (75-100 mg/kg/day) twice daily for 7 days</interventions>
    <comparator>- Reference Treatment Regimen A: injection gentamicin (4-6.5 mg/kg/day)once daily and injection procaine penicillin (40,000-60,000 units/kg/day) once daily for 7 days (14 injections in total)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment failure based on clinical criteria, which will be assessed clinically.
Definition of treatment failure in Stratum I

1.	Death anytime within 7 days after randomization (day 1-8 of enrolment).
2.	Persistence of the presenting sign/symptom suggestive of severe infection (if single presenting sign) or persistence of &gt;1 presenting sign/symptom suggestive of severe infection (if multiple presenting signs) after 72 hours of randomization (day 4 of enrolment).
3.	After initial disappearance within 72 hours after randomization, re-emergence of any presenting sign (temperature should be at least 38.0 degree Centigrade or higher on 2 or more days) 
4.	Clinical deterioration: emergence of any sign of being critically ill at any time after randomization [as defined in exclusion criteria]
5.	Emergence of any new sign of severe infection (any of the 5 signs) after 24 hours of randomization (day 3 of enrolment)
6.	Persistence of any sign of severe infection at 7 days (day 8 of enrolment).
7.	Development of serious adverse effect of the study antibiotics (death, organ failure, anaphylactic reaction, severe diarrhoea, disseminated and severe rash).
8.	Hospitalization decided by the family, anytime after admission in the study.

Definition of treatment failure in Stratum II

1.	Death anytime within 7 days after randomization (day 1-8 of enrolment).
2.	No improvement in respiratory rate at 72 hours (reduction in respiratory rate of &lt;10 breaths per minute compared to baseline) (day 4 of enrolment)
3.	Clinical deterioration: emergence of any sign of being critically ill or severe infection at any time after randomization [as defined in exclusion criteria] 
4.	Persistence of fast breathing at 7 days (day 8 of enrolment).
5.	Development of serious adverse effect of the study antibiotics (death, organ failure, anaphylactic reaction, severe diarrhoea, disseminated and severe rash).
6.	Hospitalization decided by the family, anytime after admission in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days (day 1-8 of enrolment) of enrolment and treatment initation. Once daily clinical assessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to study therapy by daily direct administration/obsvervation of therapy by study health worker and recording on a treatment form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days of enrolment and treatment initation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse through clinical observation. Definition signs of 'severe infection' (stratum I) or' fast breathing' (stratum II) disappear on day 8 of enrolment, but develop any sign of severe infection or being critically ill between day 9 and day 14. In stratum II, an additional sign would be re-emergence of fast breathing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between 8-14 days of initiation of treatment. Observed on day 11 and day 15 of enrollment by the health worker. But if needed a patient could be seen on other days between this time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serious adverse effects (such as death, organ failure, anaphylactic reaction, severe diarrhoea, disseminated and severe rash) due to study drugs observed and recorded on serious adverse event or death form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-8 days after initiation of treatment (once daily observation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stratum 1 (severe infection): One or more of the  following five signs of 'severe infection' - not feeding well, movement only when stimulated, severe chest indrawing, axillary temperature &gt;38.0 degree Centigrade or &lt;35.5 degree Centigrade and informed consent is provided by a parent (or legal guardian).

Stratum II (fast breathing only): Fast breathing i.e., respiratory rate 60 or more per minute and Informed consent is provided by a parent (or legal guardian)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Stratum I: Exclusion Criteria
- Critically ill infant characterized by presence of any of the following signs - unconscious, convulsions, unable to feed at all, apnea, unable to cry, cyanosis, bulging fontanelle, major congenital malformations inhibiting oral antibiotic intake, active bleeding requiring transfusion, surgical conditions needing hospital referral, persistent vomiting defined as vomiting following three attempts to feed the baby within ½ hour
- Very low weight (&lt;1500g at the time of presentation)
- Hospitalization for illness in the last two weeks 
- Previous inclusion in the study

Stratum II: Exclusion Criteria
- Any signs of severe infection: not feeding well, movement only when stimulated, severe chest in-drawing, axillary temperature &gt;38.0 degree Centigrade or &lt;35.5 degree Centigrade , 
- Any sign of being critically ill
- Very low weight (&lt;1500g at the time of presentation)
- Hospitalization for illness in the last two weeks 
- Previous inclusion in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>For allocation concealment, treatment code for each enrolled study infant will be sealed in an opaque envelope (different  colour envelopes for Stratum I and Stratum II).</concealment>
    <sequence>There would be two randomization schemes, one each for stratum I young infants with "severe infection" and stratum II "fast breathing only"¨. Block randomization schemes will be computer-generated off site at World Health Organization (WHO).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is an open (un-blinded) study because a double injection regimen is being compared to single injection-oral regimen combinations, and an oral only switch regimen; blinding participants and investigators by using placebo injections would thus not be justifiable.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>6900</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Congo, The Democratic Republic Of The</country>
      <state>Equateur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Nigeria</country>
      <state>Oyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Kenya</country>
      <state>Eldoret</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>World Health Organization</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>20 Avenue Appia, Geneva 1211</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Switzerland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Avenue Appia, Geneva 1211</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 23350
Seattle, WA 98102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ahmadu Bello University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 06, Shika
Zaria
Kaduna State</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Nigeria</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Ibadan</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>College of Medicine
PMB 5116
Ibadan, Oyo State</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Nigeria</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Obafemi Awolowo University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Obafemi Awolowo University Teaching Hospital
Ile-Ife
Osun State</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Nigeria</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Moi University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>P.O. Box 4606 - 030100
Eldoret</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Kenya</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>London University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine (LSHTM)
Keppel Street
London WC1E 7HT</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: To conduct a multi-centre randomized controlled trial in three countries in Africa (Democratic Republic of Congo, Kenya and Nigeria) to test the safety and efficacy of simplified antibiotic regimens for treating possible serious bacterial infection in 0-59 day-old infants 
Participants: Study participants will be young infants 0 to 59 days old, from settings in low- and middle-income countries with a high infant mortality (at least 60/1000 live births), with clinical signs of possible serious bacterial infection whose families do not accept or cannot access referral level care. Infants who are critically ill will be excluded, and the study participants will be stratified into two groups according to the severity of the possible serious bacterial infection on admission:
- severe infection: not feeding well, movement only when stimulated, severe chest in-drawing, axillary temperature &gt;38.0 degree Centigrade or &lt;35.5 degree Centigrade; and
- fast breathing alone: respiratory rate 60 or more per minute.
The study will enroll a total of 6,200 young infants -- 3,600 in the stratum of young infants with possible severe infection and 2,600 in the stratum of less severe infection.
Reference treatment (Comparison): The comparison group will receive injection gentamicin once daily and injection procaine penicillin once daily for 7 days (Treatment Regimen A, 14 injections in total).
Experimental treatments (Intervention): The treatment regimens under evaluation will be:
1.	For severe infection: 
     Treatment Regimen B: injection gentamicin once daily and oral amoxicillin twice daily for 7 days (7 injections in total);
     Treatment Regimen C: injection gentamicin once daily and injection procaine penicillin once daily for 2 days, thereafter oral amoxicillin for 5 days (4 injections in total)
     Treatment Regimen D: injection gentamicin once daily and oral amoxicillin twice daily for 2 days, thereafter oral amoxicillin twice daily for 5 days (2 injections in total)
2.	Fast breathing alone:
	Treatment Regimen E: oral amoxicillin twice daily for 7 days
Outcomes:  Treatment failure in the first week following initiation of treatment (primary outcome); death in the first week following initiation of treatment, death the week following completion of treatment, relapse in the week following completion of treatment, and severe adverse effects related to the antibiotics (secondary outcomes).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WHO Ethical Review Committee (ERC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Avenue Appia, Geneva 1211</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/02/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NCH09008</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/12/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shamim Qazi</name>
      <address>20 Avenue Appia, Geneva 1211</address>
      <phone>+41227912547</phone>
      <fax>+41227914853</fax>
      <email>qazis@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shamim Qazi</name>
      <address>20 Avenue Appia, Geneva 1211</address>
      <phone>+41227912547</phone>
      <fax>+41227914853</fax>
      <email>qazis@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shamim Qazi</name>
      <address>20 Avenue Appia, Geneva 1211</address>
      <phone>+41227912547</phone>
      <fax>+41227914853</fax>
      <email>qazis@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>