<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362990">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001290886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effectiveness of the 10,000 Steps workplace challenge in increasing health outcomes for employees at Rockhampton Regional Council.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of the 10,000 Steps workplace challenge in increasing health outcomes for employees at Rockhampton Regional Council.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1134-3331</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To examine the effectiveness of the 10,000 Steps workplace challenge in increasing physical activity of employees and volunteers of the Rockhampton Regional Council using a clustered randomised crossover trial of the 10,000 Steps workplace challenge.

Employees of the council will be randomised into 2 groups: the intervention group will receive the 10,000 steps program first for a period of 6-weeks, and the waitlist control group will receive the 10,000 steps program once the intervention group has finished the challenge, followup measurements and questionaires.  Everyone who participates in the study will be asked to complete questionnaires about the length of time they sit, their physical activity, their mood, and quality of life at the beginning of the study.  Measurements such as height and weight, and hip and waist circumference will also be taken at the beginning of the study, in a private area at each workplace by one of the researchers.  At the beginning of the 10,000 steps workplace challenge pedometers will be issued for the participants to keep. Participants  will be asked to wear the pedometer each day during the 6-week challenge and to record the number of steps they have taken each day on the Central Queensland University 10,000 Steps web site (www.10000steps.org.au).  

This website also allows monitoring team progress and provides weekly updates on the team step count- the sharing of individual's step is used as a motivational strategy. Each site will have a champion who will guide and facilitate the workplace challenge to co-workers. 
Both groups will be asked to repeat the questionnaires and measurements at 6-weeks and 12-weeks after the commencement of the study and 6-months after the end of the 10,000 steps program the study. The measurements and questionnaires are expected to take 45 minutes each time they are completed. On completion of the 10, 000 steps challenge, there will be a short evaluation of how the participants found the challenge. </interventions>
    <comparator>The randomisation of participants will involve half of the sites receiving the intervention immediately (intervention group), whilst the other half of the sites (waitlist control) are assessed but do not receive the intervention until after a waiting period of 6 weeks. All participants will be assessed immediately prior to the 10,000 steps workplace challenge, post-test after 6 weeks of participating in the challenge, and 6 months post intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total steps of physical activity measured using the Yamax Digiwalker DW-150 pedomenter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cumulatively steps are logged on the 10,000 Steps website weekly and over the 6 week intervention for the waitlist control and intervention groups.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total minutes of sitting time at work measured using the Adapted Workforce Sitting Questionnaire and Occupational Physical Activity Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (both groups), after intervention (6 or 12 weeks depending on group) and 6-months after completing the intervention for both groups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life measured using the Australian Quality of Life Scale: AQoL-15 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (both groups), after intervention (6 or 12 weeks depending on group) and 6-months after completing the intervention for both groups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood measured using Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS-21).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (both groups), after intervention (6 or 12 weeks depending on group) and 6-months after completing the intervention for both groups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity measured using self reported Active Australia Questionairre</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (both groups), after intervention (6 or 13 weeks depending on group) and 6-months after completing the intervention for both groups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index:  Researcher will measure in a private area height, weight, waist and hip measurements. Height will be measured using a Seca 213 Portable Height Measuring Instrument, weight will be measured using Tanita HD351 scales and waist and hip using Seca 203 Circumference Measuring Tape.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (both groups), after intervention (6 or 12 weeks depending on group) and 6-months after completing the intervention for both groups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Demographics </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (both groups), after intervention (6 or 12 weeks depending on group) and 6-months after completing the intervention for both groups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male and female employees of Rockhampton Regional Council will be recruited as participants for this study. Volunteers will be eligible to participate if they work at the Rockhampton Regional Council, either full-time or part-time.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Employees will be excluded if they:
Currently meet the physical activity guidelines (150 min of moderate intensity physical activity in the last week);
Have a mobility impairment; severe communication disability that compromises the ability to participate in the 10,000 steps workplace challenge or complete the outcome measures; or a cognitive deficit that impairs the ability to read and write; 
Are pregnant women or women who have had a baby in the 3-months prior to the study as their BMI is likely to vary as a result of pregnancy or recent pregnancy; 
Are current users of the 10,000 Steps program;
If they cannot safely increase their physical activity; 
If they do not speak English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be conducted using central randomisation by a computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will occur using a randomisation list (i.e. randomisation.com)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures>Active- waitlist control design ( no intervention given)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4700 - Rockhampton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Queensland Hospital and Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rockhampton Hospital, Canning St, Rockhampton, QLD 4700.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Practitioner Novice Research Scheme 2012-2013, Queensland Health.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Central Queensland Hospital and Health Service, Queensland Health.
Rockhampton Hospital, Canning St, Rockhampton, QLD 4700.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>CQUniversity</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Central Queensland University
Centre for Physical Activity Studies 
Bld 18 Central Queensland University,
Bruce Highway 
Rockhampton 4702
Queensland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In Rockhampton 64.1% of adults are overweight or obese and half of the adults do engage in sufficient levels of physical activity (PA) to achieve health benefits. A new partnership between Queensland Health, Central Queensland University and the Rockhampton Regional Council the biggest employer in the region, may improve the health of workers by introducing the 10,000 Steps Workplace Challenge. The effectiveness of this program will be studied. We will examine whether the 10,000 workplace challenge increases physical activity, reduces total sitting time, reduces obesity, and increases quality of life. The benefits may extend to a reduction in chronic disease and health care costs within the Central Queensland Hospital and Health Service.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Executive Services 
PO Box 871 
Rockhampton 4700
Queensland </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/QCQ/23</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/07/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CQUniversity HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics and Compliance Officer                                        Office of Research - Building 361                                    CQUniversity                                                                        CQ Mail Centre 
Rockhampton   QLD  4702
Queensland

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H12/10-191</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mitch Duncan Senior Post-Doctoral Research Fellow</name>
      <address>Physical Activity and Health, 
10,000 Steps Project Leader
Bld 18 Central Queensland University,
Bruce Highway
 Rockhampton 4702
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 07 49306977</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.duncan@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Karen Toms</name>
      <address>Queensland Health
Rockhampton Community Health
86 Bolsover Street 
Rockhampton 4700
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 49206900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen_toms@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Karen Toms</name>
      <address>Rockhampton Community Health
86 Bolsover Street 
Rockhampton 4700
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 07 49206900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen_toms@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Karen Toms</name>
      <address>Rockhampton Community Health 
86 Bolsover Street 
Rockhampton 4700
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 49206900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen_toms@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>