<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347861">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000118808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does exercise following distal radius fracture improve activity? A multi-centre randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is a program of exercise and advice compared to advice, more effective in improving activity on the Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation questionnaire following a distal radius fracture?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-4511</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Distal Radius Fracture</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The experimental group will receive professional advice plus a progessive exercise program in three standard consultations (approximately 20-30 minutes) held in Weeks 7, 9 and 11 (from time of injury). In consultation 1 (Week 7), patients will receive advice regarding fracture healing, pain, swelling and performance of daily light tasks. In addition, patients will commence a light exercise program to include active range of movement exercises of the hand/wrist/elbow and shoulder as well as isometric strengthening exercises of the wrist/forearm. In consultation 2 (Week 9), patients will receive advice again about fracture healing, pain, swelling and performance of daily tasks. The exercise program will be progressed to include strengthening exercises of the hand and wrist (including grip strength). In consultation 3 (Week 11), patients will receive advice about returning to more difficult functional tasks and the exercise program will be progressed to include heavier loads. Patients will also receive advice to progress and continue the exercises for one more week (this will equate to 12 weeks from time of injury). Patients will be advised to complete the exercises three times per day with sets varying from one to three depending on the exercise and progression.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive the same program of professional advice that the experimental group received. This means they will receive three standard physiotherapy consultations in weeks 7, 9 and 11 which will last between 20-30 minutes. In consultation 1 (Week 7), patients will receive advice regarding fracture healing, pain, swelling and performance of daily light tasks.  In consultation 2 (Week 9), patients will receive advice again about fracture healing, pain, swelling and performance of daily tasks. In consultation 3 (Week 11), patients will receive advice about returning to more difficult functional tasks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome Measure 1: Activity limitations as assessed by the activity specific section on the Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: baseline = 0 weeks (time of recuitment = 5-6 weeks from time of injury)
Timepoint 2: following the intervention = 6 weeks
Timepoint 3: follow up = 18 weeks (24 weeks from time of injury)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome Measure 2: The 19 item QuickDASH questionnaire will be used to measure disability of the affected upper limb</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: baseline = 0 weeks (time of recuitment = 5-6 weeks from time of injury)
Timepoint 2: following the intervention = 6 weeks
Timepoint 3: follow up = 18 weeks (24 weeks from time of injury)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome Measure 3: Accelerometers will be used to quantify the extent of arm usage (the amount and intensity of arm activity) of participatis using the mean total activity over seven consecutive days</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: baseline = 0 weeks (time of recuitment = 5-6 weeks from time of injury)
Timepoint 2: following the intervention = 6 weeks
Timepoint 3: follow up = 18 weeks (24 weeks from time of injury)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Wrist flexion, extension and supination range of movement will be measured using a goniometer and following standard administering procedures as outlined by the American Society of Hand Therapists</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: baseline = 0 weeks (time of recuitment = 5-6 weeks from time of injury)
Timepoint 2: following the intervention = 6 weeks
Timepoint 3: follow up = 18 weeks (24 weeks from time of injury)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Isometric grip strength will be measured in kilograms using a calibrated Jamar dynamometer on setting 2 to ensure maximal grip strength and with the elbow flexed to 90 degrees</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: baseline = 0 weeks (time of recuitment = 5-6 weeks from time of injury)
Timepoint 2: following the intervention = 6 weeks
Timepoint 3: follow up = 18 weeks (24 weeks from time of injury)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Pain will be measured using the 5-item pain specific section of the Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: baseline = 0 weeks (time of recuitment = 5-6 weeks from time of injury)
Timepoint 2: following the intervention = 6 weeks
Timepoint 3: follow up = 18 weeks (24 weeks from time of injury)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: Adherence to the home based exercise program will be assessed using home exercise diaries. Participants will be required to make daily entries about the number of sessions they did and the number of exericses per session. To determine home exericse adherence rates, the amount of exericse performed will be compared to the amount of exercise prescribed</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: baseline = 0 weeks (time of recuitment = 5-6 weeks from time of injury)
Timepoint 2: following the intervention = 6 weeks
Timepoint 3: follow up = 18 weeks (24 weeks from time of injury)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- All adults referred to the outpatient physiotherapy departments at the recruited health agencies following a distal radius fracture and were managed in a cast
- Able to follow simple written and verbal English instructions so that the participant can complete the prescribed exercise program and provide consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Any pre-existing inflammatory joint condition, or signs and symptoms of complex regional pain syndrome, or previous wrist fracture on the affected side
- Bilateral wrist fractures or any other injury (such as other fracture or recent surgery) to the affected limb
- Any distal radius fracture that has been managed with internal or external fixation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be adults referred to the physiotherapy outpatient department at the participating health agencies for rehabilitation following a distal radius fracture. Potential participants, as recognised by the referral made to the physitoherapy department, will receive a participant information flyer from the physiotherapy department. All individuals who have been provided with an information flyer will be invited to speak with a member of the research team for more information and possible recuitment into the study. Appointments will be scheduled for interested participants and a member of the research team to explain the clincial trial verbally and in written form. They will at this point be invited to participate in the study. Patients will be randomised at their initial consultation with the treating physiotherapist. Assignments to either control or experimental group will be sealed in sequentially numbered opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted blocks, stratified for site and hand dominance, will be prepared to ensure that both experimental and control groups will be approximately the same. Permuted blocks will be generated from a random-number table. Generation of the block allocation system will be completed by a researcher who will have no involvement in patient recruitment, assessment or treatment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/06/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3076</postcode>
    <postcode>3135</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bundoora, Victoria, 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Physiotherapy Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 1175 Toorak Road Camberwell VIC 3124</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to find out if people following a distal radal fracture recover better if they receive a progressive exercise program. Our hypothesis is that a progressive exercise program imiplemented during the rehabilitation phase following a distal radius fracture in addition to advice will achieve better recovery of upper limb activity and functional activities than advice alone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Northern Hospital
185 Cooper Street
Epping
Victoria 
3076</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill
Victoria
3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Health Sciences
Level 2
Health Sciences Buidling 2
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria
3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Bruder</name>
      <address>La Trobe University
Department of Physiotherapy
Bundoora 
Victoria
3086</address>
      <phone>+61394795853</phone>
      <fax>+61394795768</fax>
      <email>a.bruder@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Bruder</name>
      <address>La Trobe University
Department of Physiotherapy
Bundoora 
Victoria
3086</address>
      <phone>+61394795853</phone>
      <fax>+61394795768</fax>
      <email>a.bruder@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrea Bruder</name>
      <address>La Trobe University
Department of Physiotherapy
Bundoora
Victoria 
3086</address>
      <phone>+61394795853</phone>
      <fax>+61394795768</fax>
      <email>a.bruder@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Bruder</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria
3086</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94795853</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.bruder@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>