<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370894">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000784415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The reliability of point-of-care ketone analyser in newborn babies.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An interventional study to determine the  reliability of point-of-care ketone analyser in newborn babies within the first 10 postnatal days.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-2481 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>ROCKET</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Babies in the NICU for any reason, if gestation &gt;= 35 weeks and age &lt; 10 days</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will measure a ketone (betahydroxybutyrate) on a point of care analyser ("Statstrip", Nova biochemical) and by standard laboratory method. The Statstrip requires a single drop of blood and the result is available in 10 seconds. The Statstrip and the lab samples will be taken simultaneously and the results will be compared. The results will be available to the treating clinicians.
The subjects will be newborn infants in the first 10 days of life, admitted to the neonatal intensive care unit, and requiring blood tests for clinical purposes.
Each subject will be assessed once only. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control sample will be the laboratory sample, taken at the same time as the statstrip sample as an additional 0.4 ml whilst sampling for other purposes. The analysis will occur in the hospital laboratory located on the same hospital site. The testing technique in the laboratory will use a Roche Cobas 6000 analyser on the 501 module.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine in preterm and term babies in the first ten days of life the level of agreement in the measured blood glucose concentrations of betahydroxybutyrate between the point of care analyser and the laboratory analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>The first 10 days of life</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if the measured accuracy is influenced by the concentrations of betahydroxybutyrate. This will be assessed using the difference between the two sampling methods, and applying this difference to the mean concentration (ie the midpoint between the two samples). This is viewed and analysed as a Bland-Altman plot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The first 10 days of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the range of blood concentrations of betahydroxybutyrate. It is expected that the lower end of the range will be 0.0 mmol/l, but the upper end of the range is unknown. The range may reflect one or other or both methods, or the midpoints of each baby's measurement, depending on what is found from primary outcome 1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The first 10 days of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if age, sex, feeding, and reason for admission are related to the blood concentrations of betahydroxybutyrate. These variables will be prospectively gathered at the time of  each enrolment , and retained in paper form and on computer as the study progresses. The blood glucose concentrations of betahydroxybutyrate will reflect one or other or both methods, or the midpoints of each baby's measurement, depending on what is found from primary outcome 1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The first 10 days of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the variability of blood concentrations of betahydroxybutyrate. It is expected that the data will cluster at the lower end of the range, but the distribution will be assessed by histogram evaluation.  The variability will reflect measurements from one or other or both methods, or the midpoints of each baby's measurement, depending on what is found from primary outcome 1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The first 10 days of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestational age 35 to 42 completed weeks of gestation
Age &lt;= 10 days of age
Admitted to the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>10</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Major congenital anomalies
Terminal conditions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Categorical variables will be analysed using number and percent. Continuous variables will be analysed to determine the distribution, range, and variance and compared by Students t test or the Mann-Whitney U test.
Bland-Altman plots will be used to compare the two methods of analysis.
Relationships between demographic and clinical variables and ketone concentrations will be explored using regression analyses. 

Power and Sample size :
Annually, approximately 600 babies of greater than or equal to 35 weeks gestation are admitted to the Waikato Newborn Intensive Care Unit.  Of these, at least 450 babies (75%) will require a blood test.  We plan to have the blood test for the study taken at the same time as routine blood samples are taken.  

Our major aim is to test the reliability of the point-of-care analyser with the gold standard laboratory analyser.  Normal blood ketone concentrations are reported to vary over the newborn period, ranging from approximately 0.01 - 0.43 mmol/L (SD approximately 0.1mmol/L) increasing on days 2 to 3 and then decreasing.  In a deprived population of term babies (n= 578) in Nepal, blood concentrations of beta hydroxybutyrate in the first 48 hours after birth were reported to be 0.00 -1.34 mmol/L, with a geometric mean (SD) of 0.11 (.004) mmol/L. 

Brain ketone uptake is proportional to circulating concentrations.  It has been estimated that beta-hydroxybutyrate might contribute 12-13% of cerebral energy requirements at mean arterial concentrations of 0.16 - 0.28 mmol/L6.  Thus measurement of ketone concentrations to accuracy of &lt; 0.05 mmol/L is likely to be clinically meaningful.

In order to have a 95% level of confidence to detect the mean blood ketone concentration to a precision of agreement equivalent to a SD 0.2420, we would need to recruit 200 babies. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/04/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>153</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>28/04/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Waikato Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Waikato Hospital
Pembroke St
Hamilton 
New Zealand 3204</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Waikato Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Waikato Hospital
Pembroke St
Hamilton
New Zealand 3204</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Low blood sugar levels are common in babies after birth.  Exclusively breast fed babies have been shown to have lower blood concentrations of glucose and higher concentrations of ketones than babies who receive formula milk.  Ketones may provide a source of fuel for energy, particularly for the brain, when glucose concentrations are low. However if a baby does not produce ketones the brain can be starved of energy and be damaged.  Measurement of blood ketone concentrations is not routinely done as part of clinical practice. 

We aim to see whether we can reliably measure ketones in a small drop of blood.  We will measure ketones on a point-of-care analyser as well as in the laboratory, using the gold standard analysis and compare the results.  The blood test will be taken at the same time as routine blood samples are being taken.  If the point-of-care analyser can help identify accurately those at risk of brain damage when glucose concentrations are low, this may help to prevent separation of mothers and babies as breast-feeding is being established. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken St
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16 /NT A/ 67</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Deborah Harris</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit
Waikato Hospital
Pembroke St
Hamilton
New Zealand 3204</address>
      <phone>+6421471790</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deborah.harris@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Deborah Harris</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit
Waikato Hospital
Pembroke St
Hamilton
New Zealand 3204</address>
      <phone>+6421471790</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deborah.harris@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Deborah Harris</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit
Waikato Hospital
Pembroke St
Hamilton
New Zealand 3204</address>
      <phone>+6421471790</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deborah.harris@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>Angola</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Deborah Harris</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit
Waikato Hospital
Pembroke St
Hamilton
New Zealand 3204</address>
      <phone>+6421471790</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deborah.harris@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>