<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83146">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000487314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Breathe easier during exercise ~ Can Heliox improve the sensation of breathlessness and increase exercise duration in people with COPD</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can Heliox improve the sensation of breathlessness and increase exercise duration in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; A prospective randomized trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dyspnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Heliox (21% oxygen in balance Helium) Heliox will only be administered during one cardio pulmonary exercise test, at a predetermined constant work rate, until exhaustion. (anticipated to be no more than 45 mins total duration). Heliox will be stored in a large non diffusing reservoir bag from where it will pass through a humidifier prior to inhalation by the patient through a face mask/mouth piece</interventions>
    <comparator>Medical/Room Air. This comparator gas will only be administered during one cardio pulmonary exercise test, at a predetermined constant work rate, until exhaustion. (anticipated to be no more than 45 mins total duration). It will be stored in a large non diffusing reservoir bag from where it will pass through a humidifier prior to inhalation by the patient through a face mask/mouth piece</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of Dyspnoea (Intensity &amp; Qualitative Sensations). This outcome will be measured through pre validated language of breathlessness interviews (recalled and current sensations), Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) intensity scales and also a pre validated dyspnoea list of descriptor statements (Maher et al 1996). Individualised dyspnoea descriptor lists will be generated for each patient drawn from responses obtained during the language of breathless interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intensity and sensations of breathlessness will be recorded in real time, by selecting from the predetermined and individualised dyspnoea descriptor list, at regular intervals (every 2 minutes) during constant rate exercise tests.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of Muscle Fatigue (Intensity) This outcome will be measured using the prevalidated 100 point VAS scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Perception of muscle fatigue will be recorded in real time at regular intervals (every 2 minutes) during constant rate exercise tests.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise Ventilatory Parameters. These outcomes, including Oxygen Uptake (VO2max), Ventilation rates, Tidal Volumes, Inspiratory Reserve Volumes (IRV), End Inspiratory Lung Volumes (EILV), Inspiratory &amp; Expiratory times (TI &amp; TE), Oxygen Saturation (SpO2), Heart Rate (HR) &amp; Blood Pressure (BP) will be acquire in real time from samples of analysed exhaled breath (Viasys Jaeger Oxycon Delta).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Analysis of these ventilatory parameters will be recorded in real time allowing for set isotime points to be isolated and statistically analysed. It is currently proposed that this data be analysed every two minutes during constant rate exercise tests.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Are aged over 40 

Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) of at least Stage III as per the Global initiative for chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) guidelines, Forced Expiratory Volume in the first second (FEV1) &lt;= 50% predicted post bronchodilator.

Are able to give informed written consent prior to entering the study.

Can comply with scheduled visit and all study related activities</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any clearly documented history of adult asthma or chronic respiratory disorders (e.g. primary bronchiectasis, pulmonary fibrosis or any clearly documented history of adult asthma or chronic respiratory disorders (e.g. primary bronchiectasis, pulmonary fibrosis, pneumoconiosis) other than COPD.

Any contraindication for Cardio Pulmonary Exercise Testing (CPET), as per American Thoracic Society and American College of Chest Physicians guidelines (ATS/ACCP 2003)

Participating in a research study or use of any investigational drug during this studys, pneumoconiosis) other than COPD.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients will be enrolled with sequential numbers, a preprepared randomization list will be used to assign treatment arms.</concealment>
    <sequence>A preprepared computerized list will bve generated as a randomization schedule.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Repatriation General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Daws Road 
Daw Park
South Australia 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Repatriation General Hospital.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Daws Road
Daw Park
South Australia 5041</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>School of Health Sciences, University of South Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>City East Campus
North Terrace 
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Distress with breathing or shortness of breath can be a debilitating experience for people suffering from lung diseases. The severity of this sensation often precludes individuals from maintaining a normal active lifestyle. As the severity of the shortness of breath increases, so the activity performed decreases, often to the point where moving from ones bed or chair can be exhausting. The general physical and mental health consequences of this are such that these individuals and those who care for them have a significantly lower social and mental health well being. The severity of breathlessness and impairment of activity have been shown to correlate strongly with increased hospitalizations and a longer time to recovery once their condition has worsened, as in the case of exacerbations.

It is hoped that a low density gas mix, such as Heliox (21 % oxygen in balance Helium), can reduce the magnitude of muscular effort associated with breathing in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary diseases (COPD) and allow for an alteration in both the sensation and magnitude of dyspnoea allowing patients to exercise longer and at greater intensities., thus facilitating a training effect. This would allow these individuals to improve their social activity, mental health and their quality of life whilst reducing the recovery time resultant from a transient worsening of their conditions (infective exacerbations of COPD) which may have otherwise predisposed hospitalization.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Repatriation General Hospital's Human Research &amp; Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Daws Road, Daw Park, South Australia 5041</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>48/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/08/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia's Human Research &amp; Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of South Australia
Mawson Lakes Campus
Mawson Lakes Boulevard
Mawson Lakes SA 5095</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>P248/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/09/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Toby Hunt</name>
      <address>c/o Respiratory Clinical Trials
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road Daw Park
South Australia 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1008</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1195</fax>
      <email>toby.hunt@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Toby Hunt</name>
      <address>c/o Respiratory Clinical Trials
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road Daw Park
South Australia 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1008</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1195</fax>
      <email>toby.hunt@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Toby Hunt</name>
      <address>c/o Respiratory Clinical Trials
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road Daw Park
South Australia 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1008</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1195</fax>
      <email>toby.hunt@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>