<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82769">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/10/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000917235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised controlled trial comparing the Efficacy and Clinical Outcomes of Single and Double Balloon Enteroscopy in patients referred for Balloon Enteroscopy for investigation or treatment of small bowel conditions.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the Efficacy and Clinical Outcomes of Single and Double Balloon Enteroscopy in patients referred for balloon enteroscopy for investigation or treatment of small bowel conditions'</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SINGLE-01</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Balloon Enteroscopy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Small bowel conditions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Adult males and females referred for Balloon Enteroscopy for investigation or treatment of small bowel conditions will be randomised either to Single Balloon enteroscopy (SBE) or Double Balloon Enteroscopy (DBE).  

Single Balloon technology is designed to allow examination of the small bowel utilising a single balloon that maybe inflated or deflated to aid propulsion into the bowel.  This is unique as the current alternative of double balloon enteroscopy requires two balloons that need to be independently controlled.  Utilising a single balloon limits the complexity of the procedure. 

Study duration will be 2 years and patients will be recruited over 18months.

Each patient will undergo one procedure.</interventions>
    <comparator>Double Balloon Enteroscopy (DBE).

DBE involves using an instrument (enteroscope) with a flexible shaft containing a camera at one end that can be steered and advanced into the small bowel; either by beginning at the mouth or beginning at the anus.  Movement of this enteroscope through the bowel is assisted by two balloons, one which is attached to the enteroscope and one which is attached to a flexible tube through which the enteroscope is passed through.  With a combination of steering, pushing and pulling the instrument, as well as inflating and deflating the two balloons, the instrument can be safely passed into the small bowel.

Study duration will be 2 years and patients will be recruited over 18 months.

Each patient will undergo one procedure, lasting approximately 60-90minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic yield.  The diagnostic yield will be calculated by considering the number of procedures in which clinically significant positive findings were identified as a proportion of the total procedures undertaken.  This will be done for both Double Balloon Enteroscopy and Single Balloon Enteroscopy and the results will be compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conclusion of Study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapeutic yield. The therapeutic yield will be calculated by considering the number of procedures in which therapeutic intervention was undertaken as a proportion of the total procedures undertaken.  This will be done for both Double Balloon Enteroscopy and Single Balloon Enteroscopy and the results will be compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conclusion of Study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depth of insertion.  This will be measured on withdrawal of the enteroscope.  The measurement will be from the ileocaecal valve for procedures via colon and the pylorus for procedures via the mouth.

Two methods will be used:

(1) estimation every 5cm after training with a marked probe
(2) counting the number of small bowel folds encountered</outcome>
      <timepoint>Interim analysis once 100 patients have been recruited.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health care utilisation.  We will record the number of hospital admissions related to the indication for enteroscopy up to 6 months before enteroscopy as well 6 months post enetroscopy.  The two will be compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post closing of recruitment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult &gt;18 years
Clinically accepted indication for Balloon enteroscopy. Willingness to participate</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any contraindication to Balloon Enteroscopy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Fitzroy St, Fitzroy, VIC 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>35 Fitzroy St, Fitzroy, VIC 3065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of the study is to compare two different instruments that are used to assess and treat conditions of the small bowel.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research and Ethics Committee (HREC) A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Fitzroy ST, Fitzroy,
Victoria 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/08/0035</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marios Efthymiou</name>
      <address>35 Fitzroy St, Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61392882211</phone>
      <fax>+61386781032</fax>
      <email>Marios.EFTHYMIOU@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marios Efthymiou</name>
      <address>35 Fitzroy St, 
Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61392882211</phone>
      <fax>+61386781032</fax>
      <email>Marios.EFTHYMIOU@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marios Efthymiou</name>
      <address>35 Fitzroy St, Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61392882211</phone>
      <fax>+61386781032</fax>
      <email>Marios.EFTHYMIOU@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>