<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366060">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000360617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cabrini Scribe Trial 2014 - a study to investigate the relationship between emergency department scribes and emergency physician productivity - to compare physician productivity, billing and staff satisfaction with and without the assistance of a scribe during emergency medicine consultations</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study of the relationship between emergency department scribes and emergency physician productivity, billing and staff satisfaction</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-0717</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Emergency physician efficiency</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Emergency department staff satisfaction related to medical scribes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A trained medical scribe will assist an emergency physician during emergency consultations. They will take notes as directed and will assist with clerical tasks as directed. The intervention will take place for six consecutive months commencing July 2014</interventions>
    <comparator>An emergency physician will carry out their usual work without the assistance of a medical scribe which includes their usual note taking and clerical duties. Emergency physician shifts matched in advance for physician, day, time and work area will be selected from January to June shifts in 2014.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data on physician patients seen per hour in similar circumstances in close time proximity to the intervention sampling Mean and standard deviation (SD) of the number of patients seen by each physician per hour</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention: July 1st 2014 and onwards for a period of 6 months Control: January to June 2014 inclusive</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>billing rates per patient obtained from hospital database</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention: July 1st 2014 and onwards for a period of 6 months Control: January to July 2014 inclusive</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient waiting times - obtained from hospital database</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention: July 2014 and onwards for a period of 6 months Control: January to June 2014 inclusive</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ambulance bypass times - obtained from hospital database</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention: July 2014 and onwards for a period of 6 months Control: January to June 2014 inclusive</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>complaints or adverse events - obtained from hospital database and from intervention physicians</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention: July 2014 and onwards for a period of 6 months Control: January to June 2014 inclusive</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All scribed shifts and scribed patient encounters during the trial period including any where the scribe was supposed to be present but wasn't. If the scribe was asked to leave an encounter by the patient or physician the encounter will be included in the analysis.
The physicians enrolled to participate will be a convenience sample of physicians available during the specified time period. They will be voluntarily consenting to participate.
The scribe used will be one trained scribe identified in advance. This scribe will work with all the physicians.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>unscribed shifts</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The scribed shifts will be allocated to selected willing participant physicians a month preceeding the trial intervention. The physicians will be regular cabrini physicians who are agreable to participate in the trial. These physicians will be aware of the trial aims. The scribe will attend for a month and will work preallocated shifts with the physicians. The patient encounters within each shift will not be able to be chosen as these are defined by rules surrounding patient allocation that are always the same. There is computer generated allocation of the next patient to be seen and there are shift rules around regional allocation of emergency department physician allocation of work duties. These are closely enforced and only interrupted by a patient requiring resuscitation or immediate medical attention.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The minimal clinical effect size that would be useful to pursue would be an efficiency gain from 1.0 patient per hour to 1.2 patients per hour (a 20% increase). A sample size of 100 in each period would allow this difference to be detected at a 5% significance level and 80% power (two-sided) assuming a relatively conservative estimate of the SD of the number of patients seen per hour of 0.5.
The mean number of encounters per hour will be compared for the two groups using t-tests. Similarly, the mean billing rates, total ambulance bypass times and patient waiting times will be compared for the groups using parametric or non-parametric tests as appropriate.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/12/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>108</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Malvern - Malvern</hospital>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Katherine Walker</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Emergency department Cabrini Hospital 183 Wattletree Rd Malvern
3144 VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cabrini</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>183 Wattletree Rd Malvern
3144 VIC</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Michael Ben-Meir</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Emergency department
 Cabrini Hospital 
183 Wattletree Rd Malvern
3144 VIC</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is a rising medical cost base in emergency medicine. There is a rising seniority of medical staff required to safely perform the role of physician in an emergency department. The currently accepted productivity of a FACEM is one patient per hour. Much of this time is spent writing and printing
notes, faxing documents and contacting physicians. None of this work requires the skill set of an emergency physician and could be performed by a well-trained medical scribe or secretary.
To date scribes have not been used in Australian Emergency Departments and offer a novel way of addressing emergency physician productivity without compromising the quality of emergency physician work.
The degree that a medical scribe increases emergency physician productivity in emergency medicine in Australia has been investigated by this team in a pilot that lends itself to further investigation.
This is a second trial to investigate whether a medical scribe would increase emergency physician efficiency</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Published: early electronic view
Walker, K. J., et al. (2016). "Medical scribes in emergency medicine produce financially significant productivity gains for some, but not all emergency physicians." Emerg Med Australas. DOI 10.1111/1742-6723.12562

Presented - same title, Dr Katie Walker presenter
- Health Roundtable, Sydney November 2015
- ACEM ASM 2015, Brisbane November 2015</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cabrini HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cabrini Hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144
VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>01-16-06-14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katherine Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency department Cabrini Hospital 183 Wattletree Rd malvern 3144 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency department Cabrini Hospital 183 Wattletree Rd malvern 3144 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency department Cabrini Hospital 183 Wattletree Rd malvern 3144 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency department Cabrini Hospital 183 Wattletree Rd malvern 3144 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>