<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364602">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000801718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Correlation between alcohol concentration and an electroencephalogram (EEG) measure of anaesthetic depth</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The correlation between increasing breath alcohol concentration and Bispectral Index in anaesthetic registrars</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The impact of increasing alcohol on BIS (a measure of EEG activity used as a surrogate for anaesthetic depth)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will attend just one study day (for one four hour session). They will be asked to refrain from consuming caffeine from 10am on the study day. Only participants who are not rostered for clinical duties over the ensuing 24 hours will be able to participate in the study. Alcohol will be provided for study participants to consume over 3 hours. They will be asked to drink a similar amount of alcohol to that which they would normally drink at home or when out. The type and amount of alcohol consumed throughout the study will be recorded. Wine, beer, nonalcoholic drinks and snacks will be provided during the study period, and a meal will be provided at the end of the study. Four measurments of breath alcohol, and of BIS, will be taken for each participant (hourly, over the four hour study period) plus one set of baseline measurements. A single blood sample will be taken at the end of the study to confirm blood alcohol levels.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no comparator or control treatment for this study - as we are assessing the relationship between breath alcohol levels and BIS all participants will drink alcohol over the study period.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between end-expired (breathalyser) alcohol concentration and BIS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before drinking) and then every hour over four hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between blood alcohol concentration and BIS. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Four hours after starting drinking (at study end)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agreement and correlation between Anaesthetic Trainees predicted blood alcohol concentration and measured blood alcohol concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each breath alcohol concentration reading (1, 2, 3 and 4 hours)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Anaesthetic Trainees (age between 25 and 40 years) who have completed their clinical duties on a Friday afternoon and are not rostered to work for at least 24 hours.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of epilepsy; currently taking any sedating medication including analgesics such as codeine and opioids, benzodiazepines, anti-epileptics and sleeping medications; history of liver disease or impaired liver function; currently pregnant.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>No allocation of treatment or concealment of treatment in this study. 

Potential participants will be notified of the upcoming study at a department inservice. Potential participants (ie those not rostered on for working during the weekend following the study date) will be approached by a study coordinator.</concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Correlation between blood alcohol concentration and BIS will be determined. This will be followed by multivariate regression analysis including various participant characteristics to further delineate the relationship between blood alcohol concentration and BIS. Sample size calculation for this kind of study is unreliable. A previous study on healthy patients showed mean baseline BIS scores to be in the mid 90s with minimal variation.[1] We plan to study 10-20 patients. With the benefit of repeated measurements, a sample size of 10 subjects measured on 4 occasions should provide power of greater than 80% (with an alpha value set at 0.05 and beta value of 0.2) to detect a correlation of 0.3 which would be clinically relevant. 

1.  Cortinez, L.I., et al., Performance of the cerebral state index during increasing levels of propofol anesthesia: a comparison with the bispectral index. Anesth Analg, 2007. 104(3): p. 605-10</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/08/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/08/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland
New Zealand
1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland
New Zealand
1023</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Alfred</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004, Australia </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bispectral Index monitoring is commonly used intraoperatively to decrease the risk of awareness. Multiple drugs are known to affect the bispectral index and many have been studied in detail. Our aim is to determine the relationship between alcohol concentration and BIS.

Awareness is an uncommon but potentially stressful complication of anaesthesia occurring in 0.1-0.2% of surgical patients.[1] The BIS monitor processes EEG activity with time-domain, frequency domain, and bispectral analysis producing a dimensionless number between 0 and 100 with 40-60 being appropriate for surgery.[2] Large trials have shown a decrease in the occurrence of awareness when using BIS in high-risk patients.[1, 3] 
Studies have demonstrated that BIS decreases in patients with head injuries [4, 5], those with cognitive impairment such as dementia [6] and with sedation [7].  There has been a single case report detailing a case of intracranial arterial alcohol embolization in which the BIS decreased to zero[8]. We hypothesise that BIS will decrease with alcohol consumption. 
The effect of multiple drugs such as nitrous oxide, ketamine and opioid on bispectral index has been studied in detail.[2] Alcohol, a commonly consumed drug has not. Miner et al published a paper using BIS to validate the use of Altered Mental Status Scale in intoxicated patients.[9] This study did not aim to determine a relationship between alcohol concentration and BIS and included patients who may have consumed other drugs. Thus, there were potentially many confounding factors that may have influenced the relationship between alcohol concentration and BIS.

1.	Myles, P.S., et al., Bispectral index monitoring to prevent awareness during anaesthesia: the B-Aware randomised controlled trial. Lancet, 2004. 363(9423): p. 1757-63.
2.	Dahaba, A.A., Different conditions that could result in the bispectral index indicating an incorrect hypnotic state. Anesth Analg, 2005. 101(3): p. 765-73.
3.	Ekman, A., et al., Reduction in the incidence of awareness using BIS monitoring. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand, 2004. 48(1): p. 20-6.
4.	Haug, E., et al., Bispectral electroencephalographic analysis of head-injured patients in the emergency department. Acad Emerg Med, 2004. 11(4): p. 349-52.
5.	Ebtehaj, M., et al., Correlation between BIS and GCS in patients suffering from head injury. Ir J Med Sci, 2012. 181(1): p. 77-80.
6.	Erdogan, M.A., et al., The effects of cognitive impairment on anaesthetic requirement in the elderly. Eur J Anaesthesiol, 2012. 29(7): p. 326-31.
7.	Liu, J., H. Singh, and P.F. White, Electroencephalographic bispectral index correlates with intraoperative recall and depth of propofol-induced sedation. Anesth Analg, 1997. 84(1): p. 185-9.
8.	Unnikrishnan, K.P., et al., Case report: alterations in bispectral index following absolute alcohol embolization in a patient with intracranial arteriovenous malformation. Can J Anaesth, 2007. 54(11): p. 908-11.
9.	Miner, J.R., A. Gaetz, and M.H. Biros, The association of a decreased level of awareness and blood alcohol concentration with both agitation and sedation in intoxicated patients in the ED. Am J Emerg Med, 2007. 25(7): p. 743-8.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/NTA/90</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004, Australia </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>183/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Simon Mitchell</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland
New Zealand
1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 89300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sj.mitchell@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jacqueline Hannam</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland
New Zealand
1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 89308</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.hannam@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jacqueline Hannam</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland
New Zealand
1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 89308</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.hannam@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jacqueline Hannam</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland
New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 89308</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.hannam@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>