<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369711">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001366549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>EXTEND45 (EXamining ouTcomEs in chroNic Disease in the 45 and Up Study): Establishing a chronic disease population cohort examining chronic kidney disease and diabetes amongst NSW residents aged 45
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For NSW residents aged 45 and up, we seek to establish a sizeable chronic disease population cohort by linking previous 45 And Up Study patient data with private pathology and administrative datasets in order to assess health service use, health outcome measures, and clinical data. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1177-1382</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EXTEND45</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The existing 45 and Up Study is a large-scale cohort study comprising of more than 250 000 NSW residents aged 45 years of older at recruitment (representing 1 in 10 persons in the age bracket) and designed to provide information about healthy ageing.

EXTEND45 will expand on the 45 and Up Study by establishing a sizeable chronic disease population cohort. For the first time, results of diagnostic testing held by private pathology companies will be obtained by linking all participants in the 45 and Up Study using best practice linkage methodology. The linkage of pathology data will enable identification of participants with early chronic disease (such as evaluation of serum creatinine for kidney disease) and assessment of achievement of clinical targets (such as HbA1c levels for participants with diabetes). 

Concurrent linkage to administrative datasets will also occur, allowing a detailed assessment of health service use, outcome measures, and clinical data. Datasets to be included:

New South Wales Admitted Patient Data Collection [APDC], NSW mortality data from the Registry of Births, Deaths and Marriages [RBDM] and Australian Bureau of Statistics [ABS], Australian and New Zealand Dialysis and Transplant Registry [ANZDATA], Medicare Benefits Schedule/Pharmaceutical Benefits Schedule [MBS/PBS], and the New South Wales Central Cancer Registry [NSW CCR]

Data linkage between the 45 And Up dataset and these databases will be performed by the Centre for Health Record Linkage (CHeReL), using designated patient identifiers to search for and match patient information  across each source. Data from all sources will be sought from varying timelines between the start and end points of of 01/01/2005 and 31/07/2013, with this end corresponding with the patient follow up data attained during 45 And Up. 

Whilst the main focus of the study is on diabetes and CKD, another key area of interest is the proportion of participants who do or do not link to pathology company data, which will provide an indication on the utilisation of health services in the community. Therefore all participants in the 45 And Up dataset are of interest, with further analysis to be performed on those who have at least one link to any of the associated datasets.
</interventions>
    <comparator>A comparison will be made between participants who do and those who do not have pathology records over the period covered by the dataset. Pathology data will cover the period of 01/01/2006 to 31/07/2013. For the purposes of registration, participants without pathology records could be deemed the comparator group.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of pathology records coverage, namely the number of participants whose data does link to at least one pathology record, compared to those who have no links. This will provide researchers with an indication of health service utilisation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of data analysis - 31/12/2016</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of Incidence, Prevalence, and Risk Factors for Diabetes, as derived by statistical analyses of all the collected datasets</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of data analysis - 31/12/2016</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of Incidence, Prevalence, and Risk Factors for CKD, as derived by statistical analyses of all the collected datasets</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of data analysis - 31/12/2016</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the complex associations between demographic, lifestyle and individual and area level socioeconomic risk factors and chronic diseases to identify areas for future interventions such as early screening and targeted programs. To be derived by statistical analyses of all the collected datasets.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of data analysis - 31/12/2016</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To appraise comorbidities of diabetes and CKD and their impacts on the health care system. To be derived by statistical analyses of all the collected datasets</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of data analysis - 31/12/2016</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine processes of care for chronic diseases including relationships between the use of primary and tertiary health services, attainment of clinical targets, and the use of health services for older NSW residents with diabetes and CKD. To be derived by statistical analyses of all the collected datasets.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of data analysis - 31/12/2016</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>45 and Up Study participants, aged 45 and over and living in NSW</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Did not participate in the 45 and Up Study, aged under 45, not a NSW resident</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>1. Chronic disease outcomes using 45 and Up study participants without diabetes and CKD as referent groups for analyses.  
(i) Assessment of prevalence by geographic area of diabetes and CKD. 
(ii) An evaluation of demographic, lifestyle and individual and area level socioeconomic factors associated with chronic disease.
(iii) A review of achievement of clinical targets according to diabetes and CKD management guidelines and factors associated with non-adherence. 
(iv) An analysis of chronic disease endpoints including health service use, disease progression and complications will be undertaken. Associations between endpoints and demographics, socioeconomic risk factors, comorbid conditions, biochemical results and achievement of clinical targets will be calculated using regression models. 

Multivariable models will be constructed to identify independent variables. 

2. A comparative analysis of 45 and Up Study participants who link and do not link to pathology data will also take place with consideration of the following variables:
- Demographic factors
- Geographic factors
- Socioeconomic factors
- Disease-related factors

Analyses will be carried out using SAS software. Relative risks with 95% confidence intervals will be calculated for all outcomes. 

The outcomes of interest in this study are dependent on the degree to which the datasets link up with one another. Therefore sample size calculations cannot be determined until researchers are able to access the data. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>267023</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Enrolling by invitation</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Heart Foundation - Cardiovascular Research Network</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3, 80 William Street
East Sydney NSW 2011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Foundation - Cardiovascular Research Network</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 80 William Street
East Sydney NSW 2011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Amgen</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 7, 123 Epping Road
North Ryde NSW 2113</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>MSD</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 1, 26 Talavera Road
Macquarie Park NSW 2113</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Eli Lilly</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>112 Wharf Road
West Ryde NSW 2114</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic diseases are leading causes of death and disability in Australia. They are also associated with high use of health care services, contributing to major funding pressures in health care that are expected to rise over coming decades as prevalence increases . Over half of people aged 45 years or more have at least one chronic disease increasing to over 80% in those aged more than 65.  Recent focus in the surveillance of chronic disease has identified 12 conditions  which pose a significant burden in terms of morbidity, mortality and health costs, and are amenable to preventive measures. EXTEND45 will investigate two of these related conditions, diabetes and chronic kidney disease (CKD) and their comorbidities. Diabetes and CKD have been selected as they are diseases which develop slowly and are best studied in community datasets. 

Although there is a growing level of understanding about the prevalence and progression of chronic diseases, many of these studies have derived from clinical populations recruited through specialist clinics and hospital settings. The next step in understanding the care of diabetes and CKD needs to begin at a population level in order to estimate true prevalence of early disease, identify novel risk factors and determinants of progression, and to fully comprehend delivery of health care in all settings. Establishment of large population cohorts is difficult and expensive and infrequently attempted. The existing 45 and Up Study is a large-scale cohort study comprising of more than 250 000 NSW residents aged 45 years of older at recruitment (representing 1 in 10 persons in the age bracket) and designed to provide information about healthy ageing. The 45 and Up Study therefore provides a unique opportunity to study chronic diseases at a population level. Importantly, all 45 and Up participants have consented to collection of their health data for research purposes.
EXTEND45 will expand the 45 and Up Study investment to establish a seminal sizeable chronic disease population cohort. 

For EXTEND45, results of diagnostic testing held by private pathology companies will be obtained by linking all participants in the 45 and Up Study using best practice linkage methodology. The linkage of pathology data will enable identification of participants with early chronic disease and allow for assessment of achievement of clinical targets. Concurrent linkage to administrative datasets will facilitate a contemporaneous assessment of health service use, outcome measures, and clinical data. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NSW Population &amp; Health Services Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cancer Institute NSW
PO Box 41
Alexandria NSW 1435</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/CIPHS/69</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Meg Jardine</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4530</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4502</fax>
      <email>mjardine@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Will Ooi</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4579</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4502</fax>
      <email>wooi@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Meg Jardine</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4530</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4502</fax>
      <email>mjardine@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Will Ooi</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4579</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9993 4502</fax>
      <email>wooi@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>