<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368282">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000699561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Differences in endotracheal tube cuff sealing by applying four methods of endotracheal tube cuff inflation in patients undergoing general surgery procedures</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of four methods of endotracheal tube cuff inflation in terms of optimal cuff sealing in surgical population</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>endotracheal tube cuff sealing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>complications from endotracheal cuff tube overinflation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After endotracheal intubation, we would apply four different methods for ETT cuff (ETTc) inflation in four different subgroups of patients (as they occur from randomization): 
1) inflation of ETTc as usual practice and assessment of adequacy of inflation with finger estimation [Palpation], 
2) ETTc will be overinflated and then it will be checked for air return back into the syringe  [Air-return],
3) inflation of ETTc up to the point that no sound of air leakage will be heard by direct auscultation [minimal occlusive volume assessed by direct auscultation of air leak (MinVol)] and 
4) inflation of ETTc up to the point that no sound of air leakage will be heard over trachea using stethoscope [minimum air leak assessed with stethoscope (MinLeak)].
The ETTc pressure will be  measured with a non-invasive manometer via the pilot balloon. 
The duration of each method is estimated to be less than 1 minutes for the first and second method and about 2 mnutes for the third and fourth method.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment will be the application of a usual practice to assess the adequacy of ETTc inflation such as finger estimation, which will be tested against two less common methods of ETT cuff inflation estimation such as , minimal occlusive volume or minimum leak technique and one less applied method involving air return back into the syringe after cuff overinflation, with the view to ascertain optimal ETT cuff sealing practice in a surgical population.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The ETT cuff pressure obtained by each method of cuff inflation.
This will be based on the indications obtained by a non-invasive manometer applied in the pilot balloon.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Just after ETT cuff inflation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The air needed for ETT cuff inflation in each method. This will be measured as ml of air used to inflate the cuff with a pre-filled with air 10 ml-syringe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>As soon as ETT cuff inflation is completed</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of complications such as sore throat, that might occur in each method of ETT cuff inflation. This will be based on patient's self-reporting of painful sensation localized to the pharynx or surrounding anatomy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two, six and twenty-four hours postoperatively </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of complications such as hoarseness (dysphonia) that might occur in each method of ETT cuff inflation. The patient will be assessed with the GRBAS scale. This is a subjective rating scale providing a measure of the overall grade (G), roughness (R), breathiness (B), asthenia or weakness (A), and strain (S) of dysphonia as judged by the listener on a scale of 0 to 4 (0: normal, 1: mild, 2: moderate, 3: moderate to severe, 4: severe).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two, six and twenty-four hours postoperatively </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of complications such as dysphagia that might occur in each method of ETT cuff inflation. This will be assessed by Functional Oral Intake Scale numbered as 1 the worse and as 7 the best response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two, six and twenty-four hours postoperatively </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patients, ASA physical status 1 to 3, Mallampati score 1-2, oral endotracheal intubation with a high-volume and low-pressure endotracheal tube, N2O free general anesthesia, intraoperative normothermia, conventional mechanical ventilation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Tracheostomy, surgical procedures involving the neck or the upper airwa, laryngo-tracheal pathology, history of previous tracheostomy, high-frequency oscillatory ventilation, history of difficult airway management, above 2 intubation attempts and prone positioning.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment by central randomization by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerized sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 34 patients in each group is estimated for a type 1 error of 0.05 (a=0.05) and a power of 90%. An estimated reduction in ETT cuff pressure &gt; 4 cmH2O (SD 8 cmH2O) between palpation estimation  and air-return after cuff overinflation techniques is defined as the primary end-point. 
Analysis of variance (ANOVA) for repeated measures with GreenhouseGeisser correction, Comparisons between different groups were performed using one-way ANOVA for comparisons between different groups and linear regression will be used as appropriate. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Georgia Tsaousi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece
Stilponos Kiriakidi 1- GR 54636
University campus, Thessaloniki, Greece</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Greece</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We aim to investigate the applicability of one common methods of ETTc inflation such as finger estimation compared to three other less commonly applied methods in clinical practice such as minimal occlusive volume, minimum leak technique and a method with limited application involving air return back into the syringe after cuff overinflation. Thus we will study the comparable changes in ETTc pressure, the air needed for the final ETT cuff inflation and the possible complications associated with each method
We would like to test the hypothesis that the less commonly applied methods for ETTc inflation are superior compared to the finger palpation technique and among these three methods to ascertain which is the optimal ETTc sealing practice.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368282-Ethics Committee Approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Georgia Tsaousi</name>
      <address>Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece
Stilponos Kiriakidi 1 - GR54636
University Campus, Thessaloniki, Greece</address>
      <phone>+302310994855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tsaousig@otenet.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Georgia Tsaousi</name>
      <address>Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece
Stilponos Kiriakidi 1 - GR54636
University Campus, Thessaloniki, Greece</address>
      <phone>+302310994855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tsaousig@otenet.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Georgia Tsaousi</name>
      <address>Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece
Stilponos Kiriakidi 1 - GR54636
University Campus, Thessaloniki, Greece</address>
      <phone>+302310994855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tsaousig@otenet.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Georgia Tsaousi</name>
      <address>Maiandrou 32-GR 56224-Thessaloniki</address>
      <phone>+302310994855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tsaousig@otenet.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>