<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370914">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000853448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Central Australian Diabetic Maculopathy Study: Treatment Patterns and Outcomes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Central Australian Diabetic Maculopathy Study: Visual Acuity Outcomes of Laser +/- Intravitreal anti-VEGF Injections</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CADMS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NHMRC and FHF Centre for Research Excellence (CRE) in Diabetic Retinopathy App 1079864</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic maculopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Exposure arm = When lasers were found ineffective, anti-VEGFs (0.05ml avastin or lucentis) were administered on an as required basis as per standard care, and were not prescribed as part of this study. 
Laser treatment parameters were administered at the discretion of the treating clinician as per standard care. 
 Anti VEGF drugs used avastin or lucentis
1.	Intravitreal Bevacizumab (Avastin) 1.25mg/0.05ml administered every 4 to 6 weeks initially or as required
2.	Intravitreal Ranibizumab (Lucentis) 0.5mg/0.05ml administered every 4 to 6 weeks initially or as required
Ophthalmologist (TH) and Head of Department delivered the treatment/intervention as a day procedure in the Ophthalmology Department of the Alice Springs Hospital and its remote affiliate hospitals
Mode of delivery for injections was face-to-face service provision
This is an observational study where patients were followed up based on the severity of disease. The following time frames were usually followed:
Clinically significant macular edema  every 4-6 weeks until resolved
Non-proliferative Diabetic retinopathy (mild)  once a year 
Non-proliferative Diabetic retinopathy (moderate)  Twice/year
Non-proliferative Diabetic retinopathy (severe)  every 4-6 months
Pre-proliferate Diabetic retinopathy  Every 3-months
Adherence to supplementary injections following laser treatment for progression of sight-threatening diabetic maculopathy was tracked from clinical file audits between the years 2001 and 2013. The duration of the follow-up period for this study for each participant was until stabilisation or improvement of retinopathy symptoms or features, whichever occurred first.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1 = Active Control/Comparator Arm = Laser(s) for the treatment of sight-threatening diabetic maculopathy. Laser therapy for diabetic maculopathy was applied on an as-needed basis upon review as per standard care. 
Mode of delivery for laser treatment was face-to-face service provision.
The duration of the follow-up period for this study for each participant was until stabilisation or improvement of retinopathy symptoms, whichever occurred first.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in visual acuity level in logMAR letters </outcome>
      <timepoint>Last patient follow-up visit during audit period </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>N/A</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria were as follows: diabetic retinopathy patients receiving focal or macular photocoagulation at Alice Springs Hospital and/or Tennant Creek Hospital and those receiving treatment during outreach visits to remote communities. Patients were included in the study irrespective of racial background, age, location, co-morbidities and cataract status.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient data were excluded from study for the following reasons:
1. Deceased patients whose files were not accessible as those files were transferred to Iron Mountain (a repository for medical records of deceased patients) in Darwin for storage. 
2. Patients whose HRN or DOB or Names did not exist in the hospital system, and despite best efforts remained unidentifiable
3. Patients receiving laser photocoagulation for other visual problems un-related to diabetic retinopathy 
4. Patients whose files were lost or had no follow up after the first injection to analyze the treatment effect
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics; Between groups analysis both univariate and multivariate [adjusted for potential confounders].
All available treatment data were collected over the audit period, so a sample size was not calculated in advance of the audit. A post-hoc power calculation will be provided.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>352</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/06/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alice Springs Hospital - Alice Springs</hospital>
    <hospital>Tennant Creek Hospital - Tennant Creek</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alice Springs Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gap Road, Alice Springs, Northern Territory, 0870</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fred Hollows Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>52 Barry St. Carlton VIC 3053 AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NHMRC and FHF Centre for Research Excellence (CRE) in Diabetic Retinopathy</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, the University of Sydney
OFFICE:	Medical Foundation Building Level 6
9294 Parramatta Road, Camperdown NSW 2050
MAIL:Locked bag 77, Camperdown NSW 1450, Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Macular oedema (swelling of the central retina) is the commonest cause of visual loss in people with diabetes. Monthly injections of Anti VEGF are superior to conventional laser treatment when there is moderate visual loss from central macular oedema. However, monthly injections are less practical in central Australia and laser may be more effective than injections in many common clinical scenarios. Our pilot audit showed that results from laser in central Australia were equivalent to some of the original published cohorts of laser treatment. This study planned to audit results of laser treatment for diabetic maculopathy in central Australia over a longer period, and identify scenarios where laser remains an effective and affordable option in the treatment of diabetic maculopathy</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Pavani Kurra, Laima Brazionis, Jesse Gale, Katie Chen, Stewart Lake, Tim Henderson. Central Australian Diabetic maculopathy Study. Presented at 44th RANZCO annual scientific conference. November 2015.
Abstract presented in clinical and experimental ophthalmology 43:61-62. October 2015. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Australian Human Research Ethics Committee [CAHREC]</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 4066 Alice Springs NT 0871 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-13-145</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Henderson</name>
      <address> Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Road, Alice Springs, Northern territory 0871
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 895 19180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tim.Henderson@nt.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Henderson</name>
      <address> Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Road, Alice Springs, Northern territory 0871</address>
      <phone>+61 8 895 19180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tim.Henderson@nt.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Henderson</name>
      <address> Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Road, Alice Springs, Northern territory 0871</address>
      <phone>+61 8 895 19180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tim.Henderson@nt.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pavani Kurra</name>
      <address> Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Road, Alice Springs, Northern territory 0871</address>
      <phone>+61 8 895 19180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pavani.kurra@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>