<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81786">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/01/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000014459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I, Single Centre, Double Blind, Randomised, Placebo Controlled, Single Escalating Dose Study to Determine the Safety, Tolerability and Absorption of Ha44 Administered Topically to the Hair and Scalp of Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Single Centre, Double Blind, Randomised, Placebo Controlled, Single Escalating Dose Study to Determine the Safety, Tolerability and Absorption of Ha44 Administered Topically to the Hair and Scalp of Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Ha01-001</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthy subjects</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ha44 is a novel insect ovicide.  It is a lotion (0.37% or 0.74%) which is applied topically to the hair and scalp as a single dose at the start of the study.  The lotion is washed off after 10 or 20 minutes.
Four groups will be studied, each group consisting of 8 subjects, 6 of whom will be treated with Ha44 and 2 with vehicle only. The vehicle onsists of a number of excipients, all of which are listed on the FDA database of inactive ingredients and within the allowed concentrations.
The first group will be treated with 0.37% Ha44 or vehicle for 10 minutes.  After review of 7 day safety data, a second group will be treated with 0.37% Ha44 or vehicle for 20 minutes.  After review of their 7 day safety data, a third group will be treated with 0.74% Ha44 or vehicle for 10 minutes.  After review of 7 day safety data, a fourth group will be treated with 0.74% Ha44 or vehicle for 20 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Lotion constituents without Ha44 active</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of Ha44 after topical application.  Safety will be assessed by physical examination, including detailed assessment of scalp, face, eyes and ears, vital signs, 12-lead electrocardiogram, laboratory tests including haematology, clinical chemistry and urinalysis and adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be made 10, 20, 45 minutes, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 hours, 7-10 days and 25-31 days after application.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma levels of Ha44 after topical application.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Plasma Ha44 will be measured pre-dose on the day of the study and at 15, 30, 45 minutes, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine levels of Ha44 after topical application.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Urine Ha44 will be measured pre-dose and at 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24 hours after administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female subjects must be of non-childbearing potential and/or have a negative pregnancy test prior to study start and be deemed not at risk of becoming pregnant.  Females of child bearing age who are sexually active must use two forms of contraception from screening until study completion Non smoker. Full head of hairMaximum hair length no more than 6 cmBody mass index between 18 and 28 kg/m2 inclusive, with body weight between 60-100 kgIn good health, as determined by screening assessmentsAble to provide written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant or breast-feeding femalesSubjects with a history of skin sensitisation or skin allergiesSubjects with abraded or abnormal skin on the area to be tested Subjects with any dermatological disease, including eczema, dermatitis, alopeciaSubjects who have taken any prescribed systemic or topical medication within two weeks prior to dosing, except for females on the contraceptive pill.  Subjects who have taken any non-prescribed systemic or topical medication, except vitamins, within two weeks prior to dosing.  Evidence of illicit drug use, as determined by a urine drug screenHistory of alcohol abuse Subjects with a known allergy to any of the components of the formulationPrevious treatment with an investigational agent within the last 30 daysAny condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, would prevent satisfactory participation in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All study personnel, including study coordinators, nursing staff, physicians and analysts will be blinded at all times to the study treatments.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/01/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hatchtech Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>205 - 211 Grattan Street 
PO Box 4192
Parkville VIC 3052
AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hatchtech Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>205 - 211 Grattan Street 
PO Box 4192
Parkville VIC 3052
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To study the safety of Ha44 after topical administration.  Safety will be assessed by physical examination, including detailed assessment of scalp, face, eyes and ears, vital signs, 12-lead electrocardiogram, laboratory tests including haematology, clinical chemistry and urinalysis and adverse events.
Ha44 is a novel insect ovicide.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Q-Pharm Pty lmited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/12/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>QIMR No H0612-052T(P1047)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Lewis Schulz</name>
      <address>Hatchtech Pty Ltd
205 - 211 Grattan Street 
PO Box 4192
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83443194</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93475888</fax>
      <email>lschulz@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Suzanne Elliot</name>
      <address>Q-Pharm Pty Limited
PO Box 78
Royal Brisbane Hospital 
QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38453644</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38453637</fax>
      <email>S.Elliott@qpharm.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>