<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336197">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000963022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of treadmill inclination on the gait of children with Down's syndrome: a quasi-experimental study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of treadmill inclination on angular alterations, amplitude of hip and knee movement, and stance time of gait in individuals with Down's syndrome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Down's syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gait</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Down's syndrome</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The overall duration of study  was 6 months.The subjects were assessed for motor function and classified at level 1 of the Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS), were evaluated. A subjective assessment of balance was performed using a questionnaire (Berg`s Balance Scale-BBS). Spatial-temporal variables of the lower limbs were observed as well as the angular variation of the hip, knee and ankle in the sagittal plane while the individuals walked on the treadmill at two different inclinations (0% and 10%) during 2 minutes in each condition. The treadmill was then turned on and the participants walked at a comfortable speed. After two minutes, a 30-second capture was made (dynamic collection). All the individuals were submitted to collections on the treadmill with inclinations of 0%  and 10%. A one-minute rest period was given between the different conditions. The overall duration of the treadmill session was of approximately 6 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Spatial-temporal variables were observed as well as the angular variation of the hip, knee and ankle in the sagittal plane while the individuals walked on the treadmill at two different inclinations (0% and 10%).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing of variables between 0% and 10% of inclination as measured by digitised video analysis showed that the stance time increased 4,8%.
In the hip, flexion at initial contact increased 13%, flexion at swing increased 10,2%, there was a decrease of 13% in maximum extension during terminal stance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After two minutes in 0% of inclination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing of variables between 0% and 10% of inclination as measured by digitised video analysis showed that the stance time increased 6%. 
In the hip, flexion at initial contact increased 29,7%, flexion at swing increased 25,2%. There was a decrease of 25,2% in maximum extension during terminal stance. An increase of 8,7% was also observed in range of motion in the hip.
In the knee, flexion at initial contact increased 30%, maximum stance flexion increased 21,4%, range of motion increased 5,8%. In the ankle, there was decrease of 67,7% in the plantar flexed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After two minutes in 10% of inclination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children classified at level 1 of the Gross Motor Function Classification System  GMFCS; able to perform all the activities contained on the Berg Balance Scale (BBS); did not exhibit any other neurological alterations, or associated respiratory or osteomyoarticular pathologies; and exhibited good cognition that would allow completion of all the assessment procedures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals whose not understanding the instructions or for not collaborating during data collection.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>23</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio Grande do Norte</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000
Caixa Postal 1524
Natal - RN
CEP 59072-970</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Coordenacao de Aperfeicoamento de Pessoal de Nivel Superior</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Setor Bancario Norte, Quadra 2, Bloco L, Lote 06, 
CEP 70040-020 
Brasilia, DF</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to Analyze the effects of treadmill inclination on the gait of children with DS. Methodology: Twenty-three subjects (9 girls and 14 boys), mean age 8.43 ±2.25 years, classified at level 1 of the Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS), were evaluated. A subjective assessment of balance was performed using a questionnaire (Berg`s Balance Scale-BBS). Next, a kinematic analysis of gait was carried out on a 0% and 10% electric incline treadmill, using a Qualisys motion capture system. Data were analyzed using Bioestat 5.0 software at a significance level of 5%. Normality of data was checked by D`Agostino`s test and the paired t-test was applied to compare variables under the two experimental conditions. Results: A statistically significant difference was observed in the following spatiotemporal variables: reduced gait (from 108.92 (39.07) to 99.11(27.51), p&lt; 0.04), increased cycle time (from 1.24 (0.27) to 1.36 (0.34), p=0.03) and increased swing time (from 0.77 (0.15) to 0.82 (0.18), p&lt; 0.001). A statistically significant increase was found in the following angular variables: hip at initial contact (from 12.23 (4.63) to 18.49 (5.17) , p&lt;0.0001) and maximum flexion in the swing phase (from 12.96 (4.32) to 19.50 (4.51), p&lt;0.0001); knee at initial contact (from 15.59 (6.71) to 21.63 (6.48), p&lt; 0.0001); and ankle at first contact (from 2.79 (9.8) to 2.25  (8.79) , p&lt;0.0001), maximum dorsiflexion in stance (from 4.41 (10.07) to 7.13(11.58), p&lt;0.0009), and maximum plantar flexion in preswing (from 6.33(8.77) to 2.69 (8.62), p&lt;0.0004). Conclusions: Inclination acts positively on the angular and spatiotemporal characteristics of gait in children with Down syndrome, demonstrating a possible benefit from the use of this type of surface in the gait rehabilitation of this population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Not published yet. Will be submitted to Physical Therapy.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica em Pesquisa do Hospital Universitario Onofre Lopes</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av. Nilo Pecanha, 620
Petropolis
Natal - RN
CEP 59012-300</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/08/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>194/2009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Thayse de Lucena Moura Rodenbusch</name>
      <address>Rua Fernando Barbosa de Melo, 400- Edifício Villa Real- APTO 102.
Catole
Campina Grande - PB
CEP 58410-440</address>
      <phone>55 83 3332 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tatalucena@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ana Raquel Rodrigues Lindquist</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte
Centro de Ciencias da Saude
Departamento de Fisioterapia
Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000
Caixa Postal 1524
Natal - RN
CEP 59072-970</address>
      <phone>55 84 3342 2010</phone>
      <fax>55 84 3342 2000</fax>
      <email>raquellindquist@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ana Raquel Rodrigues Lindquist</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte
Centro de Ciencias da Saude
Departamento de Fisioterapia
Av. Senador Salgado Filho, 3000
Caixa Postal 1524
Natal - RN
CEP 59072-970</address>
      <phone>55 84 3342 2010</phone>
      <fax>55 84 3342 2000</fax>
      <email>raquellindquist@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>