<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372514">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000374369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of exercise on vaccination responses - the role of timing and site of active muscle</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of exercise on vaccination responses in healthy young adults - the role of timing and site of active muscle</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1193-9619 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>STEVax</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vaccine related adverse events (pain, tenderness, redness, swelling)
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vaccine-related pain
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised (by computer randomisation table) into one of four groups: Control (Con), Pre-Vaccination Leg Exercise (PreLeg), Pre-Vaccination Arm Exercise (PreArm) or Post-Vaccination Arm Exercise (PostArm). 

The PreArm and PreLeg groups will perform the exercise task and immediately after completion will receive the vaccination. The Con and PostArm groups will receive the vaccination according to standard procedure after a 15-minute resting period. The PostArm group will perform the exercise task immediately after receiving the vaccine while all other groups will rest quietly. The exercise session will be supervised by an experienced trainer. 

Exercise tasks: All the participants except for the participants allocated to the Con group will take part in 15- minute exercise. The participants allocated to PreArm and PostArm group will partake in a task involving 30 seconds of exercise followed by 30 seconds rest, alternating between 3 upper body exercises (biceps curls, lateral raise, and chest press) using an exercise band. This task has previously been used safely in a study involving young healthy adults, and was shown to increase the immune response to the Pneumococcal vaccine. The task requires minimal, inexpensive equipment, no specialised environment, is easily transportable and implementable and requires no prior exercise experience. The participant allocated to PreLeg group will also partake in a task involving 30 seconds of exercise followed by 30 seconds rest, alternating between 3 lower body exercises (squats, lunges and calf raises).

We will be using Fluquadri Adult, an influenza vaccine of 0.25 mL dose administered intramuscular into the deltoid. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be administered with 0.25 mL of the influenza vaccine and will sit quietly rested for 15 minutes while others participate in exercise. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events (pain, tenderness, redness and swelling) at the site of injection. This will be self-reported using REDCaps online survey tool. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>For 7 days following. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>site-specific vaccine pain using VAS scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately after vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>antibody response using serology antibody analysis </outcome>
      <timepoint>15-minute post vaccination, 1 month and 6 months after vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in pressure-pain threshold with exercise using an algometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 15 minutes of vaccination </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible adults between the ages of 18 - 30 years, have passed the PAR-Q, and who have not previously received the influenza vaccine in 2016, and have no contraindications to vaccination. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Contraindication to vaccination as listed in the most current Immunisation Handbook, including anyone who has experienced an anaphylactic reaction to any component of the vaccine (including yeast) or following a previous dose of vaccine; history of vaccine related allergies or side-effects; current immune disorder (e.g. glandular fever) or acute infection; pregnant or suspected pregnancy; current medication (e.g., prescription medication, anti-inflammatories); egg allergies; unable to participate in exercise activity screened by PAR-Q. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by
computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A traditional drugs trial analytic strategy will be used. As such, it will firstly be investigated whether there is any difference between treatment and control i.e. exercise groups combined and compared to the control group. Secondly, the treatment groups will be compared i.e. compared within the exercise groups only. As previous studies have found sex differences in intervention efficacy, sex will be entered as a between-subject factor in all parameter analyses. Antibody titres will be log transformed, due to skewed distribution, for statistical analysis as geometric mean concentrations; pain will be assessed as a continuous variable. For adverse event assessment comparison between the exercise and control groups will use the report of adverse events as a categorical variable (Yes/No), differences between groups will be assessed with a Chi squared test. Subsequent analysis will assess severity of adverse events as a continuous variable (t tests).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2141 - Lidcombe</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cumberland campus
75 East street
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cumberland campus
75 East street
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Kate Edwards</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
Cumberland  Campus,
75 East Street,
lidcombe NSW 2141</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Robert Booy</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>NCIRS
Locked bag 4001, The Childrens Hospital, Westmead, NSW, 2145
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ass Prof Corinne Caullaud</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>room A014, The University of Sydney,
Cumberland campus, 
75 East Street, Lidcombe NSW,2141
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms. Jacqueline Fong</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Sydney, A5.06 MO2, Mallet street, Sydney, NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Vivian Lee</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Sydney
Cumberland Campus
Rm K121, 75 East Street
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study investigates the effect of exercising different limbs (arm vs. leg), and timing (pre- vs. post-) on responses to vaccination.
A single bout of exercise has been shown to improve vaccination responses, the proposed mechanisms include increased blood and lymph flow of the exercising muscle. This suggests that arm exercise would have stronger effects than leg exercise (if a vaccine is given in the arm).
All studies of exercise effects on vaccinations have used exercise pre-vaccination. But post-vaccination exercise might be more effective as the antigen can benefits from increased blood and lymph flow and increased immune cell numbers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2 Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2015/945</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kate Edwards</name>
      <address>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Rm K207, Cumberland Campus
75 East STreet
Lidcoombe, NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9036 7396</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.edwards@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Vivian Lee</name>
      <address>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Rm K121, Cumberland Campus
75 East STreet
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 478 708 523</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vivian.lee@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Vivian Lee</name>
      <address>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Rm K121, Cumberland Campus
75 East STreet
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 478708523</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vivian.lee@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>