<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335966">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001022055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Solifenacin to relieve ureteral stent-related symptoms:
A randomized, double-blinded placebo-controlled study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For patients with ureteral stent insertion after ureteroscopic stone manipulations, is Solifenacin effective in relieving ureteral stent-related symptoms?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-0490</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SoRUSS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ureteral stent-related symptoms after ureteroscopic stone manipulation.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Solifenacin 10 mg orally per day for 2 weeks after surgery</interventions>
    <comparator>one microcellulose tablet orally per day for 2 weeks after surgery.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement of ureteral stent-related symptoms will be assessed using the ureteral stent symptom questionnaire (USSQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3 , and 14 days after ureteral stent insertion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>"Nil"</outcome>
      <timepoint>"Nil"</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>From 01/10/2010 to 30/10/2011, all patients with unilateral ureteral stones to be treated with ureteroscopy where temporary stenting is indicated will be considered for enrollment in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who had significant ureteral trauma, a preexisting ureteral stent, another secondary surgical procedure that would have impacted patient comfort, ie transurethral resection of the prostate or of bladder tumor, or urinary infection or chronic pain history will be excluded from study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization will be performed in a 1:1 ratio. Patients will be randomized to placebo and study medication using a random number assignment generated by our research pharmacy. Investigators and patients will be blinded to the randomization scheme and investigators will be blinded to the medication until study termination. Each enrolled patient who received a ureteral stent will be given a blister pack containing 14 unmarked tablets. During the stenting period all patients will be allowed to use ultracet 1# tid on demand. Overall dosage will be documented and compared.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomization</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>prospective</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state>Taiwan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mennonite Christian Hospital, Taiwan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No. 44, Min-Chuan Road, Hualien, 970, Taiwan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mennonite Christian Hospital, Taiwan</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>No. 44, Min-Chuan Road, Hualien, 970, Taiwan</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ureteral stents have been an important tool in ureteral procedures. However, indwelling ureteral stents produce varying degrees of complications and discomfort. Although manufacturers have responded with novel stent shapes, materials and drug coatings, no ideal stent has been designed to date that significantly improves these complications. Many investigators have attempted to improve stent-related symptoms by using various agents, including oral anticholinergics. However, the roles of these medications in the treatment of ureteral stent-related symptoms remained unclear. We therefore propose to conduct a randomized, placebo-controlled study to evaluate the possible role of the antimuscarinics Solifenacin for improving stent-related symptoms after ureteroscopic procedures.

The study is designed as a prospective, randomized, double blind, placebo- controlled trial. From 01/10/2010 to 30/09/2011, all patients with unilateral ureteral stones or stricture to be treated with ureteroscopy where temporary stenting is indicated will be considered for enrollment in the study. Patients will be randomly assigned in a concealed fashion to 1 of 2 groups. In group 1 (placebo group), patients will receive placebo orally once daily for two weeks. In group 2, patients will receive Solifenacin 10 mg orally once daily for two weeks. 

Randomization will be performed in a 1:1 ratio. Investigators and patients will be blinded to the randomization scheme and investigators will be blinded to the medication until study termination. We estimated 100 patients will be enrolled in this study.

Semirigid ureteroscopy will be performed in all patients using a Wolf 6Fr/7.5Fr dual operating channel semirigid ureteroscope to passively dilate the ureteral orifice and address distal ureteral pathology. Intracorporeal lithotripsy will be performed using a 0.8 J 10 Hz holmium laser. All stents will be placed under ureteroscopic guidance. 

Ureteral stent-related symptoms will be measured at various time points via telephone interview by using a 10-cm linear visual analogue scale (VAS) for evaluating suprapubic pain and voiding flank pain, and irritative domain of International Prostate Symptom Scale (IPSS), in which 0 represented no pain and 10 represented extreme pain. Patients will be asked to complete the questionnaires on postoperative day 1, day 3, and on the day of stent removal. The median absolute symptom and VAS scores will be compared for each group at each time point. 

The primary outcome measure will be the assessment of the difference in ureteral stent symptoms in the treatment group compared with the placebo group. Statistical analysis will be performed with computer software.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NA.</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NA.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mennonite Christian Hospital Institutional Review Board.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No. 44, Min-Chuan Road, Hualien, 970, Taiwan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10-06-021-FR</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>HUI-MING CHUNG</name>
      <address>NO. 44, Min-Chuan Road, Hualien, 970, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>886-3-8241457</phone>
      <fax>886-3-8241496</fax>
      <email>hchung@jhsph.edu</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>HUI-MIN CHUNG</name>
      <address>NO. 44, Min-Chuan Road, Hualien, 970, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>886-3-8241457</phone>
      <fax>886-3-8241496</fax>
      <email>hchung@jhsph.edu</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>HUI-MING CHUNG</name>
      <address>NO. 44, Min-Chuan Road, Hualien, 970, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>886-3-8241457</phone>
      <fax>886-3-8241496</fax>
      <email>hchung@jhsph.edu</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>