<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368069">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000286549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Adding negative pRESSure to improve healING (the DRESSING trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Negative pressure wound therapy versus standard care dressing to prevent surgical site infections in obese women undergoing caesarean section. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-6302</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The DRESSING Trial (RCT)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Surgical site infections in obese women following caesarean section.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>At the completion of skin closure, those women randomly allocated to the Negative Pressure Wound Therapy (NPWT) will have a PICO Trademark (Smith and Nephew) applied. The gauze based dressing will be secured over the incision with fixation strips and continuous negative pressure of 80mmHg will be delivered via a tube embedded into the gauze by a small portable battery operated device. The dressing will remain in place for 4 days, unless it becomes soiled or dislodged. If this occurs the dressing will be changed using aseptic technique. All women (both intervention and control groups) will receive prophylactic antibiotics. All other aspects of their care will be consistent between the groups.</interventions>
    <comparator>Women in the control arm  will have a standard dressing (a hydrocolloid dressing) applied by manaufacturer's recommendations at the completion of skin closure. Like the NPWT dressing, the standard dressing will remain in place for 4 days, unless it becomes soiled or dislodged. All women (both intervention and control groups) will receive prophylactic antibiotics. All other aspects of their care will be consistent between the groups.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of surgical site infection (SSI)

Presence of SSI will be assessed by visual inspection and/or through an aseptically obtained culture. Superficial SSI will be identified by at least one of the following sign; purulent discharge, organisms identified through an aseptically obtained culture, pain/tenderness/localised swelling/heat, or a diagnosis of SSI by the consulting surgeon. A deep incisional SSI will be identified by one of the following; purulent discharge, wound dehiscence, abscess formation, or diagnosis of SSI by the treating surgeon.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 2 for the period of hospitalisation and then via telephone interview at 1,2,3, and 4 week post-surgery follow-up. A data collection form will be used to collect information on wound assessment during telephone follow-up. These questions will relate to the women's self-assessment of the wound. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound complications including dehiscence, haematoma and seroma will be assessed by visual inspection. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 2 for the period of hospitalisation and then via telephone interview at 1,2,3, and 4 week post-surgery follow-up. A data collection form will be used to collect information on wound assessment during telephone follow-up. These questions will relate to the women's self-assessment of the wound. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital readmissions</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 weeks post surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>At four weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life (QOL) using SF-12</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline i.e. on recruitment and via telephone interview at 1, 2, 3 and 4 week post-surgery follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Recorded body mass index (BMI) of equal to or greater than 30kg/m2 at the first antenatal booking visit.
2. Booked for elective caesarean section.
3. Semi-urgent caesarean section (as per treating Specialist).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previous participation in the trial.
2. Being treated for an existing infection with antibiotics after admission and prior to caesarean section.
3. Non-English speaking patients without an interpreter.
4. Clinical suspicion of chorioamnionitis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible women (or their representative) will be approached for written informed consent by a Research Assistant (Registered Midwife/Registered Nurse) during their final antenatal outpatient appointment. When the consenting woman presents for surgery, a staff member or researh assistant (RA) will access a web-based randomisation service customised for this trial and be advised of group allocation at wound closure. Computer generated allocation is provided by an independent randomisation service. Allocation is fully concealed until the woman is randomised. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated. Women will be randomised to the two study groups in a 1:1 ratio, using simple randomisation stratified by hospital. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/10/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/08/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Ipswich Hospital - Ipswich</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Mother's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4305 - Ipswich</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NHMRC Centre of Resaerch Excellence in Nursing Interventions for Hospitalised Patients, Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clinical Science Building 2
Parklands Drive
Southport
Queensland 4222
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra
ACT 2601
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity is a growing global public health problem in developed nations. It is estimated that half of all Australian women of childbearing age are overweight or obese. Obese pregnant women are more likely to deliver their babies by caesarean section and are also more likely to have complications such as surgical site infections after caesarean section than non-obese women.

Wounds that fail to heal may cause considerable distress to patients and negatively affect the physical, social, emotional and economic aspects of their life. Wound complications also add to the cost of health care. 

Negative Pressure Wound Therapy has been used to aid healing since it was first developed in the late 1990s. The treatment is based on a closed sealed system that produces negative pressure to the wound surface. The wound is covered and sealed with an occlusive dressing and suction tube which is connected to a vacuum pump which provides intermittent or continuous suction. Negative Pressure Wound Therapy is being used more frequently as a way to prevent wound complications especially surgical site infection, but it has not been well tested yet.

This study will test the effectiveness of two different methods to dress surgical wounds following caesarean section. These include Negative Pressure Wound Therapy compared to current care (standard care). We are doing this research study to find out the best practice for preventing Surgical Site Infections in obese women. To do this we need to study women with a body  mass index (BMI) greater than or equal to 30 for one month following their surgery, and closely monitor their surgical wound. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Gillespie BM, Webster J, Ellwood D, Stapleton H, Whitty JA, Thalib L, Cullum N, Mahomed K &amp; Chaboyer W. ADding negative pRESSure to improve healING (the DRESSING trial): a RCT protocol. BMJ Open 2016;6:e010287. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2015- 010287</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) EC00172</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC Office
Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Level 7
Block 7
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRBW/126</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368069-BMJ Open-2016-Gillespie- (1).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Brigid M Gillespie</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing (NCREN) Centre for Health Practice Innovation (HPI) Menzies Health Institute Qld (MHIQ)  Academic 1, G01 Bldg_Rm 2.04,   GRIFFITH UNIVERSITY l Gold Coast Campus QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 9718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.gillespie@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Brigid M Gillespie</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing (NCREN) Centre for Health Practice Innovation (HPI) Menzies Health Institute Qld (MHIQ)  Academic 1, G01 Bldg_Rm 2.04,   GRIFFITH UNIVERSITY l Gold Coast Campus QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 9718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.gillespie@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Brigid M Gillespie</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing (NCREN) Centre for Health Practice Innovation (HPI) Menzies Health Institute Qld (MHIQ)  Academic 1, G01 Bldg_Rm 2.04,   GRIFFITH UNIVERSITY l Gold Coast Campus QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 9718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.gillespie@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Brigid M Gillespie</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing (NCREN) Centre for Health Practice Innovation (HPI) Menzies Health Institute Qld (MHIQ)  Academic 1, G01 Bldg_Rm 2.04,   GRIFFITH UNIVERSITY l Gold Coast Campus QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 9718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.gillespie@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>