<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335740">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000599077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Gait and postural control to change the knee loading in patients with knee osteoarthritis (OA).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with medial tibiofemoral osteoarthritis, is gait retraining more effective than a wait-list control in reducing loading on the medial side?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>GO Study (Gait and Osteoarthritis)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Knee Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Gait retraining intervention: 1) 2x30min session each week at University of Sydney, for 4 weeks, in the 3D motion analysis laboratory 2) The participant walks on a 5m force platform, each gait trial does not exceed 6-8seconds. 3) The participant is given full real-time feedback during the training, so that they are aware of their incorrect walking style. 4) A light-feedback system is set up for the participant so that while they walk, a flash would indicate that they had achieved a sub-optimal knee adduction moment (KAM) during their gait trial. The light would point toward an incorrect walking style. The light is used in this way, to reduce dependence of the subject to have the light on, whilst performing correct gait style. 5) The subject performs this optimal movement 10 times followed by a rest, with the data collector asking after each trial, using a Likert pain scale, if they felt any pain in the knee during the activity. 30 trials are undertaken altogether (3 x 10 trials). There is no specific movement that is taught, each participant will adjust their gait style on their own advice and if the light does not flash, it indicates that they are walking correctly. However, if the participant fails to keep the light off, then suggestions are made to reduce the KAM eg: walking with toes out, by the assessor.</interventions>
    <comparator>The wait-list control group will receive the similar intervention as the training groups after 4 weeks, not 12.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee adduction moment. Will be measured using Biomechanical software, Cortex 2.0 in a 3D Motion analysis lab.</outcome>
      <timepoint>It is taken at baseline, and then re-assessed at 6 weeks post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Westren Ontario and McMaster Universities index (WOMAC) is used to assess knee pain and function at baseline and at the end of the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at the end of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Must have medial knee OA in at least one knee
Good general health</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any form of secondary arthritis such as gout, pseudogout etc
Joint injury (unrepaired anterior cruciate ligament injury), injection or surgery within the past 6 months or knee joint replacement.
Knee cartilage surgery
Knee injections (e.g. Corticosteroids  cortisone); no more than 2 in the last 5 years, and only one in the last 6 months.
Acute or terminal illness 
Severe functional limitation (unable to walk unaided)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants are communtiy dwelling, and once enrolled and have completed all baseline assessments, an external research assistant (not involved in the study), will randomly allocate groups.</concealment>
    <sequence>Will use blocking randomisation using randomization.com</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cumberland Campus 
PO Box 170, 75 East Street,  Lidcombe NSW, 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cumberland Campus 
PO Box 170, 75 East Street, Lidcombe NSW, 2141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary hypothesis is that participants randomised to the 1 month gait training program will reduce KAM and improve symptoms of OA compared to the control group. Osteoarthritis is the most common musculoskeletal disorder affecting Australians and is the leading cause of pain and disability. OA is caused by rapid degeneration of articular cartilage. Knee osteoarthritis reduces physical activity level due to the associated pain, impaired gait and balance and lower-extremity muscle weakness. Osteoarthritis treatment is typically driven by a pharmacologic approach to provide analgesia and reduce inflammation, rather than employment of disease-modifying agents, or risk factor reduction, with knee replacement surgery the only option in advanced cases. Gait retraining and postural control is theoretically far more targeted to the impairments in knee OA. The primary hypothesis that participants randomised in the 1 month gait program will have a significant reduction in the KAM compared to the control group, and have a significant improvement in symptoms of OA such as pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human research ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of ethics administration
Level 6
Jane Foss Russell Building, G02
The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Maria Fiatarone Singh</name>
      <address>PO Box 170, 75 East Street,  Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.singh@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jinan Dib</name>
      <address>PO Box 170, 75 East Street,  Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61410 881 178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jdib5450@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jinan Dib</name>
      <address>PO Box 170, 75 East Street,  Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61410 881 178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jdib5450@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>