<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364224">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000554763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>OVERT Study: Optimizing Valganciclovir Efficacy in Renal Transplantation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised study comparing universal valganciclovir prophylaxis with quantitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) based preemptive therapy for cytomegalovirus (CMV) disease in renal transplant recipients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1142-8990 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>OVERT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cytomegalovirus infection after renal transplantation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral valganciclovir (VALCYTE, Roche) 900mg/day for 3 months (cytomegalovirus serology combinations: donor+/recipient+ and donor-/recipient+) or 6 months (cytomegalovirus serology combination: donor+/recipient-) after transplantation started within 1 week post transplant.

To monitor adherence to drug intake patients will asked during each clinical visit to self report their adherence to valganciclovir use. However, no calculation of tablet return or ganciclovir plasma levels will be performed. </interventions>
    <comparator>Monitoring for cytomegalovirus (CMV) DNAemia detection using quantitative real-time PCR from whole blood  once a week for 16 weeks and, subsequently, at months 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 15, 18, 21, and 24 with pre-emptive oral valganciclovir (VALCYTE; Roche) therapy at a dose of 900 mg twice daily if CMV viral load exceeds 1000 IU/mL. Pre-emptive valganciclovir will be started within 7 days and continued until reaching clearance of CMV DNAmia in 2 consecutive measurements (&lt;50 IU/mL, at least for 14 days). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute rejection diagnosed by renal allograft biopsy (defined according to Banff criteria including both cellular and humoral rejection).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moderate-to-severe interstitial fibrosis/tubular atrophy (IF/TA) in protocol biopsy at 36 months (according to Banff criteria, moderate-to-severe IF/TA will be used for sample size calculation), intrarenal expression of messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) cytokines evaluated in each biopsy for severity of IF/TA assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative incidence of cytomegalovirus (CMV) disease (defined by clinical symptoms + presence of CMV viremia by quantitative PCR CMV DNA test). </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative incidence of cytomegalovirus (CMV) DNAemia defined by positive PCR for CMV DNA in whole blood.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cytomegalovirus (CMV) ganciclovir resistant DNAemia based on UL97 or UL54 mutation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of cytomegalovirus (CMV)-specific T cell immunity assessed by Elispot-Fluorospot assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of alloreactive T cell immunity assessed by Elispot-Flurospot assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative incidence of donor specific antibodies assessed by solid antigen based (SAB) Luminex assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other infections assessed by clinical symptoms, microbiological cultures, blood tests </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative patient and graft survival (defined as death or graft loss) based on prospective observation </outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 36, and 48 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events and study drug discontinuation or dose reduction due to adverse event  based on prospective observation (examples of side effects - haematological - leukopenia, trombocytopenia, anemia, psychiatric - hallucinations+confusion, liver enzyme abnormalities, de novo post transplant diabetes, de novo malignancy, cardiovascular events, etc.) </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Renal function assessed by serum creatinine and estimated glomerular filtration rate calculated by MDRD7 formula</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 36, and 48 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily urine protein excretion and urine protein/creatinine ratio</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Delayed graft function (defined as a need of dialysis within first week post transplant) </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Late onset cytomegalovirus (CMV) disease (defined by clinical symptoms + presence of CMV DNAemia by quantitative PCR CMV DNA test).</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult renal transplant candidates, complement-dependent cytotoxicity (CDC) cross-match negative at the time of transplantation, deceased (non-heart-beating donors or dual kidney transplantation are allowed) or living (both related and unrelated, AB0 compatible or incompatible) donors with known cytomegalovirus (CMV) serology before transplantation, CMV serology: donor(D)/recipient (R) serostatus of D+/R-, D+/R+, and D-/R+, ability to sign informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unknown pretransplantation CMV serology of the donor or recipient, D-/R- CMV serostatus, treatment of systemic viral infection within 2 weeks before transplantation except for active hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection, therapy with systemic antiviral agents within 2 weeks before transplantation except for treatment of hepatitis B (lamivudine, adefovir, entecavir), white blood cell (WBC) count &lt;3.0 x 10exp9/L, platelet count &lt;100 x 10exp9/L, allergy to ganciclovir, inclusion to another clinical trial, inability to provide informed consent.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Before transplantation and after informed consent signature, eligible patients (all renal transplant candidates) will be randomized to pre-emptive therapy with valganciclovir or to valganciclovir prophylaxis. Randomization will be stratified according to donor/recipient (D/R) CMV serostatus before transplantation, i.e. high-risk patients (D+/R- subgroup) will be randomized separatelly. Transplant nephrologist will be responsible for randomization. Sequentially numbered sealed envelopes will be used for allocation concealment. </concealment>
    <sequence>random-number table, at a 1:1 ratio with the use of random block sizes.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intention-to-treat analysis.

Sample size calculation: 
For 12-month primary end point
The anticipated biopsy-proven acute rejection rate in the valganciclovir group is 10% based on our previous study (2VAL Study, manuscript in preparation) comparing valganciclovir and valacyclovir prophylaxis considering a complete replace of cyclosporine by tacrolimus in initial immunosuppression. Ninety patients are required to detect increase in the incidence of BPAR to 25% in pre-emptive therapy group (power = 0.80; alpha = 0.05). 
For 36-month primary end point
Due to high donor age and frequent use of expanded criteria donors the anticipated incidence of moderate-to-severe (Banff grade II or III) IF/TA is 40%. This number correlates with the finding obtained with valacyclovir prophylaxis in our study (Reischig T, 2012). Based on the same study in which prophylaxis was associated with 2.5 fold increased risk of moderate-to-severe IF/TA compared to pre-emptive therapy we presume a 60% decreased relative risk of IF/TA in patients with pre-emptive therapy. In such a scenario a minimum of 62 patients with late protocol biopsy is required to ensure 80% power for detection of a treatment difference with type 1 error of 0.05.
To meet both short-term and long-term end points a total of 92 subjects should be enrolled given the anticipated number of patients to be lost to follow-up.

Reischig T, Hribova P, Jindra P, et al. Long-term outcomes of pre-emptive valganciclovir compared with valacyclovir prophylaxis for prevention of cytomegalovirus in renal transplantation. J Am Soc Nephrol 2012; 23: 1588-1597
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>92</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>95</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ass. Prof. Tomas Reischig, M.D., Ph.D.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Head of Division of Nephrology, Department of Internal Medicine I Charles University Medical School and Teaching Hospital, alej Svobody 80, 30460 Pilsen Czech Republic</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Czech Republic</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Project ED2.1.00/03.0076 from European Regional Development Fund.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ministry of Education, Youth, and Physical Training of the Czech Republic, Karmelitska 7, 118 12 Prague, Czech Republic </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Czech Republic</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Charles University Research Fund (project number P36)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Charles University in Prague, Rectorate, Ovocny trh 5, 116 36 Prague</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Czech Republic</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There are two major hypothesis to test: 
1) Valganciclovir prophylaxis for cytomegalovirus infection compared to pre-emptive therapy is associated with less early acute rejection due to lower incidence of early cytomegalovirus viremia and possible immunosuppressive properties of valganciclovir.
2) Pre-emptive therapy is beneficial in long-term outcomes such as incidence of interstitial fibrosis and tubular atrophy in late biopsies due to minimizing late cytomegalovirus activation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>not available</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Charles University Hospital Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Dr. Edvard Benes avenue 13
305 99 Plzen (Pilsen)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Czech Republic</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tomas Reischig, M.D., Ph.D. </name>
      <address>Head of Nephrology Division, Internal Medicine I (Division of Nephrology and Transplant Center), Charles University Medical School and Teaching Hospital, Alej Svobody 80, 30460 Pilsen, CZECH REP. </address>
      <phone>+420 377103650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>reischig@fnplzen.cz</email>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tomas Reischig, M.D., Ph.D. </name>
      <address>Head of Nephrology Division, Internal Medicine I (Division of Nephrology and Transplant Center), Charles University Medical School and Teaching Hospital, Alej Svobody 80, 30460 Pilsen, CZECH REP. </address>
      <phone>+420 377103650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>reischig@fnplzen.cz</email>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tomas Reischig, M.D., Ph.D.</name>
      <address>Head of Nephrology Division, Internal Medicine I (Division of Nephrology and Transplant Center), Charles University Medical School and Teaching Hospital, Alej Svobody 80, 30460 Pilsen, CZECH REP.</address>
      <phone>+420 377103650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>reischig@fnplzen.cz</email>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tomas Reischig, M.D., Ph.D.</name>
      <address>Head of Nephrology Division, Internal Medicine I (Division of Nephrology and Transplant Center), Charles University Medical School and Teaching Hospital, Alej Svobody 80, 30460 Pilsen, CZECH REP.</address>
      <phone>+420 377103650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>reischig@fnplzen.cz</email>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>