<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368077">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000825550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can a point of care, whole blood test, predict clotting complications after total hip and knee replacement surgery? </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Use of preoperative rotational thromboelastography (ROTEM) assays to detect postoperative thrombotic complications following total hip and knee arthroplasty in overweight and obese patients: a pilot study. 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-6604</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>DHypercoagulability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Thrombotic complications of surgery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Knee arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hip arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Clotting disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Preoperative and postopeartive ROTEM assays will be used detect hypercoagulability defined by the presence of rapid clot formation (evidenced by a shortened clotting time or clot formation time, increased alph angle) and/or increased clot strength (evidenced by high maximum clot firmness) in whole blood. Blood will be collected in a 3.5 mL citrated tube and 3 mL hirudin tube for ROTEM and multiplate analysis, respectively. These samples will be taken immediately prior to surgery, in the immediate post-operative period, and on days 1 and 3 post-operatively. The results of the ROTEM and multiplate investigations will not alter patient treatment. Patients will be commenced on The Prince Charles Hospital venous thromboembolic prophylactic pathway which involves TED stockings, sequential compression devices, and aspirin.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of preoperative hypercoagulability as determined by ROTEM analysis.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at 4 timepoints:
1. Preopereative
2. Immediately postoperative
3. Post operative day 1
4. Post operative day 3
The patient will be deemed hypercoagulable if the ROTEM parameters are outside the normal ranges. A statistician will be employed to determine clinical thresholds using ROTEM to measure hypercoagulability, and to determine whether ROTEM can be used to predict thromboemoblic complications in overweight and obese patients. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thrombotic complications will be assessed by review of patient charts and a follow up telephone call with the patient and/or their general practitioner. The thrombotic complications of interest include cardiac death, myocardial infarction, symptomatic deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, ischaemic stroke as a composite score. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Any time up to 30 days post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Myocardial injury (defined as elevated levels of cardiac troponin I &gt; 0.04 ug/L on serum assay)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 2 and 3 postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of units of blood transfused assessed by review of hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Any time up to 30 days post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay measured by review of hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of surgery up to 30 days post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unanticipated intensive care unit admission determined when reviewing hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Any time up to 30 days post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30 day mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>Any time up to 30 days post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Platelet function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Platelet function will be measured by Multiplate analysis pre-operatively, immediately after surgery, and on days 1 and 3 postoperatively. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients undergoing elective primary hip or knee replacement surgery with a BMI greater than/equal to 25 mg/m2 or waist circumference greater than/equal to 94 cm for males or 80 cm for females.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they (1) have risk factors other than obesity for venous thromboembolism (VTE) (including previous history of VTE, malignancy, and coagulation abnormalities), (2) hypercoagulability disorders or (3) severe renal or hepatic disease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation: according to previous studies, the proportion of subjects to experience post-operative complications is 4.2% and they are more likely to have a maximum clot firmness of at least 3 units than those who do not develop complications. In order to detect this with 80% power at 5% significance level with an estimated 5% incidence of complications, a sample size of approximately 300 particpants would be required. The current pilot study would be performed on 50 patients to assess feasibility. 

Analysis plan: for the primary aim, logistic regression will be used to assess the ability of the ROTEM assay measures to predict postoperative thrombotic complications in obese and overweight patients. Classification of body mass index and weight circumference will be according to WHO guidelines. Sensitivity and specificity analysis will be performed to determine best thresholds for identifying those patients at high risk of postoperative complications; where necessary, models will be adjusted for additional confounders such as age and other comorbidities. A paried t-test of pre and post surgery will be used to compare the multiplate and ROTEM measure changes. FInally, the predictive capability of the ROTEM assay will be assessed, stratified by overweight/obese category. A p value of 0.05 will be considered significant. Analysis wil be perfomed with input from QIMR/RBWH statistics unit.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>26/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Prince Charles Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This primary aim of this study is to determine if preoperative hypercoagulability, identified by ROTEM analysis, can predict postoperative thrombotic complications in overweight and  obese patients undergoing elective lower limb joint replacements.

Secondary aims:
1. To develop clinical threshold with ROTEM parameters to identify high risk patients with increased body mass index and/or waist circumference.
2. To monitor coagulation changes with ROTEM assays and platelet function with Multiplate analyser, preoperatively and postoperatively, in this cohort of patients.
3. To assess the sensitivity of the ROTEM assay to predict high-risk patients stratified according to body mass index and waist circumference.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles hospital human research ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Stanton</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthetics and Perfusion
Level 1
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3139 4648</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.stanton@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Stanton</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthetics and Perfusion
Level 1
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3139 4648</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.stanton@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Stanton</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthetics and Perfusion
Level 1
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3139 4648</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.stanton@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Stanton</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthetics and Perfusion
Level 1
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3139 4648</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.stanton@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>