<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308356">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000823279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Chloramphenicol In Corneal Abrasions Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of lubricants versus chloramphenicol on corneal healing in patients with corneal abrasions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CICAS</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>corneal abrasions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Lubricating Ointment (Polyvisc ointment) applied directly to the eye. Dose is 2cm of ointment, 4 times a day for 2 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>chloramphenicol ointment, which is an antibacterial ointment with lubricant. Dose is 2cm of ointment, 4 times a day for 2 days.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>corneal infection. This will be assessed by a qualified examiner via a slit lamp. Signs of infection include the presence of a corneal ulcer, haziness of the cornea and presence of cells in the anterior chamber.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours post discharge from the emergency department after initial presentation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>corneal re-epithelialization assessed by a qualified examiner via a slit lamp looking for signs of persistent corneal abrasions/ulcers, delayed healing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours post discharge from the emergency department after initial presentation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>side effects of treatment (including local irritation, red eye, swelling of eye lids) assessed by a qualified examiner via a slit lamp.</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours post discharge from the emergency department after initial presentation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>corneal abrasion within last 24 hours</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>existence of corneal infection</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients with simple corneal abrasions presenting to Westmead Hospital who meet our inclusion criteria will be invited to participate. After informed consent is obtained, patients will be randomised into a control group (chloramphenicol ointment) and a treatment group (lubricant). The preparation will occur in the pharmacy (un-blinded) where ointment tubes will be stripped of identifying features and placed in envelopes. In the Emergency Department, a randomisation matrix will be used to randomise subjects to preserve a double-blinded protocol. 48 hours after treatment, patients will be followed up by specialists trained by the Department of Ophthalmology to detect signs of corneal healing and/or corneal infection</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Westmead Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hawkesbury Road
Westmead, NSW, 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chloramphenicol is the commonest ophthalmic antibiotic ointment used by non-ophthalmologists in current practice. It is prescribed by general practitioners and emergency physicians in all cases of corneal abrasions, regardless of severity or mechanism of injury. However, there has been no evidence to determine whether chloramphenicol is the optimum therapeutic agent to treat corneal abrasions. It is uncertain whether the therapeutic effect of chloramphenicol is the antimicrobial agent (decreasing microbial infiltration) or the lubricating ointment (preventing micro-abrasions and speeding corneal re-epithelialization). Further, given the widespread use of chloramphenicol as a first line therapy for uninfected injuries, a serious risk and a major concern is the development of chloramphenicol resistant bacterial species. Thus the purpose of this study is to explore whether a simple lubricating ointment is a viable alternative to chloramphenicol ointment in the treatment of corneal abrasions. If proven correct, this study could potentially revolutionize the treatment of corneal abrasions, significantly decreasing the risk of antibiotic resistant bacteria while providing a cheaper alternative for both patient and hospital.

We aim to conduct a double-blinded randomized control trial comparing chloramphenicol to a lubricating ointment with no antimicrobial properties. Both ointments will be prepared within the Pharmacy Department of Westmead Hospital (unblinded member). The labels for both ointments will be masked and each ointment will be placed in individually numbered envelopes. When a patient with a corneal abrasion presents to the emergency department at Westmead Hospital a detailed ocular examination would be undertaken. If the patient meets our inclusion criteria and informed consent is obtained, the medical officer treating the patient would be provided with a numbered envelope dictated by a randomized matrix and the masked ointment dispensed. The patient would be discharged home with an information leaflet and instructions for use of the ointment. After 2 days, the patient will be asked to represent to the emergency department for follow-up by a specialist trained by the Department of Ophthalmology to detect signs of infection, side effects to treatment and appropriate corneal re-epithelialization and healing. If any signs of infection are noted, the patient will be referred to the Westmead Eye Clinic to be seen by an ophthalmologist on the same day.

The results from this study will be entered into a database and analysed by statisticians with the intension of publishing our findings in international peer-reviewed journals.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Westmead Campus Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Westmead Hospital,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/09/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Chameen Samarawickrama</name>
      <address>Centre for Vision Research,
Westmead Hospital,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6116</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9845 8345</fax>
      <email>chameen_sama@wmi.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Chameen Samarawickrama</name>
      <address>Centre for Vision Research,
Westmead Hospital,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6116</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9845 8345</fax>
      <email>chameen_sama@wmi.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Chameen Samarawickrama</name>
      <address>Centre for Vision Research,
Westmead Hospital,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6116</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9845 8345</fax>
      <email>chameen_sama@wmi.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>