<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362101">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000226808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A safety and feasibility study of oral Triheptanoin as an add on treatment for patients (12 years or older) with medical refractory epilepsy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase IIa randomized double-blind placebo controlled study to evaluate the safety and feasibility of oral triheptanoin as an add-on treatment to adolescent and adult patients with medically refractory epilepsy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>TRIP - E</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Medical refractory epilepsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patient will be up titrated to a maximum tolerated dose of Triheptanoin during a three week titration period. (Start dose 15 ml)  The total daily dose will be between 15 and 100ml daily depending on the patients tolerability (Up to 35% of caloric input per day). Patients will be take the maximum tolerated dose over a period of 16 weeks and assessed during this time. Patients will take Triheptanoin orally three to four times per day with meals. They will be asked to complete a food and seizure diary</interventions>
    <comparator>The patient will be up titrated to a maximum tolerated dose of C8/C10 (Comparator) during a three week titration period. (Start dose 15 ml)  The total daily dose will be between 15 and 100ml daily depending on the patients tolerability (Up to 35% of caloric input per day). Patients will be take the maximum tolerated dose over a period of 16 weeks and assessed during this time. Patients will take C8/C10 (Comparator)orally three to four times per day with meals. They will be asked to complete a food and seizure diary</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety. Possible adverse events include gastrointestinal upset and diarrhoea.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored weekly during  3 week titration period and then four weekly over the 16 week treatment period. Safety will be assessed based on reported adverse events.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complience with treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be monitored weekly during the titration period and then 4 weekly during the 16 week treatment period. Complience will be assessed by amount of oil returned at each study visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability of treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be monitored weekly during the titration period and then 4 weekly during the 16 wekk treatment period.  Tolerability will be assessed based on discussions with the patient, assessment of the food diary and assessment of adverse events.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male or female patients (12 years or older) with epilepsy who have experienced at least 4 seizures of an eligible type per month over two months prior to enrolment despite treatment with at least one anti-epileptic drug at clinically appropriate doses. (Eligible seizure types are: complex partial seizures (focal dyscognitive seizures), secondary generalised seizures, simple partial seizures with motor features, primary generalised seizures, tonic seizures, atonic seizures) Patients anti-epileptic drugs over the four weeks prior to enrolment must remain stable with no change.
Patients must be able to provide informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with a severe intellectual handicap

Patients with a history of major psychiatric morbidity (such as psychiatric illness requiring hospitalisation or history of psychosis or major depression)

Patients with history of substance abuse

Patients with a history of having had psychogenic non-epileptic seizures 

Patients who have seizure clusters or other reasons that make counting of numbers of seizures inaccurate

Females who are pregnant or breast feeding

Patients with disorders affecting medium and short chain fatty acid oxidation.  This includes medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency - MCAD, short-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency - SCAD, short-chain-3 hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency SCHAD and HMG CoA (3-hydroxy-3-methyl-glutaryl-CoA) synthase deficiency.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be randomised to recieve either Triheptanoin or Placebo at Week 8 (Visit 2). Patients will be assigned a unique Identification Number, which will be allocated in ascending order of random numbers based on the predetermined randomisation schedule, and according to their chronological order of inclusion in the study. Subjects will then be allocated corresponding treatment, labelled with the same number. Confirmation of the treatment number allocated will be documented in the drug accountability records and recorded in the CRF. Triheptanoin oil and placebo oil will be identical in appearance. The nature of treatment each subject will receive will not be disclosed to the investigator, study site personnel or subjects.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation schedule (1:1 ratio triheptanoin to placebo oil treatments) will be prepared by a statistician prior to the start of the study and stratified by each study centre. This schedule will be administered by the CRO, NTA.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>58</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/11/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>St Lucia, Brisbane QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Epilepsy Therapy Project</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 742
10N Pendleton St
Middleburg VA 20118</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A study to determine the safety, tolerability and complience tripheptanoin oil, taken as an oral supplement by patients 12 years and older, who have medical refractory epilepsy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Melbourne Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Grattan Street Parkville 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 2012.059</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Karin Borges</name>
      <address>Department of Pharmacology          		
School of Biomedical Sciences
University of Queensland		
Brisbane, QLD 4072		
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 3113</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.borges@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Karin Borges</name>
      <address>Department of Pharmacology          		
School of Biomedical Sciences
University of Queensland		
Brisbane, QLD 4072		
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 3113</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.borges@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fiona Ellery</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Trials Australia
245 Burgundy Street
Heidelberg 
VICTORIA 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7042</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2251</fax>
      <email>fellery@nsri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Terence O'Brien</name>
      <address>Royal Melbourne Hospital
4th Floor Clinical Sciences Building
Royal Parade, Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9 342 4658</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>obrientj@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>