<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372437">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000529347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised control trial  the efficacy of dialectical behaviour therapy in young adult prisoners who engage in self-harm</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Will prisoners who self-harm reduce their frequency of self-harming after going through the Dialectical Behaviour Therapy intervention?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>self-harm</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>borderline personality disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>well-being</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Suicide</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention for young prisoners who self-harm will be the modified dialectical behaviour therapy by Mission Australias Triple Care Farm. The group intervention is a 12-week, biweekly group-skills session conducted by two clinical psychologists who are DBT-trained. The modules included will be on mindfulness, distress tolerance, emotion regulation and interpersonal effectiveness.  1. Sessions will be in a group therapy format with up to 10 participants per group (Triple Care Farm, 2015). DBT is a structured, skills-based program which will teach participants skills such as mindfulness (i.e. to encourage teaching in the 'here and now' and focus on the present), distress tolerance (i.e. coping skills whenever participants are in a crisis), interpersonal effectiveness (i.e. how to behave in relationships and to maintain respect at the same time) and emotion regulation (i.e. how to identify emotions and manage emotions that are unhelpful or unjustified). Besides teaching skills, participants will also be given a treatment workbook where they can fill in their own notes during sessions.

2. Duration of sessions will be 2-hours

3. Strategies to monitor adherence: Register of attendance at the beginning of each session and a diary-card, where participants will need to tick which skill they used outside therapy times and any reasons why some skills are difficult than others and this will be reviewed at the beginning of every session

4. Biweekly means two sessions a week.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as Usual: Participants in this group will receive leaflets on self-harm and alternative coping strategies and will be required to meet with the prison doctor for further monitoring. No other therapy will be provided to this group of participants throughout the 12-week period. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-harm behaviours assessed using the Inventory of Statements about Self-Injury (ISAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at Week 16 and 20 post-intervention completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Borderline Personality Disorder symptoms as assessed by the Structured Clinical Interview for Borderline Personality Disorder (SCID-BPD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 16 and 20 post-intervention completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General well-being (as observed from the Well-being Survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at Week 16 and 20 post-intervention completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotion regulation (as observed from the Difficulties in Emotion Regulation, DERS questionnaire) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at Week 16 and 20 post-intervention completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	Malaysian nationality
-	Young adult prisoner aged between 14 and 21 years of age who self-harm
-	Males and Females
-	Does not necessarily need to know how to read or write, but must be able to understand English or Malay
-	Convicted prisoners only
-	Remaining length of sentence should be at least 6 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>21</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The participant is Non-Malaysian
The participant is only able to comprehend minimum English or Malay language, and is only able to speak in his mother tongue (i.e. Chinese, Tamil or others)
The participant is over 21 years of age 
The participant has significant mental health, physical or drug and alcohol concerns that may get in the way of their involvement or threaten the safety of other participants,
The participant has less than 6 months left of his sentence</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Balanced and blocked randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Using the sample size calculation method via the G*Power program, in order to produce a medium-to-large effect size with the power of approximately 80% for an independent t-test (to see the differences between two groups), one group should have 64 participants. Consequently, two groups would yield 128 participants. However, this number would just be estimates as determining a sample size for a randomised controlled trial is highly unpredictable (i.e. many variables would affect the final sample size). 

Similar randomised controlled trials such as cognitive behaviour therapy intervention for self-harm (Slee et al., 2008); DBT for women with borderline personality disorder (Verheul et al., 2003); DBT with suicidal and self-harming adolescents (Tørmoen et al., 2014); DBT for adolescents with repeated suicidal and self-harm behaviour (Mehlum et al., 2016) among other studies included between 27 to 90 participants in their RCTs. 

Therefore, 128 participants in our study would be ideal and might just be more than enough. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>20/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/02/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Malacca</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Project Air Strategy for Personality Disorders</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Project Air Strategy for Personality Disorder, Illawarra Health and Medical Research Institute, School of Psychology, University of Wollongong, NSW, Australia, 2500</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Project Air Strategy for Personality Disorders</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Project Air Strategy for Personality Disorder, Illawarra Health and Medical Research Institute, School of Psychology, University of Wollongong, NSW, Australia, 2500</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Dr. Muhammad Muhsin Ahmad Zahari</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University Malaya, 59100 Kuala Lumpur </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Low Wah Yun</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Research Management Center, Faculty of Medicine, University Malaya, 50603 Kuala Lumpur </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dialectical behaviour therapy (DBT) has had positive outcomes in correctional settings, especially with adolescents, female inmates and those with Borderline Personality Disorder. Similarly, DBT has also been implemented specifically to reduce self-harming. However, no randomised controlled trials on DBT have been conducted to reduce self-harm in the prison setting among young adults. The purpose of this study is therefore to examine the efficacy of Dialectical Behavioural Therapy (DBT) informed treatment (as compared to treatment as usual, TAU) on young adult prisoners who self-harm or have associated borderline personality disorder symptoms. Specifically, the study aims:
1) To examine efficacy of DBT among prisoners who self-harm
2) To examine if the frequency of self-harming behaviour, thoughts and symptoms would decrease after the implementation of DBT
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Wollongong Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Wollongong, NSW, Australia, 2500</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE16/273</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Center</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Center, Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20166-2609</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372437-UOW 16-273 Approval 131016.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372437-Arina Main - PIS and CF V3.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Brin Grenyer</name>
      <address>Building 41
School of Psychology
Faculty of Social Sciences
University of Wollongong
Northfields Avenue
WOLLONGONG NSW 2522
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 3474</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4163</fax>
      <email>grenyer@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Brin Grenyer</name>
      <address>Building 41
School of Psychology
Faculty of Social Sciences
University of Wollongong
Northfields Avenue
WOLLONGONG NSW 2522
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 3474</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4163</fax>
      <email>grenyer@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Brin Grenyer</name>
      <address>Building 41
School of Psychology
Faculty of Social Sciences
University of Wollongong
Northfields Avenue
WOLLONGONG NSW 2522
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 3474</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4163</fax>
      <email>grenyer@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Brin Grenyer</name>
      <address>Building 41
School of Psychology
Faculty of Social Sciences
University of Wollongong
Northfields Avenue
WOLLONGONG NSW 2522
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 3474</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4163</fax>
      <email>grenyer@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>