<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368065">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000410550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> Changes in the pressure pain threshold in the spine after manual pumping of liver by an osteopath.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Changes in the pressure pain threshold in the cervical and dorsal vertebrae after manual pumping of liver by an osteopath in patients with pathophysiology related to liver function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Any disorder whose pathophysiology has been related with the function of the liver </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The pumping technique: To such end, the subject place in a supine position with knees bent and the therapist standing on the left hand side of the patient, near the abdominal area. The left hand goes under the costal border to lift the costal chest. The right hand rests on the lower chest on the right side to compress the liver through the costal wall. The lower hand lifts the ribs while the upper hand exerts compression. The patient is asked to inhale deeply, and on exhaling the compression is performed with the hands, and during deep inspiration.
This will be repeated for 10 respiratory cycles. Thus, through the
anteroposterior contact on the liver, using the costal inspiration, which lowers the diaphragm, the liver is pumped</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects in the Control Group follow exactly the same process for measurements, positions, contacts and breathing as the Experimental Group, with the only exception being the pumping. In lieu of any force, the therapist's hands will limited to accompanying the respiratory movements with no compression.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the effects of the liver pumping technique, onthe pain threshold to pressure on the cervical and dorsal vertebrae, using algometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately following completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the effects of the liver pumping technique, onthe pain threshold to pressure on the cervical and dorsal vertebrae, using algometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 minute following completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria will be subjects of both sexes who seek an osteopathy consultation for any disorder whose pathophysiology has been related with the function of the liver (spinal pains, headaches, sprained ankle ...), aged between 18 and 65 years, must have fasted for at least 8 hours and tolerating the supine position</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects presenting the following could not participate in the study (i) contraindication or intolerance to costal compression, (ii) psychotic problems, (iii) primary cancer or current metastases, (iv) current gastrointestinal bleeding, (v) liver transplants ( vi) polycystic liver or hepatobiliary infarction (vii) intra-abdominal infection or inflammation in acute phase, (viii) chronic liver disease of any etiology, (ix) decompensated heart failure (x) subjects who are receiving chemotherapy
and / or radiotherapy, (xi) pregnant women,</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The subjects will be formed through random ballots in sealed envelopes, assigning to the Experimental Group (EG) those subjects who draw a ballot with the number 1, and to the Control Group (CG) those subjects who drew a ballot with the number 2. An outside co-worker safeguard the sequence for those participating in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>This trial use simple randomisation. Participants randomly removed, being removed from the rest chosen on envelopes, sealed envelopes with numbers 1 and 2 written. Be so formed two groups: an intervention group and a control group. Assigning to the Experimental Group (EG) those subjects who draw a ballot with the number 1, and to the Control
Group (CG) those subjects who drew a ballot with the number 2</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>46</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Elena Rodriguez Lopez</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>pza nicaragua, 9, 9 A
Mostoles
28936 Madrid</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Elena Rodriguez</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mostoles- Madrid</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Angel Oliva Pascual Vaca</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>pza nicaragua, 9, 9 A
Mostoles
28936 Madrid</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Spain</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The osteopathic treatment of the liver has been recommended in several types of disorders in order to increase and improve the liver function.
However, there are no studies to support its effectiveness.
Therefore, through the algometer, we inten to evaluate the effect of the osteopathic manual pumping of liver technique on changes in the pain of  cervical and dorsal vertebrae in patients with different symptoms.
The conceptual hypothesis of our study will be that "the manual treatment of the liver improves the pain of cervical and dorsal vertebrae", so that a visceral manual operation may change the neural function of the viscera itself.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SEFO- scientific european federation osteopaths</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/ San Felix de Alcala 4
28807 Alcala de Henares
Madrid</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elena Sonsoles Rodriguez Lopez</name>
      <address>pza nicaragua, 9, 9 A
Mostoles
28936 Madrid</address>
      <phone>+34679336394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenasonsolesrodriguez@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elena Sonsoles Rodriguez Lopez</name>
      <address>pza nicaragua, 9, 9 A
Mostoles
28936 Madrid</address>
      <phone>+34679336394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenasonsolesrodriguez@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elena Sonsoles Rodriguez Lopez</name>
      <address>pza nicaragua, 9, 9 A
Mostoles
28936 Madrid</address>
      <phone>+34679336394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenasonsolesrodriguez@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>