<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368254">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000398505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of nurse-supported telehealth for people with heart conditions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of nurse-supported telehealth for chronic heart failure (CHF) management </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1168-7620</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Self-care behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will employ a novel 6 months telehealth intervention to complement community-based, nurse-support for CHF management. Central to this process will be the utilisation of Medtech 32, a modular practice management software. Medtech has a secure internet health portal (VitelMed) that enables individuals to upload daily clinical information, to allow them to engage electronically with the nurse to support self-management and more focussed patient care. The studys nurse will review patients online records on a weekly basis and alerts will be set up on the system to highlight when a patients data suggests clinical changes and the requirement for the patient to seek medical advice.  Patients without internet access will not be excluded from the study. They will be able to engage a family member to upload their clinical information, or will be provided with a diary to record clinical information that can be posted to the studys Project Officer who will upload information on their behalf.
To support the telehealth intervention participants will receive CHF education and have a telehealth heart failure management plan developed during an initial face to face appointment (2 hours) with the projects CHF nurse. If a face to face appointment is not possible a telephone conference will be arranged. Participants will be provided with a computer tablet and three devices that monitor their health; scales, a blood pressure monitor and physical activity monitor and will be orientated to this equipment and software at the initial appointment. These devices stream data automatically to the computer tablet which then gets uploaded to VitelMed, so that it can be accessed remotely by the studys nurse. Participants will be phoned once a week (15 minutes) for the first month to provide support for ongoing self-management and using the telehealth devices. Participants will also enter their self-management observations into the self-management database through a secure online portal for ongoing review by the projects nurse. The nurse will undertake surveillance of participants recorded details and use these to guide self-management and link the participant to their GP/Cardiologist in the event of clinical deterioration. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients will receive usual medical care from their GP, literature about CHF self-management in line with local protocols for the 6 month trial, but no telehealth support. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>self-care behaviour is assessed using Self-Care of Heart Failure Index (SCHFI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline before intervention and at 6 months (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life is assessed using Minesotta Living with Heart Faillure Questionnaire and Short Form 12</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Outcomes through access to Department of Health records held by the Data Linkage Unit (mortality and readmissions). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of nurse-supported telehealth amongst patients with CHF through Nurse-supported telehealth for people with heart conditions questionnaire which is designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness will involve three tasks: 
1.	Measuring and valuing the health system costs of implementing each intervention.
2.	Measuring and valuing the health system and associated costs of treating patients in each arm of the study for the 6-month study period following hospital discharge.
3.	Calculating the total costs of each arm of the study
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>prior hospital admission with a primary or secondary diagnosis of CHF</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Lack of fluency in English 
2. Unable to give informed consent 
3. Terminal illness such as metastatic cancer or severe hepatic/renal failure, significant cognitive impairment or physical inability to engage in self-care behaviours
4. Patients with severe end-stage CHF who are receiving palliative therapy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The sample will be drawn from patients who are treated at three Western Australia public hospitals; Royal Perth Hospital (RPH), Fiona Stanley Hospital (FSH) and Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital (SCGH). These patients will be identified from  ICD-10 codes describing a primary or secondary diagnosis of CHF and will be randomized to either the intervention or control group. Allocation not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the baseline variables, summary statistics will be constructed employing frequencies and proportions for categorical data and means and standard deviation for continuous variables. The participant characteristics will be compared using Fishers exact test for categorical outcomes and t tests for continuous variables. The primary endpoint of a composite of all cause death and rehospitalisation for worsening CHF will be analysed using the stratified log-rank test for eligible patients with age (greater than or equal to 65 vs &lt;65 years), LVEF (greater than or equal to 30% vs &lt;30%) and history of ischaemic heart disease (IHD vs non-IHD) as stratification factors. Time to events will be estimated using Kaplan-Meier curves, and hazard ratios and 95% confidence intervals will be calculated using the Cox proportional hazards models with stratification factors. Sensitivity analyses will also be performed by means of the unadjusted Cox models. P &lt; 0.05 will be considered statistically significant.

Based on the result of previous studies we estimate that the hazard ratio of the primary endpoint (all-cause death and hospitalisation for worsening CHF) of the telehealth group to the control group would be 0.60 and that the cumulative annual event rate in the usual care group would be 0.30. Based on 80% power to detect a 40% relative reduction in the risk of the primary outcome in the intervention group at 6 months, compared with the control group, and an expected death rate at 6 months of 30% in the control group using a log-rank test with a two-sided a of 0.05 we plan to plan to recruit a total sample size of 240 patients (120 in each group).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Andrew Maiorana</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science 
Faculty of Health Sciences  
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987 Perth, 
Western Australia 6845
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health, Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, Block C
189 Royal Street
East Perth 6004
Western Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic heart failure (CHF) is a complex medical condition characterised by recurrent exacerbations and a high rate of co-morbidities. An estimated 11,250 patients with CHF live within the South Metropolitan Health Service (SMHS) catchment area.  The cost of CHF to the WA Health system is significant. According to the Epidemiology Branch, Department of Health (2011), from 2000 to 2010 (financial years from 2000/01-2009/10) CHF resulted in an average of 5,168 bed days per year in SMHS hospitals alone. A recent consensus statement by the National Heart Foundation and Cardiac Society of Australia and New Zealand conceded that outcomes for patients diagnosed with CHF remain poor, often due to late diagnosis and inadequate disease management and support.

Many CHF patients are managed in primary care by their GP. However, there is currently limited support provided for GPs to conduct this challenging role, resulting in an overreliance on costly hospitalisations and use of tertiary health care when patients experience exacerbations. Moreover, in many cases, patients miss early warning signs and dont engage GP care early when their changing condition can be managed effectively in a primary care setting.  

The aim of this study is to investigate a novel intervention that involves a community nursing model that is complemented by the use of telehealth to monitor patients remotely through online software. The core component of this approach will be a multifactorial telehealth intervention, facilitated by a CHF nurse. The telehealth intervention will be patient-centred, providing patients with education and support for self-management and have a strong focus on coordination of care through feedback of clinical information to GPs to help them implement timely medical follow up. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HREC Curtin University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kent St, Bentley, Western Australia 6102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR 181/2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sheau Huey Chen (Nicole)</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science 
Faculty of Health Sciences  
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987 Perth, 
Western Australia 6845
</address>
      <phone>(+614) 30161252</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sheauhuey.chen@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science 
Faculty of Health Sciences  
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987 Perth, 
Western Australia 6845
</address>
      <phone>(+618) 9266 9225</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>A.Maiorana@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science 
Faculty of Health Sciences  
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987 Perth, 
Western Australia 6845
</address>
      <phone>(+618) 9266 9225</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>A.Maiorana@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sheau Huey Chen (Nicole)</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science 
Faculty of Health Sciences  
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987 Perth, 
Western Australia 6845
</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>