<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371358">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001210460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised trial comparing semi-structured interviews and online questionnaires administered to health professionals and consumers in identifying  the barriers and enablers to implementation of an Antenatal Corticosteroid Clinical Practice Guideline.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial comparing semi-structured interviews and online questionnaires administered to health professionals and consumers  in identifying  the barriers and enablers to implementation of an Antenatal Corticosteroid Clinical Practice Guideline.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preterm Birth</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Appropriate administration of antenatal Corticosteroids</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Use of a new bi-national antenatal corticosteroid clinical practice guideline</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Completion of a semi-structured interview (SSI):
A Face to face interview was conducted by a single researcher (EM) to maintain consistency. Interviews were conducted at a time and location convenient to the participant. The majority of interviews were conducted at the hospital site.  No explicit time restraints were applied</interventions>
    <comparator>Completion of an (online) questionnaire:
The questionnaire was developed on the web based Survey Monkey (Registered Trademark and was emailed to the participants preferred email to be completed at a time convenient to them. Reminder emails were sent out to non-responders two weeks after the initial questionnaire followed by a telephone reminder one week later if there had been no response. On rare occasions participants were provided with a paper copy of the questionnaire if they were unable to access the online version. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Composite-Overarching barriers and enablers identified by each of the two assessment methods.
Assessed by: Theoretical Domains Framework (TDF) was used to classify responses by all participants by two researchers. Specific statements were used to reflect the beliefs coded within each domain. It was then decided it these beliefs would represent a barrier or enabler to implementation.
Overarching barriers were defined by: the presence of conflicting beliefs within a domain that would signal variation in provider attitudes and beliefs, the frequency of specific beliefs across transcripts and the likely impact of the belief on the behaviour. Overarching enablers were identified by: the presence of beliefs within a domain that were likely to facilitate implementation of the antenatal corticosteroid clinical practice guideline, the frequency of those beliefs across transcripts and the likely impact of the belief on the behaviour.Differences in the barriers and enablers identified between the two assessment groups were compared.



</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of trial: April-November 2014</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Composite outcome-Effectiveness of one assessment method compared to the other 
(effectiveness defined as: time taken for participant to complete assessment method; response rate to the pre-specified questions; level of agreement; influence of the assessment method on any differences identified; and the level of response defined by a scale were 1=not applicable and 4 indicated a comprehensive answer)

Assessed by: Time taken was assessed using the online log for the online questionnaire group and the recorded time on the audiorecorder for SSI participants. A second coding framework was developed to reflect responses  from SSI and Questionnaire participants. To assess validity a second reviewer independently reviewed 10% of coded transripts that were selected at random. Responses to individual questions were compared by study group only if the questions asked were the same.  The level of agreement between the two assessment methods (SSI and Questionnaire) was assessed using Fishers exact test for each question. In questions where a statistical difference was demonstrated between the two assessment methods; proportions or relative risks were used to identify the differences between the two assessment methods and the direction of the effect. 
A third coding framework was developed to assess the leve of detail of response. The coding framework categorised responses from one to four. Where one represented the participant indicating the question was not applicable to them and four representing a detailed response. The difference in the level of response between the two assessment methods (SSI and Questionnaires) was assessed using Fishers exact test for each question.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of the trial: April to November 2014</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Level of agreement between the two assessment methods within each individual theoretical domain. 

Assessed: Questions used in both the SSI and questionnaires were grouped according to the individual behavioural domain that the question corresponded to within the Theoretical Domains Framework. Similarities in responses within the 14 behavioural domains were compared between the two assessment methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of trial: April to November 2014</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Issues identified by the different assessment methods within each domain

Assessed: Questions used in both the SSI and questionnaires were grouped according to the individual behavioural domain that the question corresponded to within the Theoretical Domains Framework. Differences in responses within the 14 behavioural domains were compared between the two assessment methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of the trial: April to November 2014</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Health professionals working within three district health boards in four maternity hospitals in Auckland, New Zealand consented to participate. Consumers were recruited postnatally from 4 neonatal units across three district health boards (DHBs) in Auckland, New Zealand. Women were eligible to participate if they had received a dose(s) of ACS prior to preterm birth at or less than 34 weeks gestation
Participants completed a semi-structured interview or questionnaire.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed, opaque envelopes were used to conceal study group allocation and were held by an independent researcher. Once eligibility of participants was confirmed including provision of  informed consent, participants were randomised to either a SSI or questionnaire. The independent researcher responsible for randomisation was contacted by telephone and the next envelope in the relevant strata was opened to reveal the study group allocation either: “SSI Group” or the “Questionnaire Group”. Following study group allocation of participants, the lead investigator (EM) contacted the participant to explain how to proceed. Due to the nature of the study it was not possible for the researcher to be blinded to group allocation during analysis of the results.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence was prepared by a statistician using a computer generated random number table. Participants were randomised to either a SSI or questionnaire. Participants were stratified by health professional (obstetrician, midwife, neonatologist/paediatrician) or consumer group and hospital site (Auckland District Health Board, Waitemata District Health Board and Counties Manukau District Health Board).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline demographics of all randomised participants were descriptively summarised within their respective study groups (SSI Group and Questionnaire Group). The Theoretical Domains framework (TDF) (Michie 2005, Cane 2012) was used to classify all participant responses into one or more of the 14 behavioural domains within the TDF framework. Two researchers independently coded responses and any differences wer resolved through discussion. The two reviewers decided whether these statements would represent a barrier or an enabler to implementation of the antenatal corticosteroid clinical practice guideline. Differences in the overarching barriers and enablers identified between the two groups were compared. 
A second coding framework was developed following data collection to reflect the responses received from the SSI and questionnaire participants. Responses to individual questions were compared by study group if the questions asked were the same. For continuous variables differences of means with 95% confidence intervals (CI) were used to compare outcomes. When the data was skewed, differences of medians with Interquartile ranges (IQR) were used. For categorical variables Fishers exact tests were used.
A template of 43 questions was used in both the SSI and Questionnaire Groups. A number of the questions had multiple items and were analysed separately. The number and proportion of questions answered were reported for each individual question and overall. 
The level of agreement between the two assessment methods (SSI and Questionnaire) was assessed using Fishers exact test for each question. 
A third coding framework was developed to assess the level of detail of response by the participants for each individual question. The coding framework categorised responses from one to four. Where one represented the participant indicating the question was not applicable to them and four representing a detailed response. The difference in the level of response between the two assessment methods (SSI and Questionnaires) was assessed using Fishers exact test for each question. The influence of the type of question [open, closed or mixed (closed with a textbox)] was explored. All analyses were undertaken using SPSS version 20.0. The threshold of significance was set at p=0.05.
No formal sample size calculation was performed. A pragmatic approach was adopted to reflect the number of participants required to acheive data saturation and to reflect the number of participants that could be recruited with each health professional group across the hospital sites. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>29/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/11/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>96</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>97</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2014</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>24/11/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Auckland
 Private Bag 92019
 Auckland 1142
 New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Centre for Growth and Development (GRAVIDA)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Liggins Institute,
The University of Auckland
 Private Bag 92019
 Auckland 1142
 New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Two commonly reported tools used to assess barriers and enablers are semi-structured interviews (SSI) and online questionnaires. Few studies have examined the similarity in responses between these two methods to see if and when comparisons are justified.Therefore the aims of this study were (1) to enhance knowledge on the optimal methods for assessment of barriers and enablers in the field of implementation science using a theoretical construct (Theoretical Domains Framework) (Michie 2005, Cane 2012) to assess which assessment method (SSI or Questionnaire) is most effective in identifying barriers and enablers to implementation of a new Antenatal Corticosteroid Clinical Practice Guideline. This is a multicentred randomised trial which conducted across four hospitals in Auckland, New Zealand among health professionals (HP) caring for pregnant women and their infants. Follow consent participants were randomised, and stratified by hospital site and health professional group (obstetrician, midwife, neonatologist/paediatrician), to a SSI or online questionnaire. The Theoretical Domains Framework was used to inform questions and to code participant responses into one or more of the 14 behavioural domains within the TDF framework and to classify them as either a barrier or an enabler to implementation of the antenatal corticosteroid clinical practice guideline. An assessment was undertaken to look at the similarity of reponses between the two methods,  the influence of the assessment method on the differences identified and the overall detail of response provided. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>1. McGoldrick E, Crawford T, Brown JA1, Groom K, Crowther CA. Semi-structured interviews or online questionnaires to identify barriers and enablers to administration of antenatal corticosteroids: A randomised trial. Perinatal Society of New Zealand 20th Annual Congress 2015, Townsville QLD. Oral presentation [Abstract ID 227710195]

2. McGoldrick E, Crawford T, Brown JA1, Groom K, Crowther CA Identifying the barriers and enablers to implementation of the new antenatal corticosteroid clinical practice guidelines among NZ health care professionals using a thematic analysis. Journal of Paediatrics and Child Health 2015;51: A271 (oral presentation)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland
New Zealand, 1142
Level 10, 40 Symonds Street</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>011193</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ADHB Research review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 14, Support Bldg, Auckland City Hospital.
 Private Bag 92024, Auckland, New Zealand, 1023</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>A+6217</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Awhina Maternity Clinical Governance Group</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lower Ground Floor, North Shore Hospital
 124 Shakespeare Rd
 Takapuna, Auckland, New Zealand, 0622
 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RM 0980712728 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CMDHB Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Counties Manukau Health
Ko Awatea Research Office
Counties Manukau DHB
Clinical Support Building
Room 253, Level 2
Middlemore Hospital
100 Hospital Road, Otahuhu
Auckland, 1640</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1741/UAHPEC011193</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Louise McGoldrick</name>
      <address>Liggins Institute
The University of Auckland, Building 505, 
Level 2, 85 Park Road, Auckland P Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142, NZ 

</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 8346 Ext 86872 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.mcgoldrick@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Louise McGoldrick</name>
      <address>Liggins Institute
The University of Auckland, Building 505, 
Level 2, 85 Park Road, Auckland P Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142, NZ 
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 8346 Ext 86872 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.mcgoldrick@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Louise McGoldrick</name>
      <address>Liggins Institute
The University of Auckland, Building 505, 
Level 2, 85 Park Road, Auckland P Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142, NZ 
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 8346 Ext 86872 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.mcgoldrick@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Louise McGoldrick</name>
      <address>Liggins Institute
The University of Auckland, Building 505, 
Level 2, 85 Park Road, Auckland P Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142, NZ 
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 8346 Ext 86872 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.mcgoldrick@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>