<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373446">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001227381p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase I trial to evaluate the safety and tolerability of GDC-0214 in healthy volunteers and patients with mild asthma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I study to evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics of GDC-0214 conducted in three parts: a single ascending dose study in healthy volunteers, a multiple-ascending dose study in healthy volunteers, and a proof of activity study in patients with mild asthma. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NONE</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>For Part A, healthy volunteers will receive a single inhaled dose of GDC-0214 or placebo.  The starting dose will be 0.15 mg inhaled.  A total of 5 sequential dose cohorts are planned: Cohort A, B, C, D, and E.  Doses will be escalated based on safety, tolerability, and available PK data.

For Part B, healthy volunteers will receive an inhaled dose of GDC-0214 or placebo once or twice daily for a total of 14 days.  A total of 4 sequential dose cohorts are planned: Cohort F, G, H, and I.  Doses will be escalated based on safety, tolerability, and available PK data.  Daily dose will not exceed those evaluated in Part A.

For Part C, subject with mild asthma will receive an inhaled dose of GDC-0214 or placebo once or twice daily for a total of 14 days.  A total of 3 sequential dose cohorts are planned.  Doses will be escalated based on safety, tolerability, and available PK data.  Dose and duration will not exceed those evaluated in Part B.

For parts A, B and C all dosing will be done in clinic under the supervision of qualified medical staff. 

A Safety Monitoring committee that will include at minimum the Medical Monitor, a drug safety scientist, and a biostatistician from the Sponsor; and will be responsible for dose-escalation decisions, with consent from the investigator.  


</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo treatment is an inhaled capsule containing lactose monohydrate with no active substance.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to characterize the safety profile associated with GDC-0214. This will be measured through observation and the severity of any adverse events, change from baseline in vital signs, and laboratory test results</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be reported after any occurrence after the first dose.  Vital signs will be collected at each study visit for part A (visit days 1 through 15). For part B and C they will be collected on visit days (1-17, 21, 28, 35 and 42).  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To characterize the PK profile of GDC 0214, Plasma concentrations of GDC-0214 will be assessed and pharmacokinetic parameters such as through AUC, tmax, Cmax, and half-life will be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To characterize the PK profile of GDC 0214 16 plasma samples will be assessed for GDC-0214 concentrations during the course of the SAD in order to sufficiently characterize PK parameters such as Tmax, Cmax,t1/2, and AUC.  Individual PK parameters will not be assessed at specific time points since they require the totality of the data.  PK will be collected on Day 1 (Pre-dose, 5 min (0.08h), 0.25h, 0.5h, 1h, 2h, 4h, 8h, and 12h). On Day 2 (24h and 36h post-dose). On Day 3 (48hr post-dose).  On Day 4 (72h post-dose) and anytime during visit days 6, 10 and 15.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Key Inclusion Criteria for Healthy Volunteers                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   Signed Informed Consent Form
        Age 18-65 years 
        Body mass index of 18-37 kg/m2 
        Weight of 50-120 kg 
        In good health, determined by no clinically significant findings from medical history, 12-lead ECG, and vital signs.  
        First forced expiratory volume (FEV1) &gt;70 % predicted 
        Forced vital capacity (FVC) &gt;2.0 L 
        Ability to demonstrate sufficient inspiratory effort using the inhaler training
        Ability to comply with the study protocol, including all study procedures
        Agreement to remain abstinent or use contraceptive methods

Key Inclusion Criteria for Patients with Mild Asthma                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      Signed Informed Consent Form
        Age 18-65 years
        Body mass index of 18-37 kg/m2 
        Weight of 50-120 kg
        Documented physician-diagnosed mild asthma for at least 6 months prior to screening, defined as:  Asthma that is controlled with as-needed reliever medication with or without a leukotriene receptor antagonist
       No use of inhaled corticosteroids within 60 days prior to initiation of study drug
        FeNO &gt;40 ppb at screening and at pre-randomization visit
        No clinically significant ECG abnormalities 
        Clinical laboratory evaluations should be within the reference range for the test laboratory unless deemed not clinically significant by the investigator and Sponsor.
        FEV1 &gt;70 % predicted 
        FVC &gt;2.0 L 
        Ability to demonstrate sufficient inspiratory effort using the inhaler training device
        Ability to comply with the study protocol, including all study procedures
        Agreement to remain abstinent or use contraceptive methods</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Key Exclusion Criteria for Healthy Volunteers
Subjects who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from Parts A and B:
        History or clinical manifestations of significant metabolic, hepatic, renal, pulmonary, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, urologic, neurologic, or psychiatric disorders, in the investigators judgment
        History of nasal polyposis or nasal polyps identified during screening physical examination
        History of anaphylaxis, hypersensitivity, or significant drug allergies
        History of severe hypersensitivity to milk proteins
        History or presence of an abnormal ECG that is clinically significant
        Any medical condition or abnormality in clinical laboratory tests that, in the investigators judgment, precludes the subjects safe participation in and completion of the study
        Illicit drug or alcohol abuse within 12 months prior to initiation of study drug
        Positive alcohol screen at screening or pre-randomization
        Recent history of smoking within the 35 days prior to initiation of study drug
        Smokers not able to pass the tobacco-related screening and who cannot refrain from smoking during the study
        Positive urine test for selected drugs of abuse at screening
        Pregnant or breastfeeding, or intending to become pregnant during the study
Women of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test result at screening or pre-randomization.
        Use of any prescription medications and products within 7 days prior to initiation of study drug and throughout the study
        Use of a investigational drug or recent participation in an investigational study 
        Positive for hepatitis panel at screening

Exclusion Criteria for Patients with Mild Asthma
Subjects who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from Part C:
        Any of the exclusion criteria for healthy volunteers above
        Lack of asthma control defined as respiratory symptoms requiring use of a reliever inhaler (e.g., 2 puffs of SABA) more than twice a day on a regular basis within 4 weeks prior to initiation of study drug (not including reliever medication used to prevent symptoms)
        Recent asthma exacerbation requiring oral corticosteroid use or urgent medical care for asthma within 12 weeks prior to initiation of study drug
        Any asthma-related history, symptoms, or findings that precludes the subjects safe participation in and completion of the study in the investigators judgment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/12/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>84</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Genentech, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 DNA Way 
South San Francisco CA, 94080</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Genentech, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 DNA Way 
South San Francisco CA, 94080</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to test the safety of GDC-0214 at different dose levels and to find out what effects, good or bad, GDC-0214 has on volunteers. This study will be conducted in three parts.  Part A and Part B will be in healthy volunteers between the ages of 18 and 65 years and Part C in patients with mild asthma between the ages of 18 and 65 years.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chris Wynne </name>
      <address>Christchurch Clinical Studies Trust
31 Tuam Street, Christchurch, 8011</address>
      <phone>+64 3 372 9478</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research@ccst.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Ryan Ceniceros</name>
      <address>Genentech, Inc.
1 DNA Way, South San Francisco CA 94080</address>
      <phone>+1-650-238-8619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ceniceros.ryan@gene.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hubert Chen</name>
      <address>Genentech, Inc.
1 DNA Way, South San Francisco, CA 94080 </address>
      <phone>+1 650-225-4619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chen.hubert@gene.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Ryan Ceniceros</name>
      <address>1 DNA Way, South San Francisco, CA 94080 </address>
      <phone>+1-650-238-8619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ceniceros.ryan@gene.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>