<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81647">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000054415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Interactions between herbal medicines and the anticoagulant warfarin</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic interactions between herbal medicines (cranberry, garlic, echinacea, policosonal, fish oil, CoEnzyme Q10, Soy, feverfew, milk thistle and evening primrose oil) and the anticoagulant warfarin - Randomised clinical trials in healthy male subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Drug interactions of warfarin with herbal medicines in healthy male subjects. Relevant to Stroke prevention and people receiving warfarin</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2 />
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2 />
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In each 3-treatment cross over clinical trial 2 herbal medicine will be studied. Dosage of the herbal medicines mentioned here are based upon the current information and subject to change in accordence with the latest clinical evidence which will be decided prior to each clinical trial.                                                                                                                                                                     Variations in pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of warfarin will be compared when single dose of 25 mg warfarin given alone orally (control) and when single dose of 25 mg warfarin given after 2 weeks of pre-treatment with each herbal medicine administered orally (intervention).                                                                                                                                                           Herbal medicines intake will be continued for one more week after warfarin administration.                                                                                                                                                                               In total 10 herbs will be studied in 5 clinical trials.                                                                                                                                                                                                               List of the proposed herbs are cranberry (6 X 500mg capsules per day of General Nutrition Corporation (GNC) cranberry juice concentrate capsules), garlic (equivalent to 4 g of fresh garlic), echinacea (4 X 1.27g tablets daily of Medi herb echinacea premium tablets), policosonal (20 mg daily), fish oil (4 g per day), CoEnzyme Q10 (50 mg per day), Soy (3.5 mg per day of phospholipids) , feverfew (100 mg of powdered feverfew daily), Milk thistle (250 mg daily of silymarin) and evening primrose oil (300 mg daily of fixed oil) .</interventions>
    <comparator>Single dose of 25 mg warfarin given alone orally (control)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Studying alterations in pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of S-warfarin.  When warfarin is given alone and when given alone with herbal medicines.  Pharmadynamic variations will be assessed by measuring International Normalised Ratio (INR) from the all the blood samples collected before and after warfarin administration at 8:00 A.M on the days of collection.  Pharmacokinetic variations will be accessed my measuring S-warfarin concentration in plasma from  samples stored at -70 C for all sample points.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples are collected at -24, -48, 0 hr before warfarin administration and 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144 and 168 hr after warfarin adminstration in all the three treatment periods in each trial.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of R-warfarin </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured from the stored blood samples at -70 C for 0 to 168 h sample points after warfarin dosing in all phases. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Platelet aggregation is measure with -24 hr blood sampels collected before warfarin administration in all the three treatment periods.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy subjects not taking other medicines including any supplements, who are non-smokers.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any condition with could effect pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamics of warfarin.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central allocation by study administrator</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer based random number generator</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A series of 5 sub-studies investigating the effect of 2 herbs (given seperately) in each substudy using a 3-treatment cross-over design with 2 weeks pre-treatment and 2 week washout</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Andrew McLachlan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Ken Williams</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will explore the clinical significane of interactions between commonly used herbal medicines with the anti-coagulant warfarin. In total 5 independent three- treatment cross over randomnised clinical trials will be conducted with similar study design. In each trial 2 herbs will be studied.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Commitees of the Univeristy of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>7839</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>7839</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Darlinghurst</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H04/073</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Andrew McLachlan</name>
      <address>Faculty of Pharmacy
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93514452</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93514391</fax>
      <email>andrewm@pharm.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Andrew McLachlan</name>
      <address>Faculty of Pharmacy
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93514452</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93514391</fax>
      <email>andrewm@pharm.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>