<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367541">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001611415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized trial of varenicline (Champix) for the treatment of cognitive and affective symptoms in Huntington's Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized trial of varenicline (Champix) for the treatment of cognitive and affective symptoms in Huntington's Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1163-7565 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>VCAS-HD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Huntington's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomised trial of varenicline using the standard dosing regimen for smoking cessation (Champix, starting dose 0.5mg/day escalating to 2mg/day) in patients with Huntingtons disease (HD).

Bulk study medication will be contained in opaque gel capsules and repackaged into identical compliance packaging by an independent pharmacy according to the randomisation schedule. Sealed envelopes containing the treatment assignment for each subject will be held by a member of the study team who is not involved in patient assessment in case emergency unblinding is required.  

Study medication will be initiated at a dose of 0.5 mg daily for 3 days, increased to 0.5 mg twice daily on days 4-7, and then increased to 2 mg/day on week 2 (the standard anti-smoking regimen).  If adverse events are noted, patients will be permitted to down-titrate by one dose level, which will then be considered their maximal dose. Patients will be maintained at the maximal dose of study medication for 10 weeks.

Varenicline and placebo will be stored at room temperature in the locked stores within the School of Pharmacy.  The School of Pharmacy holds the appropriate licenses to store these medications. 

Compliance for this trial will be defined as 80% of doses taken.   Participants will be asked to bring blister packaging from used medication to each subsequent visit in order to assess doses taken.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo capsules contain methylcellulose</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional performance (UHDRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Functional performance (UHDRS) is assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety assessed by Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Irritability assessed by the Irritability questionnaire (IRQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The frequency, intensity and burden of any reported side effects will be recorded using a standard FIBSER scale at clinic visits and at follow up telephone calls.</outcome>
      <timepoint>FIBSER performed at day 0 (baseline), days 3, 7, weeks 2, 3, 4, 8, 12	, 14 and  16</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive testing (primary outcome). Task  1: motor tapping (hand-eye coordination and manual dexterity), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive testing (primary outcome). Task  2: verbal interference (inhibition of unwanted, well-learned impulsive automatic responses), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cognitive function is assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive testing (primary outcome).  Task 3: Go-No-Go (impulsivity and attention), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cognitive function is assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive testing (primary outcome). Task 4: emotional recognition and recall (basic emotion recognition and discrimination), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cognitive function is assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive testing (primary outcome). Task 5: Switching attention (visuomotor tracking, simple attention). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cognitive function is assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive testing (primary outcome). Task 6: Executive maze (planning, abstraction, foresight, error correction), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cognitive function is assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive testing (primary outcome). Task 7: Spot the Real Word (language comprehension and estimation of premorbid intelligence quotient).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cognitive function is assessed at baseline (visit1) and then again in the final week of  treatment (week 12, visit 2).  Participants are again assessed 4 weeks after  treatment ends (week 16, visit3).  This study design allows investigation of efficacy (visit 2  vs baseline) and whether effects persist during washout (visit 3 vs visit 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age 18 years to 65 years.
2. Non-smoker
3. Outpatients with Huntingtons Disease diagnosed by a movement disorder specialist 
4. Unified Huntingtons Disease Rating Scale (UHDRS) Score between 15-30 
5. Ability to ambulate without assistance.
6. Stable dose of current regular medication for the management of HD symptoms for at  least 30 days prior to trial entry and for the duration of the trial. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity 
2. Female participant who is pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the course of the trial.
3. Significant renal or hepatic impairment.
4. Participant with life expectancy of less than 6 months, or who is inappropriate for placebo medication.
5. Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the Investigator, may either put the participants at risk because of participation in the trial, or may influence the result of the trial, or the participants ability to participate in the trial.
6. Participants who have participated in another research trial involving an investigational product in the past 12 weeks.
7. Patients with a history of substance abuse.
8. Concurrent treatment with any MAOIs, Wellbutrin, antiretroviral medications, immunosupressants, cancer chemotherapy, nicotine patches or nicotine delivery products such as e-cigarettes.
9. Dementia or other psychiatric illness at a level that, in the opinion of the clinician, prevents the patient from giving informed consent (Mini Mental Status Exam score less than 34 and, Addenbrooks Cognitive Examination-Revised (ACE-R) score &lt;65).
10. Presence of psychosis, bipolar disorder, untreated depression (BDI greater than or equal to 21).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Due to the relatively small sample population, randomisation will be balanced for age and gender and stratified based on baseline UHDRS scores.  The allocation of each participant will be noted in individual sealed envelopes and stored in the TMF </concealment>
    <sequence>randomisation of participants to groups at the baseline visit according to the computer generated list </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline comparability of the intervention and control group will be assessed by descriptive analyses of the baseline information collected.
The mean scores and standard deviations together with the total score for each of the cognitive tasks, subscales of UHDRS, HADS and IRQ scores will be reported at every visit they are collected. 
The change from baseline to visit2 and visit3 in each of the primary and secondary outcomes, between the treated and control group will be analysed using mixed model regression. If baseline characteristics are found to be substantially different between the groups, these will be adjusted for in the regression modelling. The primary and secondary main analyses will be conducted on an intention-to-treat (ITT) basis. All statistical analyses will be unadjusted except where indicated.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>11/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>23/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Oakley Mental Health Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Management Accountants Limited
Building 1, Unit A, 100 Bush Road
Rosedale, Auckland 0632
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand Pharmacy Education and Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 10,Grand Arcade Tower 
 16-20 Willis Street 
 Wellington 6011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Huntingtons Disease (HD) is a fatal, inherited neurodegenerative disorder affecting 1:10,000 people in New Zealand. HD is characterized by disorders of movement, cognition, behaviour, and functional capacity. At present there is no clinical treatment to prevent or reduce the onset or progression of HD.
It remains unclear which particular disease mechanisms are important in HD. Post mortem and genetic mouse model studies suggest that impaired cholinergic neurotransmission, through a loss of agonist (acetylcholine) rather than nicotinic receptors may be a significant contributing factor to HD pathology. These observations present a provocative argument that administration of an exogenous agonist may be an effective therapeutic strategy for HD.
The aim of this project is to investigate whether treatment with the nicotine analogue varenicline (Champix) which is currently approved for smoking cessation, can improve cognitive and psychiatric symptoms in patients with mid-late stage HD.
We will undertake a double blind, placebo controlled, randomised study of varenicline (Champix, 1mg twice daily) in patients with Huntingtons disease (HD). Specifically this study will determine whether treatment with varenicline for 12 weeks (1mg twice daily)
1. Improves patients motor function and total functional capacity
2. Improves cognitive performance in computer based tasks which assess learning and memory, attention, impulsiveness and emotional recognition
3.  Improves patients mood and reduces anxiety and irritability

The primary outcomes measure to determine the efficacy of varenicline will be functional outcome and performance in the neurocognitive test battery. Secondary outcome measures will be hospital anxiety and depression (HADS) and irritability (IRQ) clinical rating scales.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>McGregor AL, Dysart J, Tingle MD, Russell BR, Kydd RR, Finucane G
Varenicline improves motor and cognitive symptoms in early Huntington's disease
Neuropsychiatric Disease and Treatment (2016); 12: 23812386 




</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HDEC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/STH/19</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ailsa McGregor</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 4235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ailsa.mcgregor@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ailsa McGregor</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 4235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ailsa.mcgregor@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ailsa McGregor</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 4235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ailsa.mcgregor@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ailsa McGregor</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 4235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ailsa.mcgregor@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>