<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335637">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000216910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Chronotherapy (timed ingestion of medicine) for high blood pressure in patients with obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blinded, randomised, placebo-controlled, crossover study to assess the efficacy of morning or bed-time Perindopril (10mg) to treat hypertension in adult patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CH-OSA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>n/a</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following screening, patients on Angiotensin Converting Enzyme Inhibitors (ACE-i) or Angiotensin Receptor Blockers (ARBs) will undertake a washout period of 3 weeks.

All patients will then undergo a run-in period with perindopril 10mg (morning dose) to ensure medication tolerability.  The run in period will be 1 week for those previously taking ACE-i, 2 weeks for those previously on ARBs, and 4 weeks for all patients.

Patients will then be randomised to one of two anti-hypertensive treatment orders for 6 weeks and then cross over to the alternative order. The two treatment orders are.

Treatment Order 1: Perindopril 10 mg morning dose and placebo bedtime dose 
Treatment Order 2: Placebo morning dose and Perindopril 10mg bedtime dose

There is no washout period between the two treatment orders.

Following completion of both treatment orders, patients will continue with their last allocated anti-hypertensive treatment order (1 or 2) and also receive Continous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) treatment in an open label design for 8 weeks. CPAP will be delivered via a nasal mask and the pressure will be individually titrated during an in-laboratory pressure determination study prior to commencement of 8 weeks CPAP therapy. The pressure will be titrated to a level that fully prevents apnoeas and hypopneas and normalizes breathing during sleep. During the 8 weeks of CPAP treatment, patients will be encouraged to use the device every night for the entire sleep period. </interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo pill will be produced by the same manufacturer (Servier) as the active drug. The placebo tablet will be identical to the active tablet except that the active ingredient will not be added</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nigh time systolic blood pressure (determined from 24-hour ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM) in Obstructive Sleep Apnoea patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), visit 5 (End of Treatment Arm 1,week 10) visit 6 (End of Treatment Arm 2,week 16) Visit 7 (End of CPAP Arm week 24)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine the changes in other Blood Pressure indices (24 hour, daytime, night time and office Blood Pressure) and, arterial stiffness and central Blood Pressure (using Pulse Wave Analysis).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), visit 5 (End of Treatment Arm 1, week 10) visit 6 (End of Treatment Arm 2, week 16) Visit 7 (End of CPAP Arm, week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explanatory/Efficacy outcome: Pharmacokinetics. The phramocokinetics of the study drug perindopril will be investigated over a 24 hour period in a small subgroup of patients. This will help explain any differences in antihypertensive effects observed between a morning and evening dose before and after the addition of CPAP treatment for sleep apnoea.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pharmacokinetics will be examined across 24 hours at the end of the drug treatment arm (6 weeks morning versus 6 weeks evening dose) and then after 2 months treatment with CPAP.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The maximum age is 65 years as stated below. This amendment was approved by the ethics committee on 01/06/2011.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy.
Abnormal renal function or chronic kidney disease indicated by any of 
1. raised creatinine (&gt;110umol/L)
2. raised potassium (&gt;5.0 mmol/L)
3. low eGFR (&lt;60ml/min/1.73m2)
Severe hypertension (SBP&gt;=180 and/or DBP&gt;=110)
Drug resistant hypertension defined as taking more than 3 classes of BP medication
Normal Office BP (&lt; 140/90 mmHg) whilst taking anti-hypertensive medication that does not include an ACE or ARB.
ACE Inhibitor intolerance (based on the opinion of participants and study physicians) indicated by the development of new cough or symptoms of hypotension (dizziness).
Unwilling to undergo washout of ACE or ARB medication.
Shift workers who rotate to night shift.
Poorly controlled diabetes defined as Glycosolated Haemoglobin (HbA1c) &gt;=8.
Unstable Angina / Heart Failure (NYHA Class III and IV)/ Stroke.
Recent (&lt; 6 months) AMI or Revascularisation Procedure.
Significant Arrhythmia or Atrial Fibrillation.
Cognitive impairment / Psychiatric disorder / Physically unable to participate.
Recent OSA treatment with Mandibular Advancement Splint or CPAP exposure (within 3 months of screening) or prior refusal of CPAP treatment.
Severe OSA (minimum oxygen saturation &lt; 65% or RDI &gt; 80) or excessively sleepy patients at increased risk for driving-related accidents requiring immediate treatment.
More than 20% of AHI with central apnoeas.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After informed and written consent, patients will be sequentially enrolled according to a randomised list generated via a computer program by a third party who had no involvement in the trial. The outcome of which will result in sequentially numbered drug packs being distributed to sequentially enrolled subjects. Each subject will be randomised to one of the two treatment orders:
1. Perindopril morning and Placebo evening or 
2. Placebo morning and Perindopril evening and then crossing over to the alternative order. 
This final order will continue with an additional arm of CPAP treatment in OSA patients.</concealment>
    <sequence>The treatment sequence was according to a randomised, block design. It was computer generated using a SAS program utilising the RANUNI function and a random seed.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/11/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/01/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>82</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>85</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr C Phillips - Principle Investigator</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept Respiratory &amp; Sleep Medicine Level 8, Acute Services Building, Royal North Shore Hospital St Leonards NSW 2065 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke St Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the study is to investigate the efficacy of chronotherapy (altering ingestion time of study medication Perindopril) to improve and provide a better overall control of hypertension in patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnoea.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.woolcock.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hawkesbury Ethics Review Committee of Northern Sydney Central Coast Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office Level 2, Building 51, Royal North Shore Hospital, Pacific Hwy, ST Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/HARBR/51</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/03/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Craig Phillips</name>
      <address>The Woolcock institute of medical research
 431 Glebe Point Rd Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91140301</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91140011</fax>
      <email>craig.phillips@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasmina Djavadkhani</name>
      <address>The Woolcock institute of medical research
 431 Glebe Point Rd Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61291140414</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91140011</fax>
      <email>chosa@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Craig Phillips</name>
      <address>The Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
 431 Glebe Point Rd Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91140301</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91140411</fax>
      <email>craig.phillips@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Craig Phillips</name>
      <address>Dept Respiratory &amp; Sleep Medicine, Level 8, Acute Services Building, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards NSW 2065, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 94632936</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>craig.phillips@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>