<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362789">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000786897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cannabis Screening and Feedback</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of Online Cannabis Screening and Feedback in Promoting Treatment-Seeking and Reductions in Cannabis Use: Comparison of Brief Versus Extended Feedback</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-8491</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cannabis use</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention condition involves an online cannabis screening program with extended feedback and advice.  Participants are asked a series of questions about their recent cannabis use, dependence and abuse symptoms, motives for using and consequences of use, treatment seeking, health consequences, and perceived cannabis use norms. Personalised feedback and advice addressing all of these issues is then provided (e.g., the individual receives advice relating to his or her specific motives for using cannabis). Participation in the intervention takes about an hour.</interventions>
    <comparator>The participant receives the same screening questions, but much briefer feedback and advice.  Participation in the control condition takes about 45 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information/treatment seeking.  The questions will be asked in an online questionnaire, accessed via an email link one month after participating in the intervention. Some of the questions are specifically designed for the study; others are established questionnaires (Treatment Readiness Tool, General Help-Seeking Questionnaire).</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Past-month cannabis use (frequency and quantity). This will be assessed at baseline as part of the screening program, and again in the one-month follow-up assessment.  The Timeline Followback procedure will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and one month post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Past-month cannabis dependence/abuse symptoms, assessed at baseline and one month.  The GAIN-1, Severity of Dependence Scale, and components of the Cannabis Problems Questionnaire will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and one month post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with the program will be assessed in the one-month post-intervention assessment. Some of the questions are specifically designed for the study; others are established questionnaires (Satisfaction and Usability Survey, Client Satisfaction Questionnaire).</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18 years or older.

Cannabis use in the last month.

At least one symptom of cannabis abuse or dependence.

Having email</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under 18 years old.

No cannabis use in the last month.

No symptoms of cannabis abuse or dependence.

No email address.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study will be adverstised using various methods, primarily Google.  Study advertisements will provide a direct link to the screening program.  The National Cannabis Prevention and Information Centre (NCPIC) website will also contain  a direct link to the program.  The program will include initial questions and brief feedback for all individuals who access the site. Only individuals who meet the inclusion criteria as deterined by these initial questions will be offered a place in the study. This will all be determined automatically with no human involvement.  The study information sheet informs participants that they will be randomly assigned to receive either brief or extended feedback on their cannabis use.  The program will randomly assign participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>The program will randomly assign participants. Simple randomisation using computer sequence generation will be employed.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Cannabis Prevention and Information Centre (NCPIC)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 684
Randwick
NSW, 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848,
Canberra ACT 2601, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study is to compare the effects of brief vesus extended feedback and advice in promoting cannabis help/information seeking and assisting individiuals to reduce their cannabis use.

Hypotheses:
Relative to individuals who receive brief feedback, individuals who receive extended feedback will report (a) more information-seeking and help-seeking, (b) greater reductions in past-month cannabis use, (c) greater reductions in past-month cannabis dependence symptoms, (d) greater reductions in past-month cannabis abuse symptoms, and (e) greater satisfaction with the screening/feedback program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not yet established.</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW HREC
Kensington NSW
2033
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC11328</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sally Rooke</name>
      <address>PO Box 684
Randwick 
NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0450</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rooke@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sally Rooke</name>
      <address>PO Box 684
Randwick 
NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0450</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rooke@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sally Rooke</name>
      <address>PO Box 684
Randwick 
NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0450</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rooke@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>