<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83794">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000424202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The MOVE study: Improving maternal and child health nurse care for vulnerable mothers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Improving maternal and child health (MCH) nurse care through an enhanced model of MCH nurse care for mothers experiencing intimate partner violence (IPV), compared with standard MCH nurse care, in order to improve disclosure, referral to appropriate services, and increased satisfaction with MCH nursing care by MCH clients experiencing partner violence.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MOVE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intimate Partner Violence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In the first six months of the study, results of a systematic review of evidence informing current models of nurse family/intimate partner violence care will be integrated with action research by four nurses within their teams, with the goal of consensus (using AGREE Collaboration (2003) guidelines) of a new recommended model. Informed by Normalisation Process Theory to improve sustainability, this good practice model of screening and care (to be developed) will include training, clinical guidelines and recommended pathways, documentation and standards of care which will be advocated by the nurse scholars into their teams' practice. The intervention will be trialed for twelve months .The model of screening and care refers to family violence (FV) which includes intimate partner violence but is the term used by the Victorian government. Mandated screening questions also asked about the safety of children.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care, means that the four comparison nurse teams will screen to identify their clients experiencing family violence and refer to recommended family violence or other community services as necessary. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved family violence (FV) disclosure/safety planning is measured firstly by routine data of nurse reported FV safety planning rates. These are computer data that MCH teams are required to report to government as our assumption was that safety planning would occur after disclosure. We would also examine reported disclosure by survey. </outcome>
      <timepoint>15 months after intervention (31st March 2010-April 1 2011) we collected the previous year's FV routine data for all eight teams. We also collected routine data for 24 months (April 2013) after intervention completion to see whether the FV screening and care intervention was sustainable without the involvement of research staff or a trial setting.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>FV screening rates measured by routine reported government data </outcome>
      <timepoint>15 months (three months after the end of the intervention period. Routine reported government FV data were also then re-examined at 24 months to check sustainability</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved referral by MCH nurses of their clients experiencing family violence to appropriate services. This will be assessed by assessing differences in proportions of routinely reported referral rates by arm. As MCH nurses are required to report FV referral data to government, we collected these routine data from all 8 teams, as well as by questions about referral from a survey of women attending MCH centres who have given birth in the preceding twelve months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>We collected routine government reporting data at the end of the intervention (April 2011) and again in 2013 (for April 2011-2012 and April 2012-2013).

We sent a survey to over 10,000 women once after the end of the intervention 15 months after the commencement of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved client satisfaction with MCH nurse care, which will be assessed by asking women clients in the surveys outlined above.</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 months (5000 surveys) and 21 months (second 5000) after commencement of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>MCH nurse teams in the north west Melbourne suburbs</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>MCH nurse teams previously enrolled in the MOtherS' Advocates In the Community (MOSAIC) trial were invited to participate further in the 'Improving MCH nurse care for Vulnerable mothers (MOVE) study. The eight MCH nurse team clusters had previously been randomised using sealed opaque envelopes selected from a container by an independent person. Nurse teams agreed to a reverse randomisation. That is, MCH nurse intervention teams in MOSAIC would become comparison teams in the MOVE study and vice versa.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified allocation. MCH nurse teams were randomised according to numbers of births in the LGA as outlined in MOSAIC. We have reversed the randomisation outcome for this study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Teams have been allocated to either implement the new 'enhanced' model of care with comparison teams allocated to 'usual care' - that is, identification of clients as usual and referral to community based agencies if necessary.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The target sample size for women clients attending MCH centres in the eight teams was the number seen  in each arm over 12 months. This was estimated to be 22,000 in either arm. 
Routine data for screening, safety planning and referrals made by MCH nurses targeted the whole population of women with babies=&lt;12 months seeing MCH nurses in the intervention period. 
For the postal survey of women clients in the 8 MCH teams, we calculated that for an 8-10% IPV prevalence rate in the previous 12 months we could detect a predicted increase of 15% average disclosure taking into account the numbers of births in participating councils, the likely response fraction (55-65%) and also adjusted for an intra-cluster correlation of 0.02. Analysis using
multivariable logistic regression adjusted for cluster</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/06/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/06/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>44000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3018</postcode>
    <postcode>3337</postcode>
    <postcode>3058</postcode>
    <postcode>3011</postcode>
    <postcode>3072</postcode>
    <postcode>3083</postcode>
    <postcode>3121</postcode>
    <postcode>3021</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>BUNDOORA  VIC  3083</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2702
Canberra 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Social Work, University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>MELBOURNE  VIC  3010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Angela Taft</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Judith Lumley Centre
215 Franklin Street
Melbourne, VIC 3000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Rhonda Small</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Judith Lumley Centre
215 Franklin Street
Melbourne, VIC 3000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Cathy Humphreys</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Alfred Felton Chair in Child and Family Welfare Social Work
University of Melbourne 
Melbourne Victoria 3010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Kelsey Hegarty</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of General Practice
University of Melbourne
PARKVILLE  VIC  3053</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>MOVE aims to develop and evaluate an innovative model of care for MCH nurses to identify partner violence early and promote the safety of new mothers and their babies.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.latrobe.edu.au/jlc/research/reducing-violence-against-women-and-children/move</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>BUNDOORA  VIC  3083</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/08/0142</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/83794-Protocol091.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Angela Taft</name>
      <address>Judith Lumley Centre
215 Franklin St , Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>61 3 9479 8809</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8341 8555</fax>
      <email>a.taft@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Angela taft</name>
      <address>Judith Lumley Centre
215 Franklin St , Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>61 3 9479 8809</phone>
      <fax>NA</fax>
      <email>a.taft@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Angela taft</name>
      <address>Judith Lumley Centre
215 Franklin St , Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>61 3 9479 8809</phone>
      <fax>NA</fax>
      <email>a.taft@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Angela Taft</name>
      <address>Judith Lumley Centre
215 Franklin St , Melbourne
VIC 3000
</address>
      <phone>61 3 9479 8809</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.taft@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>