<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363281">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001210864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can using nicotine as a long-term substitute enhance smoking cessation over using it only as a cessation aid?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open-label randomised pragmatic policy trial examining effectiveness of short-term use of Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT) vs short- or long-term use of NRT vs short- or long-term use of NRT or electronic nicotine delivery systems for smoking cessation in cigarette smokers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1137-0793</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tobacco Addiction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Smoking cessation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Condition A (Comparator): Participants in this condition will receive: 1) A factsheet that explains the relative harmfulness of NRT compared to cigarettes; 2) A free sample of NRT products (1-2 days supply of choice of any three of gum, lozenge, inhaler or mouthspray) and instructions for use of the products. Participants will be told the products are designed to help them quit, and that the recommended use is for 8-12 weeks. Advice on recommended dose will be provided and the amount supplied for free will be determined from the participants cigarette intake and the recommended dosage schedule. However, participants will be able to use their discretion as to their individual dose. Participants may choose one of the products or a combination of two to use for a quit attempt; 3) Approximately three weeks worth of the participant's chosen NRT product (or a combination of two products, if this is their preference) will be supplied for free; and 4) Access to these products for a further 6 months at a price that reflects their lower harmfulness compared to cigarettes (ie significantly cheaper than retail price of cigarettes and lower than current retail prices for NRT). These purchases will be made via a secure website controlled by the research team. Condition B: Participants in this condition will receive: 1) A factsheet that explains the relative harmfulness of NRT compared to cigarettes similar to that provided for Condition A, but with further information on the benefits of both options (short term quit aid or long-term substitute) compared to smoking. It will emphasise complete cessation as the best option from a health perspective; 2) A free sample of NRT products (1-2 days supply of choice of any three of gum, lozenge, inhaler or mouthspray) and instructions for use of the products. Participants will be told how to use the products as a short term quitting aid (recommended use for 8-12 weeks), but also encouraged to continue using the product if they find they need to in order to refrain from smoking. Advice on recommended dose will be provided and the amount supplied for free will be determined from the participants cigarette intake and the recommended dosage schedule. However, participants will be able to use their discretion as to their individual dose. Participants may choose one of the products or a combination of two to use for a quit attempt; 3) Approximately three weeks worth of the participant's chosen NRT product (or a combination of two products, if this is their preference) will be supplied for free; and 4) Access to these products for a further 6 months at a price that reflects their lower harmfulness compared to cigarettes (ie significantly cheaper than retail price of cigarettes and lower than current retail prices for NRT). These purchases will be made via a secure website controlled by the research team. Condition C: Participants in this condition will receive: 1) A factsheet that explains the relative harmfulness of NRT compared to cigarettes with information on the benefits of both options (short term quit aid or long-term substitute) compared to smoking similar to that provided for Condition B, but with additional details on the risk profile of Electronic Nicotine Delivery Systems compared to both NRT and stopping all nicotine use. It will emphasise complete cessation as the best option from a health perspective; 2) A free sample of 1-2 days supply each of up to four products and instructions for use of the products. Participants may select from NRT products (gum, lozenge, inhaler, mouthspray) and an electronic nicotine delivery system. Participants will be told how to use the products as a short term quitting aid (recommended use for 8-12 weeks), but also encouraged to continue using the product if they find they need to in order to refrain from smoking. Advice on recommended dose will be provided and the amount supplied for free will be determined from the participants cigarette intake and the recommended dosage schedule. However, participants will be able to use their discretion as to their individual dose. Participants may choose one of the products or a combination of two to use for a quit attempt; 3) Approximately three weeks worth of the participant's chosen NRT product (or a combination of two products, if this is their preference) will be supplied for free; and 4) Access to these products for a further 6 months at a price that reflects their lower harmfulness compared to cigarettes (ie significantly cheaper than retail price of cigarettes and lower than current retail prices for NRT). These purchases will be made via a secure website controlled by the research team.</interventions>
    <comparator>Condition A (Comparator): Participants in this condition will receive: 1) A factsheet that explains the relative harmfulness of NRT compared to cigarettes; 2) A free sample of NRT products (1-2 days supply of choice of up to three of gum, lozenge, inhaler and mouthspray) and instructions for use of the products. Participants will be told the products are designed to help them quit, and that the recommended use is for 8-12 weeks. Advice on recommended dose will be provided and the amount supplied for free will be determined from the participants cigarette intake and the recommended dosage schedule. However, participants will be able to use their discretion as to their individual dose. Participants may choose one of the products or a combination of two to use for a quit attempt; 3) Approximately three weeks worth of the participant's chosen NRT product (or a combination of two products, if this is their preference) will be supplied for free; and 4) Access to these products for a further 6 months at a price that reflects their lower harmfulness compared to cigarettes (ie significantly cheaper than retail price of cigarettes and lower than current retail prices for NRT). These purchases will be made via a secure website controlled by the research team.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage in each Condition who have continuous abstinence (not smoked for 6 months or more) with or without current/recent NRT or electronic nicotine delivery system use, measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage in each Condition who have continuous smoking abstinence for 6 months or more with no NRT or electronic nicotine delivery system use for 3 months or more, measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>seven-day point prevalence abstinence measures of the above primary outcomes, measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of each Condition concurrently using NRT and cigarettes, the quantity of each consumed, their interest in quitting smoking, and interest in eventually quitting all NRT, measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of Condition C concurrently using the electronic nicotine delivery system and tobacco cigarettes, the quantity of each consumed, their interest in quitting smoking, and interest in eventually quitting all use, measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The quantity of cigarettes consumed by current smokers as a function of NRT or electronic nicotine delivery system use in each Condition, and their interest in quitting smoking, measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of each Condition that order a trial product, what product is ordered, the amount used over what period, measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team) and a review of products sent to the participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportions of each Condition that make a quit attempt and length of all quit attempts made (both from smoking and all nicotine use), measured by self-report through questionnaires (questions developed by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Current daily smokers (at least 6 cigarettes/day); ability to read and understand English; agree to receive samples of nicotine products and to try the samples; and willing to complete surveys over 12 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Currently being treated for Serious cardiovascular disease (eg heart disease, stroke), Cancer, A mental health condition that is being treated with regular medication, High blood pressure that is not controlled, Have a stomach ulcer, Have kidney or liver disease, Have an overactive thyroid or adrenal gland cancer, Use insulin for diabetes, Have asthma or chronic throat disease, pregnant or planning to become pregnant or expecting to be breastfeeding within the next 12 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Current smokers will be recruited from a commercial market research panel and sent an invitation to participate in the trial with a URL link to the online screening questionnaire.  Eligibility will be determined by a computer based on their answers to the screening questionnaire. 

Eligible participants will be required to confirm consent and then complete a baseline survey on smoking history, health status and quitting intentions. They will then be automatically randomised to one of the three conditions (A, B or C) by a computer generated random number sequence. IE allocation will be concealed as it will be an automated process performed by a computer. Participants will only be provided with information that is relevant to their allocated condition.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random number sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>23/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1563</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>17/12/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UQ Centre for Clinical Research
The University of Queensland
Building 71/918
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Site
Herston Qld 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Cancer Council Victoria</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Cancer Council Victoria
100 Drummond St
Carlton Vic 3053</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Wayne Hall</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>UQ Centre for Clinical Research
The University of Queensland
Building 71/918
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Site
Herston Qld 4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Jan Barendregt</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Population Health
University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Chris Bullen</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>National Institute for Health Innovation
Level 4, School of Population Health
Tamaki Campus
The University of Auckland
261 Morrin Road
Glen Innes Auckland 1072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Natalie Walker</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>National Institute for Health Innovation
Level 4, School of Population Health
Tamaki Campus
The University of Auckland
261 Morrin Road
Glen Innes Auckland 1072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>	Many smokers who try to quit fail in their attempt. Medicinal nicotine is currently only used as a short-term quit aid. This trial will test if offering smokers the option of using these products as long-term substitutes for cigarettes will help more smokers to successfully quit. We will also determine if offering smokers electronic nicotine delivery systems in addition to medicinal nicotine products further increases the number of smokers who quit successfully.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Human Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics
Research Management Office
UQ Research and Innovation
Cumbrae-Stewart Building (#72)
The University of Queensland
BRISBANE  QLD  4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012001117</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Coral Gartner</name>
      <address>UQ Centre for Clinical Research
The University of Queensland
Building 71/918 
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Site
Herston Qld 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33465478</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 5598</fax>
      <email>c.gartner@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Doug Fraser</name>
      <address>UQ Centre for Clinical Research
The University of Queensland
Building 71/918 
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Site
Herston Qld 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33465475</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 5598</fax>
      <email>d.fraser2@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Coral Gartner</name>
      <address>UQ Centre for Clinical Research
The University of Queensland
Building 71/918 
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Site
Herston Qld 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33465478</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 5598</fax>
      <email>c.gartner@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Coral Gartner</name>
      <address>UQCCR, Building 71/918 RBWH Site, The University of Queensland, Herston Qld 4029</address>
      <phone>61 7 33465478</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 5598</fax>
      <email>c.gartner@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>