<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343458">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000969965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>EXTEND-IA: Extending the time for Thrombolysis in Emergency Neurological Deficits - Intra-Arterial, a randomised trial of clot retrieval after intravenous thrombolysis in ischemic stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial of intra-arterial reperfusion therapy after standard dose intravenous t-PA within 4.5 hours of ischemic stroke onset utilizing dual target vessel occlusion and penumbral mismatch imaging selection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1124-4509</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EXTEND-IA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov NCT01492725</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ischemic stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intra-arterial mechanical clot retrieval with the Solitaire device after patients have received standard therapy with intravenous tissue plasminogen activator (tPA). Clot retrieval involves cerebral angiography and takes approximately 2 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard dose 0.9mg/kg (max 90mg) intravenous tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) administered once as a bolus (10%) followed by infusion over 1 hour (90%).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reperfusion at 24 hours (CT or MR perfusion imaging)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post stroke onset</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Favourable clinical response (National Institutes of Health Stroke Score - NIHSS - reduction &gt;/= 8 points or reaching 0-1) at 3 days</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 days post stroke onset</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reperfusion at 24 hrs post stroke without symptomatic intracerebral hemorrhage (CT or MR perfusion imaging)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post stroke onset</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recanalisation at 24 hrs post stroke (CT or MR angiography)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post stroke onset</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infarct growth within 24 hrs (CT and MRI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post stroke onset</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke severity (NIHSS) at 24 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post stroke onset</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptomatic intra-cranial hemorrhage (ECASS type 2 parenchymal hematoma on CT or MRI combined with &gt;/=4 point deterioration in NIHSS within 36 hours of treatment).</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 36 hours of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death due to any cause</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) 0-1 at 3 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Categorical shift in mRS at 3 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NIHSS reduction 8 points or reaching 0-1 at 3 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Rankin Scale (mRS) 0-2 at 3 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients presenting with anterior circulation acute ischaemic stroke eligible using standard criteria to receive IV tPA within 4.5 hours of stroke onset
2. Patient, family member or legally responsible person depending on local ethics requirements has given informed consent
3. Patient's age is &gt;/=18 years
4. Intra-arterial clot retrieval treatment can commence (groin puncture) within 6 hours of stroke onset.
Imaging inclusion criteria
Dual target:
5. Arterial occlusion on CTA or MRA of the ICA, M1 or M2
6. Mismatch - Using CT or MRI with a Tmax &gt;6 second delay perfusion volume and either CT-rCBF or DWI infarct core volume. 
a) Mismatch ratio of greater than 1.2, and 
b) Absolute mismatch volume of greater than 10 ml, and
c) Infarct core lesion volume of less than 70mL</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Intracranial haemorrhage (ICH) identified by CT or MRI
2. Rapidly improving symptoms at the discretion of the investigator
3. Pre-stroke mRS score of &gt;/= 2 (indicating previous disability)
4. Inability to access the cerebral vasculature in the opinion of the neurointerventional team
5. Contra indication to imaging with MR with contrast agents
6. Participation in any investigational study in the previous 30 days
7. Any terminal illness such that patient would not be expected to survive more than 1 year
8. Any condition that, in the judgment of the investigator could impose hazards to the patient if study therapy is initiated or affect the participation of the patient in the study.
9. Pregnant women (clinically evident)
10. Previous stroke within last three months
11. Recent past history or clinical presentation of ICH, subarachnoid haemorrhage (SAH), arterio-venous (AV) malformation, aneurysm, or cerebral neoplasm. At the discretion of each Investigator.
12. Current use of oral anticoagulants and a prolonged prothrombin time (INR &gt; 1.6)
13. Use of heparin, except for low dose subcutaneous heparin, in the previous 48 hours and a prolonged activated partial thromboplastin time exceeding the upper limit of the local laboratory normal range.
14. Use of glycoprotein IIb - IIIa inhibitors within the past 72 hours. Use of single or dual agent oral platelet inhibitors (clopidogrel and/or or low-dose aspirin) prior to study entry is permitted.
15. Clinically significant hypoglycaemia.
16. Uncontrolled hypertension defined by a blood pressure &gt; 185 mmHg systolic or &gt;110 mmHg diastolic on at least 2 separate occasions at least 10 minutes apart, or requiring aggressive treatment to reduce the blood pressure to within these limits. The definition of aggressive treatment is left to the discretion of the responsible Investigator.
17. Hereditary or acquired haemorrhagic diathesis
18. Gastrointestinal or urinary bleeding within the preceding 21 days
19. Major surgery within the preceding 14 days which poses risk in the opinion of the investigator.
20. Exposure to a thrombolytic agent within the previous 72 hours</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients presenting to the emergency department with acute ischaemic stroke, who are eligible for standard intravenous tPA therapy within 4.5 hours of stroke onset will be assessed for “dual target” major vessel occlusion and mismatch to determine their eligibility for randomisation into the trial. If the patient gives informed consent they will be randomised 50:50 using central computerised allocation to intra-arterial clot retrieval after IV tPA or IV tPA alone. The trial is prospective, randomised, open-label, blinded endpoint (PROBE) design.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization scheme will be based on permuted blocks to promote both group and sequential balance. Randomized patients will be stratified by site of baseline arterial occlusion into one of three groups:
1. Internal carotid artery (ICA) occlusion
2. Proximal middle cerebral artery (MCA – M1) occlusion
3. Distal middle cerebral artery (MCA – M2) occlusion</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/10/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Brain Centre
245 Burgundy Street
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A prospective, randomised, open-label, blinded endpoint phase II trial to test the hypothesis that anterior circulation ischaemic stroke patients, selected with dual target vessel occlusion and CT or MRI mismatch within 4.5 hours of onset will have improved reperfusion and early neurological improvement when treated with intra-arterial clot retrieval (Solitaire device) after intravenous tPA, compared to intravenous tPA alone. Planned recruitment of 100 patients, randomised 50:50 at approximately 12 centres in Australia and New Zealand.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NA</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/MH/247</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Bruce Campbell</name>
      <address>Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 8427</fax>
      <email>bruce.campbell@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Bruce Campbell</name>
      <address>Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 8427</fax>
      <email>bruce.campbell@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Bruce Campbell</name>
      <address>Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 8427</fax>
      <email>bruce.campbell@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bruce Campbell</name>
      <address>Royal Melbourne Hospital Grattan St Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 8427</fax>
      <email>bruce.campbell@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>