<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369987">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000180415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of an education package for increasing glaucoma knowledge and reducing anxiety in newly diagnosed glaucoma patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of an education package for increasing glaucoma knowledge and reducing anxiety in newly diagnosed glaucoma patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Glaucoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Education to newly diagnosed patients with glaucoma about the nature of the condition, treatment and daily management of treatment regimens.

Education is administered on individualised one-to-one sessions over the telephone via trained health professionals. This is a one off telephone session lasting 30 minutes. This telephone session is followed up 2-3 days later by a mail-out package of information booklets regarding the nature of glaucoma and some common issues regarding its treatment. The overall duration of the intervention period is 4 weeks, during which the telephone session and the mail-out occurs in the first 1-2 weeks. Completion of the telephone interview and mail out is recorded by study staff to ensure adherence to the intervention for all cases in the intervention arm of the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group do not receive this education during the study, however receive the education once the study period is complete (4-5 weeks)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in score achieved on Glaucoma Knowledge Questionnaire (difference between baseline and final questionnaires, the latter administered 4 weeks following completion of baseline questionnaires)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 4 weeks post baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in score achieved on the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Score (difference between baseline and final questionnaires, the latter administered 4 weeks following completion of baseline questionnaires)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 4 weeks post baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in score achieved on the Eye Drop and Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 4 weeks post baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Can read, speak and comprehend English  or have the service of a valid interpreter
New diagnosis of open angle glaucoma
Glaucoma is treated with topical intraocular pressure-lowering drops</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Recent ocular surgery (in the past 2 months)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation of the randomised sequence will be recorded onto individual sheets of paper sealed in an opaque envelope; this will be the only record of the sequence. The envelopes will be opened by the study investigators individually and sequentially following enrolment of the study, and prior to data collection, and will be used to sequentially assign participants to the study groups.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation will occur using a randomly generated sequence allocating participants on a 1:1 ratio. This sequence and the randomisation process will be concealed from the investigators enrolling participants. A computerised process will be used to generate a random sequence of numbers that fall into 2 categories; these will be respectively assigned to the control and treatment arms. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Power calculations were performed as follows. A significance level (alpha) of 5% and a power (1- beta) of 80% were chosen for two-tailed, non-paired student t test to compare final results in the glaucoma knowledge questionnaire. Predicted mean scores and standard deviation for the two groups were based on previous data.

Based on previous data the effect of education administration can be estimated to raise the score on the Glaucoma Knowledge Questionnaire by 9-12%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parkville VIC 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Carr Family Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>37 Framont Avenue
HOLLAND PARK  QLD  4121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>none</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We aim to investigate the impact of a telephone-based education schemes for newly diagnosed patients with glaucoma. Newly diagnosed glaucoma patients treated with drops are randomised to either the control or treatment arm. All have questionnaires administered over the telephone at the study outset and at completion, 4 weeks following the outset. The questionnaires include a Glaucoma-knowledge Questionnaire, an anxiety scale and an Eye Drop Satisfaction Questionnaire.

Patients in the intervention arm will receive the education in the first week of the study period. THose in the control arm will only receive that information once the study is completed. We will measure differences in changes of scores from outset to conclusion of the study looking for differences between the intervention and control groups.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Ophthalmology Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>94-98 Chalmers St, Surry Hills NSW 2010
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>48.14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Skalicky</name>
      <address>Melbourne Eye Care
338 Balaclava Rd Caulfield North VIC 3161</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9509 9293</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9509 9911</fax>
      <email>sskalicky@eyesurgery.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Skalicky</name>
      <address>Melbourne Eye Care
338 Balaclava Rd Caulfield North VIC 3161</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9509 9293</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9509 9911</fax>
      <email>sskalicky@eyesurgery.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Skalicky</name>
      <address>Melbourne Eye Care
338 Balaclava Rd Caulfield North VIC 3161</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9509 9293</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9509 9911</fax>
      <email>sskalicky@eyesurgery.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>