<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366288">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000754640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Oral paracetamol versus intravenous Ibuprofen for the treatment of patent Ductus arteriosus in premature infants: A Pilot Randomised Trial (The OVID Trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Patent Ductus Arteriosus in preterm infants treated by oral paracetamol versus intravenous ibuprofen and ductal closure.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The OVID Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patent ductus arteriosus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prematurity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Paracetamol: 15 mg/kg administered every 6 hours for a total of 3 days via nasogastric tube. This is defined as a treatment course of paracetamol.</interventions>
    <comparator>Ibuprofen: 10 mg/kg intravenously, followed by 5 mg/kg 24 hours and 48 hours later. This is defined as a treatment course of ibuprofen.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PDA closure OR reduction in size by &gt;50%; assessed by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours after completion of first medical treatment course</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of PDA closure after the first course of medical treatment, assessed by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours after completion of first medical treatment course</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Size of PDA after the first course of medical treatment, assessed by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours after completion of first medical treatment course</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of PDA closure after the second course of medical treatment, assessed by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours after completion of the second medical treatment course</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for re-treatment or surgical ligation after 2 completed courses of medical treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>During NICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestation: &lt; 30 weeks completed gestation
Post-natal age of greater than or equal to 7 days OR following the second routine cranial ultrasound assessment
Clinical suspicion of a haemodynamically significant PDA
Active praecordium, loud murmur or wide pulse pressure
The need for respiratory support (defined as CPAP/NIMV/IMV/HFO) with FiO2 of greater than or equal to  30%. These infants should have an echocardiographic assessment to confirm the presence of PDA
Echocardiographic evidence of either:
Significant left-to-right shunting across PDA (hsDA score of of greater than or equal to 6) comprising transductal diameter, velocity and left atrial aortic root ratio (10) OR 
A composite score of of greater than or equal to 16 based on our earlier publication
Infant is on minimal enteral feed defined as of greater than or equal to 10ml/kg/day</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>10</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Major congenital abnormalities
Severe intraventricular haemorrhage (IVH) (grade 3 or 4)
Evidence of coagulation dysfunction: Platelet count &lt; 100,000/microlitre or presence of blood in endotracheal/gastric aspirate, haematuria
Intrauterine growth restriction defined as &lt;3rd centile and/or reverse end diastolic flow on antenatal Dopplers.
Echocardiographic evidence of significant right-to-left shunting across PDA
Elevated serum creatinine &gt; 100 micromol/L
Concerns about abdominal problems (feeding intolerance aspirates &gt; feeding volume, bilious colour, abdominal distension)
Life threatening sepsis
Urine output of less than 1ml/kg/hour during the preceding 8 hours
Evidence of liver dysfunction or hyperbilirubinaemia requiring exchange transfusion
Decision not-to-treat by the attending neonatologist</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation of patients to treatment arm will be concealed at all times from the treating team, as it will be performed independently by the pharmacy department research section who will maintain the allocation key.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to treatment groups in a 1:1 ratio using a computer generated list of random allocation schedule. Random permuted blocks of varying sizes will be employed to ensure approximate balance of treatment allocation within each group. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistics
The study aims to recruit 60 babies, based on ductal closure rate or reduction in size of 50% as the primary efficacy measure. A sample size of 30 babies in each group will provide 80% power at the 5% level of significance to detect a difference of 37% in ductal closure rate between groups, assuming a closure rate of 13% with Ibuprofen based on NICU audit. An interim analysis will be performed for the main outcome at 50% recruitment. The study would be terminated if a difference of 37% or more in the main outcome were found. 

Statistical analysis
We will estimate the ductal closure rate in each treatment group. Difference between groups will be assessed and 95% confidence interval for the difference will be determined. Comparisons between groups will be made using Students t test. For parametric continuous data, Wilcoxon rank-sum test for nonparametric continuous data and chi-square or Fishers exact test as appropriate for categorical data. A two-sided p value of 0.05 will be chosen to indicate statistical significance. All analysis will be performed on an Intention-to-treat (ITT) basis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Newborn</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>246 Clayton Road
Clayton 
VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ductus arteriosus DA is a blood vessel that connecting the two major vessels exiting the heart. It is a normal structure that is present in every baby before birth and closes very soon after birth in healthy term babies. In babies born prematurely before 32 weeks gestation, the DA can continue to remain open (or patent PDA). The continual presence of the PDA in preterm infants may cause ongoing breathing difficulties, feeding problems or blood pressure issues. The doctors looking after your baby will generally want to give medication to close the PDA.  The standard treatment is to use a medication called ibuprofen given as an intravenous injection. Recently, doctors is Australia have become aware of reports from other centres overseas that suggest paracetamol (a common medication for fever and pain) may be as effective as intravenous ibuprofen to help close the PDA. However, these reports currently do not provide sufficient scientific proof yet to guide doctors here to use to paracetamol routinely to treat PDAs. Therefore we propose to conduct a research study to compare whether oral paracetamol is as effective as intravenous ibuprofen in treating PDAs. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14066B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Tan</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61-3-95945191</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-95946115</fax>
      <email>kenneth.tan@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Tan</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61-3-95945191</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-95946115</fax>
      <email>kenneth.tan@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Arvind Sehgal</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61-3-95945191</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-95946115</fax>
      <email>arvind.sehgal@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Tan</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61-3-95945191</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-95946115</fax>
      <email>kenneth.tan@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>