<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363104">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001113842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Walkabout: a program to increase physical activity among young adults with Down syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Walkabout: a program to increase physical activity among young adults aged between 18 and 35 years with Down syndrome and mild to moderate intellectual disability</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Young adults with Down syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Down's syndrome</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in the intervention group will complete an 8-week, mentored physical activity program called Walkabout. They will undertake to complete 150 minutes of moderate intensity physical activity per week during the program. The first 2 weeks will be a familiarisation phase, to introduce the program to the participants and allow them to adapt to the program with the aim of building up to 150 minutes of moderate activity by week 3. 

Each participant will be teamed with a student mentor who will be a physiotherapy student. The participant and their mentor will complete two walking sessions together each week (each session will be 45 minutes in duration). The other 60 minutes of activity will be individually tailored to the circumstances of the participant. A planning session on how to implement these additional 60 minutes of walking without the mentor will be conducted at the start of the intervention period with a member of the research team, and a second planning session will be undertaken after 4 weeks to review progress and to make changes if necessary. All participants will receive motivational prompts (postcard reminders). The participants will wear a pedometer while they are walking to measure the number of steps completed in each session. They will also be encouraged to walk briskly. Information about the activity they do will be noted in a log-book.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group will complete an 8-week program of social activities with a student mentor. The program will comprise social and recreational activities that would not be expected to have a fitness or training effect, such as painting, printing, music or social activities that do not incorporate a physical activity component. Each session of the social program will run for 90 minutes, equal to the time spent in the 2 mentored walking sessions each week in the intervention group. The control group participants will also receive the same level of feedback as the intervention group; they will receive postcards with simple messages similar to the motivational prompts received by the intervention group. These messages will provide information that is not intended to be motivational to increase physical activity, such as weather reports, details of a topical news story or sports results.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7-day Physical activity levels measured using accelerometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (week 0), and post intervention (week 9)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking capacity (6 minute walk test, self-selected walking speed, fast walking speed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (week 0), and post intervention (week 9)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body structure (waist circumference, weight)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (week 0), and post intervention (week 9)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of wellbeing and attitudes to physical activity (using the barriers to exercise scale, interaction with disabled persons scale and community living attitudes scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (week 0), and post intervention (week 9)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) Young adults with Down syndrome 
(ii) Mild to moderate intellectual disability, as perceived by their parents or carers
(iii) Ability to follow simple verbal instructions in English.
(iv) Fit and well enough to participate in a physical activity program.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) Participation in a physical activity program 3 months prior to their participation in the trial, 
(ii) An acute or concurrent medical condition rendering a participant unfit to participate in moderate level physical activity based on medical advice, 
(iii) A significant behavioural problem that would impact on their ability to participate,</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited to the study and undergo baseline testing before being randomly allocated to either the social or intervention group. using a concealed allocation, block randomisation method. Participants will be considered in blocks. The order of the blocks will be generated using the website randomization.org and assignments sealed in sequentially numbered opaque envelopes. Using 'randomization.org', a list of numbers from 1 to 20 will be randomly generated in 2 columns . These two columns will then represent the 'intervention' group (1st column) and 'control' group (2nd column). The relevant group name will then written on a piece of cardboard and placed in an opaque envelope with the number of the participant on the front. A researcher not involved in recruitment will allocate the participants by opening the next envelope in the sequence.</concealment>
    <sequence>The website randomization.org will be used.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faculty of Health Sciences, La Trobe University grant</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>La Trobe University, Plenty Road, Bundoora, VIC, 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Faculty of Health Sciences, La Trobe University grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University, Plenty Road, Bundoora, VIC, 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomised controlled trial will compare the effect of an 8-week mentored physical activity program called Walkabout compared with a social program for young adults with Down syndrome aged 18-35 years. Specifically, it will examine if Walkabout increases their level of physical activity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/0056</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nora Shields</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
Bldg HS3, Rm 515
Plenty Road
La Trobe University
Bundoora 
VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394795852</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.shields@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nora Shields</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
Bldg HS3, Rm 515
La Trobe University
Plenty Road
Bundoora 
VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394795852</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.shields@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>