<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364009">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000395730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of an educational resource for cardiac secondary prevention: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating whether patients with acute coronary syndrome who receive a secondary-prevention educational resource have greater attendance at cardiac rehabilitation compared to patients who receive usual inpatient education</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-6276 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute coronary syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An educational booklet produced by the Heart Foundation Australia titled 'My heart my life'.  The resource aims to support patients with coronary heart disease to understand and better manage their cardiac condition.  The booklet has 5 main topic areas: (1) My heart (explains coronary heart disease) (2) In hospital (medical tests, medications, managing emotions, preparing for discharge) (3) My recovery  (GP follow-up, cardiac rehabilitation, general information on risk factors)  (4) Services and support (role of cardiac rehabilitation and the heart foundation) (5) Take action (goal setting for personal risk factors including smoking, nutrition, alcohol, physical activity, weight, lipids, blood pressure, diabetes and psychological health).     The resource uses diagrams, text and some interactive exercises (e.g. checklists, self-evaluation and goal setting based on the stages of change model), and is intended to be given to patients to take home and use as part of their recovery.
The intervention will be provided to patients in hospital by the research assistant who will briefly explain its contents (estimated time 15 minutes).  A follow-up phone call will be made to patients at 1 month post-discharge, therefore the duration of the intervention is 1 month.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual cardiac secondary prevention education provided to all patients with acute coronary syndrome in each site. This care may include access to other Heart Foundation brochures, or individualised education sessions about coronary heart disease, risk factors and discharge planning from the patient's nurse (the My Heart, my Life resource is not given as part of usual care at Eastern Health).  The amount and intensity may differ between sites and may also vary according to day of the week and work-load demands.  The research assistant will document any education provided to the patient as part of usual care.
If provided, education sessions are usually of 10-15 minutes duration.  The follow-up period of the comparator will  be 1 month following hospital discharge.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attendance for at least one session of cardiac rehabilitation as self-reported by the patient during the 1-month phone follow-up </outcome>
      <timepoint>One month post-discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of cardiac-related readmissions to hospital and presentations to Emergency Departments since discharge (captured using hospital admission datasets)</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month post-discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in knowledge of cardiac condition and risk factors, and in self-management ability between baseline and follow-up.   A questionnaire will be used to capture the patients understanding of acute coronary syndrome (ACS) terms and knowledge of risk factors.  The ACS and risk factor knowledge questions are modified from the validated CHD Knowledge and Awareness Questionnaire (CKAQ).  
This questionnaire will also use two constructs from the validated Health Education Impact  Questionnaire.  The first construct (health directed activity) captures participants level of functional activity incorporated into lifestyle. The second construct (self-monitoring and insight) captures how an individual engages in self-monitoring of their condition. 
This questionnaire is estimated to take about 10 minutes to complete and will be administered by the research assistant.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month post-discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants who are hospitalised within one of three Eastern Health cardiology units with a preliminary diagnosis of ACS (ICD-10 codes 120, 121, 122) will be eligible for inclusion. Participants must also be eligible for referral to a cardiac rehabilitation program; this will be determined by the cardiologist and cardiology nurse caring for that patient. Patients will be aged 18 years and over.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe cognitive impairment or mental illness, unless a carer is able to complete questionnaires on behalf of the participant.  
Patients who are clinically unstable will also be excluded (eligibility to participate will be determined by the attending cardiology nurse using a check list).  
Non-English speaking patients are unable to be included as the education resource and questionnaires are written in the English language only. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited by a research assistant (RA) who will visit each cardiology unit at least twice weekly, after first liaising with the Nurse Unit Manager to identify patients with a diagnosis of ACS and their eligibility to participate in the study.  The RA will provide the participant information and consent form (PICF) and discuss the study with the patient before seeking consent.  
Patients will be randomised to intervention or control group within each CCU.  Patients will be randomised into usual care vs. intervention groups using computer generated random numbers, generated in advance and placed in numbered, sealed envelopes. After each patient has been recruited, the sequential envelope will be opened and the participant allocated to intervention or control group.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated random numbers (simple randomisation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Allowing for a 2-3 month baseline data collection period, the expected sample size would be up to 100 patients (a total of n=50 patients in each arm of the study, across the 3 sites).  A total of 1459 patients with ACS attended Eastern Health from January to November 2012 therefore this sample size is achievable. Assuming a 5% significance level and 80% power, this sample size will allow for detection of a difference in rates of attendance at CR of 30% between the control and intervention groups. This difference in attendance rates is feasible. A Cochrane review from 2010 identified three randomised controlled trials to increase uptake of CR; all improved uptake in intervention compared to control groups.  One study found that using motivational letters increased uptake by 29% (43), while using follow-up phone calls and home visits increased uptake by 30% </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Angliss Hospital - Upper Ferntree Gully</hospital>
    <hospital>Maroondah Hospital - Ringwood East</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Burwood Campus, 
221 Burwood Highway, 
Burwood, VIC 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Foundation Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>500 Collins St
Melbourne 
VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Heart disease is the leading cause of death in Australia, and patients with existing coronary heart disease (CHD) are at increased risk of further cardiac events. Most secondary prevention guidelines recommend that patients with CHD modify their cardiac risk factors.  To do this, patients require an adequate level of health literacy including awareness of their own condition and risk factors, and the knowledge to be able to make essential lifestyle modifications.  
The Heart Foundation recently updated a key resource My Heart My Life, which provides comprehensive information on recovery from heart disease. This project seeks to evaluate the effectiveness and impact of the My Heart My Life resource on patient knowledge, behaviour change and health literacy in Victoria.  Patients who have been admitted to Eastern Health with an acute coronary syndrome (ACS) will be asked to complete a Health Literacy Questionnaire (developed by Deakin University). Questions will also be asked to determine understanding of terminology and actions to take to reduce health behaviour risk factors.  Participants will then be randomised into two groups  one group who receive the My Heart My Life resource and a control group who receive usual in-patient education. A follow-up phone call will be done at one month to determine differences between the two patient groups in terms of cardiac knowledge and health-related behaviours. The results of this evaluation will determine whether patients who received the My Heart My Life resource obtain a greater understanding of their condition, report they are able to manage risk factors and are more likely to attend cardiac rehabilitation, compared with usual care. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill VIC 3128 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Beauchamp</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
Deakin University
Melbourne Burwood Campus, 
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.beauchamp@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Beauchamp</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
Deakin University
Melbourne Burwood Campus, 
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.beauchamp@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Beauchamp</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
Deakin University
Melbourne Burwood Campus, 
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.beauchamp@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Beauchamp</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
Deakin University
Melbourne Burwood Campus, 
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.beauchamp@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>