<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368975">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000922572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Influence of habitual dietary fibre intake on the responsiveness of the gut microbiota to a prebiotic</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised double-blind, placebo-controlled, cross-over trial to determine the responsiveness of the gut microbiota to a prebiotic supplement in healthy individuals with differing habitual dietary fibre intakes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-3522 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>ADAPT study- hAbitual Diet And PrebioTic</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of suboptimal diet related health conditions, i.e. obesity

</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of suboptimal diet related health conditions, i.e. diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of suboptimal diet related health conditions, i.e. cancer </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of suboptimal diet related health conditions, i.e. heart disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is an inulin/fructo-oligosaccharide prebiotic. Participants will take 16g per day (2x8g sachets taken with breakfast and dinner) of the prebiotic powder mixed into food and hot beverages for a duration of 3 weeks. After a 3 week washout period participants will also take 16g per day (2x8g sachets taken with breakfast and dinner) of placebo powder mixed into food and hot beverages for a duration of 3 weeks The study is 10 weeks in duration as there is also a 1 week run-in period at the beginning of the study. 
Adherence to the intervention will be monitored using a daily diary and by asking the participants to return unused sachets.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment is a placebo which is a digestible maltodextrin. Participants will take 16g per day (2x8g sachets taken with breakfast and dinner) of the placebo powder mixed into food and hot beverages for a duration of 3 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether an individuals habitual dietary fibre intake (high versus low, assessed using a validated food frequency questionnaire- Monash University Comprehensive Nutrition Assessment Questionnaire) influences the way in which the gut microbiota respond to a prebiotic as measured by bacterial relative abundance and bacterial diversity (alpha and beta diversity) assessed using next-generation sequencing analysis of faecal samples. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Bacterial relative abundance and bacterial diversity will be assessed before and after the 3 week long prebiotic and placebo interventions. Habitual dietary fibre intake will be assessed at baseline. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether an individual's habitual dietary fibre intake (high vs. low, assessed using a validated food frequency questionnaire- Monash University Comprehensive Nutrition Assessment Questionnaire) influences the way in which the gut microbiota respond to a prebiotic as measured by bacterial short chain fatty acid (SCFA) production assessed using gas chromatography-mass spectrometer analysis of faecal samples. </outcome>
      <timepoint>SCFA production will be assessed before and after the 3 week long prebiotic and placebo interventions. Habitual dietary fibre intake will be assessed at baseline. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether baseline gut microbiota diversity (alpha and beta diversity), assessed by next-generation sequencing analysis of faecal samples, differ between individuals with high versus low habitual dietary fibre intakes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether differing habitual dietary fibre intakes (high versus low) alters the efficacy of a prebiotic to influence appetite using a 100-mm anchored visual analogue scale appetite questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Appetite will be assessed before and after the 3 week long prebiotic and placebo interventions. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether baseline SCFA levels differ between individuals with high versus low habitual dietary fibre intakes assessed using gas chromatography-mass spectrometer analysis of faecal samples. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether the utilisation of fructans, as assessed by enzymatic assay analysis of faecal samples, differs post prebiotic supplementation in individuals with differing habitual dietary fibre intakes (high versus low) assessed using a Fructan HK enzymatic assay kit. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Fructan utilisation will be assessed before and after the 3 week long prebiotic intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate any associations between body composition, as assessed by BodPod, and gut microbiota composition and function assessed using next-generation sequencing analysis of faecal samples. This is a composite.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether baseline gut microbiota relative abundance, assessed by next-generation sequencing analysis of faecal samples, differ between individuals with high versus low habitual dietary fibre intakes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The target population for recruitment are healthy male and female individuals between the age of 19 and 65 years with a BMI of between 18.5 and 30kg/m2. Individuals will need to have either a particularly low or high habitual dietary fibre intake to be considered eligible to participate in the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Aged &lt;19 or &gt;65 years
* Taken antibiotics within the last 6 months
* Taken laxatives, gastric motility medications, prebiotic or probiotic containing foods or supplements within the last month
* Of poor health- cancer, gastrointestinal disorders (irritable bowel syndrome, inflammatory bowel disease, coeliac disease, constipation, diarrhoea, excessive bloating), autoimmune disorders, diabetes, heart disease, renal failure
* BMI &lt;18.5 or &gt;30kg/m2
* Significant weight loss or weight gain (&gt;5%) within the past year
* Significant dietary change within the past year
* Pregnant, breastfeeding or planning a pregnancy
* Food intolerance which causes gastrointestinal symptoms (i.e. lactose intolerance, gluten sensitivity)
* Smokers
* High alcohol consumers

If a potential participant is only ineligible to participate in the study because they are taking prebiotic or probiotic containing foods or supplements they can become eligible for inclusion in the study if they are willing to discontinue these foods or supplements for a month prior to starting the study and during the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>As this is a cross-over study all participants will receive the prebiotic and placebo treatments however the order in which they receive the treatments will be concealed from the participant and lead researcher. The research unit laboratory manager will be responsible for allocating the treatment order for each participant. 
The treatments will be sealed in opaque bags and will only be labelled as treatment A or B therefore the participant and lead researcher (who is administering the treatments, assessing outcomes and analysing data) will not know the order of treatment allocation. 
The appearance and taste of the treatments are similar and both treatments will be packed into sachets which will help to conceal which treatment the participants are taking. The treatments will be packed into sachets off site. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised using a computer based pre-generated treatment order as participants will be recruited one at a time over a number of months.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>NA</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The power calculations have been conducted to detect a significant increase in Bifidobacteria species as this is the main outcome measure in the prebiotic studies reviewed. As improved appetite is a key secondary outcome power calculations have also been conducted to ensure significant differences in appetite can be detected. 
Based on the studies reviewed (split plot design crossover) in order to detect a significant difference in abundance of Bifidobacteria species between the placebo and treatment groups, with a power of 80% and significance of 5%, an average of 24 participants need to be recruited. To allow for drop outs (approximately 10%) and the more subtle differences which are likely to be seen when determining the response of Bifidobacteria species to a prebiotic when comparing low and high habitual dietary fibre consumers rather than the treatment to placebo group, a total of 40 participants will need to be recruited.
Based on the studies reviewed (split plot design crossover) in order to detect a significant difference in appetite between the control and treatment groups, with a power of 80% and significance of 5%, 3 participants need to be recruited. The recruitment of 40 participants will therefore be enough to determine whether there are any differences in appetite after prebiotic consumption between individuals with high and low habitual dietary fibre intakes. 

Phyla and genus taxonomy abundance data will be analysed using non-parametric Mann-Whitney test. Alpha diversity will be analysed using non-parametric two sample t-tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>45</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>18/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Genelle Healey</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Plant and Food Research Limited
Batchelar Road
Fitzherbert
Palmerston North 4474</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The New Zealand Institute of Plant and Food Research Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Batchelar Road
Fitzherbert
Palmerston North
4474</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Chrissie Butts</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Plant and Food Research Limited
Batchelar Road
Fitzherbert
Palmerston North 4474</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Jane Coad</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Food and Nutrition
Massey University
Tennent Drive 
Palmerston North 4474</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Research has shown that the type of food consumed can influence the bacteria in the gastrointestinal tract (gut). It has also been shown that the bacteria in the gut can have an influence on human health. The presence of unfavourable bacteria within the gut has been linked to obesity, diabetes and some gastrointestinal disorders such as inflammatory bowel disease and irritable bowel syndrome. Researchers are therefore trying to determine what can be done to ensure the bacteria living in our gut are favourable to help optimise human health. A number of fibre supplements, known as prebiotics, have been shown to improve human health through their actions on favourable gut bacteria. Prebiotics are not digested by humans and therefore reach the large bowel where they are used by the gut bacteria as a source of energy.
The amount of dietary fibre consumed between individuals varies considerably. We hypotheses that if someone is already consuming foods high in dietary fibre their gut bacteria will likely respond in a different way to a prebiotic supplement than the gut bacteria of an individual with a low intake of dietary fibre foods. The aim of the study is to determine what influence an individuals long term dietary fibre intake has on how their gut bacteria respond to a prebiotic supplement. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.massey.ac.nz/adaptstudy</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Massey University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Massey University
Tennent Drive
Palmerston North 4474</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/34</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Genelle Healey</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Batchelar Road
Fitzherbert
Palmerston North 4474</address>
      <phone>+64 6 355 6108</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>genelle.healey@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Genelle Healey</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Batchelar Road
Fitzherbert
Palmerston North 4474</address>
      <phone>+64 6 355 6108</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>genelle.healey@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Coad</name>
      <address>School of Food and Nutrition
Massey University
Tennent Drive
Palmerston North 4474</address>
      <phone>+64 6 951 6321</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.coad@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Genelle Healey</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Batchelar Road
Fitzherbert
Palmerston North 4474</address>
      <phone>+64 6 355 6108</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>genelle.healey@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>