<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367500">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000034538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pre-emptive analgesia of intrapleural and serratus plane blocks for breast surgeries: A randomized prospective clinical trial

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pre-emptive Analgesia of intrapleural and serratus plane blocks on intra and post-operative analgesia for breast surgery patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast surgeries for any indication, e.g. breast cancer, cosmetic surgery, etc.
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>30 patients in each group will be randomized using closed envelops and a computer generated random numbers into 2 groups (30 patients each). Each block will be performed just after induction of anesthesia. Group I (intrapleural block):  While the patient is in the supine position, the block will be performed using number 18 Touhy needle at the 5th intercostal space in the anterior midaxillary line. The needle will be introduced while the patient is disconnected from the ventilator to avoid lung injury or pneumothorax. Loss of resistance technique will be used to identify the intrapleural space. After negative aspiration test 40 ml of 0.25% levobupivacaine will be injected in the intrapleural space.
Group II (serratus plane block):
   The patients will be in the supine position, and the ultrasound probe will be in the sagital plane over the mid clavicular  region , then we will go inferiorly and laterally till we identify the 5th rib in the mid axillary line to identify the latissimus dorsi, teres major and serratus muscles. 22G needle will be introduced in-plane in relation to the ultrasound probe, then 0.4 ml/kg levobupivacaine 0.25% will be injected in the potential space superficial to the serratus anterior muscle. In the intra-operative period; if signs of sympathetic stimulation (increase in heart rate and mean arterial blood pressure more than 20 % from the baseline values despite adequate level of anesthesia) treated with iv bolus doses of fentanyl 0.5 micogram /Kg.
In the post-operative period: Visual Analogue Score (VAS). 0 = no pain, to 10 = the most severe pain, 0-3 = mild pain ,      4-6 = moderate pain,    &gt;6 = severe pain
Patients with moderate or severe pain will receive diclofenac sodium 75 mg intramuscular injection. 
(VAS) will be recorded at  1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 18, and 24 hours post-operatively.


</interventions>
    <comparator>The active control group is group I(Intra-pleural block group) in which 40 ml of 0.25% levobupivacaine will be injected in the intra-pleural space.






</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The duration of analgesia measured from the time of injection of the local anesthetic to the time of first request for analgesia (the first time the patient feels moderate or severe pain).</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the post-operative period: Visual Analogue Score (VAS). 0 = no pain, to 10 = the most severe pain, 0-3 = mild pain ,   4-6 = moderate pain,    &gt;6 = severe pain. 
(VAS) will be recorded at  1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 18,and 24 hours postoperatively.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The quality of  block 
</outcome>
      <timepoint> Will be assessed as follows:
Complete block: Patients who will not need fentanyl intra-operatively or diclofenac sodium injection 4 hours postoperatively.
Partial block: Patients who will need either fentanyl intra-operatively or diclofenac sodium injection 4 hours postoperatively.
Failed block: Patients who will need fentanyl intra-operatively and diclofenac sodium injection 4 hours postoperatively.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analgesic consumption</outcome>
      <timepoint>Dose of fentanyl and diclofenac sodium is assessed from the time of injection of the local anesthetic until 4 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The occurrence of any complication related to the technique e.g pneumo-thorax, hemo-thorax.....etc  will be recorded. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During performing the technique and the first 24 hours </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female patients with ASA clinical status I and II scheduled for breast surgery for any indication, e.g. breast cancer, cosmetic surgery, etc  in the General Surgery Department, Tanta University Hospital, Egypt.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with pulmonary disease (empyema, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, Pulmonary disease, or previous cardio-thoracic surgery), allergy to the local anesthetic, uncooperative patients, and patients with bleeding abnormalities.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients will be randomized using closed envelops  into 2 groups (30 patients each).</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random numbers will be used.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>   For each group 26 patients will be required for the serratus plane block to increase the duration of analgesia by 20% (72 minutes) based on a previous pilot study in our department with 90 % power using a cutoff statistical significance of 0.05 % and a standard deviation of  80 and standardized difference of  0.9. We  will use 30 patients in each group for more accurate statistical analysis. Quantitative data will be expressed as mean +/- SD and qualitative data and that which will not follow the normal distibution will be expressed as median and range  will be analyzed using SPSS, P&lt; 0.05 will be considered significant</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>16/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>16/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Tanta, El Gharbia governorate</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hoda Al Said Ahmed Ezz</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>El Geish street, Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, Tanta University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, El Gharbia Governorate, Egypt.
postal code:31257</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>El Geish street, Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, Tanta University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, El Gharbia Governorate, Egypt.
postal code:31257</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ahmed Abd El-Aziz Shama</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>El Geish street, Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, Tanta University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, El Gharbia Governorate, Egypt.
postal code:31257</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Egypt</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the present study is to compare the duration and quality of pre-emptive analgesia of intrapleural and Serratus Plane Blocks in patients scheduled for breast surgeries.  

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committee of the faculty of medicine ,Tanta Univerisity, Egypt.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>El Geish street. Faculty of Medicine, Tanta Univerisity, Tanta, El Gharbia governorate, Egypt.
postal code :31257</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2674/08/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda ALsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>El Geish street, anesthesia and surgical intensive care Department, Tanta University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, El Gharbia Governorate, Egypt.
postal code:31257 </address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodaezz714@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Abd El Reheem M. Dowidar</name>
      <address>El Geish street, Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, Tanta University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, El Gharbia Governorate, Egypt.
postal code:31257 </address>
      <phone>+20 1223195015</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr.dowidar47@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Abd El Reheem M. Dowidar</name>
      <address>El Geish street, Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, Tanta University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, El Gharbia Governorate, Egypt.
postal code:31257 </address>
      <phone>+20 1223195015</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr.dowidar47@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda ALsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>El Geish street, Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care Department, Tanta University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, El Gharbia Governorate, Egypt.
postal code:31257 </address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodaezz714@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>