<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371053">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001107415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving alcohol treatment outcomes: The effect of individual patient characteristics, treatment and system variables on alcohol treatment outcomes in patients attending specialist alcohol treatment service.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Improving alcohol treatment outcomes: The effect of individual patient characteristics, treatment and system variables on alcohol treatment outcomes in patients attending specialist alcohol treatment service.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Addiction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alcoholism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Clients will be asked to complete an iPad survey at  baseline while waiting for their appointment at the clinic. A telephone survey will be completed at 3 months follow up. The primary outcome measure will be the number of heavy drinking days (&gt; 5 drinks per day) in past 14 days.
Secondary outcome measures will include the number of drinking days; total alcohol consumption; and health related quality of life. Predictor variables will include client (e.g. demographics, substance use), intervention (e.g. treatment type), and system-­level variables (e.g. process of care). The relationship between predictor and outcome variables will be examined within a multilevel modelling framework.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not Applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of heavy drinking days (&gt;5 drinks per day) in the previous 2 week. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months post-recruitment </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of drinking days in the past 2 weeks. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 month post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total alcohol consumption in the previous 2 weeks. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 month post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of alcohol dependence measured by Audit C</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life measured by SF-8</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other drug use as measure by ATOP</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment provided for withdrawal measured by a client medical record audit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type of treatment provided for withdrawal measured by client medical record audit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proposed and actual length of treatment for withdrawal measured by clinical medical record audit</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Characteristics of treatment episodes measured by clinical medical record audit</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to pharmacotherapies measured by clinical medical record audit</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of the therapeutic relationship measured by the Working Alliance Inventory in the client follow-up and staff survey. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months-post recruitment for clients and once 50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of biological confirmation of abstinence as part of treatment measured by clients medical record audit</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff turn over. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff supervision. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number and type of peripheral services. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Teaching status. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continuity of care. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participation in clinical trials. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geographic location. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Funding type. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of clients treated per year. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Organisation accreditation. This question is part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Team climate. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived team effectiveness. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continuing education. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables.</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skills and qualifications. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables.</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Implementation of evidence-based practice. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables.</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Commitment to quality improvement. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables.</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff performance management. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure system variables.</outcome>
      <timepoint>50% of clients have been recruited from centre</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Demographics and social functioning. These questions are part of a survey designed specifically for this study to measure client variables.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clients: 
(i) aged 18 years or older; (ii) presenting for new episode of treatment at the participating service; (iii) have nominated alcohol as their primary drug of concern; (iv) have used alcohol in the past 30 days; (v) have not previously been enrolled in the study in the last 6 months; and (vi) have a telephone contact number. 

Staff:
All staff from participating centres will be invited to contribute to the study if they are employed in the alcohol treatment clinic and are involved in providing direct patient care. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Additionally, the study is focusing on those treatment centres community-based providing alcohol treatment to adults. Centres are ineligible if they are services that provide withdrawal only, residential rehabilitation only, detoxification services only and/or treat less than 50 clients for alcohol as primary drug of concern in 12 months (or approximately less than 75 episodes). Participants under the age of 18 have been excluded as they are unable to give informed consent.  While non­-English speaking groups represent an important segment within the target population, translation costs for study materials will make it cost prohibitive to include this group in the current study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>3</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Psychosocial</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>7250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patient outcomes can be significantly influenced by the characteristics of the system in which health care services are delivered, independently of patient and treatment characteristics. There has been no systematic examination of the relative impact of client, treatment and systems ­level variables on outcomes for alcohol dependence. This study   aims to determine, using a prospective cohort study, the impact of: (a) individual client characteristics; (b) type of treatment; and (c) features of the system in which treatment is provided, on alcohol treatment outcomes. Eligible treatment centres will be those that provides a face­to­face specialist outpatient alcohol treatment service to adults and expect to treat at least 50 clients for alcohol as primary drug of concern in the next 12 months (or approximately 75 episodes). Fifty services across Australia will be recruited using stratified sampling. Eligible clients will be aged  18 years or older; presenting for a new episode of outpatient treatment at the service; have nominated alcohol as  their primary drug of concern; have used alcohol in the last 30 days; have not previously been enrolled in the study in the last 6 months; and have a telephone contact number. Clients will be asked to complete an iPad survey at  baseline while waiting for their appointment at the clinic. A telephone survey will be completed at 3 months follow up. The primary outcome measure will be the number of heavy drinking days (&gt; 5 drinks per day) in past 14 days. Secondary outcome measures will include the number of drinking days; total alcohol consumption; and health related quality of life. Predictor variables will include client (e.g. demographics, substance use), intervention (e.g. treatment type), and system ­level variables (e.g. process of care). The relationship between predictor and outcome variables will be examined within a multilevel modelling framework. This is the first study internationally to examine the role of three levels of variables on treatment success. It will provide critical information for policy makers on which to base minimum service standards. Clinic Staff will be invited to participate in a web-based survey, from the Director (or delegate) of their clinic providing information about their own qualifications and skills, their role in relation to the delivery of client treatment, and their perceptions about staff attitudes, team culture and client relationship within the clinic, implementation of evidence-based practice and commitment to quality improvement. One key informant from the centre will be asked to participate in a telephone interview to obtain information  number and type of staff, staff turnover, staff supervision, number and type of peripheral services, teaching status, continuity of care, participation in clinical trials, geographic location, funding type, number of clients treated per year, organisational accreditation.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Hunman Research Ethics Committe</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lookout Road 
New Lambton NSW 2305
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/05/18/4.07/ HREC/16/HNE/193</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert Sanson-Fisher</name>
      <address>W4 HMRI Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61240420713</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rob.Sanson-Fisher@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Megan Freund</name>
      <address>W4 HMRI Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+6124040834</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Megan.Freund@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robert Sanson-Fisher</name>
      <address>W4 HMRI Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61240420713</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rob.Sanson-Fisher@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Julie Crane</name>
      <address>W4 HMRI Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61240420682</phone>
      <fax>+6140420044</fax>
      <email>Julie.Crane@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>