<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370964">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000869471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Brain Injury Research in Prisons (BIRP): Prevalence of a history of acquired brain injury in South Australian prisoners and evaluation of behavioural impacts.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prevalence of a history of acquired brain injury in South Australian prisoners and significance of this for prisoners and prison system</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BIRP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acquired Brain Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase 1.  Prevalence study. Data will be collected by prison health nurses conducting the admitting health assessments. A semi-structured interview format will be used to ask about past incidences and risk factors for acquired brain injury. This will form part of their health assessment. 
Phase 2.  Observational study
Prisoners who are evaluated as having a history of ABI (fulfilled at least one or more risk factors) will be invited to meet with the nurse manager to complete 3 questionaires which is estimated will take approximately 30 minutes. The Frontal Systems Behaviour Scale and Neurobehavioural Investory will assess behavioural characteristics of participants. The demographic questionaire will ask questions about their medical and psychiatric history as well as their educational background. 
Phase 3: Qualitative investigation. 10 -15 prisoners will be invited to attend an interview with the Chief Investigator, an experienced interviewer to seek their perceptions on their experiences within the prison system, and any issues they have about returning to the community. </interventions>
    <comparator>NA</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of risk factors for history of acquired brain injury will be assessed by semi-structured interview within the initial health assessment.
ASSAULT with LOC for longer than 30 minutes 
MOTOR VEHICLE ACCIDENT with LOC longer than 30 minutes
AMATEUR/PROFESSIONAL BOXING KNOCKED OUT with LOC longer than 30 minutes
DIAGNOSIS OF STROKE
DIAGNOSIS OF BRAIN INJURY OR HEAD INJURY
SELF HARM INCIDENT with LOC longer than 30 minutes
ALCOHOL CONSUMPTION 
MALE: 6 STANDARD DRINKS/day for longer than 8 years
FEMALE: 3 STANDARD DRINKS/day for longer than 8 years
 DRUG USE 
1.for longer than 8 years OR
DRUG OVERDOSE
2.	An overdose requiring resuscitation OR
3.	An overdose with LOC for longer than 30 minutes OR
4.	An overdose requiring hospitalisation greater than 1 day
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admissions health assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frontal Systems Behaviour Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 days after admission to the prison</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurobehavioural inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 days after admission to the prison</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information about prisoner incidents</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks following admission to prison or prior to their discharge from prison (if earlier than 12 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Prisoners on the day of their admission to prison (not transfers from other prisons)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prisoners who are being transferred from another prison</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Prevalence Study Phase 1.
As the aim of the prevalence study is to determine an adequate sample size to estimate the population prevalence of prisoners with an ABI with a good precision we have considered a number of parameters in establishing a reasonable sample size.
1.	The expected prevalence. We know from other studies that numbers quoted have varied between 25% to 87%.  By estimating a 50 % prevalence for this current study, we have ensured that we calculate the highest sample size. 
2.	Precision.  If the prevalence is expected to be between 10-90%, a precision of 5% with a smaller error of estimate is recommended (Naing L et al 2006). 
3.	Expected number of non responders.  It is recommended to oversample by 10% to 20% of the computed sample size number to achieve the desired precision.  

Our estimated sample size calculation with assumptions of 5% precision, 50 % prevalence and a population size of 3302 people admitted into the prison system each year, resulted in n=345 with 95% confidence interval between the specified limits of 45% -55%.  If we are to include an additional 20% of respondents, the new target is n= 414. 
Frequency estimates will be determined, including confidence levels calculated to inform the likelihood of the unobserved target group falling within a certain range of the observed sample value.
2. Neurobehavioural Investigation Phase 2 
Descriptive statistics will be used.  The two subgroups (traumatic and non-traumatic brain injury) will be analysed and compared.
3. Qualitative Investigation Phase 3 
Thematic analysis using nVivo10 .Thematic analysis of the interview data will be undertaken where patterns are looked for and sorted into categories by two independent researchers (Patton 1990). Once the patterns, linkages and explanations have been decided, the researchers will look for rival or competing themes and explanations. This may occur inductively by looking for different ways to organize the data that might lead to different findings, or logically by thinking of other logical possibilities and then investigating whether those possibilities are supported by the data (Patton 1990). 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>414</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>3/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre, Royal Adelaide Hospital, South Australia Brain Injury Rehabilitation Services</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre
Central Adelaide Local Health Network
207-255 Hampstead Road
Northfield SA 5085
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre, Royal Adelaide Hospital, South Australia Brain Injury Rehabilitation Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre
Central Adelaide Local Health Network
207-255 Hampstead Road
Northfield South Australia 5085
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A number of studies have reported a high prevalance of people with an acquired brain injury are incarcerated in prisons throughout the world.  This study will investigate the prevalence of prisoners in SA prisons who have a history of traumatic or non traumatic brain injury from incident, stroke or substance abuse.  This prevalence study forms phase 1 of the trial. Phase 2 of the trial will investigate the neurobehavioural sequelae of those who have experienced an ABI. Phase 3 will involve a qualitative investigation with prisoners being interviewed about their experiences in prison, and preparing to leave prison to manage in the community.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Adelaide Local Health Network Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Womens Health Centre
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, South Australia, 5000
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/RAH/183</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370964-Ethics approval Letter_Killington-signed_2015_06_02.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maggie Killington</name>
      <address>SA Brain Injury Rehabilitation Services
Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre
Central Adelaide Local Health Network
207-255 Hampstead Road
Northfield  SA 5085</address>
      <phone>+6 1 400061204</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Maggie.Killington@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maggie Killington</name>
      <address>SA Brain Injury Rehabilitation Services
Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre
Central Adelaide Local Health Network
207-255 Hampstead Road
Northfield  SA 5085</address>
      <phone>+6 1 400061204</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Maggie.Killington@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maggie Killington</name>
      <address>SA Brain Injury Rehabilitation Services
Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre
Central Adelaide Local Health Network
207-255 Hampstead Road
Northfield  SA 5085</address>
      <phone>+6 1 400061204</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Maggie.Killington@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maggie Killington</name>
      <address>SA Brain Injury Rehabilitation Services
Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre
Central Adelaide Local Health Network
207-255 Hampstead Road
Northfield  SA 5085</address>
      <phone>6 1 0400061204</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Maggie.Killington@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>