<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343366">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000890932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>'Physical Activity at Home (PAAH)', Evaluation of a group versus home based physical activity program in community dwelling middle aged adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In middle-aged community dwelling adults is a physiotherapy-led home based physical activity program more effective than a community group based physical activity program in terms of long term physical activity adherance, health benefits and cost?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PAAH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>high blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>lipid disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>osteoporosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>colon cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Home based intervention.
Baseline outcome measures were taken in participants homes eliminating a number of barriers to physical activity adoption. Participants were encouraged to invite a support person to attend. After baseline measures were completed motivational interviewing was used to devise a physical activity program. A physiotherapist discussed type, frequency, intensity, duration, benefits, barriers, goals, self-monitoring and progression of physical activity aiming to achieve 30 minutes of moderate intensity physical activity on most days of the week eventually. Participants were contacted by a physiotherapist via phone providing advice and support 2 weeks after the initial assessment and them monthly over a six month period, a total of approximately 6 phone calls.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group exercise program.
This group acted as an active control, replicating standard physical activity options provided in the community. Participants attended a local YMCA for their baseline measures. Participants had a choice of times for the group based exercise program which were all during business hours. These sessions were run by a YMCA fitness instructor at the YMCA once a week, for 60 minutes, over 6 months. The exercise program involved upper and lower body strengthening exercises, gross motor skill training and aerobic fitness training. Participants were encouraged to increase their physical activity levels outside of the group sessions, aiming to achieve 30 minutes of moderate intensity exercise most days but individual physical activity programs were not specifically designed for this group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity adherence assessed via exercise diaries. Participants were encouraged to record any exercise completed in the exercise diary and return the diaries in the provided reply paid envelope at the end of the month. Exercise completed will be compared to exercise prescribed to determine adherence.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 (end of intervention period), 12, 18 and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity adherence or 'sufficient' physical activty via the Active Australia Survey. All particpants will complete this survey at the below timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6(end of intervention period), 12, 18 and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity adherence via the Actigraph GT1M accelerometer. All particpants will wear the accelerometer for a week in the month prior to the data collection points. The Active Australia Survey will be completed at the end of this week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 (end of the intervention period), 12, 18 and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aerobic capacity via the 2 minute step test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 (end of the intervention period), 12, 18 and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life via the SF-12 quality of life survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 (end of the intervention period), 12, 18 and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease biomarkers via waist circumference (cm), waist:hip ratio, body mass index (kg/m2) and blood pressure (mmHg).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6(end of the intervention period), 12, 18 and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. 50-65 years old.
2. Sedentary, that is, no participation in regular moderate or vigorous physical activity for 30 minutes 2 or more times a week for at least 6 months.
3. No serious medical conditions, such as unstable angina, uncontrolled hypertension, diagnosed or hospitalised with chest pain, heart attack or heart surgery in the past 6 months.
4. No servere functional impairments due to multiple medical or psychiatric diseases.
5. Not planning to move from the area within 2 years.
6. Only one person per household was eligible.
7. English speaking and appropriate cognitive skills to provide informed consent and actively engage in a physical activity program.
8. Medical screening was undertaken using the Sports Medicine Australia (SMA) Pre-Exercise Screening System. If a participant answered 'yes' to any of the SMA screening questions, they were asked to attend their local medical officer to receive medical clearance before they were included in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.See the above inclusion criteria.
2. Resting systolic blood pressure &gt; 200mmHg, diastolic blood pressure &gt; 100mmHg, resting heart rate &gt; 100 bpm.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>16/04/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>16/04/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>158</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2606</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nicole Freene</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
ACT
2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberra Research Student Funds</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Canberra
ACT
2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Gordon Waddington</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
ACT
2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Wendy Chesworth</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
ACT
2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Rachel Davey</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Reserach &amp; Action in Public Health
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
ACT 
2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to evaluate a new evidence based model for increasing the adoption and maintenance of physical activity in sedentary community dwelling middle aged individuals. Specifically targeting those individulas who are less likely to adopt and maintain exercise as they do not normally access the currently available community group exercise programs.


We hypothesize that
(i) There are a large number of individuals in the community aged 50-65 years who are not interested in group exercise, the common method used to increase the population's level of physical activity.
(ii) A proportion of this group would commence exercising if an alternative method of increasing physcial activity was available, such as a home based approach.
(iii) The home based program would produce health benfits equivalent to those seen in the group based exercise program for sedentary adults 50-65 years old.
(iv) Those that commence the home based program are more likely to continue with an increase in physical activity in the long term, as compared to a group based program.
(v) A home based approach to increasing physical activity with minimal support is more cost effective than a group based intervention, taking into consideration long term physical activity maintenance.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Freene N, Waddington G, Chesworth W, Davey R, Cochrane T (2013). Community group exercise versus physiotherapist-led home-based physical activity program: barriers, enablers and preferences in middle-aged adults. Physiotherapy Theory and Practice 0(0), 1-9. DOI: doi:10.3109/09593985.2013.816894.

Freene N, Waddington G, Chesworth W, Davey R, Cochrane T (2013). Physiotherapist-led home-based physical activity program versus community group exercise for middle-aged adults: Quasi-experimental comparison. Open Journal of Preventive Medicine 3, 229-237. DOI: 10.4236/ojpm.2013.32031.

Freene N, Waddington G, Chesworth W, Davey R, Cochrane T (2013). Validating two self-report physical activity measures in middle-aged adults completing a group exercise or home-based physical activity program. Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport(0) DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jsams.2013.11.002.

Freene N, Waddington G, Chesworth W, Davey R, Goss J (2011). 'Physical activity at home (PAAH)', evaluation of a group versus home based physical activity program in community dwelling middle aged adults: rationale and study design. BMC Public Health 11, 883-883.

Freene N, Waddington G, Davey R, Cochrane T (2013). Longitudinal comparison of a physiotherapist-led, home-based and group-based program for increasing physical activity in community-dwelling middle-aged adults. Australian Journal Of Primary Health.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Canberra Committee for Ethics in Human Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Canberra
ACT
2601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09-97</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
ACT
2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 2638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3033443@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
ACT 
2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 2638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3033443@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
ACT
2601</address>
      <phone>+61 02 6201 2638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3033443@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
BRUCE
ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 2638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>u3033443@uni.canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>