<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366387">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000609651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the Macintosh laryngoscope vs KingVision videolaryngoscope for routine tracheal intubation </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of the Macintosh laryngoscope vs KingVision videolaryngoscope for routine tracheal intubation in Asian female surgical patients without predictors of difficult airway</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Performance of airway device

</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Paralyzed and intubated patients for surgery without predictors of a difficult airway</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After induction of a standard general anaesthetic and 3 min after administration of a neuromuscular blocking agent, patients underwent indirect laryngoscopy and intubation with the KingVision videolaryngoscope (comprising a reusable 2.4inch video display screen and disposable blades). </interventions>
    <comparator>After induction of a standard general anaesthetic and 3 min after administration of a neuromuscular blocking agent, patients underwent conventional direct laryngoscopy and intubation with the classic Macintosh laryngoscope, which does not feature a video screen.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint is time to successful tracheal intubation. This is the interval from insertion of the laryngoscope blade into the mouth to when the tracheal tube cuff is inflated after successful intubation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After the laryngoscope has been inserted into the participant's mouth.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Successful intubation on first attempt</outcome>
      <timepoint>When the laryngoscope has been inserted into the participant's mouth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The intubation difficulty score (IDS) [the sum of 7 variables: number of intubation attempts, operators, use of alternative intubation techniques, glottic exposure, magnitude of lifting force required during laryngoscopy,need for external laryngeal pressure , and position of the vocal cords at intubation ]</outcome>
      <timepoint>At point of intubation of patient's trachea.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of blade and tracheal tube insertion (subjectively assessed from 0: easy, to 100:difficult)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At point of intubation of patient's trachea.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The quality of the view (subjectively assessed from 0: good, 100: bad)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At point of intubation of patient's trachea</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Optimization manoeuvres (repositioning of the patients head, use of external laryngeal pressure, further advancement or withdrawal of the laryngoscope blade, increased or decreased lifting force of the laryngoscope handle) and use of airway adjuncts (stylet, bougie) to aid intubation</outcome>
      <timepoint>At point of intubation of patient's trachea</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications associated with tracheal intubation eg. desaturation (SpO2 &lt;95%), oesophageal intubation, laryngo-pharyngeal morbidity ie. visible lip or dental injury, mucosal injury ( blood on laryngoscope blade). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At point of intubation of patient's trachea. An independent observer not involved in the trial assessed these outcomes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative sorethroat (Yes/No)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the PACU (post anaesthesia care unit) forty- five minutes after surgery by an independent observer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Asian patients with normal airway parameters (eg. Mallampati 1-2, thyromental distance greater than or equal to 6.5 cm, sternomental distance greater than or equal to 12.5cm, interincisor distance greater than or equal to 4cm, ability to prognath, and normal head/neck movement) scheduled for gynaecological, breast or plastic reconstructive surgery at our womens hospital. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>22</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with previously documented difficult tracheal intubation,  the morbidly obese (BMI &gt; 40), those with a  hiatus hernia, suffering symptomatic gastroesophageal reflux, and those at high risk of regurgitation or aspiration. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants were interviewed and invited to participate. Sealed, opaque envelopes concealed the group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random number table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary end-point was time to successful tracheal intubation.Sample size calculation was based on a previous study that compared  videolaryngoscope intubations with that of the intubating laryngeal mask in patients with normal airways. Power analysis showed that in order to show a difference of more than 50% in both groups with 80% power at 0.05 level of significance, 24 patients were needed in each group. 30 patients in each arm will be recruited to account for dropouts. 

Data are reported as mean (SD), medians [range] and incidences (both absolute and percentage). The normal distribution of data was tested using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Students t-test to analyze patient demographics and parametric data. The Mann-Whitney U-test was used to compare ASA status, Mallampati scores, ease of insertion/intubation, number of attempts needed between the two groups. Fishers exact test was used for comparison of side effects, and general linear model for repeated measures for haemodynamic variables. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 20.0 (SPSS, IBM Chicago, IL). P &lt;0.05 was considered significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Wendy H.L. Teoh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road, Singapore 229899</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Singapore</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Wendy H.L. Teoh</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road, Singapore 229899</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Singapore</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial compares intubation times and characteristics of using conventional direct Macintosh laryngoscopy vs. the novel KingVision videolaryngoscope to intubate the tracheas of 60 patients with normal airways.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Singhealth Centralised Institutional Review Board D</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Singapore Health Services Pte Ltd,
31 Third Hospital Avenue,
#03-03 Bowyer Block C,
Singapore 168753.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CIRB 2014-324-D</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Singapore</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wendy H.L Teoh</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia,
KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road. Singapore 229899.</address>
      <phone>+65- 63941081</phone>
      <fax>+65- 62912661</fax>
      <email> teohwendy@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wendy H.L Teoh</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia, 
KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road, Singapore 229899.
</address>
      <phone>+65- 63941081</phone>
      <fax>+65- 62912661</fax>
      <email>teohwendy@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wendy H.L Teoh</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia, 
KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road Singapore 229899.
</address>
      <phone>+65- 63941081</phone>
      <fax>+65- 62912661</fax>
      <email> teohwendy@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>