<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366961">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001013651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of a mandibular advancement appliance on Sleep Disordered Breathing in children </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of a mandibular advancement appliance on Sleep Disordered Breathing (Snoring and Obstructive Sleep Apnoea) in children</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1160-8387 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Kids Snoring Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sleep Disordered Breathing in Chlidren</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mandibular Advancement Splints (MAS)
The oral appliance that will be used in the study is a Twin-block design consisting of two removable plates; one is worn on the upper arch, the other on the lower. Each plate has matching pieces which encourage the lower jaw to posture or slide forward as the teeth come together(active MAS). 
 
The non-active appliance (sham MAS)
The Sham appliance consists of an upper and lower acrylic plate resembling the design of the active MAS, but without any component to protrude the mandible.



Children with Sleep Disordered Breathing (SDB) will be recruited and randomly assigned to two groups; both groups will receive the same treatment with active MAS and non-active MAS but in different sequences; the first group will receive three weeks treatment with active MAS, two week break (a wash-out period), and three weeks treatment with non-active MAS,the second group will receive the appliances in a reversed order. 

throughout the treatment periods a participant will be asked to wear the appliances while sleeping during the night time in addition to  2 hours during the daytime, The daily adherence to use the appliances will be monitored by providing the parents/guardians with a diary to record the actual time of appliance wearing. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (Sham MAS) will be used as a control intervention, the same participant will get the active intervention with the active mandibular advancement splints  and the participant will receive the treatment with splints resembling the design of the active MAS, but without any component to protrude the mandible. (Sham MAS)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apnea/Hypopnea Index (AHI  primary outcome) 
This is defined as number of apnea and hypopnea events recorded per hour of sleep. An apnea episode is defined as cessation of breathing for 10 seconds or longer. A hypopnea episode is defined as reduced respiratory airflow by 30% with a 4% decrease in oxygen saturation.
AHI will be assessed using the portable monitoring device. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This monitoring will be carried out four times during the study at the beginning and at the end of each treatment period .</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Snoring frequency and intensity 
Snoring sounds will be assessed using the portable PSG equipment. Reports of snoring frequency and intensity will also be collected by parents using daily diaries.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Snoring frequency and intensity will be assessed at the beginning and the end of each treatment period. Reports of snoring frequency and intensity will also be collected by parents using daily diaries.  
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep Questionnaires  
Sleep Disordered Breathing (SDB) associated symptoms will be assessed using the Pediatric Sleep Questionnaire. A questionnaire of sleep related breathing disorder scale (PSQ-SRBD scale) will also be completed by parents to ascertain the quality of the childs sleep including difficulties in getting to sleep, frequency of waking during the night, and alertness in the morning and daytime signs of sleepiness. It will also include questions about the history of the breathing difficulties during sleep, snoring, family history of SDB, and levels of household smoking. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>These questionnaires will be administered before and after each treatment period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Growth hormone levels
Blood samples will be taken from SDB children twice in the middle of each treatment period. A specialist in venipuncture will collect the samples to minimize discomfort and potential complications of venipuncture. Growth hormone will be assessed indirectly by determination of insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1) levels.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>after ten days of wearing the mandibular advancement splint and the sham splints for each participant. Then the a comparison will be done between the two times</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent-report of nocturnal enuresis
A child will be diagnosed as having urine incontinence when it occurs at least one night per week. This will be assessed during both treatment periods using diaries.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed during both treatment periods using diaries on weekly bases.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurobehavioral assessment
Behavioral changes will be assessed using the BASC-2 rating scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The BASC-2 questionnaire will be applied for four times during the study at the start and at the end of each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life
Quality of life in SDB children will be assessed using the OSA-18 and the Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory 'Trademark' (PQoL).Parents or caregivers will rate the frequency of symptoms before treatment and at the end of each treatment period.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>These questionnaires will be administered before and after each treatment period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Daytime sleepiness and related behavioral disturbances will be assessed using the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This questionnaire will be administered before and after each period of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: SDB diagnosis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: severe OSA (AHI more than ten events per hour);craniofacial syndromes and genetic syndromes; neuromuscular diseases; body mass index at or above 95th percentile of normative values.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>participants will draw a sealed opaque envelops to determine in which sequence a participant will go:
1- The mandibular advancement splints (Active MAS) in the first period of the treatment of 3 weeks, 2 weeks period of wash- out , then treatment with the Sham MAS for a period of 3 weeks.

2- The Sham MAS in the first period of the treatment of 3 weeks, 2 weeks period of wash- out, then treatment with Active MAS for a period of 3 weeks.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Because of using cross over design then it is not necessary to wait for having a specific number of participants to start the research.  
Participants will be recruited by advertising publicly and 16 participants will be allocated into two equal groups by a simple random way using sealed envelopes. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin </state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sir John Walsh Research Institute, PO Box 56, University of Otago, Dunedin 9054, New Zealand </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Ministry of Health Oral Health Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NZDA House Building 1, 195 Main Highway Ellerslie, Auckland 1051 PO Box 28084, Remuera 1541  </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand Association of Orthodontists, Foundation for Orthodontic Research &amp; Education, NZAO(FORENZAO) Charitable Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>27 Waimea Road, Nelson, 7010 New Zealand 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sleep-Disordered Breathing (SDB) varies from habitual snoring to completely stopped breathing and can be found in up to 10% of New Zealand children. SDB can cause breathlessness and frequent waking during sleep due to partial or complete obstruction of the upper airway. It can also cause growth disorders, daytime sleepiness, educational concerns, and behavioral problems. 
In the most severe cases, SDB can also lead to life-threatening events like heart failure. Therefore, SDB may have a significant impact on the well-being of children, and a considerable financial burden on the national health system. Thus, early diagnosis and treatment of SDB in children is vital to prevent health issues later.
Continuous positive air pressure and surgery (adenotonsillectomy) represent the primary treatment modalities for SDB in children. Mandibular Advancement Splints (MAS) represent an alternative treatment that is less invasive, cheaper, more comfortable and acceptable than other treatment modalities. While the efficacy of these appliances has been clearly demonstrated in adults, there is little information about their usefulness in children.
This project aims to determine the efficacy of mandibular advancement appliances for the management of SDB and related health problems in children. This project will utilise skills from multiple research groups, thus establishing a multidisciplinary research team for the study of SDB in children in New Zealand.
Children with SDB will be recruited and randomly assigned to two groups; both groups will receive the same treatment with active MAS and non-active MAS but in different sequences; the first group will receive three weeks treatment with active MAS, two weeks break, and three weeks treatment with non-active MAS, the second group will receive the appliances in a reversed order. Potential improvement in SDB symptoms and some other accompanied health related problems will be assessed using a portable breathing monitoring instrument, questionnaires, and collecting blood samples.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>the University of Otago Human Ethics Committee(Health)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Clocktower Building, University of Otago, PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054, New Zealand 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H14/054</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ngai Tahu Research Consultation Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ngai Tahu Research Consultation Committee
Research Division
University of Otago PO Box 56, Dunedin 9054 New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>No number available</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366961-Ethical Approval Letter -Efficacy of a mandinular appliace on sleep disordered breathing in children - Ghassan Idris.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366961-Maori Consultation- Efficacy of a mandinular appliace on sleep disordered breathing in children - Ghassan Idris.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366961(v17-09-2014-08-56-49)-Efficacy of a mandibular advancement appliance on sleep disordered breathing in children- Protocol-Ghassan Idris.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mauro Farella</name>
      <address>Discipline of Orthodontics, Department of Oral Sciences, School of Dentistry, University of Otago, 310 Great King Street, 9016 Dunedin, New Zealand.</address>
      <phone>+64(3) 479 5852 </phone>
      <fax>+643 479 7078</fax>
      <email>mauro.farella@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ghassan Idris</name>
      <address>Sir John Walsh Institute, School of Dentistry, University of Otago, 310 Great King Street, 9016 Dunedin, New Zealand.</address>
      <phone>+6434795664</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>idrgh523@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mauro Farella</name>
      <address>Discipline of Orthodontics, Department of Oral Sciences,  School of Dentistry, University of Otago, 310 Great King Street, 9016 Dunedin, New Zealand.</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5852 </phone>
      <fax>+643 479 7078</fax>
      <email>mauro.farella@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ghassan Idris</name>
      <address>Sir John Walsh Institute, School of Dentistry, University of Otago, 310 Great King Street, 9016 Dunedin, New Zealand.</address>
      <phone>+6434795664</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>idrgh523@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>