<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320824">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000673943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised trial of the effect of timing of nebulised hypertonic saline in relation to airway clearance physiotherapy, in people with Cystic Fibrosis lung disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised trial of the effect of timing of nebulised hypertonic saline in relation to airway clearance physiotherapy, on subjective efficacy, tolerability and overall satisfaction, and lung function parameters in adults with Cystic Fibrosis lung disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-0964</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following consent, subjects will be randomised to three timing regimes of 6% hypertonic saline (HS) inhalation over three days. Each day subjects will perform baseline spirometry, inhalation of bronchodilator, and inhalation of HS: either immediatly pre (not greater than 30 minutes pre), during (blocks of 10-15 breaths intersperced with airway clearance physiotherapy) or post (not greater than 30 minutes post) airway clearance physiotherapy in random order. 
The three inhalation regimes will be carried out over three consecutive days (no washout) at the end of a hospital admission when clinical signs have stabilised. The timing regime for that day will be performed for each airway clearance physiotherapy session. Participants will perform their usual daily number of airway clearance sessions (1-3), the same number will be performed on each of the study days. Each HS inhalation will be 4mLs (usually 15-20 minutes to deliver). Each airway clearance physiotherapy session will be 20-40 minutes with the duration for that participant similar for the three days.

A post treatment spirometry will be performed two hours post baseline spirometry each day and a VAS completed regarding ease of expectoration, tolerability and overall satisfaction for this order of inhalation and aiway clearance. The spirometry readings will be recorded with the afternoon physiotherapy treatment. Thus the pre and post spirometry readings are two hours apart at a similar time of the day on each of the study days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Three arm cross over. Standard treatment is inhalation of HS pre airway clearance physiotherapy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function (FEV1, FVC) as measured by Spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>A post treatment spirometry will be performed two hours post baseline spirometry each day The spirometry readings will be recorded with the afternoon physiotherapy treatment. Thus the pre and post spirometry readings are two hours apart at a similar time of the day on each of the study days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective efficacy, tolerability and overall satisfaction as measures on a VAS scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post treatment VAS scores will be performed two hours post baseline spirometry immediately prior to the post treatment spirometry each day The VAS readings will be recorded with the afternoon physiotherapy treatment. Thus the VAS readings are at a similar time of the day on each of the study days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria: provides informed consent; diagnosis of CF (sweat test or genotyping); Greater than or equal to 18 yrs; FEV1 within 10% of best FEV1 in the previous 6 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria: colonisation with B. cepacia;; major hemoptysis in the preceeding month; previous lung transplant; thrombocytopaenia; pregnancy or at risk of pregnancy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following consent, subjects will be randomised to three timing regimes of HS inhalation over three days (sequence of three interventions in sealed opaque envelopes). Each day subjects will perform baseline spirometry, inhalation of bronchodilator, and inhalation of HS (either pre, during or post airway clearance physiotherapy in random order).</concealment>
    <sequence>An independent blinded researcher generated sequences of inhalation for before, during and after airway clearance for the anticipated 50 participants (power calculation) using a dice roll. The order of inhalations was then sealed in an opaque envelope prior to the studies commencement.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants were aware of the timing of inhalations. Assessors were blinded to the order io inhalations.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, SSWAHS</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Missenden Road Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Missenden Road Camperdown NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Research question: To determine whether the timing of HS inhalation (before, during or after airway clearance physiotherapy) impacts the subjective efficacy, tolerability and overall satisfaction, or lung function parameters in adults with cystic fibrosis</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SSWAHS (RPA Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Building 92, RPAH
Missenden Road Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/12/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Protocol No X09-0283 &amp; HREC/09/RPAH/477</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ruth Dentice</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine
Level 11 West, Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 9515 5234</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>ruth.dentice@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ruth Dentice</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine
Level 11 West, Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 9515 5234</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>ruth.dentice@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ruth Dentice</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine
Level 11 West, Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 9515 5234</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>ruth.dentice@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>