<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366569">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000726651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The role of wheat gluten in the genesis of gastrointestinal symptoms and mental health in patients with non-coeliac gluten sensitivity: Understanding the mechanism of action.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The role of wheat gluten in the genesis of gastrointestinal symptoms and mental health in patients with non-coeliac gluten sensitivity: Understanding the mechanism of action.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-coeliac gluten sensitivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Food is supplemented with gluten: Participants will be asked to consume 2 muesli bars per day for two weeks. Each muesli bar will contain 8g of gluten. Participants will keep a food diary to monitor compliance. A two week 'wash out' period will be applied between treatment arms. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Food is not supplemented (placebo): Participants will be asked to consume 2 muesli bars per day for two weeks. The muesli bars will not have any additional supplements.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in psychological state following the consumption of gluten. Psychological state will be assessed using the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following treatment exposure (day 14)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in psychological state following the consumption of gluten. Psychological state will be assessed using the State Trait Personality Inventory
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following treatment exposure (day 14)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in psychological state following the consumption of gluten. Psychological state will be assessed using the Irritable Bowel Syndrome Quality of Life Questionnaire

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following treatment exposure (day 14)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: Change in cognitive function following the consumption of gluten. Cognitive function will be assessed using the Subtle Cognitive Impairment Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary timepoint: Following treatment exposure (day 14)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in gastrointestinal symptoms following the consumption of gluten. Gastrointestinal symptoms will be assessed using a 100mm visual analogue scale. Gastrointestinal symptoms will be reported as a composite secondary outcome. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Following treatment exposure (day 14)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Following a gluten-free diet has relieved gut symptoms
(2) Following a gluten-free diet makes patient 'feel better'
(3) Patient has had coeliac disease excluded
(4) Patient is currently adherent to a gluten-free diet
(5) Patient has well-controlled symptoms on a gluten-free diet</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Marsh 1 or 2 lesions
(2) Other significant gastrointestinal disease
(3) Other clinically significant co-morbidity
(4) Psychiatric disease
(5) Pregnancy
(6) Alcoholism</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who meet inclusion criteria will be invited to participate. Allocation of the subject for inclusion in the trial will be based on central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated list</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>49</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Gastroenterology
Level 6, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1/16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Andrea Joy Logan Scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Provided by a private family</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gluten is believed to be poorly tolerated by many Australians and is often blamed for causing a wide range of gastrointestinal and psychological symptoms. Commonly reported gastrointestinal symptoms include; abdominal pain, bloating, flatulence and altered bowel habit, as frequently reported by people suffering from irritable bowel syndrome. Commonly reported psychological symptoms include; anxiety, depression and a reduction in quality of life. 

The best studied gluten intolerance is coeliac disease.  Coeliac disease is an auto-immune condition that occurs in 1% of the Australian population. The only available treatment for coeliac disease is life-long strict avoidance of gluten containing foods (including wheat, rye and barley).  While the average daily gluten intake in a Western diet is 10-20 g (equivalent to 2-5 slices of wheat-bread), in people with coeliac disease, 50 mg (equivalent to 1/100th of one slice of wheat-bread) gluten can cause damage to the lining of the small intestine. 

Non-coeliac Gluten Sensitivity:
There is another (much larger) group of individuals, however, who believe that gluten can also cause these types of symptoms and yet, after extensive investigations by doctors and specialists, are shown not to have coeliac disease. This group of people are often referred to as having non coeliac gluten sensitivity. This condition, however, is very poorly understood and recognised by the medical profession.

Evidence for the Existence of Non-coeliac Gluten Sensitivity:
Recently completed dietary studies undertaken by our research team have found conflicting evidence for the induction of gastrointestinal symptoms following the ingestion of gluten in people believing they have non-coeliac gluten sensitivity. While an original study found good evidence that gluten can indeed cause gastrointestinal symptoms in some individuals who do not have coeliac disease this finding was not confirmed in subsequent studies.

Furthermore, our most recent study showed convincing evidence for a specific effect of gluten on mental health. In this study results indicated that short term exposure to gluten specifically induced current feelings of depression. Such findings suggest that a major effect of gluten amongst this population may be on mental health and not necessarily on gastrointestinal symptoms. This finding would also explain why participants report feeling better on the gluten-free diet despite the continuation of gastrointestinal symptoms.

Outcomes and Significance:
The purpose of this study is to investigate the role that gluten has in causing gastrointestinal symptoms and changes to mental health in people who believe they have non-coeliac gluten sensitivity. The results from this study will provide us with a more comprehensive understanding of the relationship between gluten and its influence on gastrointestinal symptoms and mental health.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Ethics and Research Governance </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>232/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Gibson</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Level 6, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61, 03, 9076 3325</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.gibson@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Simone Peters</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Level 6, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61, 03, 9903 0262</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simone.peters@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Simone Peters</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Level 6, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61, 03, 9903 0262</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simone.peters@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>