<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362328">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000397819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Brain-based learning and animated cartoons in health education</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of Brain-Based Learning and Animated Cartoons for Enhancing Healthy Habits among School Children in Khon Kaen, Thailand</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-5405</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>'Nil'</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of a range of health problems (e.g. dental caries, obesity, various communicable diseases) by means of health education to improve healthy behaviours in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Brain-based learning (BBL), video compact disc presentation of animated cartoons (VCD), and conventional teaching ( control group). 
The trial duration was 16 weeks The intervention for experimental group 1(Exp.gr.1: BBL+VCD) involved teachers inserting the BBL technique into regular classroom sessions for the students (at least 15 minutes every day) and then students watched a VCD animated cartoon. There was one cartoon story lasting 2-3 minutes for each of the Thai Ten Commandments for Health (TTCH), and new cartoon was used each day for 10 consecutive days. The students were able to repeat the same story as much as they wanted at the same day, and the cycle of one of the 10 VCD cartoons per day was repeated over the 16 week period of the trial. The intervention for experimental group 2 (Exp.gr.2: BBL only), was the same as for experimental group 1, but with the VCD component omitted. The intervention for experimental group 3 (Exp.gr. 3: VCD only) was the same as for experimental group 1, but with the BBL component omitted.  The intervention for group 4 was the control condition in which children were exposed to the classroom teaching of the TTCH using conventional teaching methods (ie without either BBL or VCD) for 15 minutes every day for 16 weeks. In each of the 4 groups, the teaching of the TTCH was supervised by the usual classroom teacher.

1.The BBL technique included the following six features: 1) readiness - creating an environment that fully immerses learners in the learning experience through various physical activities; 2) relaxation - trying to eliminate fear in learners while maintaining a highly challenging environment; 3) brain gym - exercising the brain in conjunction with classical music for five minutes; 4) brain linkage - reviewing a previous experience and linking it to a new experience by asking questions; 5) active processing - allowing the learner to consolidate and internalize information for the sole purpose of practicing healthy habits; and 6) agreement inducing practice - asking the learners to promise to practice the healthy habits that they learned both at school and at home every day.

2. The Thai Ten Commandments for Health as follows:

1.Personal hygiene including clean clothes and dressing
2.Clean teeth thoroughly and do this every day
3.Wash hands before eating and after using the toilet
4. Eat food that is cooked, clean, and without hazardous chemicals; do not eat food mixed with hazardous colors
5. No smoking, no alcohol, no drugs, no gambling, and no unsafe sex
6. Build strong relationships within the family
7. Prevent accidents by being careful
8. Exercise regularly and see the doctor annually for a health check up
9. Keep good mental health
10. Take on responsibilities and do something beneficial for society

3.LCD projectors and computer screens or television sets as visual aids were provided for  VCD cartoons at classrooms.</interventions>
    <comparator>Conventional teaching, the control group, the teachers lectured students about TTCH (at least 15 minutes every day for 16 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in knowledge and reported practice of healthy behaviours. A specially constructed self-report questionnaire, was used to assess the quantitative outcomes.
The name of this self-report questionnaire is "Self-evaluation practices of the Thai Ten Commandments for Health for students"</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 16 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>no</outcome>
      <timepoint>no</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The subjects were selected by a multi-stage sampling process in which the first stage was the identification of 40 medium-sized primary schools with similar numbers of students and teachers. A feasibility survey was then conducted to determine whether the schools were able and willing to participate in the study and, as a result, additional inclusion criteria were added: (1) the schools finally selected should not have BBL as a teaching technique, (2) they should not have used an LCD projector, computer screens or television sets as visual aids for teaching their students, and (3) the school administrators, students and their parents must consent to cooperate with the study requirements.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>9</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>School using brain-based learning and/or VCD animated cartoons of Thai Ten Commandments for Health</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Twenty-two schools met the criteria for inclusion in the study.  Sixteen schools were then selected by simple random sampling, and four schools were randomly assigned to one of three experimental groups or the control group: 263 children in experimental Group 1 were exposed to the BBL in conjunction with VCD cartoons, 254 children in Group 2 were solely exposed to BBL, 295 children in Group 3 were exposed only to VCD cartoons, and 273 children served as a control group which was exposed only to conventional methods of teaching about TTCH. Allocation was concealed by the use of numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>The random allocation of four schools to the three experimental groups and the single control group was done by simple randomization using procedures like drawing tickets in a raffle. All the school were given a number 1-16, and then four numbers drawn at random for each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>no</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/05/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1085</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <state>Khon Kaen Province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Thai Health Promotion Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>979/116-120 S.M.Tower Floor 34 Paholyothin Rd., Samsen Nai, Payathai, Bangkok 10400</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Thailand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Thai Health Promotion Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>979/116-120 S.M.Tower Floor 34 Paholyothin Rd., Samsen Nai, Payathai, Bangkok 10400</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Thailand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The results of the multiple comparison tests showed that, for knowledge, BBL+VCD was more effective than VCD on its own (p&lt;0.01) and was not significantly better than BBL on its own (p=0.09). The educational impact of a set of VCD was  not significant different  from that of BBL in knowledge of healthy habits, and the addition of BBL to VCD made no significant did not improve the effectiveness of VCD in improving healthy practices. While the BBL process alone improved practice of healthy habits more than VCD did on its own (p&lt;0.01). For both knowledge and practices, the children in all the experimental groups did better than those in the control group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>no</trialwebsite>
    <publication>An oral  presentation at Thailand Research Symposium 2011 on Aug 26-30, 2011, Bangkok, Thailand</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Khon Kaen University Ethics Committee for Human Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Khon Kaen University Ethics Committee for Human Research Office, 17th Floor, Princess Mother Memorial Building, Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University, Mitraphap Road, Khon Kaen, 40002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE510911</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Thailand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pannee Banchonhattekit</name>
      <address>Department of Health Education. Faculty of Public Health, Khon Kaen University, Mittraphap Road, Muang District, Khon Kaen province, 40002</address>
      <phone>+66 4 336 2077</phone>
      <fax>+66 4 334 7058</fax>
      <email>panban@kku.ac.th</email>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pannee Banchonhattekit</name>
      <address>Department of Health Education. Faculty of Public Health, Khon Kaen University, Mittraphap Road, Muang District, Khon Kaen province, 40002</address>
      <phone>+66 4 336 2077</phone>
      <fax>+66 4 334 7058</fax>
      <email>panban@kku.ac.th</email>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pannee Banchonhattekit</name>
      <address>Department of Health Education. Faculty of Public Health, Khon Kaen University, Mittraphap Road, Muang District, Khon Kaen province, 40002</address>
      <phone>+66 4 336 2077</phone>
      <fax>+66 4 334 7058</fax>
      <email>panban@kku.ac.th</email>
      <country>Thailand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>