<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82750">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/06/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000286347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of exercise options in newly-diagnosed patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial of exercise training versus standard guideline-based care on vascular function in subjects with newly-diagnosed type 2 diabetes mellitus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Comparing intensive exercise regime (physiotherapy led sessions  3x 1hr per week) with standard guideline exercise (self led 30 minutes of moderate exertion on most days per week).
Total duration of study is 22 weeks (once 32 subjects have been recruited) 
There will be 2 weeks between crossing over.</interventions>
    <comparator>1st arm - Comparison of intensive exercise regime versus active control. Active control includes exercise advice given as standard care out with the trial.
2nd arm - Comparison of self directed exercise program following New Zealand guidelines on exercise versus active control. Active control includes exercise advice given as standard care out with the trial.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in flow-mediated dilation in the brachial artery in the forearm before and after the administration of sub-lingual Glyceryl trinitrate. We will be using a portable ultrasound device (General Electrics ? Logiq e) to make the brachial artery measurements.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and after each 8 week exercise intervention (which may include active control)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central aortic blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, and after each 8 week exercise intervention (which may include active control)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in mean brachial blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and after each 8 week exercise intervention (which may include active control)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in fasting lipid levels (cholesterol, HDL-c, &amp; triglyceride). This will be assessed using blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and after each 8 week exercise intervention (which may include active control)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in urine albumin:creatinine ratio</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and after each 8 week exercise intervention (which may include active control)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in insulin resistance as calculated by homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and after each 8 week exercise intervention (which may include active control)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Quality of life as measured by the Short Form 36 (SF-36) Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and after each 8 week exercise intervention (which may include active control)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients to be included in this protocol must:
1. Be aged &gt;30 years and =60 years
2. Have type 2 diabetes mellitus (maximum of 2 years since diagnosis) in accordance with American Diabetes Association criteria treated with diet or metformin oral hypoglycemic medication with an HbA1c 6.5-10% at baseline.
3. Provide written informed consent to participate in the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A patient with any of the following conditions prior to randomisation will not be enrolled into the study:
1. Diabetic nephropathy (urine albumin creatinine ratio (ACR) &gt;200mg/mmol) 
2. Known non-diabetic renal disease as indicated by haematuria, active urinary sediment or casts
3. Serum creatinine &gt;150 µmol/L in men and ?130 µmmol/L in women
4. Morbid obesity with body mass &gt;160kg
5. Abnormal baseline Electrocardiogram (ECG), or inducible ischaemic changes on baseline exercise tolerance test
6. Pregnant, nursing a child, or planning a pregnancy at the time of this study
7. History of type 1 diabetes defined as age of onset &lt;20 years and/or history of continuous treatment with insulin since diagnosis
8. History of cigarette smoking, drug or alcohol abuse
9. Co-morbid conditions that are likely t o affect ability to participate in an exercise program:
a. Severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) as evidenced by hospitalization for decompensation within 6 months of randomization, chronic treatment with oral steroids, or a resting oxygen saturation (SAO2) &lt;90 mm Hg
b. Congestive heart failure (CHF) corresponding with New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class II, III and IV or an N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide (NT-proBNP) level &gt;350
c. Severe ischaemic heart disease (IHD) with acute coronary event, and/or coronary artery bypass graft (CABG), and/or percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) in the previous 60 days.
d. Severe peripheral vascular disease
e. Severe arthritic disease of the feet, knees, hips, or lower spine
f. Severe liver disease with icterus and plasma bilirubin =60 µmmol/L, plasma transaminase = 3-fold upper limit of normal, albumin &lt;30 g/L or coagulopathy 
g. Hematological disorders including hemoglobin &lt;110 g/L or platelet count &lt; 80,000/mm3
10. Gastrointestinal bleeding in the previous 60 days, 
11. Malignancy other than basal cell carcinoma.
12. Any other disease or condition which in the opinion of the investigator could make them unsuitable for entry.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is at a central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>2 separate parallel cross-over groups</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Clinical Research &amp; effective practice (CCRep)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Clinical Research &amp; effective practice (CCRep)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 2 diabetes mellitus has become a significant health problem worldwide, and Counties-Manukau has a disproportionately high prevalence of diabetic people compared to other regions in New Zealand. This is because of the high proportion of Maori and Pacific people who are genetically susceptible, more likely to be obese, and less likely to exercise. Compared with non-diabetic individuals, type 2 diabetic patients have a 3-4 fold increased risk of macrovascular disease and often succumb to coronary artery disease and stroke. Treatment of diabetes based solely on dietary and pharmacologic interventions is difficult and often fails. It is well recognised that some increase in regular exercise is essential to deliver long-term weight reduction and to meet management targets for glucose, lipid and blood pressure control. Yet, recent research studies give confusing and sometimes contradictory messages about the optimal frequency and intensity of exercise.  The aim of the current study is to investigate whether a regular intensive supervised circuit training regimen will provide better vascular outcomes compared with the standard exercise advice provided in the New Zealand Type 2 Diabetes Guideline (2002) in a group of newly-diagnosed type 2 diabetic subjects.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health, 3rd Floor, Unisys Building, 650 Great South Road, Private Bag 92522, Penrose, Auckland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/07/12/136</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Ajith Dissnayake</name>
      <address>Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 21 977 839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>AMDiss@middlemore.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kenneth Muir</name>
      <address>Middlemore Hospital
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 9 276 0044 extn 2946</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>MuirK@middlemore.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>