<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372004">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000006347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of GAME (Goals Activity Motor Enrichment) for infants at high risk of cerebral palsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Harnessing Neuroplasticity to Improve Motor Performance in Infants with Cerebral Palsy: a Pragmatic Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>GAME trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>1120031 (NHMRC)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cerebral palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: GAME (Goals Activity Motor enrichment) has 3 key elements
1.  Motor training. Motor goals  are first identified by parents and then the therapist identifies and explains to families the factors limiting performance. Training is then designed to target goal achievement. Training is goal-oriented, relevant, task specific, providing the necessary repetition required to learn to perform the new goal behaviours independently. 
2.  Parent coaching in motor training. During the dace to face sessions, parents are coached in how to provide motor training and cognitive stimulation within their childs natural playtime. They are educated about usual developmental trajectories and how to advance progress. 
3. Environmental enrichment.  GAME is provided in the natural home environment where training is personalised to the infants enjoyment  translating to more intense, specific and relevant practice. GAME intervention enriches the: (a) physical environment by setting up the home with activities and materials entice infant-generated motor practice at the appropriate level of challenge; (b) cognitive environment by encouraging infant problem solving and self-correction of errors; (c) sensory environment by providing evidence-based interventions that improve backdrop capacity for learning; and (d) social environment by coaching parents to be sensitive, responsive and communicative to infant cues.
This intervention is designed to be individualised to the child and family
DOSE: intervention sessions will be offered weekly from enrolment until age 2 years (corrected for prematurity). A maximum of 91 sessions (depending on age at enrolment) will be provided.
Each session will be about 1 hour. Parents will carry out a home programme to increase the dose but it will be up to the parents how much they do based on family ecology and preferences. 
WHO: GAME intervention will be provided by a physiotherapist and/or occupational therapist. The therapists will design the home program in collaboration with the family and it will be provided in written format.
FIDELITY: Intervention fidelity will be assessed by the chief investigators using a fidelity checklist, appraisal of home programs and site visits
</interventions>
    <comparator>STANDARD CARE INTERVENTION: "Standard care (SC) describes the current follow-up and/or therapeutic interventions used when an infant at high risk of CP is discharged from hospital. It is not possible to standardise the frequency, intensity or type of interventions received in the SC group. Therapeutic approaches used and modes and intensity of delivery are varied. All SC providers tend to use a combination of centre based visits and home programs. Some infants in SC will receive home visits as well as clinic based appointments. Intervention approaches vary and are typically eclectic borrowing from a variety of therapy intervention paradigms including neurodevelopmental therapy and the developmental skills approach.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peabody Developmental Motor Scales - second edition</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary end point is 24 months, interim measures will be taken at 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gross Motor Function Measure-66</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary end point is 24 months, interim measures will be taken at 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PEDI-CAT</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary end point is 24 months, interim measures will be taken at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development -III (cognition)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary end point is 24 months, interim measures will be taken at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infant Toddler Quality of Life Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary end point is 24 months, interim measures will be taken at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) will be acquired on 3T scanners. Along with standard radiological images, we will acquire high-resolution structural images and multi-shell high angular resolution diffusion weighted images (HARDI; R1,R2). Structural images will be used to investigate cortical thickness and folding, sulcal depth, deep gray matter volumes, and ventricular shape and their relationship to motor skills. Diffusion images will be used to assess structural connectivity (connectome) using an approach adapted from that described by us previously. Structural integrity of connections will be assessed using quantitative metrics, including corrected streamline number (R3) and neurite orientation dispersion index (R2), as well as standard diffusion tensor metrics (fractional anisotropy, mean diffusivity). The relationship between structural integrity of connections and motor skills will be investigated</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Please update to (c) Diagnosis of cerebral palsy OR
(d) diagnosis of high risk of cerebral palsy via:
 (i) General Movements Absent fidgety score + abnormal brain MRI/CUS indicating cerebral palsy; OR (ii) General Movements Absent fidgety score + Hammersmith Infant Neurological Evaluation score &lt;57@ 12-weeks / &lt;59 @ 26-weeks of age; OR (iii) Abnormal brain MRI/CUS indicating cerebral palsy + Hammersmith Infant Neurological Evaluation score &lt;57@ 12-weeks / &lt;59@ 26-weeks of age </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion (B) should now read:
"severe vision impairment (unable to fix and follow in good light)"</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After consent and baseline measures, infants will be centrally randomised to GAME or control intervention from concealed opaque envelopes obtained by the site investigator over the phone from independent personnel at a non-study site.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be computer generated at the Clinical Trials Centre. Participants will be stratified by site and by severity of neonatal brain injury score to ensure treatment balance across groups. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analyses will employ the Full Analysis Set comprising all randomised patients, by intention to treat. Primary outcome and other continuous variables will be compared by t-tests and general linear models when normally distributed and with equivalent non-parametric tests when they are not. The primary analysis will assess the effect of the intervention unadjusted for any baseline factors. Secondary analysis will assess the effect of the intervention adjusted for baseline patient characteristics including, neonatal MRI motor severity scores, age at enrolment, parents socioeconomic status, and total dose of therapy.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/12/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Sydney Children's Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Mother's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Casey Hospital - Berwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Frankston Hospital - Frankston</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3806 - Berwick</postcode>
    <postcode>3021 - St Albans</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>3076 - Epping</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Camperdown, Sydney 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421. Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Cerebral Palsy Alliance</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest, NSW 2086
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Each year, 600 Australians are diagnosed with cerebral palsy with a $4 billion annual socioeconomic burden. One third never walk. The National Disability Insurance Scheme ranks early intervention to improve disability as its top priority.
We have developed an early training intervention ("GAME" Goals Activity Motor Enrichment) based on the key neuroscience principles of activity dependent plasticity and enriched environments and on successful training interventions known to work in older children with cerebral palsy and adults post stroke.
GAME is the only published protocol of an infant friendly early, intense, specific training intervention grounded in contemporary neuroscience, tested for safety and early efficacy, and is acceptable to parents. 
This new pragmatic, single blind randomised controlled trial (RCT) in 300 infants with cerebral palsy or at high risk of cerebral palsy aims to evaluate the effects of GAME versus traditional passive early intervention on gross and fine motor skills at two years of age. We will also evaluate the secondary outcomes of neuroplasticity on MRI,
cognitive skills and quality of life. In this pragmatic trial, infants will receive experimental GAME training (once weekly therapist provided+ daily parent provided) versus control (traditional therapy alone). Both groups will be dose matched according to the standard
National Disability Insurance Scheme early intervention funding package. Experimental and control treatments will continue until the infants 2nd birthday.
Assessments will be carried out at baseline, prior to randomisation and at 1 and 2 years of age (corrected for prematurity).
The expected clinical outcomes of our trial are that infants who received our intervention will have significant and lasting motor and cognitive gains that lessen the severity of their cerebral palsy and improve their quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cerebral Palsy Alliance HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-11-03</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Iona Novak</name>
      <address>Cerebral Palsy Alliance Research Institute
The University of Sydney
PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 409078917</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>inovak@cerebralpalsy.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Iona Novak</name>
      <address>Cerebral Palsy Alliance Research Institute
The University of Sydney
PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 409078917</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>inovak@cerebralpalsy.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Iona Novak</name>
      <address>Cerebral Palsy Alliance Research Institute
The University of Sydney
PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 409078917</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>inovak@cerebralpalsy.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cathy Morgan</name>
      <address>Cerebral Palsy Alliance Research Institute
The University of Sydney
PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086
</address>
      <phone>+61 408205542</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cmorgan@cerebralpalsy.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>