<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368855">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001083482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The VOICE Study  Valuing Opinions, Individual Communication and Experience: Building the evidence base for undertaking Patient-Centred Family Meetings in palliative care: a mixed methods study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is a Patient-Centred Family Meeting intervention feasible and acceptable in specialist palliative care units?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The VOICE Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Palliative Care</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The proposed intervention is a planned face to face Patient-Centred Family Meeting held soon after admission to an inpatient unit at the specialist palliative care facility where the intervention is being undertaken. The duration of the meeting will be 60 minutes, although this may vary depending on the needs of the patient and other participants.  The patient needs and concerns are pre-eminent, along with those of the family member(s). The intervention is designed to be "patient-centred" with the focus of the meeting being on the patient setting the agenda in advance so that their concerns and issues are addressed. This is in contrast to the usual model of family meetings where the agenda is led by the health care team.  The meeting will be scheduled as soon after the patient's admission as is practicable rather than on an "ad hoc" basis and be conducted in a private space unless the condition of the patient makes this inappropriate. The patients will be requested to invite the family member(s) they wish to attend the meeting and will be encouraged to invite whomever they consider as "family", and not necessarily blood relatives.  The meeting will be convened with members of the palliative care multidisciplinary team, with facilitation provided by the palliative care consultant or registrar.  Discussion at the meeting may include clinical and psycho-social issues, preparation for death, and other key areas of importance for that patient and family. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control arm of the study will be the usual standard of care for palliative care inpatients at a second specialist palliative care facility. For these patients, standard care may include a family meeting, either planned or "ad hoc", if required by the palliative care team or requested by the their family/carer(s) and/or patient. However patients recruited at the control site may not participate in a family meeting as part of their care. Any scheduled family meeting will be run according to current practice at the control site.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the feasibility of a Patient-Centred Family Meeting in specialist palliative care units for patients, families and clinicians. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the intervention site, a Patient-Centred Family Meeting Semi-structured Interview Schedule will be undertaken with participating patients 1-2 days post-meeting which includes questions related to the feasibility of the Patient-Centred Family Meeting.
At the control site,  a Patient semi-structured Interview Schedule will be completed post-meeting if the patient participates in a family meeting as part of standard care. 
At the intervention site, a Patient-Centred Family Meeting Feedback Questionnaire will be completed by the family participant post meeting (by Day 14) of the patient admission which includes questions related to the feasibility of the Patient-Centred Family Meeting.
At the control site, a Family Meeting Feedback Questionnaire will be completed post meeting (by Day 14) of the patient admission if a family participates in a family meeting as part of standard care.
At the intervention site, the Patient-Centred Family Meeting Multidisciplinary Staff Focus Group Semi-Structured Interview Schedule will be used to evaluate the feasibility of clinicians participating in Patient-Centred Family Meetings in. Clinicians will only be required to attend one focus group according to their availability.
A Family Meeting Observation Sheet will record key elements of the Patient-Centred Family Meeting during the meeting, including participants' (patients, families, clinicians) attendance, reasons for non-attendance of participants, patient agenda completed and used during the meeting, time of meeting and be used to assess feasibility.
Screening to recruitment ratio, time taken to recruit and recruitment drop-outs will also be recorded. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the acceptability of a Patient-Centred Family Meeting in specialist palliative care units for patients, families and clinicians.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the intervention site, a Patient-Centred Family Meeting Semi-structured Interview Schedule will be undertaken with participating patients 1-2 days post-meeting which includes questions related to the acceptability of the Patient-Centred Family Meeting.
At the control site,  a Patient semi-structured Interview Schedule will be completed post-meeting if the patient participates in a family meeting as part of standard care.
At the intervention site, a Patient-Centred Family Meeting Feedback Questionnaire will be completed by the family participant post meeting (by Day 14) of the patient admission which includes questions related to the acceptability of the Patient-Centred Family Meeting.
At the control site, a Family Meeting Feedback Questionnaire will be completed post meeting (by Day 14) of the patient admission if a family participates in a family meeting as part of standard care.
At the intervention site, the Patient-Centred Family Meeting Multidisciplinary Staff Focus Group Semi-Structured Interview Schedule will be used to evaluate the acceptability of clinicians participating in Patient-Centred Family Meetings. Clinicians will only be required to attend one focus group according to their availability.
A Family Meeting Observation Sheet will record key elements of the Patient-Centred Family Meeting during the meeting and be used to assess acceptability.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the suitability of the measures from the patient and family perspective.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the intervention site, the QUAL-EC (Patient) and National Cancer Collaborative Network (NCCN) Distress Thermometer will be completed by patients prior to participation in a Patient-Centred Family Meeting and 1-2 days post Meeting. At the control site the same measures will be completed with the patient completing the baseline measures Day 3-5 of admission and repeat measures Day 7-10 following admission. Questions will be included in the Patient Semi-structured Interview Schedule to assess the suitability of the patient measures. This will include the patient's views about the relevance of the questions and their preference for any particular measure(s), A proportion of family members from the intervention and control sites will also participate in an interview which will include discussion about the family member's views about the relevance of the questions and their preference for any particular measure(s).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the feasibility of the measures from the patient and family perspective.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the intervention site, the QUAL-E (Family) National Cancer Collaborative Network (NCCN) Distress Thermometer (Holland, 1999) and PHQ-4 (Patient Health Questionnaire-4 Family) will be completed by families prior to participation in a Patient-Centred Family Meeting and Day 14 of patient admission. 
At the control site the same measures will be completed at the same time points as the intervention site. 
Completion rates of the patient and family measures and amount of missing data will be recorded following completion of the measures by patients and family members.
Questions will be included in the Patient Semi-structured Interview Schedule to assess the feasibility of the patient measures.  This will include time taken to complete the measures and any issues the patient had with completing the measures. 
A proportion of family members from the intervention and control sites will also participate in an interview which will include discussion about time taken to complete the measures and any issues the family member had with completing the measures,</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patient inclusion criteria
(a)	Adult patient aged over 18 years who have been admitted to a participating specialist palliative inpatient facility within the last 7 days;
(b)	Have a terminal illness (a prognosis of less than 12 months, but expected to live at least 14 days i.e. the average length of the protocol);
(c)	Able to identify a family member (or equivalent person) who consents to participate in the study involving attendance at the Patient-Centred Family Meeting or standard family meeting if convened;
(d)	Are classified in accordance with the Palliative Care Outcomes Collaboration (PCOC) palliative care phases at time of recruitment as being either Stable, Unstable or Deteriorating;
(e)	Able to physically participate in a Patient-Centred Family Meeting assessed using the Australian Modified Karnofsky Performance Score and obtaining a score of greater than or equal to 30;
(f)	Be able to read and speak English (patients who are visually impaired will be offered assistance with the consent forms and surveys);
(g)	Be able to provide valid, informed consent.

Family inclusion criteria
(a)	18 years of age or older;
(b)	Invited by the patient to participate in a Patient-Centred Family Meeting;
(c)	English language and cognitive skills are sufficient to complete baseline information and validated questionnaires and who are able to contribute effectively in the Patient-Centred Family Meeting or standard family meeting if convened;
(d)	Be able to provide valid, informed consent and participate in the Patient-Centred Family Meeting.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient exclusion criteria
a)	Terminal phase (Phase 4 measured by the PCOC Phase assessment) or imminently dying; 
b)	Presence of delirium measured by validated tool e.g. NuDESC (Leonard et al.);
c)	Be cognitively impaired measured by the Mini-Mental State Examination assessment with a score &lt; 24/30; 
d)	Not able to identify a family member (or equivalent person) who agrees to participate in the Patient-Centred Family Meeting or standard family meeting if convened;
e)	Not able to read and speak English;
f)     Patients who experience significant family conflict such as an abusive family relationship or history of domestic violence.

Family exclusion criteria
(a)	Less than 18 years of age;;
(b)	Has been excluded by the patient to participate in the Patient-Centred Family Meeting;
(c)	English language or cognitive skills are not sufficient to complete baseline information and validated questionnaires and who are unable to contribute effectively in the Patient-Centred Family Meeting or a standard family meeting if convened. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>The intervention arm will be Greenwich Hospital (HammondCare), Greenwich and all patients eligible for the study will be recruited to the intervention. 
The control arm will be Sacred Heart Supportive and Palliative Care Service, St Vincent's Hospital, Darlinghurst.
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Mixed method quasi-experimental study with pre-post-test data collection using a control and an intervention site.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) will be used to analyze the quantitative data.  
Descriptive statistics will be used to summarise the baseline and follow-up data including demographics, Distress Thermometer, PHQ-4, QUAL-EC, QUAL-E (Family).  Differences on these variables (Distress Thermometer, QUAL-EC and QUAL-E (Family) between the intervention group and control group will be assessed.   
The data from the Patient Semi-structured Interviews, Family Feedback Questionnaires and staff focus groups will be analysed taking theoretical and procedural direction from grounded theory.
As this is a feasibility study there is no way to conduct a sample size calculation since no information on the effect size of the outcome is available. The number of participants for the qualitative component of the study has been considered to be a minimum of 20 for each patient and family group in the two arms of the study.  Creswell (1998) supported a 20-30 sample size when using grounded theory and this method will be used for the qualitative analysis.  The qualitative nature of the study will be supplemented by the addition of patient and family quantitative measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/08/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/07/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>8</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sacred Heart Hospice - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Greenwich Hospital - Greenwich</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - Greenwich</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Jane Phillips</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Professor of Nursing, 
Director IMPACCT - Improving Palliative, Aged and Chronic Care through Clinical Research and Translation
Faculty of Health 
University of Technology Sydney 
PO Box 123
Ultimo NSW 2007</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Notre Dame Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 944
Broadway  NSW  2007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Liz Lobb</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Research Cottage
Calvary Health Care Kogarah
PO Box 261
Kogarah  NSW  1485</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Christine Sanderson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>C/O Research Cottage
Calvary Health Care Kogarah
 PO Box 261 
Kogarah NSW 1485</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to determine if a planned Patient-Centred Family Meeting held soon after a patients admission to an inpatient palliative care unit, is feasible and acceptable to the patient, their family and clinicians. In addition, the study seeks to better understand the benefits and burden of participating in Patient-Centred Family Meetings from the perspective of the patient, family and clinician and to assess if the outcome measures that have been selected are suitable and feasible from the patient and family perspective. 
The primary hypothesis is that conducting a planned Patient-Centred Family Meeting soon after admission to a specialist inpatient palliative care unit is feasible and acceptable to patients, families and clinicians.
The Patient-Centred Family Meeting will be the intervention in one of two specialist palliative care facilities. The other facility will be the control site where standard care, that may include a family meeting, is provided and observed. Inpatients aged over 18 years with a terminal illness newly admitted to one of the two palliative care facilities who are able to consent and have a family member willing to participate will be included. A minimum of 20 patients and a minimum of an equivalent number of family members will be recruited at each site. More than one family member may be included in recruitment. 
At the intervention site, outcome measures will assess patient and family distress and satisfaction with quality of life at end-of-life, before and after the Patient-Centred Family Meeting. Interviews with patients and families and focus groups with clinicians will be undertaken after the Patient-Centred Family Meeting to understand the experience of these participants concerning the intervention. A Family Meeting Observation Sheet will capture key components of both types of family meeting to enable comparison of family meeting practices and factors contributing to this practice. 
At the control site, the same quantitative measures will be undertaken at the same time points. Interviews with patients and families at the control site will only occur if a family meeting was convened as part of the standard care of the patient. 
A statistical electronic application will analyse the quantitative data and provide results. Patient, family and clinician interview data will be analysed using qualitative data analysis techniques. 
It is expected that this research will provide evidence about the acceptability, feasibility and value of family meetings in palliative care for patients, families and clinicians.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent’s Hospital, Darlinghurst HREC Executive Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 6, de Lacy Building 
St Vincents Hospital 
390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst  NSW  2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/SVH/33</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Phillips</name>
      <address>IMPACCT - Improving Palliative, Aged and Chronic Care through Clinical Research and Translation
Faculty of Health
University of Technology Sydney</address>
      <phone>+612 95144822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jane.phillips@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Philippa Cahill</name>
      <address>C/O Research Cottage
Calvary Health Care Kogarah
PO Box 261 
Kogarah  NSW  1485</address>
      <phone>+61 434077674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>philippa.cahill1@my.nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Philippa Cahill</name>
      <address>C/O Research Cottage
Calvary Health Care Kogarah
PO Box 261 
Kogarah  NSW  1485</address>
      <phone>+61 434077674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>philippa.cahill1@my.nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Philippa Cahill</name>
      <address>C/O Research Cottage
Calvary Health Care Kogarah
PO Box 261 
Kogarah  NSW  1485</address>
      <phone>+61 434077674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>philippa.cahill1@my.nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>