<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365479">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001334695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of low salt weight loss diets on the way blood vessels work</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of weight loss diets low in dietary sodium compared to pre weight loss diet on endothelial function in overweight to obese adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight or obese </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Blood vessel function: flow mediated dilatation, pulse wave velocity and augmentation and blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomized controlled cross over study. 

Participants will be randomised into two equal groups matched for body mass index (BMI), sex, age. 

One group (1) will start with an energy restricted diet using meal replacement low in sodium (meal replacement will be provided for breakfast, lunch and dinner) for 8 weeks followed by a 2 week weight maintenance period on a normal salt diet and finish with a control period of 8 weeks following their normal pre study diet. 
The second group (2) will start by following their usual diet for 8 weeks followed by 8 weeks weight loss (as above) finishing with 2 weeks weight maintenance.
 
This study will last for a total of 18 weeks. Participants will be asked to attend maximum 8 appointments at the University of South Australia. The duration of the visits will vary between 15 minutes and 1.5 hours (visits where all measurements are taken will last approximately 1.5 hours (baseline, after 8 weeks weight loss/ control period and after the 2 weeks weight stable period) visits during the weight loss period will last approximately 15 minutes).

In the weight loss period participants will attend the University clinic every two weeks to be weighed and to collect meal replacement for the next 2 week period (duration of visit approximately 15 minutes). 

In the control period participants will be asked to attend the University clinic after 8 weeks (duration approximately 1.5 hours). In this period they will be continuing on their usual diet.

To assess food habits a food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) will be completed a t baseline. 3 day diet diaries will be completed at baseline, after 8 weeks weight loss/control period and after the 2 week weight stable period. As a compliance measure weight loss and amount of meal replacement sachets used will be measured. Participants will be asked to return all used and unused meal replacement sachets to be counted.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control period of 8 weeks is a non-intervention period where participants consume their usual diet and do not lose weight</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Flow mediated dilatation (FMD) of the brachial artery will be measured using ultra sound
</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 8 weeks after either control or weight loss and after 2 weeks weight stability</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pulse wave velocity (PWV) and augmentation index(AI) will be measured using a SphygmoCor Registered Trademark XCEL (AtCor Medical)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks weight loss/ controlm period and after 2 weeks weight stability</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure (BP) will be measured using and automated sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 8 weeks after either control or weight loss and after 2 weeks weight stability</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24h urine sodium, potassium will be measures in a certified commercial laboratory</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 8 weeks after either control or weight loss and after 2 weeks weight stability</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bloods for Plasma sodium &amp; potassium, nitrates/nitrites, ICAM-1 &amp; VCAM-1, E-selectin &amp; endothelin-1</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 8 weeks after either control or weight loss and after 2 weeks weight stability</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight, height and waist circumference</outcome>
      <timepoint>All visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>overweight to obese (BMI greater than or equal to 27 kg/m2) men and women, weight stable within the last 6 months, BP (SBP) &lt;160 mmHg and (DBP) &lt;90 mmHg</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>BMI less than 27 kg/m2, serious illness e.g.  Cancer, liver or kidney disease or not willing or able to follow diet for the study period, alcohol intake above 1 standard drink/day and not willing to decrease intake</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants from the general population will be recruited via advertisments, flyers and postings on facebook, GumTree and Twitter.
Eligibility to the study will be determined via a short telephone interview.
Allocation will not be concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized via random number system using the software program clinstat </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Participant number
The power to detect a weight difference of 10kg was based on a previous parallel weight study where a change of 10 kg (SD 13) was seen at 6 months and a change in FMD of 1. 5% (SD 2.4) seen in a previous study. This gives us 80% (p&lt;0.05) confidence to determine a difference in FMD of 1.5% with 21 participants in each group. A 30% dropout is expected therefore 56 participants will be recruited.


After testing data for normal distribution, a repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) with meal and time as within-subject factors will be used to assess the effects of diet intervention on the dependent variables over time.  Age and BMI will be included as covariates. If there is a significant main effect of time, post hoc comparisons will be performed with Bonferronis correction for multiple comparisons to determine changes in the dependent variables relative to baseline. Correlation between variables will be analyzed using Pearson's product-moment coefficient test. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>25</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/06/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>City East Campus
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide
SA 5000 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>City East Campus
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide
SA 5000 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to see if a combination of weight loss and low salt diets have a beneficial effect on how blood vessels work.
We hypothesise that decreasing salt in the diet and losing weight will improve blood vessel function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Would you like help to lose weight? 

OVERWEIGHT VOLUNTEERS WANTED

	
Effects of weight loss &amp; diet quality on blood vessel function 
We will be looking at the effect of weight loss using a low sodium meal replacement diet on markers of cardiovascular disease (all meal replacement will be provided)

We would like to hear from you if you are:

* Over 18 years old
* Overweight (otherwise healthy)

If you would like to learn more, please contact us for further information:

Call Eva Pedersen at 8302 1025

Or E-mail at: eva.pedersen@unisa.edu.au

Research Associate, 
University of South Australia, East Campus, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000
</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide 
SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>31833</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/12/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>University of South Australia City East Campus North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jennifer.Keogh@unisa.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>University of South Australia City East Campus North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jennifer.Keogh@unisa.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>University of South Australia City East Campus North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jennifer.Keogh@unisa.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>University of South Australia City East Campus North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jennifer.Keogh@unisa.edu.au </email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>