<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336871">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000672954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised, cross-over trial of upright sitting versus alternate side lying during nebulised delivery of medication to improve the pattern of aerosol deposition in participants with cystic fibrosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, cross-over trial of upright sitting versus alternate side lying during nebulised delivery of medication to improve the pattern of aerosol deposition in participants with cystic fibrosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-1029</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will inhale 4mL technetium-99m DTPA radioaerosol in two positions in random order throughout the nebulisation period of 20 minutes for each of the positioning regimens on two separte days:   1. Upright sitting: or 2. Alternate Side Lying: (alternated between left and right at each minute)
The two study days will have a minimum of 48 hours washout between them and not greater than 7 days (to ensure clinical stability).
After each nebulisation a gamma camera will perform a 20 minute deposition scan incorporating a 2 minute transmission scan to outline the three-dimensional margin of the lung fields. This data will be reconstructed to determine the distribution of the deposited radioaerosol in the lungs. A 15% improvement in uniformity of deposition is the proposed minimum difference that would make the alternate side lying strategy worthwhile in CF patient populations.</interventions>
    <comparator>Upright Sitting is the control condition. Alternate side lying the experimental</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 3-dimensional map of the lung fields will be divided into unit volumes (voxels). The amount of radioactivity in each voxel will be calculated. The standard deviation of the radioactivity across all voxels within the margins of the lung fields will be used as an index of uniformity of the pattern of deposition for each participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post 20 minutes of inhalation on each of two study days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of the loaded dose (dose loaded in nebuliser - residual remining in nebuliser post 20 minutes of inhalation in MBq) delivered to the body (decay corrected gamma camera body image dose in MBq).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post 20 minutes of inhalation on each of two study days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of the delivered dose (dose loaded in nebuliser - residual remining in nebuliser post 20 minutes of inhalation in MBq) that deposited in the lungs. (decay corrected lung gamma camera image dose in MBq).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post 20 minutes of inhalation on each of two study days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The concentration of the dose in the apical regions compared to the concentration for the whole lung. The 3-dimensional map of the lung fields will be divided into unit volumes (voxels). The amount of radioactivity in each voxel will be calculated. The ratio of apical:non-apical deposition of radioactivity will be determined by the mean number of counts per voxel in the apical one third of the lung field divided by the mean number of counts per voxel in the basal two thirds of the lung field.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post 20 minutes of inhalation on each of two study days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria: To participate in this study, a person must:
1	be 18 years of age or older
2	be able to read, write and comprehend English
3	have cystic fibrosis, diagnosed by sweat test or genotyping 
4	have an FEV1 within 10% of the best recorded value as an outpatient during the previous 6 months
5	be willing to inhale a 4mL radioaerosol and undergo a 20min gamma scan, on two occasions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria: A person will be ineligible to participate in this study if s/he:
1	has significant malignant, neurological or musculoskeletal comorbidity, according to clinic records
2	has hepatomegaly, hepatosplenomegaly, or intestinal obstruction, according to clinic records 
3	is unable to perform spirometry reproducibly
4	is pregnant, or is sexually active and unwilling to use contraception during the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Willing participants will then be requested to sign a consent form to participate in the study, which will be co-signed by an independent witness. Eligibility will then be confirmed with reference to the willing participant’s clinic records. Once enrolled in the trial, each participant will be invited to attend the Department of Nuclear Medicine on two days separated by a washout day. Participants will then be randomised, by flipping a coin, to one of two positions:
1. Upright sitting: to be maintained throughout the nebulisation period of 20 minutes, or
2. Alternate Side Lying: to be alternated between left and right at each minute during the nebulisation period of 20 minutes. 
Participants will be requested to adopt this position and maintain a normal tidal breathing pattern during the subsequent standard study inhalation. When participants return for their second study day, they will adopt the other positioning regimen.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomised, by flipping a coin, to one of two positions for the first day. The other position performed on the second day</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>During the sidelying day the side of commencement will be determined by flipping a coin</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>13</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>RPAH Missenden Road Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Physiotherapy Research Fuondation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 1175 Toorak Road, Camberwell VIC 3124
Postal Address: PO Box 437, Hawthorn BC VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Research question: To determine whether alternate side lying improves uniformity of deposition of an inhaled aerosol compared to upright sitting in participants with cystic fibrosis (CF).

Methods: Inclusion criteria: greater than or equal to 18 years of age, confirmed CF, stable lung function.
Participants will inhale a 4mL radioaerosol in two positions in random order throughout the nebulisation period of 20 minutes:   1. Upright sitting: or
	                        2. Alternate Side Lying: (alternated between left and right at each minute) 
After each nebulisation a gamma camera will perform a 20 minute deposition scan incorporating a 2 minute transmission scan to outline the three-dimensional margin of the lung fields. This data will be reconstructed to determine the distribution of the deposited radioaerosol in the lungs. A 15% improvement in uniformity of deposition is the proposed minimum difference that would make the alternate side lying strategy worthwhile in CF patient populations.

Significance of project: In many patient populations (for example, cystic fibrosis, HIV, asthma and bronchiectasis), the pattern of deposition of inhaled medication is poor and non-uniform. Typically the upper lobes receive a reduced dose compared to the rest of the lung. The ability to deliver a drug more uniformly to the lung using the simple strategy of side lying may have a significant impact on treatment efficacy, acceptability and compliance for people with lung disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SSWAHS (RPA Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Building 92
RPAH Missenden Road Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Protocol No X09-0018 &amp; HREC/09/RPAH/27</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ruth Dentice</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine Level 11
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 95155234</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>ruth.dentice@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ruth Dentice</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine Level 11
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 95155234</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>ruth.dentice@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ruth Dentice</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory Medicine Level 11
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 95155234</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>ruth.dentice@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>