<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335019">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001032044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of palliative care extended packages at home</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised control trial of effect of palliative care extended care packages at home, for palliative care patients with complex needs or terminal care on time out of hospital</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PEACH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Palliative Care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>advanced cancer and other non cancer life limiting illness in advanced stage</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group (PEACH) involves rapidity in response (where services can be put in place within 24 hours), and higher intensity of hands on nursing hours above what is provided in usual care. This may include nursing services (utilising agency nursing staff) overnight and for longer duration including 24 hour nursing for duration of the package (maximum 3 - 5 days). It also coordinates allied health input (occupational therapy, physiotherapy, pastoral care) if equipment or other services are needed. The intervention will be differ on a case by case basis and is for a maximum of up to 24 hours/ day for 7 days duration. The study duration is 4 weeks which includes a followup phase.</interventions>
    <comparator>usual community or hospital based care. This will include referral to primary care nurses, specialist palliative care medical/nursing services and community allied health and equipment services. The provision of these services will be based on individual assessment and current waiting times for access. The patient may need to remain in hospital until services are available.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>number of days out of institutional care (determined from medical records of admissions to hospital and patient/caregiver report of date of admission to residential care)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in symptom score (from baseline) at end of package and at 28 days (Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional status (questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of patients who die at home (questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>caregiver quality of life (questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Family Inventory of needs score (success of meeting caregiver needs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days from baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Patient of the Palliative Care Team 
2.General Practitioner currently involved in care at home or willing to be involved on discharge from hospital.
3. Patient lives with carer or will have a carer on discharge.
4. Ability to communicate sufficiently in English or have caregiver or family member who can communicate in English and assist them to complete assessments.
5. Informed consent.
6. Age greater than 18.
7. Also must meet one of the following criteria:
a. A patient with complex and unstable symptom management and high care needs whose clinician thinks admission/readmission to hospital may be prevented by the package.
b. A patient with complex and unstable symptom management and high care needs currently admitted in acute hospital /Palliative care unit who may not be discharged without comprehensive community services.
c. A patient wishing to receive end of life care (anticipated to be within 72 hours duration) at home.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>not meeting above inclusion criteria

no other exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients and their caregivers who meet the criteria for a PEACH package will be asked if they are interested in participating in an evaluation of community palliative care services delivered by different approaches. A participant information sheet describing the evaluations and assessments will be provided and written informed consent. This information sheet will explain that the approach will be randomly allocation to the two different ways of providing services to palliative care patients in the community. Once the participant has been randomised staff will be aware of allocation so non blinded.

Allocation concealment was acheived by 1) central randomisation by phone 2) Person determining eligibility and obtaining consent was unaware of group participant would be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation schedules will be developed using random number tables, with intervention for each patient allocated according to a block randomisation  schedule held by the central registry</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/10/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/11/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>32</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>South West Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Liverpool Hospital, Elizabeth Street Liverpool New South Wales 2174</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Dept of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Palliative Care section, Commonwealth Dept of Health and Ageing, GPO Box 9848 Canberra ACT</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to evaluate individual care packages compared with usual care for complex and unstable symptom management and high care needs patients wishing to return home earlier from hospital or Palliative Care units AND for those requiring high level End of Life Care who wish to remain at home. This may include patients who have cancer or non-cancer diagnoses. Care packages at home could include nursing, domestic support, and equipment provision as well as more expeditious access to Specialist Palliative Care multidisciplinary team (MDT) services and General Practitioners. The evaluation project will explore the net incremental effect on patients and caregivers outcomes and associated net incremental costs relative to usual care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>McCaffrey, N. Agar, M. Harlum, J. Karnon, J. Currow, D. Eckermann, S. (2013). Is home-based palliative care cost effective? An economic evaluation of the Palliative Care Extended Packages at Home (PEACH) pilot. BMJ Supportive and Palliative Care; 2013;3(4):431-5</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service (SSWAHS) Human Research Ethics Committeee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Liverpool Hospital, Elizabeth Street,
Liverpool Sydney 2170 NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/LPOOL/108</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Meera Agar</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney
Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care 
Faculty of Health,  University of Technology Sydney
PO Box 123 Ultimo NSW 2007
Office: Level 3, 235 Jones St, Ultimo NSW 2007 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meera.agar@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Meera Agar</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney
Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care 
Faculty of Health,  University of Technology Sydney
PO Box 123 Ultimo NSW 2007
Office: Level 3, 235 Jones St, Ultimo NSW 2007 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meera.agar@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Meera Agar</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney
Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care 
Faculty of Health,  University of Technology Sydney
PO Box 123 Ultimo NSW 2007
Office: Level 3, 235 Jones St, Ultimo NSW 2007 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meera.agar@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meera Agar</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care 
Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney
PO Box 123 Ultimo NSW 2007
Office: Level 3, 235 Jones St, Ultimo NSW 2007 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meera.agar@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>