<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363930">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000355774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>diabetic foot ulcer and shock wave therapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of Shock Wave Therapy on Chronic Diabetic Foot Ulcer: A Single-Blinded Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>diabetic foot ulcer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>shock wave therapy (SWT-group): The ulcer had been cleaned with saline, and the necrotic tissues had been removed, and the ulcer had dried before application of SWT. To avoid cross-contamination, each ulcer was covered with a sterilized transparent plastic thin film that allows 100% transmission of waves through it. Ultrasound gel was applied to the area on the skin in contact with the shock wave probe. Patients received SWT at frequency of 100 pulse/cm2, and energy flux density of 0.11mJ/cm2. The probe was held vertically against each ulcer by direct contact with slight pressure to minimize power loss due to beam divergence. 

After each session, the therapist inspected the area surrounding ulcer for adverse events such as dermatitis, erythema, infection, excessive granulation and necrotic tissue. The SWT was applied once a week, with one-week interval, and with a minimum of four and a maximum of eight sessions base on healing rate.

duration that SWT was applied at each session depend on wound surface area (5-10minutes).
In addition, patients received standardized wound care consisting of debridement, blood-glucose control agents, and footwear modification for pressure reduction. Wound dressing was changed once a day by the patient, their family members, or home-health care providers, depending on the patients individual capabilities and resources.</interventions>
    <comparator>patients in the control group received standardized wound care consisting of debridement, blood-glucose control agents, and footwear modification for pressure reduction. Wound dressing was changed once a day by the patient, their family members, or home-health care providers, depending on the patients individual capabilities and resources.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1-Wound surface area measurement
The percentage of decrease in wound surface area (WSA) due to interventions was recorded. The therapist placed sterilized transparency sheet over the wound and traced the wound perimeter using a permanent marking pen. Each wound was traced three times to ensure the reliability of measurement. The tracing was digitalized using the A4 G-Note 7100 tablet with cordless mouse and two stylus pen (KYE systems, Corp, China), and then imported to a specialized software program (Photoshop C4me) to calculate WSA. The percentage of reduction in WSA was determined from the following equation:

               %WSA = [initial WSA (cm2) - WSA (cm2) at x weeks] X100
                                               initial WSA (cm2) 
The percentage of wounds that had completely healed was detected at each measurement time.  The wounds were labeled completely healed only if they clinically closed (100% re-epithelization) without drainage or dressing requirement. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The percentage of reduction in WSA was calculated after the end of interventions 8-week and after 20-week follow-up assessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The time to complete healing 
it was recorded as the number of days from the beginning of the treatment to the date in which the wound achieved complete healing. If healing did not occur within the 20 weeks, the patient was considered to be nonhealing and no time was recorded.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>time was recorded  at 8 weeks, at 20 weeks follow-up </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound bed preparation scores 
The wound bed preparation scores and the percentage of granulation and necrotic tissues and presence of the exudates have been determined. The presence of exudates was determined as: none, minimal, moderate and heavy, based on wound bed preparation scores developed by Falanga et al .</outcome>
      <timepoint>it was calculated after the end of interventions 8-week  and after 20-week follow-up assessment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who met the following criteria were included in this study: (1) diagnosis of type I and II diabetes; (2) Grade 2 diabetic foot ulcer (DFU) according to the University of Texas Diabetic Foot Wound Classification System (wound penetrating to tendon or capsule, not involving bone or joint); (3) ulcer has been resisted to conservative treatment &gt; 3 months; (4) ulcer measures &gt; 0.5cm and &lt; 5 cm at any dimension; (5) patient should have had peripheral neuropathy, as defined by insensitivity to a 10-g monofilament and (6) patient should be willing to participate in the study and comply with the follow-up. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients were excluded if they had: (1) evidence of local infection, acute cellulitis, osteomyelitis or gangrene anywhere in the affected extremity; (2) presence of renal, hepatic, neurologic or malignant diseases; (3) severe protein malnutrition (serum albumin &lt; 2.0 g/dl) or severe anemia (Hgb &lt; 7.0 g/dl); (4) an ankle-brachial index &lt; 0.7, absence of the dorsalis pedis or posterior tibial arteries pulse; or (5) pregnancy. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects were recruited from the general surgery department and the outpatient clinic, King Saud Medical City, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.  The study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee at King Saud Medical City. 
The randomization was completed by generating blocks of numbers. The numbers were assigned as a treatment group and sealed in opaque envelopes containing black paper labeled with treatment received. </concealment>
    <sequence>A single-blinded, randomized controlled study was conducted from May 2010 to September 2012. 

we generated a computerized random number list and the subject allocation.
sequence was created from the list.Therapist who evaluated patients and analyzed data were blinded to the treatment received.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Continuous variables were presented as mean and standard deviation while categorical variables were described by frequency and percentage. 
Because most of the measured data were not normally distributed, nonparametric tests had been used for analyses. The Wilcoxon test was used to test the differences in outcome measures within group. The MannWhitney U test was used for comparison between the groups.  Significant differences were assumed at p &lt;0.05. Statistical analyses were performed using Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) version 17.0).
Based on type I error, probability set at 0.05, with 90% power, detection of 20% differences between treatment groups required 19 patients for both groups(total of 38 patients). The sample size would be increased to 45 for possible dropout.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/05/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>24/07/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>21/10/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>38</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <state>Riyadh </state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>king Saud university, Rehabilitation Research Chair</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rehabilitation Research Chair
King Saud University 
Riyadh, Saudi Arabia  
P.O. Box, 10219, Riyadh, 11433

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Rehabilitation Research Chair, king Saud University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rehabilitation Research Chair
King Saud University 
Riyadh, Saudi Arabia  
P.O. Box, 10219, Riyadh, 11433

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Saudi Arabia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>King Saud Medical City, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>King Saud Medical City, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia
Riyadh, Saudi Arabia  
P.O. Box, 2897, Riyadh, 11196</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is a little research in Saudi Arabia on diabetic foot ulcer  (DFU) prevalence, management or cost. However, surveys suggested that the incidence of diabetes is 23.7%, and it is extremely higher in urban areas. The diabetic foot lesions constitute a major complication with an overall prevalence of 10.4%. Those lesions are linked with increased health cost, diminished quality of life, and prolong functional disability.

Many adjunctive therapies are designed for the care of DFU, involving hyperbaric oxygen therapy,  vacuum-assisted wound closure, low level laser therapy and electrical stimulation. However, the results from these studies are inconsistent and reported limited success with no conclusive remark on its use. Therefore, the development of new effective noninvasive modalities for management of diabetic wounds is extremely important to reduce both patients' suffering from chronic wounds and the cost of treatment. 

For the past 20 years, extracorporal shockwave therapy (SWT) has been used for the wide range of musculoskeletal disorders. Recently, SWT was shown to be valuable for treatment of chronic wound, such as bedsores, vascular and diabetic ulcers burn wounds and skin flaps.
 
However, these studies were limited clinical trials with the low level of evidence in respect to the criteria of the Center for Evidence-Based Medicine.  Moreover, systematic review concluded that lack of evidence and rigorous study design made it difficult for clinicians and therapists to support using of SWT in wound healing. Furthermore, clinical trials are required to assess the optimum SWT treatment parameters, such as duration and frequency of therapy and types of wound remains.
Therefore, this single blinded, randomized controlled study was conducted to examine the efficacy of SWT on the healing rate and wound surface area (WSA) in chronic diabetic foot ulcers.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committee at King Saud Medical City</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>King Saud Medical City, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. 
king Abdullaha road,Riyadh
P.o.Box 2897, Riyadh, 11196 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/01/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Saudi Arabia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mohammed Taher Ahmed Omar</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Sciences Department 
 College of Applied Medical Sciences
 King Saud University 
 Riyadh, Saudi Arabia  
 P.O. Box, 10219, Riyadh, 11433
</address>
      <phone>+966542115404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>momarar@cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mohammed Taher Ahmed Omar</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Sciences Department 
 College of Applied Medical Sciences
 King Saud University 
 Riyadh, Saudi Arabia  
 P.O. Box, 10219, Riyadh, 11433
</address>
      <phone>+966542115404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>momarar@cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mohammed Taher Ahmed Omar</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Sciences Department 
 College of Applied Medical Sciences
 King Saud University 
 Riyadh, Saudi Arabia  
 P.O. Box, 10219, Riyadh, 11433
</address>
      <phone>+966542115404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>momarar@cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mohammed Taher Ahmed Omar</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Sciences Department 
 College of Applied Medical Sciences
 King Saud University 
 Riyadh, Saudi Arabia  
 P.O. Box, 10219, Riyadh, 11433
</address>
      <phone>+966542115404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>momarar@cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>