<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370661">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001627448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of a model of GP and pharmacist collaboration in primary care in reducing unplanned hospital readmissions: REMAIN HOME study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating a model of GP and pharmacist collaboration in primary care in reducing unplanned, all-cause hospital readmissions: REMAIN HOME study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-7390 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>REMAIN HOME - REducing Medical Admissions INto Hospital through Optimising MEdication</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients prescribed five or more long-term medicines being discharged from hospital </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Patients having a hospital admission related to heart failure or COPD being discharged from hospital </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a multi-faceted and collaborative service, involving a clinical pharmacist integrated into a medical centre to assist patients in transitioning back into primary care. The intervention is targeted at the level of the medical centre. A practice pharmacist will be co-located in each medical centre during the intervention phase for approximately 12 hours per week. The length of time a medical centre receives the intervention will depend on where they are randomised to in the stepped wedge design, from one month to seven months.

There will be four components to the intervention which will apply to each patient enrolled in the study during the intervention phase:
1. Medication management consultation with practice pharmacist 
2. Consultation with GP 
3. Practice pharmacist to follow-up with patient, GP, community pharmacy and other health professionals involved in the patients care
4. Further follow-up as required 

Medication management consultation:
Participants will receive a face-face minute medication management consultation (45 - 60 minutes) with the practice pharmacist in a private room at the attended medical centre as soon as possible after discharge from hospital. During this time, the pharmacist will perform a comprehensive medication review to identify any medication-related problems, assess medication adherence, review the participants medication discharge letter and discuss any changes made to medication during hospital admission with the participant. The pharmacist will also review the participants medical records at the practice and reconcile any differences as required. The pharmacist will discuss the intended treatment plan and any problems or concerns the participant may have regarding their medication and/or medical conditions. The pharmacist may also liaise with the participants community pharmacy as required .
 
Consultation with GP:
Directly after the consultation with the pharmacist, the patient will have a consultation with their GP to and to consider any changes made by the pharmacist or hospital during the admission, discuss the recent admission from hospital and future management plans. This will take 15 - 30 minutes. 

Follow up :
The pharmacist will follow up with the participant within five days either via the phone or face-to-face at the attended medical centre (10-30 minutes). Furthermore, the pharmacist will liaise with the participants GP, other prescribers and community pharmacist based upon clinical need.

Further follow up will be based upon clinical need.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients will receive standard/usual care provided by the medical centre. This would usually involve the patient following up with their general practitioner after discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of unplanned, all-cause hospital readmissions in the intervention group compared to control/usual care. This will be assessed through review of hospital medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of unplanned, all-cause hospital readmissions in the intervention group compared to control/usual care.
This will be assessed through review of hospital medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 3 and 6 months after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of ED presentations in the intervention group compared to control/usual care. This will be assessed through review of hospital medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 3, 6 and 12 months after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of hospital treatment plans received in the intervention group compared to control/usual care.
This will be assessed through review of medical centre medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days and 30 days after discharge </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants reviewed by their GP in the intervention group compared to control/usual care.
This will be assessed through review of medical centre medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of visits to the enrolled medical centre in the intervention group compared to control/usual care.
This will be assessed through review of medical centre medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Costs to the healthcare system associated with the intervention (including the costs of providing the intervention, unplanned hospital readmissions, ED presentations, and related GP visits) in the intervention group compared to control/usual care.

This will be assessed through review of hospital and medical centre medical records. The primary source of hospital cost estimates (i.e. cost of a particular readmission) will be derived from the National Efficient Cost (NEC) and National Efficient Price (NEP) data that are collected and published annually by Australias Independent Hospital Pricing Authority (IHPA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 3, 6 and 12 months after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Description of views of the intervention from GPs, practice pharmacists and participants involved in the study.
This will be assessed through self-report questionnaires. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months after commencement of trial (i.e. end of study intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Prescribed 5 or more long-term prescribed medicines on discharge OR reason for admission was related to heart failure or Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)
*Have nominated a GP working in an enrolled medical centre in their hospital records which they see majority of the time.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they are:
*Receiving active radiation therapy or chemotherapy for malignant conditions
*Admission was for planned  dialysis
*In palliative care as reflected by the treatment regimen (e.g. cessation of preventative medicines)
*Unable to attend a medication review and the follow up within the time frame
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patient recruitment will occur by research assistants who will screen patients daily being discharged  for eligibility to enter the trial and recruit those that do.  Once the patient has been enrolled, the research assistant will notify the project coordinator who will be able to determine whether the medical centre that the participant is attending is in the control or intervention phase. If the medical centre is in the intervention phase (or lead in phase), the project coordinator will pass the participant details onto the practice pharmacist performing the intervention. The project coordinator will collect data from all participant’s hospital and medical centre records around the hospital admission and current medical history. 
The medical centre randomisation list will be kept centrally by the project coordinator, and research assistants recruiting participants into the study will be blinded to the medical centre randomisation schedule throughout the study. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>The unit of randomisation is the study medical centre, not the recruited patient. Medical centres will be randomised to intervention or control phase using a stepped wedge design. 
Stratified randomisation will be used to achieve a balance between medical centres in Brisbane North and South PHNs, while maintaining randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a stepped-wedge cluster design trial which has a unidirectional crossover design where all clusters begin in the control phase and cross over to the intervention at different time points. The intervention will be delivered at the level of the medical centre and cluster randomisation will be used to allow for randomisation to occur at the level of the cluster (medical centre) instead of the participant. 
Blinding of the intervention to staff at the medical centre and to participating patients is not possible as the presence of the pharmacist in the medical centre will indicate they are in the intervention phase. Research assistants will remain blinded to the randomisation schedule throughout the study. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size was calculated for the primary outcome, the rate of all-cause unplanned readmissions at 12 months from date of hospital discharge, using a method that takes into account the: intracluster correlation coefficient (ICC), expected baseline number of readmissions, effect of the intervention and power of the study. We followed methods described by others to determine the sample size needed, assuming a random effect for cluster (medical centre) and a fixed effect for each step to account for time.  We have been conservative in our estimate of the ICC as we have limited a priori data to inform this value and also because the ICC is a process outcome, which usually have larger ICCs.

Whilst the analysis will be a Poisson regression of rate of re-admission, the study has been powered on a binary proportion outcome. This is because there is no data on which to estimate current rate of readmission and sample size methodology for stepped wedge studies does not currently exist for rate outcomes. This is a limitation of the sample size calculation, but the estimate of power will be conservative because the analysis will make full use of the number of readmissions. Literature from Australian studies suggests that 45% of patients discharged from medical inpatient units and 61% from Geriatrics Evaluation and Management units have an unplanned readmission within one year. A meta-analysis on pharmacist-led medication reconciliation at hospital transition found a reduction in all-cause readmissions of 19% by the intervention. A hospital discharge program involving medication reconciliation and telephone follow up reduced readmissions (combined with ED visits) by 30% in general medicine patients.

We expect only minimal variation in cluster sizes and so have not allowed for varying cluster sizes. With 14 clusters, and 20 patients recruited per cluster per month (except during the transition phase), gives an expected total sample size of 2,240 participants. Using these estimates and expected loss to follow up of approximately 20%, the design will have in the region of 80  90% power to detect a change in proportions of unplanned readmissions from 0.3 to 0.2 for a range of ICCs (from 0.05 to 0.15). 

An intention-to-treat analysis will be conducted. All participants will be included in the analysis. Each medical centre will be classified as being in the intervention or the control phase based on their pre-specified randomised crossover time, regardless of whether crossover is achieved at that time.

In the primary analysis, differences in readmissions will be modelled using a mixed effects Poisson regression model with an offset to incorporate the number of days of follow up, a random effect for cluster and a fixed effect for each step to account for any temporal trend. Temporal trends may include seasonal variation in readmissions or changes in practice. We also intend to allow for both levels of clustering at the analysis stage - clustering by hospital and medical centre. We will do this by including both a random effect for medical centres and hospitals. If this model does not converge, we will include a fixed effect for hospital (as there will not be many hospitals) and a random effect for medical centre. Follow up time for each person will be the number of days from discharge for index admission to the earlier of 12 months post discharge; death or loss to follow up for example because of moving out of the region.

Secondary analysis will be conducted using similar techniques, but using different link functions as appropriate. Descriptive statistics will used to report the level of agreement with survey statements used to elicit the views of the intervention from GPs, practice pharmacists and participants involved in the study.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Logan Hospital - Meadowbrook</hospital>
    <hospital>Caboolture Hospital - Caboolture</hospital>
    <hospital>Redcliffe Hospital - Redcliffe</hospital>
    <hospital>Queen Elizabeth II Jubilee Hospital - Coopers Plains</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>The Wesley Hospital - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>Greenslopes Private Hospital - Greenslopes</hospital>
    <hospital>Holy Spirit Northside - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>St Andrew's War Memorial Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Brisbane Private Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Private Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christopher Freeman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence (PACE)
Level 4
20 Cornwall St
Woolloongabba
Brisbane
Queensland 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>HCF Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO BOX 4242 
Sydney, NSW, 2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brisbane South PHN</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>First Floor Building 20, Garden City Office Park,
2404 Logan Road, Eight Mile Plains QLD 4113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brisbane North PHN</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 845
Lutwyche
QLD 4030</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The transition of patients with chronic and complex conditions from hospital back into the community setting is a critical time with an increased risk of medication misadventure and re-hospitalisation. 
AIM:
The aim of this study is to investigate whether a model of structured GP and pharmacist care reduces unplanned hospital readmissions in patients taking multiple medicines. 
METHOD:
This study will include 2240 people who have been discharged from hospital taking 5 or more medicines and attend an enrolled medical centre. Participants will be recruited at discharge from hospital and the intervention will be in 14 different medical centres across South East Queensland. Depending on when the participant is discharged, they will be placed in the control or intervention phase. 
Participants in the control phase will receive usual care from their medical centre. This means the patient would consult their GP as per normal standards for that practice for a patient discharged from hospital. 
Participants in the intervention phase will be followed up after discharge by a pharmacist working in the medical centre they attend. The practice pharmacist will organise a time for the participant to come into the medical centre and to discuss the changes made during their hospital stay and review the participants medicines. After a consultation with the pharmacist, the participant will have a consultation with their GP to receive any new scripts they may need and to consider any changes recommended by the hospital or pharmacist. The practice pharmacist will follow up with the participant within five days of the first consultation. The practice pharmacists may also contact other health professionals involved in the participant's care as required.
It is hoped that a pharmacist and GP reviewing a patients medicines and changes made during hospital will reduce the likelihood of the patient being readmitted to hospital.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.remainhomestudy.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's hospital Human Ethics Research committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Block 7
Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital
Butterfield St
Herston, QLD, 4029
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QRBW/410</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane QLD 4072 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UnitingCare Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5, 192 Ann St
Brisbane QLD 
Australia 4000 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Greenslopes Research and Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Freeman</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence (PACE)
Level 4, 20 Cornwall st
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Queensland 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33461727</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.freeman4@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Holly Foot</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence (PACE)
Level 4, 20 Cornwall st
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Queensland 4102</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3346 1900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.ross1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Holly Foot</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence (PACE)
Level 4, 20 Cornwall st
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Queensland 4102</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3346 1900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.ross1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Holly Foot</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence (PACE)
Level 4, 20 Cornwall st
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Queensland</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>h.ross1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>