<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82895">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000344392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sleeping sound with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can managing sleep problems in children with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) improve child sleep, behaviour, quality of life, and school attendance?  a pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this pilot study is to determine the acceptability and feasibility of two different models of managing sleep problems in children with ADHD. 
The models differ in level of intensity of the treatment given. The first model (intensive model) consists of basic sleep hygiene strategies, education about normal sleep and sleep cycles, tailored sleep management plan, and sleep diary. These interventions will be delivered in the first consultation (each consultation will be 40 minutes long). The second session will take place approximately two weeks after their initial consultation to reinforce strategies and monitor progress. Families will be contacted by telephone approximately two weeks after this visit to refine strategies and to make a third appointment if the family are continuing to have difficulties.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active - The second model is a one session model of treating sleep problems - basic sleep hygiene strategies, education about normal sleep and sleep cycles, given generic written information around common sleep problems. This intervention will take place one 40 minute consultation. These families will not receive further face to face or telephone follow-up.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The acceptability, frequency of use and ease of use of each component of the intervention as per our previous RCTs (Hiscock H et al  Arch. Dis. Child. 2007 92: p. 952-958; Hiscock H et al BMJ, 2002;324:1062-1067). Parents will be asked to rate how helpful they found various components of the program on a four point scale (very helpful, a little helpful, not helpful, didn't receive this advice). Parents will also be asked to rate how often they were able to put the advice received into practice on a 5 point scale (almost all of the time, about half of the time, about a quater of the time, less than a quater of the time, did not receive this advice)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Barriers to participation in the study, attendance at consultations and uptake of interventions as per our previous parenting RCT (Hiscock H et al  Arch. Dis. Child. 2007 92: p. 952-958; Hiscock H et al BMJ, 2002;324:1062-1067).  Parent will be asked what were the best and worst things about the program, how we could improve the program, and if they would recommend this program to friends/family.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary caregiver report of child sleep problem - none, mild, moderate or severe. This question is used in the Longitudinal Study of Australian Children to monitor parental concerns about their child's sleep.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 &amp; 5 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children's Sleep Habits Questionnaire - validated 33-item measure of dyssomnias and parasomnias</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 &amp; 5 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory 4.0-Parent version (Peds-QL) - validated 23-item measure of child health-related quality of life including physical, emotional, social, and school functioning.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 &amp; 5 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>School attendance - over the preceding 6 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 &amp; 5 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression Anxiety Stress Scale - validated 21-item measure of adult depression, anxiety and stress.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 &amp; 5 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver work attendance - over the previous 6 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 &amp; 5 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Health Questionnaire (CHQ) PF5014 - emotional impact, time impact and family activities subscales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 &amp; 5 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) School aged children with ADHD who have a moderate/severe sleep problem by primary caregiver report
2) Children must meet the American Academy of Sleep Medicine diagnostic criteria for any of the following: sleep onset association disorder, limit setting disorder, delayed sleep phase, primary insomnia or anxiety.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children with suspected obstructive sleep apnoea identified from parental responses to the 3 items in the Child Sleep Habits Questionnaire, (which screens for obstructive sleep apnoea) will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The research assistant will then explain the pilot to eligible families. Interested families will be mailed a baseline package including: (1) parent information statement, (2) two written informed consent forms – one to sign and keep, the other to return to the study team, (3) baseline survey and (4) a reply-paid envelope.  We will seek approval from the Royal Children’s Hospital’s Ethics in Human Research Committee to conduct this project. Upon receipt of the signed consent form and baseline survey, families will be randomly allocated to either a one session education-based model or a 2 to 3 session intensive management model. Families will be randomised using a pregenerated random number sequence provided by an independent statistician from the hospital’s Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics Unit.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Community Child Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Road, Parkville Vic 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Foundation for Children</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Financial Markets Association 
Level 3 Plaza Building, 95 Pitt Street, Sydney 2000
GPO Box 3655 Sydney NSW 2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Murdoch Children's Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Road, Parkville Vic 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) affects up to 7.5% of Australian children. Between 50 and 70% of parents also report that their ADHD child has a sleep problem. Such sleep problems are associated with poorer child behaviour, concentration, and school attendance as well as poorer parent mental health and work attendance. 
We want to know if managing sleep problems in ADHD children can improve these outcomes. We plan to conduct a pilot study to determine the acceptability and feasibility of two different models of managing sleep problems in children with ADHD. Model 1 will consist of a single consultation about normal sleep and sleep cycles, sleep hygiene advice, and providing parents with generic written information around common child sleep problems. Model 2 will consist of 2 to 3 consultations including normal sleep and sleep cycles, sleep hygiene advice and behavioural strategies tailored to the childs specific sleep problem(s). Results will inform a planned, randomised controlled trial (RCT) to determine the effectiveness of the most acceptable and feasible approach.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Children's Hospital (RCH) Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Road, Parkville Vic 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>28067</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/05/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Harriet Hiscock</name>
      <address>Centre for Community Child Health
The Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Road, Parkville Vic 3052</address>
      <phone>93456910</phone>
      <fax>93455900</fax>
      <email>harriet.hiscock@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Harriet Hiscock</name>
      <address>Centre for Community Child Health
The Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Road, Parkville Vic 3052</address>
      <phone>93456910</phone>
      <fax>93455900</fax>
      <email>harriet.hiscock@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Harriet Hiscock</name>
      <address>Centre for Community Child Health
The Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Road, Parkville Vic 3052</address>
      <phone>93456910</phone>
      <fax>93455900</fax>
      <email>harriet.hiscock@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>