<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366482">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000861651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Trial to Measure Efficacy of Training Nursing Students in Mental Health First Aid</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to measure the efficacy of delivering Mental Health First Aid training to first year nursing students at Curtin University.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mental health literacy and helping skills</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Suicide</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will participate in a face to face 13 hour Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) course. The course will run over 2 days consisting of 2 x 6.5 hour sessions. 
The MHFA course addresses several mental health issues such as depression, anxiety, suicide, eating disorders, and self injury. The course used videos, group activities and the MHFA manual to work through the course content. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control will have no exposure other than any usual mental health promotion. 
The control group will be offered the online MHFA course at 2 months after the second post questionnaire has been completed by all participants. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health literacy including: stigma toward people with a mental health problem, social distance, confidence, helping behaviours and knowledge.
These outcomes will be assessed by using a existing pre and post questionnaire created by Mental Health First Aid Australia. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre Mental Health Fist Aid course), post Mental Health First Aid course and 2 month follow-up 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>First year, internally enrolled Curtin University nursing students at the Bentley campus. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under the age of 18 years and not enrolled in first year nursing, not enrolled internally, or not at the Bentley campus</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer by centrally based administrator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Once all students have been allocated an identifying number, using the RAND function in Excel, students will be randomly allocated into two groups, intervention or control group. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size has been determined by the practicalities of working in a large university which requires delivering the intervention when it will be convenient to run classes that fitted university scheduling requirements and clinical rotations for the students. Assuming a high correlation of 0.8 for the baseline-post measurements it will be necessary to have 50 students in each group to detect 5% level of significance with 90% power in order to detect medium effect sizes for both continuous and dichotomous outcomes. A total of 63 students will be recruited for each group to account for 20% attrition from baseline to post intervention.The intention-to-treat principle will be used in the analysis, where all participants who completed the baseline questionnaire will be included in analysis regardless whether they complete the whole intervention. Acknowledging there may be attrition at the follow-up, the missing values for the non-respondents will be their baseline scores. This will assure no false improvement in efficacy. Data will be analysed using SPSS Version 22.

The demographics of the participants in the intervention and control groups will be compared using the independent samples t-test or Pearsons Chi-square test to measure differences including gender, country of birth. The primary outcome measures (described above) will be calculated following validated MHFA scoring methods reported in the literature. Repeated measures analysis of variance will be employed to assess continuous measures with the intervention and control group over three time points (baseline, post intervention and six weeks post intervention). Logistic regression will used to assess changes in dichotomous variables. The significance level will be set at 5%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>126</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6102 - Bentley</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>WA Centre for Health Promotion Research - Curtin University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia
6845
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Seed Funding Grant - School of Public Health Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Public Health
Faculty of Health Sciences
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia
6845
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This intervention seeks to measure the efficacy of Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) training with first year nursing students.
Participants will be recruited and randomly assigned to the control or intervention group. The intervention group will receive MHFA training. It is hypothesised that the MHFA training will increase the mental health literacy of the nursing students within the intervention group.
The control group will be waitlisted and be eligible to complete the MHFA training post trial. 
 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
PO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SPH-74-2013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gemma Crawford</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4851</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.crawford@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gemma Crawford</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4851</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.crawford@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gemma Crawford</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4851</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.crawford@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gemma Crawford</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4851</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.crawford@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>