<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366709">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000921684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Youth Online Wellbeing Initiative: A randomised controlled trial of online self-help Acceptance and Commitment Therapy for adolescents with anxiety</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of an online self-help Acceptance and Commitment Therapy intervention for reducing stress and anxiety in adolescents with anxiety</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stress
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The ACT online assisted self-help online intervention will comprise 2 components: 1) working through weekly material from the ACT adolescent self-help book, Get Out of Your Mind and Into Your Life for Teens: A guide to living an extraordinary life. Content includes, normalisation of anxiety, acceptance of emotions, defusion of thoughts, developing self awareness, mindfulness, and valued action; and 2) an online platform that will contain video, audio and reading material, weekly comments and prompts from therapists, with the ability for participants to receive and send private messages to therapists.
There will be 2 ACT treatment arms. The first will be the online self-help program described. The second ACT condition will receive the same two components as Condition A, plus five additional telephone support sessions with a trained ACT therapist to support their use of the program (an initial 30-minute introductory call at the start of the study, and four 10-minute fortnightly support telephone calls). The approximate time commitment is 1 hour per week over an 8 week intervention period.</interventions>
    <comparator>A standard assisted self-help intervention will be an active control condition comprising two components: 1) CBT written self-help material, as published by beyondblue, with content including psychoeducation on anxiety, problem solving, exposure, relaxation skills, goal setting; and 2) an online platform with equal capacity for video, audio, and reading material, and messaging between participants and therapists as Condition A; however the therapeutic model will be changed to standard CBT. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety, as assessed by the Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (SCAS). The SCAS is a 45-item self-report scale linked to DSM-IV anxiety disorders. The SCAS will be administered online.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The SCAS will be administered at pre-intervention (week 0), post-intervention (week 8) and 3 months post-follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Valued living, as assessed by the Keyes Psychological Well-being scale. This is a 12-item self-report scale that will be administered online.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Keyes Psychological Well-being scale will be administered at pre-intervention (week 0), post-intervention (week 8) and 3 months post-follow up.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mindfulness, as assessed by the Child and Adolescent Mindfulness Measure. This is a 10-item self-report scale that will be administered online.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Child and Adolescent Mindfulness Measure will be administered at the beginning of the intervention (week 1), mid intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 8), and 3-month post intervention follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological flexibility, as assessed by the Avoidance and Fusion Questionnaire for Youth (AFQ-Y). This is an 8-item self-report scale that will be administered online.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The AFQ-Y will be administered at the beginning of the intervention (week 1), mid intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 8), and 3-month post intervention follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Sub-clinical levels of anxiety
The ability to understand spoken and written English 
Access to a computer with broadband Internet connection</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>20</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Active suicidality, intellectual disability, illicit substance use</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>168</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre, the University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Poplar Road, Parkville, VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue: the national depression initiative</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>40 Burwood Rd, Hawthorn VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study aims are: 1) to determine the efficacy of ACT wherever they are to reduce anxiety and improve valued living for adolescents with anxiety; 2) to identify the level of program intensity (therapist support) required to achieve positive program outcomes; 3) to determine the mechanisms of change surrounding the intervention that are critical to program outcomes; and 4) to determine consumer acceptability, satisfaction, and geographical reach of an assisted online self-help mode of delivery.

t is hypothesised that 1) adolescents who receive the ACT online program will show greater improvements in anxiety and valued than adolescents in the active control group; 2) adolescents who receive the ACT online program plus telephone support will show greater improvements in anxiety and valued living than adolescents who receive both ACT and control online self-help programs; and 3) that the mechanisms of change for the ACT conditions will be increased post intervention psychological flexibility and mindfulness. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Melbourne Behavioural and Social Sciences HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 1, 780 Elizabeth Street The University of Melbourne Vic. 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1441479</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louise Hayes</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
35 Poplar Road, Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61393423758</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louiseh@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Louise Hayes</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
35 Poplar Road, Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61393423758</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louiseh@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louise Hayes</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
35 Poplar Road, Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61393423758</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louiseh@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Ridd</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
35 Poplar Road, Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61393423758</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.ridd@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>