<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371429">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001250426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MOZambique snApshot of emeRging Trends (MOZART) Disease Surveillance Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>MOZambique snApshot of emeRging Trends (MOZART) Disease Surveillance Study of Communicable versus Non-Communicable Diseases and Injuries in Urban Referral Hospitals of Mozambique</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-1550 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>MOZART</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Communicable and Non-Communicable Diseases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The MOZART Disease Surveillance Study is a prospective, multi-centred study with random profiling of representative case presentations at three tertiary hospitals in Mozambique (Hospital Geral de Mavalane, Hospital Central da Beira and Hospital Central de Nampula). For each participating hospital, electronic surveys will be conducted face-to-face for 30 consecutive days at a time (primary outcome data). A minimum target of 1000 participants will determine the ratio/proportion of all cases selected for more detailed profiling at each site. Accordingly all emergency presentations during the study period will be monitored via the point of entry to the hospital's emergency department with basic information recorded to determine the overall case-load of emergency presentations during the 30-day snap-shot period. Based on their order of presentation (selection of every fifth or sixth case), participants will be approached by MOZART personnel , and if informed consent is provided, subject to more detailed clinical following (including hospital outcome). The 30-day snapshots will be replicated at all three sites to capture seasonal changes in profile between the wet and dry seasons (secondary outcome data). As noted, all patients presenting to the Emergency Departments during the study period will be eligible for screening and those recruited by trained health professionals will be followed from point-of-admission up until discharge. Two Microsoft Access Questionnaire Databases were conceived jointly by Instituto Nacional de Saude (INS), Mozambique and the Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research (MMIHR), Australian Catholic University, Australia. A final version was built in Portuguese at MMIHR where the Patients Registration profile (name, residential suburb, contact details and hospital identification) are collected at the participating hospitals on dedicated study laptops and then stored with the INS to ensure the privacy of each patient. Health data (basic demographics, risk profile, medical history, admission details, and treatment) for each patient are then anonymously recorded on an external database and then transferred to, analysed, recorded, and stored by Data Management at the MMIHR. The methodologically and systematically closed- and open-questions in the electronic database provides efficient means of data entry, storage, and management.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of the MOZART study is to determine the balance between CDs and NCDs in three major hospitals in Mozambique. We will collect data from a minimum of 3,500 patients during the initial and follow-up 30-day snapshot periods for the three participating hospitals (minimum of 7000 patients during the combined wet and dry season snapshots) - by completing electronic surveys using Microsoft Access and then following up patients' discharge details from the hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be followed from point-of-admission up until discharge over the initial 30-day snapshot/observation period for each participating hospital (to be completed between April 2016 and December 2017).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome for the MOZART study is to compare the balance between CDs and NCDs in three major hospitals in Mozambique during the "wet" and "dry" season by completing a second observational survey in the opposite season to the first. To match data from the initial surveys, we will collect data from a minimum of 3,500 patients during the second 30-day snapshot period for the three participating hospitals - by completing electronic surveys using Microsoft Access and then following up patients' discharge details from the hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be followed from point-of-admission up until discharge over two 30-day snapshot/observation periods for each participating hospital conducted in two different seasons (wet and dry) between April 2016 and December 2018.

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>During each study period (initially four sets of 30-day snap=shot periods followed by a repeat snap-shot in the opposite season), all patients (i.e. 24 hours a day) presenting to the emergency department of the participating hospitals will be recorded and cases randomly selected for more detailed clinical profiling. All selected patients, regardless of age, will be included in the screening process.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded from the study if they are unable to respond to the trained nurses or the study survey team (i.e., unconscious, confused due to mental illness, severely ill, or under the influence of illicit drugs) unless the study team is able to obtain data from a family member/partner.  
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The study will be undertaken and reported according to STROBE guidelines for observational studies. As the eligible population for screening includes every patient presenting at the emergency department over a 30-day period (varying from 4,000-6,000 patients per month depending on the hospital), a systematic selection process of consecutive cases (according to arrival sequence) will be applied to achieve a minimum target of 1,000 patients per snapshot period. Based on recruitment during the first phase of screening (completed in April 2017) a target of 7000 participants has been established.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>7</followup>
    <followuptype>Days</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Random sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>7000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>3644</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <state>Maputo City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <state>Nampula</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <state>Sofala</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research Centre for Research Excellence, Australian Catholic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>215 Spring Street
Melbourne VIC
3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Instituto Nacional de Saude</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Av. Eduardo Mondlane/Salvador Allende
Caixa Postal 264
Maputo  Mozambique
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Mozambique</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research Centre for Research Excellence, Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>215 Spring Street,
Melbourne VIC
3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Instituto Nacional de Saude</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Av. Eduardo Mondlane/Salvador Allende
Caixa Postal 264
Maputo  Mozambique</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Mozambique</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Both Communicable diseases (CDs) and Non-Communicable diseases (NCDs) are a growing public health concern worldwide. However, there is limited data describing the epidemiological balance between CDs and NCDs in developing countries. In sub-Saharan Africa, NCDs are responsible for a third of the disability-adjusted life year burden, and are becoming critical health issues. Mozambique, where the population is expected to double by 2030 and life expectancy is increasing will be a key barometer of epidemiological transition in the region. Our primary aim is to examine and describe the current and likely epidemiological balance between CDs and NCDs within the Mozambique population. 
The MOZambique snApshot of emeRging Trends (MOZART) Disease Surveillance Study is a prospective, multi-centre study with random profiling of one-in-five representative case presentations at four tertiary hospitals in Mozambique. For each participating hospital, surveys will be conducted for 30 consecutive days at a time and then replicated in a different season, to capture seasonal changes in profile between the wet and dry seasons. All patients presenting to the Emergency Departments during the study period will be eligible for screening and those recruited will be followed from point-of-admission up until discharge.
This unique study, to be undertaken in a low-resource setting will provide invaluable data in respect to the balance of CDs and NCDs in different regions of Mozambique, and at different times of the year. The initial pilot study confirmed both the feasibility (&gt;1300 cases comprehensively profiled) and value of the study in this regard.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mozambican National Bioethical Committee/Ministerio da Saude, </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Instituto Nacional de Saude &amp; Universidade Eduardo Mondlane
Avenida Eduardo Mondlane, 1008
Maputo, Mozambique
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Mozambique</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ana Mocumbi</name>
      <address>Instituto Nacional de Saude &amp; Universidade Eduardo Mondlane
Avenida Eduardo Mondlane, 1008
Maputo, Mozambique
</address>
      <phone>+258 2143 1103 / +258 2131 1038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amocumbi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ashley K Keates</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Australian Catholic University
215 Spring Street
Melbourne VIC
3000</address>
      <phone>+61 477 166 859</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kimberley.Keates@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Simon Stewart</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Australian Catholic University
215 Spring Street
Melbourne VIC
3000</address>
      <phone>+61 438 302 111</phone>
      <fax>(+613) 9663 5726</fax>
      <email>Simon.Stewart@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ashley K Keates</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Australian Catholic University
215 Spring Street
Melbourne 
3000</address>
      <phone>+61 477 166 859</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kimberley.Keates@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>