<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368551">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000587505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Residential Ocular Care Study: A Multi-Centered, Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial comparing the effectiveness of an innovative and comprehensive new eye care model with usual care for individuals in Residential Aged Care Facilities</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Residential Ocular Care Study: A Multi-Centered, Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial comparing the effectiveness of an innovative and comprehensive new eye care model with usual care for individuals in Residential Aged Care Facilities</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vision impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mobility</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Falls</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is the Residential Ocular Care (ROC) intervention model, which is a novel model of eye care for people living in residential care facilities. This
comprehensive model includes a thorough on-site eye examination with four subsequent intervention
options for those with vision impairment, namely: 
(a) refraction and spectacle provision - glasses will be prescribed; 
(b) cataract surgery - participants will be referred to the Royal Victorian Eye and Ear hospital as a public patient where surgery costs will be covered, or they can elect to go privately but will have to cover any out of pocket costs. Reimbursement will be covered for travel to and from the surgery as well as for preop assessments and 2 post op assessments;
(c) low vision rehabilitation - participants will be referred to Vision Australia where low vision therapists will conduct a low vision examination and dispense low vision aids. A follow up session and training session on how to use the aids will also be provided; and 
(d) referral to an ophthalmologist for medical and surgical treatments for conditions likely to cause loss of sight or ocular discomfort. If our vision assessment uncovers cases of vision impairment not covered by the other interventions a referral will be made to an appropriate ophthalmologist at a local public hospital for medical treatment or surgical interventions as required at no cost to the participant. 

Participants will only be given one of the 4 interventions specified above that best suits their need.

The ROC Model of care will be administered at Baseline visits where one of the four interventions will be given. 

Quality of life questionnaires will be administered at baseline, 2 month and 6 month.

At 6 month optometrists will conduct another comprehensive eye tests

The onsite comprehensive eye examinations are carried out by the Optometrist from the Australian College of Optometry and involve testing of visual acuity, subjective refraction and reading fluency. Examinations will be carried out to assess intraocular eye pressures, visual fields and dilated examinations of the back of the eye. Scans will also be taken of the back of the eye. </interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator will be the usual care group. Usual eye care for residents is informal although some facilities may use a mobile optometric unit to conduct yearly assessments. 

The usual care group will not receive any intervention at baseline however quality of life questionnaires will be administered at Baseline, 2 month and 6 month. 

At 6 month optometrists will conduct a comprehensive eye test.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effectiveness of ROC with usual care on presenting and best corrected near vision
Assessed with the Bailey Lovie Logmar near vision chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effectiveness of ROC on presenting best corrected distance vision.
Assessed with a Logmar Vision Chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 2 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effectiveness of ROC on residential care-specific daily functioning.
Assessed with the IVI-RC questionnaire


</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-2 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To quantify the cost effectiveness of ROC at 6 months post intervention. 

A cost effective analysis to quantify the health improvements gained relative to the resources expended will be conducted. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effectiveness of ROC on overall and vision specific quality of life. 

Assessed with the EQ-5D and Quality of Vision questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-2 and 6 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effectiveness of ROC on depression assessed by the ACFI 10 - Cornell Scale for Depression questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>1-2 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effectiveness of ROC on rates of falls by obtaining data from the facility using a falls risk questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected for falls 3 months prior to baseline visit and 6 months after baseline visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effectiveness of ROC on residents eye care utilisation. Using a questionnaire that asks them if they are using their eye care (eg. glasses, magnifiers), what activities they use them for and for how long. 
intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria
(i) Presenting distance vision of 6/15 or less and/or Near vision of N8 or less in both eyes
(ii) Ability to speak English
(iii) People deemed not cognitively impaired as determined by the Psychogeriatric Assessment Scale (PAS) questionnaire. A score of &lt;15 in the PAS is deemed eligible.  
(iv) Ability to undergo visual acuity testing and provide reliable results</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria
(i) Presenting distance vision of 6/12 or better and/or Near vision of better than N8 in both eyes
(ii) Inability to speak English
(iii)People with a cognitive impairment as determined by the Psychogeriatric Assessment Scale (PAS) questionnaire. A score of &gt;15 in the PAS is deemed ineligible. 
(iii) Non-english speaking residents
(iv) inability to be tested for vision
(v) contraindication(s) as indicated by general practitioner responsible for residents care. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization schedules will be developed at the Centre for Eye Research Australia using a list of
computer generated pseudo-random numbers designed to yield expected assignment ratio of 1:1. For
logistical reasons and to minimise confounding effects, we will randomize by residential care facility into
ROC or usual care. This will be undertaken by the Project Manager and facilities will be informed of the
allocation after the screening consultations.
After the patient has given written informed consent, and screening and baseline data have been obtained
and passed eligibility review, the resident will be assigned an identification code made up of the residential
care facility, and a 3 digit no along with the patients’ initials. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>395</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Eye Research Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne
VIC 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health Medical Record Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ROC study aims to compare the effectiveness of a new model of eye care (Residential Ocular Care) with the Usual care received in aged care homes on presenting and best corrected near and distance vision. It will also assess the effectiveness off ROC on various aspects of quality of life, depression, rate of falls and eye care utilisation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mercy Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mercy Hospital for Women
Floor 6, Administration, 163 Studley Road
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>R13-52AC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ecosse Lamoureux</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia
Level 1, 32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne
VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9929 8434</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ecosse@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Marios Constantinou</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia
Level 1, 32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne 
VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9929 8434</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mariosc@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Marios Constantinou</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia
Level 1, 32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne 
VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9929 8434</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mariosc@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>