<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365937">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000348651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Fun 'n Fitness Exercise Program (Falls Prevention Program)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Exercise for balance: A randomised controlled trial to evaluate the safety, feasibility, efficacy and mediators of group exercise to reduce falls in aged care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-3347 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>High falls risk</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This research will evaluate a group exercise program that aims to prevent falls and improve balance among residents of Churches of Christ run aged care facilities in Queensland. 

Study design
The study is designed as a single-blinded 12-month cluster randomized controlled trial. 

Centres and Participants 
Churches of Christ (CofCQLD) operates 18 residential aged care facilities in Queensland. The 14 centres with more than 25 residents each will be involved in this study. The centres will be matched pair wise according to number of residents and low/high care ratio; from each pair, one centre will be allocated to the intervention group and one centre will be allocated to the control group using a blinded randomisation procedure. Randomisation will take place after completion of baseline testing. Sample size calculations showed that over 600 participants are needed to detect statistically significant differences in falls risk; the total number of residents in these 14 sites is 1103. 

Intervention group
Participants will be invited to attend twice weekly, 30-45 min group exercise sessions within the premises of the residential aged care facility for a 12 month period. The sessions are led by lifestyle coordinators and supervised by a physiotherapist. The sessions involve a range of group-based exercises designed to incorporate all the major components that are found to support and manage fall risks among older people, including strength, balance, fitness/endurance, and gait.  Further falls prevention strategies incorporated within the program include dual-tasking, enhancement of speed of reaction and the ability to take that step to regain balance, and bodily coordination. The program is designed to allow participants of all ability levels to participate and be challenged whilst encouraging and supporting each other. Examples of exercises include:
-	Range of motion and stretching in warm up and cool down
-	Variations in standing balance  chair support, side stepping, weight shift, arm movements
-	Sit to stands  slow and faster; skiers exercise
-	In chair exercises at fast pace for upper and lower limbs to challenge cardiovascular fitness
-	Coordination  throwing and catching balls, eyes follow and finger-to-nose movements 
-	Speed of reaction using coloured boards  pointing to correct colour on boards with foot as called by leader at speed</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group
The control group will receive usual care. As participants who are receiving structured muscle strengthening and balance training similar to those in the exercise program will be excluded from the study, usual care for our participants is not likely to involve structured supervised exercise.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls, defined as (i) proportion of fallers, (ii) the number of falls, (iii) number of injurious falls, and (iv) time to each fall. 

The dates of each fall as well as details surrounding each fall will be extracted from the centres incidents database. Falls are recorded centrally by each centre as part of standard procedure. This information will be given to the researchers monthly during the intervention as well as for the 12 months after the end of the intervention to assess sustainability of the intervention effect.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 12 and 24 months following baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical functioning 

A battery of functional performance tests will be used to assess mediators of fall risk - including muscle strength (repeated chair stand test), balance (four-test balance scale and sway-meter), and usual walking speed (6-metre walk test) under single (usual walking) and dual tasking (naming animals and subtracting serial 7s). Grip strength will also be tested as a measure of upper body strength. Prior to these tests a demonstration of each test will be given by the tester. Functional performance measures will be conducted in a standardised order and with appropriate rest periods between trials. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and again 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 6 months, 12 months following baseline testing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Well-being

Physical and mental well-being will be assessed with the Dementia Quality of Life Questionnaire (DQoL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and again 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 6 months, 12 months following baseline testing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants are Churches of Christ Queensland residents from aged care centres aged 65 years and older. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Residents will be excluded from participating in the trial if they: (i) are confined to their bed or are wheelchair dependent at all times, (ii) are unable to stand or remain standing unaided, or (iii) have any medical conditions (musculoskeletal, cardiopulmonary or metabolic) that would prevent their safe participation in the exercises program. Residents will also be excluded if they have been receiving regular (1 or more times per week on average) physiotherapy or exercise therapy that involves balance and/or muscle strengthening exercises similar to those included in the intervention during the past 6 months or anytime during the intervention period.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>(i)	During information sessions for Churches of Christ Queensland (CofCQLD) staff at each of the sites, the aim and protocol of the study will be explained. All queries from staff will be addressed. 
(ii)	Local CofCQLD staff will assist with recruitment by providing names of residents meeting inclusion criteria and these residents and their relatives or power of attorney and/or statutory health guardian will be contacted by project staff to explain the study and consent procedure. Oral and written information will be provided. 
(iii)	If willing to participate, the residents and their relatives or power of attorney and/or statutory health guardian will be asked to sign informed consent.

Churches of Christ (CofCQLD) operates 18 residential aged care facilities in Queensland. The 14 centres with more than 25 residents each will be involved in this study. The centres will be matched pair wise according to number of residents and low/high care ratio; from each pair, one centre will be allocated to the intervention group and one centre will be allocated to the control group using a blinded randomisation procedure. Allocation concealment was performed via central randomisation by a computer.

Randomisation will take place after completion of baseline testing. Sample size calculations showed that over 600 participants are needed to detect statistically significant differences in falls risk; the total number of residents in these 14 sites is 1103. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations showed that, with a significance level of 0.05, a power of 80%, an intra-class-correlation of 0.07 to adjust for the clustering effect, an annual fall rate of 60% in the control group, and an expected 30% reduction in proportion of fallers in the intervention group, 250 participants would be needed per group. Taking into account a drop-out rate of 25%, a minimum of 313 participants per group should be high enough to detect statistically significant differences. 

The proportions of fallers will be compared between the intervention and control groups. Group differences in number of falls and number of injurious falls will be tested using Cox Proportional Hazards models with extension for multiple events. This analysis allows inclusion of the number of falls as well as the time to each fall resulting in optimal power. Potential effect modification of baseline cognitive and physical functioning will be tested; if significant, the results will be presented for the relevant subgroups. Differences in pre-post intervention scores on measures of physical function and quality of life will be compared between the intervention and control groups using multi-level regression analyses. To examine which factors mediate the programs effectiveness, structured equation modelling will be used to model the effect of each of the potential mediators on the fall risk. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Tina Skinner</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Human Movement Studies (#26B), Room 520
Cnr Blair Drive &amp; Union Road
The University of Queensland, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane Qld 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Human Movement Studies, The University of Queensland Strategic Seed Funding</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Human Movement Studies (#26B)
Cnr Blair Drive &amp; Union Road
The University of Queensland, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane Qld 4072
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Geeske Peeters</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Human Movement Studies (#26B)
Cnr Blair Drive &amp; Union Road
The University of Queensland, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane Qld 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Churches of Christ Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Churches of Christ in Queensland
41 Brookfield Rd. Kenmore QLD 4069
P.O. Box 508 Kenmore QLD 4069
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Carmela Lagasca</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Churches of Christ in Queensland
41 Brookfield Rd. Kenmore QLD 4069
P.O. Box 508 Kenmore QLD 4069
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Delma Glindemann</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lady Small Haven Aged Care Service
Churches of Christ Care
60 Allchurch Avenue Benowa QLD 4217
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sandy Brauer</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health &amp; Rehabilitation Sciences
Therapies Annexe Building 84
Level 8, Room 805
The University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD 4072
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Susan Tett</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Pharmacy, The University of Queensland
Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence
Level 4, 20 Cornwall Street
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102

</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Each year, about 2 in 3 adults living in aged care centres falls at least once. These falls can have serious consequences such as injuries and mobility limitations or fear to fall again. Churches of Christ Queensland have designed an exercise program to prevent falls and improve balance among residents of aged care centres. This study aims to evaluate the feasibility and efficacy of this exercise program. The outcome of this study will help inform and facilitate ongoing improvements in falls prevention and management.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>http://www.hms.uq.edu.au/news/study-set-to-reduce-falls-in-aged-care/</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Coordinator
UQ Research &amp; Innovation
Cumbrae-Stewart Building (72)
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND QLD 4072
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014000043</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tina Skinner</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies (#26B), Room 520
Cnr Blair Drive &amp; Union Road
The University of Queensland, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane Qld 4072
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 8810</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tskinner@hms.uq.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Carmela Lagasca</name>
      <address>Churches of Christ in Queensland
41 Brookfield Rd. Kenmore QLD 4069
P.O. Box 508 Kenmore QLD 4069</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3363 1755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carmela.lagasca@cofcqld.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Geeske Peeters</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies (#26B)
Cnr Blair Drive &amp; Union Road
The University of Queensland, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 9999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.peeters@uq.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tina Skinner</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies (#26B), Room 520
Cnr Blair Drive &amp; Union Road
The University of Queensland, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 8810</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tskinner@hms.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>