<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369994">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000506493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of Aerobic Exercise in Sitting Posture versus Aerobic Exercise in Standing Posture in older adults with Knee Osteoarthritis and overweight. Randomized Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of Aerobic Exercise in Sitting Posture versus Aerobic Exercise in Standing Posture in older adults with Knee Osteoarthritis and overweight. Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Knee Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight and Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Aerobic Exercise in Sitting Position (Experimental Group) 

A group of patients suffering Knee Ostearthritis (KOA) will be asked to execute 30 minutes of Aerobic Exercises seated on a chair. The intensity of the exercise is in the range of 50-70% maximal heart rate.
This 30 minutes are organized as follows: 
*Five minutes of warm-up: In a seated position:  1 minute of hip flexo-extension to the extent possible. 1 minute of hip flexo-extension while shoulder up and down movements are executed , 1 minute of hip flexo-extension while protraction and retraction of the shoulders are performed, and 1 minute of hip flexo-extension while shoulders rolls are executed. Finally 1 minute of rest. 
*Twenty-five minutes of aerobic phase: Patients are asked to execute hip flexo-extension during this 25 minutes without stopping. During this time a sequence of one minute movements with the upper extremity is performed. First exercise of the sequence:  90 degrees of shoulder flexion alternating right and left arms.  Second exercise: Touch the knee with the contralateral hand. Third exercise: Clap in front of him with 90 degrees for shoulder flexion. Fourth exercise, patients perform elbow flexo-extension. Fifth exercise of the sequence: consists in hugging himself. This sequence is repeated 5 times. 
*Five minutes of cooldown: The same exercises of the warm-up but this time in reverse order.
As with the control group, fifteen minutes of inferior limb strengthening and fifteen minutes of stretching exercises (both regulated by the pain threshold of each subject) will follow this Aerobic Exercise. Strengthening will be executed in a lying position: 10 quadriceps, hamstring, adductors, abductors and sural triceps, isometric contractions, held for 10 seconds with 2 seconds of rest between each repetition, both legs.  The stretching will be also performed in a lying position, as follows: 10 Quadriceps, hamstring, adductors, abductors and sural triceps elongations, held for 10 seconds with 2 seconds of rest between each repetition both legs.
This program will be performed 3 times a week during 4 weeks at the Centro de Especialidades para el Diagnostico y Tratamiento de Azuqueca de Henares (Specialization of Diagnosis and Treatment Center of Azuqueca de Henares), every session will be led by the 2 investigators both graduated as physiotherapists and working in this project. Once the 12 supervised sessions achieved, a DVD reminder of the routines worked during previous sessions, and produced by the team of investigators will be given to each and every patient in order to enable them to continue the treatment at theirs homes 3 times a week for 8 weeks.
To improve the adherence to the treatment, a self-register format is provided to the patient (a calendar in which the patient will match the days he accomplished the exercise), this paper should be returned to the team every 4 weeks.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Aerobic Exercise in Standing Position (Control group).

A group of patients suffering Knee Ostearthritis (KOA) will be asked to walk in the intervention room (normal walk, without treadmill) for 30 minutes as an Aerobic Exercise. The intensity of the exercise oscillates between 50-70% maximal heart rate.
The 30 minutes of aerobic exercise are organized as follows:
*Five minutes of warm-up: 4 minutes of light walk and 1 minute of rest.
*Twenty-five minutes of aerobic phase:  25 minutes of more vigorous walk (in the range of 50 and 70% maximal heart rate).
*Five minutes of cooldown: 1 minute of rest and 4 minutes of light walk.

Fifteen minutes of inferior limb strengthening and fifteen minutes of stretching exercises (both regulated by the pain threshold of each subject) will follow this Aerobic Exercise. Strengthening will be executed in a lying position: 10 quadriceps, hamstring, adductors, abductors and sural triceps, isometric contractions, held for 10 seconds with 2 seconds of rest between each repetition.  The stretching will be also performed in a lying position, as follows: 10 Quadriceps, hamstring, adductors, abductors and sural triceps elongations, held for 10 seconds with 2 seconds of rest between each repetition both legs.
This program will be performed 3 times a week for 4 weeks in the Centro de Especialidades para Diagnostico y Tratamiento de Azuqueca de Henares (Specialization of Diagnosis and Treatment Center of Azuqueca de Henares), every session will be guided by the 2 investigators, both graduated as physiotherapist, and working in this project. Once the 12 sessions supervised by the investigators will finish, a DVD reminder of the routines worked during previous sessions will be given to each and every patient in order to enable them to continue the treatment at home 3 times a week during 8 weeks. This digital support is produced by the investigation team.
To improve the adherence to the treatment, a self-register format is provided to the patient (a calendar in which the patient will match the days he accomplished the exercise), this paper should be returned to the team every 4 weeks.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee pain assessed using VAS: 100 mm Visual Analogue Scale  validated. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after 12 sessions (4 weeks), after 24 sessions (8 weeks)  and after 36 sessions (12 weeks)  of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Pain, Stiffnes and Physical Function in knee Osteoarthritis is assessed using WOMAC: Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after 12 sessions (4 weeks), after 24 sessions (8 weeks) and after 36 sessions  (12 weeks) of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life is assessed using: SF12: Short Form 12 Health Surveys. 12 items for psychometrically-based physical component summary (PCS) and mental component summary (MCS) scores  Validated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after 12 sessions(4 weeks), after 24 sessions (8 weeks) and after 36 sessions (12 weeks) of treatment.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment adherence is assessed using Adherence percentage and The Therapeutic Exercise Adherence Questionnaire  designed specifically for the study. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 sessions (4 weeks) ,24 sessions (8 weeks) and 36 sessions  (12 weeks) of treatment.  
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weightloss is assessed by measuring the weigth of each patient in Kg. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 sessions (4 weeks) ,24 sessions (8 weeks) and 36 sessions  (12 weeks) of treatment.  
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and women age 50 to 80, with clinical diagnosis of Knee Osteoarthritis by the doctor assigned in the Centro de Especialidades para el Diagnostico y Tratamiento de Azuqueca de Henares (Specialisted Center of Diagnosis and Treatment  of Azuqueca de Henares) and  enrolled with overweight or obese, considering overweight as Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt; 25 kg/m2 and Obesity as (BMI) &gt; 30 Kg/m2.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients unable to walk or exercise without funtional aids, patients with previous knee surgery, and patients with serious unstable medical and psychological condition and patientes with advanced stage of osteoporosis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The investigators will prepare 26 sealed opaques envelopes, 13 of them will have the word “seated” and 13 the word “stand” that represent the group to which the subject will be allocated. Once the investigators will selected the subjects eligible for inclusion in the trial, patients will be asked by the external evaluators to choose one sealed opaque envelope, this way, the allocation concealment method will be used.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using procedures like coin-tossing and dice-rolling. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a randimized controlled trial. 

The variable pain was selected as the primary measure in this study. 
It has been considered a size effect (ZE) ZE=0.25. The correlation between repeated measurements is assumed at 0.5.  Taking in compte that 4 measures has been realized (pre-intervention, post12, post24 and post36 in two treatment groups, the sphericity correction was determined in 0,5. 
The statistic power was set up at 0.80, with an alpha level of 0.05, so, a total sample size of 24 patients was estimated. And considering 15% of the losses, it was estimated to reach a total of 26 patients, with 13 subjects per group, using the Gpower Software 3.0.18.

Data will be organised and analysed with the SPSS 22 for Windows. 
Two interventions will be compared on an intention to treat basis, irrespective of the degree of compliance with the exercise programme, across 4 measurements, baseline, after 12, 24 and 36 sessions of treatment. 
Between group differences will be compared using unpaired T Tests.
Descriptive data will be expressed as mean median and standard deviation. 
The significance level will be set
at p=0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>20/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/04/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>26</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>26</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/09/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Azuqueca de Henares, Guadalajara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidad de Alcala de Henares</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Campus Universitario - C/ 19, Ctra. Madrid-Barcelona, Km 33,600, 28805 Alcala de Henares, Madrid Espana. </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidad de Alcala de Henares</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Campus Universitario - C/ 19, Ctra. Madrid-Barcelona, Km 33,600, 28805 Alcala de Henares, Madrid, Espana. </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Centro de Especialidades para el Diagnostico y Tratamiento de Azuqueca de Henares </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>C/Progreso 1, 19200 Azuqueca de Henares, Espana</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Spain</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this study is to investigate whether Aerobic Exercises executed in a Sitting Position are more effective than Aerobic ones performed in a Standing Position, both, for treating Knee Osteoarthritis (KOA) on major adults with overweight and obesity.
The greater load applied over the joints, the greater degeneration the joint suffers; and because of the great number of people suffering joints degeneration due to the overweight factor, it is necessary to implement a new therapeutic alternative to adjust to the necessities of this patients. This can be done by making them practice an aerobic training outload by employing a chair as a therapeutic tool. 
Scientific evidence suggests that the most effective non pharmacological treatment against the KOA is the execution of a program of exercises based on Aerobic Exercise, in combination with strengthening and stretching exercises.  For this reason, it is proposed to compare two different kinds of aerobic exercise (standing position (control group, by walking 30 minutes), and sitting position (experimental group, by movements sitting in a chair guided by the investigators for 30 minutes). Immediately both groups will execute the same protocol of 15 minutes of Strengthening exercises (10 isometric quadriceps, hamstring, adductors, abductors and sural triceps contractions held for 10 seconds with 2 seconds of rest between each repetition of both legs), plus 15 minutes of Stretching exercises (quadriceps, hamstring, adductors, abductors and sural triceps stretching held for 10 seconds with 2 seconds of rest between each repetition of both legs). This way, the only difference between groups will be the kind of Aerobic Exercise they will perform.
This program could be divided in two phases:
1.	Supervised by the investigators: Participants will attend in groups 3 sessions per week during 4 weeks (12 sessions) to complete this program leaded by the investigators. 
2.	 Individually, each participant will execute the same exercise routine at home, following a DVD provided by the investigators, 3 time a week for 8 weeks (24 sessions).
This way, every intervention group will be evaluated at baseline, after 12, 24 and 36 sessions of treatment with their respective test as follows:
Pain with the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS); Pain, Stiffness and Functional Capacity measured with the Western 'Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC); the qualitys life evaluated with the Short Form 12 Health Survey (SF12); and the Adherence to the Theurapeutic Exercices tested by the percentage and The Therapeutic Exercise Adherence Questionnary  (non validated). 
The investigators hypothesize that Aerobic Exercises in a Sitting Position are more effective than in a Standing Position ones to treat patients with KOA and Overweigh or Obesity.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica de la Investigacion y de la Experimentacion Animal de la Universidad de Alcala.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ctra. Madrid-Barcelona Km 33,600. 28805  Alcala de Henares Madrid.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CEIM/HUM/2015/29</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite Etico de Investigacion Clinica del Hospital Universitario Principe de Asturias. </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Carretera Alcala-Meco, s/n, 28805 Alcala de Henares, Madrid</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>OE 28/2015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369994-Aprobación Comité Universidad.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369994-Dictamen y conformidad OE28-15 HUPA.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Betsy Denisse Perez Huerta</name>
      <address>Universidad de Alcala de Henares - Campus Universitario - Fisioterapia -Ctra. Madrid-Barcelona Km 33,600. 28805  Alcala de Henares Madrid.</address>
      <phone>+ 34 69 23 15 150</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>betsy.perez@edu.uah.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Betsy Denisse Perez Huerta</name>
      <address>Universidad de Alcala de Henares - Campus Universitario - Fisioterapia -Ctra. Madrid-Barcelona Km 33,600. 28805  Alcala de Henares Madrid</address>
      <phone>+ 34 69 23 15 150</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>betsy.perez@edu.uah.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Betsy Denisse Perez Huerta</name>
      <address>Universidad de Alcala de Henares - Campus Universitario - Fisioterapia -Ctra. Madrid-Barcelona Km 33,600. 28805  Alcala de Henares Madrid</address>
      <phone>+ 34 69 23 15 150</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>betsy.perez@edu.uah.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Betsy Denisse Perez Huerta</name>
      <address>Campus Universitario - Fisioterapia -Ctra. Madrid-Barcelona Km 33,600. 28805  Alcala de Henares Madrid</address>
      <phone>+ 34 69 23 15 150</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>betsy.perez@edu.uah.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>