<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365239">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001363774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> A double-blind placebo-controlled trial of a Lactium and Zizyphus complex for sleep</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> A double-blind placebo-controlled trial of a Lactium and Zizyphus complex for sleep</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1149-3113 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Poor quality sleep</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Lactium and Zizyphus complex, LZ Complex3 a herb and supplement complex, 2 tablets (1600mg/tab) daily before retiring for sleep, for 14 days.

Drug tablet return; Daily completion of participant diary; compliance check at clinic visits. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (Isomalt) 2 tablets daily before retiring for sleep, for 14 days.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome: To assess overall sleep quality using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) in healthy adults experiencing sleep problems.</outcome>
      <timepoint>on days 8, 9, 11, 15, 22 and 29.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess overall sleep quality using: Leeds Sleep Evaluation Questionnaire (LSEQ); Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS); Insomnia Severity Index (ISS) and a Daily Sleep Diary </outcome>
      <timepoint>LSEQ, ESS &amp; ISS on days 8, 9, 11, 15, 22 and 29. Daily Sleep Diary: Day1 through to Day 22.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess daytime functioning and physical fatigue using: Chalder Fatigue Scale and the Burckhardt Quality of Life scale.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: on days 8, 9, 11, 15, 22 and 29.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess mood and anxiety using composite scores from: Bond-Lader, STAI-S, Stress &amp; Fatigue Visual Analogue Mood Scales and cognitive performance Purple Multi-tasking framework.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mood timepoints: on days 8, 9, 11, 15, 22 and 29.
Anxiety timepoints: on days 8, 9, 11, 15, 22 and 29.
Cognitive Performance Timepoints: on days 8, 22 and 29.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess stress reactivity using: Bond-Lader Visual Analogue Scales and the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI-s) for Adults and Fatigue Visual Analogue Mood scales. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: on days on days 8, 22 and 29.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety of LZ Complex3 in this population using:
Adverse Event reporting.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: from entering the study until the end of study visit (visit 4 / day 29).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess post treatment effects of all secondary outcomes using: Leeds Sleep Evaluation Questionnaire (LSEQ); Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS); Insomnia Severity Index (ISS);Chalder Fatigue Scale and the Burckhardt Quality of Life scale; Bond-Lader Visual Analogue Scales; Fatigue Visual Analogue Mood scales; State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI-s) and the PURPLE multitasking framework.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To assess the post treatment effects up to 1 week following 2 weeks of treatment from the end of treatment Visit 3 on Day 22 to the follow-up Visit 4 on Day 29.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory Objective, sleep quality using Actigraphy to explore cross-validation of endpoints</outcome>
      <timepoint>From D8 to D29</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>I01. Individuals with no significant diagnosed diseases by the judgment of the Investigator, who self-report sleeping difficulties over a 1 month prior to the screening call.
I02. Age range 18-65 years
I03. Body Mass Index 18-30 kg/m2
I04. Normal vital signs 
I05. Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index Score greater than 5. 
I06. Typical bedtime between 9 pm and 12 am.
I07. Symptoms consistent with Primary Insomnia established at screening. 
I08. Signed written informed consent </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>E01. Hospital Depression and Anxiety Scale (HADS) depression score greater than 8 and/or anxiety score greater than 12 (assessed at screening)
E02. Regular use of illicit drugs, excessive or inappropriate use of over the counter (OTC) or prescription drugs or excessive use of alcohol (assessed by the Investigator or delegate and/or reported by the potential participant) 
E03. Smoking more than 10 cigarettes a day 
E04. Consumption of stimulants: more than 10 cups of tea or coffee (or equivalent of other caffeine containing drinks), thus exceeding an intake of more than 2 litres a day and/or consumption of these drinks after 5 p.m.
E05. Allergy to milk proteins, latex or LZ Complex 3 ingredients
E06. Subjects with a primary sleep disorder (sleep apnoea-hypopnoea, periodic limb movement disorder, restless legs syndrome, narcolepsy, idiopathic hypersomnia, Kleine-Levin syndrome)
E07. Use of medicinal products for sleep disorders (e.g. hypnotic agents, anxiolytics, herbal remedies, homeopathy for hypnotic purposes) in the month prior to inclusion, or exhibiting withdrawal symptoms from the use of medicinal products for sleep disorders at screening.
E08. On-going non-pharmacological treatment of sleep disorders (e.g. cognitive behavioural therapy, relaxation therapy) 
E09. Expected sleep disturbance from external sources during the study period (such as young children or other household disturbance).
E10. Previous failure on prescription sleep medication 
E11. Pregnancy or lactation
E12. Current sleep disturbance due to pain or a general medical condition including but not limited to Pain, Cystitis, Urinary frequency, Heart burn or others by the judgment of the Investigator would preclude participation in the study.
E13. Sleep Efficiency greater than 85% AND Sleep Onset Latency below 31 minutes AND Wake after Sleep Onset below 31 minutes (assessed during week 1 using the Consensus Sleep Diary).
E14. Participants who withdraw consent during screening (participants who are not willing to continue or fail to return).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Numbered treatment kits, manually assigned.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation
Created by SAS (statistical software) 
Checked by programmer and independent statistician 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Saint-Hilaire et al (2009) conducted a trial of Lactium and found a difference between active and placebo which emerged after 14 days and was most evident at 28 days. The study used parametric statistics and presents medians and ranges. However it is possible to use these to estimate effect size drawing on the methodology of Hozo et al 2005. These provide effect sizes of approximately 0.4 and 0.65 at day 14 and 28 respectively. We suggest that the effect size for LZ Complex3 will be similar to the day 28 value for the following reasons: the addition of other active ingredients which may summate or act synergistically with lactium and the use of a placebo run-in which will effectively screen out placebo responders. 
The following calculation is based on the assumption that there will be an effect size of around 0.5 i.e. a medium effect size (0.5). We predict that there will be an advantage for LZ Complex3 so the calculation is based on a one-tailed test with 80% power to detect a change at the a equals 5% level (see output below): 

t tests - Means: Difference between two independent means (two groups) 
Analysis: A priori: Compute required sample size 
Input: Tail(s) equals Two 
Effect size d equals 0.5 
a err prob equals 0.05 
Power (1-Beta err prob) equals 0.8 
Allocation ratio N2/N1 equals 1 

Output: Noncentrality parameter d equals 2.8284271 
Critical t equals 1.9789706 
Df equals 126 
Sample size group 1 equals 64 
Sample size group 2 equals 64 
Total sample size equals 128 
Actual power equals 0.8014596 

The required number of participants for each treatment arm is calculated at 64.
To account for 33% of patient dropouts/non-compliance, the total number of participants to be included in the two week double-blind randomised treatment period will be 170.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/12/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/12/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>170</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>171</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3122 - Hawthorn</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi Australia pty ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Talavera Corporate Centre
Building D, 12-24 Talavera Road
Macquarie Park, NSW 2113</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sanofi Consumer Healthcare pty ltd
(sanofi-aventis group)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>87 Yarraman Place,
Virginia, QLD, 4014</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Swinburne University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Human Psychopharmacology 
Swinburne University 
ATC 1009, Mail H24, PO Box 218
Hawthorn 
Victoria, 3122
AUSTRALIA
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study is investigating the effects of supplementation with a herbal complex called LZ Complex3 on sleep quality, daytime functioning, mood and brain function.  The complex contains a combination of herbal ingredients that have individually been used to improve aspects such as sleep quality, mood, and calmness. The complex also contains dietary supplements that may provide nutritional support for sleep. However, there has not been any studies to date that has looked at the combination of these ingredients together and their effect on sleep quality.         </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The Centre for Human Psychopharmacology at Swinburne University is investigating the effects of 3 weeks supplementation with a herbal complex on sleep quality, mood and brain function.
You may be eligible if you are:
*Experiencing sleeping difficulties (for over a month)
*Age 18-65 years
*In good physical health &amp; free from major diseases
*Not taking any medications or supplements for sleeping
*Non smoker
During the sessions you will be asked to complete a number of sleep and mood questionnaires and undergo a computerised task.

You will be asked to take a daily supplement for 3 weeks

Please note there will be further inclusion criteria to participate in the study. 

You will be compensated for your time at the end of the trial. If you or someone you know are interested in taking part in this clinical trial and would like further information, please contact: Sarah Benson
Phone: +61392144506
Email: swinsleep@gmail.com
</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Ltd.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road
Dulwich SA 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-04-174</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Scholey</name>
      <address>Director, Centre for Human Psychopharmacology
ATC 1009, Mail H24, PO Box 218
Swinburne University
Melbourne 
VIC, 3122 
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+6139214 8932</phone>
      <fax>+6139214 5525</fax>
      <email>andrew@scholeylab.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rebekah Miles</name>
      <address>Head of Communications Consumer Healthcare
Sanofi Consumer Healthcare 
87 Yarraman Place
Virginia
QLD, 4014</address>
      <phone>+61732128794</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rebekah.Miles@sanofi.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Smith</name>
      <address>Manager Research  Product Innovation
Sanofi Consumer Healthcare 
87 Yarraman Place
Virginia
QLD, 4014</address>
      <phone>+61732128670</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Amanda.Smith4@sanofi.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tracy Gandu</name>
      <address>Clinical Project Leader
Sanofi Australia pty ltd
Talavera Corporate Centre
Building D, 12-24 Talavera Road
Macquarie Park 
NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61286662325</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tracy.gandu@sanofi.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>