<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336495">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000136909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ecstasy Check-Up:  A multi-site trial of a brief intervention for ecstasy use</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Ecstasy Check-up: A multi-site trial of a brief intervention for ecstasy use</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ecstasy and other substance use</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Research Group: Within one 50-minute session, the participant explores his/her ecstasy use and values. The specialist then offers feedback regarding the participant's use and provides participants with practical skills for reducing use. Suggestions are made that are in line with the participant's values. It is the decision of the participant to use these skills or not, and they are not pressured to quit or reduce their ecstasy use.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will be randomly allocated either to the Ecstasy Check-Up discussion (Research group) or education-only discussion (Control Group).  Participant's in the control group, receive an educational factsheet that contains the latest facts about ecstasy. They will be given up to 15 minutes to discuss the factsheet with the E-check-up specialist. Participant's in the research group receive the educational factsheet, along with feedback from their assessment. Participants in the research group spend 50 minutes discussing their ecstasy use, feedback, and values.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be ecstasy use measured by conducting a Timeline Followback interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1, 4 and 6 month follow up interviews</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client satisfaction of E Check Up discussion, measured by administering the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire( CSQ-8).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month Follow up interview</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Have used ecstasy in the past 3 months, aged 16 years and over, fluency in English and willing to provide at least 2 locators</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have not used Ecstasy in the last 3 months, are aged less than 16 years old and are not literate in English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment efforts will involve advertisements in the free street press and postings on a range of relevant websites. 

Fliers will be distributed to university campuses and music venues.  When potential participants initially make contact, they will be screened for eligibility, usually by telephone. Those who are ineligible or do not consent to participate in the study will have their details kept for reporting on the reasons for ineligibility. 

When participants appear to meet inclusion criteria, an appointment will be made for a face-to-face discussion about Ecstasy use and values. E Check Up Specialists  who complete the baseline assessments are blind to study condition. Sealed opaque envelops, which contain the randomised condition, are not opened until after a participant is deemed eligible for study inclusion.</concealment>
    <sequence>Software that produces random number sequencing</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>175</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Drug &amp; Alcohol Research Centre
Randwick Campus
R1, 22-32 King Street
Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation (IHBI)
60 Musk Avenue
Kelvin Grove Urban Village
Kelvin Grove, Queensland, 4059</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Our long-term goal is to decrease ecstasy use in Australia by motivating ecstasy users, through brief and early information and discussion, to reduce their use through providing research based information and discussion. The objective  of the proposed research is to evaluate a brief discussion based on motivational interviewing (Ecstasy Check-Up) for regular ecstasy users (1 session) compared with an educational control discussion, which involves provision of an informational booklet regarding the facts and fiction on ecstasy use.  

The primary hypothesis of the proposed study is that the one-session brief motivation interviewing discussion will be associated with lower levels of ecstasy use and dependence than the education only discussion. E Check Up sessions in which the specialist more strongly adheres to motivational interviewing principles are expected to have better outcomes.

Additionally, our secondary hypothesis is that participants in the study will like and gain some positive aspects from both conditions, regardless if they have been assigned the research or the education discussion.

The research is of benefit to participants as it offers an opportunity for them to manage their ecstasy use. This lifestyle change has many benefits including improvements in physical and mental health. This benefit, however, cannot be guaranteed; it is dependent on participants engagement with the discussion. 

At the baseline session, all participants will be assured that any information they provide will remain strictly confidential (within the limits of legal confidentiality and duty of care). After written informed consent is provided and all questions and concerns have been answered, the baseline assessment will occur.

At one-, four-, and six-month follow-ups the research assistant will conduct face-to-face follow-ups with all participants using the measures collected at the baseline assessment. The outcome measures will be modified to assess the relevant durations at each visit. For example, the measures will assess the last 90 days during the baseline assessment, and the past 30-days at the one-month follow-up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Research Services
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3
The University of New South Wales  NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09377</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Melissa Norberg</name>
      <address>National Drug &amp; Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Randwick Campus
R1, 22-32 King Street
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0260</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0201</fax>
      <email>m.norberg@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Laila Khawar</name>
      <address>National Drug &amp; Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Randwick Campus
R1, 22-32 King Street
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0352</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0201</fax>
      <email>l.khawar@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jennifer Mackenzie</name>
      <address>National Drug &amp; Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Randwick Campus
R1, 22-32 King Street
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0352</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0201</fax>
      <email>jenniferm@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>