<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362457">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000506897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Parental presence on bedside clinical rounds (PPBCR) in a neonatal intensive care unit (NICU).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of parental participation on bedside clinical rounds for their child in NICU compared to non-participation on parental satisfaction and level of parental stress.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1130-6411</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PPBCR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parental presence on bedside clinical rounds in NICU</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>* The intervention involves the participant (parents or guardian) accompany health care professionals on their bedside clinical rounds to their child. 

* After obtaining consent, the participant will be randomised to one of two arms: 
1. Attending bedside clinical rounds with health care professionals (PPBCR) group or 
2. Non-attending bedside clinical rounds with health care professionals (Non-PPCBR) group. 

* Parents will rotate between the above two arms but they will have a break (washout period) before changing from one group to the other.

* The duration of time spent in each group and in washout period depends on their infant gestation. If the infant gestation is more than 30 weeks then duration will be 3 days in each group and washout period (thats total of 9 days in the whole study). If the infant gestation is less than or equal 30 weeks then duration will be 7 days in each group and washout period (thats total of 21 days in the whole study).

* At conclusion of each arm, the participant will be asked to complete: 
1. NICU parental stressor scale and 
2. A satisfaction survey about being involved in clinical bedside rounds.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator or control involves the parents not accompanying health care professionals on their bedside clinical rounds to their child.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>At the conclusion of each of the study arms [study (PPCBR)/control (PPCBR)], parents or guardians will be asked to complete satisfaction surveys which include questions pertaining to parent's insights regarding inclusion or exclusion from bedside clinical rounds. The survey includes questions regarding:
1. Knowledge and understanding
2. Communications and collaboration
3. Privacy and confidentiality
4. Parental Stressor Scale for hospitalized infants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The survey should be completed at the conclusion of each study arm:
1. After attending rounds for 3 or 7 days according to infant gestation 
2. After being excluded from rounds for 3 or 7 days according to infant gestation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents (mother and/or their partners) or guardians who fulfil the following criteria will be approached for inclusion in the study:

If their infant is anticipated to stay in NICU for minimal of 11 days. This cut-off is taken as the intervention (PPCBR and non-PPCBR) and washout period will take minimum of 3 days each. In addition we allowed first 2 days for not being included in the study as most mothers will be recovering from delivery/Caesarean Section/Anaesthesia etc).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Parents (mother and/or their partners) or guardians who fulfil the following criteria will be excluded from the study:

1. If their infant is anticipated to stay in NICU for less than 11 days

2. If their infant is anticipated to be transferred to another NICU or local hospital in less than 11 days after admission.

3. Refused to participate in the study

4. Parents or guardians who do not have good command of English (it is not practical to include an interpreter during the rounds as this might put pressure on interpreter service (eg. to attend rounds at 08:30 daily for 7 days per patient and also it will lead to significant delay in the rounds).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Parents will be randomised to start with PPCBR or non-PPCBR intervention using computer generated randomisation protocol. This is done by accessing the trial management website (http://www.discoverquick.com/) which was designed by statistician and information technology consultant not involved in the trial. Access to the website require a password and is restricted to the research team. The randomisation protocol (allocation and sequence) is concealed from the research team and parents and is managed by the trial management website.</concealment>
    <sequence>The sequence will be generated by accessing a randomisation and sequence protocol. This is done by accessing the trial management website (http://www.discoverquick.com/) which was designed by statistician and information technology consultant not involved in the trial. Access to the website require a password and is restricted to the research team. The randomisation protocol (allocation and sequence) is concealed from the research team and parents and is managed by the trial management website.
To ensure that equal number of parents of extremely premature infants are randomised to start with PPCBR and non-PPCBR intervention, we will stratify the randomisation by infant's gestation (gestation less than or equal 30 and more than 30 weeks) using block randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>110</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Abdel-Latif Mohamed</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Neonatology, The Canberra Hospital, Building 11, Level 3, Yamba Drive, 
Garran, ACT 2605</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canberra Hospital Private Practice Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Canberra Hospital Private Practice Trust Fund,
The Canberra Hospital, 
Building 6, Level 3, Yamba Drive,
Garran, ACT 2605</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Why are we doing this study? 
* ACT Health and The Canberra Hospital are motivated to provide care that is both family and patient centred. Currently in the Centre for Newborn Care parents are not involved in clinical bedside rounds. This study will allow parents to attend these rounds for a specified period and gain feedback from the experience via surveys. 

* We aim to use the information gained from this study to introduce a new way of doing clinical beside rounds in our soon to be completed Womens and Childrens Hospital.


What does the study involve?
* After obtaining consent, the participant (parents or guardian) will be randomised to one of two arms: 
1. PPBCR group (attending bedside clinical rounds with health care professionals) or 
2. Non-PPCBR (non-attending bedside clinical rounds with health care professionals). 
* Each group depending on the babys gestation will rotate between attending and not attending rounds spending 3 (if the infant gestation is more than 30 weeks) or 7 (if the infant gestation is less than or equal 30 weeks) days in each group with a similar break in between. 
* The participant will be given regular updates on their baby condition during non-PPCBR and washout break
* At conclusion of each arm, the participant will be asked to complete: 
1. NICU parental stressor scale and 
2. A satisfaction survey about being involved in clinical bedside rounds



What do we hope to achieve with this study?
Through your involvement in this study we aim to:
* Improve communication between families and the clinical team within the Centre for Newborn Care.
* Families being more aware of current clinical management and care plan for their babies, in turn reducing stressors they may experience.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Human Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ACT Health Human Research Ethics Committee Secretariat, Canberra Hospital, Yamba Drive, Garran ACT 2605</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.6.11.121</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/07/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Abdel-Latif Mohamed</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatology, The Canberra Hospital, Building 11, Level 3, Yamba Drive, Garran ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 4056</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 3112</fax>
      <email>Abdel-Latif.Mohamed@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Margaret Broom</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatology, The Canberra Hospital, Building 11, Level 3, Yamba Drive, Garran, ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 3111</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 3112</fax>
      <email>Margaret.Broom@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Abdel-Latif Mohamed</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatology, The Canberra Hospital, Building 11, Level 3, Yamba Drive, Garran ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 4056</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 3112</fax>
      <email>Abdel-Latif.Mohamed@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>