<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371273">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001058460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Long-term effects of Tai Chi in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Long-term effects of Tai Chi on exercise capacity and quality of life in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be asked to undertake an eight-week supervised exercise program of Sun-style Tai Chi. The Tai Chi training will be delivered in a group setting, with a maximum of three participants per group, by a physiotherapist and/or physiotherapy assistant accredited in Sun-style Tai Chi training. Participants will attend two one-hour supervised Tai Chi training sessions each week, and will aim to train at a moderate level of breathlessness or exertion (equivalent to a score of three on the modified Borg 010 scale). To increase the training demand of Tai Chi, participants will be asked to imagine pushing against resistance during all movements or to squat lower in certain movements. Wrist weights of between 0.5-1.5 kg will be worn by participants who do not reach a moderate level of dyspnoea or exertion during training. 

On completion of the supervised program, participants will then be asked to continue with a home-based, unsupervised maintenance Tai Chi program five times weekly for six months. Participants will aim to practice Tai Chi for at least 30 minutes during each home-based session, including a warm-up and cool-down. A training booklet and DVD will be provided to assist with Tai Chi practice at home. During this six-month period, participants will also receive monthly booster sessions of supervised Tai Chi training. There will be six one-hour booster sessions in total. The intensity of Tai Chi training may be adjusted during booster sessions to ensure that participants are exercising at a moderate level of breathlessness or exertion. The addition of monthly booster sessions of supervised Tai Chi training will provide additional real-time feedback during the six-month maintenance program and may enhance compliance with unsupervised home practice of Tai Chi.

Participants will be asked to record the duration and intensity of Tai Chi practice at home in a training diary during the entire intervention period. Adherence to the supervised Tai Chi training program will be monitored by recording attendance at each supervised training session and by reviewing the participants training diary each month. Adherence to the maintenance Tai Chi program will also be monitored using the training diary.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise capacity (6-minute walk test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, completion of the supervised Tai Chi program at 8 weeks, 3 months into the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program, completion of the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program at 6 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life (St Georges Respiratory Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, completion of the supervised Tai Chi program at 8 weeks, 3 months into the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program, completion of the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program at 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance (Brief-BESTest)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, completion of the supervised Tai Chi program at 8 weeks, 3 months into the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program, completion of the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity (SenseWear Armband, Bodymedia, Pittsburgh, USA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be asked to wear the SenseWear Armand for seven days, 24 hours a day, at each assessment time point: Baseline, completion of the supervised Tai Chi program at 8 weeks, 3 months into the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program, completion of the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program at 6 months. The SenseWear Armband is only to be removed for showering or if skin irritation occurs.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy (Patient Activation Measure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, completion of the supervised Tai Chi program at 8 weeks, 3 months into the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program, completion of the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with supervised and unsupervised Tai Chi training</outcome>
      <timepoint>Attendance during the eight-week supervised Tai Chi program, self-reported practice in a training diary during the eight-week supervised Tai Chi program, self-reported practice in a training diary during the six-month home-based Tai Chi maintenance program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction with the Tai Chi training program (study-specific questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of the home-based unsupervised maintenance Tai Chi program at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function (spirometry)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, completion of the supervised Tai Chi program at 8 weeks, 3 months into the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program, completion of the home-based Tai Chi maintenance program at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Medical diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) / forced vital capacity ratio of &lt; 0.7; FEV1 between 20% to 80% of predicted normal)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Acute exacerbation of COPD in the last month; musculoskeletal, cardiovascular or neurological conditions likely to adversely affect performance during assessments or training; participation in any supervised exercise training within the last 12 months; limited English language skills which might hinder their understanding of the Tai Chi instructions; requirement for supplemental oxygen during testing or training procedures.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The effects of the eight-week supervised Tai Chi training program will be determined by calculating the mean differences within the group for all outcomes from baseline to the eight-week time point using a paired t-test.  Uncertainty about the size of the mean differences within groups will be quantified with 95% confidence intervals. The effects of the six-month home-based unsupervised maintenance Tai Chi training program will be determined by calculating the mean differences within the group for all outcomes from the eight-week time point to the three- and six-month time points respectively using a paired t-test to identify whether any improvements have been sustained. The three- and six-month time points will also be compared to baseline using a paired t-test to determine if the combination of the supervised and unsupervised Tai Chi program resulted in improvements being better than baseline for all outcome measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Mona Vale Hospital - Mona Vale</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>2103 - Mona Vale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study aims to investigate the effects of a maintenance Tai Chi intervention on exercise capacity and quality of life in people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). This will be a prospective cohort study where people with COPD will be recruited from two sites in Sydney, Concord Repatriation General Hospital and Mona Vale Community Health Centre. All participants will be asked to undertake an eight-week, twice weekly, supervised Tai Chi exercise program using Sun- style Tai Chi at one of the sites. On completion of the supervised program, participants will then be asked to continue with a home-based, unsupervised maintenance Tai Chi exercise program five times weekly for a six-month period. Outcomes will be measured at baseline, at eight weeks following the supervised Tai Chi program and again at three and six months into the maintenance Tai Chi program.  Outcomes will include exercise capacity, quality of life, physical activity, balance, participants attitudes to management of their health care, compliance with short and long-term Tai Chi training, and satisfaction with the maintenance Tai Chi training.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee – Concord Repatriation General Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Concord Research Office
Ground Floor  Building 20
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Road
CONCORD NSW 2139
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/CRGH/18</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371273-HREC16CRGH18_Study_protocol.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371273-HREC16CRGH18_Participant_information_sheet.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zoe  McKeough</name>
      <address>Rm 0203, O Block
Cumberland Campus C42
75 East St
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe NSW Australia 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9269</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9278</fax>
      <email>zoe.mckeough@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zoe McKeough</name>
      <address>Rm 0203, O Block
Cumberland Campus C42
75 East St
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe NSW Australia 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9269</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9278</fax>
      <email>zoe.mckeough@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zoe McKeough</name>
      <address>Rm 0203, O Block
Cumberland Campus C42
75 East St
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe NSW Australia 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9269</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9278</fax>
      <email>zoe.mckeough@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zoe McKeough</name>
      <address>Rm 0203, O Block
Cumberland Campus C42
75 East St
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe NSW Australia 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9269</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9278</fax>
      <email>zoe.mckeough@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>