<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320900">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000283077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to evaluate whether increased codeine levels are seen when both codeine and ketamine are given in small doses to well volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Mechanistic basis for the use of ketamine as an adjuvant to opioid analgesia  a pharmacokinetic drug-drug interaction study to define any clinically relevant drug to drug interaction between codeine and ketamine in healthy volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The possibility that  ketamine,an anaesthetic medication but which is also  used at much lower doses, to help try and control severe chronic nerve pain, may  increase the effective blood levels of opioids such as codeine or morphine that are often given in conjunction with ketamine.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>This study is looking at drug metabolism not pain management or anaesthesiology</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study exposure is for 4 days and commences with a comprehensive medical assessment to identify that the participants  meet the eligibility criteria.Participants will take in total 9 doses of 30mg of codeine orally every 8 hours. The first 5 doses will be taken at home, ie days 1 and 2 of the study. On day 3 the participants will continue to take the codeine 30mg every 8 hours orally but will be monitored in hospital from 08.00 to 16.00. 11 samples of blood will be taken at predetermined times throughout the day and at the same time vital signs, pulse, respirations and blood pressure, will be measured by a registered nurse. On day 4 the participant will again be monitored in hospital from 08.00 hours to 16.00 hours. The final dose of codeine 30mg orally will be given at 08.00 hours and at the same time ketamine 0.5mg per kg of body weight up to a maximum of  40mg will be given intravenously  over 5 minutes. Again 11 blood samples will be taken at predetermined times throughout the day, and vital signs , pulse, respirations and blood pressure will be measured at the same time. An intravenous cannual, a small plastic tube, will be inserted  into a vein in the arm on both days 3 and 4 which will be used to collect the 11 blood samples on each day, thus eliminating the need to insert a needle into the vein each time a blood sample is required. 
On both days 3 and 4, whilst in hospital, all urine passed by the participants will be collected.</interventions>
    <comparator>no treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To define any clinically relevant drug to drug interaction between codeine and ketamine in healthy volunteers. This will be measured by taking in total 22 blood sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 08.00. 08.30, 09.00, 09.30, 10.00, 11.00, 12.00, 13.00,14.00,15.00 and 16.00 on days 3 and 4 of the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This study will allow the relationship between opioid metabolism in the 
 presence of ketamine to be delineated in a way that can inform 
 clinical practice if the phase III study is positive.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The samples of blood and urine collected will be analysed in the laboratory over the next few months and results should be available within 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Given that morphine and codeine are metabolised through the same pathways, this study will also inform practice with morphine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The samples of blood and urine collected will be analysed in the laboratory over the next few months and results should be available within 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Given the almost universal prescribing of ketamine in the presence of an opioid, this study will have wide implications for practice internationally in acute pain including post-operative analgesia, chronic pain and palliative care</outcome>
      <timepoint>The samples of blood and urine collected will be analysed in the laboratory over the next few months and results should be available within 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participant is capable of completing all participant assessments and complying with the study procedures, is able to give fully informed written consent, Normal performance status = Australian-modified Karnofsky performance stauts of 100.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any history of drug or alcohol abuse, any known allergy to either of the study medications,alcohol consumption during the trial period, on any regular or as needed medications including opioids and Non Steroidal Anti Inflammatory Drugs(NSAIDs),anaemia, renal dysfunction with creatinine clearance calculated as less than 25 ml/minute. Hepatic impairment defined as 2 times upper limit of mormal for 2 or more hepatic enzymes, International normalized ratio (INR &gt;1.2 ) not treated with warfarin, documented respiratory failure induced by any opiate medication,recent seizures or history of uncontrolled epilepsy, medically assessed history of uncontrolled hypertension, cardiac arrhythmias, cardiac failure, ischaemic heart disease or history of cerebral vascular accident, cerebral trauma, intracerebral mass or previous intracerebral haemorrhage, currently taking monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) or who have been taking non-reversible monoamine oxidase inhibitors within 4 weeks prior to study entry or reversible MAOIs within 5 days of study entry, history of increased intraocular pressure (e.g. glaucoma), schizophrenia, acute psychosis,  acute intermittent porphyria, uncontrolled hyperthyroidism,women pregnant or lactating and if  at risk of pregnancy must have appropriate and effective contraception in place.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/11/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/12/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/01/2010</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/01/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders University- Department of Clinical Pharmacology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Foundation Daw Park</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Daws Road 
Daw Park
South Australia 5041</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Flinders University Department of Palliative Support Services.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>700 Goodwood Road 
Daw Park SA 5041</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pain from damaged nerves is a common problem particularly in the aged and those with medical problems including diabetes, vascular disease and cancer.A medication called ketamine which is used for anaesthetics is, at much lower doses, also used to help try and control severe chronic nerve pain. In an experiment that has been carried out at Flinders University in the laboratory, it appears that ketamine may increase the effective blood levels of opioid pain killers such as codeine or morphine that are often given in conjunction with ketamine. This study will evaluate whether increased codeine levels are seen when both codeine and ketamine are administered in small doses to well volunteers.Ketamine is already being evaluated in a clinical study by a team led by Flinders University at eight sites across Australia for severe nerve-based pain. This study will be a definitive study on the place of ketamine in the control of chronic, complex pain and should be finished in mid-2010.This study will have huge importance if ketamine is shown to be of clinical benefit. To date, it may well be that the perceived clinical benefit is only because of its effect on increasing the blood levels of strong pain killers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 
SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/09/0324</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor John Miners</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 8204 4131</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5114</fax>
      <email>john.miners@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Aine Greene</name>
      <address>Southern Adelaide Paliative Services 
700 Goodwood Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1057</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1201</fax>
      <email>aine.greene@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Ms Aine Greene</name>
      <address>Southern Adelaide Paliative Services 
700 Goodwood Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 2865</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1201</fax>
      <email>Aine.Greene@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Miners</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology Flinders Medical Centre Flinders Drive Bedford Park SA 5042  </address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 8204 4131  </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5114  </fax>
      <email>john.miners@flinders.edu.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>