<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336458">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000101987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Long Arm Casting Versus Splinting After Manipulation of Distal Third Radius Fractures in Children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pediatric Distal Third Radius Fractures Treated with Long Arm Casting Versus Sugar Tong Splinting : A Comparison of Re-reduction Rates</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Auckland District Health Board - ADHB5006</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Distal Radius Fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Sugar Tong Splint.  A sugar tong splint is made of paris of plaster and goes along the posterior aspect of the elbow and extends along the front and back of the forearm and wrist.  The sides of the forearm and wrist are left free to allow for swelling.  The splint is wrapped with an elastic bandage and immobilizes the elbow, forearm, and wrist.  This will be administered by the on call registrar in the emergency department at the time of the initial consultation.  

The elastic bandage about the sugar tong splint  will be tightened at week 1 if the splint has loosened.  The splint will then be changed to an above elbow cast at the 2 week visit assuming no loss of reduction.    This cast will be placed by the clinic nurses in fracture clinic.   The cast will be maintained for 3-4 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Above Elbow Casting.  An above elbow plaster of paris cast will be placed by the on call orthopaedic registrar in the emergency department at the time of the initial consultation.  This plaster goes around the entire arm from the upper arm through the hand to provide rigid, circumferential  immobilization of the affected arm.  The cast will be left on for a total of 5-6 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Remanipulation rates.  X-rays of the fractured wrist will be taken at 1,2, and 6 weeks after initial manipulation and immobilization.  These x-rays will be evaluated by the primary investigator.  If there is angulation of &gt;20 degrees on either the AP or lateral x-ray of the wrist, the patient will need to undergo remanipulation of the wrist under general anesthesia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, and 6 weeks after initial manipulation and immobilization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cast Complications.  Patients and parents will be given a questionnaire form at the 6 week visit asking if they 1) ever had their cast split during the treatment period due to the cast being too tight and 2) needed the cast to be replaced or overwrapped due to the cast loosening or breaking.  In addition, patients and parents will be asked the same questions during their 1, 2, and 6 week visits by the orthopaedic registrar/fellow that evaluates them in clinic.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1,2, and 6 weeks after initial manipulation and immobilization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pediatric patients age 3-14 years old that 1) are diagnosed with distal third radius fractures with or without associated ulna frctures, 2) require closed reduction of the fracture, 3) are treated with closed reduction at Starship Childrens Hospital,  and 4) informed consent is obtained.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Open fractures, 2) fractures manipulated outside of Starship Childrens Hospital, 3) nondisplaced fractures or those fractures not requiring reduction, and 4) any irreducible fracture requiring open reduction and/or internal fixation or percutaneous wiring.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants in the study will be identified in the emergency department by the orthopaedic registrar on call.  Patients qualifying for the study will be given information sheets regarding the study by the emergency department nurses and the orthopaedic on call registrar will discuss the study with the patients and parents.  If a patient decides to participate in the study, they will be treated with manipulation and either casting or splinting.  

Prior to starting the study, a computer generated randomized sequence of interventions (cast or splint) will be performed.  Based on this randomized sequence, patients will then be treated with either a splint or a cast as they are enrolled into the study. 100 sealed opaque envelopes will be marked 1-100 and a piece of paper stating either “cast” or “splint” will be placed inside each envelope as determined by the randomized sequence.  These envelopes will be made by an independent person not involved in the study so that the order is not known to any of the treating physicians.  The on call registrars enrolling patients will not know the method of treatment until patients have agreed to participate in the study and the envelope has been opened.</concealment>
    <sequence>Prior to starting the study, a computer generated randomized sequence of interventions (cast or splint) will be performed.  Based on this randomized sequence, patients will then be treated with either a splint or a cast as they are enrolled into the study. 100 sealed envelopes will be marked 1-100 and a piece of paper stating either “cast” or “splint” will be placed inside each envelope as determined by the randomized sequence.  These envelopes will be made by an independent person not involved in the study so that the order is not known to any of the treating physicians.  The on call registrars enrolling patients will not know the method of treatment until patients have agreed to participate in the study and the envelope has been opened.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Starship Childrens Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Pediatric Orthopaedics
2 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland, New Zealand
1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Starship Childrens Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Pediatric Orthopaedics
2 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland, New Zealand
1023</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current standard of treatment following closed reduction of pediatric distal third radius fractures involves the placement of a well molded cast to maintain reduction.  Casts provide rigid, circumferential immobilization.  Because of the fixed diameter of the cast, there is minimal ability for the cast to accomodate fluctuations in soft tissue swelling that occurs after an acute injury.  In the acute phase, casts can cause compression of neurovascular structures if wrapped too tightly.  As the swelling resolves, the cast loses its ability to maintain fracture reduction due to a loss of contact between the cast material and the extremity.  Studies have shown up to a 35% re-reduction rate in pediatric distal third radius fractures after manipulation and casting.

This study is designed to investigate if the application of a sugar tong splint with an elastic bandage immediately following closed reduction will lead to a decrease in the rereduction rate.  A sugar tong splint with an elastic bandage is capable of accomodating changes in soft tissue swelling and should provide enough stability to maintain fracture reduction.  The hypothesis is that the sugar tong splint will lead to a reduction in remanipulation rates.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/10/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kenneth Huh</name>
      <address>Department of Pediatric Orthopaedics
2 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland, New Zealand
1023</address>
      <phone>022 658 4355</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k_huh@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kenneth Huh</name>
      <address>Department of Pediatric Orthopaedics
2 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland, New Zealand
1023</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)22 658 4355</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k_huh@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kenneth Huh</name>
      <address>Department of Pediatric Orthopaedics
2 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland, New Zealand
1023</address>
      <phone>022 658 4355</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k_huh@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>