<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83862">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000295246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigation of Genetic Predictors of the Response to Selective Serotonin Re-Uptake Inhibitors Treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigation of Genetic Predictors of the Response to Selective Serotonin Re-Uptake Inhibitors (SSRI) Treatment in individuals suffering from major depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Antidepressant</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Treatment prediction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>escitalopram in doses 10-20mg per day, during 12 weeks, oral administration</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Montgomery-Asberg's Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) (remission score &lt; 12)
The genotypic frequencies of serotonin transporter gene were compared between remitters and non-remitters to escitalopram medication.  Additionally, the mean change on the MADRS scale was compared between serotonin transporter genotypes at week 12 of escitalopram medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome was measured at the following time points: week 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HRSD) (remission score &lt; 8)
The genotypic frequencies of serotonin transporter gene were compared between remitters and non-remitters to escitalopram medication.  Additionally, the mean change on the HRDS scale was compared between serotonin transporter genotypes at week 12 of escitalopram medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary outcome was measured at the following time points: week 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Both genders 
Major Depression diagnosis according to Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV) criteria 
At severity of depression of at least moderate as indicated by a Montgomery-Asberg's Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score of 22 or higher 
Only secondary current comorbid anxiety disorder</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Bipolar disorder 
Psychotic disorder or features 
Current eating disorders 
Mental retardation 
Any pervasive developmental disorder or cognitive disorder 
Alcohol or drug abuse-related disorders within 12 months prior to baseline 
Acute infections, neurological or any other unstable general disorders, serious suicide risk, formal behaviour therapy, or systematic psychotherapy, pregnancy or breastfeeding 
A history of hypersensitivity or non-response to escitalopram</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>135</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Estonia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tartu University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Raja 31, 50417, Tartu</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Estonia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tartu University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Raja 31, 50417, Tartu</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Estonia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The antidepressant medications are among the most commonly prescribed pharmacological agents in patients with mood and anxiety disorder. Despite recent advances in antidepressant pharmacotherapy, there is a pressing need for substantial optimization and improvment of outcome of pharmacotherapy of psychiatric disorders by providing individualized and science-based treatment guidelines. Besides it is rather difficult in clinical practice to predict, which patient will response to a certain pharmacological treatment well and which one less so. Putative predictors of response to antidepressant include demographic and clinical characteristics, personality traits, biological markers and psychophysiological features. Recently the research studies shown that divergences in antidepressant efficacy may be related to genetic variations of patients. The pharmacogenetic studies have multiplied in recent decade due to the impact that such studies may have in everyday clinical practice once reliable predictors could be identified. The pharmacogenetic research using new deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) microarray-based technology can reasonably be expected to contribute to the prediction of likelihood of treatment response and risk of development of adverse side effects in individual patients in case of antidepressant treatment. By reducing costly treatment failures and the likelihood of serious adverse events, pharmacogenetic testing may help to improve the treatment possibilities for chronic diseases, reduce the burden prescription drug costs, and lower the costs of drug development. The further detailed investigation of peripheral gene expression profiles may help to identify responsible genes that underlie the process of development of affective disorders and open novel horizons for understanding molecular mechanisms of psychopharmacological treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Maron E, Tammiste A, Kallassalu K, Eller T, Vasar V, Nutt DJ, Metspalu A.
Serotonin transporter promoter region polymorphisms do not influence treatment
response to escitalopram in patients with major depression. Eur
Neuropsychopharmacol. 2009 Mar 7. [Epub ahead of print] PubMed PMID: 19272758.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Board Name: Estonian State Agency of Medicines</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Nooruse 1, 50411, Tartu</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007-002649-19</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Estonia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eduard Maron</name>
      <address>Raja 31, 50417, Tartu</address>
      <phone>+3727318812</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eduard.maron@kliinikum.ee</email>
      <country>Estonia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eduard Maron</name>
      <address>Raja 31, 50417, Tartu</address>
      <phone>+3727318812</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eduard.maron@kliinikum.ee</email>
      <country>Estonia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>