<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363883">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000331730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A placebo-controlled, randomized, double-blind trial of the effects of modified release 4-aminopyridine on upper limb impairment in Multiple Sclerosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A placebo-controlled, randomized, double-blind trial of the effects of modified release 4-aminopyridine (fampridine) on upper limb impairment in Multiple Sclerosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1140-7612</utrn>
    <trialacronym>FULS (Fampridine Upper Limb Study)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Modified release oral 4-aminopyridine (fampridine) 10mg twice daily for eight weeks.  Adherence will be monitored by drug tablet return.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (glucose pill), oral administration, twice daily for eight weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Upper limb function using time to complete 9-hole peg test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2, 4, 8 weeks and 1 month after completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central motor conduction time measured using transcranial magnetic motor evoked potentials</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 weeks and 1 month after completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cortical excitability measured using transcranial magnetic stimulation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 weeks and 1 month after completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pattern-shift visual evoked potential latency of the p100 (measured using Synergy electromyography machine)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8 weeks and 1 month after completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Upper extremity muscle strength measured using neurological examination (MRC scale of muscle power) and grip strength measured using a hand-held dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2, 4 and 8 weeks and 1 month after completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensory discrimination capacity using standard indices of texture discrimination (Fabric Matching Test), limb position sense (Wrist Position Sense Test) and tactile object recognition (functional Tactile Object Recognition Test).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2, 4 and 8 weeks and 1 month after completion of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Multiple sclerosis; impaired upper limb function (NB this applies to the group of 40 patients; there will also be 20 healthy controls who are being included primarily for validation of electrophysiological measurements as there are no published normal values for these parameters.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age &lt; 18 years; history of seizures or epilepsy; hypersensitivity to fampridine; moderate/severe renal impairment; pregnancy; current or recent (60 days) MS relapse; alternative likely cause for upper limb impairment (e.g. peripheral neuropathy, injury); current or recent (60 days) therapy with corticosteroids; current therapy with benzodiazepines; recent (within 60 days) addition of new therapy for multiple sclerosis including disease-modifying therapies and symptomatic therapies. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The electrophysiological studies and clinical assessments will be assessed using repeated measures ANOVA. Correlations between changes in electrophysiology parameters and performance on the 9-hole peg test will be examined using Pearson correlation coefficients. One-way ANOVA will be used to compare the measures at baseline between fampridine responders and non-responders. This will be repeated after medication. Post hoc analysis with pairwise paired t test and Bonferroni correction will be used to compare all significant interactions.

Regarding sample size calculation: As an index of possible effect size, Goodman et al studied the response of lower limb function measured by timed 25 foot walk in patients with MS treated with Fampridine. If we assume the same effect size, to achieve a power of 80% with a significance level (alpha) of 0.05, we calculate that 38 patients in each group (fampridine, placebo) would be needed to statistically identify differences in upper limb function between the groups.  However, given that there may well be differences in response based on measures of upper limb and lower limb function, a more relevant approach might be to base the calculation on the data of Erasmus et al, who assessed performance of the 9 hole peg test in patients with MS and controls. Using their figures, in order to reliably show a 40% improvement using a power of 80% and alpha 0.5, 16 patients are sufficient in drug- and placebo-treated groups. Taking into account an assumed attrition rate of 10% of the participants through the period of the study, these two approaches to sample size calculation and the feasibility of conducting a single centre study, we believe a sample size of 20 in each group, treated and placebo will provide statistically valid findings.  20 control participants are also being recruited to make a sample size total of 60.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
VIC 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Biogen Idec</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 1
Level 5
123 Epping Road,
North Ryde 
NSW
2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study involves a new drug, Fampyra (modified release 4-aminopyridine) which has recently become available for the treatment of walking disability in MS.  It is not yet known whether the drug could also be helpful in treating other symptoms of MS such as upper limb dysfunction or visual problems.  In addition, it is not known how Fampyra works and why it seems to work better in some people than others.  This study seeks to answer some of these questions by testing the effects of the drug on upper limb impairment and using a selection of clinical and electrical tests of nerve function.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard MacDonell</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.macdonell@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marion Simpson</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marion.simpson@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marion Simpson</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marion.simpson@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marion Simpson</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
VIC 3084</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>