<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368188">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000285550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An evaluation of two contact lenses in experienced lens wearers to determine differences in lens comfort and lens clinical performance when lenses are each worn for two weeks</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, bilateral, randomised, double-masked, cross-over clinical trial to compare the clinical performance of formofilcon B silicone hydrogel daily disposable lenses against somofilcon A silicone hydrogel daily disposable lenses when worn for 2 weeks on a daily wear basis by experienced lens wearers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Subjective comfort of contact lenses</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ocular surface response to contact lenses </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This trial will be a prospective, bilateral, randomised, double-masked, cross-over masked clinical trial. Participants will wear two lens typfor two weeks on a single-use, daily wear basis with a minimum two day wash-out between lens types. The lens types are formofilcon B and somofilcon A. Both lens types are classified as silicone-hydrogel material with water contents of 48% and 56% respectively. Lenses will be power-matched for each participant. Minimum wearing time will be 5 days/week and 6 hours/day. There is no maximum wearing time provided lenses are not slept in overnight. There will five visits: Baseline, Stage 1: lens fit, Stage 1: 2-week visit, Stage 2: lens fit, Stage 2: 2-week visit. These visits will involve assessment of visual acuity, assessment of ocular comfort using questionnaires employing a 1-10 numeric rating scale and ocular response by examination with a slit-lamp biomicroscope (a specialised microscope for viewing the eye). All contact lenses will be prescribed and all assessments will be carried out by an optometrist. Participants will be instructed to return all used lens packets and any unused contact lenses.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control (somofilcon A) - cross over study</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular comfort while wearing contact lenses, assessed by questionnaire specifically designed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Stage 1: Fitting, Stage 1: 2-week visit, Stage 2: Fitting, Stage 2: 2-week visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular dryness while wearing contact lenses, assessed by questionnaire specifically designed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Stage 1: Fitting, Stage 1: 2-week visit, Stage 2: Fitting, Stage 2: 2-week visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective vision while wearing contact lenses, assessed by questionnaire specifically designed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Stage 1: Fitting, Stage 1: 2-week visit, Stage 2: Fitting, Stage 2: 2-week visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Corneal staining while wearing contact lenses, assessed with slit-lamp biomicroscopy and graded using the Brien Holden Vision Institute grading scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Stage 1: Fitting, Stage 1: 2-week visit, Stage 2: Fitting, Stage 2: 2-week visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bulbar hyperaemia while wearing contact lenses, assessed with slit-lamp biomicroscopy and graded using the Brien Holden Vision Institute grading scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Stage 1: Fitting, Stage 1: 2-week visit, Stage 2: Fitting, Stage 2: 2-week visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Limbal hyperaemia while wearing contact lenses, assessed with slit-lamp biomicroscopy and graded using the Brien Holden Vision Institute grading scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Stage 1: Fitting, Stage 1: 2-week visit, Stage 2: Fitting, Stage 2: 2-week visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
Be at least 18 years old, male or female.
Be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses.
Be correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses.
Be an experienced lens wearer.
Be able to insert and remove contact lenses
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus.  Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment. However, such ocular medications can be prescribed as per standard optometric care during the clinical trial.
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings / are known to affect a participants ocular health / physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial. 
NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial product is used.
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
Previous corneal refractive surgery.
Contraindications to contact lens wear.
Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products.
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.
Pregnancy: (Formal testing of pregnancy is not required. A participants verbal report is sufficient).

The Investigator may, at his/her discretion, exclude anyone who they believe may not be able to fulfil the clinical trial requirements or it is believed to be in the participants best interests.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who satisfy the inclusion/exclusion criteria are enrolled in the trial. A participant is considered “successfully enrolled” when the Investigator agrees that they conform to the inclusion / exclusion criteria, and on successful fit of clinical trial products. 
The order in which lenses are worn will be randomised.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation plan will be generated from http://www.randomization.com/. The website’s second random generator will be used to create a block random permutation of the two lens types within each participant. The generated randomisation list will be copied from the website by the biostatistician and applied through the Clinic Data Management system.
The randomisation code for solution will be applied (and broken if required) by a Clinical Coordinator (CC), and clearly documented. The Investigator will not have access to this randomisation code until the trial is completed and final data analysis performed.
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>13/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>13/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>28</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Institute </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker
Street University of New South Wales, NSW
2052 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker
Street University of New South Wales, NSW
2052 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pegavision</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>No.5, Shing Yeh St., Kwei Shan Hsiang, Taoyuan Hsien 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial will compare the clinical performance of somofilcon A and formofilcon B contact lenses worn for two weeks.
The hypothesis is the subjective responses with test lenses are not different to the control contact lenses.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road
Eastwood 
South Australia 5063
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Clinical Research and Trials Centre (CRTC)
Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, NSW 2052 </address>
      <phone>+612 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Clinical Research and Trials Centre (CRTC)
Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, NSW 2052 </address>
      <phone>+612 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Clinical Research and Trials Centre (CRTC)
Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, NSW 2052 </address>
      <phone>+612 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Clinical Research and Trials Centre (CRTC)
Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, NSW 2052 </address>
      <phone>+612 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>