<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371561">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001521415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Online-interventions against depression for adults. Does the ordering of treatment components matter for symptom improvements?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does ordering matter? The effect of counterbalancing behavioral activation and cognitive restructuring in a guided self-help online-intervention for depressed individuals.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Guided online-intervention. 

Duration and general information:

The intervention lasts 6 weeks. Participants need to invest approximately 90 minutes per week/module. The modules are completed over multiple (two to seven) shorter sessions per week, depending on the task at hand and on participant's preferences. Every week a different topic relevant to depression is presented and the participants are instructed to perform cognitive-behavioral tasks in order to reduce their symptom severity. All treatment content (psychoeducational content as well as specific treatment tools) is delivered online. Participants gain individualized password-protected access to an online-platform.

Participants receive weekly written feedback via e(lectronic)-mail from a trained psychologist (personally assigned; psychologist with at least finished itermediate examination of their psycho-therapeutic training). Psychologists comment on participants' letters/activities/tool usage and to provide further instructions as well as emotional support. Psychologists are provided with standardized text blocks, which are completed by individualized feedback lines. 

Participants are able to contact a psychologist at any time if they need to via e-mail on the website (additional contact on demand). They receive an answer within two working days.

Adherence: Login of participants is monitored. Inactive participants will automatically receive login-reminders via e-mail after 3, 7, 14 and 20 days of inactivity to increase adherence. 

Participants are guided by a team of psychologist trained in the use of online-interventions. 
The treatment-specific training of psychologists takes 3 days (8 hours each) and gives theoretical background regarding online-interventions for depression and concrete instructions on how to use the platform and to interact with participants. Additional information on how to react in critical situations (e.g. suicidal participants online) is provided. An intervention manual is provided to ensure the psychologists adherence to the treatment. Meetings for supervision-purposes are scheduled monthly. Both an researching psychologist on the area of online interventions and a licensed psychotherapist provide the training as well as the supervision. 

Contents, aims and methods of the intervention in detail:
The RCT contains two treatment arms (Arm 1: BAF - Behavioral Activation First; Arm 2: Cognitive Restructuring First - CRF) . Both arms contain the same treatment modules, e.g. the same psychoeducational content as well as the same treatment techniques. Both treatment arms differ in the ordering of behavioral activation and cognitive restructuring techniques (see control condition). 

Arm 1: BAF  ordering of provided treatment modules:

Insight in depressive symptoms (Week 1)
Topic: Symptoms of depression 
Aim: Insight into own symptoms.
Method: Expressive writing

Behavioral activation I (Week 2)
Topic: Positive activation
Aim: Insight into own behavior related to depressive symptoms, increasing own level of activity.
Method: Calendar of daily activities, diary of positive daily events

Behavioral activation II (Week 3)
Topic: Lack of motivation, difficulties to perform positive activities.
Aim: Coping with difficulties, increasing own level of activity.
Method: Written coping plans in the calendar of daily activities

Cognitive Restructuring I (Week 4)
Topic: Thought processes that worsen depressive symptoms.
Aim: Insight into own thoughts related to depression; cognitive restructuring.
Method: Cognitive bias modification training

Cognitive Restructuring II  (Week 5)
Topic: Distorted perceptions that worsen depressive symptoms.
Aim: Insight into own perceptions related to depression; cognitive restructuring
Method: Cognitive bias modification training and thought protocols

Relapse prevention (week 6)
Topic: "Alarm signals" that indicate relapse 
Aim: Developing strategies to prevent relapse, summing up own participation in program. 
Method: Expressive writing

</interventions>
    <comparator>Duration, contents, methods, adherence monitoring, contact possibilities and training of  described above and identical over conditions. Participants work for 6 weeks online and are provided with the same psychoeducational contents and are given the same tasks, but the ordering of behavioral activation techniques and cognitive restructuring is changed: 


Arm 2: CRF  ordering of provided treatment modules:

Insight in depressive symptoms (Week 1)
Cognitive Restructuring I (Week 2)
Cognitive Restructuring II  (Week 3)
Behavioral activation I (Week 4)
Behavioral activation II (Week 5)
Relapse prevention (Week 6)
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression: mean Beck Depression Inventory-II score (BDI-II)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression: mean Patient Health Questionnaire-9 score (PHQ-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
Within treatment (immediatly before starting week 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety: mean Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7 item scale score (GAD-7)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Bias: mean Cognitive Styles Assessment score (COSTA-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Within treatment (immediatly before starting week 2 and 4)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-Efficacy: mean General Perceived Self-Efficacy Scale score (GPSE)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Support: mean Berlin Social Support Scale score (BSSS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participation: mean Index zur Messung von Einschränkungen der Teilhabe [Index of barriers of participation] score (IMET)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Well-Being: mean WHO-5 score </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Well-Being: mean EUROHIS_QOL score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Theapy evaluation: mean Questionnaire on Therapy Expectation and Evaluation (PATHEV) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Stress: mean Patient Health Questionnaire stress module (PHQ-S) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)
3-months followup
6-months followup
12-months followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Illness-Perception: mean Illness Perceptions Questionnaire-Revised (IPQ-R) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapy Expectations: 3 items from the EUHEALS questionnaire
(expectation of efficacy, perceived usefullnes of approach, recommend to a friend)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Values: mean Perceived Values Questionnaire (PVQ) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-Treatment (immediately before start of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change Mechanisms: mean Scale for the Multiperspective Assessment of General Change Mechanisms in Psychotherapy (SACiP) subscale scores (mastery, resource avtivation, emotional bond, problem actuation, clarification of meaning, agreement on collaboration)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within treatment (immediatly before starting week 2 and 4)
Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>adverse events during treatment and effect on well-beeing, 7 items 
* general occurance of adverse events
* open question: description of adverse event
*  time-point of occurance
*  relation between adverse event and specific treatment techniques
* influece on well being at time-point of occurance
* current influence on well-being
* reporting of adverse event to coach
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Treatment (immediately after completion of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>German-speaking adults suffering from depression with access to the internet</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Schizophrenia, schizotypal and delusional disorders (F20-F29)
Sucidal participants
Severely depressed participants
Patients in concurrent psychotherapeutic treatment </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central radomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer software using a random number generator. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants of both treatment arms receive the same treatment modules, however, the ordering of behavioral activation and cognitive restructuring differs between both treatment arms  [Arm 1: Expressive Writing  behavioral activation  cognitive restructuring  expressive writing; Arm 2: Expressive Writing  cognitive restructuring  behavioral activation  expressive writing]</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>4000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>all federal states</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Freie Universitaet Berlin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Freie Universitaet Berlin
AB Klinisch-Psychologische Intervention
Habelschwerdter Allee 45
14195 Berlin </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Germany</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Techniker Krankenkasse (public health care provider)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bramfelder Str. 140
22305 Hamburg</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Germany</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Christine Knaevelsrud</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Freie Universitaet Berlin
AB Klinisch-Psychologische Intervention
Habelschwerdter Allee 45
14195 Berlin </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Germany</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background:
Psychological treatments via the internet have proven effective in reducing depressive symptom complaints. A first evlaluation of the provided treatment programm yielded large pre-post-effects on depression, anxiety, perseverative thinking, and well-being. However, little is known about the influence of temporal ordering of provided treatment modules on symptom improvements, patterns of change, treatment adherence and if different groups of individuals are affected differently. Therefore, systematic evaluations of temporal ordering effects are necessary to gain deeper insight into which treatment components are the most critical ingredients for successful online interventions for depression. 

Intervention: 
Depressed participants are allocated at random to a two-armed cognitive-behavioral online-intervention with regular weekly contact to a psychologist (guided intervention). The two treatment arms differ in the ordering of provided treatment modules [Arm 1: Expressive Writing  behavioral activation  cognitive restructuring  expressive writing; Arm 2: Expressive Writing  cognitive restructuring  behavioral activation  expressive writing].  Both treatment arms receive the same psychoeducational information about their symptoms and treatment modules to reduce depressive complaints (e.g. positive activation, cognitive restructuring, emotional insight). Engaging tools on the website help participants with the completion of these tasks. 

Method:
Both groups are compared with regard to therapeutic outcomes (e.g. depressive symptoms),  the influence of the ordering of provided treatment modules on symptom change and adherence, as well as predictors of treatment-success.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethikkommission der Freien Universitaet Berlin</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Prof. Dr. Annette Kinder
Vorsitzende der Ethikkommission
der Freien Universitaet Berlin
Habelschwerdter Allee 45
14195 Berlin</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>125 /2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371561-125_Beschlussmitteilung.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Knaevelsrud</name>
      <address>Freie Universitaet Berlin
AB Klinisch-Psychologische Intervention
Habelschwerdter Allee 45
14195 Berlin</address>
      <phone>+49 - (0)30 838 - 55736</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.knaevelsrud@fu-berlin.de</email>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Knaevelsrud</name>
      <address>Freie Universitaet Berlin
AB Klinisch-Psychologische Intervention
Habelschwerdter Allee 45
14195 Berlin</address>
      <phone>+49 - (0)30 838 - 55736</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.knaevelsrud@fu-berlin.de</email>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Knaevelsrud</name>
      <address>Freie Universitaet Berlin
AB Klinisch-Psychologische Intervention
Habelschwerdter Allee 45
14195 Berlin</address>
      <phone>+49 - (0)30 838 - 55736</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.knaevelsrud@fu-berlin.de</email>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Pavle Zagorscak</name>
      <address>Freie Universitaet Berlin
AB Klinisch-psychologische Intervention
Habelschwerdter Allee 45
14195 Berlin </address>
      <phone> +49 - (0) 30 - 83860358 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.zagorscak@fu-berlin.de</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>