<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372590">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000488303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>GotRhythm: A tailored music therapy and real-time biofeedback mobile phone app to promote rehabilitation following stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A tailored music therapy and real-time biofeedback mobile phone app (GotRhythm) to promote rehabilitation following stroke</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>none</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: a novel mobile software application GotRhythm  uses mobiles and wireless wearable sensors to deliver music-motor therapy to patients with real-time feedback of movement data to the patient via the application to enhance motivation and compliance. It incorporates individualised music, wearable sensors and biofeedback to deliver a simple and inexpensive rhythmic auditory stimulation (RAS) motor training protocol to patients. As a person completes training tasks, GotRhythm collects data relating to motion and movement accuracy and provides information on motor performance (via the application) that can be correlated with any physiological response elicited by the app. GotRhythm is capable of supporting a wide array of sensors to support a variety of physical modalities including both upper and lower limb tracking as well as gross and fine motor skills. 

Location of intervention: The training will take place under supervision at Bentley Hospital outpatients clinic. GotRhythm training will be tailored to the participants specific injury in consultation with the clinicians at the hospital. Training will be in addition to the usual stroke rehabilitation programme recommended by their clinician throughout the study period. Usual stroke rehabilitation does not include rhythmic auditory stimulation (RAS) and these patients will not receive any GotRhythm training. 

The procedures, mode of delivery, materials and who does the intervention: A series of participant-specific movement tasks focusing on different body parts will be created to match the rehabilitation goals of each patient. Movements such as grasping, knee, elbow and wrist flexion and extension, as well as walking, can all be accommodated within the GotRhythm system. Patients will wear non-intrusive sensors on the relevant body part that link wirelessly to the app. An allied health professional in the rehabilitation clinic will control the GotRhythm training by assigning a suitable rhythm (beats per minute) for each participant, using songs chosen by the participant. Beat speed will be adjusted to suit each patients abilities during a session and also progressively over the 6-week intervention period.

Frequency of intervention and assessments/data collected: Participants in the intervention group will receive 6-weeks of intervention consisting of a supervised, 20minute music entrainment session conducted three (3) times each week for six (6) weeks. There will be 2 blocks of therapy:
1. Therapy block 1 - 3 x 20mins/wk x 3 weeks = total of 9 sessions
2. Therapy block 2 - 3 x 20mins/wk x 3 weeks = total of 9 sessions
Participants will therefore receive a total of 18 sessions (= 360mins of therapy in total).  Each session is identical, and there are no differences between the sessions in Therapy Blocks 1 &amp; 2.
It is likely these sessions will be conducted on Monday/Wednesday/Friday of each week. Block 2 will follow straight on from Block 1 (following the schedule of sessions). 
Participants will be assessed at i) baseline (0 weeks), ii) mid intervention point (+3 weeks) and iii) the end of the intervention period (+6 weeks). The mid-point assessment will be conducted after the final session of Block 1.

We will look at i) compliance with the intervention ii) improvement in targeted motor task iii) generalisation of sensory motor control and iv) cortical excitability.

The data collected, and schedule of assessments is summarised in Figure 1 (uploaded as attachment on ANZCTR registration form)</interventions>
    <comparator> Control group:  Participants in this group will receive their usual stroke rehabilitation therapy during the trial period, but will not have any GotRhythm music-motor therapy sessions.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with the intervention: GotRhythm records the length of time each patient engages with the app. 

We will track each participants progress and their adherence to their rehabilitation program by recording minutes engaged with the app for each therapy session.  This will give total minutes engaged for Therapy Block 1 and Therapy Block 2 and thus a Total compliance measure ([minutes engaged Block 1+minutes engaged Block 2]/360mins)




</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at 3 weeks (end of Therapy Block 1) and at the end of the intervention period (6 weeks) (end of Therapy Block 2).  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensory motor control: The Fugl-Meyer Assessment of Motor Recovery is a stroke-specific, performance based impairment index that evaluates motor functioning, balance, sensation and joint functioning in patients following stroke.  

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at baseline, 3 weeks and at the end of the intervention period (6 weeks). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cortical excitability: To assess the short- and long-term benefits of GotRhythm on the motor cortex, We will use transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) to measure cortical excitability.  A single TMS pulse applied to the primary motor cortex elicits a motor evoked potential (MEP). The amplitude of the MEP provides a measure of motor cortical excitability which reflects functional neuroplasticity changes. 



</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at baseline, 3 weeks and at the end of the intervention period (6 weeks).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Targeted motor task: We will assess music-motor synchrony using the in-built measures of GotRhythm by measuring the proportion of motor task repetitions that match app metronome.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at baseline, 3 weeks and at the end of the intervention period (6 weeks). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cortical inhibition: To assess the short- and long-term benefits of GotRhythm on the motor cortex, we will use transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) to measure cortical inhibition. Paired pulse TMS will be used to assess specific motor inhibitory processes that contribute to the MEP amplitude.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at baseline, 3 weeks and at the end of the intervention period (6 weeks).  

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>neurologically impaired adults  specifically, patients who have suffered an acute stroke and are attending outpatients at the stroke clinic.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Excluded from study if:
	a) &lt;18 years age
	b) pregnant
	c) unstable co-morbid medical or psychiatric disease
	d) history of seizures/epilepsy or family history of same
	e) metallic foreign body implant in the head
	f) implanted device/s
	g) Traumatic Brain Injury or other brain-related condition
	h) history of illness causing brain injury
	i) History of drug abuse
	j) Severe headaches/migraines with aura
	k) Previous adverse reaction to TMS.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes will be used for randomisation.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Consenting participants will be randomised using a computer generated sequence of numbers.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Bentley Health Service - Bentley</hospital>
    <postcode>6102 - Bentley</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley WA 6009
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Perth Hospital Medical Research Foundation (RPH-MRF)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Perth Hospital Medical Research Foundation 
PO Box 2323, East Perth WA 6892
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study aims to investigate the effect of a novel mobile phone based music-motor therapy software application (app) on human motor control and brain activity.  There is considerable interest in using music therapy combined with movement as a way to change the brain and improve functional recovery following injury to the central nervous system.  To date, current therapies incorporating movement and rhythmic cues (metronome or music) are effective at improving upper extremity motor control and gait in neurological disorders, including Parkinsons Disease, Stroke, and Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI).  However, these therapies have a number of limitations, including lack of feedback about motor responses in relation to the music, and lack of portability.  We have developed a novel mobile software application  GotRhythm  that uses mobiles and wireless wearable sensors to deliver music-motor therapy to patients with real time biofeedback.  The proposed study will investigate the effectiveness of this new music-motor therapy app at improving motor control in patients following neurotrauma.  We will determine how music-motor therapy influences brain activity by using non-invasive brain stimulation techniques.  This study will give us a deeper insight into the underlying physiological mechanisms of music-motor therapies  and allow us to optimise future treatments.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5, Colonial House
Royal Perth Hospital
Wellington Street, PERTH WA 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RGS0000000044</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372590(v28-03-2017-14-39-47)-Figure 1 GotRhythm Schedule of assessments.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Etherton-Beer</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
Service 1, Geriatric Medicine
197 Wellington Street
PERTH WA 6000
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92242750 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9224 8009</fax>
      <email>christopher.etherton-beer@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Etherton-Beer</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
Service 1, Geriatric Medicine
197 Wellington Street
PERTH WA 6000
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92242750 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9224 8009</fax>
      <email>christopher.etherton-beer@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Christopher Etherton-Beer</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
Service 1, Geriatric Medicine
197 Wellington Street
PERTH WA 6000
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92242750 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9224 8009</fax>
      <email>christopher.etherton-beer@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>