<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1013">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/01/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000172505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Balance, strength and related falls risk factors in people with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders (PWH), and feasibility of a targeted home exercise program to improve balance.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Balance, strength and related falls risk factors in people with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders (PWH), and feasibility of a targeted home exercise program to improve balance.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Haemophilia and other bleeding disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Two groups of participants will be recruited, a group of 30 adults with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders, and a goup of 30 age and gender matched controls.  All participants will undergo a baseline assessment consisting of laboratory measures of balance, clinical measures of balance, falls history, falls risk, falls self efficacy, pain level, and disease severity.  Following baseline assessments the haemophilia and other bleeding disorders group will be provided with an individualised, tailored balance and strengthening home exercise program.  The balance and strengthening exercises will be selected from the Otago exercise program, and the exercises will be selected, by a qualified physiotherapist, based on results of the baseline assessment.  Participants will undertake the exercise program for four months, with ongoing support from the physiotherapist.  Following the exercise program intervention the participants from the haemophilia and other bleeding disorders group will have the baseline assessment measures repeated.</interventions>
    <comparator>No intervention is given to the controls.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. the falls and falls related history and balance and mobility as a risk factor for falls in people with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. whether an individualised tailored home exercise program targeting balance and strength in adults with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders will improve balance and strength in this population</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured through the follow-up assessment at the conclusion of the exercise program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Which measures of balance performance (laboratory and clinical) are most useful in identifying balance impairment in people with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. What the association is between balance performance and falls risk. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. What the association is between balance performance and falls efficacy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. What the feasibility and effectiveness is of a tailored home exercise program in improving balance in adults with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 4-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants must be willing and able to give informed consent. They must also be able to stand unsupported for greater than 30 seconds. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if there is presence of additional co-morbidities that confer risk of falls, or if they have had lower limb surgery within the previous two months. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Haemophilia Foundation of Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Haemophilia Foundation of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Health professionals working with people with haemophilia and other bleeding disorders (PWH) report a concern that patients appear to be at increased risk of falls and serious injuries from falls.  However, to date there is no published research about falls risk in samples of adult haemophilia patients or any research quantifying the extent of balance dysfunction in PWH.

Therefore this project aims to:
- Determine which measures of balance performance are most useful in identifying balance impairment in PWH in comparison to healthy age and gender matched controls;
- Evaluate the association between balance performance and falls risk;
- Evaluate the association between balance performance and falls efficacy (confidence in mobility); and
- Evaluate the feasibility and effectiveness of a tailored home exercise program in improving balance and related outcomes for PWH.

Thirty adults with haemophilia or other bleeding disorders and 30 age and gender matched healthy adults will be recruited.  All participants will undergo a baseline assessment of laboratory measures of balance, clinical measures of balance, falls risk, falls efficacy, activity level, pain, disease severity and health related quality of life.  

Following the initial assessment the participants from the haemophilia group will be provided with an individually tailored balance and strengthening home exercise program from a physiotherapist, based on the results of the initial assessment.  The participants will be required to undertake the home exercise program for four months, during which time they will receive two visits from the physiotherapist, who will review them and provide any support required.

At the end of the four month program the participants from the haemophilia group will undergo the baseline assessment again in order to evaluate their progress.

This pilot work will be useful to inform health care providers, and PWH, about the magnitude of the problem of balance dysfunction, what methods are most appropriate to identify this risk, and whether standard balance training exercises will be useful in this group.  If successful, further studies will be required with a large sample to evaluate whether this approach can reduce falls in this group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>188/05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Keith Hill</name>
      <address>National Ageing Research Institute
PO Box 31
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872639</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872153</fax>
      <email>k.hill@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Marcia Fearn</name>
      <address>National Ageing Research Institute
PO Box 31
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872512</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872153</fax>
      <email>m.fearn@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>