<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82235">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/08/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000438459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Self-Management versus Usual Care of Mastitis Following Childbirth: A Randomised Control Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Self-Management versus Usual Care of Mastitis Following Childbirth: A Randomised Control Trial to measure the prevalence of mastitis in breastfeeding women following childbirth</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mastitis in mothers following childbirth</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast feeding</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Self-Management of mastitis use of an educational flow chart for the period of six months following recruitment into the study</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care of mastitis postnataly, involves the identifying that a mother has mastitis usually by her General Practioner (GP) or other health care professinal. The mother would than follow treatment as recommended.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure the prevalence of mastitis in breastfeeding women following childbirth</outcome>
      <timepoint>six months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure breastfeeding confidence, exclusivity and duration in breastfeeding women following child birth</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure General Practioner (GP) visits of breastfeeding women following childbirth that develop mastitis with or without the use of the educational self-management interventin tool</outcome>
      <timepoint>six months after childbirth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Breastfeeding women aged 18 years and over that give birth at the Gold Coast Hospital</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>women who dont have access to a phone
women that are non-English speaking
women with babies in special care nursery</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Breastfeeding women will be recruited from the Gold Coast hospital following the birth of their child. Recruited subjects will be:
1.Randomised (using a randomised table of numbers). 
2.Randomisation will be done by a third party at Bond University.
3.Sealed opaque envelopes will be used to conceal the intervention.
4.Allocation concealment will be achieved by the principal investigator when recruiting participants being blinded to which intervention the subject is allocated. to achieve this a random selection of  concealed opaque envelope (containing intervention details) will be used. This will take place when participants are recruited into the study. 
5.Both the principal investigator and the participants will be blinded to treatment allocation.
6.The allocation schedule will be kept on a disc and locked in a secure filing cabinet.
7.The principal investigator, the participants and the statistician will be blinded to the intervention allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants that are breastfeeding will be recruited from the Gold Coast Hospital after childbirth. Recruited subjects will be randomised using a randomised table of numbers. The randomising process will be done by a third party so that the principal investigators and subjects will be blinded to their treatment allocation. Participants will be given a plan envelop with either the intervention or comparator information in it.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/01/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4215</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bond University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PHCRED Faculty of Health Science &amp; Medicine 
Bond University 
Gold Coast QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bond University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PHCRED Faculty of Health Science &amp; Medicine 
Bond University 
Gold Coast QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Gold Coast Health Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Gold Coast Health Service 
108 Nerang st
Southport Gold Coast
QLD 4215</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Developing recurring mastitis is an area of research where there is little published work. Studying mastitis management after childbirth may lead to improved understanding of the outcomes for breastfeeding duration. We therefore wish to conduct a Randomised Control Trial (RCT) that will examine the outcomes of Self-Management of mastitis versus Usual Care in breastfeeding women following childbirth.
The study intends to: 	Measure the prevalence of mastitis in a population of breastfeeding women. Measure breastfeeding duration and exclusivity in a population of breastfeeding women. Trial the Self-Management of mastitis intervention. Measure womens beastfeeding confidence.
Hypotheses
Self management of mastitis lowers the rate of GP visits
Self management of mastitis increase breastfeeding confidence
Self management of mastitis increase breastfeeding duration
Self management of mastitis increase breastfeeding exclusivity</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>R0606</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/08/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Neil Smart</name>
      <address>PHCRED Health Science &amp; Medicine
Bond University
Gold Coast QLD 4229</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 4453</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5595 4122</fax>
      <email>nsmart@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mrs Maree Crepinsek</name>
      <address>PHCRED Health Science &amp; Medicine
Bond University
Gold Coast QLD 4229</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 4494</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5595 4122</fax>
      <email>mcrepins@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mrs Maree Crepinsek</name>
      <address>PHCRED Health Science &amp; Medicine
Bond University
Gold Coast QLD 4229</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 4494</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5595 4122</fax>
      <email>mcrepins@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>