<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308129">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000537257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of exercises on suprahyoid muscles and hyoid movement during swallowing in healthy individuals: investigation by ultrasound</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of exercises on suprahyoid muscles and hyoid movement during swallowing in healthy individuals: investigation by ultrasound</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>none</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>dysphagia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be assigned to one of two exercise groups: modified head-lift manoeuvre (group one) or a placebo treatment which is known to not influence swallowing physiology (group two). 

Exercise programme:
The instructions for each participant will vary depending on the exercise group they have been assigned to. Procedures for the two groups will be as follows:

Group 1 : Modified Head-lift manoeuvre 
Participants assigned to the modified head-lift manoeuvre exercise group will be instructed to sit in an upright position. A theraband (elastic exercise band) will be fixed around their head. They will be instructed to open their mouth against the resistance of the theraband and hold it for one minute, and then rest one minute. The sustained jaw-opening against resistance will be repeated a total of 3 times. Then they will be instructed to to briefly open their mouth against the resistance. They will repeat this brief jaw-opening 30 times. Verbal feedback will be provided throughout regarding the mastery of task performance.

 
Each participant will then be given an exercise record sheet to take home, and instructed to carry out the practiced exercise 3 times per day, 5 days per week for 6 weeks. Each of the 3 daily sessions will involve 33 repetitions of the assigned exercise (30 rapid ball squeezes and 3 sustained squeezes for the placebo group, and 33 jaw-openings for the modified head-lift group). 

Intervention tasks will be supervised by research clinician (speech language therapist)</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2: Placebo exercise 
Participants assigned to the placebo exercise group will carry out an exercise protocol outlined by Shaker and colleagues. They will be given a commercially available rubber ball and will be instructed to squeeze the ball in their right hand for one minute. The sustained ball squeeze will be repeated a total of 3 times. They will then be instructed to briefly squeeze the ball and then relax. They will repeat this brief exercises  30 times. Verbal feedback will be provided throughout regarding the mastery of task performance.  The ball squeezing task serves as a placebo by engaging the patient in a smiilar treatment protocol to the experimental task with no indication of physiologic effect. This task has been used in prior swallowing research as a placebo.


Each participant will then be given an exercise record sheet to take home, and instructed to carry out the practiced exercise 3 times per day, 5 days per week for 6 weeks. Each of the 3 daily sessions will involve 33 repetitions of the assigned exercise (30 rapid ball squeezes and 3 sustained squeezes for the placebo group, and 33 jaw-openings for the modified head-lift group). 

Intervention tasks will be supervised by research clinician (speech language therapist)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% increase in maximal anterior hyoid movement during swallowing as measured with ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment and after 2, 4, 6 weeksof treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% change in two dimensional muscle size as measured by ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment and after 2, 4,6 weeks of treamtent</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>healthy adults aged 21+</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>history of neurological or swallowing impairment; injury or illness to head and neck.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After a potential participant has passed screening procedures for inclusion in the study and signed informed consent the researcher who is providing the treatment will contact the primary investigator who will provide the treatment group assignment.  Therefore allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was 'off-site' or at a central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated randomisation table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>28</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Canterbury</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 4800
Christchurch</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Maggie-Lee Huckabee</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Van der Veer Institute
66 Stewart St
Christchurch</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the treatment of swallowing disorders, a commonly used exercise is the head-lift manoeuvre. This technique requires an individual to lie on their back and repeatedly raise their head to look at their toes. This movement strengthens the muscles under the chin that are involved in swallowing. Although this exercise has been shown to be quite effective, some patients with swallowing impairments are not able to perform the technique, due to weakness, or neck/spine injuries. This study will evaluate the effectiveness of a modified manoeuvre in which the mouth is opened against resistance, thus specifically exercising only muscles under the chin, rather than all neck muscles. This task could be easily performed by most patients. This study will be completed by 28 healthy individuals assigned to one of two treatment groups. One group will perform the the modified manoeuvre, the other group will complete a placebo exercise of squeezing a ball, over a period of six weeks three times a day. Changes in muscle size and hyoid movement will be measured using ultrasound.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Upper South A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/07/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/07/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Maggie-lee Huckabee</name>
      <address>Van der Veer Institute
66 STewart St
Christchurch
8011</address>
      <phone>6433786070</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maggie-lee.huckabee@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Maggie-Lee Huckabee</name>
      <address>Van der Veer Institute
66 Stewart St
Christchurch
8011</address>
      <phone>6433786070</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maggie-lee.huckabee@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Maggie-Lee Huckabee</name>
      <address>Van der Veer Institute
66 Stewart St
Christchurch
8011</address>
      <phone>64 3 378 6070</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maggie-lee.huckabee@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>