<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336857">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001031954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled study to evaluate the effect of Testofen, a specialized extract of Trigonella foenum-graecum (Fenugreek) seed on sexual function and quality of life (QOL) in healthy females.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled study to evaluate the effect of Testofen, a specialized extract of Trigonella foenum-graecum (Fenugreek) seed on sexual function and quality of life (QOL) in healthy females.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TFN-FLS11</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Fenugreek</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Female sexual function, energy and stamina</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Capsules, 2/day 

Formula: Per capsule: Trigonella foenum-graecum  (Fenugreek/Testofen) seed extract, 300mg, gelatin, maltodextrin

Daily Dose: 600 mg Fenugreek</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo capsule, Oral

2 capsules/day (same as the active treatment)

Each capsule contains maltodextrin only</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	Assess efficacy of the Investigational product on sexual function using the DISF-SR (female) and the Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI) at Baseline, week 4 and week 8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4 and week 8</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess efficacy of the Investigational product on individual parameters of female sexual function using the domain and sub domain scores of the DISF-SR (female) and FSFI at Baseline, week 4 and week 8</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the efficacy of the Investigational product on frequency of sexual encounters using participant diary and DISF-SR Question 3.5</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the efficacy of the Investigational product on quality of current sexual functioning using DISF-SR Question 5.4</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the efficacy of the Investigational product on reducing fatigue using the Multi-dimensional Fatigue Symptom Inventory (MFSI); total, general, emotional, physical, mental and vigor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the efficacy of the Investigational product on reducing stress using the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Base and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7.	 Assess sex steroid levels at Baseline and at week 8 of treatment;
I.	Total testosterone
II.	Free testosterone 
III.	Sex hormone binding globulin (SHBG)
IV.	Estradiol (E2)
V.	Androstenedione
VI.	Dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA)
VII.	Follicle Stimulating Hormone (FSH)
VIII.	Luteinizing Hormone (LH) 
IX.	Progesterone
X.	Prolactin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the efficacy of Investigational product on general health parameters; weight, basal metabolic rate (BMI), and sleep.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore potential correlations between libido and relational intimacy measured by Dimensional Relationship Quality (DRQ) at baseline and week 8</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore correlations between libido and non-sexual variables at baseline: age, weight, BMI, levels and type of exercise, hours of sleep/night, alcohol intake, number of children, length of time in current relationship and income levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability to be determined by electrolyte/liver function test (E/LFT), Full Blood Count (FBC), sex hormone levels, and participant reporting of their menstrual cycle pattern and any adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible women must be:
25-50 years old and in generally good health
Pre-menopausal with normal cycles (28-34 day cycles)
On Contraceptive pill and/or actively using contraception for at least 3 months
In her own judgment, in a stable, monogamous sexual relationship that is perceived to be secure and communicative
Believe that sexual problems were not to be considered caused by relationship/partner problems. 
Score &gt; 26 on the FSFI (clinical cut-off point for not being sexually dysfunction). (Weigel et al 2005).
Partner with normal libido and prepared to answer a questionnaire at completion of the study (posted questionnaire with pre-paid return envelope).
Able to adhere to protocol requirements
Able to give informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Eligible women must not:
Have received androgen therapy at any time during the past 3 months 
Be pregnant or attempting to conceive
Be breastfeeding or be lactating for at least 3 months prior to study
Be experiencing any chronic or acute life stress relating to any major life change
Be experiencing depression and/or receiving medication for such illness or disorder
Be receiving statins or other drugs known to impact on steroid hormone levels
Have had a major illness, active gall bladder disease, or gynecological or breast surgery within the last 6 months
Have a history of breast, endometrial, or other gynecological cancer at any time before study participation or other cancer within the last 5 years
Be on medication for diabetes
Have a history of cerebrovascular disease, thrombo-embolic disorders, heart attack, or angina at any time before study participation or thrombophlebitis within the last 5 years
Taking any of these drugs that have anticoagulation and antiplatelet effects on a daily basis for any conditions:  aspirin, diclofenac (Voltaren, Clonac, Diclohexal, Dinac, Fenac), meloxicam (Mobic, Movalis), piroxicam (Mobilis, Feldene), ibuprofen (Brufen, Rafen, Neurofen), and naproxen (Proxen, Naprosyn, Inza, Crysanal, Naprogesic).  
Have abnormal laboratory test results upon initial screening for this study
Have previously participated in a clinical trial within 30 days or received an investigational medication within 30 daysAllergy to fenugreek or any of the excipients or ingredients in this capsule.
Have abnormal laboratory test results for this study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The potential participants are screened by the medicial monitor for inclusion in the study.
The eligible participants are enrolled by Investigator and provided with a "Numbered Container" that is identical to all other containers and contains the same information on the label, except for the NUMBER.  
The investigator is blinded to the product randomized with the numbered containers labelled prior to delivery to Investigational Site. 

Product allocated as participants are enrolled in sequential order (1-80).</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer randomized software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>RCT</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/10/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AZPA International</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>48 Translink Drive, Keilor Park Victoria 3042 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AZPA International</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>48 Translink Drive, Keilor Park Victoria 3042</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Gencor Nutrients, Inc.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>920 E. Orangethorpe Avenue
Suite B, Anaheim, CA 92801</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a double-blind, randomised, placebo-controlled study to evaluate the efficacy of an orally-dosed herb Fenugreek seed extract, on libido and general quality of life in healthy women.

We are looking to see if the herbal medicine can change libido, weight, stress levels, and energy levels over 2 menstrual cycles (approximately 8 weeks). We are also looking to see if there is any change in hormone levels after taking the herbal medicine for the 8 weeks.

In this type of study, we use a placebo as the control group (only contains inactive ingredients) to determine if the product is effective.  Participation in the study will last approximately 10 weeks. Participants will be asked to take the medication for 8 weeks, exactly 2 menstrual cycles, with questionnaires and a blood test at the beginning and follow-up at week 4 and week 8.  

This kind of treatment assignment and randomization (study herb selection by chance) are only carried for research studies. These procedures are being performed for the purposes of the study and are not part of your routine care. The chance of you receiving the active treatment is 50%.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Recruitment:   http://www.trialfacts.com - Click on ASN female libido study.</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Clinical Trial Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, 88 Jephson Street
Toowong, QLD, 4066</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>QCTN HREC Number: 2011001</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Beth Steels</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 68 
New Farm Brisbane
 QLD 4005</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3162 0909</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>beth@asnresearch.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Rao</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 68 
New Farm Brisbane 
QLD 4005</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3162 0909</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@asnresearch.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Rao</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 68 
New Farm Brisbane
QLD 4005</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3162 0909</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@asnresearch.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>