<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82723">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000626369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Antibiotic drop instillation during continuous contact lens wear.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot, prospective, open label, randomised, controlled, parallel design, three-month clinical trial to assess the safety of twice daily instillation of antibiotic versus saline drops during bilateral continuous wear of marketed contact lenses in experienced wearers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contact lens wear</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Twice daily instillation of TOBREX (tobramycin 0.3%) antibiotics drops (two drops on waking and two drops prior to sleep each night) during continuous lens wear compared to a control group using saline drops over a three month period</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group will instil saline drops (two drops on waking and two drops prior to sleep each night) instead of antibiotic during continuous (or extended) lens wear over a 3 month period</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the safety of twice daily antibiotic drop instillation during day and night continuous wear. Primary safety variables include ocular discomfort, history, ocular examination, bulbar and limbal ocular redness, palperbral conjunctival redness and roughness, corneal and conjunctival staining. History (including medical and general health) will be recorded on the Participant History File at all visits. Ocular examination using slit-lamp biomicroscopy will be carried out at baseline and every visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ocular examination using slit-lamp biomicroscope will be carried out at baseline and all follow-up visits (i.e. 2 weeks after baseline and monthly thereafter). Trial duration is three (3) months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>No emergence of bacterial resistance or over-growth of fungus on ocular surface. To be assessed by ocular and throat swabs and aseptic collection of worn lenses. Emergence of bacterial resistance will be examined by assessing the numbers of bacteria that show resistance to the antibiotic over time using standard "minimum inhibitory concentration" assays. Emergence of fungal overgrowth will be examined by assessing the percentage of microbial colonies that are fungi of the total microbial counts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ocular and throat swabs will be taken at baseline, 2-weeks after baseline, 4 weeks after baseline and monthly thereafter until the 3 month time point. Worn lenses will be aseptically collected at monthly visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
Be at least 18 years old;
Be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be "normal" and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses;
Have vision correctable to at least Snellen Visual Acuity of 6/12 (metres) or better in each eye with contact lenses, which means the participant can read within 3 lines of the nominal performance for human distance visiion (i.e. 6/6).
Be experienced at wearing contact lenses</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-existing ocular irritation that would preclude contact lens fitting; 
Had eye surgery or any systemic or ocular medication within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
Undergone corneal refractive surgery;
Worn RGPs or orthokeratology lenses within the previous two weeks;
Contraindications to hydrogel contact lens wear; 
Contraindication / allergy to tobramycin;
Be currently enrolled in another clinical trial or have participated in a clinical trial within the previous two weeks.
Females are excluded from the trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be pre-screened for suitability by way of a routine eye examination which includes refraction, visual acuity and general eye health. 
Informed consent will be obtained prior to any clinical trial procedures. Participants will be randomly allocated into either the saline or antibiotic drop instillation group. Concealed allocation will be by way of central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participant will be randomly assigned to either the saline or antibiotic drop group. A randomisation plan will be generated from http://www.randomization.com/. The randomisation list will be generated based on an independent group design.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Bilateral lens wear</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CIBA VISION Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>11460 Johns Creek Parkway, Duluth, Georgia 30097-1556</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CIBA VISION Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>11460 Johns Creek Parkway, Duluth, Georgia 30097-1556</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this pilot trial is to assess the safety of antibiotic drop instillation compared to a control group using saline drops instead of antibiotic during continuous lens wear.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Vision Cooperative Research Centre and Institute for Eye Research Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Rupert Myers Building 
Gate 14, Barker St
University of New South Wales, NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>08/02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>M. Willcox</name>
      <address>Level 4, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker St, University of New South Wales, Kensington, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>m.willcox@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>J. Ozkan</name>
      <address>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker St, University of New South Wales, Kensington, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>J. Ozkan</name>
      <address>Level 4, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker St, University of New South Wales, Kensington, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>