<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372578">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001530314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Pursuit of Wellbeing: Staff and Parent Wellbeing in Disability Services</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Trialling an intervention to support the wellbeing of parents of children with a disability and staff wellbeing: The Pursuit of Wellbeing Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1194-3587 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PoW Study (The Pursuit of Wellbeing: Staff and Parent Wellbeing in Disability Services)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mental health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parental mental health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Job-related wellbeing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Yooralla will be implementing the program (intervention) across the service's six sites (using a staged process - stepped wedge study design) and all Key Workers and Managers will receive the program as part of their systems change directed by the Executive Management.
The training component of the intervention will be delivered to the first 2 sites in September 2017 with 2 additional sites crossing over to receive the intervention 3 months later in December 2017 and the final group of 2 sites crossing over to receive the intervention in March 2018. Implementation of the program is ongoing once the group of hubs have been exposed to the intervention. 

The program will include:
1) Key worker and Manager training to support parental wellbeing, including information around supporting parental wellbeing, particularly to identify red flags and be able to refer onto appropriate supports; as well as supporting staff job-related wellbeing. 
Delivery
Key workers will receive 1 x day of training at their place of employment which will be delivered as two modules 1) strengthening capacity to support parental wellbeing and 2) staff wellbeing and role boundaries. Managers will receive an additional 2 hours of training which will focus on strategies to strengthen support for their staff around staff self-care for their wellbeing and promoting debriefing and counselling options if experiencing heightened stress or distress. The training will be delivered by a professional organisational psychologist, and designed to include educational modules, role-play activities and discussion. 
Modules
a) Strengthening capacity to support parental wellbeing
	How to identify issues with a parents wellbeing; identifying mental health red flags; how to support the wellbeing of parents and carers of children with a disability; dealing with complex families; addressing parental and family wellbeing through routine care and referral to appropriate services
	Role play activities about: how to manage difficult conversations with parents 

b) Staff wellbeing and role boundaries
	How to identify and manage stress in the workplace; self-care strategies; clearer outline of key worker roles, responsibilities and boundaries. Team support strategies. 
	Role play activities: how to debrief with another staff member and your manager
	Utilising the referral pathways document 

c) Manager Training  
	How to identify and manage stress in the workplace for yourself and your staff; promotion of key worker role boundaries. Team support strategies. 
	Role play activities: how to debrief with your staff member 
	Providing expertise in parental wellbeing and assuming the Champion role for your team. 

2) Access to someone with expertise in parental wellbeing (to be known as the Champion). Managers will receive extra training (as described above) to support them in their conversations with Key Workers on supporting parents wellbeing and to act as a 'champion' for the team. This aims to build the capacity of managers to assist key workers with potentially difficult work events. This will be provided as necessary to staff, time dependent on staff needs and will involve debriefing and problem solving between managers and staff . This is tailored specifically for staff. 

3) Provision of a referral pathways document (mental health supports, peer supports and other relevant local services)  this document will be developed for each Hub and provided to all Key Workers and Managers. The referral pathway document will be introduced during the training and will be an ongoing resource for the organisation. This resource will be updated as necessary by the Director of Allied Services and Wellbeing. 

4) Formalised debriefing process for staff  ensuring staff are aware of the options for de-briefing and counselling. Access to debriefing process for staff will be introduced during the manager training and will be an ongoing process for the organisation. Managers will share this information with their staff at team meetings and promote the use of regular debriefing or as necessary. Staff will be familiar with debriefing and counselling options within the organisation , such as during fortnightly supervision meetings or confidential access to the Employee Assistance Program (EAP). 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Using a stepped wedge cluster control design allows each hub or cluster to act as its own pre versus post control and, in the first two periods, there are at least two hubs acting as controls and at least two hubs receiving the program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Key Workers and Managers self-efficacy (confidence) in supporting the wellbeing of parents. 
Instrument: Developed items based on Bandura's recommendation that self-efficacy questionnaire's are task-specific</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every 3 months after randomisation for 9 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Key Workers and Managers perceptions of supervisory support
Instrument: Perceived Supervisor Support scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every 3 months after randomisation for 9 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff job-related mental wellbeing
Instrument: Warr's Job related wellbeing measure; Mental wellbeing will be measured  also using the Shortened Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Wellbeing Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every 3 months after randomisation for 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent satisfaction with Key Workers
Instrument: New items  have been developed to assess mothers perception of support from their key worker. This scale has been designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every 3 months after randomisation for 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent wellbeing
Instrument: Mental wellbeing will be measured  also using the Shortened Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Wellbeing Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every 3 months after randomisation for 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost consequence analysis: Is the program good value for money and affordable 
Instrument: Short version of WHO Health and Performance Questionnaire (HPQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, every 3 months after randomisation for 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Staff: Currently employed staff working within the service (Yooralla's Children's Services Early Childhood Intervention Service) receiving the intervention. 
Parents: Parents who access the Early Childhood Intervention Service receiving the intervention </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No exclusion criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Partly randomized design. Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>For managerial reasons, the first two hubs will not be randomly selected. Two hubs will be selected based on readiness to undergo the trial and will receive the program immediately after baseline is established, with the remaining four hubs randomised, two at a time, every 3 months thereafter. In this way, hubs that were previously acting as control hubs, will progressively receive the program. 
Simple randomisation using a randomisation table of random digits will be used to randomise the remaining 4 hubs. Cochran, WG (1977) Sampling techniques. 3rd Edition, John Wiley &amp; Sons.  Page 19, Table 2.1, entered at row 09 and column 22.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study uses a stepped wedge cluster non-randomized  controlled trial design. The stepped wedge design is suitable for a phased evaluation approach, such as this, in which there is an imperative to allow all participants to have access to the new program. The design also allows each hub or cluster to act as its own pre versus post control and, in the first two periods, there are at least two hubs acting as controls and at least two hubs receiving the program. We seek to minimize potential bias by not revealing to the Key Workers  when the new program is scheduled to be allocated to their hub.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The repeated measurements (four in total) on individuals in the 6 hubs over the three 3-month periods will be analysed using linear mixed models. For measurement scales that are not too coarse (e.g. &gt; 7 distinct values) the statistical analyses will make use of the REML algorithm to fit the mixed model. This algorithm will take account of missing (at random) assessments and also allows the exploration of various autocorrelation models for the repeated measurements. Comparison of the control and new program means (adjusted for period effects) will be assessed with an F-test. If required, after inspection of diagnostic plots of residuals and fitted values, an empirical logit transformation will be used to re-analyse any item-scales that are bounded and coarse. Generalized linear mixed model techniques will be used to analyse binomial or other categorical data. Cumulative effects of exposure to the new program on key outcome variables will also be explored using the same methods. The final analysis will be conducted after all participants have had adequate opportunity to be assessed at the end of the third period (i.e. at 9 months) and the database has been locked.
The focus groups and interviews will be recorded and transcribed verbatim. Qualitative data will be analysed and coded for emergent themes using a grounded theory approach.
The sample size (6 hubs) is essentially pragmatically determined and limited by the number of hubs in Victoria and the roll-out period for the intervention.  We expect approximately 8 out of 10 Key Workers located at each hub to consent to be repeatedly assessed (at 0, 3, 6 and 9 months) following the start of the study and approximately 3 out of the 10 families that they each support to consent to be surveyed during the study.  The implications of this pragmatic choice, for the investigation of the outcome variables, can be explored by considering one of the key outcome measures, namely the mental well-being of Key Workers as assessed by the short Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (SWEMWBS). Accordingly we expect to have 192 observations of the SWEMWBS (6 hubs x 8 Key Workers x 4 measurement occasions). Based on 1000 simulations of this BDOS (viz SWEMWBS) for each conjectured scenario we find the study has 80% power to detect an increase, due to the intervention, in the mean well-being of 2.6 units (i.e. an effect size of 0.61) when the ICC is 0.25 and there is allowance for a mild global increasing, and confounding, trend of up to 2 units across the 9 months of the study.  Moreover, when, optimistically, ICC=0.5, the power, ceteris paribus, increases to 93% and a smaller effect difference of 2.08, i.e. an effect size of 0.49, can be detected with 80% power. Accordingly, we conclude that this study has moderate to high power to detect small to moderate effect sizes for outcome variables that are measured repeatedly on Key Workers.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>83</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, 207 Bouverie St, Carlton, VIC 3053</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GHD Building Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke St, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Yooralla </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 14, 595 Collins St Melbourne, VIC, 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Deakin University Health Economics</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Deakin University, Burwood Hwy, Burwood, VIC, 3125</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Royal Children's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>50 Flemington Rd, Parkville, VIC, 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Alfred Centre, 99 Commercial Rd, Melbourne, Vic, 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Centre for Developmental Disablity Health Victoria - Monash Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>122 Thomas Street, Dandenong, VIC, 3175</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a trial of a capacity building program to build the self-efficacy of Early Childhood Intervention Service staff (known as key workers) to support parental mental wellbeing and therefore their own wellbeing. Strategies to improve the mental health of parents of children with a disability are urgently needed, and are timely given the current rollout of the National Disability Insurance Scheme (NDIS) in Australia. This program is needed to break the vicious cycle of poor mental health in parents of children with a disability that leads to poorer short and long term outcomes for themselves, their child and their family. Staff will receive the program as part of organisational change to improve both parent and staff mental wellbeing. Applying a capacity building framework and assessing changes in self-efficacy of professionals this program was developed to not only benefit the wellbeing of parents of children with a disability but also the wellbeing of their Key Workers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://mspgh.unimelb.edu.au/centres-institutes/centre-for-health-equity/research-group/jack-brockhoff-child-health-wellbeing-program/research/physical-health-and-wellbeing/yooralla-partnership</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Melbourne Health Sciences Human Ethics Sub-Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 1, 21 Bedford St, North Melbourne
The University of Melbourne
VIC 3051</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1648536</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372578-Signed approval Letter from HESC.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Lisa Gibbs</name>
      <address>Jack Brockhoff Child Health and Wellbeing Program, The Centre for Health Equity, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, The University of Melbourne, Level 5, 207 Bouverie St, Carlton, Vic, 3057</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0920</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lgibbs@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Dana Young</name>
      <address>Jack Brockhoff Child Health and Wellbeing Program, The Centre for Health Equity, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, The University of Melbourne, Level 5, 207 Bouverie St, Carlton, Vic, 3057</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90359870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dana.young@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Dana Young</name>
      <address>Jack Brockhoff Child Health and Wellbeing Program, The Centre for Health Equity, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, The University of Melbourne, Level 5, 207 Bouverie St, Carlton, Vic, 3057</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90359870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dana.young@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Dana Young</name>
      <address>Jack Brockhoff Child Health and Wellbeing Program, The Centre for Health Equity, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, The University of Melbourne, Level 5, 207 Bouverie St, Carlton, Vic, 3057</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90359870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dana.young@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>