<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336180">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000954022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open randomised clinical trial involving Haloperidol, Olanzapine, Quetiapine, Risperidone, and Ziprasidone in first episode never-treated psychosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Antipsychotic discontinuation in first-episode never-treated psychosis: an open randomised clinical trial involving Haloperidol, Olanzapine, Quetiapine, Risperidone, and Ziprasidone</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Antipsychotic discontinuation in first episode psychosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients were randomized to open-label antipsychotic treatment with the following dose ranges: olanzapine 7.5-40 mg/day, risperidone 1.5-7.0 mg/day, quetiapine 1001500 mg/day, and ziprasidone 40240 mg/day.  Study medication was administered orally with the doses prescribed at the treating psychiatrist's discretion. Participants randomized to each second generation antipsychotic received the assigned antipsychotic for 12 months on a daily basis.</interventions>
    <comparator>Haloperidol arm: orally administration for 12 months on a daily basis. Doses ranged from 1.5-8.5 mg/day at the treating psychiatrist's discretion.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Retention of patients on treatment was considered a measure for effectiveness (primary outcome measure) and defined as the time to discontinuation from the antipsychotic to which patients were originally randomized.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (antipsychotic-naive), 6 weeks, 3 months, 9 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom change at each timepoint as measured by the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (antipsychotic-naive), 6 weeks, 3 months, 9 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom change at each timepoint as measured by the Calgary Depression Symptom Scale (CDSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (antipsychotic-naive), 6 weeks, 3 months, 9 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Premorbid Adjustment using the PAS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Showing psychotic symptoms at admission (having a score of 4 or more on PANSS positive scale items 1, 3, 5, or 6) and being naive of antipsychotic, antidepressant or mood stabilizer treatment.

Signing a consent document</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Presence of a major medical or neurological disease, mental retardation, suspicion of substance use directly contributing to the emergence of symptoms (not merely a comorbid condition) and previous treatment with psychotropic drugs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients were recruited from psychiatric emergency units from 3 hospitals located in the metropolitan area of Barcelona, Spain. 
Eligible subjects met inclusion criteria and did not meet exclusion criteria.
Allocation was performed by the psychiatrist's in charge of the patient's inclusion and consisted in contacting by phone the holder of the allocation procedure at a central administration site. Patients were immediately randomized to antipsychotic treatment to haloperidol, olanzapine, risperidone, quetiapine, or ziprasidone.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomization followed a 1:1:1:1:1 procedure into the 5 treatment groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2002</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Barcelona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lilly</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avda de la Industria 30, 28108 Alcobendas, Madrid</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fundacio La Marato TV3</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ganduxer 117, 08022 Barcelona</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The goal of this study was to perform a pragmatic, open, randomized clinical trial comparing the 12-month effectiveness (measured by time to discontinuation) of several second-generation antipsychotic drugs, with that of low doses of haloperidol in never-treated FEP.
Method: 150 patients were randomized to open-label antipsychotic treatment with haloperidol, olanzapine, risperidone, quetiapine, and ziprasidone. Retention of patients on treatment was considered a measure for effectiveness (primary outcome measure). Secondary outcomes included symptom change by antipsychotic as measured by the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Ramirez N, Arranz B, Salavert J, Alvarez E, Corripio I, Duenas RM, Perez V, San L
Predictors of schizophrenia in patients with a first episode psychosis
Psychiatry Res 175: 11-14 (2010)


Arranz B, San L, Ramirez N, Duenas RM, Perez V, Salavert J, Corripio I, Alvarez E 
Clinical and serotonergic predictors of nonaffective acute remitting psychosis in patients with a first-episode psychosis
Acta Psychiatr Scand 119 : 71-77 (2009)


Arranz B, Rosel P, San L, Ramirez N, Duenas RM, Salavert J, Centeno M, del Moral E. 
Low baseline 5-HT2A receptors predict clinical response to olanzapine in first-episode schizophrenia patients
Psychiatry Res 153 : 103-109 (2007)


Arranz B, San L, Duenas RM, Centeno M, Ramirez N, Salavert J, del Moral E 
Lower weight gain with the orally disintegrating olanzapine than with standard tablets in first-episode never treated psychotic patients
Hum Psychopharmacol Clin Exp 22 :11-15 (2007)


Reynolds GP, Arranz B, Templeman L, Fertuzinhos S, San L
Negative and depressive symptom response to antipsychotic treatment of drug-naive psychotic patients is predicted by a 5-HT1A receptor gene polymorphism
Am J Psychiatry 163: 1826-1829 (2006)


Templeman LA, Reynolds GP, Arranz B, San L
Polymorphisms of the 5-HT2C receptor and leptin genes are associated with antipsychotic drug-induced weight gain in Caucasian subjects with a first-episode psychosis
Pharmacogenet Genomics 15(4): 195-200 (2005)


Arranz B, Rosel P, Ramirez N, Duenas MR, Fernandez P, Sanchez JM, Navarro M.A., San L
Insulin resistance and increased leptin concentrations in antipsychotic-free and not in naive first-episode schizophrenic patients
J Clin Psychiatry 65 :1335-1342 (2004)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica de Investigacion Clinica. Hospital San Rafael</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Passeig Vall Hebron 107-117, 08028 Barcelona</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/11/2001</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Luis San, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Passeig Sant Joan de Deu, 2
ES 08950 Esplugues de Llobregat, Barcelona</address>
      <phone>+34 629736820</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>12636LSM@COMB.CAT</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Luis San, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Passeig Sant Joan de Deu, 2
ES 08950 Esplugues de Llobregat, Barcelona</address>
      <phone>+34 629736820</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>12636LSM@COMB.CAT</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Luis San, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Passeig Sant Joan de Deu, 2
ES 08950 Esplugues de Llobregat, Barcelona</address>
      <phone>+34 629736820</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>12636LSM@COMB.CAT</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>