<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347705">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001184965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mindfulness, cognitive processes and coping in chronic illness: insights from a study of joint replacement surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Mindfulness, cognitive processes and coping in chronic illness: a randomised controlled trial to evaluate the effect of mindfulness training prior to total joint arthroplasty on post-operative pain and physical function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will participate in a group program called Mindfulness training (MT) prior to undergoing total hip or knee replacement. Participants will be required to attend 8 weekly group sessions where they will share their experience with peers and learn a number of mindfulness skills to manage stress. They will also be expected to complete homework exercises 6 days a week in between sessions. Prior to entry to the program one interview will be held with the psychiatrist and one with the psychologist who will be facilitating the program. This will allow an introduction to the program and an informed decision about whether the program is suitable for them or not. 
The group sessions will run once a week for 8 weeks. All sessions will be facilitated by both a qualified, trained mindfulness facilitator and will be of 2.5 hours duration. There will be an additional all day session on the Saturday of the 6th week and you will be invited back for a booster day-long work shop 3 months post-surgery. The session will provide you with education regarding the psychological impact of chronic pain and stress and will teach you a number of different mindfulness skills.  At the completion of each session participants will be given mindfulness exercises to practise during the week. All sessions will take place in a group room at the study institution.

Total knee replacement is a single surgical procedure whereby the diseased knee joint is replaced with artificial one. The knee is a hinge joint which provides motion at the point where the thigh meets the lower leg. During a total knee replacement, the end of the thigh (femur) bone is removed and replaced with a metal shell. The end of the lower leg bone (tibia) is also removed and replaced with a channelled plastic piece with a metal stem. Depending on the condition of the kneecap portion of the knee joint, a plastic "button" may also be added under the kneecap surface. The procedure is performed under either a general or spinal anaesthetic and takes about 1 hour

Total hip replacement is a single surgical procedure whereby the diseased hip joint is replaced with an artificial one. The hip joint is composed of a ball and socket, with the surface of each covered by cartilage. A number of conditions and diseases can cause the cartilage surfaces to degenerate, which in turn leads to pain, stiffness, and disability. Both the ball (femoral head) and socket (acetabulum) are replaced during total hip replacement surgery. Different materials can be used in total hip replacement. Commonly, the femoral head is replaced with a metal ball and stem and a metal cup is secured into the acetabulum with a polyethylene socket. The procedure is performed under either a general or spinal anaesthetic and takes about 1 hour</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will undergo total hip or knee replacement alone</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Will be self-reported pain and physical function measured on the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities (WOMAC) Osteoarthritis Index. The WOMAC consists of 24 items covering three subscales: pain (five items), stiffness (two items) and physical function (17 items). The pain and physical function subscales will be used, each subscale transformed to a score ranging from 0 to 100, with a higher score indicating greater pain and physical function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological well being: will be derived from the 12-item Short Form Health Survey mental component score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: will be measured using the WHOQOL-BREF, a 26-item Quality of life Assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and Anxiety: data will be derived from the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), a validated instrument for detecting states of depression and anxiety and severity of emotional disorder in patients under treatment in hospital medical, surgical and outpatient departments and the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS), a validated and sensitive measure of treatment effect</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self Efficacy: will be measured using the Arthritis Self-Efficacy Scale, a 20-item questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mindfulness: the Mindful Awareness Attention Scale (MAAS) is a 15 item measure assessing mindfulness and its role in psychological well-being</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carver Brief COPE Questionnaire: a 28-item questionnaire to measure coping styles</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Irrational Scale: a 20-item measure of cognitive distortions</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brief Illness Perceptions Questionnaire: a 9-item measure of illness perceptions</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, and 3 and 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness of MT program plus total joint replacement compared to total joint replacement alone

Information regarding utilisation of health services, including medications and in- and outpatient services, will be captured by linkage of our database to administrative and clinical databases maintained by the study institution.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>On the surgical waiting list for primary total joint replacement for end stage osteoarthritis at the study institution</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) Revision surgery or surgery for neoplastic disease; (ii) Inability to provide informed consent due to mental incompetence (e.g., intellectual disability, dementia) (mild cognitive impairment (MCI) would not be cause for exclusion); (iii) active drug or alcohol use disorder which in the opinion of the investigators makes the patient unsuitable for participation in the trial (iv) limited English language fluency (v) evidence at interview or on the Memory Complaints Questionnaire (MCQ) of presumptive cognitive impairment requiring clinical assessment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>When a subject has fulfilled all study criteria allocation take place. The patient’s assignment will be performed by the data manager who will have no direct contact with the subject either before or after assignment. The clinicians involved in the assessment or treatment of patients will have no role in the assignment process. Opaque envelopes containing patient assignment will be prepared.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random assignment will be computer generated by a researcher not directly involved in the study. Randomisation will be clustered into groups of random size of between 8 and 12 to ensure even distribution without bias</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/09/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/10/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>145</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Peter Choong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Orthopaedics
St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Level 3 Daly wing
35 Victoria parade
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2702
CANBERRA
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor David Castle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mental Health Services
St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Level 2, 46 Nicholson Street
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Michael Salzberg</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mental Health Services
St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Level 2, 46 Nicholson Street
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Michelle Dowsey</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Orthopaedics
St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Level 3 Daly wing
35 Victoria parade
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Kaveh Monshat</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mental Health Services
St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Level 2, 46 Nicholson Street
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Simon Knowles</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculity of Life and Social Sciences
Swinburne University of Technology
PO Box 218
Hawthorn 3122
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objectives of this research project are to: (1) identify levels of distress in patients on a waiting list for total joint arthroplasty (TJA), and (2) to determine whether administering an eight-session group mindfulness training intervention prior to surgery will improve the physical recovery of patients undergoing TJA. It is hypothesized that (1) levels of pain will be adversely associated with depression, anxiety and lower Quality of Life; (2) the intervention will lead to better tolerance of symptoms, and improved quality of life. Mindfulness is the awareness that emerges through paying attention on purpose, in the present moment, and non-judgmentally to the unfolding of experience moment by moment. Training involves instruction in a number of meditation techniques as well as teaching on how to remain focused on the present moment in day to day activities. There is now extensive scientific evidence showing that mindfulness training leads to an improvement in emotional and physical symptoms in a variety of disorders such as chronic pain, cancer, depression, anxiety and substance use among others. We propose to undertake a 3 year randomised controlled trial in patients with end stage osteoarthritis on the waiting list for TJA. The study will recruit 150 patients and randomly allocate them to receive the current standard of care for TJA or a combination of Mindfulness training (MT) followed by TJA. We plan to measure pain, function, quality of life, coping and mental health via validated questionnaires, as well as the cost effectiveness of a strategy that combines MT and TJA, compared to TJA alone. These measures will be taken prior to surgery and at 3 and 12 months post TJA surgery. Participants will all be followed for one year at which time the benefits in terms of health improvements after TJA will be, compared.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Knowles, S.R., Nelson, E.A., Castle, D.J., Salzberg, M.R., Choong, P.F.M. &amp; Dowsey, M.M. (2016). Using the common sense model of illness to examine interrelationships between symptom severity and health outcomes in end-stage osteoarthritis patients. Rheumatology, 55, 1066-1073.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The St. vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Human Reseach Ethics Committee - A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-A 143/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Nelson</name>
      <address>St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Department of Orthopaedics
Level 3 Daly wing
35 Victoria parade
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 3516</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9416 3610</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.nelson@svha.org.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Dowsey</name>
      <address>St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Department of Orthopaedics
Level 3 Daly wing
35 Victoria parade
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 3955 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9416 3610</fax>
      <email>mmdowsey@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Nelson</name>
      <address>St. Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
Department of Orthopaedics
Level 3 Daly wing
35 Victoria parade
Fitzroy 3065
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 3516 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9416 3610</fax>
      <email>Elizabeth.Nelson@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Choong</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics, St Vincent?s
Hospital (Melbourne), PO Box 2900, Fitzroy, Melbourne, Vic. 3065, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9231 3980 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9416 3610</fax>
      <email>pchoong@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>