<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363987">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000400763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to compare the capsule formulation of BIT225 to the original powder formulation in healthy participants.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Open-Label, Randomised, Single Dose, Crossover Pharmacokinetic Study Comparing a Capsule Formulation of BIT225 to the Current Oral Suspension Administered in Healthy Participants.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-4972 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>BIT225-007</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatits C Virus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>BIT225 powder 400mg, single dose, oral administration
or
BIT225 4 x 100mg capsules, single dose, oral administration

followed by the alternate dose form 10-14 days later.
Dosing will supervised within a Phase I unit.  
The concentration of drug in the blood will be measured using a validated assay as described in the primary outcome.</interventions>
    <comparator>The original powder formulation is the control.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the pharmacokinetic characteristics of a single dosage of BIT225 suspension (400 mg) and capsule formulation (4 x 100 mg) in healthy participants. 
The concentration of BIT225 in the blood will be measured using a validated liquid chromatography/ mass spectrometry method. 
Pharmacokinetic parameters such as the area under the concentration (AUC) versus time curve, maximum concentration (Cmax), time to maximum concentration (Tmax), half life, clearance will be used to assess the primary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>96 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the tolerability of BIT225 400 mg in suspension compared to 4 x 100 mg BIT225 capsule formulation following a single dosage in healthy participants. 
Tolerability will be assessed by comparison of treatment emergent adverse events, changes in vital signs, ECG parameters, and routine laboratory tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 14 days post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.  Be male or female (of non-child bearing potential), aged between 18 and 49 years (inclusive).
2.  Healthy participants  defined as participants who are free from clinically significant illness or disease as determined by their medical history, physical examination, 12- lead ECG (QTc less than 450 ms) and clinical laboratory determinations.
3.  Normotensive (systolic BP less than 140 mm Hg and diastolic BP less than 90 mm Hg).
4.  Body Mass Index (BMI) btween 19 and 29 kg/m2.
5.  Weight between 55 kg and 110kg.
6.  Participants who smoke less than one cigarette or tobacco form (including cigars) per month in the last 12 months.
7.  Adequate venous access in the left or right arm to allow collection of a number of blood samples.
8.  Fluent in the English language.
9.  Provide written informed consent to participate in the study and be willing to comply with the study procedures.
10.  No abnormal finding of clinical relevance at the screening evaluation.
11.  Agree to use a combination of two approved methods of contraception, from screening and until 30 days after administration of the study drug.  
12.  Females must have a negative pregnancy test at Screening (baseline) and Day -1.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>49</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.  Currently taking or have taken antiretroviral therapy in the last 30 days.
2.  Any condition that would interfere with drug absorption (e.g. chronic diarrhoea).
3.  A history of pancreatitis or hepatitis within the previous 3 years.
4.  Abnormal laboratory test results, deemed clinically significant by the Medical Officer (Principal Investigator or medically qualified nominee), within 21 days before enrolment, including anaemia (haemoglobin less than 11.0 g/dl for men and 10.0 g/dl for women), neutropenia, thrombocytopenia and elevated liver function test results more than two times the upper limit of normal. Renal function impairment (Creatinine clearance less than 50mL/min).
5.  Unable to withhold concomitant medication for 48 hours prior to dosing and for the duration of confinement.
6.  As a result of medical review, physical examination or screening investigations, the Medical Officer considers the participant unfit for the study.
7.  Positive urine drug test or alcohol breath test at screening.
8.  Use of macrolide antibiotics (eg. Erythromycin), azole antifungal agents (eg. Ketoconazole) within 30 days of study dosing.
9.  Evidence of clinically relevant oral, cardiovascular, haematological, gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, endocrine, pulmonary, neurologic, psychiatric or skin disorder.
10.  History of epilepsy.
11.  History of coronary diseases, peripheral vascular diseases, cerebrovascular accident, transient ischaemic attack, uncontrolled hypertension or signs/symptoms of ischaemic heart disease.
12.  Acute therapy for a serious infection within 30 days of study entry.
13.  Positive screening test for Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) or Hepatitis C antibody and HIV.
14.  Have participated in a clinical trial or receipt of an experimental therapy within 60 days prior to dosing.
15.  Blood donation of greater than 550 mL within 90 days before the first dose administration.
16.  Consumption of grapefruit or grapefruit juice within 14 days prior to the first day of study confinement and through to completion of the confinement period.
17.  Those who regularly drink more than four (4) units of alcohol daily (1 unit = 300 mL beer, 1 glass wine, 1 measure spirit) or those who may have difficulty abstaining from alcohol during the 36 hours prior to dose administration and until completion of blood sampling.
18.  Unwilling or unable to fast for the 10 hours prior to dosing.
19.  Women of child bearing potential, pregnant or breast feeding women.
20.  Male partners of pregnant females.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by placing all 14 randomisation numbers in a box.  The first 7 numbers withdrawn were allocated to receive the powder formulation in the first cycle.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics such as mean, standard deviation and coefficient of variation for all pharmacokinetic parameters will be calculated.
The number of participants was based on the FDA Guidance for Industry, Bioavailability and Bioequivalence Studies for Orally Administered Drug Products (2003).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>14</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Biotron Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 1.9, 56 Delhi Rd
North Ryde  NSW  2113</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Biotron Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 1.9, 56 Delhi Rd
North Ryde  NSW  2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BIT225 powder has been used in several trials to date to investigate safety and effectiveness.  A capsule formulation, being a more acceptable dose form than the powder, has been developed for use in future trials and as a possible future marketed formulation.  This trial is to compare a single dose of the capsule to a single dose of the powder to see how much of the drug gets into the bloodstream and how long does the body take to remove it, what is the maximum concentration of the drug in the bloodstream after a single dose, and how well the capsule is tolerated compared to the powder form.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road
 Dulwich
 South Australia 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janakan Krishnarajah</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research Limited
1st Floor, B Block, 
Hospital Avenue, 
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6382 5100</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9381 4453</fax>
      <email>jkrishnarajah@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Miller</name>
      <address>Biotron Limited
Suite 1.9, 56 Delhi Rd
North Ryde  NSW  2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9805 0488</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9805 0688</fax>
      <email>mmiller@biotron.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Miller</name>
      <address>Biotron Limited
Suite 1.9, 56 Delhi Rd
North Ryde  NSW  2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9805 0488</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9805 0688</fax>
      <email>mmiller@biotron.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Bronwyn Williams</name>
      <address>Biotron Limited
Suite 1.9, 56 Delhi Rd
North Ryde  NSW  2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9805 0488</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9805 0688</fax>
      <email>bwilliams@biotron.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>