<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373022">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001063303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Influence of overweight or obesity on the dynamic balance in 2nd cycle students of Portuguese elementary school</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Influence of childhood obesity on dynamic balance in 2nd cycle students of Portuguese elementary school</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1196-7979</utrn>
    <trialacronym>IofCOonDBin2ndCSofPES</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Childhood Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dynamic balance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an observational study aimed to understand the incidence of obesity in schoolchildren by 5th and 6th school grade students from both gender of the School Group Infante D. Henriques from Viseu, as well as the possible relation with the balance.
This 5th and 6th grade population was chosen according to two different school periods, the entrance and exiting level for the twice Basic Education Cycle, This study have taken one month from participant selection process, personal identification questionnaire fill, in order to assess body weight, a Body mass index (BMI) was conducted. Each student completes a single assessment session of approximately 30 minutes. BMI was calculated and the subjects were classified as follows: obesity, overweight, normal weight and thinness according to the proposed limits. This dues to our intent of seeing if there was already possible to compare children with BMI above ideal with children with ideal BMI in order to understand the influence of BMI and dynamic postural balance.  The Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT), which is a measure of dynamic postural control, and has been chosen because it is a reliable test that evaluates dynamic stability in different planes because it is economical and validated..
The test was performed in the school gymnasium, where adhesive was applied to the soil in order to perform a star in which its segments were about 120 cm long and arranged at 45° between them, arranged with the help of the goniometer.
The children were instructed that they should engage in the interception of the ribbons (being the center), so that later they would only have one foot placed in it so that with the other foot they tried to reach as far as possible the 8 segments in the following Order: Anterior, Posterior, Lateral; Medial, Anterolateral, Posterior-medial, Antero-medial, Posterior-Lateral.
To facilitate childrens understanding, they were told that they should reach as far as possible the 8 vectors in the following order: North, South, East, West, Northeast, Southwest, Northwest, Southeast, and were also given the opportunity to experience the Before measurements are taken. The children performed the test and the measurements of the amplitudes reached by both lower limbs were taken for comparison.

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis a Body mass index (BMI, assessed by stadiometer and digital scales) was conducted (Viester, et al., 2013; Desouzart, Filgueiras, Matos, &amp; Marques, 2016), in order to assess body weight,</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial evaluation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis a dynamic balance through Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT) (Bicici, Karatas, &amp; Baltaci, 2012).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial evaluation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between Body mass index (BMI, assessed by stadiometer and digital scales) and dynamic balance through Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT) (Bicici, Karatas, &amp; Baltaci, 2012).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i] to be aged between 10 and 11 years; ii] understand the aims of the study and agree to participate voluntarily; iii] the provision of informed consent by students parents and guardians</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i] Presence of pathology a known health condition of rheumatological, orthopedic, cardio-respiratory, oncological pathology and / or diagnosed coronary disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The children performed the test and the measurements of the amplitudes reached by both lower limbs were taken for comparison.
It is relevant to note that in the test any repetition was discarded if the child moved the supporting leg from the center of the figure, was unable to maintain balance in the supporting leg during the test and deviated from the segment being evaluated.
As for the measurements, these were removed with a tape measure after the child placed the test foot and always the interception of the vectors (center) to the distal end of the hallux.
In order to know whether there are actually changes in balance, the method of Olmsted, Carcia, Hertel &amp; Shultz (2002), which defines that in order to conclude if there is an osteoarticular imbalance, is necessary to have a difference of 4 centimeters of amplitude in the same segment between both Member States
SPSS, 23.0 version was used in order to treat all the statistical data. Descriptive statistics were performed, considering all the variables obtained. Due to the small number of the sample and to facilitate the analysis, the variables of BMI were grouped, and we considered four groups: obesity, overweight, normal weight and thinness. The statistically level of significance was establish in p = 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>314</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/07/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data analysis is complete</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Viseu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Piaget Institute of Viseu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Campus Universitário de Viseu
Estrada do Alto do Gaio
3515-776 Galifonge, Lordosa  Viseu</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Portugal</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Piaget Institute of Viseu</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Campus Universitário de Viseu
Estrada do Alto do Gaio
3515-776 Galifonge, Lordosa  Viseu</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Portugal</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity is a chronic disease characterized by the breakdown of balance synergies in the muscle and joints, which may lead to decreased stability and postural adaptations. The main objective was to compare children with body mass index (BMI) above ideal with ideal and to understand the relationship between BMI and balance in 2nd cycle students. The sample of 20 students aged between 10 and 11 years. Methodology: The collection methods used were the BMI and Star Excursion Balance Test (SEBT) to cross the results of these two variables and to understand their relationship RESULTS: 55% of the children had a BMI above the ideal, being 30% were overweight and 25% were obese. Of the children above the ideal BMI, 81.8% are female (54.5% overweight and 27.3% obese). Subjecting the population to SEBT, it was observed that children with BMI above ideal and with a dismetria the amplitudes obtained in SEBT by both lower limbs mainly reveal present balance alterations. Conclusion: Due to the anthropometric changes caused by obesity and changes in the center of gravity, this conduction modifies the motor pattern and stabilization, which negatively influences postural control and reduces the balance of obese individuals.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ethical committee of Piaget Institute</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Campus Universitário de Viseu
Estrada do Alto do Gaio
3515-776 Galifonge, Lordosa  Viseu</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Portugal</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gustavo Desouzart</name>
      <address>Campus Universitário de Viseu
Estrada do Alto do Gaio
3515-776 Galifonge, Lordosa  Viseu</address>
      <phone>+351 232 910 100</phone>
      <fax>+351 232 910 189</fax>
      <email>gustavodesouzart@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gustavo Desouzart</name>
      <address>Campus Universitário de Viseu
Estrada do Alto do Gaio
3515-776 Galifonge, Lordosa  Viseu</address>
      <phone>+351 232 910 100</phone>
      <fax>+351 232 910 189</fax>
      <email>gustavo.desouzart@viseu.ipiaget.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gustavo Desouzart</name>
      <address>Campus Universitário de Viseu
Estrada do Alto do Gaio
3515-776 Galifonge, Lordosa  Viseu</address>
      <phone>+351 232 910 100</phone>
      <fax>+351 232 910 189</fax>
      <email>gustavo.desouzart@viseu.ipiaget.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>