<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364066">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000442707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Reducing impulsivity in repeat violent offenders using a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (sertraline)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Reducing impulsivity in repeat violent offenders using a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (sertraline)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-9617 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>REINVEST</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Offending behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Impulsivity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anger</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Aggression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention consists of 100mg sertraline or placebo sertraline taken orally, once per day for 12 months duration. The medication used in this trial will be in tablet form.

Sertraline is an anti-depressant of the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) class. It is primarily used to treat major depression in adults as well as obsessive-compulsive, panic, and social anxiety disorders in both adults and children. According to the Australian Statistics on Medicines 2007 (latest available data), SSRIs were the most commonly prescribed anti-depressant in Australia with over 8.5 million scripts issued in that year. Among SSRIs, sertraline was the most commonly prescribed anti-depressant.  

The selected dose is 100mg/day which is common when used as an antidepressant. Sertraline may be prescribed up to 200mg/day. 



</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo will contain the inactive ingredients of setrona: microcrystalline cellulose, calcium hydrogen phosphate, sodium starch glycollate, hydroxypropyl cellulose, magnesium stearate, white Opadry, hypromellose, titanium dioxide, macrogol 400, purified talc. The placebo tablets will be identical in shape, colour and levry to the Setrona. The dosing will be the same as the active and as an oral tablet.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Offending behaviour.  

Re-offending will be determined by linking the participant list to the NSW Bureau of Crime Statistics Reoffending Database (ROD) which records individuals' criminal court appearances over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed retrospectively at 12 months following commencement of the intervention or control treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impulsivity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Impulsivity will be assessed every six weeks using the Barratt Impulsivity Scale.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anger</outcome>
      <timepoint>Anger will be assessed every six weeks following the commencement of the intervention or control treatment using the Anger, Irritability and Aggression questionnaire.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression</outcome>
      <timepoint>Depression will be assessed every 12 weeks following the commencement of the intervention or control treatment using the Beck Depression Inventory. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Irritability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Irritability will be assessed every six weeks following the commencement of the intervention or control treatment using the Anger, Irritability and Aggression Questionnaire</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male sex; 
Over the age of 18 years; 
Prior conviction for 2 or more violent offences; 
Score of 70 or above on the Barratt Impulsiveness Scale; 
Medically fit to undertake the trial;
Able to provide informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current use of any serotonergic drug (e.g. SSRI, SNRI, TCA);
History of adverse drug reactions to SSRI; 
Current use of any anti-psychotic medication;
Severe mental illness 
Considered to be at high risk of suicide; 
Anticipation of receiving a custodial sentence;
Significant renal or hepatic impairment;
Inability to provide informed consent; 
Conviction for murder or child sexual assault;
Impending deportation, moving interstate, returning to a remote/inaccessible area.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will also be recruited from those serving community orders under the aegis of Corrective Services NSW, Community Offender Management at sites in the Sydney metropolitan and outer metropolitan areas. A targeted approach will be used whereby Corrective Services NSW will provide a list of those potentially eligible for the study (e.g. male, over 18, two or more convictions for violence). Those who express an interest in the study will receive a follow-up visit from a research nurses. At this meeting they will be provided with a full explanation of the study and the inclusion/exclusion criteria will be examined. Those who express an interest in the study and meet the basic inclusion criteria will be invited for a medical assessment to determine medical suitability for the trial prior to commencement. 

Randomisation will occur centrally by the NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre (Sydney University) and forwarded to the pharmacy for distribution of the medication.  
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be performed using computer generated random blocks to ensure that in every block 50% of subjects are randomised to active and 50% to placebo. Similarly, the Level of Service Inventory instrument will be used to ensure that those at 'medium' to 'high' risk of reoffending are evenly allocated to the two arms of the study. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size of 340 (170 in each group) will provide 80% power, with a 5% significance level, to detect a 30% relative difference in recidivism at 1 year between the active and placebo groups (e.g. SSRI 35% recidivism and placebo 50% recidivism). This is within the range of values obtained for other studies, and a conservative estimate for good quality interventions in the criminal justice area. The study will also have 80% power, with a 5% significance level, to detect differences in continuous outcomes of one third of a standard deviation. 

Comparison of baseline measures will be performed using independent t-tests for continuous variables (or non-parametric equivalent) and ch-squared analysis for categorical variables. Efficacy of the treatment (vs. placebo) will be evaluated using a chi-squared test with recidivism within 1 year (i.e. arrest, court appearance or reincarceration) as the outcome, and treatment group as the explanatory variable. 

Efficacy of the treatment will also be evaluated using survival analysis with time to reoffending as the outcome and the explanatory variable of active or placebo SSRI. 

Change in scores from baseline to 12 month follow-up for the behavioural measures will be compared between treatment and placebo groups using a t-test. Analysis will be intention to treat. In those prescribed SSRI (ie. the treatment arm of the study) changes in BIS-II and BDI-II from baseline to 12 months will be compared between those with s/s versus any l using a repeated measures analysis.  
All analyses will be intention to treat. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>340</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of NSW</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Human Research and Ethics Committee
Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Corrective Services NSW</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Henry Deane Building 
20 Lee Street 
Sydney NSW 2000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hunter New England Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Locked Bag 1 
New Lambton NSW 2305
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bureau of Crime Statistics and Research</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NSW Bureau of Crime Statistics and Research
GPO Box 6
SYDNEY NSW 2001
AUSTRALIA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
ABN 15 211 513 464
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Justice &amp; Forensic Mental Health Network</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 150
MATRAVILLE NSW 2036
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Violence is a leading cause of death and injury worldwide and a large percentage of prison inmates have histories of violent offending. Numerous studies attest to a strong association between poor impulse control (impulsivity) and violent crime. Impulsivity has been shown to be associated with reduced tone in neural pathways within the brain for which serotonin is the principal neurotransmitter. In a number of studies of impulsive-aggressive individuals, the administration of selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) has been associated with reduced aggression, impulsivity and depression. To date, there has been no systematic study of the potential benefits of SSRIs for incarcerated impulsive violent offenders who are at high risk of repeat offending. This trial will examine the effectiveness of treatment with an SSRI in impulsive violent offenders on reoffending using a double blind RCT design.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Pilot study publication: 
Butler T, Schofield P, Greenberg  D, Allnutt S, Indig D, Carr V,  DEste C, Mitchell P, Ellis A, Knight L.  Reducing impulsivity in repeat violent offenders: an open label trial of a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor. ANZ Journal of Psychiatry. 2010; 44:11371143</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research and Ethics Committee 
Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 11390</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Aboriginal Health and Medical Research Council</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 1565, Strawberry Hills, NSW 2012</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>822/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Corrective Services NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Henry Deane Building 
20 Lee Street 
Sydney NSW 2000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/26576</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>tony butler</name>
      <address>Kirby Institute 
UNSW
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 9257</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0891</fax>
      <email>tbutler@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>tony butler</name>
      <address>Kirby Institute 
UNSW
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 9257</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0891</fax>
      <email>tbutler@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>tony butler</name>
      <address>Kirby Institute 
UNSW
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 9257</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0891</fax>
      <email>tbutler@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>tony butler</name>
      <address>Kirby Institute 
UNSW
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 9257</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0891</fax>
      <email>tbutler@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>