<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343330">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000860965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of parental anxiety management on child anxiety treatment outcomes: a controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Parental anxiety management versus no parental anxiety management as an adjunct to cognitive behaviour therapy for childhood anxiety disorders: changes in anxiety diagnosis and anxiety symptoms.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety disorders in children and parents</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Parental Anxiety Management (PAM) for experimental group. This program is based on cognitive behavioural therapy, 5 x 40mins sessions delivered in a group format, once per fortnight. The treatment components included: psychoeducation, cognitive restructuring, time management, problem-solving, and gradual exposure for the parents. ALL children and families received cognitive behavioural therapy [Cool Kids treatment program (Rapee, Wignall, Hudson, and Schniering, 2000)] 10 x 2 hour sessions delivered in group format, once a week. These sessions included psychoeducation, cognitive restructuring, problem-solving, assertiveness training, and gradual exposure. Both parents and children were involved in the Cool Kids treatment program. For families randomly assigned to the PAM group, the PAM program was conducted simultaneously with the Cool Kids treatment program over the 10-week period. For families that were randomly assigned to the PAM program, the program was offered to both parents. Moreover, both anxious and non-anxious parents were randomly allocated to the PAM program.</interventions>
    <comparator>No Parental Anxiety Management group (No PAM or CBT only group): This group completed the Cool Kids but the parents in this group did not receive the parental anxiety management program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence/absence of anxiety disorder assessed by the Anxiety Disorder Interview Schedule for Children (ADIS-IV-C/P; Silverman &amp; Albano, 1996). Presence/absence of anxiety disorder assessed by the ADIS for the parents' anxiety difficulties (ADIS-IV; Brown, Di Nardo, &amp; Barlow, 1994).</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental and child reported anxiety symptoms: 

Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (Spence, 1998) for the child's anxiety 

Depression Anxiety Stress Scale - 21 Items (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995) for the parent's anxiety</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>principal anxiety disorder for the child</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>13</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Intellectual and developmental disability, psychoses, disabling medical condition and concurrent psychological treatment. Youths with co-morbid behavioral disorders who had a clinical severity rating of 6 or more were also excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following a brief telephone screen, parents signed consent forms at the assessment and children provided verbal assent. Children who met criteria for inclusion and agreed to participate were allocated to a group based on the child's age. Allocation was concealed: clinicians determined the child's eligibility for the study and then the clinic administration team conteacted the research officer who held the allocation schedule.</concealment>
    <sequence>The first author used a schedule from a random number generator (computer software obtained online) to assign each group to treatment condition and to therapists.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/01/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Balaclava Rd
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: The current trial examined whether the inclusion of a parental anxiety management (PAM) program in addition to family cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) was more efficacious than family CBT only in treating childhood anxiety disorders. Method: Two hundred and nine children (aged 6-13 years) with a principal anxiety disorder were randomly allocated to a 5 session PAM program (n = 109) in addition to family CBT or family CBT only.  Results: Overall, results revealed that the addition of PAM did not significantly improve principal anxiety diagnostic outcomes for the child or the parent compared to the CBT only group at post-treatment and 6-month follow-up. Results further suggest that children with non-anxious parents were more likely to be diagnosis-free for any anxiety disorder compared to children with anxious parents at post-treatment and 6-mth follow-up. Conclusions: The present findings indicate that the addition of PAM in its current format did not lead to additional gains in diagnostic status when used as an adjunct to family CBT in the treatment of the childs anxiety disorder. The addition of PAM did not lead to a sufficient decline in parental anxiety disorders over and above the decline observed across time for children receiving CBT. Parental anxiety status impacted on child diagnostic outcome: Children were less likely to be diagnosis-free following treatment if they had a parent who also had an anxiety disorder.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Hudson, J.L., Rapee, R.M., Lyneham, H.J., Wuthrich, V., Edwards, S., Seeley, E., &amp; Gar, N. (September, 2009). Treating parent anxiety to enhance the efficacy of cognitive behavioural treatment for children with anxiety disorders. Paper presented at the Australian Association for Cognitive and Behaviour Therapy, Perth, Australia.

Rapee, R.M., Hudson, J.L., Schniering, C.A., Lyneham, H.J., Wuthrich, V., Edwards, S.,Seeley, E., &amp; Gar, N. (November, 2008). Treating parent anxiety to enhance the efficacy of cognitive behavioural treatment for children with anxiety disorders. Paper presented at the Association for Behavioral &amp; Cognitive Therapies, Orlando, FL

Hudson, J.L., Rapee, R.M., Lyneham, H.J., Wuthrich, V., Edwards, S., Seeley, E., &amp; Gar, N. (September 2011). Treating parent anxiety to enhance the efficacy of family-based cognitive behavioural treatment for childhood anxiety disorders. Paper to be presented at The European Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Reykjavik, Iceland.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University 
NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/09/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE23SEP2005-R04293</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Jennifer L. Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Balaclava Rd
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 8668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhudson@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Jennifer L. Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Balaclava Rd
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 8668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhudson@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Jennifer L. Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 8668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhudson@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>