<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371127">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001010482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot randomised control trial of a problem-solving intervention tailored to quality of life difficulties experienced by patients with diabetic retinopathy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot randomised control trial of a problem-solving intervention tailored to quality of life difficulties experienced by patients with diabetic retinopathy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DMP_INT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic retinopathy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomised to the intervention arm will receive six (minimum) or eight (maximum) complete weekly problem-solving training (PST) sessions provided by trained eye care staff. The first PST session will be combined with the introductory session which will be delivered as an individual one-on-one session (face to face).  The remaining PST sessions will be conducted over the telephone and the participant can decide whether they feel they need the 7th and 8th session, which are optional. Between sessions, participants will be expected to attempt to put problem solving techniques into practice and develop goals necessary to fulfill solutions to problems.  Progress review will be conducted at the beginning of each session. All telephone calls are recorded and the frequency and duration of each session monitored.

Introductory session
The introductory session will briefly recap an overview of diabetes with targeted awareness of diabetic retinopathy (DR) risk factors; HbA1c targets, blood pressure, cholesterol, obesity.  From here, a discussion on how DR impacts upon a persons quality of life will be presented.  This will followed by explaining the nature of, and rationale behind, PST in the context of diabetes and DR related quality of life (QoL).  Participants will be informed of the overall goal of PST which is to present and apply problem solving skills to assist them to live a fuller life despite their DR and the chronic nature of their diabetes. Thus the main goal is to modify the participants perceptions and beliefs that may interfere with attempts to engage in optimal problem solving efforts and ultimately optimal self-management practices.  An explanation regarding the format and time interval of PST sessions will be discussed. 
The introductory session will be the gateway to highlighting individual QoL problem areas faced by the participant. Responses from the primary diabetes related QoL questionnaire; the Diabetes Distress Scale (DDS), will be discussed.  Responses from the DDS will form the basis of a problem list.  The problem list will then be used to guide the order in which the participant chooses to address each problem. Discussions around diabetes distress and QoL can be enhanced by use of the Wheel of Life which is a method of encouraging discussion around how diabetes affects the main areas of an individuals life. This approach may assist the PST process by identifying the issues surrounding the problem.
The number of problems discussed will be tailored to each participant. Some problems may need more than one session to solve. Each PST session is expected to last around 45 to 60 minutes and will aim to apply the full problem solving technique (discussed below) to address a single problem area per intervention session. 

Problem Solving Sessions
The basis of PST is guiding the participant through a systematic 7 stage process. Briefly, the 7 stages address the following: (Manual available with complete details).
1.	Selecting and defining the problem
The first step of the PST process is to describe all aspects surrounding the problem such as the when, where, how the problem occurs.
2.	Set realistic goals
The second step is to set a goal orientated around the way the participant would like to see the problem change.  
3.	Brainstorming
Brainstorming involves encouraging the participant to think about as many possible and differing solutions to the problem.
4.	Pros and Cons
The participant is facilitated to consider the pros (advantages) and cons (disadvantages) for each possible solution that is reported.  This process involves considering the impact of potential obstacles and barriers to achieving solutions, for example the influence of time, money and family support.
5.	Choose the most feasible solution
The participant is facilitated to choose the most appropriate and appealing solution/s to the problem.
6.	Determine a plan of action
Once a solution/s is selected, a plan entailing all the individual steps to achieving the solution is constructed with the participant.  This includes the who, what, when and how details in carrying out a series of actions leading to resolving the problem.  For example, what specifically needs to done, how frequently, how often and how practices can be weaved into the participants routines and lifestyle.
7.	Evaluate the outcome at next visit
A review of a participants adoption of problem solving techniques and skills is required at this step.  This is combined with consideration of how PST has worked for individual problems and whether ongoing attention is required in certain areas, whether this be related to the actual problem itself or in the action plan surrounding goal setting, needs refinement.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to this arm will be followed at the Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital pragmatically and has the same face to face follow ups as the intervention group. They have access to the internal diabetes educator as deemed appropriate by their treating Ophthalmologist (= usual care).  

All participants will be questioned, using a check list, at each follow up regarding any potential factors that may influence their diabetes control in-between assessments such as changes in medication/s, number of sick days, negative life events and periods of medication non-adherence.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes Distress Scale (DDS)
This is a 17 item questionnaire that assesses diabetes related emotional distress across 4 domains; emotional burden, physician, regimen and interpersonal related. Developed from the PAID and QSD-R
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, and 3 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)
This 9 item questionnaire is useful for screening, monitoring and measuring the severity of depression. It is responsive to change and is quick to conduct.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, and 3 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social-Problem Solving Inventory  Revised (SPSI-R)
The SPSI-R short version consists of 25 questions.  It is based on a five-dimensional model of problem solving and provides five scales. Two of the scales measure problem orientation dimensions: positive problem orientation (PO) and negative problem orientation (NO). The remaining three scales are considered problem solving skills scales. These include rational problem solving (RP), impulsivity/carelessness style (IC) and avoidance style (AS). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, and 3 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Summary of Diabetes Self Care Activities - SDSCA
The 11 item version questions participants about the frequency of self-care activities within the preceding 7 days (0-7) and covers 5 domains; diet, blood glucose testing, exercise, foot care and smoking. Scoring is based on the number of days the self-care behaviour was enacted. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, and 3 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>RetBANK - This is a short-form questionnaire adapted from a comprehensive item bank specifically developed to identify quality of life issues for people with diabetic retinopathy across 9 domains. For this study we will be using a select number of items from 5 domains; activity limitation/mobility (21 items), health concerns (12 items), social (12 items), convenience (10 items) and economic (5 items), an optional domain if the participant is working. Items for each domain were carefully selected according to their content and to ensure that the spectrum of difficulty was represented.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, and 3 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Diabetes Quality of Life - Brief clinical inventory (DQL) -
The DQL is based on the Diabetes Quality of Life (DQOL) and has been used in both people with type 1 and 2 diabetes. It features 15 items that cover general diabetes specific QOL areas across 4 domains; impact of treatment, worry about future effects of diabetes, satisfaction with treatment and worry about social/vocational issues.  A total score, sum of scores for each item, produces an overall score with the higher the number representing the more positively rated QOL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, and 3 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Haemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) - which equates to the average blood glucose measure over the previous 3 months, derived from a blood sample after overnight fasting</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, and 3 and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Type 2 diabetes  on oral medication and/or insulin 
*Evidence of diabetic retinopathy
*Self-reported difficulties on the Diabetes Distress Scale (an overall score greater than or equal to 3 indicates distress)
*English speaking 
*Able to give written informed consent
*No cognitive impairment as measured by the 6CIT 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Type 1 diabetes
*No evidence of diabetic retinopathy
*Self-reported difficulties on the Diabetes Distress Scale (overall score &lt;2.0
*Non-English speaking 
*Unable to give written informed consent
*Cognitive impairment as measured by the 6CIT 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/11/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>27/02/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Eye Research Australia (Department of Ophthalmology, The University of Melbourne)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1
32 Gisborne St
East Melbourne VIC 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 11 Lancaster Place
Canberra Airport ACT 2609
AUSTRALIA </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To our knowledge there have been no studies examining problem-solving therapy (PST) specifically in people with diabetic retinopathy (DR), yet from our first study we established that this group face the greatest risk of depression and reduced quality of life (QoL) as well as showing poorer diabetic control compared to those without DR.  PST has been shown to be an essential skill for effective diabetes management and effective in reducing diabetes related emotional distress and depressive symptoms. However there is a need for more research that integrates problem-focused and emotion focused interventions in diabetes management. 
Addressing diabetes specific distress, stress management and healthy coping, some of the key underlying subjective QoL experiences, may improve glycaemic outcomes.  This study also would provide novel research specific to those that have ophthalmological diabetic complications. We propose to adopt a PST designed for primary care that teaches problem solving skills and assists individuals with DR to find practical solutions to vision-related and diabetes-related problems.  In doing so we anticipate that participants will adopt a more positive problem solving orientation that will hopefully empower them to subsequently improve their psychological well-being.  It has been previously established that developing a problem solving pattern and working through individual solutions assists with perpetuating more positive behavioural habit loops.  As a result, this intervention may also have knock on effects in improving diabetes self-management behaviours as this has been shown in previous studies. 

Hypothesis 
Individuals with diabetic retinopathy who receive tailored problem solving training will show improved quality of life and psychological well-being compared to individuals undergoing usual care.

Aim 1:  To develop a tailored, problem solving based program that targets individual quality of life difficulties. 

Aim 2: To assess, using a randomised control trial, the effectiveness of this program in improving participants quality of life and psychological well-being (reducing diabetes related distress and depressive symptoms).
Investigation will also be undertaken to assess whether enhancing problem solving skills have a direct influence on a participants ability to self-manage their diabetes including improving overall glycaemic control and adopting recommended lifestyle practices.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital Human Research &amp; Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>32 Gisborne St
East Melbourne VIC 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/815H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ecosse Lamoureux</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia
Department of Ophthalmology - The University of Melbourne
Level 1 Peter Howson Wing
32 Gisborne St
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9929 8067 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9929 8030 </fax>
      <email>ecosse@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gwyn Rees</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia
Department of Ophthalmology - The University of Melbourne
Level 1 Peter Howson Wing
32 Gisborne St
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9929 8048</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9929 8030 </fax>
      <email>grees@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gwyn Rees</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia
Department of Ophthalmology - The University of Melbourne
Level 1 Peter Howson Wing
32 Gisborne St
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9929 8048</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9929 8030 </fax>
      <email>grees@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Marian Saeed</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia
Department of Ophthalmology - The University of Melbourne
Level 1 Peter Howson Wing
32 Gisborne St
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9929 8161 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9929 8030 </fax>
      <email>marian.saeed@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>