<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320950">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/12/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001082291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Shyness 7: Self-guided Internet based education for social phobia with or without motivational strategies. A randomized controlled study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial of self-guided Internet based education for social phobia comparing motivational strategies vs. no motivational strategies on severity of symptoms of social phobia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Social phobia (an anxiety disorder)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two groups: 1) Self-guided Internet based education for social phobia with written exercises to promote motivation (motivational strategies) with automatic email reminders, or; 2) Self-guided Internet based education for social phobia with automatic email reminders. All participants will meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for social phobia. All participants will complete 8 lessons of Internet based education about management of symptoms of anxiety and social phobia. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with social phobia, taking a further 20 minutes per summary. Participants in Group 1 will receive weekly reminder emails and will have access to written exercises to promote their motivation to continue with the program. Participants in group 2 will receive weekly reminder emails. The duration of the program is 10 weeks, but participants will be contacted 3 months post program and asked to complete follow-up questionnaires. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 3-months post-education. These will take about 20 minutes to complete. The educational materials are based on the Shyness Program, which applies cognitive behavioural techniques.</interventions>
    <comparator>Internet based education for social phobia with automatic reminder emails.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social phobia is measured by the Social Phobia Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-education, post-education, and at 3-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social phobia is measured by the Social Interaction Anxiety Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-education, post-education, and at 3-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 3-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured by the Kessler-10 (K-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-education, post-education, and at 3-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability is measured by the Sheehan Disability Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 3-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet DSM-IV criteria for social phobia - Internet access + printer access. - Australian citizen- Males and females.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current substance abuse/dependence- Psychotic disorder- Current or planned psychological treatment during study duration- Change in medications during last 1 month or intended change during study duration.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply on line, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via structured diagnostic interview (MINI 5.0.0). Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study. Allocation concealment will occur by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is off-site.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation list will be generated prior to the study using computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/09/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/11/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/11/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>110</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>110</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales at St Vincent's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales at St Vincent's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is part of a research program examining the efficacy of Internet based education and treatment programs for people with social phobia and other commmon mental disorders. This project compares the effectiveness of simple written motivational strategies at encouraging people with social phobia to complete the 8 lessons in the Program. We expect that people who receive the motivational exercises (in addition to weekly reminder emails) will complete more lessons and report greater benefit from the program than participants who do not receive access to the motivational strategies, but do receive email reminders.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.virtualclinic.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Titov N, Andrews G, Johnston J, Schwencke G, Choi I. The Shyness program: Longer term benefits, cost-effectiveness, and acceptability. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2009;43:36-44. 
Titov N, Andrews G, Choi I, Schwencke G, Mahoney J. Shyness 3: An RCT of guided versus unguided Internet based CBT for social phobia. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2008;42:1030-1040. 
Titov N, Andrews G, Schwencke G. Shyness 2: A replication of Shyness 1. Are the results reliable, and who benefits? Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2008;42:595-605. 
Titov N, Andrews G, Schwencke G, Drobny J, Einstein D. Shyness 1: Distance treatment for social over the Internet. A randomized controlled trial. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2008;42:585-594. 
Titov N, Andrews G, Choi I, Schwencke G, Johnston J. Internet-based cognitive behavior therapy for social phobia without clinical input is effective: a pragmatic RCT of two types of reminders. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2009;43:913-919.

Titov N, Gibson M, Andrews G, McEvoy P. Internet treatment for social phobia reduces comorbidity. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2009;43:754-759.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales (UNSW) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Kensington Campus NSW2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC09151</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C/- Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety Disorders (CRUfAD) UNSW 299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83821732</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83821721</fax>
      <email>nickt@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C/- Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety Disorders (CRUfAD) UNSW 299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83821732</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83821721</fax>
      <email>nickt@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C/- Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety Disorders (CRUfAD) UNSW 299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83821732</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83821721</fax>
      <email>nickt@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nick Titov</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>