<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335629">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000510044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot Trial of an Internet Intervention for Depressive Symptoms: OnTrack Depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A preliminary evaluation of the efficacy of an integrated internet-based treatment vs a brief internet-based treatment for depression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>5 modules of integrated treatment.
a) all modules are internet-based.
b) each module can be done at the client's own pace. they could be completed in one sitting (approximately an hour each) but it is recommended that the client pace themselves and complete the modules on a weekly basis.
c) the overall length of the intervention is 3 months because participants are prompted via email to check in weekly for 3 months to complete mood monitoring (online rating of best and worst mood for day which takes approximately 1 minutes to complete) while they continue to implement changes instigated by the modules.
d) general topics in the 5 modules are 1) identifying and planning for triggers and early warning signs of depression 2) mindfulness and behavioural activation 3) problem-solving and cognitive-behavioural therapy (CBT) and continuing mindfulness 4) building relationships and conflict resolution and continuing mindfulness 5) reviewing personal changes, goal setting for the future, and continuing mindfulness.</interventions>
    <comparator>Brief intervention only: 1 module of identifying and planning for triggers and early warning signs of depression.
a) the module is internet-based.
b) the module can be done at the client's own pace, but it could be completed in one sitting (approximately an hour).
c) the overall length of the intervention is 3 months because participants are prompted via email to check in weekly for 3 months to complete mood monitoring (online rating of best and worst mood for day which takes approximately 1 minutes to complete) while they continue to implement changes instigated by the module.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressed mood - measured by the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale - 21 (DASS-21) and daily worst mood ratings.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 3 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether depression outcomes from internet treatment are moderated by treatment expectancy (measured on a scale of 1-100), number of modules accessed or tools completed, or use of mindfulness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment expectancy at baseline.
Module access and completion at 3 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether depression outcomes from internet treatment are predicted by previous major depressive episodes (e.g. 0, 1-2, 3 or more), or quality of life (measured by World Health Organization Quality of Life - Brief Form [WHOQOL-BREF]).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-IV (DSM-IV) criteria for a lifetime major depressive episode and/or score at least 14 on the Depression scale of the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (e.g., 'moderate' depression)
4) sufficient english to complete treatments and assessments without translation
5) able and willing to access internet/email/text messages</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) reported weekly alcohol consumption in the last month of more than 14 units/week for 2 weeks for females and more than 28 units/week for 2 weeks for males 2) use of injectable drugs in the previous month 3) daily use of an illicit substance 4) history of psychosis lasting more than 2 days 5) diagnosis of bipolar disorder 6) acutely suicidal 7) self harm requiring medical treatment in last 12 months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>participants will view www.ontrack.org.au  in response to a referral or advertising and will register to receive a screening call. During the call they are given information about the research. If they are interested in participating the screening information sheet is read over the phone and the participant provides verbal consent for screening. If they meet screening eligibility requirements they are sent an email link that takes them to the consent form and online assessment questionnaires. Following this they receive a baseline assessment phone call and complete 7 days of daily worst mood ratings. Once all baseline assessments are completed they are randomly allocated to one of 2 treatment groups and provided with a username and password to access the online program. The person conducting the baseline assessments will have no way of knowing which treatment group the client will be allocated to as it is randomly generated by the computer program.</concealment>
    <sequence>simple randomisation - computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/02/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>60 Musk Ave, Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychology &amp; Counselling, Queensland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, O Block, B Wing,
QUT Kelvin Grove Campus, 
Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove, 
Queensland, Australia, 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor David Kavanagh</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation,
60 Musk Ave,
 Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study is a randomised controlled trial aiming to test the preliminary efficacy of an internet-based intervention for people with depressive symptoms. There will be 2 groups of randomly allocated participants who will be followed up after 3 months of an online program: 1. Brief Intervention Group  will be an active control condition providing a minimum, ethically feasible treatment including Psychoeducation on depression, a Personal Diary for recording mood, and tools for detecting and planning for triggers and early warning signs of depression. 2. 5 Module Treatment Group  will include the components of the Brief Intervention Group as well as specific modules involving Mindfulness Meditation, Social support/relationships, Problem Solving and CBT strategies, Pleasant Activity Scheduling, and reviewing personal changes and making future goals. Primary predictions are that the 5 Module Treatment group will have superior depression outcomes at 3 months compared to the Brief Intervention group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ontrack.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Unit
Level 4,
88 Musk Avenue,
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1000000040</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Kavanagh</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave, 
Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31386143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ontrack@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Kavanagh</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave, 
Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31386143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ontrack@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Kavanagh</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation 60 Musk Ave, Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31386143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.kavanagh@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>