<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364109">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000642785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of footwear on running performance and injury risk</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In distance runners, do lightweight running shoes, compared to standard running shoes, improve running performance and reduce risk of injury?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Running-related injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A lightweight running shoe with minimal cushioning and reduced heel lift will be the intervention in this study. The total duration of the study intervention is 26 weeks. This will consist of an initial 20 week transition period where partipants allocated to the intervention group will gradually switch from running in their previous shoe to the lightweight shoe with minimal cushioning and a reduced heel lift. In the first week following allocation this will consist of using the lightweight running shoe with minimal cushioning and reduced heel lift for 5% of the total running performed for that week. This duration will increase by a further 5% each week so that in week 20 participants will be performing 100% of their running in the lightweight running shoe with minimal cushioning and a reduced heel lift. Weeks 21-26 will involve all running in the lightweight running shoe with minimal cushioning and a reduced heel lift. 

Adherence to this intervention protocol will be monitored in a study diary that participants will be required to fill out daily. </interventions>
    <comparator>A standard cushioned running shoe with a built-up heel will be the control treatment. The cushioned shoe will be gradually introduced over the first 20 weeks in the same manner described for the intervention shoe. And weeks 21-26 will involve all running in the cushioned running shoe with a built-up heel. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5 km time trial performance</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks following randomisation to treatment group. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Injury incidence: a participant will be considered injured for the entire duration of each week that they answer yes to the question in the previous seven days have you experienced an injury that has required the use of medication, a visit to a health professional or a reduction in running speed, distance or duration? This will be followed by questions exploring the cause and medical diagnosis. Assessment will be undertaken by participants in a study diary and will occur on a weekly basis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks following randomisation to treatment group. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Running economy measured during sub-maximal treadmill running and determined from the expired gases collected by a Hans-Rudolph two-way non-return breathing valve that will be connected to a ParvoMedics gas analysis system. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks following randomisation to treatment group. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Running biomechanics assessed during overground running trials. Running kinematics will be measured using a 12 camera VICON MX F20 system. Running kinematics will be measured using four force platforms aligned in series. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks following randomisation to treatment group. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric, concentric and eccentric calf muscle strength measured using a Biodex isokinetic dynamometer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks following randomisation to treatment group. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bone mineral density at the proximal tibia, calcaneus and metatarsals measured using a Lunar Prodigy dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry scanner.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks following randomisation to treatment group. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Run a minimum of 15 km per week.
5 km time trial performance less than 23 minutes.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous history of running in a lightweight running shoe with minimal cushioning and reduced heel lift.
Run with a midfoot or forefoot footfall.
Previous history of orthotic use with running shoes in the previous 3 months.
Previous history of muculoskeletal injury that affected running within the previous 3 months.
Previous history of invasive surgery that affected running within the previous 12 months. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited via public advertisement at local running clubs, fitness centres and running events. Participants who meet the eligibility criteria will be required to provide written informed consent prior to enrolment. 

Allocation to treatment will be performed by an independent investigator who is not involved in data collection and is located in a seperate area of the building. </concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation via minimisation using 5 km time trial time recorded at a familiarisation visit as the minimisation variable. </sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation was based on detecting a Cohen's d effect size of 0.3 for the primary outcome of 5km running performance using an analysis of covariance. This calculation was performed using the formula described by Borm et al. (2007) and an estimation of the correlation between 5km performance measured at baseline and at follow-up that was obtained from South Australian 5km road race results in 2011 and 2012 (Athletics SA 2012). The Cohen's d effect size of 0.3 was based on previous research that has investigated differences in running economy between lightweight and standard running shoes (Warne et al. 2013; Perl et al. 2012; Squadrone et al. 2009; Divert et al. 2008; Hamill et al. 1988)

Borm GF, Fransen J, Lemmens WAJG. A simple sample size formula for analysis of covariance in randomized clinical trials. J Clin Epidemiol. 2007;60:1234-8. 
Athletics South Australia 2012, viewed 1st October 2012, http://www.athleticssa.com.au/wp/wordpress/?page_id=408
Warne JP, Warrington GD. Four-week habituation to simulated barefoot running improves running economy when compared with shod running. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2013; doi:10.1111/sms.12032
Perl DP, Daoud AI, Lieberman DE. Effects of footwear and strike type on running economy. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2012;44:1335-1343.
Squadrone R, Gallozzi C. Biomechanical and physiological comparison of barefoot and two shod conditions in experienced barefoot runners. J Sports Med Phys Fitness. 2009;49:6-13. 
Divert C, Mornieux G, Freychat P, et al. Barefoot-shod running differences: shoe or mass effect? Int J Sports Med. 2008;29:512-8. 
Hamill J, Freedson PS, Boda W, et al. Effects of shoe type on cardiorespiratory responses and rearfoot motion during treadmill running. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 1988;20:515-521. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>9/10/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>76</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>61</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>City East Campus, Frome Rd, Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is currently no scientific evidence concerning the direct effect of running shoes on running performance and prevention of injury. It has been suggested that excessive cushioning in running shoes may have had the unintended effect of weakening the foot and altering the way that people run. Lightweight running shoes with minimal cushioning and reduced heel lift have been shown to increase muscle strength and cause potentially beneficial changes to the way that we run. Lightweight running shoes may be of benefit to runners wanting to improve running performance and prevent injury. The aim of this project is to investigate the long term effects of running shoes on running performance and prevention of injury.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Fuller JT, Thewlis D, Tsiros MD, Brown NAT, Buckley JD. The long-term effect of minimalist shoes on running performance and injury: design of a randomised controlled trial. BMJ Open 2015;5:e008307. 

Fuller JT, Archer J, Buckley JD, Tsiros MD, Thewlis D. The reliability of dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry measurements of bone mineral density in the metatarsals. Skeletal Radiol. 2015 [Epub ahead of print] DOI: 10.1007/s00256-015-2227-0.

Fuller JT, Thewlis D, Tsiros MD, Brown N &amp; Buckley JD. Training in a minimalist shoe increases ankle joint loading and 5km running performance. 20th European College of Sports Science Congress, Malmo, Sweden, June 2015. 

Fuller JT, Thewlis D, Tsiros MD, Brown N &amp; Buckley JD. Training in a minimalist shoe improves running performance in trained distance runners. ASICS Sports Medicine Australia Conference, Gold Coast, Queensland, October 2015. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>General Purpose Building, Mawson Lakes Campus Mawson Lakes Boulevard Mawson Lakes, SA 5095</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>31065</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joel Thomas Fuller</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
City East Campus
Frome Rd Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 (08) 8302 1315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fuljt001@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joel Thomas Fuller</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
City East Campus
Frome Rd Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 (08) 8302 1315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fuljt001@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joel Thomas Fuller</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
City East Campus
Frome Rd Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 (08) 8302 1315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fuljt001@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>