<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336618">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000965909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of a parenting intervention for promoting positive home learning environments and learning outcomes for children in disadvantaged families: the Early Home Learning Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of group-based and group plus home-based parenting interventions for promoting positive home learning environments and learning outcomes for children in disadvantaged families</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EHLS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>parenting confidence and self care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>early child development (emergent literacy)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention (smalltalk program) is based on an evidence based model which comprises of two child-focused domains (Quality Everyday Interactions and Stimulating Environment) and two parent-focused domains (Parent Self-Care and Parent Confidence). It also includes a fifth domain, Community Connectedness. The smalltalk program seeks to build on existing parenting strengths and target specific parenting skills known to promote child language and learning. It incorporates strategies that assist parents to adequately meet their own needs as a person and a parent.

The intervention is embedded in two existing service platforms  Maternal and Child Health (MCH) parent groups for children aged 6 to 12 months and Supported Playgroups (SPG) for children aged 1 to 3 years. The intervention is delivered across two levels of intensity  lower intensity: a supported playgroup or parenting group that includes smalltalk parenting strategies and higher intensity: a supported playgroup or parenting group that includes smalltalk parenting strategies plus individual coaching of families in their home.  
In the SPG platform: the lower intensity program involves 1 x 2 hour group session per week over a period of 10 weeks; and the higher intensity program involves 1 x 2 hour group session per week over a period of 10 weeks, plus 1 x 1 1/2 hour home coaching visit fortnightly (total of 6 visits).
In the MCH platform: the lower intensity program involves 1 x 2 hour group session per week over a period of 6 weeks; and the higher intensity program involves 1 x 2 hour group session per week over a period of 6 weeks, plus 1 x 1 1/2 hour home coaching visit fortnightly (total of 6 visits).</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator group is a usual care or standard supported playgroup or parent group that does not include any smalltalk parenting content. 
The groups run for 2 hours each week for a period of 10 weeks in the SPG platform and 6 weeks in the MCH platform.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent outcomes: Enhanced parent confidence and self-care (Self-efficacy; Kessler psychological screener; PANAS positive affect scale; SF-12; Coping), parent relational skills (Warmth and Hostile parenting; Infant Growth and Development Indices - IPCI) and teaching (Infant Growth and Development Indices - IPCI) skills.
These constructs will be measured through questionnaires (self report) and in-home observation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The time points of data collection for all conditions (standard, lower intensity and higher intensity) are T1 = Baseline (before group commencement), T2 = Post (after the last group session) and T3 = Follow up (5 months after group). 
Note. The SF-12 will only be administered at T1 and T3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Home learning environment outcomes: Improved parent activities with their child (Eg. Parent reads books to child), parent verbal responsivity (Eg. Parent plays rhyming games with child), home literacy environment (Eg. Literacy exposure). Decreased household chaos (Environmental chaos in the home scale).
These constructs will be measured through questionnaires (self report).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The time points of data collection for all conditions (standard, lower intensity and higher intensity) are T1 = Baseline (before group commencement), T2 = Post (after the last group session) and T3 = Follow up (5 months after group).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child outcomes: Enhanced child language and emergent literacy. Expressive and receptive communication was assessed using the following: Ages and Stages Questionnaire: 3rd Ed. - Communication sub-scale; Communicative Development Index: SF; Infant Growth and Development Indices - ECI.
These constructs will be measured through questionnaires (parent self report) and in-home observation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The time points of data collection for all conditions (standard, lower intensity and higher intensity) are T1 = Baseline (before group commencement), T2 = Post (after the last group session) and T3 = Follow up (5 months after group).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child outcomes: Enhanced child socio-emotional wellbeing and general development. These outcomes were assessed using 4 behavioural difficulty items from the NEILS study; Ages and Stages Questionnaire: 3rd Ed. - Fine motor and Personal-social sub-scales; Infant Growth and Development Indices - IPCI).
These constructs will be measured through questionnaires (parent self report) and in-home observation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The time points of data collection for all conditions (standard, lower intensity and higher intensity) are T1 = Baseline (before group commencement), T2 = Post (after the last group session) and T3 = Follow up (5 months after group).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Service outcomes: Enhanced capacity of existing child and family services. This was assessed though a number of items related to use of health and support services (Eg. MCH) and impact of service use on work and regular routine.
These constructs will be measured through questionnaires (parent self report).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The time points of data collection for all conditions (standard, lower intensity and higher intensity) are T1 = Baseline (before group commencement) and T3 = Follow up (5 months after group).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible to participate, parents/carers must meet the following essential criteria:
- At least one child in the age range of their assigned treatment group: MCH platform  6 to 12 months at group commencement; or SPG platform - 1 year to 3 years at group commencement.
- Ability to speak and understand basic spoken English

In addition to the above criteria, parents/carers may also be eligible if they meet one of the following (optional) criteria:
- single parent families
- indigenous families
- health care card
- young parent families (&lt;25 years of age)
- socially isolated
- very low income
- culturally and linguistically diverse backgrounds
- concern as indicated by PEDS</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>36</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Families will not be eligible to participate if:
- The parent/carer does not speak English.
- The parent/carer those would benefit from other services (Eg. High level intervention from child protection or other)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment
Regardless of whether they are eligible for the maternal and child health platform or the supported playgroup platform, participants will be identified via MCH services or community referrals in their local government area (LGA). A rolling recruitment strategy will be applied.
The MCH representative or community service organisation (CSO) will briefly introduce the study to the family. If willing, the MCH representative or CSO will obtain verbal consent from the family and pass their details onto the LGA’s Site Coordinator. The Site Coordinator will contact the family, explain the study in more detail, obtain verbal consent and mail out a Participant Information and Consent form. When the researcher visits the family’s home for the first home assessment, they will ask the family to provide their written consent.  

Allocation concealment:
A computer program designed by Dr Ukoumunne from the MCRI will be used to ensure the appropriate randomisation occurs. This will be conducted independently by Dr Ukoummune (or staff member) for this process.
As the unit of randomisation is the locality, concealment occurs at the level of locality. Sites and localities will be randomised and informed of the outcome of the randomisation, after they have given full consent to participation in the trial. As individual participants are recruited to programs (conditions) offered by their nearest service, they will not be blinded to allocation at recruitment.</concealment>
    <sequence>This study employs a stratified, blocked, cluster randomised design. Individual participants are clustered according to the geographical location of their nearest service (the locality identified for participation in the research), with localities randomised within strata to one of three intervention conditions (condition 1 = usual care group; condition 2 = group with smalltalk parenting strategies; condition 3 = group with smalltalk parenting strategies plus home coaching). Each locality will be assigned 1 program variant (condition), i.e. the locality is the unit of randomisation. Stratification is used to ensure that conditions are randomised in a blocked design, to provide at least one program for each condition within each site (LGA or combination of LGAs).
As there are three conditions, randomisation occurs in blocks of three localities, as follows:
1)	Each site (LGA or combined LGA) will provide the study team with the finalised list of localities available to conduct programs. Localities in each site (LGA) will be stratified into blocks of three. Where the number of localities within a site is a not multiple of three (e.g. 4, 5, 7 or 8 localities), the first 3 (or 6) localities will be put in the within-site blocks. The remainder will be placed in a ‘pool’ to create cross-site blocks with the ‘left-over’ localities from other sites. 
2)	Within-in site blocks will be randomised in a balanced design: 1 locality in each block will be randomised to conditions 1, 2 and 3. 
3)	Localities in the cross-site pool will be allocated into blocks of three, with the ‘left-over’ localities from the same site, allocated to the same block (thereby ensuring that these localities by nature of their block allocation, will be randomised to different conditions). Localities in each cross-site block, will then be randomised in a balanced design to conditions 1, 2 and 3.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3020</postcode>
    <postcode>3036</postcode>
    <postcode>3042</postcode>
    <postcode>3810</postcode>
    <postcode>3250</postcode>
    <postcode>3233</postcode>
    <postcode>3260</postcode>
    <postcode>3072</postcode>
    <postcode>3070</postcode>
    <postcode>3073</postcode>
    <postcode>3199</postcode>
    <postcode>3198</postcode>
    <postcode>3910</postcode>
    <postcode>3552</postcode>
    <postcode>3523</postcode>
    <postcode>3758</postcode>
    <postcode>3175</postcode>
    <postcode>3173</postcode>
    <postcode>3171</postcode>
    <postcode>3172</postcode>
    <postcode>3174</postcode>
    <postcode>3018</postcode>
    <postcode>3016</postcode>
    <postcode>3194</postcode>
    <postcode>3192</postcode>
    <postcode>3196</postcode>
    <postcode>3152</postcode>
    <postcode>3178</postcode>
    <postcode>3337</postcode>
    <postcode>3338</postcode>
    <postcode>3023</postcode>
    <postcode>3939</postcode>
    <postcode>3931</postcode>
    <postcode>3915</postcode>
    <postcode>3912</postcode>
    <postcode>3689</postcode>
    <postcode>3690</postcode>
    <postcode>3691</postcode>
    <postcode>3030</postcode>
    <postcode>3029</postcode>
    <postcode>3140</postcode>
    <postcode>3793</postcode>
    <postcode>3158</postcode>
    <postcode>3777</postcode>
    <postcode>3797</postcode>
    <postcode>3805</postcode>
    <postcode>3632</postcode>
    <postcode>3220</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Parenting Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5/232 Victoria Parade
East Melbourne, 3002
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Education and Early Childhood Development</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2 Treasury Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Jan Nicholson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Murdoch Children's Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital, Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Donna Berthelsen</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Queensland University of Technology
B Block Level 4, Queensland University of Technology
412 Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is strong evidence that parents and the home learning environment are the most influential forces in shaping childrens early learning. The literature has shown family focused interventions can improve the quality of home learning environments for young children. In addition, interventions that support families to facilitate their childrens learning also enable parents to be more knowledgeable and confident in their own abilities to meet their parenting responsibilities.
The purpose of this study is to develop and evaluate an evidence-based parenting program to support parents to provide an enriched home learning environment for their very young children that enhances childrens development in the first three years of life. 
This will be achieved through the development of a parenting program this is embedded into existing service platforms  supported playgroups and maternal and child health parent groups.  The smalltalk program aims to build on existing parenting strengths and targets specific parenting skills that are known to promote child language and learning, such as quality interactions, reading at home, and play, in addition to strategies to promote parental self-care.  
The program will be delivered across two levels of intensity (intervention): lower intensity - a supported playgroup or parenting group that includes smalltalk parenting strategies and higher intensity - a supported playgroup or parenting group that includes smalltalk parenting strategies plus individual coaching of families in their home. The comparator group is a usual care supported playgroup or parent group that does not include any smalltalk parenting content.
All families will be assessed at three time points: T1 = Baseline (before group commencement), T2 = Post (after the last group session) and T3 = Follow up (5 months after group). Each assessment will involve both a telephone interview and an in-home observation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.earlyhomelearningstudy.net.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>50 Lonsdale St
Melbourne VIC 3000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>8/10/2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Naomi Hackworth</name>
      <address>Parenting Research Centre
5/232 Victoria Parade
East Melbourne, 3002
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8660 3581</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8660 3599</fax>
      <email>nhackworth@parentingrc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Naomi Hackworth</name>
      <address>Parenting Research Centre
5/232 Victoria Parade
East Melbourne, 3002
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8660 3581</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8660 3599</fax>
      <email>nhackworth@parentingrc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>