<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366740">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000934640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Telemedicine for Insulin Treated Gestational Diabetes Mellitus (TeleGDM)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of Telemedicine plus Usual Care for Insulin Treated Women with Gestational Diabetes Mellitus (TeleGDM): An Exploratory Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial and Qualitative Evaluation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1159-4007</utrn>
    <trialacronym>TeleGDM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Telemedicine (Intervention)
Telemedicine will be an add-on (adjunct) to usual care and TeleGDM will refer to Telemedicine plus usual care. The duration of the intervention will be from enrollment until delivery of the baby. 

Women recruited to this arm will continue monitoring their BGL, insulin dosing and symptoms according to diabetes education and counseling advice. The difference to usual care alone is that the women in the TeleGDM arm will upload their BGL via a USB cable connection of the glucometer to the computer, and manually enter insulin, dietary/meal information and symptoms data to an online personal health record (PHR). Four BGL readings a day (one preprandial, and three postprandial (breakfast, lunch, dinner) readings) are expected as per usual care. The PHR is set up with every second day automatic reminder to upload data. In addition a Credentialed Diabetes Educator Registered Nurse  (CDE-RN) can message the patients if data are not uploaded as expected.

When new data are upload an alert email is automatically sent to the CDE-RN, who in turn reviews the data, coordinates care with the other GDM clinic team members and provides feedback and/or care advice to the patients via the PHR (email) messaging and SMS system. This approach reduces the need for clinicians to wait for patients to bring data on paper diary to their scheduled appointment at a later time, usually 1-2weeks. That is, the TeleGDM approach will provide the ability for a timely response and action in order to deliver individually tailored GDM management in response to the patients needs. It is expected clinicians will still schedule face-to-face appointment as usual and recall patients as they normally would based on their clinical decision making. </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment (Usual Care)
Usual care is as described above with the exception of telemedicine. Under usual care patients record self monitoring data on a paper diary which they bring to their scheduled clinic appointment. Care advice or change to treatment plans may be given during the appointment or via telephone.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient service utilisation: Assessed as a composite of scheduled face-to-face consultations, unscheduled face-to-face consultations, and telephone consultations

GDM consultation encounters data will be collated from hospital medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to baby delivery. 

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic control. This will be assessed using BGL data. For women in the intervention group BGL data will be obtained from readings they upload to personal health record (Telemedicine system). BGL data for women in the usual care arm will be obtained from their paper based diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to baby delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Macrosomia assessed using foetal ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>2nd and 3rd trimester</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes self efficacy using the Diabetes self Empowerment Scale Short Form (DES-SF) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Study enrollment and at 6 weeks from study entry.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction assessed using the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire (CSQ-8). </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks from study entry.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinician satisfaction using the Canada Health Infoway System And Use Assessment Survey questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months from study commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Service provision costs. This will be estimated from billable service provision per care episode and will be obtained from hospital administrative data and subscription to use the online personal health record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collated at participant's completion of study activities at delivery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Technology capability and capacity assessed a composite of measures of volume of system usage: login encounters, frequency of data uploads, volume of messages between patients and clinicians over the system, volume of technical glitches or queries. 

The data will be collated from the online personal health record logs.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of study activities (delivery by the last enrolled woman, approximately 12 months from the start of recruitment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of neonate admissions to special care nursery. Information will be obtained from hospital medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baby delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type of delivery (normal vaginal delivery, caesarean delivery or instrument deliveries). Data will be collated form medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baby delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin adjustments assessed as the frequency of insulin adjustments and the number of days between adjustments and information will be collated form medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From enrollment to baby delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Large for gestational age (LGA) assessed as weight greater than 90th percentile. Weight will be obtained from medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baby delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>IADPSG criteria based clinical diagnosis of GDM confirmed by OGTT

24-33 weeks of gestation or earlier diagnosis if in high risk group

Management of hyperglycaemia with insulin and no more than 35 weeks gestation.

Smartphone/tablet with internet access and/or internet connected personal computer

Not requiring an interpreter to navigate through the health care system</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Adequate blood glucose control without insulin

Other pre-existing (pre-pregnancy) diabetes mellitus (T1DM or T2DM) or glucose intolerance.

Currently taking or took corticosteroids in the previous 3months.

Require an interpreter to navigate the healthcare system.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The GDM clinicians, primarily the credentialed diabetes educators will identify eligible patient participants and notify them of the study. The CDE-RNs then direct the prospective participants to the lead member of the researcher team. This member will conduct screening, provide detailed briefing about the project and seek informed consent from eligible prospective participants.

Following informed consent, a participant is then randomly allocated the study arm/group (TeleGDM or Usual Care) by revealing this from a concealed envelope.

</concealment>
    <sequence>A stratified randomisation list of TeleGDM and Usual Care will be generated by a statistician who is independent of the study. The list will be generated using Stata 13 statistical analysis software. The strata will be high risk of GDM based on previous history of GDM or any of the known risk factors of GDM.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>In addition to summary descriptive and univariate statistics, TeleGDM will be compared to usual care using the following:

i) Ordinal regression for clinic/service utilisation
ii) Logistic regression for categorical outcomes: caesareans, macrosomia, SCN admission 
iii) Linear regression for continuous variables: glycaemic control, baby birthweight, costs, glycaemic variability (MAGE)
iv) Survival analysis of BGL data: time to glycaemic stability, time to insulin adjustment
v) T-test or non-parametric equivalent: satisfaction surveys scores
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <hospital>Craigieburn Health Service - Craigieburn</hospital>
    <hospital>Broadmeadows Health Service - Broadmeadows</hospital>
    <postcode>3076 - Epping</postcode>
    <postcode>3064 - Craigieburn</postcode>
    <postcode>3047 - Broadmeadows</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>General Practice and Primary Health Care Academic Centre
School of Medicine,The University of Melbourne 
200 Berkeley Street
Carlton VIC 3053</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Northern Health (Small Research Project Grant 2014)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>185 Cooper Street
Epping, Vic 3076</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) is a condition of poor blood sugar control occurring during pregnancy. The poor sugar control is associated with poorer pregnancy outcomes, such as large babies often leading to caesarean deliveries, other pregnancy complications and diabetes in the future. About half of all women with GDM need insulin to control blood sugars. Special care needs to be provided to this group of women which involves intensive and frequent support for insulin management, adding to increased workloads on limited GDM services. Telemedicine is another way that people can be provided with health services while they are away from the hospital. In this approach patients send their heath monitoring information over the mobile phones or internet to healthcare providers who in turn review the information and provide advice to the patients.

This project aims to use telemedicine to support care for women with GDM and it will be carried out at TNH as a major randomised controlled pilot study. Women who agree to be part of this project will monitor their BGL, insulin and symptoms at home. The women will send this information to the hospital via an online system called Online Health Portfolio for review by the GDM care team. If a patient has readings that are outside desired levels, the team at the hospital can then provide advice immediately via text message without the need for the woman to wait for the next hospital appointment. The project will evaluate whether a new new approach (telemedicine) used as part of of usual care, is able to reduce the workload on the GDM service, whether women who receive telemedicine will have better or similar pregnancy outcomes as women who will receive usual care alone and whether telemedicine will result in cost savings.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Northern Hospital
185 Cooper Street
Epping 
Victoria 3076</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PO11/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Tshepo Rasekaba</name>
      <address>General Practice and Primary Health Care Academic Centre
School of Medicine,The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley Street, Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+613 9035 5018</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tshepo.rasekaba@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Tshepo Rasekaba</name>
      <address>Northern Clinical Research Centre (NCRC)
Northern Health

185 Cooper Street 
EPPING VIC 3076</address>
      <phone>+613 8405 8399 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email> tshepo.rasekaba@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Tshepo Rasekaba</name>
      <address>General Practice and Primary Health Care Academic Centre
School of Medicine,The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley Street, Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+613 8405 8399 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tshepo.rasekaba@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>