<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335613">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000496011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A non-invasive way to protect against the stress of surgery for heart disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The protective effect of remote ischaemic preconditioning in congenital heart disease patients undergoing cardiopulmonary bypass surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiopulmonary by-pass surgery-associated ischemia-reperfusion stress in paediatric patients with congenital heart disease.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Remote Ischemic Preconditioning (RIPC) will be instituted by four 5-minute cycles of leg ischemia with intervening 5 minutes of reperfusion immediately following induction of standard anaesthesia in the operating room.  A standard WelchAllen blood pressure cuff is placed on the mid-to upper thigh of the leg which is free of intravenous (i.v.)/arterial lines. Inflating the blood pressure cuff to a pressure exceeding the patients systolic pressure by 30 mmHg will constrict the site to interrupt local blood flow and thus perfusion of the lower leg (i.e. if systolic pressure is 70mmHg then the cuff will be inflated to 100mmHg). The cuff would be deflated to permit reperfusion. Blood flow interruption and restoration will be monitored by standard pulse-oxymetry. RIPC is performed after the patient has been anesthetised while routine central lines are being placed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control (Placebo) patients will have sham placement of cuff without inflation.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The identification of whether the molecular signalling response (proteome and intracellular signal transduction) in blood (plasma and lymphocyte mitochondria) and cardiac mitochondria (resected tissue) that normally occurs in patients undergoing congenital heart surgery with cardiopulmonary by-pass support is altered by RIPC-treatment (highly regulated, non-invasively-induced, localised leg ischaemia (5min) and reperfusion (5min) for 4 cycles) before surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples collected at baseline, and post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours . Myocardial resected tissue, intraoperatively.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The total doses of inotropic, chronotropic, and afterload reducing agents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours .</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial blood gases measured from blood samples by blood gas machine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples collected at baseline, and post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours .</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean systemic arterial, and right atrial pressures via in-line catheters and pressure transducers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 12, and 24 hours after aortic cross clamp release.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum glucose measured by hospital pathology biochemical assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples collected at baseline, and post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative serum electrolytes measured by hospital pathology biochemical assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples collected at baseline, and post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative serum arterial lactate measured by hospital pathology biochemical assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples collected at baseline, and post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative blood urea nitrogen measured by hospital pathology biochemical assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples collected at baseline, and post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative creatinine measured by hospital pathology biochemical assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples collected at baseline, and post-operatively at 3, 6, 12, 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative fluid balance (i.e. recorded total volume and type of fluid intake, urine output, and chest tube drainage).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from day of operation until discharge from hospital (generally after 10-12 days).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ventilator rates and pressures recorded for estimates of lung function and compliance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From day of operation until extubation of ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative total hours of mechanical respirator ventilation required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The tally of hours from day of operation until extubation of ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of days in the cardiac intensive care unit and the hospital are recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from day of operation until discharge from hospital (generally after 10-12 days).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The total number of days in hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from day of operation until discharge from hospital (generally after 10-12 days).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with tetralogy of Fallot having surgery for the first time.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with chromosomal defects, associated congenital lung malformations and haematological disorders</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The implementer of the RIPC or Sham control/placebo treatment protocols will open one sealed envelope in numerical order immediately prior to placement of the blood pressure cuff and they will apply the RIPC treatment or sham control protocol accordingly.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random allocation is made in blocks in order to keep the sizes of the 2 treatment groups similar. Due to the expected relative uniformity of condition in the patient group and the small number of subjects the design will not be stratified. The randomisation will be performed in secret by a member from Heart Research (not involved in working for the trial) using SPSS statistical software generated randomisation and will place each designation sequentially in numbered envelopes 1 to 40, for patient 1 to 40 and the envelopes will be signed and sealed.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Igor Konstantinov</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Cardiac Surgery
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Michael Cheung</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Cardiology
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Salvatore Pepe</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Heart Research, 
Murdoch Children's Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Vera Ignjatovic</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Haemotology Research, 
Murdoch Children's Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Lay Summary:
Support of the blood circulation during heart surgery using the heart-lung bypass machine is inevitably associated with organ damage and associated reduced function. This is due to reduced blood flow (ischemia), the effects of restoration of flow (reperfusion injury) and the subsequent inflammation that is caused. The body has its own way of protecting itself against reduced blood flow and oxygen by a mechanism known as preconditioning. In essence, brief periods of mild ischemia are protective against a subsequent more severe episode of ischemia. These periods of mild ischemia can be of the organ itself or of another organ in the body. For example ischemia of the leg can protect the heart against ischemia, so called remote preconditioning.  We have shown in animal and human models that remote preconditioning using a tourniquet (or blood pressure cuff) placed around a thigh for brief periods (similar in duration to when taking blood samples from children) reduces the amount of injury to heart muscle by 50% and also leads to improved heart and lung function. We have shown that remote preconditioning in a similar way protects the organs of a heterogeneous group of children undergoing cardiac surgery, resulting in better function of the heart and lungs and also a reduction of the inflammatory response to the heart-lung machine. This could potentially reduce the problems in looking after children after surgery and also reduce the amount of time spent in the intensive care unit. 
We will study paediatric patients undergoing heart surgery inorder to identify key protein and metabolic changes that occur within this 'heart-protection' protocol. All interventions will be performed during the period of routine general anaesthesia at the time of surgical repair. We will study the degree of organ injury induced by heart-lung bypass using standard intensive care parameters and equipment for measuring lung function. The degree of plasma and blood cell metabolic function will be assessed by laboratory tests. Blood samples will be taken from indwelling catheters routinely placed at the time of surgery and not require additional venepuncture. Measurements will be made prior to surgery and also at set time intervals in the first 24 hours postoperatively to determine the evolution of effects.

Primary Objective: 
Does remote ischemic preconditioning (RIPC) modify the global plasma proteomic and mitochondrial response in patients undergoing congenital heart surgery?   

Hypothesis: 
RIPC induces significant changes to global proteomic response in plasma and the metabolic function in heart muscle and lymphocyte mitochondria of patients undergoing congenital heart surgery. 

Aims:
To assess in blood plasma and lymphocyte/myocardial mitochondria the impact of RIPC on the global proteomic and mitochondrial metabolic function response to heart surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass support.

Secondary Objectives:
Does RIPC modify clinical markers of injury and cardiopulmonary function post-Cardiopulmonary bypass in patients undergoing congenital heart surgery?   

Hypothesis: 
Remote IPC reduces post-cardiopulmonary bypass  release of markers of cellular injury and permits recovery of cardiac pump function with less complication including inotrope requirement in patients undergoing congenital heart surgery. 

Aims:
To assess the impact of remote IPC on lactate release, inotrope requirement, and standard clinical cardiopulmonary assessments in response to heart surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass support.

This small randomised, blinded, surgical trial of preoperative therapy with highly regulated, brief, non-invasively-induced, localised leg ischaemia and reperfusion, will test for the capacity to invoke remote ischemic preconditioning-related molecular signalling (proteomic and metabolic) changes.  The study will recruit 40 paediatric tetralogy of patients to RIPC treatment or SHAM RIPC (Placebo control) treatment groups and is expected to be completed by the end of March 2012.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>29133</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Igor Konstantinov</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiac Surgery
Royal Childrens' Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455200</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93456386</fax>
      <email>Igor.Konstantinov@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Igor Konstantinov</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiac Surgery
Royal Childrens' Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455200</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93456386</fax>
      <email>Igor.Konstantinov@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Salvatore Pepe</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology
Royal Childrens' Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93454114</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93456001</fax>
      <email>salvatore.pepe@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>