<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320605">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/10/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000876291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>To determine a practical pH cutoff level for safer confirmation of nasogastric tube placement</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To determine a more practical pH cutoff level than pH&lt;4 for safer confirmation of nasogastric tube placement in children without increasing the risk of not identifying a misplaced tube in the lung.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1111-8403</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>pH testing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>nasogastric tube position</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To directly compare pH results of gastric aspirate samples in children receiving enteral feeding with endotracheal aspirate samples in children in intensive care requiring tracheal suctioning over a 6 month period. Particularly to examine potential overlap of pH results between the aspirate samples which is where the cutoff for identification of a misplaced tube would occur. This data can then be used to establish a reliable and clinically practical pH cut-off value for gastric aspirate without risking the safety of the patient by not identifying a misplaced nasogastric tube (NGT) in the lung.</interventions>
    <comparator>All paediatric intensive care unit (PICU) patients within this age range who required endotracheal suctioning as part of their routine care were recruited to obtain endotracheal aspirate samples for pH testing over a 6 month period</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We compare the range of pH results between gastric and endotrachael aspirate samples, with particular interest in the area of overlap between the two samples. This data will help to determine a reliable and practical pH value to confirm NGT placement, without increasing the risk of not identifying a misplaced NGT.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Gastric aspirate samples taken prior to administration of enteral feed (minimum once per day to maximum 2 hourly) until NGT is removed over the 6 month period.
Endotracheal aspirate samples collected at every tracheal suctioning procedure for patients in ICU (minimum once per day to maximum 2 hourly) until tracheal suctioning is no longer required as routine care over the 6 month period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients aged over 4 weeks at the Royal Children's Hospital (RCH) receiving enteral nutrition (nasogastric or gastrostomy) were recruited to the study. In addition, all paediatric intensive care unit (PICU) patients within this age range who required endotracheal suctioning as part of their routine care were also recruited to obtain endotracheal aspirate samples for pH testing.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>4</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>less than 4 weeks of age</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>670</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Children's Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Alfred Felton Bequest</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ANZ Trustees Limited 
Level 4, 100 Queen St Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nutricia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>12-24 Talavera Rd
Macquarie Park NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Children's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dept of Nutrition and Food Services
Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Confirmation of correct nasogastric tube (NGT) placement is essential to ensure the safe delivery of nutrition without the risk of morbidity and mortality associated with misplacement in the lung resulting in aspiration, pneumonia, pneumothorax or death. Previous studies indicate a pH &lt; 4 is indicative of gastric aspirate and hence a reliable indicator of correct NGT placement. At the Royal Childrens Hospital (RCH) in Melbourne, the current practice is to use this pH cut-off &lt; 4 based on Methenys work, but this is not always clinically practical. The use of antacid medication and/or the presence of enteral feeds due to delayed gastric emptying may be contributing factors in a higher pH result, casting doubt on NGT position. A number of different clinical methods have been reported to determine NGT position including auscultation (listening for air passed down the tube), aspirate colour, administering oral fluids or flushing NGT with oral rehydration solution (ORS), but none are evidence-based methods. Radiography confirmation is the gold standard but has limited application secondary to availability, cost and radiation exposure. This study was undertaken to directly compare pH results of gastric aspirate samples with endotracheal aspirate samples, and particularly to examine potential overlap of pH results between the aspirate samples. This data can then be used to establish a reliable and clinically practical pH cut-off value for gastric aspirate without risking the safety of the patient by not identifying a misplaced NGT in the lung. Whilst undertaking this study, an adverse nasogastric-feeding incident occurred in the UK which led to the formation of a working party to challenge the assumptions and rituals of NGT placement. An NGT algorithm was developed using a risk assessment approach to improve the safety of NGT fed children and increase the awareness of the risks to health care providers. Subsequently, the National Patient Safety Agency (NPSA) published an alert that accepted a pH cut-off &lt;5.5 as being an acceptable risk. This was decided by expert opinion and consensus rather than the result of new clinical research. This current study will provide further evidence for this consensus statement and ensure that our recommendations are based on evidence-based practice and lead to reduced patient risk. We compare the range of pH results between gastric and endotrachael aspirate samples, with particular interest in the area of overlap between the two samples. This data will help to determine a reliable and practical pH value to confirm NGT placement, without increasing the risk of not identifying a misplaced NGT.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics in Human Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Murdoch Children's Research Institute (MCRI)
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
PArkville VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EHRC 25101A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Heather Gilbertson</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Food Services
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>613 9345 5663</phone>
      <fax>613 9345 6496</fax>
      <email>heather.gilbertson@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Heather Gilbertson</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Food Services
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>613 9345 5663</phone>
      <fax>613 9345 6496</fax>
      <email>heather.gilbertson@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Heather Gilbertson</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Food Services
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>613 9345 5663</phone>
      <fax>613 9345 6496</fax>
      <email>heather.gilbertson@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>