<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372217">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000258358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The role of gait determinants in people with knee osteoarthritis in relation to results of healthy people</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The role of gait determinants in the mechanism of limiting oscillation of center of gravity in people with knee osteoarthritis in relation to results of healthy people</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>gonarthrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In all participants is planned single measure of gait analysis. 

The first author will enroll 50 patients from a list of patients for total knee replacement. Persons qualified for the research were patients of the Department of Orthopedic and Trauma Surgery of Gabriel Narutowicz Municipal Hospital in Krakow, Poland, who will have total knee replacement. 

The qualification for research  group will be based on the simple randomisation. Allocation of patients to the group will be  decided upon the coin-tossing. Heads  person is participating in the research, tails  person does not take part in the research. Subjects for the research will be always qualified by the same person (the first author).  This is part of screening prior to enrolment to ensure a random selection of patients are included

1. Measurement of kinematic and kinetic gait parameters based on a three-dimensional motion analysis, with the use of the Vicon 250  system together with a dynamometric platform. The analysis will cover:
-angular changes in 3 planes of motion of knee, hip and ankle joints
-changes in the length of selected muscles
- changes in ground-reaction forces
-spatio-temporal parameters: the number of steps per minute, single and double support time, stride length and time, gait velocity
 
2. The knee function assessment with the use of the Lysholm scale will be performed as well as the WOMAC assessment scale.

Vicon 250 system
Vicon 250 system, as a research tool, allows for an objective assessment of gait and processing of the obtained kinematic and spatio-temporal parameters. It consists of five cameras, a set of 39 passive markers and data station.
Small markers (25 mm diameter) coated with reflective material, adheres to the skin at characteristic points of the bone and joint axes. Camera emit flashes at a frequency of 120 Hz with a wavelength at the border of the infrared and visible light, which when reflected from passive markers back to the camera and are recorded by the measuring system. The resulting two-dimensional images from the cameras are processed in the station on the three-dimensional image data (Workstation, Body Builder, Polygon)
Prior to the registration gait through the system Vicon 250, each respondent will be able to freely walk along the  20m path, any number of times during 30 min in order to adapt to the environment and the equipment used. Proper phase of the study will consist of a 6-times passage of pathh with natural speed.
For each patient 30 steps with a stabilized, natural speed will be selected, in order to characterize the individual gait pattern. The collected data will be subjected to computer analysis. On the basis of anthropometric measurements will be modeled gait respondents in the application BodyBulider and then visualized in the form of a research report in the Polygon.

Overall duration of the examination 2 hours:
1. 1 hour to prepare the patient - affixing the markers on the skin, getting used to the system and markers
2. 1 hour measurements - several times crossing the 20 meter path</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be the healthy people, aged 40 - 60 years who have no evidence of current dysfunction of musculoskeletal, nervous, circulatory and other diseases affecting the gait pattern. Control sample will count 50 people, of both sexes.
The qualification for control group will be based on the simple randomisation. Allocation of patients to the group will be  decided upon the coin-tossing. Heads  person is participating in the research, tails  person does not take part in the research. Subjects for the research will be always qualified by the same person (the first author). 
The healthy participants will also complete the Vicon 250 and WOMAC assessments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kinematic parameters of gait assessed by Vicon system:
1. angular changes knee, ankle and hip joints
2. spatio-temporal measurements
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after measurement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kinetic parameters of gait assessed by Vicon system:
1. ground reaction force</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after measurement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee function assessed by WOMAC and Lysholm scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after measurement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Study group:
1. Diagnosed advanced osteoarthritis of the knee (stage III / IV)
2. Score &lt; 60 in the Lysholm scale,
3. Score &gt; 45 in the WOMAC scale,
4. Written consent of the patient to participate in research,
Control group:
1. Lack of injuries and diseases of the musculoskeletal system and neurological diseases.
2. Written consent of the patient to participate in research,</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Study and control group
1. Age below 40 and above 60 years 
2. 30 &lt; BMI &lt;19
3. Identified coexisting diseases such. neurological, cardiac, advanced diabetes, uncontrolled high blood pressure and other diseases that may affect the gait pattern,
3. acute injuries and inflammation within the motor organs,
4. the overall poor health of the test,

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis of the collected material in the first stage will include testing the normal distribution of variables (Shapiro-Wilk test). Then, depending on the results of the calculated ratios are descriptive statistics such as the arithmetic mean (x) and standard deviation (s) or median and deviation quadrant.
517/5000
Depending on the distribution of the variables for testing the significance of differences between mean values of the variables will be used analysis of variance [ANOVA (F test) verification by test post hoc Tukey, or in the absence of normal distribution of results, the non-parametric test for two dependent samples (Wilcoxon test ). The differences between the curves of changes of angles in a standardized gait cycle in the joints of the lower limbs and spatial movements of the pelvis will be assessed on the basis of an analysis of the profiles.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Random sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Malopolska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Physical Education in Krakow</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Physical Education in Krakow
Al. Jan Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Physical Education in Krakow</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Physical Education in Krakow
Al. Jan Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine the real impact of the determinants of gait to save energy by reducing vertical oscillation OSC, in patients with advanced osteoarthritis of the knee and healthy.
The studies will be carried out in the Laboratory of Biokinetics at the Academy of Physical Education in Krakow, involving 50 patients aged 40-60 years, of both sexes, with gonarthrosis.
The control group will be the healthy people, aged 40 - 60 years of both sexes.
In the study of locomotion three-dimensional motion analysis system will be used.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bioethics Commission at the Regional Medical Chamber in Krakow</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bioethics Commission at the Regional Medical Chamber in Krakow
ul. Krupnicza 11a
31-123 Krakow</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/KBL/OIL/2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372217-bioethics approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Aleksandra Kulik-Warchala</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education in Krakow
Al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48126831065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aleksndra-kulik@o2.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katarzyna Ogrodzka</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education in Krakow
Al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48126831065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katarzyna.ogrodzka@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katarzyna Ogrodzka</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education in Krakow
Al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48126831065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katarzyna.ogrodzka@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katarzyna Ogrodzka</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education in Krakow
Al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>katarzyna.ogrodzka@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>