<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82694">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/03/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/03/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000151336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Obesity prevention impact of removing caffeine from soft drinks</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of removing caffeine from soft drinks on total energy intake and soft drink consumption in young adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Energy intake in healthy populations</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Caffeinated soft drinks. Subjects will be asked to consume a prepared soft drink containing 130mg/L (the same amount present in popular cola beverages). During the first 2 weeks of the study they will be asked to consume 600mls per day, for the following 4 weeks of the study, they will be asked to consume as much or as little of the drink as they like and record the amount consumed in a daily log book.</interventions>
    <comparator>Non-caffeinated soft drink. Subjects will be asked to consume a prepared soft drink, identical to the intervention exposure drink expect for the absence of caffeine. During the first 2 weeks of the study they will be asked to consume 600mls per day, for the following 4 weeks of the study, they will be asked to consume as much or as little of the drink as they like and record the amount consumed in a daily log book.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Energy intake as assessed using 4 day food record and nutrient analysis using Foodworks Pro 2005 (Xyris software QLD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average energy, intake assessed over 4 days during week 0, will be compared with average energy intake assessed over 4 days during week 6.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Soft drink consumption will be recorded daily using a daily log book.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Soft drink intake will be measured daily and the data will be condensed into average weekly consumption for analysis.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight (kg)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Body weight will be measured on two occasions, week 0 and week 6.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beverage liking determined using a 9 point Leichart scale ranging from 'like extremely' to 'dislike extremely'.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Beverage liking will be measured at week 0 and will be compared with beverage liking measured during week 6.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged between 18-30yrs.
Not pregnant or lactating.
Currently consume sugar sweetened, caffeine containing soft drinks.
Weight stable (no change in body weight in past 6 mths greater than +/- 2kg)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Do not currently consume sugar sweetened caffeinated beverages</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The person responsible for determining eligibility of subject will be onsite and will be responsible for the daily operation of the intervention program. They will allocate subjects to either group A or B using a computer generated allocation system (Minim by Stephen Evans, Simon Day and Patrick Royston) following subject consenting to take part in the study. The person allocating subjects and responsible for the daily management of the trial will not be aware which beverage has been assigned to group A or group B.</concealment>
    <sequence>The method used to generate the sequence in which the subjects will be randomised will be Dynamic allocation by minimisation, with sex being the minimisation variable. This will be achieved using the Minim program by  Stephen Evans, Simon Day and Patrick Royston available from http://www-users.york.ac.uk/~mb55/guide/minim.htm</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>SPSS Version 21.0 software (IBM SPSS) was used for the statistical analysis of the data. 
Two-way between groups ANOVA.  
Pearsons product-moment coefficients correlations used for exploring the relationship between average SSB consumption, liking of SSB, BMI, and dietary intake.

The power calculation is based on an estimated effect size of 150ml/day soft drink consumption, which is the observed reduction in the UK trial in 7-11 year olds from an educational program. (James et al BMJ 2004;328:1237) The observed variance in sugar sweetened beverage consumption in a large nationally representative sample of American 18 year olds is 310mls/day with an average intake of 327ml/day.(Striegel-Moore J Pediatr 2006;148:183-7) Among Australian youth who consume soft drinks (akin to the subjects in the study), the mean intake is 480mls/day.   Therefore 100 subjects are needed to complete this study to give an 80% chance of seeing a difference in intake between conditions. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/04/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/04/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/05/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3125</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway
Burwood VIC 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetes Australia Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5th Floor, 39 London Circuit
Canberra City ACT 2600

GPO Box 3156
Canberra 2601
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research program will test the hypotheses that removing caffeine from soft drinks will significantly decrease liking of and energy intake from these products and that this reduction in energy intake is sufficient to reduce average body weight in the Australian population. 

This project has two key aims:
1. To determine if the removal of caffeine from soft drinks results in a decreased consumption of these beverages.
2. To use these results to model the effect of caffeine removal from soft drinks on total energy intake and body weight of the Australian Population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Conference presentation: ICO Stockholm 2010 Caffeine increases consumption of sugar sweetened beverages Riddell, LJ1, Keast, RSJ1, Swinburn, B1
Published: Obesity Reviews July 2010 vol 11, issue S1 pg 297
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services
Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood VIC 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/03/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC 17-2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Russell Keast</name>
      <address>School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences Deakin University 221 Burwood Highway Melbourne VIC 3125 Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6944</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9244 6640</fax>
      <email>russell.keast@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Russell Keast</name>
      <address>School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences Deakin University 221 Burwood Highway Melbourne VIC 3125 Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6944</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9244 6640</fax>
      <email>russell.keast@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lynn Riddell</name>
      <address>School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences
Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9251 7270</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9244 6017</fax>
      <email>lynn.riddell@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Lynn Riddell</name>
      <address>School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences
Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood VIC 3125</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9251 7270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lynn.riddell@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>