<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365109">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001147774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised controlled trial of the oral contraceptive pill use to reduce bacterial vaginosis (BV) recurrence following recommended antibiotic therapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In women with bacterial vaginosis (BV), does taking the oral contraceptive pill in addition to recommended antibiotic therapy, compared to taking recommended antibiotic therapy alone, reduce the risk of BV recurrence?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1148-7961 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>SToPBV: Strategies to prevent bacterial vaginosis</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bacterial vaginosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sexually transmitted infections</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomised controlled open-label trial of the oral contraceptive pill for prevention of BV recurrence following recommended antibiotic therapy. All participants in this trial will be given current recommended antibiotic treatment for BV, in keeping with standard of care, prior to being assessed for eligibility for the trial. This antibiotic will predominantly be metronidazole orally 400 mg twice a day for 7 days, however, clinicians will be able to prescribe a 7-day regimen of oral or vaginal clindamycin, which has equivalent efficacy, if patients are unable to tolerate metronidazole or it is contraindicated.

Intervention:
Arm one: Combined oestrogen and progesterone containing oral contraceptive pill (OCP) commencing on day 8 and administered for six months. 

Randomisation will be occurring for the OCP which will be a standard monophasic 30mcg ethinyl oestradiol pill with 150 mcg of levonorgesterol, unless otherwise clinically indicated, or preferred by the participant or clinician. It will be prescribed in the standard 21 day active, 7 day placebo pill regimen.

Adherence to the OCP will be monitored by monthly self-report within questionnaires.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will not receive the intervention of the oral contraceptive pill for 6 months, however will receive standard recommended antibiotic treatment (ie oral metronidazole for 7 days) in keeping with standard clinical care.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recurrence of BV defined as 3-4/4 Amsel criteria and a Nugent score of 4-10. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 6 months of randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recurrence of BV defined by Amsel method (3-4/4 Amsel criteria) and Nugent score 4-10</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 3 months of randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recurrence of BV defined by Nugent score 7-10</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 1 month, and within 3 and 6 months, of randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women will be eligible if they:
i) Are 18-45 years of age, 
ii) Are symptomatic with BV, defined as a Nugent score of 4-10 and 3-4 Amsel criteria, 
iii) have a past history of one or more episodes of BV
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women will be ineligible if they are: 
i) concurrently diagnosed with pelvic inflammatory disease (PID)
ii) confirmed to be pregnant at the time of recruitment, or wish to conceive within the next 6 months, 
iii) known to be HIV positive, 
iv) unwilling or unable to comply with the requirements of the study protocol, 
v) already currently using a hormonal method of contraception, 
vi) known to have contraindications to OCP according to WHO criteria (e.g. focal migraine, history of deep venous thrombosis [DVT], hypertension etc)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sampling frame:
Women for this study will be recruited from Melbourne Sexual Health Clinic (MSHC), and referred to the service from Family Planning Victoria (FPV) and local general practices which specialise in women’s health. MSHC is the largest sexual health service in Victoria and diagnoses 500-550 cases of BV annually and has established relationships with FPV and local general practices. 

Randomisation:
Women that consent will be randomly assigned to one of the two study arms using a computer-generated sequence. A researcher, with no clinical input into this trial, will generate and hold the random number sequence. Randomisation will occur in blocks to ensure that the allocation of women to the two arms occurs at a similar rate over the recruitment period.

Allocation concealment: Once a woman is enrolled in the study, the research nurse will open the next consecutive sealed envelope to determine her group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A researcher, with no clinical input into this trial, will generate and hold the random number sequence. Randomisation will occur in blocks to ensure that the allocation of women to the two arms occurs at a similar rate over the recruitment period.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed using STATA and SPSS. Cumulative recurrence of BV will be determined for the overall study population and by randomisation group at each interval of follow-up. Proportions will be compared using Chi-square and Fishers Exact tests where appropriate, and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) will be calculated. All statistical tests will be two-sided and a level of p&lt;0.05 considered significant. Kaplan-Meier methods will be used to generate survival curves and estimate time until BV recurrence by randomisation group. The log rank test will be used to compare survival distributions between the two randomised groups. Cox proportional hazards models will be used to estimate the hazard ratio and 95% CIs for the effect of randomisation assignment on time to first BV recurrence. The primary analysis will be an intention to treat. Secondary analyses will include modified intention to treat and per-protocol analyses, and multivariate and cox regression analyses to account for any differences in baseline characteristics between treatment groups, and for factors known to be clinically-associated with BV recurrence.

With a total sample size of 266 (133 per group) we will have 80% power to detect a 40% reduction in BV recurrence from 40% in the control group to 24% in the OCP group (2-alpha=5%). Assuming a six month loss to follow-up of 15% in keeping with our previous trials, 314 women will be recruited (157 per arm).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>314</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>95</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/09/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>24/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3053 - Carlton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Grattan St, Parkville, Vic 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research Council GHD Building Level 1 16 Marcus Clarke St, Canberra 2601 ACT</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Grattan St, Parkville, Vic 3010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University Central Clinical School</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash University Central Clinical School
Level 6 of the Alfred Centre
The Alfred
55 Commercial Road, Melbourne VIC 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alfred Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Vic 3004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash University Central Clinical School
Level 6 of the Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Burnet Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>A/Prof Gilda Tachedjian
Burnet Institute
85 Commercial Road
Melbourne
Victoria
3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dr Jim Manos
Department of Infectious Diseases &amp; Immunology, Sydney Medical School
The University of Sydney
Room 671, Blackburn Building D06, 
The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>OVERALL AIM: This randomised controlled trial is aiming to establish if women who take the oral contraceptive pill (OCP) have a lower risk of getting bacterial vaginosis back again (called BV relapse or recurrence) after routine recommended antibiotic treatment.

OTHER AIMs: we also aim to determine the mechanisms, or reasons, as to how using the OCP may be reducing womens risk of getting BV back again. This will involve exploring the effects of oral contraception on healthy vaginal bacteria and BV-associated bacteria, and the effects on natural vaginal sugars and acids and immune markers. 

BACKGROUND AND SIGNIFICANCE: Bacterial vaginosis is the commonest causes of abnormal vaginal discharge in women of reproductive age affecting between 12-30% of women, suggesting it may currently affect at least 1 million Australian women. It can be associated with important complications such as miscarriage, premature birth and low birth weight, pelvic infection, and increased susceptibility to HIV and sexually transmitted infections (STIs). We have shown that BV relapse is common even after recommended treatment. However, we have found in two studies that women using combined (oestrogen &amp; progesterone containing) hormonal contraception appeared to have half the risk of BV recurrence following recommended antibiotics compared to women not taking the pill. We further confirmed this finding by meta-analysis of published literature in which we showed that in 55 studies, women using hormonal contraception had a reduced risk of BV recurrence. However, no randomised controlled trials have been conducted and how hormonal contraception reduces a womens risk of BV is unknown. We hypothesise that this could be happening via different mechanisms/actions such as increasing the levels of natural vaginal acids and by altering the vaginal immune response which may cause normally occurring healthy vaginal bacteria to increase and for less healthy BV-associated bacteria to decrease. 

HOW WILL WE DO THIS: This is a trial of 314 women who have been diagnosed with BV and prescribed the standard antibiotic treatment. Half of the participants (157 women) will be randomised to the oral contraceptive pill for 6 months, and the other half to no OCP for 6 months. We anticipate that those who take the pill will have a reduced risk of getting BV back again but this remains to be proven in this trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.mshc.org.au/stopbv/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Health Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>404/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catriona Bradshaw</name>
      <address>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre
Alfred Health
580 Swanston St
Carlton Victoria, 3053
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 6253</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6757</fax>
      <email>CBradshaw@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catriona Bradshaw</name>
      <address>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre
Alfred Health
580 Swanston St
Carlton Victoria, 3053
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 6253</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6757</fax>
      <email>CBradshaw@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catriona Bradshaw</name>
      <address>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre
Alfred Health
580 Swanston St
Carlton Victoria, 3053
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 6253</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6757</fax>
      <email>CBradshaw@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lenka Vodstrcil</name>
      <address>Monash University
Melbourne Sexual Health Centre
580 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93416232</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6757</fax>
      <email>lvodstrcil@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>