<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369214">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001010583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MEDINA: Mediterranean Dietary Intervention Study in Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD) patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of a Mediterranean Dietary Intervention on insulin resistance and hepatic steatosis in patients with Nonalcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD).
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MEDINA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition> Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mediterranean Dietary Intervention versus standard diet.
This involves randomizing patients to either a Mediterranean Diet intervention arm versus a standard diet (low fat, moderate Carbohydrate) intervention. An Accredited Practicing Dietitian (APD) will provide a dietary consult for intervention patients to follow a Med Diet protocol or patients following a standard protocol (low fat, Australian Guide to Healthy Eating). A food hamper representing typical Mediterranean Diet foods (for example olive oil, nuts, natural Greek yoghurt, legumes) will be provided to the intervention group and a supermarket voucher will be provided for the standard group to purchase low fat, moderate carbohydrate food products to achieve the dietary goals. These will be provided at baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks.
Meal plans and recipe books are all provided at baseline to the relevant diet group. The intervention will be run over a 12 week period with a further 6 and 12month follow up to assess duration of effect and feasibility of sustaining the diet.
The dietary intervention and standard diet consults will be delivered by an APD through a face-to-face consultation initially and face-to-face consultations at mid-intervention (6 weeks) and post-intervention timepoints. There are regular phone call reviews to check dietary compliance at weeks 2, 4 and 9.
A dietitian will administer the intervention and to monitor adherence food diaries, food frequency questionnaire, plasma fatty acids and urinary hydroxytyrosol will be used as measures for compliance.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The standard diet is modeled on the Australian Guide to Healthy Eating and the Heart Foundation's Guidelines of a low fat, moderate carbohydrate diet. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin Resistance as measured by Homeostasis Model Assessment of Insulin Resistance (HOMA-IR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on insulin resistance will be assessed at 6 and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hepatic Steatosis as measured by Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy (MRS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on hepatic steatosis will be assessed at 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention. 
Please note, this measure will not be assessed at 6 weeks due to cost of MRS, therefore we will measure at baseline and end-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Liver Function tests as measured by blood tests  - ALT, ALP, GGT</outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on liver function will be assessed at 6 and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammatory cytokine markers will measured (Leptin, Adiponectin, high sensitivity C-Reactive Protein) using serum blood analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on inflammatory cytokines will be assessed at 6 and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants that exhibit an improvement in lipid profile by 20% from baseline - assessing total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, Triglycerides from serum levels in blood OR lipid profile - assessing total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, Triglycerides from serum levels in blood. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on blood lipid levels will be assessed at 6 weeks and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Liver stiffness measured via Fibroscan (Registered Trademark) and CAP (Controlled Attenuation Parameter). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on liver stiffness will be assessed at 6 and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometric measures analysed with a calibrated stand on scales. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on anthropometry will be assessed at 6 and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effects of Mediterranean Diet diet on blood pressure will be measured using sphygmomanometer </outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on blood pressure will be assessed at 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life measures via AQoL-8D and SF 36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on quality of life will be assessed at 6 and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition analysis with bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on body composition as measured by BIA will be assessed at 6 and 12 weeks from the beginning of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DEXA will be offered to all participants at La Trobe University to assess changes in fat and lean muscle mass.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The effects of the intervention on body composition as measured by DEXA will be assessed at 12 weeks (post intervention) from the beginning of the intervention and compared to pre-intervention DEXA.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be included if they are &gt;18years, BMI 20-40kg/m2, Patients must have had at least one elevated serum aminotransferase (ALT) level (&gt;20U/L female,
&gt;30 U/L male) during the past 6 months and at screening have a level between &gt;1.5 and &lt;5 times Upper  Limit  of  Normal  (ULN)  in  the  absence  of  another  cause  of  liver  disease.  Diagnosis of NAFLD upon u/s.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if: they are non-English speaking; refusal or inability to give informed consent; average weekly alcohol ingestion &gt;140g males or females; a current or past history of cardiovascular, cerebrovascular or peripheral vascular disease; presence of clinically relevant pulmonary, gastro-intestinal, renal, haematological, neurological, psychiatric, systemic or any acute infectious disease or signs of acute illness; Women who are pregnant or currently breastfeeding; Psychosocial or gastrointestinal (malabsorptive conditions e.g. coeliac disease) contraindications included bulimia nervosa, substance abuse, clinically significant depression, or current psychiatric care. Recent (within 3months of screening visit) change in dose/regimen or introduction of Vitamin E, Vitamin C or high dose Vitamin D, fish oil or probiotics. Participation in any other clinical study targeting diet and lifestyle factors.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who consent to participate in the study will be randomised (using a computer generated stratified approach generated by a statistician) into the MD (intervention) group or the standard care (control) group. The person determining the subjects eligbility was not involved in the computer generation of stratification and randomization. </concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified allocation based on gender, presence of diabetes and cirrhosis</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intention-to-treat (ITT) will be used to analyse the primary and secondary endpoints. Kaplan-Meier (K-M) plots and Coxs proportional hazard models will be used to analyse and compare rates of events between control and treatment groups. Proportional hazard assumptions will be examined to ensure the validity of the conclusion drawn. For quantitative endpoints (e.g., HOMA-IR), t-test and linear regression will be used to compare the two groups.  If normality assumption is not fulfilled, non-parametric tests such as Wilcoxon rank-sum (Mann-Whitney) test will be used instead. All statistical analyses will be performed using 5% significance levels. When multiple hypothesis testings are performed (e.g. with SNP data), Bonferroni correction will be used to adjust the significance levels.
Power &amp; Sample size: The sample size has been powered to observe a change in insulin resistance as defined by HOMA-IR of 1.0 unit in the 12 week intervention period. With an 80% significance to p&lt;0.05, we aim to recruit 47 participants per arm (94 in total) allowing for a 20% drop out rate. We envisage that to recruit this number of participants will take 24 months. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>11/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>94</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Discipline of Dietetics and Human Nutrition
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria 3086  </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Discipline of Dietetics and Human Nutrition
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria 3086  
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine if the Mediterranean Diet (MD) compared to standard care (low fat diet), can reduce the severity of NAFLD and other symptoms often associated with NAFLD namely the Metabolic Syndrome (MetS). The components of the MetS which this study aims to monitor and potentially reduce includes: high blood pressure, increased waist circumference, elevated triglycerides (bad fats in the blood), reduced HDL cholesterol (good fats in the blood) and elevated glucose levels. These symptoms are referred to as the Metabolic Syndrome (MS).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Health, 55 Commercial Road, Prahran, Melbourne, 3181, Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>76/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Audrey Tierney</name>
      <address>Health Sciences Building 3, Room 438
Discipline of Dietetics and Human Nutrition
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria 3086
</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 3 9479 5253</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0) 3 9479 5768 </fax>
      <email>A.Tierney@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Audrey Tierney</name>
      <address>Health Sciences Building 3, Room 438
Discipline of Dietetics and Human Nutrition
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 3 9479 5253</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0) 3 9479 5768 </fax>
      <email>A.Tierney@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>American Samoa</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Audrey Tierney</name>
      <address>Health Sciences Building 3, Room 438
Discipline of Dietetics and Human Nutrition
Department of Rehabilitation, Nutrition and Sport
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria 3086</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 3 9479 5253</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0) 3 9479 5768 </fax>
      <email>A.Tierney@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>