<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367971">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000551594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase II Study of Ibrutinib, Rituximab and mini-CHOP (cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone) therapy in very elderly patients with newly diagnosed Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma (DLBCL)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II Study of Ibrutinib, Rituximab and mini-CHOP therapy in very elderly patients with newly diagnosed DLBCL</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IRiC study: Ibrutinib R-mini-CHOP in elderly DLBCL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ALLG NHL29</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>elderly DLBCL</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - High grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pre-phase prednisone at a dose of either 40mg/m2 IV or 100mg orally (depending on drug available IV or oral) daily for 5-7 days will be mandatory. All subjects will receive ibrutinib 560mg orally daily, rituximab 375mg/m2 IV (rounded up as per local investigator discretion to the nearest 100mg) on day 1, cyclophosphamide 400mg/m2 IV day 1, doxorubicin 25mg/m2 IV day 1, vincristine 1mg IV and prednisone 40mg/m2 IV or 100mg orally daily on a 21 day schedule aiming for a total of 6 cycles. This will be followed directly by 2 cycles of ibrutinib 560mg orally daily and rituximab 375mg/m2 IV on day 1 (rounded up as per local investigator discretion to the nearest 100mg) on a 21 day schedule. 
Pegfilgrastim G-CSF 6mg subcutaneous injection on day 4-5 of each cycle as tolerated. </interventions>
    <comparator>Single arm study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to assess the safety of ibrutinib-R-mini-CHOP in subjects with DLBCL as measured by deliverability. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Deliverability of Ibrutinib-R-mini-CHOP as measured by:
Average Relative Total Dose (ARTD), and 
Average Relative Dose Intensity (ARDI) Hyrniuks model RDI = Total Dose Delivered/Total Time (DDI) / SDI for each cycle and for the total of 8 cycles.

  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to assess the efficacy of ibrutinib-R-mini-CHOP in subjects with DLBCL as measured by overall survival.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Overall survival (OS) at 2 years.  
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary objectives include assessing the:
toxicity of ibrutinib-R-mini-CHOP

Treatment related toxicities that are Grade 3 or worse will be captured using NCI CTC V4.03.

Cardiac toxicity will be measured by left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF).


The number (%) of patients with treatment related toxicities that are Grade 3 or worse will be calculated and summarised.

The number (%) of patients with cardiac toxicity as measured by left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) will be calculated and summarised.  Cardiac toxicity is defined as &gt;=10% absolute decline of LVEF to a LVEF &lt;=50%.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary safety analyses will be based upon the safety population. Assessed bi-annually for a minimum of 2 years post treatment (follow up period).
The number (%) of patients with treatment related toxicities that are Grade 3 or worse will be calculated and summarised.

The number (%) of patients with cardiac toxicity as measured by left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) will be calculated and summarised.  Cardiac toxicity is defined as &gt;=10% absolute decline of LVEF to a LVEF &lt;=50%.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary objectives include assessing the:
efficacy of ibrutinib-R-mini-CHOP measured by response rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Response rate (CR, PR, SD, PD, relapse after CR) after cycle 4 and end of treatment
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary objectives include assessing the:
progression free survival,  and disease free survival (for subjects in CR) in subjects with DLBCL.
Composite outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary endpoints include:
Progression free survival.  An event is defined as death from any cause, relapse for CR subjects, progression during or after treatment, and changes of therapy during treatment.

Disease free survival for patient in CR.  An event is defined as relapse, progression during or after treatment, or death.

The number (%) of patients who are progression free and disease free at 2-years will be calculated.
 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival by IPI (International Prognostic Index) subgroup and ABC (Activated B-Cell) phenotype/genotype will be assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Overall survival at 2 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Subject must be 75 years of age or older
2. No prior treatment for DLBCL excluding prednisone
3. Histologically confirmed de novo CD20+ DLBCL 
4. Stage I bulky (largest dimension of lesion &gt;/= 6cm), II, III or IV disease by the Ann Arbor Classification
5. At least 1 measurable site of disease according to the 2014 Recommendations for Initial Evaluation, Staging and Response Assessment of Hodgkin and Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma  the Lugano Classification. The site of disease must be greater than 1.5 cm in the long axis regardless of short axis measurement. An extranodal lesion should have a longest diameter of &gt; 1cm.
6. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status score of 0, 1, or 2 (this can be as measured after any pre-phase prednisone)
7. LVEF within institutional normal limits, as determined by Gated Heart Pool Scan, or if not available, echocardiogram
8. Minimum life expectancy of 3 months
9. Haematology values must be within the following limits: 
a. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;=1.0 x10^9/Lindependent of growth factor support
b. Platelets &gt;=100x10^9/L or &gt;=50x10^9/L if bone marrow involvement independent of transfusion support in either situation
10. Biochemical values within the following limits:
a. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt;= 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN)
b. Total bilirubin &lt;= 1.5 x ULN unless bilirubin rise is due to Gilberts syndrome or of non-hepatic origin
c. Creatinine Clearance (as measured by Cockroft Gault) &gt;/= 40 mL/min/1.73m2 
11. Each subject (or their legally acceptable representative) must sign an informed consent form (ICF) indicating that he or she understands the purpose of and procedures required for the study and are willing to participate in the study. 
12. Men who are sexually active must be practicing a highly effective method of birth control during and after the study consistent with local regulations regarding the use of birth control methods for subjects participating in clinical trials. Men must agree to not donate sperm during and after the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>75</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. History of treated lymphoma of any subtype 
2. CNS or meningeal involvement
3. Contraindication to any drug in the chemotherapy regimen 
4. Serious active co-morbid disease according to the investigators decision
5. Poor renal function, defined as a Creatinine Clearance Rate (as measured by Cockcroft Gault) &lt; 40 mL/min/1.73m2 
6. Poor hepatic function, defined as Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN) and/or total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN unless bilirubin rise is due to Gilberts syndrome or of non-hepatic origin
7. Poor bone-marrow reserve, defined as absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1.0x10^9/L independent of growth factor support and/or platelet count &lt; 100x10^9/L or &lt; 50x10^9/L if bone marrow involvement independent of transfusion support in either situation
8. History of malignancy during the past 3 years, with the exception of non-melanoma skin cancers or stage 0 (in situ) carcinoma.
9. Treatment with any investigational drug within 30 days before the planned first cycle of chemotherapy
10. Requires anticoagulation with warfarin or equivalent vitamin K antagonists 
11. Requires treatment with strong CYP3A inhibitors
12. Requires treatment with fish oil
13. Prior anthracycline use &gt;= 150 mg/m2
14. History of stroke or intracranial haemorrhage within 6 months of enrolment
15. Unable to swallow capsules or malabsorption syndrome, disease significantly affecting gastrointestinal function, or resection of the stomach or small bowel, symptomatic inflammatory bowel disease or ulcerative colitis, or partial or complete bowel obstruction
16. Known bleeding disorders (e.g. von Willebrands disease)
17. Major surgery within 4 weeks of enrolment
18. Any life-threatening illness, medical condition, or organ system dysfunction which, in the investigators opinion, could compromise the subjects safety, interfere with the absorption or metabolism of ibrutinib capsules, or put the study outcomes at undue risk
19. Clinically significant cardiovascular disease such as uncontrolled or symptomatic arrhythmias, congestive heart failure, or myocardial infarction within 6 months of screening, or any Class 3 (moderate) or Class 4 (severe) cardiac disease as defined by the New York Heart Association Functional Classification
20. Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or active Hepatitis C Virus (HCV; RNA polymerase chain reaction [PCR]-positive) or active Hepatitis B Virus (HBV; DNA PCR-positive) infection. Only patients who are HBV surface antigen (HBVsAg) and/or HBV core antibody (HBVcAb) positive are required to undergo HBV DNA PCR testing. Subjects with PCR-negative HBV or who are HBV core antibody positive are permitted in the study but must be on HBV prophylaxis. 
21. Any uncontrolled active systemic infection requiring intravenous (IV) antibiotics.
22. Vaccinated with live, attenuated vaccines within 4 weeks of enrolment .</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/07/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Orange Health Service - Orange</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <hospital>The Tweed Hospital - Tweed Heads</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Border Medical Oncology - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>2298 - Waratah</postcode>
    <postcode>2800 - Orange</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>2485 - Tweed Heads</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ground floor, 35 Elizabeth Street, Richmond, VIC 3121</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Janssen-Cilag Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1-5 Khartoum Road
Macquarie Park, NSW, 2113
AUSTRALIA
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will evaluate the deliverability and efficacy of Ibrutinib-R-mini-CHOP chemotherapy in elderly patients with newly diagnosed diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL). Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 75 years or above and have been newly diagnosed with DLBCL for which you have received no prior treatment (excluding prednisone). Study details All participants in this study will be treated with a chemotherapy regime known as Ibrutinib-R-mini-CHOP. This will include treatment with the drugs prednisone (orally), ibrutinib (orally), rituximab intravenously ((IV) - i.e. administered directly into the vein), cyclophosphamide IV, doxorubicin IV, vincristine IV and Pegfilgrastim G-CSF (subcutaneous injection). Treatment duration will be for up to 8 x 28 day cycles as tolerated. All participants will be regularly assessed for a minimum of 2 years in order to evaluate the safety, toxicity and effectiveness of treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Concord Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW 2139, Australia 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group (SCGG) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Trotman</name>
      <address>Concord Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW 2139, Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+612 9767 7243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Judith.Trotman@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Trotman</name>
      <address>Concord Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW 2139, Australia </address>
      <phone>+612 9767 7243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Judith.Trotman@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Trotman</name>
      <address>Concord Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW 2139, Australia </address>
      <phone>+612 9767 7243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Judith.Trotman@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Grigo</name>
      <address>Australiasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group
Ground floor, 35 Elizabeth Street, Richmond,VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+613 8373 9722</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.grigo@allg.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>