<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373708">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001410347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>What are the possible benefits of Robotic-Assisted Gait Training and how much training is needed: A pilot randomised clinical trial with children with Cerebral Palsy.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of Robotic-Assisted Gait Training on self-perception of performance and participation, using the Canadian Occupational Performance Measure (COPM), and how much training is needed to determine change:  a pilot randomised clinical trial with children with Cerebral Palsy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1202-6495</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pilot 3-arm randomised controlled trial investigating the effects of Robotic-Assisted Gait Training (RAGT) in children with cerebral palsy (CP)
Arm 1: Six-week waitlist then random allocation into two or four (30-40 minute) RAGT sessions per week for six weeks.
Arm 2: two (30-40 minute) sessions of RAGT per week for six weeks
Arm 3: four (30-40 minute) sessions of RAGT per week for six weeks.
RAGT sessions: approximately 1 hour, with 30-40 minutes of this active 1:1 (individual) therapy using the Lokomat Pro in sessions conducted by the Robotics and Innovation Physiotherapist at the Women's and Children's Hospital. These sessions will be carried out at the Little Heroes Foundation Centre for Robotics and Innovation at the Women's and Children's Hospital. All sessions are conducted following the Hocoma Lokomat manual, and directions and session plans are created based on clinical reasoning by paediatric physiotherapists.
In the first session of the intervention blocks, pre-assessment data will be collected and recorded (approximately 1 hour) before an acclimatisation session in the Lokomat®Pro (30-40 minutes). Each subsequent intervention session will be 60 minutes long which will include around 10-20 minutes of heart rate and blood pressure measures, set up and fitting time, 30-40 minutes of active RAGT, and five minutes for completion of final assessments. During the active RAGT period, a range of avatar-based games and biofeedback information will be used to target different goals as determined by the COPM assessment. The three Lokomat® variables that will be adjusted regularly throughout sessions are treadmill speed, weight support and guidance force. These changes will be made subject to Borgs rating of percieved exertion scores being ideally 13. Treadmill speed would be increased, and weight support decreased if it appears the child requires an increased challenge or is progressing well between sessions. Guidance force is the amount of assistance the Lokomat® is providing the child to walk in the physiological gait pattern. This would be decreased to provide an additional challenge or as a motivational technique using the biofeedback charts. Throughout the RAGT sessions, children will be given feedback on progress as compared to previous sessions and achievements can be logged and shown in real time on the video screen. At the last intervention session, the post-assessments will be undertaken (approximately 1 hour). The assessments will be repeated six weeks after the intervention period. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1 (control): Six week wait list then random allocation into two or four (30-40 minute) RAGT sessions per week for six weeks
Arm 2: two (30-40 minute) sessions of RAGT per week for six weeks
Arm 3: four (30-40 minute) sessions of RAGT per week for six weeks.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Canadian Occupational Performance Measure (COPM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gross Motor Function Measure sections D and E (GMFM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standardised muscle circumference of thigh and calf (centimetres)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up. Using a tape measure that will be used consistently throughout the protocol.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart rate (beats per minute)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention assessment, at the beginning of each intervention session, post-intervention assessment and 6 week follow up assessment. Taken using a finger tip pulse oximeter.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% Max Heart rate
to be calculated from Heart rate (BPM) at the end of the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A finger tip pulse oximeter will be used at the end of each RAGT session and the value used to calculate % max heart rate.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Borgs Rating of Perceived Exertion Scale (RPE)</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be asked every 10 minutes per session to indicate the level of exertion to determine the required change of Lokomat variables (rating of 13 ideal).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Australian Spasticity Assessment Scale (ASAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of motion of lower limbs;</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up. Taken using a goniometer. The same goniometer will be used throughout the protocol.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Selective motor control in lower limbs
Knee:
Position: Sitting
Ask the participant to extend, flex then extend the knee while keeping the hip flexed. For example: Straighten your knee as much as you can, then bend it and straighten again. Try to do this without leaning further back or moving your other leg. I will take you 
through the motion first, and then I
d like you to do it yourself.  
Ankle:
Position: Sitting. The knee is extended and the examiner supports the calf.  Assess passive ankle 
dorsiflexion ROM with the knee extended. The knee may be flexed to approximately 20 degrees if needed to accommodate hamstring and/or 
gastrocnemius tightness. 
Instructions  
Ask participant to dorsiflex, plantar flex then dorsiflex the ankle while maintaining knee extension. For example: 
Keeping your knee straight while I support your leg, move your foot up, down then up again.  I will take you through the motion first, then 
Id like you to do it yourself. </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gross Motor Function Classification Scale (GMFCS)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Mobility Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Two-minute walk test (2mwt)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up. Will require a stopwatch and a tape measure to lay out a 20 metre path.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebral Palsy Quality of Life Questionnaire (CP QOL-Child)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Childrens Assessment of Participation and Enjoyment (CAPE) </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure (mmHg)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention assessment, at the beginning of each intervention session, post-intervention assessment and 6 week follow up assessment.
Taken using an automatic mobile blood pressure monitor stand. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preferences for Activities of Children (PAC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6 week follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria:
Children with a diagnosis of Cerebral Palsy 
GMFCS level of II-IV
Aged 5 to 14 years
Able to follow instructions, and to participate in a minimum of 45 min of active physical therapy
Able to communicate pain, discomfort and report on perceived level of exertion
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria:
Body weight: less than 15kg or more than 135kg
Femur length: less than 23cm or more than 47cm
Unable to sustain vertical position for &gt;20 minutes (orthostatic)
Knee flexion contracture of &gt;10°
Knee valgus &gt;40°
Orthopaedic surgery &lt;9 months for soft tissues and &lt;18 months for lower limb bony surgery
Botulinum Toxin (Type A) injection in the previous four months or planned during study period
Uncontrolled seizure disorder
Weight-bearing restrictions
Pregnancy
Behavioural problems/inability to offer consent in addition to guardian.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation via third party not involved in recruitment</concealment>
    <sequence>sequence is computer generated , and stratified to GMFM to ensure equal numbers of each level in each arm.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants are randomly allocated into three groups as described above. One group (arm 1) of participants will be assigned to 'waitlist' before allocation to two or four RAGT sessions per week for six weeks. A second group (arm 2) will receive two sessions of RAGT per week for six weeks. The third group (arm 3) will receive four sessions of RAGT per week for six weeks.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>n=10
Multiple ANOVA tests to be conducted for COPM, GMFM and 2MWT to see the difference between groups.
A repeated measures ANCOVA will be used to compare the effects of the different intensities of RAGT.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>3/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Womens and Childrens Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women's and Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>72 King William Rd, North Adelaide SA 5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Little Heroes Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>77 King William St, North Adelaide SA 5006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of South Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>108 North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gait disorders in children can result from a number of conditions including cerebral palsy (CP),
myelomeningocoele and traumatic brain injury. Such disorders can have a profound effect on the components of walking, as well as the functional participation of children in their home, school and other natural environments. Robotic-Assisted Gait Training (RAGT) is an emerging option in physical rehabilitation for adults and children with disorders impairing their ability to walk. RAGT devices such as the Lokomat®Pro support an individual on a treadmill while the robotic exoskeleton moves the lower limbs to simulate walking. 
There have been positive results from the use of RAGT in adult spinal cord injury and stroke populations for improvement in gait speed and endurance; however, the outcomes were not always better than traditional physiotherapy. Currently, there is weak and inconsistent evidence that RAGT may benefit children with CP with recommendations that higher level research investigates the role and potential of RAGT in this population. Additionally, many studies have failed to consider the impact of RAGT on participation outcomes. A limitation of the current literature is that no study has investigated different training schedules (frequency and intensity) of RAGT in children with CP and there is no consensus on the best schedule to promote functional improvement.  Therefore, this study aims to investigate how RAGT should be prescribed and its impacts on body structure and function, activity and participation domains of the ICF. This research has the potential to aid in the development of clinical practice guidelines for the use of RAGT in children with CP.

Aims of research
This project will pilot test robotically-assisted gait training (RAGT) in children with cerebral palsy to:
1.	Establish the most effective dosage for RAGT in terms of a) frequency and b) intensity of session, to induce clinically meaningful improvement in lower limb functioning, (as measured by the outcome measure listed in 'procedures and measurement')
2.	Establish the measurements of outcome that demonstrate the most improvement from baseline after treatment to capture relative effectiveness across the ICF domains.
Hypotheses:
1.	In children with CP, we hypothesise that a relationship exists between increased intensity and/or frequency of RAGT sessions and clinically meaningful improvement in lower limb performance (on ICF outcome measures).
2.	We hypothesise that the greatest change in outcome measures will occur in the group with the higher dosage of RAGT therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Health Network Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide 5006
South Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/WCHN/48</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373708-WCHN Ethics Approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373708-Lefmann, Russo and Hillier.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Emma Lowe</name>
      <address>c/o C7-66
University of South Australia, City East Campus, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide, SA, 5001</address>
      <phone>+61458973642</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lowel002@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Remo (Ray) Russo</name>
      <address>Head of Research, Paediatric Rehabilitation Department
Women's and Children's Health Network
72 King William Road, North Adelaide SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61-8-8161-7220</phone>
      <fax>+61-8-8161-8488</fax>
      <email>ray.russo@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Remo (Ray) Russo</name>
      <address>Head of Research, Paediatric Rehabilitation Department
Women's and Children's Health Network
72 King William Road, North Adelaide SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61-8-8161-7220</phone>
      <fax>+61-8-8161-8488</fax>
      <email>ray.russo@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Emma Lowe</name>
      <address>c/o C7-66
University of South Australia, City East Campus, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide, 5001</address>
      <phone>+61458973642</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lowel002@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>