<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367301">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001164684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effectiveness of quadriceps strengthening with and without blood flow restriction in the treatment of knee cap pain (patellofemoral pain)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of quadriceps strengthening with and without blood flow restriction in the treatment of patellofemoral pain</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patellofemoral pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will perform Low intensity blood flow restriction training on the affected leg only.

This group will perform 15 minutes (total) of exercises on the stationary bicycle, leg press and leg extension. These exercises will be performed 3 times per week for 8 weeks.

The cycling will be for 5 minutes based at an intensity that the participant considers "light".

The blood flow restriction training group will perform exercises at 30 % of their maximum strength for 4 sets. The sets will consist of repetitions of 30, 15, 15 and 15. Each repetition will take 3 seconds, and there will be a 30 second rest between each set.

Physiotherapists will prescribe the exercises. The blood flow restriction will be applied using a pneumatic cuff with a handheld sphygmomanometer (width 10cm). The cuff will be applied to the proximal thigh. The cuff will be applied only for the leg press and leg extension exercises and will remain on between sets of exercises, but removed after the exercise is completed (cuff will remain on for approximately 4 minutes for leg press and 4 minutes for leg extension, with a 2 minute break between exercises with the cuff off).

Arterial occlusion pressure will be measured with Doppler ultrasound on initial assessment, by placing the ultrasound over the tibial artery at the ankle, and the cuff around the proximal thigh. The cuff will be inflated until the artery is occluded (this process is the equivalent of taking a blood pressure reading). The pressure of the cuff to be used during exercises will be 60% of the arterial occlusion pressure.

Participants will tick off which exercises were completed on each session in an exercise log to monitor adherence to the program.</interventions>
    <comparator>The strengthening group (comparator group) will perform exercises prescribed by physiotherapists at 70 % of their maximum for 3 sets of 12 repetitions, or to volitional fatigue. With a 30 second rest between sets.

This group will perform 15 minutes (total) of exercises on the stationary bicycle, leg press and leg extension. These exercises will be performed 3 times per week for 8 weeks.

The cycling will be for 5 minutes at an intensity that the participant considers "light". Leg press and leg extension will each take approximately 4 minutes to complete, and there will be a 2 minute rest between exercises.

Participants will tick off which exercises were completed on each session in an exercise log to monitor adherence to the program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patellofemoral pain (VAS), worst pain in the past week. 100mm scale.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, and 24 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8 and 24 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kujala anterior knee pain scale- measures of patellofemoral pain and function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8 and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quadriceps muscle size- measured with real time ultrasound as muscle thickness (cm) at the mid thigh and distal thigh.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric quadriceps muscle strength measured with a Humac Dynamometer at 60 degrees of flexion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global rating of change in pain, rated as 1. Much worse, 2. Worse, 3. Same, 4. Improved, 5. Much Improved</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patellofemoral pain with daily activity (VAS). Worst pain with squatting, stairs, or prolonged sitting on a 100mm scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pain at the front of the knee for 8 weeks or longer
Atraumatic onset of symptoms
Pain with any two of running, squatting, prolonged sitting, jumping, kneeling.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Knee ligament injury, knee surgery, dislocation/subluxation Inflammatory arthritis
Participated in strengthening exercises with leg weights for longer than 4 weeks in the past 6 months.

Cardiovascular conditions, including high blood pressure (&gt;140/90), diabetes, unexplained chest pain or heart condition, fainting or dizzy spells during physical activity/exercise that causes loss of balance, pregnancy or other contra-indications to exercise.
 
Conditions affecting blood flow or blood clotting</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects responding to posters in sports medicine clinics, or online call or email the investigator.

Participants will be screened by phone and on presentation to the testing room to determine if they are eligible to participate.

Allocation will be done off site by an independent person who has been assigned this role.</concealment>
    <sequence>A random number generator will be used with Microsoft Excel</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>SPSS will be used for all statistical analysis (statistical significance P&lt;.05). One way ANOVA will be used to assess if differences are present at baseline between groups for age, gender, body mass index (BMI) and symptom duration. 

To determine group differences over time Repeated Measures Analysis of variance (ANOVAs) or Generalised Estimating Equations will be performed for scores on pain(visual analogue scale (VAS)), and function (Kujala anterior knee pain scale), quadriceps muscle strength and quadriceps muscle thickness at 0, and 8 weeks; VAS and Kujala anterior knee pain scale will also be assessed at 4, 24 and 52 weeks.

Power analysis with G Power suggested 70 participants were required to detect a large effect size between the groups. Significance &lt;.05. alpha error prob 0.95.


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/08/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>7/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>79</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lachlan Giles</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of physiotherapy, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic, 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University Lower Extremity and Gait Studies</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic, 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Kate Webster</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of occupational therapy, School of Allied Health, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic, 3086</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patellofemoral pain is common in people who participate in activities and sports that involve running. Improved treatment outcomes in patellofemoral pain are required as recent research has established a link between patellofemoral pain and future osteoarthritis of the knee. Common interventions such as quadriceps strengthening exercises are effective at reducing pain for many people with patellofemoral pain.

Quadriceps strengthening is likely to have an effect in improving patellofemoral pain because of resultant increases in quadriceps size and strength. However some people with patellofemoral pain are unable to perform exercises with a resistance that significantly strengthens the quadriceps because pain limits their ability to perform the exercises. Blood flow restricted training can increase muscle size and strength at lower resistance than typical strengthening programs, and may therefore be a suitable method of improving quadriceps size and strength in those unable to perform traditional quadriceps strengthening exercises effectively.

Blood flow restricted training involves placing an inflatable cuff around a limb before performing strengthening exercises. The placement of the cuff reduces blood flow within the limb during the exercise. It is hypothesised that limited blood flow causes the muscle to work harder than in normal blood flow conditions, and therefore improvements in muscle size and strength can be obtained at lower resistance than conventional exercises.


This study will compare 8 weeks of low resistance quadriceps strengthening with blood flow restriction to the current gold standard treatment of 8 weeks of quadriceps strengthening. Participants will be assessed at 0, 4, 8, 24 and 52 weeks. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Faculty Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/200</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Lachlan Giles</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic, 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394795871</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lsgiles@students.latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Lachlan Giles</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic, 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394795871</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lsgiles@students.latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Lachlan Giles</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic</address>
      <phone>+61394795871</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lsgiles@students.latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Lachlan Giles</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotheapy, La Trobe University, Bundoora, Vic</address>
      <phone>+61394795871</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lsgiles@students.latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>