<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336925">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000580976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of population-based disease management services (encompassing population analytics and telephone health coaching) on cost and hospitalisation for privately insured Australians with selected chronic conditions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised control trial to evaluate the ability of a full service disease management program (encompassing population analytics and telephone health coaching), in comparison to simple program awareness building, to impact on subsequent health care costs and hospitalization for privately insured individuals with specific conditions and identified risks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CAPICHe
Costs to Australian Private Insurance - Coaching Health</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hospital, medical and prostheses costs borne by private insurers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Disease management services from Bupa Health Dialog including mailed program awareness notifications, tailored mailed educational material, tailored outreach material designed to encourage individuals with specific risks to talk with a Health Coach, outbound Health Coach outreach and follow-up calls (a minimum of two calls in first two months with no maximum number of calls being set), access on an inbound telephonic basis to Health Coaches, and mailed Health Coach selected educational and other material.

Duration of the intervention is for 12 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive usual care unless they opt-in to receive health coaching.

Individuals randomly assigned to the Control Group will receive a letter outlining the service provided by BUPA Health Dialog. This letter will contain a phone number that participants may choose to ring should they wish to receive health coaching. Put simply, a health coach will not ring the participant directly. 

If a participant assigned to the usual support group actively seeks health coach engagement, they will receive the same service provided to a participant assigned to the intervention group i.e. health coaching.  Health coaches will have information available about the members derived from claims data and will have all the same educational resources at their disposal as they do for the intervention group.  The health coaches will not have specific information that identifies control group members as such. Regardless of level of interaction with health coaches, all individuals assigned to the Control will be analysed as such. 

It is worth noting that experience in other settings leads us to believe that the proportions of individuals who will actively seek Health Coach engagement with mailed outreach only will be very small, 3% or less.  This will enable the differentiation of service levels between the intervention and control to be quite high. To ensure this is the case in the Australian setting, the number of members falling into this category will be reviewed on a six monthly basis.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is the total (non-maternity) cost for health fund members.  Cost in this study is measured from the perspective of a private health insurer. That being, the total benefit paid calculated as the summation of hospital, medical (excluding Medicare component) and prostheses. Ancillary benefits will not be included as the role of the intervention in impacting on a range of benefits including dental and optical is not sufficiently well defined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly until paid claims have accrued for a full 12 month period after he or she is randomized into intervention and control.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Costs (non-maternity) per member in the intervention year by type of service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly until paid claims have accrued for a full 12 month period after he or she is randomized into intervention and control.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of inpatient (non-maternity) hospitalisations in total in the intervention  year. Outcome is assessed based on data linkage to private insurance claims.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after he or she is randomized into intervention and control.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Same day non- maternity admission rates in the intervention year. Outcome is assessed based on data linkage to private insurance claims.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after he or she is randomized into intervention and control.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of non-maternity inpatient bed days in the intervention year. Outcome is assessed based on data linkage to private insurance claims.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after he or she is randomized into intervention and control</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hold hospital cover with Bupa Australia (and have done so for at least 12 months continuously immediately prior to recruitment);

Have claims evidence of  diagnosis of low back pain, diabetes, coronary artery disease, congestive heart failure, or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease;

Are the highest risk member of their household based on predicted  risk; and 

Have claims-based predicted  risk level above a pre-determined threshold of 0.061. This is equivalent to a predicted cost for the following 12 months of $3,050 or more.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any individual who shares a household with a previously assigned study subject;

Individuals targeted by Bupa Health Dialog for similar services prior to study initiation (the COACH program for cardiovascular disease, the Genesis Heart Care program for quality improvement, and the Medibank Health Solutions Psychiatric Program); 

Individuals involved in other potentially related chronic disease management programs through Bupa Australia prior to study initiation

Individuals with claims evidence prior to study initiation of: End Stage Renal Disease, AIDS, Haemophilia, Necrotizing fasciitis, organ transplant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects are identified for enrolment each month based on qualification of inclusion criteria including a minimum risk score of 0.061. This is equivalent to a predicted cost for the following 12 months of $3,050 or more.

Risk scores are recalculated monthly based on new claims data that becomes available. Each month, a sample of subjects who meet the inclusion criteria are randomly selected using SAS Surveyselect procedure (SAS statistical software version 9.1.3). The proportion selected from those who meet the inclusion criteria is dependent on the capacity of the health coaches.

A total target population of at least 36,000 recruited; a sampling ratio of 4 intervention group participants for every one control group participants.

A stratified random allocation design is used to produce concordance between the intervention and control groups on baseline demographics and risk score. The strata selected for the randomisation are the five chronic conditions.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation was created using SAS Surveyselect procedure (SAS statistical software version 9.1.3) with the default simple random sampling option and stratified by chronic condition with a 4:1 allocation ratio to intervention
and control. 

For each monthly batch of data, a seed value of nine digits was obtained by the statistician using random number generator with replacement from 0 to 9 for each of the nine digits. The Surveyselect procedure generates uniform random numbers using a prime modulus multiplicative generator with modulus 231 and multiplier 397204094. This means that it is very unlikely randomisation will be repeated.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/05/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/06/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>47310</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>48397</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/06/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>BUPA Health Dialog</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>801 Glenferrie Road
Hawthorne NSW 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BUPA Foundation (Australia)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Bridge St
Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>BUPA Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>50 Bridge St
Sydney NSW 2000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Griffith University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Medicine
Logan Campus L03 2.43
Griffith University
Meadowbrook 4131
Queensland,</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A prospective study of 36,000 subjects will be undertaken to assess the impact of a chronic disease management services encompassing population analytics and telephone health coaching on health service utilisation and costs. Identification and predictive models based on health fund administrative data will be used to identify subjects with selected chronic conditions (congestive heart failure, coronary artery disease, diabetes, low back pain, coronary obstructive pulmonary disease) who have high likelihood of future health utilisation and costs in the subsequent twelve months. These subjects will be randomly assigned to either receive active outreach including outbound phone calls to encourage program participation or to receive only basic information about the program. Health coaching will be delivered over the phone, by specially trained and qualified nurses and tailored to the individuals need. It aims to empower subjects through goal setting and support.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Byrnes JM, Goldstein S, Venator B, Pollicino C, Ng SK, Veroff D, Bennett C, Scuffham PA. The impact of population-based disease management services for selected chronic conditions: the Costs to Australian Private Insurance--Coaching Health (CAPICHe) study protocol. BMC Public Health 2012; 12(114):1-6</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>GRIFFITH UNIVERSITY HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics
Office for Research
Room 3.55
Building G39
Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus
Parklands, Qld 4222</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MED/12/11/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Scuffham</name>
      <address>Centre for Applied Health Economics, N78_2.42 Nathan Campus, Griffith University, Nathan, Qld 4111, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 373 59132</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.scuffham@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Paul Scuffham</name>
      <address>Centre for Applied Health Economics, N78_2.42 Nathan Campus, Griffith University, Nathan, Qld 4111, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 373 59132</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.scuffham@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joshua Byrnes</name>
      <address>Centre for Applied Health Economics, N78_1.11 Nathan Campus, Griffith University, Nathan, Qld 4111, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 373 59107</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.byrnes@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Scuffham</name>
      <address>Centre for Applied Health Economics, N78_2.42 Nathan Campus, Griffith University, Nathan, Qld 4111, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 373 59132</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.scuffham@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>