<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369602">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000139471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Chilled Plus Program: Helping Adolescents with Anxiety and Depression. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Feasibility and Outcome of Internet Delivery of Transdiagnostic Cognitive-Behaviour Therapy for Adolescent Anxiety and Depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1176-3545</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Chilled Plus program is a cognitive behavioural treatment that incorporates the latest research in working with negative emotions. The program consists of 8 online modules accompanied by weekly phone calls with a trained therapist. The treatment targets anxiety and depression symptoms. Modules are released on a weekly basis (adolescents complete one module per week before their phone session). All together there is around 4 hours of work to do each week including the module, completing homework tasks and engaging in the phone calls. 

Module one provides psycho-education on the cycle of anxiety and depression, avoidance and managing emotions. It includes videos of people that have stories about their worries and moods (actors), and covers handling suicidal feelings. 

Module two explores identifying avoidance patterns, developing goals and exploring values, identifying motivation levels and developing a list of enjoyable activities to begin regularly participating in. 

Module three looks at the cost and benefits of avoidance, teaches the steps to goal-directed action to overcome avoidance and introduces the concept of stepladders. 

Module four includes a review of the first stepladder created and making a plan for the next steps over the coming weeks. It includes common problems to stepladders and possible solutions. It also teaches new skills to work with negative emotions, and explores developing creative ways to boost motivation. 

Module five highlights common thinking mistakes (e.g. catastrophising, filtering, overgeneralising, etc.) made by people with anxious or depressed feelings, teaches the basic steps of realistic thinking and continues with planning the next steps of the adolescents stepladder. 

Module six covers different types of coping strategies and problem solving, as well as assertiveness training and how to handle teasing and bullying. 

Module seven looks at how to overcome loneliness, how to build relationships, how to deal with family problems and further review of the next steps on the adolescents stepladders. 

Module eight addresses what to do if things go wrong and symptoms reappear and looking to the future (e.g. further goal setting). It concludes with videos of the same people from module one talking about their lives since they used the skills in the program. 

Each module requires participants to complete worksheets, monitor their thoughts, feelings and actions and complete personal projects (e.g. stepladder practice, mindfulness practice, etc..). 

The phone calls with the adolescents occur once a week over the 8 week program and last for 25 minutes. The weekly phone calls with parents last 10 minutes, with the exception of Weeks 1, 5 and 8 consisting of 30 minute phone calls. These phone calls occur after the adolescents phone call. The aim of the calls with the adolescent is for the therapist to support the adolescent, help them problem solve any difficulties they might be experiencing in the program and to provide them with someone to talk to if things are difficult. The 10 minute phone calls with parents aims to provide a check in on how the child is going and how they are progressing with the program and to answer any questions the parents have around how best to support their child. The parents may also present questions from the content provided in the parent companion. 

Treatment adherence for adolescents is monitored via data collected from the treatment website on login times, worksheet completion and pages viewed. Treatment adherence for clinicians is monitored via weekly supervision and the recording of all sessions for independent review to ensure treatment fidelity. </interventions>
    <comparator>A wait list control group is being utilised in the current study. Following the completion of an 8 week waiting period the participant receives the intervention. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of diagnoses as measured by the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for Children (ADIS-C; Silverman &amp; Albano, 1996) according to DSM-5 criteria. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnostic interviews will be conducted prior to group allocation, following the 8 week waiting period for the wait list group, immediately following treatment and three months following treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of diagnoses as measured by the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for Children (ADIS-C; Silverman &amp; Albano, 1996) according to DSM-5 criteria. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnostic interviews will be conducted prior to group allocation, following the 8 week waiting period for the wait list group, immediately following treatment and three months following treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure change in symptomatology via the Short Mood and Feelings Questionnaire (SMFQ; Sharp, Goodyer &amp; Croudace, 2006).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be administered prior to group allocation, following the 8 week waiting period for the wait list group, immediately following treatment and three months following treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure change in symptomatology via the Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (SCAS; Spence, 1998)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be administered prior to group allocation, following the 8 week waiting period for the wait list group, immediately following treatment and three months following treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure change in symptomatology via the Children's Automatic Thoughts Scale (CATS; Schniering &amp; Rapee, 2002)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be administered prior to group allocation, following the 8 week waiting period for the wait list group, immediately following treatment and three months following treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure change in symptomatology via the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SD; Goodman, 1997).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be administered prior to group allocation, following the 8 week waiting period for the wait list group, immediately following treatment and three months following treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure change in life interference via the Adolescent Life Interference Scale (ALIS; Schniering et al., 2013).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be administered prior to group allocation, following the 8 week waiting period for the wait list group, immediately following treatment and three months following treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Participants must meet DSM-5 criteria for both an anxiety disorder and a depressive disorder. 
2. Gender: male and female
3. Age range: 12-17 years
4. Willingness to provide informed consent and willingness to participate and comply with the study requirements. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Participants who are at current risk for suicide.
2. Participants who are actively self-harming
3. Participants with unmanaged psychotic symptoms
4. Participants in physically/sexually abusive environments.
5. Participants receiving pharmacological treatment who are not willing to keep medication stable throughout the duration of the study. 
6. Participants with bipolar depression. 
7. Participants who cannot speak english.
8. Participants with no access to the internet. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was "off-site" or at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation) was utilised. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study will consist of two groups: Active treatment and wait-list condition each of which will include approximately 60 treatment completer participants. Sixty subjects per group post treatment corresponds to a power of .85 at p = .05,  2-tailed for a moderately small effect size of .25, which is conservative power. 

Analysis plan: differences between groups will be examined using hierarchical mixed models containing random intercept and random slope terms as well as fixed effects for treatment received. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Carolyn Schniering</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Psychology,
Macquarie University,
Sydney. NSW. 2109
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>43 Hunter St, Parramatta NSW 2150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Ron Rapee</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Psychology,
Macquarie University,
Sydney. NSW. 2109
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Danielle Einstein</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Psychology,
Macquarie University,
Sydney. NSW. 2109
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Adolescents with a combination of anxiety and depression have especially severe symptoms that can cause major impact on their lives. While we already have good treatments for teenagers with either anxiety or depression alone, there are no good treatments currently available for adolescents with both problems. This trial will evaluate the effects of a new treatment for adolescents with mixed anxiety and depression that teaches them new ways of thinking, acting, and feeling. It is delivered over the internet and is assisted by 8 sessions with a therapist over the telephone. Adolescents will be randomly allocated to either receive the new treatment (called Chilled Plus) or to wait for 8 weeks (after which these adolescents will also get the program). We expect that those adolescents who immediately enter the program will show large reductions in anxiety and depression and improvements in quality of life. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>chilledplus.org.au </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Ethics Commitee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University,
Sydney. NSW. 2109
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201300828</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carolyn Schniering</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Sydney, NSW, 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 02 98506741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carolyn.schniering@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Kirkman</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Sydney, NSW, 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9850 6741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jess.kirkman@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carolyn Schniering</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Sydney, NSW, 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 02 98506741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carolyn.schniering@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Kirkman</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Sydney, NSW, 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9850 6741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jess.kirkman@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>