<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83309">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/10/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/12/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000608369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of aminophylline for infants less than 12 months of age with bronchiolitis, requiring admission to intensive care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of aminophylline in infants less than 12 months of age with bronchiolitis who require intensive care, to assess if aminophylline is superior to placebo in reducing the duration of ventilatory support.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bronchiolitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Aminophylline will be given, as a continuous infusion,  for 3 days (72 hours) or until discharge from the Intensive Care Unit, whichever is sooner</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (normal saline) will be given, as continuous infusion,  for 3 days (72 hours) or until discharge from the Intensive Care Unit, whichever is sooner</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of respiratory support (mechanical ventilation or nasal continuous positive pressure).  This information will be recorded manually by the treating physician on documentation provided.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days (120 hours) from admission to ICU, or until discharge from the Intensive Care Unit: whichever is sooner.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay in the Intensive Care Unit.  This information will be recorded manually by the treating physician on documentation provided.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from the Intensive Care Unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of children requiring mechanical ventilation.  Type of ventilatory support will be recorded manually by the treating physician on documentation provided.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days (120 hours) from admission to Intensive Care Unit, or until discharge from ICU: whichever is sooner.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of children receiving any form of respiratory support (including nasal continuous positive pressure).  Type of ventilatory support will be recorded manually by the treating physician on documentation provided.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days (120 hours) from admission to ICU, or until discharge from ICU: whichever is sooner.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clinical diagnosis of bronchiolitis, defined as a first or second episode of wheezing or respiratory distress associated with an upper respiratory tract infection
Admission to a paediatric intensive care unit</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Contraindication to aminophylline (previous severe reaction, previous atrial or ventricular arrythmia, previous seizures, previous liver dysfunction)
Episode of apnoea requiring treatment with aminophylline
Previous admission to the study
Pertussis isolated on nasopharyngeal aspirate</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/10/2002</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/09/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>274</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>45</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Frank Shann</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Childrens' Hospital,
50, Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Society (ANZICS) Foundation.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10 Ievers Terrace  Carlton
Victoria  3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bronchiolitis is a common, acute, viral infection of the lower respiratory tract. It is mostly seen in children less than 1 year of age, but does affect children up to 2 years of age. Each year, several children with severe bronchiolitis need admission to the intensive care unit. These children experience significant breathing difficulty and around 50% are ill enough to need help with breathing through a breathing machine called a mechanical ventilator. The normal treatment for these children is to support their breathing, and to give them adequate nutrition and fluids. Aminophylline is a medicine we know from previous research that improves the function of the diaphragm, the major breathing muscle. Aminophylline also stimulates the respiratory centre in the brain, which stimulates the body to breathe. This tells us that aminophylline might be a helpful drug to use when treating children with severe bronchiolitis. Some doctors use this medicine because they believe it works. Others do not use this medicine because they do not believe it works. 
The purpose of this research project is to see whether aminophylline makes a difference in the treatment of children with bronchiolitis. We will compare a group of children who receive the standard treatment for bronchiolitis with a group of children who receive the standard treatment and aminophylline. We will compare the duration of mechanical ventilation and the length of intensive care and hospital stay in both groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Trial published as Turner A, Shann F, Delzoppo C, Henning R, Slater A, Beca J, Erickson S, Butt W. A multicentre, randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of aminophylline for bronchiolitis in infants admitted to intensive care. Critical Care and Resuscitation 2014 Sep; 16(3): 220-224.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital, Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>50, Flemington Road, Parkville
Victoria 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Frank Shann</name>
      <address>Royal Childrens' Hospital,
50, Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455220</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shannf@netspace.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Frank Shann</name>
      <address>Royal Childrens' Hospital,
50, Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455220</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shannf@netspace.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Frank Shann</name>
      <address>Royal Childrens' Hospital,
50, Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455220</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shannf@netspace.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Frank Shann</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit, Royal Children's Hospital, Parkville, Victoria 3052, Australia</address>
      <phone>61 3 93291079</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shannf@netspace.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>