<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362697">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000707864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes in mens health after bariatric surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A questionnaire-based study of the self-reported health and quality of life of severely obese men seeking bariatric surgery, before and 1 year after primary bariatric surgery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-2172</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sexual function</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of life</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bariatric surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a questionnaire-based study of 140 severely obese men from around Australia who will have elected to undergo bariatric surgery for weight loss and will undergo routine pre- and post-surgical clinical care. All data will be collected in a coded and de-identified format.
Before surgery, each participant will complete questionnaires about sexual, occupational and social function and quality of life. Anthropometric, demographic, medical and medication history information will also be collected from the surgical practice where the participant was recruited. 
All questionnaires and data collection will be repeated 12 months after bariatric surgery.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in sexual function, assessed by change in score on the International index of erectile function (IIEF), with a 3.0-point improvement being clinically relevant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will complete the IIEF at baseline and 1 year post-bariatric surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in quality of life, assessed by percentage change in total scores and scores on each scale of the SF-36 and work productivity, assessed by percentage change in scores on the Endicott Work Productivity Scale (EWPS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will complete the SF-36 and EWPS at baseline and 1 year post-bariatric surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The relationship between baseline anthropometry, medical history and medication use and changes in sexual function (assessed using the IIEF), assessed using linear regression and logistic regression, in exploratory analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will complete the IIEF at baseline and 1 year post-bariatric surgery. The change in score between timepoints will be explored in the context of baseline medical history, anthropometry and medication use.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The relationship between baseline anthropometry, medical history and medication use and changes in quality of life(assessed using the SF-36), assessed using linear regression and logistic regression, in exploratory analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will complete the SF-36 at baseline and 1 year post-bariatric surgery. The change in score between timepoints will be explored in the context of baseline medical history, anthropometry and medication use.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The relationship between percentage weight loss and changes in sexual function (assessed using the IIEF).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will complete the IIEF at baseline and 1 year post-bariatric surgery and will have bodyweights recorded at baseline and 1 year, allowing percentage weight loss to be calculated.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The relationship between percentage weight loss and changes in quality of life(assessed using the SF36).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants will complete the SF-36 at baseline and 1 year post-bariatric surgery and will have bodyweights recorded at baseline and 1 year, allowing percentage weight loss to be calculated.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The cross-sectional associations between demographic (marital status, employment, ethnicity), anthropometric (weight, BMI, waist circumference)and comorbidity characteristics (medical history, medication use, HADS questionnaire for symptoms of anxiety and depression), and sexual dysfunction (assessed using IIEF) and poor quality of life (assessed via SF-36 and EWPS) in severely obese men. General linear regression and logistic regression analyses will be performed, in an exploratory manner.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measures will be recorded at baseline and 1 year post-surgery, but for this exploratory analysis, only baseline data will be considered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Severely obese men presenting for any primary bariatric surgery.
Aged 18 years or over.
Eligible for bariatric surgery according to the criteria of the surgical practice through which they are enrolled.
Able to give written informed consent for participation in the study which includes completing questionnaires at 1 year after surgery.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Men taking any medications or undergoing other therapy specifically for erectile dysfunction.
Men who have previously had any form of bariatric surgery.
Men who do not have the capacity to give written informed consent for their involvement in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/05/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>24/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>37</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2153</postcode>
    <postcode>2217</postcode>
    <postcode>3155</postcode>
    <postcode>3123</postcode>
    <postcode>4305</postcode>
    <postcode>4120</postcode>
    <postcode>2290</postcode>
    <postcode>2065</postcode>
    <postcode>4066</postcode>
    <postcode>3121</postcode>
    <postcode>6150</postcode>
    <postcode>4812</postcode>
    <postcode>3016</postcode>
    <postcode>3128</postcode>
    <postcode>2600</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne  VIC  3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Allergan</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4
810 Pacific Highway
Gordon, NSW 2072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity has become a worldwide public health problem and severe obesity causes among other things, impaired quality of life above and beyond the impact of medical complications of the disease. Evidence links obesity with low self-esteem, poor body image, sexual dysfunction, and  poor quality-of-life, while lifestyle changes and weight loss may improve these parameters.
The aim of this study is to examine sexual function and overall quality of life among men with obesity. There is currently little known about the obesity-related health problems that are specific to Australian men, and we think it is likely that men have significant health concerns. We also believe that weight loss after bariatric surgery may significantly improve mens health, sexual function and quality of life. In order to investigate this, we are asking men who are planning to have bariatric surgery to complete a set of surveys before their surgery and again 1-year after their surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Building 3E, Room 111
Monash University Clayton Campus
Clayton  VIC  3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/02/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF09/3250 - 2009001771</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Health Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital 
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne  VIC  3004
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>210/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Dixon  </name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne  VIC  3004
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1115</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>john.dixon@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Dixon  </name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne  VIC  3004
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1115</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>john.dixon@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Dixon</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne  VIC  3004
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1115</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1100</fax>
      <email>john.dixon@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Dixon</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne  VIC  3004
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.dixon@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>