<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365225">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001203741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pre-emptive intravenous ketorolac analgesia does not alter the risk of bleeding after tonsillectomy in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>the preoperative use of intravenous ketorolac analgesia does not alter the risk of bleeding after tonsillectomy in children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>the use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs for post-tonsillectomy analgesia in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions> children scheduled for tonsillectomy with or without adenoidectomy were randomized to receive a slow IV infusion over 15 min of either Ketorolac 1mg kg -1, after induction of anesthesia.</interventions>
    <comparator>the control treatment was a slow IV infusion over 15 min of  Paracetamol 15 mg kg-1, after induction of anesthesia.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measures was the difference between the two groups as regards the hemoglobin level. Hemoglobin (Hb) level was measured in the laboratory as a part of the routine preoperative preparation for tonsillectomy at the hospital. Additionally, non-invasive hemoglobin level (SpHb) was assessed at the same time when blood was drawn from the child for the routine preoperative laboratory investigations, using a multi-wavelength pulse oximetry.SpHb measurement was assessed on arrival at the post anesthesia care unit (PACU) and repeated at 12h, 24h postoperatively and another measurement was obtained at the 7th postoperative day. </outcome>
      <timepoint>the 7th postoperative day</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> the difference between the two groups as regards the pain scores  ., pain intensity was assessed by an anesthesiologist,  blinded to the treatment group using an objective pain score (OPS) immediately upon PACU admission, then 30min, 1h, 2h, 4h, and 6h postoperatively. This OPS  took into account the childs blood pressure, crying, movement and agitation, with each variable scoring 02 points (best to worst). </outcome>
      <timepoint>6h postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of postoperative vomiting </outcome>
      <timepoint>24h after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ASA physical status I children scheduled for tonsillectomy with or without adenoidectomy. All patients enrolled in this study had normal blood counts, with normal coagulation profile (prothrombin time, activated partial thromboplastin time, platelet count, and bleeding time.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>7</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> Exclusion criteria included the use of paracetamol or NSAIDs within 6 h or any other analgesic medication within 12 h before surgery, and a known allergy to any of the study drugs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The required sample size was calculated using the G*Power(copyright) software version 3.1.0 (Institut fur Experimentelle Psychologie, Heinrich Heine Universitat, Dusseldorf, Germany).
The primary outcome measures were the difference between the two groups as regards the pain scores and hemoglobin level. It was estimated that a sample of 70 patients per group would have a power of 82% to detect a medium effect size (d) of 0.5 as regards the outcome measures using a two-sided U test and setting the type I error at 0.05.
Data were analyzed on a personal computer using the IBM(copyright) SPSS(copyright) Statistics version 21 (IBM(copyright)Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). The Shapiro-Wilk test was used to test the normality of numerical data distribution. 
Normally distributed data were presented as mean (SD) and the unpaired t test was used for intergroup comparisons. Skewed data were presented as median (interquartile range) and the Mann-Whitney U test was used to compare between-group differences. For comparison of paired skewed data, the Wilcoxon signed ranks test was used. Repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare differences among serial measures.
Categorical data were presented as ratio or as number (percentage) and differences between the two groups were compared using the chi square test or Fishers exact test, when appropriate.
P &lt; 0.05 is considered statistically significant. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/12/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/12/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/05/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>147</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <state>eastern province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname> king Abdulaziz Naval Base Hospital. </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>king Abdulaziz Naval Base , Jubail, 31951 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> king Abdulaziz Naval Base Hospital. </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> king Abdulaziz Naval Base , Jubail, 31951 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Saudi Arabia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background
Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) inhibit platelet aggregation and prolong bleeding time, which may increase the risk of postoperative bleeding. We investigated the effects of ketorolac (a NSAID) on intra- and postoperative hemorrhage with pediatric tonsillectomy.
Methods 
One hundred forty seven children, aged 2-7 years scheduled for tonsillectomy with or without adenoidectomy were randomized to receive a slow IV infusion over 15 min of either Ketorolac 1mg kg -1 (Group K, n=74) or Paracetamol 15 mg kg-1(Group P, n=73) after induction of anesthesia. Perioperative non-invasive hemoglobin (SpHb) was assessed preoperatively and several times after surgery. Bleeding times were measured before and after surgery. Intraoperative blood loss was estimated. Intensity of postoperative pain was measured using an  objective pain scores (OPS). Incidence and severity of post-tonsillectomy bleeding (PTB) were recorded till the 7thpostoperative day.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hospital Ethics and research Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>king Abdulaziz Naval Base Hospital, Jubail 31951.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Saudi Arabia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Waleed M. Abdelmageed</name>
      <address>king Abdulaziz Naval Base Hospital , Jubail, 31951,PO Box:413                                          
                                                              </address>
      <phone>+966 55 7189366</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>walidabdelmageed@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Waleed M. Abdelmageed</name>
      <address> king Abdulaziz Naval Base Hospital , Jubail, 31951,PO Box:413  </address>
      <phone>+966 55 7189366</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>walidabdelmageed@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Waleed M. Abdelmageed</name>
      <address>  king Abdulaziz Naval Base Hospital , Jubail, 31951,PO Box:413</address>
      <phone>+966 55 7189366</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>walidabdelmageed@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Waleed M. Abdelmageed</name>
      <address>   king Abdulaziz Naval Base Hospital , Jubail, 31951,PO Box:413</address>
      <phone>+966 55 7189366</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>walidabdelmageed@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>