<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362950">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000919819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot randomised controlled trial of electronic screening and brief intervention (e-SBI) to increase uptake of referral for specialist care among hospital outpatients with possible alcohol dependence</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Among hospital outpatients who screen positive for possible alcohol dependence, are those randomly assigned to receive electronic screening and brief intervention (e-SBI) more likely than those assigned to screening alone to accept or attend an outpatient appointment for further assessment?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention comprises 5-10 minutes of electronic motivational assessment and personalised feedback on alcohol consumption via an iPad. Specifically, participants in the intervention group complete: the 10-item Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT); questions concerning the largest number of standard drinks consumed on one occasion in the last four weeks, the duration of the drinking episode in hours, and body weight for the purpose of estimating their blood alcohol concentration; and the 10-item Leeds Dependence Questionnaire (LDQ).

On completion of the above, participants in the intervention group will receive personalised feedback comprising the following:
(i) the patients AUDIT score and guidance on its meaning;
(ii) an estimated blood alcohol concentration (BAC) for their heaviest episode in the previous month with information on the behavioural and physiological sequelae of various BACs, and traffic crash relative risk;
(iii) estimates of spending per month;
(iv) a bar graph comparing episodic consumption with medical recommendations, and that of adults of the same age and gender;
(v) a bar graph comparing weekly consumption with medical recommendations, and with adults of the same age and gender;
(vi) an LDQ score with an explanation of the associated health risk and information about how to reduce that risk.

Further web pages will be presented as options, offering facts about alcohol, tips for reducing the risk of alcohol-related harm, and information as to where medical help and counselling support could be found.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group only completes the first 3 items of the AUDIT, known as the AUDIT Consumption subscale (AUDIT-C). Subjects in the control group will not receive personalised feedback.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion who accept an appointment at the Drug and Alcohol Outpatient Clinic.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion who attend the appointment at the Drug and Alcohol Outpatient Clinic.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of standard drinks in the past week assessed by a 7-day retrospective diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUDIT score with a reference period of the past 6 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of drinking days in the past week assessed by a 7-day retrospective diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of standard drinks per drinking day in the past week assessed by a 7-day retrospective diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion who exceed 2009 NHMRC recommended upper limits for risk of acute harm (no more than 4 drinks per occasion) in the past week assessed by a 7-day retrospective diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion who exceed 2009 NHMRC recommended upper limits for risk of chronic harm (no more than 14 drinks per week) in the past week assessed by a 7-day retrospective diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported use of services to reduce drinking.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients attending the Ambulatory Care Centre will be eligible for inclusion if they are 18 years of age or older, live in the Hunter New England Local Health District, provide informed consent, and screen positive for possible alcohol dependence indicated by an AUDIT-C score &gt; 9.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who cannot read English, unable to self-administer the e-SBI instrument via an iPad, or are moving to an unknown address during the next 12 months (ie., will be lost to follow-up) will not be recruited.

Following screening, participants will be excluded if they:
(i) have not consumed any alcohol in the past 12 months;
(ii) report they are currently receiving treatment for their drinking;
(iii) do not screen positive for possible alcohol dependence (AUDIT-C &lt;10);</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research assistants located in one of the waiting areas in the Ambulatory Care Centre (ACC) will be trained in the application of a study protocol stipulating they should invite the next patient leaving the reception desk (awaiting a medical consultation) to participate in the study, obtain informed consent, and log the participant onto an iPad. When the participant has finished with the iPad, the research assistant will return to the reception desk to recruit the next patient. In the event that there are no patients leaving the reception desk (for a period of 5 minutes), research assistants will invite patients occupying particular seats in rotation around the waiting area (clockwise and then anticlockwise). As randomisation after screening will be effected by computer, research staff will not be aware of participants’ group allocations. Participants will be blind to the true nature of the study also as they will be asked to consent to participate in a series of surveys rather than a trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Kypros Kypri</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4 West
HMRI Bldg
CALLAGHAN NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
CANBERRA ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is little evidence on how to care for patients with alcohol dependence who are not seeking treatment for their drinking. Research has shown that only a small proportion of such patients take up a referral for specialist care. This pilot study, utilising the NHMRC funded "Hospital Outpatients Alcohol Project" framework, will determine the feasibility of conducting a large trial designed to establish whether e-SBI can increase uptake of specialist care in this group of patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No.1
NEW LAMBTON NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/05/16/4.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Integrity Unit
HA148, Hunter Building
The University of Newcastle
CALLAGHAN NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2012-0272</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Kypros Kypri</name>
      <address>Level 4 West
HMRI Bldg
CALLAGHAN NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61,2,40420536</phone>
      <fax>+61,2,40420044</fax>
      <email>Kypros.Kypri@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Kypros Kypri</name>
      <address>Level 4 West
HMRI Bldg
CALLAGHAN NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61,2,40420536</phone>
      <fax>+61,2,40420044</fax>
      <email>Kypros.Kypri@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Natalie Johnson</name>
      <address>Level 4 West
HMRI Bldg
CALLAGHAN NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61,2,40420552</phone>
      <fax>+61,2,40420044</fax>
      <email>Natalie.Johnson@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>