<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365507">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000068662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Patient safety in Public Primary Care Clinics in Malaysia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Community Trial using Multi-pronged Systems-based Interventions to Improve Medical Errors In Ministry of Health Primary Care Clinics with comparison clinics</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111111513983</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NMRR-07-770-1042 
(Registered in www.nmrr.gov.my)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patient Safety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intention of developing the intervention package was to reduce or to prevent medical errors in primary care. This included diagnostic errors and management errors. The research team emphasised practicality and sustainability of the intervention package for the improvement of care in primary care setting.

The intervention package consisted of the following: training, audit process, pharmacy safe netting and materials specially designed for use during the implementation of the intervention.

The intervention package consisted of educational training, structured process change, additional review methods and patient education.  The educational training was a 3-day workshop to the intervention group. Structured process changes included a clinic desktop flip chart (with rapid diagnostic and management guides), formatted paper records (new case sheet, continuation, asthma record sheet, hypertension record sheet, hypertension follow-up record), provision of peak flow meters, and carbon paper for copying prescriptions onto records. The Integrated Management of Childhood Illnesses Mothers card, an educational pamphlet on child health to improve parents recognition of danger symptoms and signs in children, were given when applicable.  

Prescription safety net was done to identify errors and to provide immediate feedback to prescribers. Monthly clinical audit by primary care physicians with health care providers were used for review with immediate feedback to rectify errors and monitoring and to reinforce intervention. Personnel were interviewed to provide feedback on the intervention package. 

Fidelity checks on processes and the availability of materials were conducted monthly throughout the intervention. Three months after the intervention implementation, medical records were randomly sampled from 12 clinics and  expert panel sessions were convened to review the medical records for errors.
 
The total duration of the intervention was 3 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Current Usual practice</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic errors:	Errors deemed to have occurred when the history or physical examination did not match the problem or diagnosis stated in the medical records.

Random samples of outpatient records were selected and reviewed by trained family physicians (expert panel review).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post implementation of intervention package</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Management errors:	Errors deemed to have occurred if there was an error in investigation, medication or in the decision making process.

Random samples of outpatient records were selected and reviewed by trained family physicians (expert panel review).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post implementation of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Likelihood of errors to cause serious morbidity/mortality	 for both short and long term complications, as assessed for each record by a team of two expert panel reviewers.

Random samples of outpatient records were selected and reviewed by trained family physicians (expert panel review).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post implementation of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preventability of error:	Assessed on a 6-point scale from virtually no evidence for preventability to virtually certain of evidence for preventability.
Random samples of outpatient records were selected and reviewed by trained family physicians (expert panel review).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post implementation of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Primary care centres were selected based on the stratification criteria (geographical location: Peninsular Malaysia and Sabah/Sarawak; highest category of personnel manning the clinic: Family Medicine Specialists, Medical Officers and Assistant Medical Officers [Medical Assistants]).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Did not consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A community trial, intervention was allocated to specific clinics, and all patients/health care providers and managers at the participating clinics received the intervention</concealment>
    <sequence>not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A health systems research that involved multipronged interventions targetted mainly at modifying the behaviours of the health care providers and managers</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Proportions and confidence intervals, with pooled estimated across centres using meta analysis.

Sampling:
The participating regions were conveniently selected due to cost concern, but within each region, the intervention clinics were randomly chosen, with the corresponding control clinics selected to match the intervention clinics in terms of clinic type and general set up.

To detect the difference of 10% between 2 study groups (case and controls): P0=0.05 (5% improvement in control group) and P1=0.15 (15% improvement in intervention group) , with alpha 0.05 and power of 80%, we need a sample size of 140 in each group. With consideration of dropout rate of 10-15%, we decide to take 160 in each group . 
Details of the parameters used in the calculation are below: 
P0=0.05 (5% improvement)
P1=0.15 (15% improvement)
alpha= 0.05, Power= 80%
M=1 (equal sample size for 2 study groups), Ratio of 2 groups = 1:1
N1= 140 (intervention) + 10% = 154 (round up to 160)
N2= 140 (control) + 10% = 164 (round up to 160)
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/05/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/05/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2008</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/06/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1920</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health Malaysia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Institutes of Health Secretariat
Ministry of Health Malaysia,
Institute for Health Management
Jalan RUmah Sakit Bangsar
50590 Kuala LUmpur
Malaysia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NIH Research Grant, Ministry of Health Malaysia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Institutes of Health Secretariat
Ministry of Health Malaysia,
Institute for Health management
Jalan RUmah Sakit Bangsar
50590 Kuala LUmpur
Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A controlled interventional study was conducted in 12 conveniently selected health centres. A preliminary managerial clinical audit done April 2007 had showed numerous deficiencies.  

Results were used to design an intervention package that  emphasized sustainability, supervision and incorporation of existing systems/mechanisms. This intervention was implemented in 6 clinics from March to May 2008. 

Three months post intervention, medical records were randomly sampled from each clinic from May to June 2008. A second expert panel session was convened to review the medical records selected post-intervention. Medical records were retrieved and assessed. Each medical record was reviewed by two Family Medicine Specialists (expert panel review) for diagnostic and management errors. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research &amp; Ethics Committee, Malaysia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Medical Research &amp; Ethics Committee, Malaysia
NIH Secretariat, 
Institute for Health Management
Jalan Rumah Sakit Bangsar'
50590 Kuala LUmpur
Malaysia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/06/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MREC MRG-07-LOI-HSR-1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Khoo Ee Ming</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Care Medicine, 
University of Malaya Primary Care Research Group,  
Faculty of Medicine, 
University of Malaya, 
Jalan Lembah Pantai, 
50590 Kuala Lumpur </address>
      <phone>+60379581376</phone>
      <fax>+603-79577941</fax>
      <email>khooem@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sondi Sararaks</name>
      <address>Health Outcomes Research
Institute for Health Systems Research
Ministry of Health Malaysia
Suites. 55-1,  55-2, 55-4, 55-4 Setia Avenue, 
No. 2 Jalan Setia Prima S U13/S
Seksyen U13 Setia Alam
40170 Shah Alam,
Selangor</address>
      <phone>+603-3359 6006</phone>
      <fax>+603-3359 6015</fax>
      <email>sararaks.s@ihsr.gov.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Khoo Ee Ming</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Care Medicine, 
University of Malaya Primary Care Research Group,  
Faculty of Medicine, 
University of Malaya, 
Jalan Lembah Pantai, 
50590 Kuala Lumpur 
Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60379581376</phone>
      <fax>+603-79577941</fax>
      <email>khooem@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sondi Sararaks</name>
      <address>Health Outcomes Research
Institute for Health Systems Research
Ministry of Health Malaysia
Suites. 55-1,   Setia Avenue, 
No. 2 Jalan Setia Prima S U13/S
Seksyen U13 Setia Alam
40170 Shah Alam,
Selangor</address>
      <phone>+603-3359 6006</phone>
      <fax>+603 3359 6015</fax>
      <email>sararaks.s@ihsr.gov.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>