<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368146">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000241538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Writing for Health: A randomised controlled trial of an online benefit-finding writing intervention for adults with type 1 or type 2 diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of an online benefit-finding writing intervention versus an online use-of-time writing intervention in reducing diabetes distress in adults with type 1 or type 2 diabetes mellitus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 and Type 2 diabetes mellitus
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes self-care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two web-based interventions on the Writing for Health online program:
Arm 1) Benefit-finding writing: Participants are asked to write online about any positive thoughts and feelings about their experience with diabetes.
Arm 2) Use of time writing (active control condition): Participants are asked to write in detail about how their time was spent that day and plans for how their time will be spent the following day and week. 

Both interventions involve participants writing online, on the Internet-based Writing for Health program, for 15 minutes once a day, for three consecutive days. 

Participants are asked to rate their current mood online immediately before and after each online writing session.

Participants will be sent automated emails reminding them to log on when they are due to complete a writing session or an online follow-up questionnaire.

The Writing for Health program involves an online information and consent procedure, online screening questionnaires with automatic feedback and online registration for eligible participants who provide informed consent to participate.
Participants will complete online questionnaires at pre-program, during the program, post-program and at one-month and three-month follow-up.  

Participants in both arms are provided with feedback on their score categories (eg mild) on measures of symptoms of depression and anxiety, at baseline, one-month and three-month follow-up.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator intervention is the active control condition of writing online about use of time. Participants are asked to write in detail about how their time was spent that day and plans for how their time will be spent the following day and week. 

Both the intervention group and the active control group are asked to write online for 15 minutes per day, once a day, for three consecutive days.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes distress as measured by the Diabetes Distress Scale.  The Diabetes Distress Scale is a 17-item self-report measure of psychosocial stress associated with diabetes  and includes four reliable subscales: emotional burden, physician-related distress, regime-related distress and interpersonal distress.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Benefit finding in diabetes, as measured by the Benefit Finding Scale-Diabetes.  The 17-item Benefit Finding Scale was developed to assess benefit finding in women with breast cancer, and has previously been adapted for use in diabetes.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes self-care as measured by the Summary of Diabetes Self-Care measure.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety symptoms, measured by the GAD-7</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression symptoms, measured by the PHQ-9</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-care utilisation, assessed by asking participants to report the number of times they have visited a doctor or other healthcare professional over the past month.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-rated health, assessed by the single item In general, how would you rate your health at present, with responses rated on a five-point scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month and 3 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Positive and negative affect, as measured by the 10-item International Positive and Negative Affect Schedule Short Form (I-PANAS-SF)  Immediate Version</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately before and after each of the three writing sessions  (within intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention satisfaction, as measured by the Feedback Questionnaire, which was developed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be aged 18 years or older, have ever received a diagnosis of type 1 or type 2 diabetes, live in Australia, have access to the Internet, provide informed consent and be able to register online using an email address.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have received a diagnosis of a psychotic or bipolar disorder or dementia; current significant symptoms of depression (scoring 10 or above on the PHQ-9) or anxiety (scoring 8 or above on the GAD-7); current suicidal ideation; history of self-harm or suicide attempt; current psychological therapy; difficulty reading or writing in English; inability to type for 15 minutes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Interested potential participants are invited on the Writing for Health website to read the Participant Information and to provide informed consent online in order to proceed.  

Potential participants are then asked to complete online screening questionnaires, which provide automatic feedback as to whether they are eligible to participate.  

Eligible participants can then register online and create an account with the Writing for Health program.  This process includes an automatic email being sent to the participant requesting activation of their account and a further automatic email confirming when registration is complete.  

Following registration, the participant is then asked to complete further online pre-intervention questionnaires.  Once completed, the participant is then informed of the condition to which they have been randomly allocated when they commence their intervention (the first writing session). The Writing for Health program software, developed using the University of New South Wales eHealth Authoring Tool, randomly allocates participants using a block design method. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated block design method</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Repeated measures ANOVA/mixed modelling.

Data will be analysed on an intention-to-treat basis.

Previous research has reported effect sizes ranging from small to large.  Assuming a medium effect size (i.e. GPower f(v) test = 0.40), power at 80%, significance set at 5% (p=.05), a sample of 73 will be required to demonstrate statistical significance.  However, allowing for a 30% attrition rate, we will recruit 104 participants. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>8/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>104</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>88</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>10/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faces in the Street: Urban Mental Health Research Institute, St Vincent’s Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 OBrien Centre, St Vincents Hospital, 390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Sydney, NSW 2010, AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Faces in the Street: Urban Mental Health Research Institute, St Vincent’s Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6 OBrien Centre, St Vincents Hospital, 390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Sydney, NSW 2010 AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Black Dog Institute building, Hospital Rd, Prince of Wales Hospital, Randwick, Sydney, NSW 2031, AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Black Dog Institute building, Hospital Rd, Prince of Wales Hospital, Randwick, Sydney, NSW, 2031, AUSTRALIA</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomised controlled trial will be conducted, using the online Writing for Health program, to examine the efficacy of Internet-based writing exercises focusing on benefit-finding in diabetes, versus an active control condition, in reducing diabetes distress and increasing perceived benefits of living with diabetes (primary outcomes) and reducing symptoms of depression and anxiety and increasing diabetes self-care and self-reported general health (secondary outomes).

Adults with type 1 or type 2 diabetes visiting the Writing for Health website, in response to advertisements, will be invited to participate in the study.  

Following informed consent and an online screening procedure, participants will be randomly allocated to one of two interventions: 
i) Benefit-finding: Writing about any positive thoughts of feelings about experiences with diabetes; or 
ii) Use of time: Writing about how time has been spent this day and will be spent next week.

Both interventions  in the Writing for Health program involve writing online for 15 minutes once a day, for three consecutive days. 

Participants will complete online questionnaires at pre-intervention, during the program, post-intervention, and at one and three month follow-ups.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://writingforhealth.ehat.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent’s Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, Level 6 deLacy Building, St Vincents Hospital, 390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010 AUSTRALIA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/SVH/379</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Wilhelm</name>
      <address>Faces in the Street: Urban Mental Health Research Institute and Consultation Liaison Psychiatry, St Vincent's Hospital

Level 4, O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Sydney, NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1540</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kay.wilhelm@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Joanna Crawford</name>
      <address>Faces in the Street: Urban Mental Health Research Institute  St Vincent's Hospital

Level 6, O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Sydney, NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>SVHS.WritingForHealth@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Joanna Crawford</name>
      <address>Faces in the Street: Urban Mental Health Research Institute  St Vincent's Hospital

Level 6, O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Sydney, NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>SVHS.WritingForHealth@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Joanna Crawford</name>
      <address>Faces in the Street: Urban Mental Health Research Institute  St Vincent's Hospital

Level 6, O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Sydney, NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>SVHS.WritingForHealth@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>