<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363461">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000033741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the DEAL Project  A Web-based intervention for co-occurring depression and alcohol use in young people </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The DEAL Project evaluation: A brief, Web-based intervention for co-occurring depression and problematic alcohol use in young people (18-25)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1138-3643 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>DEAL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>alcohol abuse/dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The DEAL Project program: This program is a 4-week (four hour long sessions) psychological treatment delivered entirely via the Internet. Participants access the web-based sessions from their home computer (or other preferred port for Internet access). Participant-selected pseudonym usernames/emails serve as their login code for the website, and will provide access to the screening tools and the DEAL Project (DEpression ALcohol) intervention. Content of the sessions include CBT and motivational enhancement strategies, in the form of the previously developed intervention for depression and alcohol misuse that was effective in reducing depression and alcohol use when provided in computer-delivered format (the SHADE program). Participants are asked to complete each session of DEAL Project Web-based intervention in sequence, a week apart, from the point of randomisation. The Website tracks participants progress through each weekly module, with automated email reminders sent to the participants nominated email address.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is attention-control condition program first developed for the ANU WellBeing Study in which participants read information about environmental health, nutrition, stroke, physical activity, medicines in the home, temperature extremes, oral health, blood pressure and cholesterol, heart health, bacteria and food-borne illnesses, calcium and back pain. In order to replicate the interactive component of the active treatment arm, participants also complete online questionnaires that probe health factors, physical and artistic activities, education and hobbies, social, financial, and family roles, work habits and stress, medications, pain and nutrition, and alcohol use. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression symptoms and diagnosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 5, 12, and 24 weeks after intervention commencement. Depression symptoms and diagnosis will be assessed using the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Drinking quantity/frequency.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 5, 12, and 24 weeks after intervention commencement. Drinking quantity/frequency will be assessed using the TOT-AL.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 5, 12, and 24 weeks after intervention commencement. Quality of Life will be assessed using the  Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL) scale.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DASS-21 anxiety</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 5, 12, and 24 weeks after intervention commencement using DASS-21.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DASS-21 stress</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 5, 12, and 24 weeks after intervention commencement using DASS-21.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hazardous alcohol use</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 5, 12, and 24 weeks after intervention commencement using Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>alcohol abuse/dependence symptomatology</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 5, 12, and 24 weeks after intervention commencement using the WHO Composite International Diagnostic Interview (CIDI).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Age of 18-25 years; (2) Current depressive symptoms (score of 7+ on DASS-21  Depression); (3) Harmful drinking as measured by the AUDIT (score of 8+) (4) Ability to access the Internet (either in the private residence of the participant, or willingness to use the public library/other suitable venue with Internet access); (5) Australian residency. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Psychotic symptoms lasting &gt;2 days; (2) Non-English speakers; (3) Serious risk of suicide (thoughts of suicide or a wish to commit suicide in past two weeks); (4) Daily use of cannabis/weekly use of amphetamines.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be automated within the program and therefore trial researchers will be blind to randomisation. Randomisation will be created using an online program, which can only be accessed after eligibility is confirmed. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised to one of the two study groups using the online program Research Randomizer (simple randomisation using computer software).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data coding and analysis will be carried out by the authors using available software packages. Data on screening, refusals, and dropout are coded and reported as per CONSORT, and primary analyses use intention-to-treat. Preliminary analyses check for any baseline or health service utilisation differences that may confound with condition effects; later analyses control for these as necessary. Categorical and continuous measures of outcome will be examined using mixed or marginal longitudinal models (i.e., mixed model repeated measures, generalised estimating equation modelling) as appropriate. These approaches enable the inclusion of participants with missing data, without using inferior techniques such as last observation carried forward, when data is missing at random. A completers analysis on all participants completing at least 75% of the modules will be undertaken as a secondary analysis. In addition, comparisons on selected demographic and clinical characteristics will be made between completers and those who dropped out of treatment, to help detect any biases in outcome measures. The potential effects of a number of covariates and confounders will be modelled in the major analyses (e.g. borderline symptoms (MSI-BPD), medication status, drug use index (OTI ), gender, involvement in additional mental health treatments).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/03/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>104</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/09/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mark Deady</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
2052 Sydney</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council
(NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of New South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of the study is to evaluate the DEAL Project program, a brief, Internet-based intervention specifically designed for people aged 18 to 25 years with depression and co-occurring problematic alcohol use. This will be the first RCT of an Internet-delivered treatment for comorbid depression and problematic alcohol use in any age group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.dealproject.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Deady M, Mills KL, Teesson M, Kay-Lambkin F. An Online Intervention for Co-Occurring Depression and Problematic Alcohol Use in Young People: Primary Outcomes From a Randomized Controlled Trial. J Med Internet Res 2016;18(3):e71. DOI: 10.2196/jmir.5178</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Secretariat
UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3, South Wing
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC12546</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mark Deady</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</address>
      <phone>+61293850320</phone>
      <fax>+61293850222</fax>
      <email>m.deady@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mark Deady</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293850320</phone>
      <fax>+61293850222</fax>
      <email>m.deady@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mark Deady</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293850320</phone>
      <fax>+61293850222</fax>
      <email>m.deady@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mark Deady</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293850320</phone>
      <fax>+61293850222</fax>
      <email>m.deady@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>