<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81672">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/11/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000461594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Female Sex Hormones over the Course of the Menstrual Cycle on Optimal CPAP Pressures Used in the Treatment of Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Female Sex Hormones over the Course of the Menstrual Cycle on Optimal Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) Pressures Used in the Treatment of Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) over 5 weeks at home. The patients will be experienced CPAP users and will also be reviewed on mask fit and knowledge of how use the CPAP machine prior to commencing the study. Positive air pressure is applied to the upper airway via a mask, respiratory tubing and CPAP machine interface to splint the pharynx during sleep every night for 5 weeks. The CPAP machine continuously records CPAP pressure levels, air leak, and respiratory events throughout each night. This recorded data will be downloaded onto a desktop computer at the end of the study period. The menstrual cycle will be followed using body temperature measurements (digital oral measurements) measured by the patients each morning at home immediately on arousal from sleep, and a weekly intravenous blood sample will be taken from the patients for competitive binding immunoassays of plasma progesterone and oestradiol levels.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Observing any changes in CPAP pressure requirement over five weeks (one menstrual cycle). Estimated that this will occur during the early Luteal phase of the menstrual cycle. The Luteal phase is defined as the period of time following the mid-cycle surge in Luteinising Hormone, and is associated with ovulation. The Luteal phase ends at the beginning of the following menses (menstrual period).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over five weeks (one menstrual cycle).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients will be required to note any changes in their normal daily activities as well as medication and alcohol or caffeine intake, in a daily journal supplied by the investigators for 5 weeks, to evaluate if there are any confounding factors that would affect airway patency, sleep quality or core body temperature.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pre-menopausal.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Other sleep disorderMenstrual cycle disorderTreatment with oral hormone replacementSevere medical, psychological or psychiatric co-morbidities.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute for Breathing and Sleep</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Breathing and Sleep</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is evidence to suggest that female sex hormone changes (primarily progesterone), during the luteal phase of the menstrual cycle, have protective effects against airway collapse in obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA), thus maintaining airway patency and preventing occlusion. In premenopausal women, who have a cyclical pattern of hormone concentrations over the menstrual cycle, OSA appears to be milder, suggesting that OSA is underdiagnosed in this population sub-group. The treatment of choice for OSA by most sleep physicians is continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), in which positive air pressure is applied to the upper airway via a mask to splint the pharynx during sleep. To date there appears to be no investigations into the effects of female sex hormones on CPAP pressures as a result of menstrual cycle stage. This study aims to determine whether there is a significant change in the optimal CPAP pressures delivered by an autotitrating CPAP machine over the course of the menstrual cycle in relation to changes in female sex hormones progesterone and oestradiol. For the purposes of this study, optimal pressure is defined as the pressure which is 95% of the maximum pressure delivered by an autotitrating CPAP machine over the sleep period (Pmax 95). Patients will be provided with a ResMed AutoSet (Ryde, Australia) CPAP machine for a period of 5 weeks. Each CPAP machine is capable of continuously recording CPAP pressure levels, air leak, and respiratory events throughout each night. This recorded data will be downloaded onto a desktop computer at the end of the study period. The menstrual cycle will be followed using body temperature measurements (digital oral measurements) measured by the patients each morning at home immediately on arousal from sleep, and a weekly intravenous blood sample will be taken from the patients for competitive binding immunoassays of plasma progesterone and oestradiol levels. Patients will be required to note any changes in their normal daily activities as well as medication and alcohol or caffeine intake, in a daily journal supplied by the investigators.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter-New England Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Colette Navin</name>
      <address>Institute for Breathing and Sleep
Austin Health
Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94963688</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>colette.navin@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Maree Barnes</name>
      <address>Institute for Breathing and Sleep
Austin Health
Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965756</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maree.barnes@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>