<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336011">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000987066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>STroke imAging Prevention and Treatment (START): PrePARE Prediction and Prevention to Achieve optimal Recovery Endpoints after stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>STroke imAging Prevention and Treatment (START): PrePARE Prediction and Prevention to Achieve optimal Recovery Endpoints after stroke</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>START_PrePARE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Protocol No: NTA0902</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognition</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Occupational therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The START_PrePARE study is an observational cohort study that is part of the START program of study. In addition it will be linked as a sub-study of the START _EXTEND study, ACTRN: 12610000011088, which is a randomised, multicentre, double blinded, placebo controlled phase 3 trial within a larger cohort study of ischaemic stroke patients. Blood biomarkers, lesion location, and diet and lifestyle factors will be investigated in relation to post-stroke depression and functional outcome in the total START cohort, including START-EXTEND (up to n = 200). In START-PrePARE we will investigate the relationship between advanced imaging (resting state activity, cortical thickness and fibre tract integrity) and functional outcome and depression over time in a cohort of 100 patients. Assessments will include: 

Biomarker (blood sample) collection at baseline, Day3, 3 months and 12 months;

Neurological and functional assessment at Day 3-7, 3 months and 12 months: NIHSS, mRS and BI;

Cognition at Day 3-7, 3 months and 12 months: Montreal Cognitive Assessment;

Diet and Lifestyle questionnaires at Day 3-7, 3 months and 12 months: Cancer Council of Victoria diet questionnaire, Rapid Assessment of Physical Activity questionnaire;

Depression at Day 3-7, 3 months and 12 months; (Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale with non-verbal supports if necessary);

Advanced brain imaging at 3 and 12 months;

Functional status at 3 and 12 months: Cognition (Mini Mental State Examination, Trails-B, Digit span, Shape Cancellation Task, Raven Colored Progressive Matrices, Stroop test), and Sensorimotor (Action Research Arm Test, Tactile Discrimination Test, Timed up and go test);

Participation at 3 and 12 months: Activity Card Sort-Aus 

Quality of Life at 3 and 12 months: Stroke Impact Scale and Work and Social Adjustment Scale;

Mortality and recurrent stroke at 3 and 12 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional and structural changes in the brain: i.e cortical thickness, fibre tract connection and functional resting-state connections.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression (Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale with non-verbal supports)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional status: Functional Independence (mRS), Cognition (MoCA, MMSE, Trails-B, Digit span, Shape Cancellation Task, RCPM, Stroop test), and Sensorimotor (Action Research Arm Test, Tactile Discrimination Test, Timed up and go test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participation (Activity Card Sort)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (Stroke Impact Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality and recurrent stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients presenting with ischaemic stroke.
2. Patient, family member or legally responsible person depending on local ethics requirements has given informed consent for participation in the START_PrePARE study
3. Patients age is &gt; 18 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients who are non-English speaking
2. Contraindication to MR imaging on 3Tesla scanner.
3. Pre-stroke MRS score of greater or equal to 2 (indicating previous disability)
4. Any terminal illness such that the patient would not be expected to survive more than 1 year.
5. Pregnant women (clinically evident)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/06/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>13/04/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Epworth Richmond - Richmond</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Stroke Research Institute (NSRI)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Brain Centre, 245 Burgundy Street, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisations (CSIRO)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 10
Clayton South VIC 3169</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Brain Research Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Melbourne Brain Centre, 245 Burgundy Street, Heidelberg, 3084</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Melbourne
Grattan Street
Victoria 3010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke and depression are two of the highest ranked diseases in the Burden of Disease rankings of the World Health Organisation. Depression is a common sequela of stroke, with recent estimates between 30-60% of all stroke patients. Depression after stroke is often under diagnosed despite the fact that effective treatment exists. Good predictors of depression that could be used to identify at risk patients early as part of the clinical care pathway for stroke currently do not exist. 

This study aims to investigate the association between poststroke depression and 1) novel imaging markers of brain structure and function as identified by specialized MRI, and 2)functional outcomes including cognition, mood, sensorimotor function, and participation in daily activities.

START-PrePARE is an observational cohort study that is part of the START program of study. In addition it will be linked as a sub-study of the START-EXTEND study (NTA 0901), which is a randomised, multicentre, double blinded, placebo controlled phase 3 trial within a larger cohort study of ischaemic stroke patients. START-PrePARE will comprise 100 patients. Participants consented onto the START-PrePARE study will be seen at their hospital at baseline, Day 3-7, 3 months and 12 months for collection of bloods and a series of research tests investigating mood, thinking ability (cognition), diet and lifestyle. The patients will also travel to a central site in Melbourne (the Melbourne Brain Centre), at 3 month and 12 month time points. Here advanced MR imaging, plus more advanced clinical measures of mood, cognition, sensori-motor function and participation will be performed. Investigators and patients will remain blinded to START-EXTEND treatment designation. 

At Baseline a blood sample will be taken, two brief neurological assessments will be conducted and a medical history will be obtained. 3-7 days following stroke, participants will have another blood test, one brief neurological assessment and three questionnaires conducted asking about their diet and lifestyle and their mood and cognition. At the 3 month and 12 month visits participants will have specialised brain MRI scans which will approximately take 40 minutes plus set up time. They will also be given 10 short assessment tasks and three questionnaires to measure functional outcomes including cognition, mood, and movement as well as participation in household, leisure and social activities and quality of life. These assessments will be administered by a qualified therapist, and will take approximately 120 minutes. The blood test and neurological assessments will be conducted at hospital and the 10 short tasks will be conducted at the Melbourne Brain Centre or at the participant's place of residence if more convenient.

All information collected will be recorded without any identifying information and kept private and confidential. 

An independent Data Safety Monitoring Committee has been set up to monitor safety for START-PrePARE patients for the duration of the trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.csiro.start.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Ma H, Parsons MW, Christensen S, Campbell BCV, Churilov L, Connelly A, et al. (2012)A multicentre, randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled Phase III study to investigate EXtending the time for Thrombolysis in Emergency Neurological Deficits (EXTEND). Int J Stroke 7, 74-80
Tse, T., Douglas, J., Lentin, P., Linden, T., Churilov, L., &amp; Carey, L. M. (2014). Reduced activity participation 3 months after stroke associated with increased levels of depressive symptoms and stroke severity: An observational cohort study. Paper presented at the Stroke Society of Australasia 25th ASM, Hamilton Island, 30th July  1st August. Int J Stroke 2014:9(Supp 1)21. doi:10.111/ijs.12297
Yusoff, S. Z. B., Tse, T., Carey, L. M. (2015). Factors impacting Quality of Life in stroke survivors at 3 and 12 months post-stroke: A longitudinal study of an Australian stroke cohort. International Journal of Stroke, 10(Suppl 3): 29-29.
Carey, L. M., Crewther, S., Salvado, O., Linden, T., Connelly, A., Wilson, W., Tse, T et al. (2015). STroke imAging pRevention and treatment (START): A longitudinal stroke cohort study: Clinical trials protocol. International Journal of Stroke, 10(4), 636-644. doi: 10.1111/ijs.12190
Palmer SM, Crewther SG, Carey LM and The START Project Team (2015) A meta-analysis of changes in brain activity in clinical depression. Front. Hum. Neurosci. 8:1045. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2014.01045
Nguyen, V. A., Carey, L. C., Giummarra, L., Faou, P., Cooke, I., Howells, D. W., Tse, T., Macaulay, L., Ma, H., Davis, S. M., Donnan, G. A., Crewther, S. G. (accepted 23/05/2016). A Pathway Proteomic Profile of Ischemic Stroke Survivors Reveals Innate Immune Dysfunction in Association with Mild Symptoms of Depression - A Pilot Study.  Frontiers in Neurology.
Tse, T. and L. M. Carey (2016). Longitudinal changes in activity participation after mild stroke. Asia Pacific Stroke Conference combined with Stroke Society of Australasia. Brisbane, Queensland, Australia, Cerebrovascular Diseases.
Tse, T. and L. M. Carey (2016). The Activity Card Sort  Australia: Validation and reliability in an Australian stroke cohort. Asia Pacific Stroke Conference combined with Stroke Society of Australasia. Brisbane, Queensland, Australia, Cerebrovascular Diseases.
Nguyen, V. A., Carey, L. C., Giummarra, L,. Faou, P., Cooke, I., Howells, D. W., Tse, T., Macaulay, L., Ma, H., Davis, S. M., Donnan, G. A., Crewther, S. G. (2016). A Pathway Proteomic Profile of Ischemic Stroke Survivors Reveals Innate Immune Dysfunction in Association with Mild Symptoms of Depression - A Pilot Study. Asia Pacific Stroke Conference combined with Stroke Society of Australasia. Brisbane, Queensland, Australia, Cerebrovascular Disease
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Level 6 East, Main Building
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
300 Grattan St
Parkville
Victoria 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009.079</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Henry Buck Building 
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria, 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/01/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2010/03588</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Epworth HealthCare Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bridge Road,
Richmind 3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>54812</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bundoora, 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10-071</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Medical Centre, Southern Health Research Governance </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>246 Clayton Road,
Clayton 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/MH/76 SSA/10/SHB/22</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Health Office for Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Furlong Rd, 
St Albans, 3021</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/MH/76 2009.079</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leeanne Carey</name>
      <address>Melbourne Brain Centre, 245 Burgundy Street, Heidelberg, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90357088</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90357303</fax>
      <email>Leeanne.carey@florey.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elise Cowley</name>
      <address>Melbourne Brain Centre, 245 Burgundy Street, Heidelberg, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90357232</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2881</fax>
      <email>ecowley@neurotrialsaustralia.com </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tamara Tse</name>
      <address>Melbourne Brain Centre, 245 Burgundy Street, Heidelberg, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90357146</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90357303</fax>
      <email>ttse@nsri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leeanne Carey</name>
      <address>Melbourne Brain Centre, 245 Burgundy Street, Heidelberg, Vic, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7088</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Leeanne.carey@florey.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>