<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308267">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000637246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise to enhance smoking cessation outcomes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An exercise package to increase smoking quit rates in New Zealand adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Fit2Quit</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>U1111-1117-7679</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking cessation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A comprehensive exercise programme involving individual consultation and exercise prescription, face-to-face and telephone support, provision of strategies (goal setting, scheduling and planning of exercise, mood management) to maintain exercise will be provided over six months by trained exercise facilitators. 
A total of ten sessions will be provided over the six months and will include one face-to-face meeting at the beginning and then weekly telephone calls for the first month, fortnightly for the next month, and then monthly for the duration of the study. 
The face-to-face meeting will be approximately 60 minutes in duration with the phone calls between 10-20 minutes long. 
The exercise package will be delivered in addition to usual smoking cessation services delivered through Quitline. 

Quitline (Me Mutu) is a national smoking cessation service provided by the Quit Group that offers telephone delivered behavioural support (three sessions) and an eight-week supply of Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT) at a heavily subsidized rate for smokers. 

Current standard cessation practice at the New Zealand Quitline (as at April 2008) is as follows: Quitline issues by post, two (or sometimes three) four-week Quit Cards (with a 90 day expiry) and makes routine support calls by telephone over eight weeks.  These support calls are administered by Quitline advisors as required. Quitting support generally involves an average of three follow-up telephone calls, each lasting about 10-15 minutes.  However, if people dont want to receive support calls, they are not scheduled but callers are advised that they can phone Quitline at any time for support. Participants take each four-week Quit Card to a pharmacist in exchange for subsidised patches, gum and/or lozenges ($5 per item per four-week course of NRT).  The strength of NRT patch, gum, and/or lozenges to be used by each participant is determined by the Quitline advisor (as per their dosage guidelines) as to the degree of each persons nicotine dependency. 

The exercise intervention will commence within one-week of participants commencing usual stop smoking treatment through Quitline, and will be provided weekly for the first six-weeks and will gradually reduce in frequency to monthly for the remainder of the programme.</interventions>
    <comparator>Those in the control group will receive usual care delivered through Quitline only. Current standard cessation practice at the New Zealand Quitline (as at April 2008) is as follows: Quitline issues by post, two (or sometimes three) four-week Quit Cards (with a 90 day expiry) and makes routine support calls by telephone over eight weeks.  These support calls are administered by Quitline advisors as required. Quitting support generally involves an average of three follow-up telephone calls, each lasting about 10-15 minutes.  However, if people dont want to receive support calls, they are not scheduled but callers are advised that they can phone Quitline at any time for support. Participants take each four-week Quit Card to a pharmacist in exchange for subsidised patches, gum and/or lozenges ($5 per item per four-week course of Nicotine Replacement Therapy; NRT).  The strength of NRT patch, gum, and/or lozenges to be used by each participant is determined by the Quitline advisor (as per their dosage guidelines) as to the degree of each persons nicotine dependency.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported (questionnaire) abstinence for 6 months from the quit date with no more than 5 cigarettes in total from that date, confirmed by an expired air carbon monoxide (CO) reading of less than 10ppm (as per the Russell Standard).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-report (questionnaire) of not smoking single puff in the last 7-days at the completion of the study medication</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-report (questionnaire) severity of withdrawal symptoms and urges to smoke</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in body weight. Participants will be weighed on digital scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical activity. Physical activity will be assessed using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ).
An objective measurement of physical activity will be provided using the Actigraph accelerometer, which participants will wear for seven consecutive days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>IPAQ questionnaire will be assessed at baseline, weeks 8 and 24

The Actigraph accelerometer will be administered at baseline and 24 weeks only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical fitness. Participants will complete the Harvard Step test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Currently interested in quitting, want to be physically active, smoke at least ten cigarettes (including roll your own) per day and smoke their first cigarette within 30 minutes of waking. Contactable by telephone and able to provide consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People with contraindications to regular exercise (e.g., disability, unstable angina) and with contraindications to using NRT.
Having had a myocardial infarction within the last 2 weeks; unstable or progressive angina pectoris, Prinzmetals angina, severe cardiac arrhythmia or a stroke in the acute phase; or are on warfarin. 
Current users of NRT products or users of non-cigarette tobacco products</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruited through Quitline, contacted by researchers and screened for eligibility, sent study participant information and given an appointment time for the initial (screening) visit. At this visit trained researchers will obtain written informed consent, and collect data. 
Researchers will randomise participants after the baseline assessment using a central computerised randomisation service (via a wireless connection).
 A web-based participant registration system that will require entry of participant details before the computerised randomisation procedure can continue will ensure allocation concealment</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation, stratified to ensure balance for key prognostic factors (self-reported ethnicity, and sex).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Ralph Maddison</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clinical Trials Research Unit, Level 4, School of Population Health, University of Auckland, Tamaki Campus, Morrin Road, Glen Innes, 1072, Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 110 Stanley Street, Auckland, 1010, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Chris Bullen</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clinical Trials Research Unit, Level 4, School of Population Health, University of Auckland, Tamaki Campus, Morrin Road, Glen Innes, 1072, Auckland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Hayden Mc Robbie</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>General Practice, Level 3, School of Population Health, University of Auckland, Tamaki Campus, Morrin Road, Glen Innes, 1072, Auckland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Marewa Glover</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Tobacco Control, Level 4, School of Population Health, University of Auckland, Tamaki Campus, Morrin Road, Glen Innes, 1072, Auckland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/P Harry Prapavessis</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Kinesiology, University of Western Ontario, Ontario, N6A 3K7</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Canada</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people want to stop smoking but find it difficult because of withdrawal symptoms and weight gain. Exercise appears to make withdrawal easier and reduces weight gain. However; it is unclear whether exercise together with standard stop smoking support (counselling plus nicotine replacement therapy) helps more people stay free from smoking in the long term than with stop smoking support alone.  To investigate this, we propose undertaking a study in which smokers who want to stop will be randomly allocated to receive either standard stop smoking treatment alone or standard stop smoking treatment plus an exercise programme. The exercise programme will run for six months and includes an exercise prescription, telephone and face-to-face support, strategies to maintain exercise levels and referral to community group exercise programmes. If the addition of this exercise intervention to standard stop smoking treatment shows it is cost-effective it will have good potential for widespread adoption.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Multi-region ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Ministry of Health
1-3 The Terrace
Level 1
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/09/08/090</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/07/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Ralph Maddison</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019 Auckland Mailing Centre, 1142.</address>
      <phone>+649 3737599 ext 84767</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.maddison@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Ralph Maddison</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019 Auckland Mailing Centre, 1142.</address>
      <phone>+649 3737599 ext 84767</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.maddison@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Ralph Maddison</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019 Auckland Mailing Centre, 1142.</address>
      <phone>+649 3737599 ext 84767</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>regtrials@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>