<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366283">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000543684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The analgesic efficacy, tolerability, safety and pharmacokinetics of a sublingual wafer formulation of ketamine in burns patients undergoing painful dressing changes </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The analgesic efficacy, tolerability, safety and pharmacokinetics of a sublingual wafer formulation of ketamine in burns patients undergoing painful dressing changes </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1156-5606 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>KET002</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL KNOWN</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Burns</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each patient will be dosed on two occasions, dressing change one and two, with a single dose of two 25mg racemic ketamine wafers or a single dose of two placebo wafers sublingually. The two treatment occasions will be separated by a minimum wash out period of 24 hours. The sequence of the two treatments will be randomly assigned. </interventions>
    <comparator>Two sublingual placebo wafers      </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome is Numerical rating scale (NSR) for pain intensity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline, and then at five minute intervals from commencement of dressing change until 20 minutes. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Burn specific pain anxiety scale (BSPAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Measurements carried out immediately prior to start of dressing change, 20 minutes after start of dressing change and 2 hours after dosing. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess time to rescue analgesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: from commencement of dressing change until rescue analgesia is required or 20 minutes have lapsed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess incidence of use of rescue medication in participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Before 20 minutes have elapsed from start of dressing change.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess safety using vital signs including systolic and diastolic blood pressure, pulse rate and pulse oximetry, body temperature and respiratory rate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Prior to commencement of dressing change and at completion of dressing change.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess safety using pulse oximetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: measured continuously from dosing until completion of the dressing change.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess adverse events for safety. Examples include: an unfavourable and uintended sign such as an abnormal laboratory finding, symptom or disease temporally associated with the use of the iinvestigational product. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: AE probing performed prior to start of dressing change, 20 minutes after start of dressing change and 2 hours after dosing. Also, spontaneous AE reporting by participant at any time. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of ketamine using blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Schedule A: PK samples will be taken at 10, 20 and 40 minutes, and at 2 and 4.5 hours folloowing dosing.
Schedule B: PK samples will be taken at 0.5, 1, 1.5. 3 and 6 hours following dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess safety using laboratory investigations (biochemistry, haematology and urinalysis). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline and 24 hours after dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate participant's assessment of treatment on a 5-point Likert Scale (poor, fair, good, very good and excellent). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Following completion of the dressing change on each treatment occassion. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine participant's treatment preference</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Following completion of the second dressing change at the 24 hour timepoint. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Adult burn patients aged 18-65 years requiring at least two anticipated dressing changes of likely duration at least 20 minutes and anticipated to be sufficiently painful that procedural analgesia is clinically indicated.

2) Good general health without clinically significant renal, hepatic, cardiac or respiratory disease, as determined by the Investigator.

3) Agree to and be capable of understanding and signing an Informed Consent Form.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Cirrhosis or other evidence of clinically significant disorder in hepatic function, as determined by the Investigator.

2) Renal impairment as evidenced by estimated creatinine clearance (CrCL), from the Cockcroft-Gault method, of less than 30 mL/min.

3) Any condition in which a significant elevation of blood pressure would be hazardous, e.g. severe cardiovascular disease, heart failure, severe or poorly controlled hypertension, recent myocardial infarction, current stroke or cerebral trauma, intracerebral mass or haemorrhage.

4) History of hypersensitivity to ketamine or any of the excipients.

5) Suspected increased cerebrospinal fluid pressure.

6) Glaucoma.

7) Current (within the last six months) major affective disorder, as assessed by the Investigator.

8) Uncontrolled hyperthyroidism.

9) Acute intermittent porphyria.

10) Pregnant or breastfeeding women.

11) Participation in another clinical trial of an investigational agent within 30 days of entry into the present trial.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All participants are to provide written informed consent before any trial related procedure. Participants will be assigned a unique screening number consisting of two parts, a centre number (assigned by the sponsor) and a Participant number. The investigator will assign participant numbers sequentially. Once assigned, participant identification numbers will not be reused and will remain with the participant throughout the trial.
Participants must meet all inclusion and exclusion criteria to be randomized to trial treatment.

The method of allocation of concealment used will be sealed opaque envelopes in order for treatment to remain blinded. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly allocated in a 1:1:1:1 ratio to one of the following four treatment sequences:

1.Ketamine for treatment one and ketamine for treatment two.
2.Placebo for treatment one and placebo for treatment two.
3.Ketamine for treatment one and placebo for treatment two.
4.Placebo for treatment one and ketamine for treatment two.

Within each treatment sequence (1, 2, 3 or 4) participants are further randomised in a 1:1 fashion to the order of the PK sampling schedule, A for dressing one and B for dressing two, or vice versa. The treatment is blinded, the PK sampling schedule is not blinded.

Computerised sequence generation will be used to create the random order for the allocation of subjects into different groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Standard descriptive statistics (n, mean, median, minimum, maximum and SD) will be used to summarise all continuous variables by treatment, treatment sequence and time point. Categorical measures will be summarised by frequency and percentage, for each treatment, treatment sequence and time point.
The NRS scores for pain will be analysed using a mixed model for repeated measures (MMRM) analysis with factors for treatment, treatment sequence, dressing change, baseline NRS and a random term for participant. Aspects of the cross-over trial, namely carryover effects will be explored. 
An appropriate variance-covariance matrix will be employed.
Additional analyses of the primary outcome will be undertaken including:
1) Inclusion of a time dependent covariate for use of rescue analgesia in the MMRM
2) A Per Protocol (PP) analysis including only values recorded prior to administration of rescue medication
3) Analysis using an MMRM of the time-averaged AUC.

Time to rescue will be analysed by an appropriate multivariate failure time model and presented graphically with Kaplan/Meier plots by treatment and by treatment sequence. 
Incidence of rescue medication use will be summarised and analysed with a generalized linear mixed model. Factors used for the primary analysis of the primary outcome (NRS score) will be included in the model. The logit link will be employed.
Anxiety assessments will be analysed using an MMRM as described for the primary outcome (NRS).
The participants assessment of treatment will be summarised by treatment and treatment sequence using frequency and percentage of participants selecting each value on the Likert scale.
The frequency and percentage of participants preferring each treatment, or with no preference, will be summarised and exact 95% confidence limits presented.
Mixed effects modelling will be used to obtain estimates of PK parameters, related variability and to explore potential PKPD relationships. 

This is an early phase trial with limited information on the expected effect size or, more importantly, on the variability. A sample size of 40 participants (10 for each treatment sequence) is a large enough sample size to provide a reasonably precise estimate of the difference between ketamine and placebo and to provide a reasonable estimate of variability and carry-over effects as assessed with the Balaam design. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6847 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ix Biopharma Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o MKG &amp; Partners, 24 Augusta Street 
Willetton, WA 6155
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mr Eddy Lee
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ix Biopharma Pty Ltd
77 High Street, Suite 03-11/12
High Street Plaza, Singapore 179433</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Singapore</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The change of dressing in burns patients is a painful procedure; however, the pain is only short-lasting. Therefore pain relief requires a fast, but short acting method. Options widely used are inhalation of Entonox (a pain relieving gas mixture), short acting morphine-like tablets or administration of morphine-like drugs by patient-controlled analgesia pumps. In Royal Perth Hospital ketamine, a short-acting pain killer has been used successfully via patient controlled analgesia pumps for many years and, since the Bali disaster, by use of administration under the tongue (as liquid or lozenge made by hospital pharmacy).
A new preparation of ketamine as a wafer, to be administered under the tongue, has been shown to have a rapid onset of effect with minimal adverse effects in volunteers. This could be a promising way to provide pain relief for dressing changes without the need for an intravenous line and with minimal adverse effects. The new medication will be tried in in-patients of the burns unit requiring painful dressing changes. The medication will be compared to placebo wafers, but patients can at any time ask for rescue analgesia, which will include the methods mentioned above. It is expected that ketamine wafers provide better analgesia than placebo with less need for rescue analgesia than placebo. The results of this trial will permit further development of this promising new form of pain relief.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Office
Level 5, Colonial House
Royal Perth Hospital
Murray Street
Perth WA 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC 2012/175</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Schug</name>
      <address>Pharmacology, Pharmacy and Anaesthesiology Unit
School of Medicine and Pharmacology
The University of Western Australia Anaesthesia
Level 2, MRD Building G Block
Royal Perth Hospital
GPO Box X2213
Perth, WA 6847
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8  9224 0201</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 9224 0279</fax>
      <email>stephen.schug@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Schug</name>
      <address>Pharmacology, Pharmacy and Anaesthesiology Unit
School of Medicine and Pharmacology
The University of Western Australia Anaesthesia
Level 2, MRD Building G Block
Royal Perth Hospital
GPO Box X2213
Perth, WA 6847
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8  9224 0201</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 9224 0279</fax>
      <email>stephen.schug@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Rolan</name>
      <address>Director, Drug Development
Discip0line of Pharmacology
Faculty of Health Sciences
5th Level, medical School North
University of Adelaide, SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (0) 40 567 0420</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0) 8 8224 0695</fax>
      <email>paulrolan@ixbiopharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Cutri</name>
      <address>Natalie Cutri
Ground Floor
28 Dalgleish Street
Thebarton 5031
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 8159 6255</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 8 8159 6348</fax>
      <email>Natalie.Cutri@cprservices.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>