<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335291">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000356066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of testosterone and a nutritional supplement on hospital admissions in under-nourished, older people.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of testosterone and a nutritional supplement on hospital admissions in under-nourished, older people.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Hospitalization</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of Life Years</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Body Composition</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Frailty Score</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nutrition Score</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Strength in under-nourished, older people.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Nutritional liquid supplement 2 times per day (180 ml) for 12 months,
and oral capsule andriol testocaps (testosterone undecanoate) (40mg daily women, 80mg twice daily men) for 12 months.

The vanilla nutritional supplement delivers 70.97kJ/180 mls, 0.186g protein, 0.98 g fat and 35-45 g carbohydrate.
The chocolate nutritutional supplement delivers 95.48 kJ/180 mls, 0.186 g protein, and 0.98 g of fat.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo oral capsule contains microcrystalline cellulose only.
(40mg daily women, 80mg twice daily men) for 12 months.

Placebo liquid supplement 2 times per day (180 ml) for 12 months.

The Nutritional placebo supplement has the following caloric content:
Chocolate 180 ml, energy 95.48 kj, fat 0.98 gm, protein 0.186 gm,
Vanilla 180 ml, energy 70.97 kj, fat 0.98 gm, protein 0.186 gm</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days in hospital and number of hospital admissions assessed by telephone contact with participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality-adjusted Life Years (QALYS).
The (QALY) is a measure of disease burden, including both the quality and the quantity of life lived. It is used in assessing the value for money of a medical intervention. The QALY model requires utility independent, risk neutral, and constant proportional tradeoff behaviour. The QALY is based on the number of years of life that would be added by the intervention. Each year in perfect health is assigned the value of 1.0 down to a value of 0.0 for death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional Health assessed by questionnaires and blood tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walk time assessed by physical activity cut-off time to walk 15 feet (based on the short version of the Minnesota Leisure Time Activity Questionnaire).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frailty Score assessed by questionnaire Fried?s Frailty Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grip Strength assessed by hand grip dynamometer test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fat Free Mass assessed by Bioelectrical Impedance analysis (BIA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Men and women aged 65 years or older who are under-nourished, as defined by 
Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA) score 17-23.5 out of 30.
AND 1 or more of 
A body mass index (BMI) of less than 22 kg/m2 
Weight loss in the 3 months before enrolling in the study
2.Living independently in the community (not in a hospital, nursing home or hostel)
3.Understand and sign the informed consent document, able to communicate with the investigator, and understand and comply with the requirements of the study.
4.Women who are taking oestrogen or other hormone replacement therapy (HRT) may take part, as may women who are not taking HRT. If a woman is taking HRT she must have been on a stable dose for at least 3 months before enrolment in the study. If not on HRT, she must not have been taking it for at least 3 months before enrolment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Elevated haematocrit (HCT) levels (&gt;50%)
2.Past or present history of prostatic cancer in men (Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) levels [&gt; age-related normal range and/or irregular prostate on prostate examination]) 
3.Men with a past/present or family history of male breast cancer
4.Women with a past/present history of breast cancer.
5.Pre-existing androgenic signs or symptoms in women of concern to either subject or investigator (deep voice, hirsutism, acne, androgenic hair loss).
6.Depression (Yesavage Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS) Score &gt; 12)
7.Significant cardiac failure (New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional classification system Class III and above)
8.Abnormal liver function tests ( Alanine transaminase ALT, Gamma-glutamyltransferase GGT, bilirubin or alkaline phosphatase test ALP &gt; 2x upper limit of normal)
9.Nephrotic syndrome; 24h urine protein &gt; 3 grams (24h urine save performed if dipstick positive proteinuria at screening) AND/OR estimated/calculated creatinine clearance (by the equation of Baracskay and Jarkoura for ambulatory elderly subjects [Cr clearance = 4.4/serum creatinine (mmol/L) + (88-age)] &lt; 30 ml/min AND/OR serum creatinine concentration &gt; 0.2mmol/l. 
10.Any disease, which in the opinion of the investigator is likely to lead to death within 1 year
11.Folsteins Mini Mental State Examination [MMSE] score of &lt; 23
12.Testosterone or other androgen therapy in the four months before starting the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Method 1: Domiciliary/geriatric assessment services at the three campuses will approach new clients about their willingness to consider participation in this study and be approached by researchers. 

Method 2: Using similar approaches, investigator clinicians and other geriatrician/gerontology colleagues will refer consenting subjects from their rehabilitative, ambulatory or outreach services for further contact and review by the research officer. Any subjects who have only recently been in hospital will be enrolled into the study 3 months after the last hospitalization and once health status is stabilized.

Method 3: Television or newspaper advertisement.

Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was off-site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be randomised to one of two study groups (n= ˜100/group) by a stratification system to ensure that an equal number of men and women will be allocated to each treatment. There will be stratification by study site to allow for possible differences in subjects recruited between sites, within each sex at each site.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital, 
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South, SA 5011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Council Secretary NHMRC GPO Box 1421. CANBERRA ACT 2601.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sydney Southwest Area Health Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Concord Hospital
Hospital Road, Concord
NSW 2139</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alfred Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Division of Rehabilitation, Aged and Community Care
c/o Caulfield Hospital 
260 Kooyong Road, Caulfield 3162</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Weight loss and under-nutrition is common in older people and associated with poor outcomes.  This includes increased rates of hospital admissions.
In a pilot study of ndernourished older, community dwelling people we found that daily treatment for one year with a combination of testosterone tablets and a nutritional supplement produced a significant reduction in hospitalizations.  We propose a larger, multicentre study to explore and hopefully confirm this exciting, potentially important finding.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Northern Adelaide Health Service Ethics of Human Research Committee The Queen Elizabeth Hospital and Lyell McEwin</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital Woodville Road 
Woodville South SA 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Renuka Visvanathan</name>
      <address>Director, Aged &amp; Extended Care Services Level 8b
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital Woodville Road 
Woodville South SA 5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82226887</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>renuka.visvanathan@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Cynthia Piantadosi</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital Woodville Road 
Woodville South SA 5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81334014</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cynthia.piantadosi@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Renuka Visvanathan</name>
      <address>Director, Aged &amp; Extended Care Services Level 8b
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital Woodville Road 
Woodville South SA 5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82226887</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>renuka.visvanathan@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>