<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308241">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000675224</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Killer T cell Therapy for Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Adoptive Immunotherapy for Epstein-Barr virus associated Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>QHKUPNPC01</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Queensland Institute of Medical Research project number P1069</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epstein-Barr virus associated Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>20-40 x 10^6 autologous Latent Membrane Protein Epstein-Barr Nuclear Antigen-1 (LMP/EBNA1) specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTL) administered by fortnightly intravenous infusion. A minimum of 2 infusions and a maximum of 6 (subject to sufficient LMP-CTL being generated).</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability: Safety of adoptive transfer will be monitored by blood tests to check full blood cell counts, biochemistry and liver function. Vital signs will be monitored and any adverse events will be recorded and treatment provided if required. A quality of life questionnaire will also assist in monitoring the tolerability of the adoptive transfer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and tolerability will be assessed through monitoring the patient on the day of each adoptive transfer - every 2 weeks for up to six transfers.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy:Efficacy will be assessed via immunological and virological monitoring - using Enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot (ELISPOT), tetramer and intracellular cytokine staining methods to measure CTL function ex vivo, and measuring Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) levels in the blood using real time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to detect the BALF5 gene. 

Efficacy will also be assessed via clinical monitoring. Reduction of tumour burden will be assessed via clinical examination and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and/or computed tomography (CT) scans</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post adoptive immunotherapy monitoring will be done at baseline, prior to each adoptive transfer (every 2 weeks for six transfers) and monthly until six months after the first adoptive transfer. 

Reduction of tumour burden will be assessed at baseline and follow up scans will occur at 1, 2, 3, 4 &amp; 6 months from the time of initial adoptive transfer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age 15 years or above.
2. Geographically accessible for follow up
3. Informed consent (from patient, or patient and parent/guardian if aged &lt; 16 years) Approved hospital interpreters will be used for patients who do not have sufficient understanding of English for informed consent to be obtained without the use of an interpreter.
4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status 0, 1, 2 or 3
5. Previously diagnosed with stage II, III or IV nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC)
6. Life expectancy of at least 3 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. EBV negative tumour
2. Inability to identify an LMP/EBNA1 peptide to stimulate CTL cultures
3. Positive serology for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)
4. Serology indicating active Hepititis B Virus (HBV) infection or carrier status for HBV (N.B. Positive serology for HBV indicating previous but cleared infection with HBV would not be an exclusion criteria.)
5. Serology indicating active Hepititis C Virus (HCV) infection
6. Significant non malignant disease (e.g. severe cardiac or respiratory dysfunction)
7. Psychiatric, addictive or any conditions which may compromise the ability to participate in this trial
8. Prior cancers, except those diagnosed &gt; 5 years ago with no evidence of disease recurrence and clinical expectation of recurrence of &lt; 5%, or successfully treated non-melanoma skin cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix.
9. Currently receiving immunosuppressive therapy, including corticosteroids.
10. Pregnancy, or unwilling to use adequate contraception.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable (non randomised trial)</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable (non randomised trial)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>There will be 2 treatment groups:
1.Patients with stage II, III and IV NPC  in remission 
2.Patients with stage II, III and IV NPC  with refractory or recurrent disease</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/01/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Hong Kong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Queen Mary Hospital
Pokfulam Road
Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>300 Herston Road
Herston
QLD
4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>300 Herston Road
Herston
QLD
4006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) is associated with a number of human malignancies including nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC). 100% of undifferentiated NPC tumours are EBV- positive meaning the virus is localised to the tumour cells. We are attempting to develop immunotherapy as an alternate treatment for nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC) in addition to radiotherapy, chemotherapy and surgery. This immunotherapy would be in the form of adoptive transfer. This requires that a certain type of white blood cell found in the body known as killer T-cells or technically "cytotoxic T lymphocytes" (CTL) be isolated from the NPC patients own blood. These T cells are trained in the laboratory to become more efficient at recognising and destroying EBV infected tumour cells.  Adoptive transfer is when the EBV-specific T cells are given back to the patient via intravenous infusions. This phase I adoptive immunotherapy trial aims to determine the safety, tolerability and efficacy of adoptive transfer of EBV specific T cells for NPC. The study will be carried out in collaboration with The University of Hong Kong, The Queensland Institute of Medical Research (QIMR) and The Princess Alexandra Hospital, Brisbane. A total of 50 eligible participants will be enrolled on the trial (35 from Hong Kong and 15 from the Princess Alexandra Hospital). Following informed consent, a 200-400ml blood sample will be collected from each participant and transported to the Q-Gen laboratory at QIMR in Brisbane where laboratory staff will begin to grow the T cells with a recombinant adenovirus. This process will take about 15 days. The recombinant adenovirus expresses small fragments from NPC-associated viral proteins this technique is used to stimulate the killer T cells in the laboratory. This adenovirus has been modified in such a way that it is non-infectious and does not cause any disease. This stimulation should result in the T cells being able to recognize EBV proteins on the NPC tumour that are there because of the EBV in the tumour. After recognising these proteins, the T cells will try to kill the tumour.  After the killer T cells have been grown they will be purified and all residual adenovirus removed. They will be tested for safety, sterility and specific activity before being transported back to the treating hospital. The participants will undergo several baseline assessments, including blood tests. The killer T cells will be given back to the participant via adoptive transfer.  Infusions of between 20-40 x 10^6 CTL will be given intravenously on a fortnightly basis, for up to six infusions. Participants will be monitored once a fortnight for the first 12 weeks and then once a month for four months. Monitoring will involve a series of blood tests and MRI scans. Participants will be on the trial for a total of 33 weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board of the University of Hong Kong /  Hospital Authority Hong Kong West Cluster</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 901
Administration Block
Queen Mary Hospital
102 Pokfulam Road</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/02/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>UW 07-032</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>QIMR
300 Herston Road
Herston
Brisbane
Queensland
4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Rajiv.Khanna@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katherine Matthews</name>
      <address>QIMR
300 Herston Road
Herston
Brisbane
Queensland
4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0412</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Katherine.Matthews@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sashika Naidoo</name>
      <address>QIMR
300 Herston Road
Herston
Brisbane
Queensland
4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0433</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3362 0109</fax>
      <email>Sashika.Naidoo@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>QIMR 300 Herston Road Herston Brisbane Queensland 4006 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Rajiv.Khanna@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>