<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335295">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000268044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of the spasticity on the linear standards of gait in hemiparetic individuals</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of the spasticity on the linear standards of gait in hemiparetic individuals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To analyze the effect of the spasticity in the linear standards of gait in hemiparetic individuals and to correlate it with the articular largeness of the ankle. The total duration of the study lasted 1 year</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group of healthy individuals between 50 and 65 years</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Regarding the parameters of linear motion between the groups analyzed, the average total distance traveled (DTP) was 14.52 m for the stroke group and 32.16 m for the control group (p &lt;0.0001) and was 23,75s in the stroke group and 19.02 in the control group (p &lt;0.0001). To analyze these variables was used Nagasaki Protocol (1994)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at one year after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The variables consist of linear parameters of gait, the average score for the stroke group for the average step length (SL) was 0.45, Cadence (CAD) and 1.0 speed (VEL) 0.65 m / s while in the control group had an average of 1.05 for SL, 1.03 for CAD and 1.69 m / s for VEL. Only the values of SL and VEL were statistically significant (p &lt;0.0001), whereas CAD was not significant compared between groups (p = 0.1932). To analyze these variables was used Nagasaki Protocol (1994)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at one year after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relating the degree of spasticity of the gastrocnemius muscle group of strokes with the parameters of DTP and time obtained the relationship: patients with grade 0 of spasticity had an average of 32.16 m and 19.02 s DTP time. For individuals in the group with stroke degree of spasticity of the gastrocnemius 1 DTP was 17.8 m long and 22.2 s, who had grade 2 to DTP was 16.2 m long and 26.6 for grade 3 and an average of 9m DTP and 21.47 s for the time spent on the route. To analyze the spasticity of the gastrocnemius muscle was used the Modified Ashworth Scale and parameters of linear motion, the protocol of Nagasaki (1994)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at one year after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relating the degree of spasticity of the soleus muscle of both groups were obtained: average DTP 32.16 m long and 19.02 for grade 0 (control group), DTP 17.8 m and 22.86 s time to grade 1, DTP 11 , 24m and length of 24.65 s to grade 2. Relating the degree of spasticity of the gastrocnemius muscle with the spatial and temporal parameters of gait (SL, CAD and VEL) was obtained: individuals who had grade 0 the average of SL was 1.05, 1.03 CAD, VEL of 1.69 m / s, for 1 degree of spasticity, the SL was 0.56, 0.98 and CAD VEL 0.86 m / s, for grade 2 was obtained from 0.49 SL, 1.02 for CAD and 0.65 m / s VEL and patients who had grade 3 to SL was 0.29 CAD 1.01 and 0.44 VEL m / s. The relationship of the degree of spasticity of the soleus muscle with the spatial and temporal parameters of gait (SL, CAD and VEL) was analyzed and it was found: individuals who had grade 0 the average was 1.05 SL, CAD 1 , 03, VEL of 1.69 m / s, for grade 1 to SL was 0.54, the CAD of 0.99 and 0.76 VEL m / s, for grade 2 was obtained 0.36 for SL, 0 , 98 CAD and 0.48 m / s for VEL. To analyze the spasticity of the soleus muscle was used the Modified Ashworth Scale and parameters of linear motion, the protocol of Nagasaki (1994)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at one year after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We included individuals who had right hemiparesis and submit between 50 and 65 years of age. The control group, the individuals selected were healthy, aged 50-65 years and handed to greater reliability of the research.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We excluded individuals unable to walk or use any means to help or even showing any disturbance that influences the balance, vestibular and neurological disorders and deformities, unstructured, have good cognitive control and have left hemiparesis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Case control</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Nove de Julho - Faculdade Marechal Rondon</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Vicinal Dr. Nilo Lisboa Chavasco, 5000 - Sao Manuel - SP - CEP: 18650-000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Nove de Julho - Faculdade Marechal Rondon</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Vicinal Dr. Nilo Lisboa Chavasco, 5000 - Sao Manuel - SP - CEP: 18650-000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Gustavo Luvizutto</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Avenida da Saudade, 225 - Sao Manuel -SP - CEP: 18650-000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To analyze the effect of the spasticity in the linear standards of gait in hemiparetic individuals, ie, observe if there is interference from a muscle on the hard floor of the individual</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gustavo Jose Luvizutto</name>
      <address>Distrito Rubiao Junior, s/n - Botucatu/SP - CEP: 18618970</address>
      <phone>+55 14-38116049</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gluvizutto@fmb.unesp.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gustavo Jose Luvizutto</name>
      <address>Avenida da saudade - 225 - Centro - Sao Manuel/SP - CEP: 18650-000</address>
      <phone>+55 14-38411284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gluvizutto@fmb.unesp.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>