<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343156">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000778987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Captopril and Nifedipine in Treatment of Hypertension in Children with Post-streptoccal Acute Glomerulonephritis with Hypertension- A Randomized Control Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of Captopril and Nifedipine in Treatment of Hypertension in Children with Post-streptoccal Acute Glomerulonephritis with Hypertension- A Randomized Control Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-6303</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Control of Blood Pressure in Patients with Post-sterptococcal Acute Glomerulonephritis (PSAGN)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Renal profiles in patients with Post-streptococcal Acute Glomerulonephritis (PSAGN)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a Randomized Control Trial study with 2 independent groups.
We will be using a generic Captopril (CAPTOHEXAL (Registered Trademark) 12.5 COR) produced by Hexal AG, Germany for Captopril and a generic Nifedipine produced by Sai Mirra Innopharm from India. 
The Nifedipine, a 3,5-dimethyl 2,6-dimethyl-4-(2-nitrophenyl)-1,4-dihydropyridine-3,5-dicarboxylate compound, is rapidly absorbed after oral administration. It is detectable in the serum after 10  15 minutes and the peak blood levels occur in approximately 30 minutes. Its half life is approximately 2 hours. It is metabolized mainly in the liver. 
The Captopril (CAPTOHEXAL (registered Trademark) 12.5 COR), is a (2S)-1-[(2S)-2-methyl-3-sulfanylpropanoyl] pyrrolidine-2-carboxylic acid compound. Following oral administration of Captopril, rapid absorption occurs and detectable in 15 minutes with peak blood levels at about one hour. After administration oral dose, the apparent elimination half-life for total radioactivity in blood is about 12 hours for the 12 to 48 hours time interval. It is primarily eliminated in the urine. 
The Nifedipine will be packed in a dosing of 5 mg each and the Captopril will be packed in 6.25mg each. Both medications will be wrapped in an aluminum foil. The packing of these medications into aluminum foil will be done by the pharmacist and should be identical so to eliminate bias. With this method, the caretaker, the patient and researcher will be blinded with the treatment. Block randomization will be done by a computer program. A list containing computer-generated assigned number then will be generated. The list will be kept by the pharmacist. The researcher or the first doctor in charge of patient will enroll the patient once consent is taken and inclusion criteria are fulfilled and the pharmacist will enroll the patient according to the randomization list.
Before the patient is started on the treatment, parameters such as duration of illness before presentation, history of preceding infection, weight and height, blood pressure before treatment, renal profile, full blood count, complement levels, ASOT and anti- DNase B level will be recorded. 
The Nifedipine and Captopril will be titrated according to response. The dosage of Nifedipine and Captopril given will be based on weight and the age of the patient. This will ensure that the given drug will fall onto the therapeutic ranges of each medication. 
After the medication is initiated, the blood pressure will be monitored 1/2  hour, 1 hour, 4 hours, 8 hours, 12 hours and 24 hours after administration on day one and subsequently daily (early morning at 8.00 am) during the course of the treatment, until the patient is discharged. Blood pressure will be taken in supine position and using a single automated BP monitoring device (DINAMAP (Registerd Trademark) with appropriate cuff size using according to the NHBPEP (National High Blood Pressure Education Program) Working Group on High Blood Pressure in Children and Adolescence 2004 recommendations. 
Additional antihypertensive can be used to control the blood pressure if it is not controlled after 3 hours of starting the treatment and if there is a risk of patient developing hypertensive encephalopathies. Only Frusemide can be used for this and can be given as per needed basis. If the risk of hypertensive encephalopathy in inevitable, patient will be started on intravenous antihypertensive, i.e Sodium Nitroprusside and patient will be excluded from the study. Apart from blood pressure, we will monitor the Blood Urea, Creatinine, [UK/(UNa+K)] Ratio, and Beta-2 Microglobulin, on the third day of the treatment to compare the levels between pretreatment and the post treatment difference. 
Statistical analysis will be done by using SPSS software version 12.0.1, with results of the blood pressure, total duration of medication, hospitalization and normalization of BP will be explained in means and compared. It is then tested with Independent Student T- test for confirmation of the difference of blood pressure means. As for the duration of blood pressure normalization and duration of hospital stay, Mann- Whitney test will be used for confirmation.</interventions>
    <comparator>The study compares between two drugs in controlling BP in Post-streptococcal Acute Glomerulonephritis (PSAGN). One group will receive Captopril and the other Nifedipine (randomised).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the of blood pressure control in patients with PSAGN with hypertension in patients receiving Captopril and Nifedipine. This will be determine by normalization of blood pressure control by means of automated blood pressure measuring device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the blood pressure control in patients with PSAGN with hypertension in patients receiving Captopril and Nifedipine by means of reading of blood pressure using ann automated blood pressure machine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the duration needed for blood pressure control (i.e Systolic and diastolic BP of &lt; 95 percentile according to the height and age)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the need of additional anti-hypertensive (i.e: Frusemide) in conjunction with the tested anti-hypertensive in controlling the blood pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the changes in the renal functions occurring in both of the tested group</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the total duration of Captopril and Nifedipine used and the total duration of hospital stay in each Captopril and Nifedipine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the duration needed for blood pressure control (i.e Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure of &lt;95 percentile according to the height and age), by means of medical equipment and clinically.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine of the total duration of Captopril and Nifedipie used, by means of clinical evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the duration of hospital stay in each Captopril and Nifedipine, by clinical evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hospital admission until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the need of additional anti-hypertensive (i.e: Frusemide) in conjunction with the tested anti-hypertensive in controlling the blood pressure by means of clinical evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the changes of renal function occurring in both of the tested group, by means of laboratory test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before treatment and at the third day after treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients with clinical signs and symptoms PSAGN with hypertension (Blood Pressure of &gt; 95 percentile of their respective height, age and gender) with the age between 1 year old to 12 years old, weight of 10 kg to 50 kg. 
Clinical sign and symptoms of PSAGN includes history and clinical findings of facial puffiness and hematuria (urine RBC detected), decreased urine output or symptomatic hypertension. It preceded with history of impetigo or pharyngitis.  Blood investigations includes complement levels, throat swab, positive ASOT or anti-DNAase.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)Patients non post-streptococcal AGN i.e: SLE with Lupus Nephritis, Nephrotic syndrome, etc
2)Patients with PSAGN without hypertension (defined as BP &gt; 95 percentile according to height, age and gender).
3)Encephalopathic patients defined as having seizures, severe headache and having fundoscopy changes that needs urgent antihypertensive or intravenous antihypertensives.
4)Second episode of PSAGN with hypertension.
5)Other causes of elevated BP i.e Essential Hypertension, Phaeochromocytoma
6)Patients with known renal problems</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was "off-site"</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kelantan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universiti Sains Malaysia (USM)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Health Campus,
Jalan Raja Perempuan Zainab II,
Kubang Kerian, 16150
Kota Bharu, Kelantan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universiti Sains Malaysia (USM)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Health Campus,
Jalan Raja Perempuan Zainab II,
Kubang Kerian, 16150
Kota Bharu, Kelantan</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This aim of the study is to determine which oral antihypertensive drugs is more effective in achieving control of hypertension in children with Post-streptococcal Acute Glomerulonephritis. The study is a randomised control trial  double-blinded comparing between oral Captopril (ACE inhibitor) and Nifedipine (Calcium channel blocker). Our hypothesis is that Captopril is more effective in controlling hypertension than Nifedipine based on the current pathophysiology of PSAGN. All children diagnosed with PSAGN based on the specified criteria will be included in the study. Management of the patient will be guided by specified standard guidelines and both groups will receive either drug A or B in concealed packet depending upon randomization sequence generated earlier. Parameters like how fast normalization of blood pressure achieve,duration of hospital stay, the need for additional treatment, and biochemical profile related to renal function will be recorded and later analyse.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Research Ethics Committee (Human), Universiti Sains Malaysia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Universiti Sains Malaysia
Kampus Kesihatan, 
16150 Kubang Kerian,
Kota Bharu, Kelantan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/11/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mohammad Ikram bin Ilias</name>
      <address>Jabatan Pediatrik, Tingkat 6,
Hospital Universiti Sains Malaysia,
Jalan Raja Perempuan Zainab II, 
Kubang Kerian, 16150,
Kota Bharu, Kelantan</address>
      <phone>+60199115628</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drikram@kk.usm.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Aznor Fadly Bin Azim</name>
      <address>Jabatan Pediatrik, Tingkat 6,
Hospital Universiti Sains Malaysia,
Jalan Raja Perempuan Zainab II, 
Kubang Kerian, 16150,
Kota Bharu, Kelantan</address>
      <phone>+60163906285</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aznor_atid@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>