<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308248">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000610235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Health and Unflued Gas Heaters Study: The Impact of Unflued Low NOx Gas Heaters on Lung Function and Respiratory Symptoms in Schoolchildren.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In schoolchildren aged 8 to 12 years, is exposure to unflued low NOx gas heaters, compared to flued gas heaters, associated with worse lung function and more frequent respiratory symptoms?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HUGHS</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory Health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Low NOx unflued gas heaters
The exposure period is schooldays each week (Monday to Friday).  The washout period between exposures is the weekend (Saturday and Sunday).
The low NOx unflued gas heaters will be used in alternating weeks during the 6 week exposure assessment.  The low NOx unflued gas heaters will be used for a total of 3 weeks and the flued gas heaters will be used for a total of 3 weeks.  The classroom teacher will not know which type of heater is the exposure heater for the week.  The classroom teacher will make decisions about the need for heating in the classroom.  This will be in line with their usual practice.</interventions>
    <comparator>Flued vs unflued low NOx gas heaters

The flued gas heater has a vent to the outside and emissions from the heater are vented to the outside.  The low NOx unflued gas heater does not have a vent.

The flued gas heaters will be used in alternating weeks during the 6 week exposure assessment.  The low NOx unflued gas heaters will be used for a total of 3 weeks and the flued gas heaters will be used for a total of 3 weeks.  The classroom teacher will not know which type of heater is the exposure heater for the week.  The classroom teacher will make decisions about the need for heating in the classroom.  This will be in line with their usual practice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second (FEV1)

Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second (FEV1) will be assessed by Mini-Wright Digital Peak Flow Meter (Clement Clarke International).  Children will record three FEV1 manoeuvres each morning and each night during the 6 week exposure assessment period.  The Mini-Wright Digital will electronically store with date and time stamp all FEV1 manoeuvres.</outcome>
      <timepoint>average over one week periods</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>exhaled nitric oxide

The test is performed by having the child breath room air in through a scrubber, designed to remove nitric oxide from ambient air.  The child will stand, with a nose clip on and inhale and exhale three times through the scrubber then immediately after the third inhalation the subject will exhale through a rotameter.  The rotameter incorporates a flow sensor and the subject will be instructed to maintain the expiratory flow rate at about 200 mls per second, by keeping a floating ball between two sets of flow rate markers.  The device will also incorporate a manually operated valve. Initially, the valve is set to be open to the room allowing the technician to discard the dead space volume. After approximately one to two seconds of expiration, the technician turns the valve to direct the airflow into a 3L impermeable polyethylene (Scholle Industries, Adelaide, Australia) collecting bag. The subject is instructed to continue to exhale down to near residual volume. This procedure will be repeated up to two or three times until approximately 1L was collected into the bag.  Within 6 hours of collection, the contents of the impermeable polyethylene bag will be aspirated into a chemiluminescent analyser (Model 42C; Thermo Environmental Instruments, Franklin, MA) to measure nitric oxide (NO) concentration in parts per billion (ppb).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of each one week period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>respiratory symptoms
Symptoms include Cough, Wheeze or Chest tightness, Fever, Sore throat, Runny or blocked nose, Soreness of teeth or gums, Eye irritation, Stomach ache
Children will record symptoms each morning and each night in a paper diary during the 6 week exposure assessment period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>over the one week period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Classrooms: 1) in Blue Mountains or Southern Highlands region of NSW
2) heated by low NOx unflued gas heaters
3) no artificial ventilation or other heating sources
4) suitable for installation of flued gas heater
5) Year 3 to Year 6 students
Students: all students within these classes are eligible</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Classrooms: 1) artificial ventilation or other heating source
2) unsuitable for installation of flued gas heater
Students: those who, in the opinion of the class teacher, would not be able to undertake the procedures outline below due to physical or intellectual disability or due to inability to communicate in English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a cluster-randomised cross-over study all participants will receive both conditions.
During a six week period in the winter months either the low NOx unflued gas heater or the flued gas heater will be in active mode for one week periods. These periods will be arranged in three consecutive pairs. For each classroom, the order of operation of the unflued and flued gas heaters will be randomised separately for each pair of weeks. Hence, each classroom will be using a low NOx unflued gas heater for three one week periods and a flued gas heater for three one week periods. During this time the heaters will be operated at the discretion of the class teacher, in the usual way, according to heating need. The class teacher and the students within the classes will not be aware which of the heaters is in active mode, that is, they will be blinded to the exposure.</concealment>
    <sequence>We will used a computer generated randomisation for the first of each pair of weeks for each class.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2780</postcode>
    <postcode>2575</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NSW Department of Education and Training</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 33, Sydney NSW 2001
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Department of Education and Training</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 33, Sydney NSW 2001
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>NSW Department of Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Locked Mail Bag 961
North Sydney NSW 2059
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is provide the NSW Department of Education and Training (DET) and other current or potential users of low NOx emission heaters with independent, reliable and unbiased evidence of their short-term impact on exposure to pollutants, symptoms and function in primary school-age children.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.woolcock.org.au/hughs.htm</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6
Jane Foss Russell Building ? G02
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>04-2009/11667</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Wafaa Ezz</name>
      <address>Box M77 Missenden Road Post Office
Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91140455</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91140014</fax>
      <email>wafaaezz@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Wafaa Ezz</name>
      <address>Box M77 Missenden Road Post Office
Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91140455</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91140014</fax>
      <email>wafaaezz@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Valennia Tan</name>
      <address>Box M77 Missenden Road Post Office
Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91140353</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91140013</fax>
      <email>velse@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>