<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83246">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000631303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Australasian Antenatal Study To Evaluate the Role Of Intramuscular Dexamethasone versus Betamethasone prior to preterm birth to increase survival free of childhood neurosensory disability  a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Australasian Antenatal Study To Evaluate the Role Of Intramuscular Dexamethasone versus Betamethasone prior to preterm birth to increase survival free of childhood neurosensory disability  a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>A*STEROID</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Long-term childhood neurosensory disability following antenatal corticosteroids given to women at risk of preterm birth at less than 34 weeks gestatation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dexamethasone (antenatal corticosteroid) - 2 syringes of 12 mg dexamethasone (dexamethasone sodium phosphate - a non-sulphite containing preparation) administered as 2 intramuscular injections, 24 hours apart.</interventions>
    <comparator>Betamethasone (antenatal corticosteroid) - 2 syringes of 11.4 mg betamethasone (as Celestone Chronodose 11.4 mg) administered as 2 intramuscular injections, 24 hours apart.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite of incidence of death (defined as stillbirths, deaths from live born infants before hospital discharge and deaths after hospital discharge) or any neurosensory disability in the children (includes the neurosensory impairments of cerebral palsy, blindness, deafness and any developmental delay defined as a standardised score more than 1 SD below the mean (&lt;-1SD)).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years' corrected age.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite of incidence of death or major neurosensory disability in the children (with major neurosensory disability defined as severe and moderate disability and includes blindness, deafness, cerebral palsy in a child non-ambulant by 2 years of age or a standardised score &lt;-2SD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years' corrected age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual components and severity of the primary outcome (cerebral palsy, blindness, deafness, developmental delay).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years' corrected age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal outcomes including intraventricular haemorrahge (IVH), severe intraventricular haemorrhage (IVH), periventricular leukomalacia (PVL), retinopathy of prematurity needing treatment, patent ductus arteriosus needing treatment, use of inotropes, respiratory distress syndrome, severity of any neonatal lung disease, chronic lung disease (need for oxygen at 36 weeks post-menstrual age), use of mechanical ventilation, confirmed infection within the first 48 hours, infection after the first 48 hours, body size at birth (weight, length and head circumference) and at discharge home after birth</outcome>
      <timepoint>At primary hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Childhood outcomes: developmental domains as measured by Ages &amp; Stages Questionnaire (Bricker &amp; Squires 1999)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 year corrected age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Childhood outcomes: Body size and corresponding Z scores, General health of the child (including use of health services since primary hospitalisation), Childhood respiratory morbidity, Blood pressure Z scores and proportions in hypertensive ranges and Behaviour</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years corrected age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal perinatal infectious morbidity (defined as clinical chorioamnionitis requiring intrapartum antibiotics, use of postpartum antibiotics).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 6 weeks post hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women are eligible for the trial if they are at risk of preterm birth at less than 34 weeks gestation, have a singleton or twin pregnancy, have no contraindications to the use of antenatal corticosteroids and give informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women are not eligible if they have chorioamnionitis requiring urgent delivery, a higher order multiple pregnancy, have already received antenatal corticosteroids, have known fetal lung maturation, or are in the second stage of labour.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible women are counselled and must give signed, informed consent. Trial entry details are given and eligibility is confirmed, the woman is randomised by contacting the central telephone randomisation service at the University of Adelaide. Assignment to one of two treatment groups: either the dexamethasone group or the betamethasone group.  A Study Number and a corresponding numbered treatment pack will be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will use balanced variable blocks and will be created using computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation) by researchers not involved in clinical care.  Assignment to either group will be stratified for collaborating centre, gestational age (&lt;28 weeks, &gt;= 28 weeks gestation), and number of fetuses (1 or 2).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/03/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/02/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1499</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1509</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women’s and Children’s Hospital, SA</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>72 King William Road,
North Adelaide 
SA , 5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Physical address:
Level 5, 20 Allara Street
Canberra ACT 2601

Postal address:
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this randomised controlled trial is to determine whether giving antenatal dexamethasone to women at risk of preterm birth at less than 34 weeks gestation increases the chance of their children surviving free of
neurosensory disability at 2 years corrected age, compared with women given antenatal betamethasone.
The primary hypothesis of the study is that, compared with betamethasone, antenatal dexamethasone given to women
at risk of preterm birth (less than 34 weeks gestation) reduces the risk of death or any neurosensory disability, caused
by impairments such as cerebral palsy, blindness, deafness or developmental delay, in their children at 2 years
corrected age.
Specific aims are to assess whether dexamethasone has greater short-term benefits than betamethasone (a greater reduction in the risk of intraventricular haemorrhage as suggested by a new systematic review) and whether there are longer-term effects on childhood neurological function, including motor function, cognition and behaviour, as well as body size, blood pressure and general health.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.adelaide.edu.au/arch/research/clinical_trials/asteroid.html</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children, Youth &amp; Women's Health Service (CYWHS) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Women's and Children's Hospital,
72 King William Road,
North Adelaide 
SA  
5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REC2074/7/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Caroline Crowther</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide
Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology
Level 1, Queen Victoria Building
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William St
North Adelaide
SA
5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8161 7647</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8161 7652</fax>
      <email>caroline.crowther@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Pat Ashwood</name>
      <address>Australian Research Centre for Health of Women and Babies (ARCH)
Discipline of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
The University of Adelaide
Women's and Children's Hospital
King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8161 7767</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8161 7652</fax>
      <email>pat.ashwood@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Pat Ashwood</name>
      <address>Australian Research Centre for Health of Women and Babies (ARCH)
Discipline of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
The University of Adelaide
Women's and Children's Hospital
King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8161 7767</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8161 7652</fax>
      <email>pat.ashwood@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Caroline Crowther</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology 
Level 1, Queen Victoria Building 
Women's and Children's Hospital 
72 King William St 
North Adelaide SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8161 7619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroline.crowther@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>