<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364154">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000566730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Natural Course of Hot Flash Symptoms in Men Receiving Androgen-Deprivation Therapy for Prostate Cancer  a Pilot Investigation.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In men receiving androgen-deprivation therapy for histologically confirmed prostate cancer, what is the natural course of hot flash symptoms?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Natural course of hot flashes in men with prostate cancer, receiving ADT for the first time. </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This pilot study will prospectively follow a cohort of 20 men with hormone naive prostate cancer who have been commenced on ADT in the form of LHRH analogues. This study will be conducted over a total of three years. Participants will be asked to complete a Hot Flash Score form. The Hot Flash Score will be measured at 1, 2 and 3 months following the initiation of androgen-deprivation therapy, and then every 3 months for total twelve-month period. Hot Flash score forms will be completed 6-monthly thereafter, for the remainder of the observation period. In addition to the Hot Flash Score, patients will have their baseline and progression testosterone and Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) levels measured as part of their standard of care. No additional pathology tests will be undertaken compared to men who would otherwise not be enrolled in this study. </interventions>
    <comparator>Nil.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objectives of this study is to determine the natural course of hot flash symptoms in men with receiving ADT for histologically confirmed, hormone-naive prostate cancer. 

Men will complete a validated questionnaire called the Hot Flash Score. This will be completed at 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months following the commencement of ADT. Thereafter, it will be carried out on a 6 monthly basis until completion of the study at 3 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The study cohort will be followed for a total of three years. The suggested clinical observation period is monthly for the first three months, three-monthly for the first year, and six-monthly thereafter, until the total three-year observation period concludes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	To measure the frequency and severity of hot flash symptoms in men receiving ADT using a validated hot flash instrument.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Hot Flash Score will be measured at 1, 2 and 3 months following commencement of ADT and every thereafter 3 months until 12 months following commencement of ADT.  For the remainder of the observation period, the Hot Flash Score will be completed every 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	To record any impact that testosterone and PSA levels may have on recorded hot flashes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Testosterone will be measured at 3 and 12 months. PSA will be measured at three months, and then every three months thereafter for the first twelve months. PSA will be measured six-monthly thereafter, until the end of the three year observation period. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men with histologically confirmed and hormone-naive prostate cancer, being commence on androgen-deprivation therapy for the first time. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria include previous androgen-deprivation therapy, participant inability to complete a hot flash score independently, and an ECOG status of 2 or more. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A student T-test will be used for parametric data and Wilcoxon matched pairs for non-parametric data. Categorical analysis will be conducted using a Chi Square test. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Professor Henry Woo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 406, SAN Clinic, 185 Fox Valley Road, Wahroonga.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>A/Prof Henry Woo,</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 406, SAN Clinic, 185 Fox Valley Road, Wahroonga.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Cindy Garcia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hornsby Hospital, Palmerston Rd  Hornsby NSW 2077, Australia.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is observing the natural course of hot flash symptoms in men receiving androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) in the form of luteinizing hormone releasing hormone (LHRH) analogues for histologically confirmed hormone-naive prostate cancer.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a male with histologically confirmed and hormone-naive prostate cancer and have commenced on ADT in the form of LHRH analogues for the first time.

Trial details
In this study, you will be observed for a total period of 3 years. You will be required to complete a validated questionnaire called the Hot Flash Score. This will need to be completed at 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months following commencement of ADT. Thereafter, you will be required to complete the Hot Flash Score questionnaire every 6 months until the completion of the study at 3 years. All other treatment and investigations will be carried out according to standard care  that is, no additional pathology tests will be undertaken compared to men who would otherwise not be enrolled in this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>
    </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Adventist Hospital (SAH) Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>185 Fox Valley Road
WAHROONGA NSW 2076</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Henry Woo</name>
      <address>Sydney Adventist Hospital, Suite 406, SAN Clinic. 185 Fox Valley Road, Wahroonga. NSW. 2076. 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9473 8850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hwoo@urologist.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cindy Garcia</name>
      <address>Hornsby Hospital, Palmerston Rd  Hornsby NSW 2077, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9477 9123</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cindy.jc.garcia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cindy Garcia</name>
      <address>Hornsby Hospital, Palmerston Rd  Hornsby NSW 2077, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9477 9123</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cindy.jc.garcia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>