<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368508">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000532505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pain Management in the Aged Care Population: The Impact of Light Therapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Will the implementation of Light Therapy (either bright or natural light) decrease pain levels in an aged care population, as opposed to no intervention/care as usual.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-9826</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain in an older population</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The two interventions being tested are Bright Light Therapy (arm 1) and Natural Light Therapy (arm 2). All participants will wear Actiwatches throughout the study, to monitor sleep and wake cycles, activity, and light exposure. All participants will be required to complete a Sleep Diary each day, detailing their sleep the previous day and night. Pain levels will be measured utilising the Brief Pain Inventory. 
Arm 1: Group 1 will be placed in a control group for the first 2 weeks, receiving care as usual. After this, Group 1 will be administered Bright Light Therapy using bright light therapy glasses. The researcher will attend PresCare aged care facility every morning for 10 days (2 weeks, Monday to Friday), to administer the glasses to participants. Participants will wear these glasses for 30 minutes each morning, between the hours of 6:30am and 7:30am. The glasses emit blue-green 500 nm dominant wavelength, UV-free light, and participants will be exposed to 30 minutes at 506 lux. The glasses have an adjustable nose piece, one size fits all. The glasses green light source has been independently tested for ocular safety to the standard CEI IEC 62471. The green light has been shown to be more effective in impacting older populations circadian rhythms due to clouding of the eye, which influenced the choice of glasses to be utilized or this study. After the 2 weeks, Group 1 will receive care as usual again, acting as a control group, still completing Sleep Diaries and wearing the Actiwatches. 
Arm 2: Group 2 will be a control group for the first 2 weeks, receiving care as usual but wearing the Actiwatches and completing the Sleep Diary. After 2 weeks, Natural Light Therapy will be administered to the group of participants. This will entail participants being exposed to natural sunlight for a block of 30 mins per day, to determine the impact of natural light on pain, and allow a comparison between Bright Light and Natural Light Therapy. Participants will be taken outside in the morning for 30 mins, and will be exposed to natural light for this time. After this, Group 2 will receive care as usual for another 2 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Both groups will receive care as usual for the first 2 weeks of the study, followed by Group 1 receiving bright light therapy for 2 weeks, and Group 2 receiving natural light therapy intervention for 2 weeks. Both groups will then receive care as usual as a control group again for another 2 weeks.
Each group will be administered the Brief Pain Inventory at baseline, after the first 2 weeks, after 4 weeks, and then at 6 weeks, at each differing intervention arm.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain scores as measured using the Brief Pain Inventory.
This measures pain severity and pain interference.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This measure will be administered to both groups at baseline, at 2 weeks (completion of care as usual/control 1), 4 weeks (the cessation of light therapy interventions), and 6 weeks (completion of care as usual/control 2).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>While sleep quality/quantity is not a primary outcome, the correlation between sleep and pain is well-documented, and sleep quality will be discussed as a secondary composite outcome. Sleep diaries will be kept by all participants, to monitor quality and quantity of sleep for 6 weeks, the duration of the study. This will also record napping throughout the day, and degree of restfulness after sleep.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily throughout the intervention, from Day 1 to Day 42.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidental light exposure will be a secondary outcome that will be monitored for. This is to identify any differences between individuals, and account for light exposure outside of the light therapy. Actiwatches will be worn by all participants to monitor sleep, activity and light exposure throughout the study. These will be worn by both groups, to monitor incidental light exposure and control for additional light exposure. Actiwatches are lightweight, waterproof and non-obstructive, and have been scientifically proven to monitor the sleep-wake cycle, activity and light exposure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Actiwatches to be worn throughout the experiment, from Day 1 - Day 42. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activity levels of participants will be a secondary outcome that will be monitored for. This is to identify any changes in activity levels as the intervention progresses, and account for any differences in pain outcomes. Actiwatches will be worn by all participants to monitor sleep, activity and light exposure throughout the study. These will be worn by both groups, to monitor activity levels throughout. Actiwatches are lightweight, waterproof and non-obstructive, and have been scientifically proven to monitor the sleep-wake cycle, activity and light exposure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily through the intervention, from Day 1 to 42.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be aged 65 and up, reporting pain, and scoring an average of 4 or above on the Brief Pain Inventory pain severity scale. Participants must be cognitively able to complete the Brief Pain Inventory and a sleep diary, either verbally or written.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>For both intervention arms, GP or clinical nurse approval will be sought before commencing the interventions. People who are taking photosensitizing medications are to be excluded, unless written approval from a doctor or clinical nurse can be obtained. The Bright Light Therapy glasses do not produce the wavelengths that photosensitizing medications react to, but it has been recommended that using any light therapy should be avoided, as well as avoiding direct sunlight until you are no longer using photosensitizing medication. 

For intervention Arm 1, exclusion criteria includes people with epilepsy, people who suffer from manic depressive psychosis or bipolar. People with cataracts, glaucoma or retinal disorders will need written permission from a doctor or clinical nurse in order to participate. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This study will be quasi-randomized. Due to stringent inclusion and exclusion conditions, participants who are ineligible to participate in the Bright Light Therapy intervention arm will be allocated to the Natural Light Therapy intervention arm if eligible. Bright Light Therapy intervention arm participants will consist of people who meet all the inclusion criteria, and have doctor or clinical nurse approval. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This intervention will utilise a small-n single case AB design.
By looking at each participant as a single case, due to the presumed small sample size, descriptives and graphs will be produced to demonstrate data and any significant effect sizes. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>6</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Stephanie Zylstra</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Central Queensland University
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Individual - Stephanie Zylstra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Central Queensland University
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Individual - Lynne Parkinson</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CQUniversity, Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Lynne Parkinson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Central Queensland University
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sandra Thomson, Facility Manager</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PresCare Alexandra Gardens
20 Withers St North Rockhampton QLD 4701</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Lynne Parkinson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>CQUniversity, Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is looking at the impact of light therapy on pain levels in an older population. There will be two participant groups, group 1 will receive bright light therapy using light therapy glasses, and group 2 will receive natural light therapy. Both groups will receive their specified light therapy for 10 days (2 weeks, Monday to Friday), and will also have two weeks with care as usual before and after receiving light therapy. Group 1 will receive care as usual for the first 2 weeks, then bright light therapy first for 2 weeks, followed by another 2 weeks of care as usual. Group 2 will also receive 2 weeks of care as usual for the first 2 weeks, and will then receive 2 weeks of natural light therapy. This will be followed by another 2 weeks of care as usual. It is hypothesised that light therapy will reduce reported pain levels in an older population. The Brief Pain Inventory will be administered at baseline, 2 weeks, 4 weeks and 6 weeks of the study. A daily Sleep Diary will be kept by all participants, and an Actiwatch2 will be worn for the duration of the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Queensland University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services (Bldg 32 Level 2)
CQUniversity Australia
Bruce Highway
North Rockhampton QLD 4701</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368508-Brief Pain Inventory.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368508-Participant Consent Form.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368508-Participant Demographic Questions.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368508-PresCare approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368508-Sleep Diary.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368508-Actiwatch2 Brochure.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lynne Parkinson</name>
      <address>B32, CQuniversity
Bruce Highway, Rockhampton
QLD 4701</address>
      <phone>+61409698382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.parkinson@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Stephanie Zylstra</name>
      <address>Central Queensland University
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</address>
      <phone>+61409698382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.zylstra@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Stephanie Zylstra</name>
      <address>Central Queensland University
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</address>
      <phone>+61409698382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.zylstra@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Stephanie Zylstra</name>
      <address>Central Queensland University
Bruce Highway
Rockhampton QLD 4701</address>
      <phone>+61409698382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.zylstra@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>