<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335971">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000774022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of ocular comfort and physiological ocular changes in symptomatic and non-symptomatic contact lens wearers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, multiple group, cross-over bilateral, double-masked clinical trial assessing ocular comfort and ocular changes in symptomatic and non-symptomatic contact lens wearers when using two commercially-available contact lens/solution combinations</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contact lens wear</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ocular comfort</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a multiple-group, cross over, bilateral, double-masked clinical trial. Participants will use 2 combinations of lens/solution: ACUVUE ADVANCE/AQuify and PureVision/OPTI-FREE RepleniSH  for seven consecutive days on a daily wear basis commencing the day after initial lens dispense. Visits will take place on day 1 and 8 of lens wear with each combination, and a minimum wash-out period of 48 hours will apply between each lens/solution combination.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control- cross over study</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular comfort as measured by subjective ratings:
This will involve a 1-10 Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) in steps of 0.1, where 1 = extreme discomfort and 10 = no discomfort, and a 2 point Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) where the midpoint corresponds to comfort without contact lens, the lower end of the scale is described as 'unbearable' and the upper end is left open</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 2, 5, 6, 8 of each treatment arm</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular response. this will be assessed with a slit lamp biomicroscope, which is a specialised microscope used to view the eye</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1 and 8 of each treatment arm</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be "normal" and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses; 
Has vision correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses;
Have participated in at least one of previous matrix trials (ANZCTR #: 12608000329369) and satisfy criteria for 'symptomatic' or 'non-symptomatic'. The definitions of  'symptomatic' or 'non-symptomatic' below are based solely on a participant's experience in previous matrix trials:
Symptomatic contact lens wearers are defined as participants who have experienced a one point decrease or more in end-of-day ocular comfort compared to comfort-on-insertion at three scheduled visits.
Non-symptomatic contact lens wearers will be classified as either 'primary' or 'secondary'. Secondary wearers will only be used if insufficient numbers are available from primary wearers:
Primary wearers: participants who have experienced a less than one point decrease in end-of-day ocular comfort compared to comfort-on-insertion at three scheduled visits.
Secondary wearers: participants who have not experienced a one point decrease or more in end-of-day ocular comfort compared to comfort-on-insertion at any scheduled visit, provided at least two visits were attended. 
Participants who have completed two or more matrix trials and satisfy the definition for both symptomatic and non-symptomatic wearers will be excluded from this trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including keratoconus and herpes keratitis) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjogrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosis. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
An active corneal infection or any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication up to 12 weeks prior to and during the trial;
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse manner or risk providing a false positive. 
N.B. Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial;  
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
Previous corneal refractive surgery;
Contraindications to contact lens wear;
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial;
Participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks for dispensing studies and 48 hours between in-house studies;
Be pregnant;</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/10/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/05/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, 
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, 
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to determine whether ocular comfort can improved in symptomatic contact lens wearers by using a lens/solution combination which offers consistent performance</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Tilia D, Lazon de la Jara P, Peng N, Papas EB, Holden BA.
Effect of lens and solution choice on the comfort of contact lens wearers
Optom Vis Sci. 2013 May;90(5):411-8</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>VIHEC Human Research Ethics Committe</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>VisionCRC Ltd, Level 4, North Wing, RMB
Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293856165</phone>
      <fax>+61293857404</fax>
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293856165</phone>
      <fax>+61293857404</fax>
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293856165</phone>
      <fax>+61293857404</fax>
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street, UNSW, Sydney NSW 2052  </address>
      <phone>+61293857404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>