<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367805">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000375550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of temperature change during operation of obesity.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study to examine if anesthesia during laparoscopic abdominal surgery induces thermoregulatory response changes in the obese. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>anesthesia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>60 patients will be enrolled in the study with laparoscopic abdominal surgery under general anesthesia. Patients will be divided into two groups according to body mass index (Group I: if BMI is equal ot greater than 30 and Group II: if BMI is below than 24.9). In all cases, to avoid errors in body temperature measurements arising from the
diurnal rhythm, body temperature measurements were taken in the morning between 08:30 and 13:00 hours.
After preoxygenation with 100% O2, intravenous induction of anesthesia was obtained with 2-2,5 mg/kg propofol 0.6mg/kg rocuronium and 0.1 mcg/kg remifentanyl. After endotracheal intubation, anesthesia was maintained with 5-6% desflurane in 50% air-50% O2. Respiration was continued mechanically
and was adjusted to 30 to 40 mmHg ETCO2. In addition, to partially humidify and heat inhaled gases, a disposable humidifier was added to the breathing circuit. When necessary, patients were given additional doses of remifentanyl infusion and rocuronium. To remove the residual
muscle relaxant effects during recovery from anesthesia, 0.04 mg/kg neostigmine, and when required, 0.01 mg/kg intravenous atropine was used. When laryngeal reflexes and adequate spontaneous breathing returned, the patients were extubated.
The patients's temperature will follow every 5 minutes during operating room and postanesthetic care unit. Temperatures will record from central temperature, axillary, wrist, finger, thigh, cruris.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will be generated from patients with normal body mass index (&lt;24.9).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nasopharengeal temperature
(nasopharengeal temperature measured via anesthesia machine)</outcome>
      <timepoint>before anesthesia induction, in 5-minute intervals after the induction of
anesthesia, and in arrival to PACU</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean skin temperature [0.3 (Tchest+Tarm) + 0.2 (Tthigh+Tcalf)]
(peripheral temperatures measured via anesthesia machine
thermometers)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>before anesthesia induction, in 5-minute intervals after the induction of anesthesia until arrival to PACU.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean body temperature [0.64 x Tcentral + 0.36 x Tskin]
(tympanic temperature measured via infrared thermometer, but peripheral
temperatures measured via anesthesia machine thermometers)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>before anesthesia induction, in 5-minute intervals after the induction of anesthesia until arrival to PACU</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shivering score (0: no shivering, 1: presence of one or more of such findings as piloerection, peripheral vasoconstriction, and peripheral cyanosis without muscle movement, 2: presence of muscle activity observable in single muscle group, 3: presence of muscle activity in more than one muscle group, 4: presence of significant muscle activity observed in the whole body)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission to post anesthetic care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The study was included 60 patients aged between 18-60 years whose physical status was in the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) I-III risk group and were scheduled for laparoscopic abdominal surgery. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with inflammatory diseases, diabetes mellitus, muscle disease, hypo/hyperthyroidism, cardiac, hepatic and renal diseases, Parkinson disease, Reynold syndrome, a history of using drugs that are known to affect body temperature (Beta-blockers, calcium channel blockers,
clonidine, steroids, anti-epileptic, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, benzodiazepine), drug and alcohol addiction, obesity were excluded from the study. In addition,
patients whose surgery was shorter than 60 minutes and longer than 180 minutes were also excluded from the study. Patients having a greater than 30% change in
hemodynamic parameters during the surgery, those who needed to use a vasopressor or vasodilator, and those who required a blood transfusion were excluded from the study as well.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analyses will perform using IBM SPSS (Statistical Package for the Social Sciences) version 20. Data distribution was analyzed using the analysis of variance. Parametric data was expressed as the mean ± standard deviation. Following the assessment of age, weight, height, BMI, duration of surgery and all parametric data with variance analysis, an independent t test was used for between-group comparisons. Within-group comparisons were performed with paired sample t test. ASA risk class within the groups was assessed using chi-square test.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Elazig</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ayse Belin OZER</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation, Firat University Medicine School, 23119, Elazig</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Hypothermia is the most common thermoregulatory disorder encountered during anesthetic methods and it can cause complications. Subcutaneous fat tissues increse in the obese. Therefore, aim of this study has observed whether anesthesia induced thermoregulatory respones changes in the obese.

Methods: Our study will include 60 patients aged 18-60 years within the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) I-III risk group who will scheduled for laparoscopic abdomen surgery. Patients will divide into two groups according to body mass index (in Group II, BMI&lt; 24.9 and Group I &gt; or equal 30). Probes for measuring the nasopharengeal membrane and peripheral temperature will place in patients, and their mean skin temperature and mean body temperature will assess immediately before the induction of anesthesia and 5, 10, 15, 20, 30, 45, 60, 90 and 120 minutes after the induction of anesthesia. Shivering score will record at postanesthesia care unit. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Firat University  Ethical Evaluation Commission Chairman</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Firat University  Ethical Evaluation Commission Chairman
Firat University
23119,Elazig</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/12/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ayse Belin OZER</name>
      <address>Firat University Medicine Faculty Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Department 23119, Elazig</address>
      <phone>+90 533 4478924</phone>
      <fax>+90 424 2388096</fax>
      <email>abelinozer@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ayse Belin OZER</name>
      <address>Firat University Medicine Faculty Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Department 23119, Elazig</address>
      <phone>+ 90 533 447 8924</phone>
      <fax>+90 424 2388096</fax>
      <email>abelinozer@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ayse Beklin OZER</name>
      <address>Firat University Medicine Faculty Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Department 23119, Elazig</address>
      <phone>+90 533 4478924</phone>
      <fax>+90 424 2388096</fax>
      <email>abelinozer@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ayse Belin OZER</name>
      <address>Firat University Medicine Faculty Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Department 23119, Elazig</address>
      <phone>+90 533 4478924</phone>
      <fax>+90 424 2388096</fax>
      <email>abelinozer@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>