<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335779">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000642088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Fit 4 Fun Program: Promoting physical fitness and health in primary school children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of a school-based physical fitness intervention on physical activity behaviours, physical fitness levels and attitudes towards physical fitness in primary school children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Fit 4 Fun</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical fitness in primary school children</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity in primary school children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Fit 4 Fun Program is an 8-week comprehensive school-based health-related fitness program designed for Stage 3 primary school students. Its effectiveness and suitability for use in primary schools will be evaluated through a Randomized Control Trial (RCT) feasibility study in two primary schools. The Fit 4 Fun program will take a multi-faceted approach to physical fitness education by involving students, staff, parents and family members in a range of fun and challenging activities designed to increase knowledge, skills and attitudes regarding physical fitness and health. The Fit 4 Fun Program was developed in accordance to the NSW Personal Development, Health &amp; Physical Education (PDHPE) K-6 curriculum and is grounded in Bandura's Social Cognitive Theory and Harter's Competence Motivation theory. The program facilitates behaviour change by targeting the following mediators of change: self-efficacy, social support, self-monitoring and enjoyment. The Fit 4 Fun program focuses on the three areas of a 'Health Promoting School' by having programs that combine to improve the physical fitness behaviours and attitudes of children and their families. They are:- 1) Home: the children complete an 8 week home activity program with their parents and siblings &amp; / or friends. The program is completed 4 times for week and not only engages the participants in a range of innovative fitness-based activities and games but also provides activities specifically designed to enhance skills is self-evaluation, physical fitness assessment and goal-setting. The children are provided with a home activity booklet and access to equipment. 2) Curriculum: the students participate in 8 weekly PDHPE lessons (60min) that are specifically designed to improve knowledge, skills, understanding and appreciation of the role that physical fitness and fitness assessment plays in improving health. The lessons combine theoretical and practical learning experiences across the 4 health-related fitness components (flexibility, muscular fitness, body composition and cardio-respiratory fitness). The teachers and students are provided with work booklets, all resources and learning materials. 3) School Environment: during recess and lunch breaks, children are encouraged to participate in a wide range of fun activities, small-sided games and fitness challenges to not only get the children physically active but to improve their physical fitness levels. The children are provided with game cards and equipment, and are encouraged to be self-motivated &amp; directed during their break times.</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait list control. Schools in the control group will receive the intervention at the completion of the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-Related Physical Fitness 1) Cardiorespiratory fitness will be assessed using the 20m shuttle test (beep test) 2) Muscular fitness will be assessed using the 7-stage sit-up test, the Basketball Throw test, Cadence Push-Up test and Wall Squat Test. 3) Flexibility will be assessed using the Sit &amp; Reach test and the Shoulder Stretch test. 4) Body Composition will calculated using measurements from height (stadiometer) and weight (callibrated scales).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at the completion of the intervention (10 weeks after basline measures).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Physical Activity will be assessed using at least 5 days of pedometery (4 week days and 1 weekend day)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at the completion of the intervention (10 weeks after basline measures).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Perceptions of physical fitness &amp; fitness testing: using a questionnaire (students &amp; teachers). The questionnaire is a purpose designed survey assessing participants thoughts and feelings about physical fitness and fitness testing. Demographic information will also be collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at the completion of the intervention (10 weeks after basline measures).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stage 3 Primary School Children (year 5 &amp; 6).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>9</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>13</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All students in the Stage 3 class will participate in the program, however, only the students who provide signed consent letters will complete the assessments and evaluations. Students will also be ineligible to be included in the program evaluation if they currently have a medical condition or physical injury preventing testing or training (they will be able to participate in the program).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Two primary schools from the Lake Macquarie Region will be invited to participate in the feasibility study of the Fit 4 Fun Program. a) Initial contact – The school Principals will be contacted by Narelle Eather and invited to participate in the study. The Principals will be provided with an information statement outlining the feasibility study in detail. If the Principal consents to the school’s participation in the study then Narelle Eather will make contact with the Stage 3 teacher to seek permission to conduct the feasibility study with their class. The classroom teacher will also be given an information statement outlining the Fit 4 Fun program and their role during the delivery stage. A consent form will be collected from the participating teacher. b) Recruitment – Once a school has expressed interest in the project and have returned their consent forms, Narelle Eather will contact the school and request an opportunity to present the research proposal to students. Information leaflets will be distributed at a school assembly. All parents and students will be provided with information and consent letters. Once all consent letters have been collected and eligibility determined then baseline assesments will be conducted and randomisation will occur at the school level. Allocation will be concealed and conducted after eligibility has been determined. The allocation of groups will be conducted 'off-site' and the allocation schedule will be announced by the off-site administrator.</concealment>
    <sequence>A simple randomisation method of a coin test will be conducted to allocate schools to either the control or the treatment conditions. This method ensures that all schools will have an equal likelihood of allocation to either the control or intervention group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Wait list control design. Participants assigned to the control group will receive the intervention at the completion of the study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/04/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>56</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Narelle Eather</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Health and Physical Education Building (HPE)
The University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW. 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Narelle Eather</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Health and Physical Education Building (HPE)
The University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW. 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Newcastle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW. 2308</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to evaluate the impact of a school-based health-related fitness intervention (Fit 4 Fun) on the fitness and activity levels, and attitudes towards phsyical fitness, of Stage 3 primary school students. The study will assess changes over 10 weeks and the feasibility and efficacy of the program for use in primary schools will be assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Callaghan Campus,
University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2009-0397</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Narelle Eather</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
School of Education
Callaghan Campus,
University Drive,
NSW, 2308.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49216232</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49217407</fax>
      <email>Narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Narelle Eather</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
School of Education
Callaghan Campus,
University Drive,
NSW, 2308.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49216232</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49217407</fax>
      <email>narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Narelle Eather</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
School of Education
Callaghan Campus,
University Drive,
NSW, 2308.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49216232</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49217407</fax>
      <email>narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Narelle Eather</name>
      <address>HPE 310
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>0425302312</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>