<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83713">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000945921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early lung disease in young infants and young children with cystic fibrosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The relationship between the lung clearance index, airway infection and inflammation and systemic inflammatory markers in infants and young children with cystic fibrosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Early lung disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Newborn screened infants with cystic fibrosis less than 3 years of age attending the Cystic Fibrosis clinic at Sydney Children's Hospital Randwick will be prospectively recruited for bronchoalveolar lavage, infant lung function testing, a chest xray and venepuncture. 
A control group of similarly aged healthy infants undergoing sedated cardiac echo or a DMSA scan will also be recruited for infant lung function testing over the same period thus serving as the normative or reference population for  infant lung function.
Healthy in fants and infants with CF will undergo sedated lung function on a single occasion over a duration of approximately one hour.</interventions>
    <comparator>Healthy infants and young children without previous respiratory, cardiac or neurologic imparirment attending Sydney Children's Hospital RANDWICK for a sedated cardiac echo or DMSA renal scan will be approached to undergo lung function as a follow on procedure whilst sedated for their primary investigation</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung Clearance Index measured by a multiple-breath washout  (MBW) method using a commercially available Infant Lung Function Testing System (Exhalyzer R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline: One-off measurement in this cross-sectional  case-control study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bronchoalveolar lavage markers of infection (measured by quantitative microbiologic culture) and inflammation (neutrophils, totol cell count , neutrophil elastase and interleukin-8, and the S100 proteins)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline: one off measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systemic markers of inflammation including the S100 proteins and C-reactive protein and blood neutrophils in additon to urinary desmosine</outcome>
      <timepoint>All at baseline as a one off measurement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of an abnormal ph probe indicating gastro-oesophageal reflux (only in children with CF)</outcome>
      <timepoint>All at baseline as a one off measurement only in subjects with CF</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Cystic fibrosis infants under age 3 years and healthy control children under 3 years of age will be recruited for sedated lung function testing. CF children up to 5 years of age will also undergo venepuncture and urine analysis for desmosine determination</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Chronic neonatal lung disease
Other respiratory disease
Cardiac disease
Neuurologic disease
Respiratory infection in the 3 weeks prior to infant lung function testing</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Case control</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Yvonne Belessis MBBS(Hons) FRACP MPH PhD</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Children's Hospital 
High Street
RANDWICK, NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of New South Wales</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Randwick, NSW 2031</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Although the lungs in children with cystic fibrosis (CF) are essentially normal at birth, airway infection and inflammation may begin within the first few weeks of life. As postnatal lung development, including significant alveolarisation continues during the first 2-3 years of life, this is a vulnerable period where undiagnosed infection and chronic inflammation may lead to irreversible tissue damage and lung disease. Identifying and treating infection (especially with Pseudomonas), in early childhood may prevent significant lung disease, reduce morbidity and improve survival. 
Early infection is often subclinical and conventional screening methods such as sputum microbiology, chest radiology and lung function, are either not possible or insensitive to detect disease in this age group. Upper airway cultures such as throat swabs or cough suction specimens correlate poorly with lower airway pathogens and the currently available systemic markers of inflammation lack sensitivity. Bronchoaclveolar lavage (BAL) is considered the gold standard for identifying airway infection and inflammation in young children with CF. The association between BAL markers of infection and inflammation and sensitive infant lung function testing such as the multiple breath washout test which determines the lung clearance index has not been studied. 
This study will investigate early CF lung disease by assessing the relationships between BAL markers of infection/inflammation, the lung clearance index, systemic markers of neutrophil inflammation (S100 proteins) and urinary desmosine. The study will also determine the prevalence of gastro-oesophageal reflux and the relationship between BAL pepsin and airway infection and inflammation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentations:
1. Early detection of cystic fibrosis lung disease: LCI predicts BAL evidence of infection and inflammation. TSANZ 2009

2. BAL pepsin is associated with infection in infants and young children with cystic fibrosis and is suggestive of concurrent microaspiration in early CF lung disease. TSANZ 2008</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney and Illawarra Health Service- Eastern Section</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hospital Research and Ethics Committee (HREC) Prince of Wales Hospital High Street 
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/01/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/02/0098</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Yvonne Belessis</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital 
High Street
RANDWICK, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 2 93821246</phone>
      <fax>61 2 93821580</fax>
      <email>y.belessis@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Yvonne Belessis</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital 
High Street
RANDWICK, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 2 93821246</phone>
      <fax>61 2 93821580</fax>
      <email>y.belessis@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Yvonne Belessis</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital 
High Street
RANDWICK, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 2 93821246</phone>
      <fax>61 2 93821580</fax>
      <email>y.belessis@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>