<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368483">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000520538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dancing for Parkinsons disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Dance Therapy for Parkinsons Disease: A Feasibility Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1 - Mixed dancing. Participants in the Mixed Dancing group will receive a 60 minute dancing class weekly for 8 weeks at a dance studio. The dance classes will be held by experienced dance teachers along with trained assistants. The mixed dancing group will include a preliminary warm up consisting of stretching, balance and postural exercises. The dancing class will use mixed dance genres such as jazz, ballet, tap dance, Irish dance, perform sitting on a chair and standing up. The sets will be chosen to improve range of movement, coordination, balance, rhythm, strength, gait and activities of daily living. The cool down will include stretching and relaxation exercises. Participants shall also do a simple and safe home program sitting on a chair once per week for 8 weeks at the time of the dancing classes. The participants will receive a DVD with 40 minutes of dance exercises based on the mixed classes to be perform at home.

Adherence will be monitored with participant's list, home program diary and exit questionnaire. All participants will complete a exit questionnaire after the program with question regarding the dance program.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2 - Tango. The other group will receive Argentine Tango classes for up to 60 minutes weekly for 8 weeks at a dance studio. The sessions will be held by a different dance teacher along with trained assistants. The protocol will include warm up, dance steps and cool down using Argentine Tango. Participants shall also do a simple and safe home program sitting on a chair once per week for 8 weeks at the time of the dancing classes. The participants will receive a DVD with 40 minutes of dance exercises based on the Tango classes to be perform at home.

Adherence will be monitored with participant's list, home program diary and exit questionnaire. All participants will complete a exit questionnaire after the program with question regarding the dance program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome for this trial is feasibility, which includes four specific sub types. 

FEASIBILITY. The specific feasibility outcomes comprised (i) the number of people agreeing to participate in the dancing classes, (ii) the number who completed all pre-tests and follow up tests, (iii) compliance with each of the dancing classes and home programs and (iv) the number of adverse events. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Feasibility outcomes were assessed in different time points:
(i) the number of people agreeing to participate in the dancing classes - Recruitment and admission phases 
(ii) the number who completed all pre-tests and follow up tests - Before intervention and after discharge 
(iii) compliance with each of the dancing classes and home programs - During the eight weeks of intervention
(iv) the number of adverse events - During the eight weeks of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility - Timed up and Go</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants were assessed two time: - Baseline - before dancing classes - After 8 weeks of the dance program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freezing of gait - Freezing of gait questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants were assessed two time: - Baseline - before dancing classes - After 8 weeks of the dance program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance - Berg Balance Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants were assessed two time: - Baseline - before dancing classes - After 8 weeks of the dance program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activities of daily living and motor impairment - UPDRS II and III</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants were assessed two time: - Baseline - before dancing classes - After 8 weeks of the dance program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - PDQ - 39</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants were assessed two time: - Baseline - before dancing classes - After 8 weeks of the dance program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of the dance program will be measured by the incidence of adverse events during the classes or home program. The adverse events will be described, as well as severity of injury, need for hospitalization and reason for withdrawal the program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the 8 week intervention period participants will be monitored. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait and balance - Functional Gait Assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants were assessed two time: - Baseline - before dancing classes - After 8 weeks of the dance program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will have been clinically diagnosed with Parkinson's disease, be aged 20 to 85 years, male or female, Stage I - IV modified Hoehn and Yarh scale were included.
(mild to moderate impairment) and be without cognitive deficits (scores &lt;24 on Mini Mental State Examination). People will need to be independently mobile and able to travel to the dance venue to be included. They will not receive any money for attending. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they are unable to walk six metres with assistance or gait aid or if they have pain. They will also be excluded if they have cognitive impairment as defined as a score of less than 24 on the Mini Mental Examination test, any neurological disease other than Parkinson's. Individuals who are unable to understand written and spoken English will be excluded. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After screening procedure for eligibility and baseline testing,  participants were randomized to one of the groups. A third party used the computer generated number sequence to allocate participants according to the baseline testing time. Sealed opaque envelopes were used.</concealment>
    <sequence>We used computer generated number sequences for randomization. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>According to previous feasibility studies about dancing for PD at least 20 participants were determined to be required. The feasibility results were summarized using the Consort Statement Flow Diagram.  We analysed the number of people recruited in a 2 month period, the number of these who agreed to participate in the dancing classes, the number who completed all pre-tests and follow-up tests, the compliance with each of the dancing classes and home programs (%) and the number and type of adverse events. We also analysed the data for the secondary variables from pre-test to post-test using Repeated measures ANOVA.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>21</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>La Trobe University - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CAPES Foundation, Ministry od Education of Brazil.

* One of the researchers (Priscila Alves da Rocha) received a scholarship from the Brazilian government for this research.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>State / City: Brasilia / DF
Country: Brazil
Postcode: 70040-020
Setor Bancario Norte - Quadra 2 Bloco L - Second floor</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Meg Morris</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>La Trobe University - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to evaluate the feasibility and safety of dancing classes for individuals with Parkinson's disease (PD). We will compare mixed genre dancing classes with Argentine tango classes. Mobility, walking performance, quality of life and wellbeing will be assessed up to one week before, up to one week after the program. Our hypothesis is that participants in the mixed dancing group will improve the outcomes analysed more than the ones on the tango group. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>The article will be submitted to a journal soon. It was not published yet.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Human Ethics Committee (UHEC) - La Trobe University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>La Trobe University - Human Ethics Officer

Secretariat  SHE College Human Ethics Sub-Committee
Ethics and Integrity / Research Office

La Trobe University Bundoora - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>S15/22</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368483-S15-22 Approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Priscila Alves da Rocha</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086

College Science, Health &amp; Engineering </address>
      <phone>+610435409284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>P.rocha@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meg Morris</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086

College Science, Health &amp; Engineering
</address>
      <phone>+61 0433 405 662 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.morris@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meg Morris</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086 

College Science, Health &amp; Engineering
 </address>
      <phone>+61 043 5409 284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.morris@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Priscila Alves da Rocha</name>
      <address>La Trobe University, Bundoora - Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Melbourne VIC 3086

College Science, Health &amp; Engineering
</address>
      <phone>+61 043 5409 284</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>P.rocha@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>