<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372239">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000970347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Targeted gluteal exercise program versus sham exercise program for people with hip osteoarthritis (the GHOST trial (Gluteal exercise for Hip OSTeoarthritis): A randomized controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Targeted gluteal exercise program versus sham exercise program for people with hip osteoarthritis (the GHOST trial (Gluteal exercise for Hip OSTeoarthritis): A randomized controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-1408</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>hip osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Comparison of two exercise programs
Participants will be randomly allocated to the GHOst intervention or the sham intervention. Both groups will receive standardised education for hip osteoarthritis, delivered by a physiotherapist and supplemented with handouts. Education will focus on an understanding of the condition and advice on physical activity.   

The intervention (Gluteal Hip Osteoarthritis; GHOst) program will consist of once weekly, 30-minute supervised physiotherapy sessions and a self-managed exercise program over 12 weeks. The self-managed home exercise program will consist of the same exercises prescribed during the supervised sessions. The initial physiotherapy session will be a one to one session for one hour, incorporating education and exercises, delivered by the physiotherapist. The additional supervised sessions will be conducted in an individual or group setting (i.e. 1-3 participants per session), based on availability of participants and scheduling of the community physiotherapist. Participants will only attend group sessions with other participants who have been randomised to the same intervention. Whether participants attended group or individual sessions will be documented by the physiotherapist, and accounted for as a covariate in statistical analysis. 

The GHOst protocol is composed of three phases; gait retraining, motor control, and pelvic stability with global strengthening.  The aim of the gait retraining phase is to normalize, prevent or retard gait related impairments that are commonly associated with hip osteoarthritis. Physiotherapists will instruct participants to normalise stride length and asymmetry. The second phase of the GHOst intervention aims to promote the function of the anterior hip muscles using targeted, functional progressions of a squat and bridge exercise. The third phase of the GHOst protocol aims to improve pelvic stability and overall lower limb and trunk strength and function. These exercises progress from isometric hip hitching exercises, through to high resistance strength training of multiple muscle groups (e.g. double leg squat and dead-lift) with the aid of thera-band and power-bands to achieve the required 'heavy' load dose.  

Each phase can begin simultaneously at their first supervised physiotherapy session. Exercises are progressed based on quality (judged by the physiotherapist) and symptoms (pain not exceeding 5/10). All phases will be incorporated into each session, with approximately 5 minutes for gait retraining and the remaining time used for motor control and pelvic stability.  

Daily exercise adherence will be monitored with an exercise diary
</interventions>
    <comparator>Sham exercise program
The control group will receive a 12 week sham exercise program not focused on the rehabilitation of gluteal muscles, but still instructed by a physiotherapist. Participants will receive the same number and duration of supervised sessions as the GHOst intervention group. There are four stages of sham gluteal exercises that include gluteal squeezes, seated hip abduction, standing lateral flexion with feet apart and standing lateral trunk flexion with feet together. This will be combined with low resistance quadriceps and calf exercises including seated knee extensions and seated calf raises. 

The self-managed home exercise program will consist of the same exercises prescribed during the supervised sessions. Daily exercise adherence will be monitored with an exercise diary. Each phase (e.g. gluteal, quadriceps, calf) can begin simultaneously at their first supervised physiotherapy session. Exercises are progressed based on quality (judged by the physiotherapist) and symptoms (pain not exceeding 5/10). All phases will be incorporated into each session, so that participants complete gluteal, quadriceps and calf exercises in all sessions. 
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index
(WOMAC)- Physical Function item
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 (baseline), 7 (mid-intervention), 13 &amp; 27 (post-intervention)
Primary timepoint is 13 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity by triaxial accelerometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 (baseline), 13 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function- 40 m fast-paced walk test


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 (baseline), and 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric hip strength using handheld dynamometer. Hip abduction, adduction, flexion, extension, internal rotation, external rotation.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 (baseline) &amp; 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain: The average pain over the previous week will be assessed using an 11-point numerical rating scale (NRS), anchored by 0 = no pain and 10 = worst pain possible. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 (baseline), 7, 13 &amp; 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip dysfunction and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (HOOS);  Oxford Hip Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 7, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as assessed by the Assessment of Quality of Life Questionnaire (AQoL). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 7, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>International Physical Activity Screening Questionnaire (Short)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 7, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Catastrophizing Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 (baseline), 7, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global Rating of Change: An 11-point scale where participants are asked to rate their overall change in condition. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 7, 13, &amp; 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle size. A sub-group of 30 participants only (15 in each group). Muscle size of the lateral hip muscles will be measured using magnetic resonance imaging. One site only </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 and 13.

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gluteus medius and minimus muscle activity - fine-wire electromyography (EMG). Recorded in a sub-group of 30 participants (15 in each group)- one site only</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 and 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function- Stair climb test</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks (baseline) and 13 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function - 	Chair stand test</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks (baseline) and 13 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brief Fear of Movement Scale for Osteoarthritis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 (baseline), 7, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Health Questionnaire-9</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0 (baseline), 7, 13, 27</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle adiposity. A sub-group of 30 participants only (15 in each group). Muscle adiposity of the lateral hip muscles will be measured using magnetic resonance imaging. One site only </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 and 13.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i)	aged &gt; 35 years; 
(ii)	pain in the hip or groin for more than 3 months; 
(iii)	pain intensity over the past week of 3/10 or more on a numerical rating scale during functional tasks like walking, climbing stairs or climbing in/ out of a car; 
(iv)	radiographic confirmation of hip osteoarthritis with Kellgren-Lawrence score = 2;
(v)	Mild to moderate disability indicated by;
          (a) Oxford hip score of 25-45 indicating mild to moderate disability;
          (b) Still able to reciprocally ascend and descend 10 stairs unaided;
          (c) still able to safely walk one city block;
          (d) still able to jog 5 meters</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Volunteers will be ineligible for the following reasons; 

(i)	Other musculoskeletal lower limb conditions requiring assessment or treatment in the last 6 months; 
(ii)	Primary complaint of gluteal tendinopathy (clinical diagnosis), low back pain or referred back pain; 
(iii)	History of hip trauma or surgery on the affected side (leading to secondary hip osteoarthritis); 
(iv)	Known knee joint pathology or reduced knee range of motion (&lt;90 deg Flexion)
(v)	Corticosteroid use (oral or intra-articular) in the past 3 months
(vi)	Neurological impairment or condition affecting lower limb function
(vii)	Conditions or factors affecting their ability to take part in the exercise intervention, e.g, unavailable for a 12 week intervention period, routine use of gait aids, uncontrolled hypertension, or morbid obesity (BMI&gt;40); 
(viii)	Systemic inflammatory disease (e.g. rheumatoid arthritis); 
(ix)	Unable to write, read or comprehend English.

In addition, participants at one site (total of 30 participants) will be asked to complete a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan and undergo fine-wire electromyography (EMG) of gluteus minimus and gluteus medius muscles. These volunteers will be ineligible to participate if they have contraindication to fine-wire EMG (e.g. fear of needles, taking blood thinning medication) or MRI (e.g. pacemaker, claustrophobia).  
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An investigator (off-site at a central administration site) not involved in participant screening or recruitment will be responsible for generating the allocation sequence (stratified by site). Group allocations will be concealed in serially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes for each site. These envelopes will be posted to a research assistant at each site who is not involved in participant screening or recruitment. The research assistant will open the envelopes sequentially according to participant number and notify the trial physiotherapist of the participant’s group allocation prior to the participant’s first appointment (after screening for eligibility, enrollment and baseline testing). </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a web based randomization program (https://www.randomizer.org/) with a 1:1 allocation ratio stratified by site (4 sites)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The minimal clinically important difference for the WOMAC is 6 physical function units and the SD of change in WOMAC over 13 weeks is 9.2 units. based on these values, a total sample size of 76 participants (38 per group) is required to detect a clinically important difference between sham and intervention groups, with a power of 80% and an alpha of 0.05. To account for potential drop-outs similar to those reported in previous studies we will recruit 90 participants (45 per group). 

Statistical analysis will use intention to treat principles and on a per-protocol basis. Data analysed will focus on detecting the between group treatment and within group treatment effects (with effect sizes and 95% confidence intervals) at each of the follow up time points. A linear mixed model will be used for the primary analysis of the changes in the WOMAC and the accelerometry data due to its advantages in modelling the influence of nonlinear, individual differences over time. Adjustments will be made for the respective baseline outcome measures, as-well as age, sex and BMI.  The secondary outcomes will be assessed using t-tests or Mann Whitney U tests, adjusting for baseline differences if required. The global rating of change scale will be dichotomised to define "success" as those with a score of "Moderately Better" to "Very Much Better" (i.e. +3 or more). A generalized mixed model (adjusted for baseline differences and covariates) will be used to assess differences in the proportion of "successes" between groups over each time point. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>0</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Bendigo Health Care Group - Bendigo Hospital - Bendigo</hospital>
    <postcode>3550 - Bendigo</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>College of Science, Health &amp; Engineering
PO Box 199
Bendigo
VIC 3552</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arthritis Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 255 Broadway
Glebe NSW 2007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>College of Science, Health &amp; Engineering
PO Box 199
Bendigo
VIC 3552</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Queensland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
St Lucia campus
Brisbane
QLD 4067</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Otago</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Anatomy
PO Box 913
Dunedin
NZ 9054
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoarthritis (OA) is a common condition affecting many people. The number of people affected with hip OA is expected to rise exponentially over the coming years due to the ageing population and growing obesity rates. Conservative, targeted interventions (including exercise) are theoretically considered important in order to negate the economic cost and potential adverse events related to the typical intervention for end-stage hip OA; total hip replacement. However, recent studies conclude that current rehabilitation programs are limited in terms of improving hip function and reducing pain. It is suggested that current programs are ineffective due to their inability to target the right muscles, and they don't align with progressive resistance strength and conditioning principles, limiting their scope to cause effective change in muscle function over time.  
Our research team has devised an innovative exercise program that targets the hip muscles that are most affected in people with hip OA. Using these techniques, in combination with contemporary strength and conditioning principles, we wish to investigate whether this program has better success in improving function, pain and quality of life than a standard exercise program. 

This study is being conducted jointly by La Trobe University, University of Queensland and University of Otago and will recruit 90 participants over 4 sites (Bendigo, Melbourne, Brisbane and Dunedin).
This research is funded by Arthritis Australia and La Trobe University.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bendigo Health HEC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bendigo Health
Bendigo
VIC 3550</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/BHCG/3</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rod Green</name>
      <address>College of Science, Health &amp; Engineering
La Trobe University
PO Box 199
Bendigo
VIC 3552</address>
      <phone>+613 5444 7282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rod.green@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rod Green</name>
      <address>College of Science, Health &amp; Engineering
La Trobe University
PO Box 199
Bendigo
VIC 3552</address>
      <phone>+613 5444 7282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rod.green@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rod Green</name>
      <address>College of Science, Health &amp; Engineering
La Trobe University
PO Box 199
Bendigo
VIC 3552</address>
      <phone>+613 5444 7282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rod.green@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rod Green</name>
      <address>College of Science, Health &amp; Engineering
PO Box 199
Bendigo
VIC 3552</address>
      <phone>+613 5444 7282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rod.green@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>