<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371084">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000999437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Playing Actively Together (pit-a-PAT) Study: Pilot testing an innovative program for parents to increase young childrens active play and reduce screen time for a healthy start to life</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Playing Actively Together (pit-a-PAT) Study: Pilot testing an innovative program for parents to increase young childrens active play and reduce screen time for a healthy start to life</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>pit-a-PAT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The pit-a-PAT intervention is remotely-delivered to parents over six weeks via twice weekly mobile phone text messages and online content. The text messages provide short motivational or informational messages as well as links to content on the website. Website content includes downloadable videos, infographics, and written material proving information to assist parents with strategies to increase active play and reduce screentime in their young children (1-3 years of age). There is no requirement for parents to go to the website or spend a set amount of time on it, this is at their own discretion. Examples of modules covered: physical activity and sedentary behaviour guidelines for young children; ideas for active play; strategies for getting children off screens and engaging in active play.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group is a wait-list control; they received the full program after the follow up measures are taken (i.e., 6 weeks after their baseline assessments).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time child spends in physical activity (total activity including light-, moderate-, and vigorous-intensity) assessed by accelerometers worn for one week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (T1), post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (12 weeks after baseline).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent proxy-reported time child spends watching television and using other screens (screen-time). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (T1), post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (12 weeks after baseline).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility: recruitment and retention - recruitment numbers will be recorded and retention calculated by the number of participants still enrolled in the program post-intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity parenting practices - assessed using a parent-report questionnaire developed by the research group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (T1), post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (12 weeks after baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental efficacy for influencing their child's physical activity and sedentary behaviours - assessed using a parent-report questionnaire developed by the research group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (T1), post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (12 weeks after baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental knowledge of recommended levels of physical activity and sedentary behaviour and benefits of these behaviours for young children - assessed using a parent-report questionnaire developed by the research group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (T1), post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (12 weeks after baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental modelling: parents own physical activity and sedentary behaviour levels - assessed using the Active Australia Survey and previously validated questions on adult screen time (Salmon J, Owen N, Crawford D, Bauman A, Sallis JF. Physical activity and
sedentary behavior: a population-based study of barriers, enjoyment,
and preference. Health Psychol 2003;22:178-88).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (T1), post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (12 weeks after baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Program evaluation - assessed by the following: (1) open ended questions asking parents to report on what they liked and didn't like about the program overall and what (if anything) it made them do differently with their child; (2) 5-point likert scale responses on the usefulness and relevance of different aspects of the program; (3) number of text messages of different types (e.g. with links to videos, infographics, website) they read and number of each that gave them ideas that they used with their child.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents were eligible to participate if their child was aged between 1 and 3 years and had commenced walking. Parents were also required to be fluent in English. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Child not yet walking or outside the 1-3 year age range at commencement of the program. Parent not fluent in English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A researcher not involved in recruitment or delivery of the intervention held the randomisation schedule and was contacted to provide the allocation once a participant consented and was deemed eligible.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using online computer software was used</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Linear regression with bootstrapping for continuous outcomes and logistic regression for binary outcomes. Analyses on intention to treat basis. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>9/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>113</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>21/11/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition, Deakin University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood VIC 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition, Deakin University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood VIC 3125</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot intervention was tested in a randomised controlled trial involving approximately 100 families. It involves an innovative intervention remotely-delivered to parents (via mobile phone text messaging and online) which aims to increase physical activity (active play) and reduce screentime in their young children (1-3 years of age). A wait-list control design was implemented where control families received the intervention following a wait-list period. This design involved data collection at 3 time points, baseline (0 weeks), post intervention (6 weeks) and follow up/post wait list control receiving intervention (12 weeks). Children's physical activity and time spent in screen-based behaviors was measured via parent proxy reported surveys and also measured objectively using accelerometers at the 3 time points throughout the study. Measures of parental physical activity-related parenting practices, confidence, knowledge and modelling (parents' own physical activity and screen viewing) were also collected by self report. Being a pilot-trial, measures of feasibility and acceptability including retention and parent evaluation of the study components were also collected.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood VIC 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>147_2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kylie Hesketh</name>
      <address>Deakin University
Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood 3125
VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 924 46812</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.hesketh@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kylie Hesketh</name>
      <address>Deakin University
Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition 
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood 3125
VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 924 46812</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.hesketh@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kylie Hesketh</name>
      <address>Deakin University
Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition
221 Burwood Highway,
Burwood 3125
VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 924 46812</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.hesketh@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>