<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335108">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000112066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>High- versus low-energy density preloads in overweight/obese men: acute effects on gastric emptying, gut hormone release and energy expenditure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>High- versus low-energy density preloads in overweight/obese men: acute effects on gastric emptying, gut hormone release and thermogenesis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>To determine the acute effect of manipulating the energy density of a meal by increasing its fat content, on subsequent energy intake at lunch, in obese men.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>To determine whether the effect of energy density is related to changes in mediators of energy intake including gastric emptying, gut hormone release, postprandial thermogenesis and appetite sensations.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Experimental design - The study will utilise a single-blind, randomized cross-over design and measure gastric emptying, gut hormone release, diet-induced thermogenesis, appetite perceptions, and subsequent energy intake in response to three oral preloads: 1. High energy density (HED) 2. Low energy density, high fat (LedHF); and, 3. Low energy density, high protein (LedHP).  Details of the preloads are described below. 

Preloads - The energy densities and macronutrient compositions of the 3 semi-solid test preloads are: 1. High energy density (HED; 1.48 kcal/g; 999 kcal; g fat/protein is 62/30); 2. Low energy density, high fat (LedHF; 1.15 kcal/g; 777 kcal; g fat/protein is 37/29); and, 3. Low energy density, high protein (LedHP; 1.15 kcal/g; 777 kcal; g fat/protein is 22/63). All preloads will be matched for grams of carbohydrate, volume (673 g), palatability, smell, texture and look.  The total energy of all preloads will represent between ~30% of estimated daily energy requirement for overweight men. All preloads will comprise of varying quantities of milk, natural yoghurt, frozen raspberries, cream, water, sugar, cornflour and gelatine. Each will also contain 5 ml of egg yolk that is labeled with 75 kBq of Octanoic acid sodium salt [1  14C] for the assessment of gastric emptying rate. In addition, whey protein isolate and cream will be used to manipulate the protein and fat contents of the preloads. 

Experimental protocol - On 3 occasions, each separated by 3-7 days, subjects will have their fasting and postprandial energy expenditure, appetite profile, gastric emptying, gut hormone release and subsequent energy intake measured. Fasting energy expenditure will be determined by indirect calorimetry using a clear plastic ventilated hood and the TrueOne metabolic monitor while subjects lay in the supine position at rest (no fidgeting or talking allowed) for 40 minutes from 0800h. The amount of oxygen consumed and carbondioxide (CO2) produced in the breath is used to measure the amount of energy expended. Afterwards, a cannula will be inserted into a forearm vein to collect blood. In addition, a baseline sample of their breath will be collected for the assessment of gastric emptying rate; for this, subjects will be asked to blow through a straw which is connected to a glass scintillation vial that contains 0.5 mmol of a proprietary CO2 trapping agent. The 14C-Octanoic acid breath test is a validated, indirect marker for the rate of liquid and semisolid gastric emptying. The quantity of breath 14C02 (disintegrations per min, DPM) will be measured using Liquid Scintillation Counting. The activity of 14CO2 in the breath and expressed as a percentage of the original dose ingested in the preload, at the respective time points, will be plotted against time and non-linear regression modelling of the data will be used to determine the lag time (defined as the time before any radioactivity is excreted via the breath), 50% emptying time, the amount of meal retained at 180 mins and gastric emptying coefficient. Subjects will then consume, in random order, one of the three semi-solid experimental preloads.  10 minutes will be allowed to finish the preload. Subjects will then return to the bed and rest quietly under the ventilated hood for a further 3 hrs to measure postprandial energy expenditure for the determination of diet-induced thermogenesis. Blood will be drawn for the samples for the determination of plasma concentrations of glucose, insulin, gut hormones (ghrelin, glucagon like peptide-1 (GLP-1), peptide YY (PPY), cholecystokinin (CCK). At the same time points appetite ratings (fullness, hunger, desire to eat and amount of food that could be eaten) will be recorded using validated 100-mm visual analogue scales. Breath samples to assess gastric emptying will also be collected. At the end of the 3 hours, a cold buffet-style meal will be offered to subjects and they will be asked to eat until comfortably full over a 30 min period.</interventions>
    <comparator>HED</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastric emptying using the 14C-Octanoic breath test. The 14C-Octanoic acid breath test is a validated, indirect marker for the rate of liquid and semisolid gastric emptying. The quantity of breath 14C02 (disintegrations per min, DPM) will be measured using Liquid Scintillation Counting</outcome>
      <timepoint>At -15 min and at 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105, 120, 165, 180 and 210 min after consumption of preload'.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma glucose, insulin and gut hormones (ghrelin, GLP-1, CCK, PPY). Blood samples were drawn from subjects every 15 minutes until t=60, and then every 30 min from t = 60 - 180 min and then once more at t=210 min after the buffet lunch. Radioimmunoassays were used to determine the concentration of these hormones in plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At -15 min and at 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 210 min after consumption of preload'.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting energy expenditure and diet-induced thermogenesis - energy expenditure will be determined by indirect calorimetry using a clear plastic ventilated hood and the TrueOne metabolic monitor while subjects lay in the supine position</outcome>
      <timepoint>At -15 min and every 15mins between t =0 - 180 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite ratings including hunger, fullness, thirst, desire to eat, and amount of food desired to eat using Visual Analogue Scales questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>At -15 min and at 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 180 and 210 min after consumption of preload</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Energy intake - subject were offered a cold buffet-style meal (t = 180 - 210 min). The meal will be weighted before and after consumption to for the assessment of energy intake using Foodwork</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between t = 180 - 210 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects will all be males between age 18 -55 years, with a body mass index (BMI) of 27 -35 kg/m2. Subjects will be required to consume less than 20g of alcohol per week, be non-smokers, free of gastrointestinal or chronic disease and not currently taking medication.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Each subject will be questioned prior to the study to exclude:
-significant gastrointestinal symptoms, disease or surgery 
-use of prescribed or non-prescribed medications which may affect energy metabolism, gastrointestinal function, body weight or appetite 
-lactose intolerant/ other food allergy(s) 
-current gallbladder or pancreatic disease
-diabetes mellitus 
-epilepsy
-cardiovascular or respiratory diseases
-any other illnesses as assessed by the investigator (including chronic illnesses not explicitly listed above)
-high performance athletes
-current intake of &gt; 2 standard drinks on &gt; 5 days per week
-current smokers of cigarettes/cigars/marijuana
-current intake of any illicit substance
-restrained eaters (score &gt; 12 on the three factor eating questionnaire)
-experience claustrophobia in confined spaces
-prior exposure to a dose of radiation in the past 12 months
-unable to comprehend study protocol</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects were recruited via newspaper advertisement or flyers which were posted in the local paper (Adelaide Advertiser), displayed within the University of Adelaide and the Royal Adelaide Hospital. Concealment allocation was not used in this study.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Christine Feinle-Bisset</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Discipline of Medicine Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>A/Prof Christine Feinle-Bisset</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Discipline of Medicine Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Natalie Luscombe-March</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Discipline of Medicine Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aims are to determine:
i)	the acute effect of manipulating the energy density of a meal by increasing its fat content, on subsequent energy intake at lunch, in obese men.
ii)	whether the effect of energy density is related to changes in mediators of energy intake including gastric emptying, gut hormone release, postprandial thermogenesis and appetite sensations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>080317</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/05/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Radhika Seimon</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5039</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>radhika.seimon@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Radhika Seimon</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5039</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>radhika.seimon@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Radhika Seimon</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5039</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>radhika.seimon@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>