<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366560">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000806561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The pre-diabetes intervention package in (PIPI) primary care study: Can a practice nurse-led structured dietary approach prevent progression to diabetes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Determining the effect of a structured practice nurse delivered dietary advice programme compared with usual delivery of dietary advice on weight and HbA1c in people with prediabetes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PIPI - Primary care</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prediabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Nurse Training Programme
Practice nurses at the four intervention practices and community education nurses will undertake a 6-hour training course, which will include nutrition principles, dietary assessment, goal setting, the context within which nutrition advice is given and how to measure height, weight and waist circumference. The course will be both theoretical and practical. The dietary content of the course will be based on the 2004 Diabetes and Nutrition Study Group of the European Association for the Study of Diabetes (EASD) evidence based guidelines for nutritional approaches to the treatment and prevention of diabetes mellitus. Dietary assessment and interpretation in the primary care setting, internal and external factors affecting food choices, culture, behaviour change and effective communication of dietary information will be included in the course. The course will be delivered by study investigators (public health physican, research dietitian, and research nurse/teacher) with input from a local dietitian (DS). A training manual will provide reference material, as well as research protocols. 
A 3-hour update course will be run at 6 months. This will be case study based, using a selection of cases seen by the intervention practice nurses to illustrate particular challenges encountered when providing study participant dietary consultations. 
A local dietitian will be readily available by email and phone to answer any questions from the practice nurses or discuss specific cases. The dietitian will also arrange monthly practice case review meetings with the practice nurses.   
Participant Dietary Advice Programme
Participants will be asked to complete a brief dietary assessment, Starting the Conversation, a validated eight-item simplified food frequency instrument designed for use in primary care and health-promotion settings. Starting The Conversation (STC) was minimally modified, with permision, for the New Zealand context. The practice nurse will review the responses to the Starting the Conversation (STC) dietary assessment and ask additional dietary prompt questions to gain a better understanding of the participants dietary habits. The nurse will also enquire about additional contextual information such as the household membership and budget, who purchases the household foods and specific dietary requirements or choices such as vegetarianism, and take anthropometric measures (height, weight and waist circumference). A weight goal with the aim of a 5% weight loss over 6 months will be determined. The responses to the STC diet assessment, and the additional dietary and lifestyle questions will be used to inform three dietary goals negotiated with the participant, and the provision of individualised dietary advice tailored to their situation. This baseline appointment will take 30-45 minutes (including the study consent process). Fifteen minute follow-up sessions will be arranged 3 weeks later, then at 3 months and 6 months.
Patient management system key messages 
The three individually tailored dietary goals determined between the practice nurse and participant will be incorporated into the general practice patient management systems. These messages will facilitate opportunistic targeted advice and guidance by GPs, thus reinforcing information provided at practice nurse dietary consultations. The goals/messges will be reviewed and updated accordingly at follow up practice nurse appointments.
  </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will continue to receive prediabetes dietary advice as currently delivered ('standard care'). Standard care can include dietary advice given by practice nurses according to their current knowledge and supplemented by dietary advice pamphlets. A referral may be sent to a dietitian for specialised dietary advice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight measured in light clothing using calibrated digital scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) measured from a blood sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference measured with no clothing using a Lufkin Executive thinline (2m) tape measure </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index (BMI) calculated from weight (measured in light clothing using calibrated digital scales) and height (measured with no shoes using a calibrated stadiometer). 
BMI = weight in kilograms divided by (height in metres squared).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure measured using a calibrated automated sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipids (total cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, triglycerides) measured from a blood sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Prediabetes (defined as HbA1c in the following range 41-49mmol/mol, or fasting plasma glucose in the following range 6.1-6.9mmol/L) diagnosed during the last 9 months
* Aged less than 70 years
* Body Mass Index greater than 25 kg/m2
* Able to communicate in English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Taking Metformin
* Pregnant
* Terminal illness
* Unwilling to try to implement dietary advice provided by   practice nurses</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participating Practices
In the study region there are two similar size provincial towns. For pragmatic reasons, practices in one provincial town will be the intervention practices and those in the other town will be the control practices. Four practices in each town will be invited to participate in the study. Participating intervention practices will be similar to the control practices. All will  have employed practice nurses, and will include practices with a high proportion of enrolled patients have a high New Zealand deprivation index score. 

Existing Eligible Participants
At study start all patients with prediabetes registered at participating general practices will be identified by running a patient management system computer query to find all those diagnosed with prediabetes within the last 3 months. A study information sheet and invitation letter will be sent to those patients who meet the study eligibility criteria. Within 5-7 days of the study information sheet and invitation letter being sent, a study practice nurse will call the patient to a first study appointment for those who agree to participate.

New Eligible Participants
After study start, any people newly diagnosed with prediabetes who fulfil all the eligibility criteria at participating practices will be invited to participate in the study.
All participating patients registered at the four control practices will be control participants, and all participating patients registered at the four intervention practices will be intervention participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>This is a non-randomised trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size
A standard deviation of 18kg for weight and a correlation between baseline and follow-up of 0.95 were obtained using data from the 2008/09 New Zealand Adult Nutrition Survey and 2005 data from the Otago Diabetes Register. To detect a difference of 4kg in weight at 6 months with 90% power using the 5% level of significance requires 84 people in each group allowing for a 20% drop out.

Statistical Analysis Plan
Mixed models, with a random effect for practice will be used to analyse the data. The model will include a term for treatment and the baseline measure. It may also include additional variables to adjust for imbalance in the baseline characteristics. Chained equations using an appropriate model will be used to impute the missing data. This will be followed by a sensitivity anlaysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>168</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>156</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>26/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hawke's Bay</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kirsten Coppell</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Edgar Diabetes and Obesity Research
Dunedin School of Medicine 
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is an urgent need to implement effective prediabetes management strategies to reduce the increasing health and economic costs of New Zealands growing diabetes epidemic. Good clinical trial evidence has demonstrated that lifestyle advice prevents progression from prediabetes to diabetes. Evidence showing how similar results can be achieved in real world settings is limited. Our non-randomised study aims to compare the effect of a multilevel primary care based prediabetes lifestyle intervention with current practice on weight and HbA1c in patients with prediabetes at 6 months, and to undertake a process evaluation. A collaborative prediabetes management package including practice nurse education and patient management system messages will be implemented in four general practices in a provincial town. Outcome measures will be compared with four usual care (control) practices in another provincial town. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1.	Coppell KJ, Freer T, Sharp K, Norton J, Spedding T, Engelbrecht R, Stride D, Gurdit-Singh, Hill J, Abel S, Ward L, Gray A, Whitehead L. Baseline characteristics of a high risk prediabetes population in New Zealand  the prediabetes intervention package in (PIPI) primary care study. Accepted Oral presentation, NZ Society of the Study of Diabetes Annual Scientific Meeting, Rotorua (May 2016). p45  
2.	Abel S, Whitehead L, Coppell KJ. Process Evaluation of the prediabetes intervention n primary care (PIPI) study. Accepted Oral presentation, NZ Society of the Study of Diabetes Annual Scientific Meeting, Rotorua (May 2016). p46
3.	Abel S, Whitehead L, Coppell KJ. Factors influencing dietary improvement behavior amongst patients with prediabetes. Accepted Oral presentation, NZ Society of the Study of Diabetes Annual Scientific Meeting, Rotorua (May 2016). p81
4.	Whitehead L, Crowe M, Coppell, K. Developing and evaluating complex interventions: enhancing the role of qualitative research. Accepted Oral presentation, 15th Annual Qualitative Methods (QM) Conference, Glasgow (May 2016)
5.	Coppell KJ, Freer T, Sharp K, Norton J, Spedding T, Engelbrecht R, Stride D, Gurdit-Singh, Hill J, Abel S, Ward L, Gray A, Whitehead L. Characteristics of a high risk prediabetes population in New Zealand  the prediabetes intervention package in primary care study. Poster presentation, 14th Symposium of the International Diabetes Epidemiology Group, Vancouver (December 2015). 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health &amp; Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health 
c/-Medsafe, level 6 Deloitte House
10 Brandon St
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTA/114</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kirsten Coppell</name>
      <address>Edgar Diabetes and Obesity Research
Dunedin School of Medicine 
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
</address>
      <phone>+64 3 470 9074</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kirsten.coppell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Trish Freer</name>
      <address>Health Hawke's Bay Ltd
PO Box 11141
Hastings 4158

</address>
      <phone>+64 6 871 5655</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Trish@healthhb.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kirsten Coppell</name>
      <address>Edgar Diabetes and Obesity Research
Dunedin School of Medicine 
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 470 9074</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kirsten.coppell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Joanna Norton</name>
      <address>Edgar Diabetes and Obesity Research
Dunedin School of Medicine 
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4740999 ext 8035</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joanna.norton@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>