<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82088">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/06/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000344493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of intensive individualised behavioural support and traditional medical treatment for the behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia (BPSD).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In aged care residents with dementia does intensive individualised behavioural support produce better outcomes than traditional medical treatment alone for the management of BPSD?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia (BPSD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group 1 participants will receive the study intervention:- intensive individualised behavioural support.  This will comprise a behavioural assessment and development of a behavioural plan, which will include interventions from at least some of the following categories: (a) Reactive strategies - strategies which provide situational management, (b) Proactive strategies - strategies such as environmental change, teaching new skills to participants or their carers, making adjustments to behavioural triggers and/or reinforcers.  Participants in Group 1 will concurrently receive psychiatric assessment and treatment, as recommended by a Consultant Psychiatrist.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2 participants will receive the control condition, which is traditional medical treatment.  This will comprise psychiatric assessment and treatment, as recommended by a Consultant Psychiatrist.  Case management will be provided by a Registered Psychiatric Nurse (RPN).  
Outcome measures for both groups will be carried out between 8 and 10 weeks post baseline, at which time interventions are typically completed and clients are generally ready for discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in the severity and frequency of BPSD and carer stress.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 8-10 weeks post baseline and at 6 months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in participant well-being. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 8-10 weeks post baseline and at 6 months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced use of medical services (GP visits, admissions to ED or psychiatric inpatient units).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The number of GP visits and admissions will be recorded for the 2 months prior to each measurement point (baseline, 8-10 weeks post baseline and 6 months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced use of psychotropic medication and medication side-effects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Current psychotropic medications will be listed at each measurement point.  Side-effects will be assessed from a file review for the 2 week period prior to each measurement point.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Participants will all have dementia, with a score of less than 24 on the Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE). 2.Participants will all present with at least one of the behavioural symptoms itemised on the Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory (CMAI)3. Participants will all have informed consent to participate granted by their next of kin4. Participants will all reside in an aged care residential facility (high or low care)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. MMSE score of 24 or above2. No behavioural symptoms itemised on the CMAI3. Informed consent not granted by next of kin4. Participant does not reside in an aged care residential facility</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>One of the registered psychiatric nurses within BST has a dedicated role to assess each referral to the team for inclusion/exclusion criteria regarding the study.  Once the participant is deemed eligible, an internally generated ID number is forwarded to an off-site researcher who then randomly allocates them to one of the treatment conditions based on coin tossing.</concealment>
    <sequence>Coin tossing</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kuruvilla George, Consultant Psychiatrist and Director, Eastern Health's Aged Persons Mental Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Eastern Health's Aged Persons Mental Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project aims to investigate the most effective and efficient ways of providing treatment to patients with dementia and BPSD.  The research team has previously carried out a preliminary pilot project, which suggested that intensive individualised behavioural interventions had beneficial effects in terms of reducing problem behaviours.  However, there was no control or comparison groups, making it difficult to associate the reduction of behavioural problems with the psychosocial interventions, with any certainty.
The research team propose to contribute to research in this area by carrying out a group comparison study, comparing intensive indivdualised behavioural interventions with traditional medical treatment.  Participants will all be patients referred to Eastern Health's Behaviour Support Team (BST) from aged care facilities with dementia and BPSD, where consent for participation has been given by next of kin.  Information regarding the participants' behaviours, cognition, mental state, use of medications and medical services will be collected via observation, interview and questionnaires, involving both participants and their carers.  Carers will also complete questionnaires regarding their perceptions of caring for participants.  This information will be collected at baseline, post intervention and at 6-month follow-up.  This information will serve as outcome data.
The two treatment conditions have been described earlier in this application.  At the present time, there is no RCT evidence to support the efficacy of intensive behavioural programmes with this population, for these behavioural issues.  It is anticipated that evidence regarding efficacy provided by this research would then be used to support proposals to increase resources to provide these interventions more widely.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health's Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Catherine Hudgson</name>
      <address>Peter James Centre
Suite 2
1st Floor
46 New Street
Ringwood VIC 3134</address>
      <phone>+61 3 98811101</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 98794055</fax>
      <email>catherine.hudgson@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Catherine Hudgson</name>
      <address>Peter James Centre
Suite 2
1st Floor
46 New Street
Ringwood VIC 3134</address>
      <phone>+61 3 98811101</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 98794055</fax>
      <email>catherine.hudgson@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>