<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="123">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/08/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000137695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Multicentre Randomised Controlled Trial Comparing Two Strategies for the Diagnosis of Invasive Aspergillosis in High-Risk Haematology Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicentre Randomised Controlled Trial Comparing Two Strategies for the Diagnosis of Invasive Aspergillosis in High-Risk Haematology Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ASPID</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group (ALLG): ALLG SC01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Invasive Aspergillosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study design: A multicentre, randomised parallel-group trial which compares 2 strategies for the diagnosis of Invasive Aspergillosis (IA) in patients undergoing allogeneic haematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) and in patients undergoing intensive combination chemotherapy for acute leukaemia. Eligible patients will be stratified by centre and randomised 1:1 to the either the current standard diagnostic strategy (comparator or control arm) or the new diagnostic strategy (intervention arm) for IA.  The study will not be blinded to enrolled patients or participating clinicians. However the assessment of the endpoints/outcomes will be by the Outcome Committee who will be blinded to the patients randomisation status.Experimental Protocol:Comparator arm: The current standard diagnostic work-up for IA will be implemented in patients with persistent or recurrent neutropenic fevers despite broad-spectrum antibiotics. The diagnostic components of this arm include serial blood cultures and serial urine, faeces, sputum and mouth swill samples for fungal culture; chest x-ray, high resolution computerised tomographic (HRCT) scan of thorax; bronchoscopy and culture of bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) fluid; biopsy for histological examination etc. The results of the tests will determine the type of antifungal therapy given namely, empiric antifungal therapy or fungal therapy for proven or probable IA as per the predefined treatment protocol.New diagnostic strategy (index arm): Screening will be performed with Aspergillus galactomannan enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (GM-ELISA) and an Aspergillus nested polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay twice weekly for inpatients and weekly for outpatients. The results of the tests will determine if antifungal therapy is administered as per the same predefined treatment protocol, the timing of HRCT scan and what other procedures (e.g. bronchoscopy and culture of bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) fluid etc.) are performed to further investigate persistent or recurrent neutropenic fevers. Duration on study:Each patient will be followed using the trial protocol for 26 weeks or until death, if earlier  Sample size calculation and duration of study: 300 patients per arm are required to detect a 12% absolute reduction (i.e. from 40% to 28%) in the proportion of patients treated with empiric antifungal therapy. An interim analysis is planned. The expected accrual rate is 240 patients per year, thus the expected duration of the trial including follow-up will be 3 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Current standard diagnostic strategy (comparator or control arm)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients treated with at least 1 course of empiric antifungal therapy as per protocol definition</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 26 weeks following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>IA-related mortality rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other invasive fungal infection-related (IFI) mortality rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>all-cause mortality rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean number of hospital admissions</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median hospital length of stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total duration of antifungal therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nephrotoxicity rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hepatotoxicity rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median number of courses of empiric antifungal therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median number of invasive procedures performed to diagnose IA and cost data associated with treatment and complications.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All secondary outcomes will be measured at 26 weeks post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Undergoing allogeneic haematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) for any reason OR Undergoing intensive combination chemotherapy for acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) or acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (ALL). 2.Has given written informed consent. Non-English speaking patients are eligible once written informed consent is obtained via the appropriate interpreter. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Other immunocompromised states (e.g. HIV infection, solid organ transplantation, autoimmune conditions treated with immunosuppressants etc.) besides those outlined in the inclusion criteria above. 2.Currently enrolled in an antifungal treatment trial (not an antifungal prophylaxis trial). 3.Past history of proven or probable IA (as per standardized definitions) during a previous cycle of chemotherapy. 4.Currently have active IA or other active invasive fungal infection. 5.Prior enrolment in this study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Computer generated allocation in Trial Centre, arm revealed only after patient registration</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/08/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/09/2005</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/05/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>240</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/12/2009</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data analysis is complete</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities,Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>-</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC project grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>-</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>O. Morrissey, S. Chen, M. Slavin for the Australia and New Zealand Mycology Interest Group and Australasian Leukaemia Lymphoma Group. Randomized Controlled Trial of Two Diagnostic Strategies for Invasive Aspergillosis (IA) in High-Risk Hematology Patients. 51th ICAAC Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy,  Chicago, IL,  September 17-20, 2011

Morrissey CO, Chen SC, Sorrell TC, Bradstock KF, Szer J, Halliday CL, Gilroy NM, Schwarer AP, Slavin MA. Design issues in a randomized controlled trial of a pre-emptive versus empiric antifungal strategy for invasive aspergillosis in patients with high-risk hematologic malignancies. Leukemia &amp; Lymphoma. 2011;52(2):179-193

Morrissey CO, Chen SC, Sorrell TC, Milliken S, Bardy PG, Bradstock KF, Szer J, Halliday CL, Gilroy NM, Moore J, Schwarer AP, Guy S, Bajel A, Tramontana AR, Spelman T, Slavin MA, Australasian Leukaemia Lymphoma G, the A, New Zealand Mycology Interest G. Galactomannan and PCR versus culture and histology for directing use of antifungal treatment for invasive aspergillosis in high-risk haematology patients: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet Infect Dis. 2013;13(6):519-528

Macesic, N., Morrissey, C.O. , Liew, D, Gilroy, N, Chen, S.C-A, Slavin, M. Cost-effective analysis of a biomarker-based versus the standard culture and histology-based diagnostic strategy for invasive aspergillosis (IA) in high-risk hematology patients. 19th Congress of the International Society for Human and Animal Mycology (ISHAM), Melbourne, May 2015. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Melbourne Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/08/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>MelbournePeter MacCallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Westmead Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Monica Slavin</name>
      <address>Infectious Diseases Unit
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St. Andrew's Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96561526</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Monica.Slavin@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Orla Morrissey</name>
      <address>Infectious Diseases Unit
Alfred Hospital
Level 2 Burnet Institute
Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92762000 (Pager 4260)</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92766557</fax>
      <email>email o.morrissey@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>