<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335738">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000598088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tolerability study of Maxigesic in patients with Mild to Severe Pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Maxi-Analgesic Tolerability Study: 
Open-Label, Phase IV, Multi-Centre Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of Maxigesic in Patients with Mild to Severe 
Pain.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AFT-MX-5

AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Interventions:
The combination of paracetamol and ibuprofen (paracetamol 500 mg + ibuprofen 150 mg per tablet)

Treatment Period:
Acute Pain Treatment group:  2 tablets every 6 hours for a minimum of 48 hours to 14 days
Chronic Pain Treatment group: 
Fixed dosing group: 2 tablets every 6 hours between 15 days and 3 months
Flexible dosing group: 1-2 tablets every 4 or 6 hours up to a maximum of 8 tablets per day between 15 days and 3 months</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants received Maxigesic. No comparators will be used in the study. 

Safety data observed in the current study will be compared with previously published safety data of paracetamol alone or ibuprofen alone

The dose response relationship between the number of tablets taken and the pain intensity will be compared in the flexible dosing group with the fixed dosing group.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the safety profile of the combination of paracetamol and ibuprofen with the estabilished safety profile of paracetamol and ibuprofen when administered alone.

The incidence of known Non-steriod Anti-inflammatory Drugs (NSAID) and paracetamol side effects will be specifically evaluated (gastrointestinal side effects such as stomach pain/ulceration and bleeding; and effects on liver such as clinical hepatotoxicity).

All adverse events reported in the patient diary and from the site visit notes recorded by investigators will be collected and assessed at the end of the study. The rate oberseved in the study will be grouped using Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) categories and compared with published data for combination therapies (NSAID + paracetamol) and individual therapies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute pain group: from 48 hours to 14 days following administration of the first study drug. Data will be collected at 21-28 days after the last dose of study drug. 
Chronic pain group: from 15 days to 3 months following administration of the first study drug. Data will be collected at 21-28 days after the last dose of study drug</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The tolerability of the combination of paracetamol and ibuprofen will be evaluated by assessing the number of participants who stop taking the study drug due to side effects. 

Data will be recorded on the patient diary and site visit notes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute pain group: from 48 hours to 14 days following administration of the first dose of study drug. Data will be collected after the last dose of study drug.  
Chronic pain group: from 15 days to 3 months following administration of the first dose of study drug. Data will be collected after the last dose of study drug.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of participants who stop taking study drug due to a lack of efficacy will be counted in the chronic pain treatment group to evaluate the proportion of patients achieving adequate pain relief.

Data will be recorded on the patient diary and site visit notes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Chronic pain group only: from 15 days to 3 months following administration of the first dose of study drug. Data will be collected after the last dose of study drug.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The relationship between the number of tablets taken and the visual analogue scale (VAS) pain intensity score among those with chronic pain allocated to the flexibel dosing group will be evaluated. 

The number of tablets taken and the VAS pain score will be recorded on the patient diary daily. The Pain VAS is to be completed in the participant?s diary immediately prior to a dose of Maxigesic and should be completed at the same time each day. Participants in the Chronic Pain Treatment Group are required to complete the Pain VAS every day until completion of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Chronic pain group only: from 15 days to 3 months  following administration of the first study drug. Data will be collected after the last dose of study drug.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pain level over the duration of the study will be evaluated by daily single measurements of 24 hour pain level using a visual analogue scale (VAS). 

The Pain VAS is to be completed in the participant?s diary immediately prior to a dose of Maxigesic and should be completed at the same time each day. Participants in the Acute Pain Treatment Group complete the Pain VAS every 24 hours after their first dose of Maxigesic until they no longer require treatment. Participants in the Chronic Pain Treatment Group also complete the Pain VAS every day until completion of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute pain group: from 48 hours to 14 days following administration of the first study drug. VAS pain score will be assessed daily on the patient diary and data will be collected after the last dose of study drug. 
Chronic pain group: from 15 days to 3 months following administration of the first study drug. VAS pain score will be assessed daily on the patient diary and data will be collected after the last dose of study drug.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The calculated pharmacokinetic parameters from a subset of patients with acute pain (N=25-30) will be compared with published population pharmacokinetic parameters. 

Approximately three blood samples will be requested from study participants who are using Maxigesic for the relief of post-operative pain (i.e. in the acute pain treatment group). It is intended that the samples are obtained at a range of times across the dosing interval of six hours and the actual times of dosing and blood sample collection will be recorded so that the pharmacokinetic modelling can be conducted. Population estimates of pharmacokinetic parameters (volume of distribution, absorption rate half-time and clearance) obtained using non-linear mixed effects modelling will be compared with published population pharmacokinetic parameters.  It is expected that approximately 25-30 study participants requiring post-operative pain relief will provide blood samples for this analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute pain group only: approximately 3 blood samples will be taken at various time during the dosing intervals of 6 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Provide written informed consent before initiation of any study-related procedures
Be aged at least 18 years and not more than 80 years old on the day of consent
Require treatment of mild to severe pain due to either acute or chronic pain
Acute pain includes: Dental pain including tooth/teeth extraction; Post-operative pain after minor surgery e.g. cutaneous surgery, hernia; Post-operative pain after moderate surgery e.g. orthopaedic surgery, abdominal surgery, episiotomy; Muscle and ligament sprain; Skeletal trauma;Dysmenorrhoea

Chronic pain includes: Osteoarthritis;Rheumatoid arthritis; Low back pain</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Has taken any NSAID or paracetamol within 12 hours prior to study initiation other than aspirin less than or equal to 150mg/day for prevention of cardiovascular disease.
Has taken another analgesic other than paracetamol or an NSAID within 3 days prior to study initiation.
Known to be pregnant or possibly pregnant.
Has been in a clinical trial involving another study drug in last 30 days prior to baseline. 
Currently treated with an angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor, warfarin, steroid (other than dexamethasone intra-operatively), cyclosporin, tacrolimus or methotrexate.
Patient weight &lt; 50kg at baseline.
Is suffering from any other disease or condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, means that it would not be in the patients best interest to participate in this study.
Has any of the following NSAID and/or paracetamol contra-indications:
Hypersensitivity to aspirin or other NSAID
Hypersensitivity to paracetamol
Severe known haemopoetic, renal or hepatic disease, immunosuppressant
History of gastric ulceration, indigestion, stomach pain or bleeding
Currently suffering from dehydration through diarrhoea and/or vomiting
History of severe asthma defined as previous steroid treatment or hospital admission</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be allocated to acute pain treatment group or chronic pain treatment group depending on their disease conditions whether acute pain or chronic pain treatment is required. Investigators will decide whether a patient shall be allocated to an acute pain treatment group or a chronic pain treatment group. Participants' study number for acute pain treatment group and chronic pain treatment group will be generated separately. 


In the chronic pain treatment group, participants will be randomized into either fixed dosing group (2 tablets every 6 hours) or flexible dosing group (1-2 tablets every 4-6 hours up to a maximum of 8 tablets per day). A set of sealed opaque envelopes will be used for the randomization allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>For the chronic pain treatment group, the randomization code will be generated by an independent statistician through computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Not applicable</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>The study was withdrawn due to administrative reason </withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street, Takapuna, Auckland, 0622</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street, Takapuna, Auckland, 0622</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Both paracetamol and ibuprofen are relatively safe when administered at over the counter (OTC) dose and their safety profile has been well-estabilished for many years. 

A combination of paracetamol and ibuprofen has been proved to be more effective than each individual component in a phase 3 clinical trial in an acute pain model (ACTRN:12606000291583). However, the safety observation in the same trial is only for 48 hours. In many clinical circumstances, the pain relief period is required to be up to 14 days such as post-operative pain relief for some moderate surgery. 

At the same time, it is proposed to observe the safety profile for long term use (up to 3 months) in patients with chronic pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3rd Floor, Unisys Building, 650 Great South Road, Penrose, Auckland, 1061</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Zhang</name>
      <address>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street, Takapuna, Auckland, 0622</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hartley Atkinson</name>
      <address>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street, Takapuna, Auckland, 0622</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hartley@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennifer Zhang</name>
      <address>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street, Takapuna, Auckland, 0622</address>
      <phone>+64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hartley Atkinson </name>
      <address>Level 1, 129 Hurstmere Road, Takapuna, Auckland </address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 488 0232 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hartley@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>