<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364540">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000742774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study to test recruitment methods, feasibility and study
procedures for a planned randomised controlled trial of the
MindBabyBody program: an antenatal mindfulness intervention to reduce depression, stress and anxiety</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to test recruitment methods, feasibility and study
procedures for a planned randomised controlled trial of the
MindBabyBody program: an antenatal mindfulness intervention to reduce depression, stress and anxiety</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MBB</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Perinatal depression, anxiety, and stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The MindBabyBody program comprises a 6-session mindfulness-based group therapy program based on Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy (MBCT) and developed by Dr Krisinte Mercuri specifically for use in pregnancy. Participants are introduced to the mindfulness approach, and mindfulness strategies including formal and informal meditation practices and mindful movement.
This program is currently being offered at The Royal Women's Hospital as part of their clinical services, specifically targeting women with current or previous mental health concerns. The intervention in the pilot
study will be promoted to all women attending the antenatal clinic as a program which is aimed at managing stress and mood during pregnancy and the postnatal period.

Each session runs for approximately 2 hours, and occurs weekly for six weeks. Each session involves a period of formal meditation, a discussion of the participant experiences of mindfulness practice, a weekly topic for discussion (focused on features of mindfulness relevant to pregnancy and motherhood) and some simple mindful yoga stretches. Each week suggestions are given for home practice with repetition emphasised as a significant reinforcer of new skills.
In the post-program questionnaire, participants who have completed the MindBabyBody program will be asked questions about the level of formal and informal practice they have completed throughout the program. Attendance records will also be kept. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants allocated to the control group will receive care as usual through the Royal Women's Hospital. The main aim of the pilot study is to test different recruitment strategies, including the universal recruitment of women into a randomised controlled trial. The use of a  non-treatment control group is important in determining the acceptability of recruitment to a randomised controlled trial for potential participants.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recruitment method.
As a pilot study, we are focused on assessing feasibility issues. Each participant enrolled in the study will be asked the two following questions:
1) How did you first hear about the study, and 
2) When did you decide to enrol in the MindBabyBody pilot study. 
Response options for these questions are:
- I read the information sheet provided in my booking-in pack
- I received information about the study at the Childbirth Education classes
- I received information about the study at a physiotherapy class 			?
- I was given information about the study by a researcher in the Royal Womens Hospital antenatal booking clinic 
- My midwife recommended the program to me 	

We are using two questions because of the possibility that women maybe exposed to more than one recruitment method. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant characteristics (such as age, current gestation, parity, marital status, education level, employment status).
As a pilot study, we are focused on feasibility issues, and we are interested in participant characteristics according to the method of recruitment. These will be assessed using a questionnaire specifically designed for this pilot study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant retention.
As a pilot study, we are focused on feasibility issues, such as length of study measures, and the ability to retain participants in a non-treatment control group. 
Participant retention will be assessed by the number of questionnaires returned for control and intervention groups. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8-weeks post baseline, and 3 months postpartum. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal depression assessed via the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8-weeks post baseline, and 3 months postpartum. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal anxiety measured via the State-Trait Anxiety Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8-weeks post baseline and at 3 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal stress measured via the Perceived Stress Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8-weeks post baseline, and at 3 months postpartum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal Psychological Distress, measured by the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS). 
We will also compare how the DASS subscales perform compared to the three separate measures assessing depression, anxiety and stress in regards to treatment outcome. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8-weeks post baseline, and at 3 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Greater than 12 weeks gestation
Booked in to give birth at the Royal Womens Hospital 
Aged 18 50 years

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Greater than 32 weeks gestation
Insufficient fluency in English to participate in mindfulness sessions and/or complete written questionnaires in English
Serious current mental morbidity such as severe suicidal ideation.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/06/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Childrens Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Women's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Mindfulness interventions are emerging as a potentially promising intervention to reduce mental health problems in the perinatal period, however there is a need for more robust evidence supporting their efficacy. The current proposal outlines a pilot study with the primary aim of exploring feasibility issues to inform the development of a randomised-controlled trial of a mindfulness-based intervention in pregnancy. We propose to test and evaluate a range of recruitment strategies designed to maximise uptake of a program offered to women booked in to give birth at the Royal Women's Hospital.

We aim to recruit around 45 women to this pilot study. Participants in the project will complete study questionnaires at three time-points: pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at a three months postpartum follow-up. Questionnaires will include standardised measures of depression, anxiety, stress, and mindfulness. The postnatal follow-up questionnaire will include items on maternal postnatal quality of life and child outcomes (cry-fuss-sleep behaviour). Analysis will focus on uptake via different recruitment methods and assess rates of ongoing participation, engagement, and acceptability of study instruments. 

The data collected in this study will be used to inform the development of a large scale randomised controlled trial evaluating a mindfulness-based group intervention in pregnancy for reducing perinatal anxiety and depression. In addition, the pilot study will support and develop collaborative links between staff at The Royal Women's Hospital and researchers in the Healthy Mothers, Healthy Families group at the Murdoch Childrens Research Institute.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hannah Woolhouse</name>
      <address>Healthy Mothers Healthy Families
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
WL5 Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9936 6619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hannah.woolhouse@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hannah Woolhouse</name>
      <address>Healthy Mothers Healthy Families
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
WL5 Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9936 6619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hannah.woolhouse@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hannah Woolhouse</name>
      <address>Healthy Mothers Healthy Families
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
WL5 Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9936 6619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hannah.woolhouse@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hannah Woolhouse</name>
      <address>Healthy Mothers Healthy Families
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
WL5 Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC, 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9936 6619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hannah.woolhouse@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>