<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336548">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000190909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does the rate of weight loss influence the success of long term weight management?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised Clinical Control trial in Obese Adults Investigating Rapid and Gradual Weight Loss on Weight Maintenance.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1145-6429 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>RWLM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase 1:Weight Loss Phase

Arm 1: Rapid Weight Loss Group- subjects will consume a commercially available VLCD preparation (Optifast(R)) for three months. During this phase 3 meals a day (Breakfast, Lunch and Dinner) will be replaced with a nutritionally sound meal replacement in a liquid form called Optifast (R). To administer these liquid meals participants will add the Optifast(R) powdered sachet (40grms) to 200ml of water and shake vigrously in a closed container. The Optifast shakes are approximately 150-200 calories per shake. The Optifast shakes contain all the energy, macro and micro nutrients required to reach recommended daily intakes (RDIs).  Participants will also have biweekly contact with the dietician who will instruct the subjects to follow a VLCD.  During this weight loss phase participants will be required to lose at least 15% of their body weight (approximately 1.50kg/week). 

Arm 2: Gradual Weight Loss Group- subjects will be instructed bi-weekly by a dietician to follow a weight loss program similar to the Australian Guide to Healthy Eating and at least one meal a day will be replaced with a optifast(R) meal for nine months. During this weight loss phase subjects will be required to lose at least 15% of their body weight (approximately 0.5kg/week). 


Phase 2: Weight Maintenance Phase

All participants will be monitored for the following 3 years post phase 1.</interventions>
    <comparator>Rapid Weight Loss Group vs Gradual Weight Loss Group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the weight outcome at three years following rapid or slow weight loss. 
Bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA) will be used to assess this outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following diet phase.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the impact of personality, social functioning and motivation to the maintenance of weight loss at two different rates.
The following questionnaires will be used to assess this outcome: the following validated questionnaires: The Big Five Inventory (to assess personality type); Social Provisions Scale (to assess social supports); The Ways of Coping Checklist (Revised WCCL-R) (to assess coping skills); The Weight Locus of Control Scale (to assess perceived locus of control) and the Three Factor Eating Questionnaire (to assess eating behaviours)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of diet phase and 3 years following diet phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare short and long term physiological adaptations following weight loss at two different rates. In order to assess this outcome blood will be collected pre-intervention, following the diet phase (3 and 9 months) and annually for three years during the weight maintenance phase for the analysis of the following nutrients and hormones: Insulin, glucose, leptin, ghrelin, cholecystokinin (CCK) at both a fasting and post-prandial state.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of diet phase and 3 years following diet phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria
The criteria for inclusion in the trial are:
*Healthy men and women aged 18-70 years with a desire to lose weight
*Weight stable for 3 months 
*BMI &gt;30kg/m2</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Pregnancy or breast feeding
*History of surgical procedures or laxative abuse for weight loss
*The use of any VLCD or weight lowering drugs in the past three months
*Known major weight change in the previous six months (&gt;10% body weight)
*Inability to attend scheduled examinations and visits
*Inability to follow the study instructions, or unlikely to be compliant to the dietary prescription provided
*For females taking an oral contraceptive pill: dose must have been stable for the past three months
*For females using hormone replacement therapy: dose must have been stable for past 3 months
*For participants receiving thyroid preparations or thyroxin treatment: dose must have been stable for the past three months
*Surgical intervention planned during the study
* Any recent (less than six months) cessation of smoking and current smokers
*Participation in another study, or administration of any investigational drug in the past three months
*Uncontrolled and clinically significant disease or known malignancy that could interfere with the study conduct
*Presence of any clinically significant renal or endocrine disease (including diabetes) according the Investigator or as revealed by screening blood tests</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants were recruited using radio, newspaper advertisements and word-of-mouth. A written participant information and consent form was sent to each potential participant and they were encouraged to read and discuss the form with family and their doctors and to ask any questions during their first visit and before signing the consent form. 
Subjects were randomised to the rapid and gradual weight loss groups using a randomised block design with random block sizes that accounts for potential confounding factors such as gender, age and BMI. A research assistant located away from the clinic and not involved with the study held the randomisation list and under the supervision of the study statistician allocated participants to treatment groups. The research assistant kept the randomisation sequence private, only revealing a treatment allocation after receiving information demonstrating that the participant was eligible and had consented to the trial. Investigators (other than the study statistician) did not have access to the randomisation list at any time during the duration of the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/08/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/03/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Austin Health - Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <postcode>3081 - Heidelberg Heights</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1, Boronia Centre, 
Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, 
300 Waterdale Rd, 
Heidelberg Heights, 
Victoria 3081</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Committee</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Austin Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Henry Buck Building 
    Austin Hospital
    145 Studley Road
    Heidelberg
    Victoria
    Australia, 3084</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This was a non-blinded, 2 phase, randomised dietary intervention trial investigating if the rate of weight loss is important in long-term weight maintenance; if physiological adaptations encouraging weight regain are different with different rates of weight loss; if these adaptations reverse with time and if psychological profile can help us choose if slow or rapid weight loss is best suited to a particular psychological profile. 
Participants were obese (BMI 30.0 - 45.0 kg/m2) and aged between 18 and 70 years. Following telephone and onsite screening 200 subjects commenced phase 1 of the trial (weight loss phase) and were randomised by strata to either a rapid or gradual weight loss program. During this phase appointments were at the same interval with similar quality of dietary education materials for all subjects. Projected weight-loss graphs were personalised to each participant and utilised at each visit to compare expected and actual weight-loss achieved at each time point. Both the rapid and gradual weight loss group had prescriptions for the same overall energy deficit (105,000 kcal or 430,500 kJ). The rapid weight loss group were asked to accumulate the deficit over 3 months while the gradual weight loss group had to accumulate the same deficit over 9 months. In both treatment groups, participants were instructed to undertake at least 30 minutes a day of mild to moderate intensity exercise (e.g. brisk walk). Participants attended fortnightly for individual consultations with the same qualified dietitian. During these visits, they had anthropometry measurements taken and were given dietary counselling based on their individual needs in order to remain on their projected curve and achieve their target weight of 15% weight loss.
All participants who successfully achieved 15% weight loss in phase 1 were eligible to enter into phase 2 (weight maintenence phase) of the trial. During phase 2 participants followed a weight maintenance diet which was individualised for each participant and similar to the Australian Guidelines for Healthy Eating(Smith A 1998). Individual sessions were conducted with the study dietitian quarterly for the three years following phase I. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Unit
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Rd 
PO box 5555 Heidelberg 
Victoria 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/08/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2008/03279</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/06/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Joesph Proietto</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine- Austin Health
University of Melbourne,
Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, 
300 Waterdale Rd 
Heidelberg Heights, 
Victoria, 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 2250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.proietto@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Katrina Purcell</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine- Austin Health
University of Melbourne,
Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, 
300 Waterdale Rd 
Heidelberg Heights, 
Victoria, 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 39496 4025</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>purcellk@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>katrina purcell</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine- Austin Health
University of Melbourne,
Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, 
300 Waterdale Rd 
Heidelberg Heights, 
Victoria, 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4025</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>purcellk@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Joseph Proietto</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine- Austin Health
University of Melbourne,
Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, 
300 Waterdale Rd 
Heidelberg Heights, 
Victoria, 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 2250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.proietto@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>