<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347925">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001009808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Healthy Bowels Study - A randomised controlled trial of transcutaneous electrical stimulation to treat constipation caused by anorectal retention in children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Children (aged 4-8 years) with chronic constipation caused by anorectal retention treated with current best treatment (CBT) plus transcutaneous electrical stimulation compared to CBT alone comparing laxative usage after 8 weeks of TES.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-9593</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Healthy Bowels Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Constipation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Randomised Current Best Treatment (CBT) vs. CBT plus transcutaneous electrical stimulation (TES). 
Open treatment, Blinded analysis.

CBT involves 4 x 3hours patient education sessions (12 hours in total) which include basic digestive function, prescriptive diet and maintenance medication. These are given over 4 weeks before the 8 weeks of TES commences.

TES involves patients having daily stimulation using the TES device (4 electrode pads over the abdomen and lower back) for one hour daily for 8 weeks.

For entry patients will be assessed for anorectal retention by A/ History and presence of palpable faecaloma B/ confirmation by radio-nuclear transit study

All subjects receive: 
a disimpaction regime using over the counter stool softener and laxative (similar to bowel washout used before colonoscopy), education on how the bowel works, controlled diet and fluid intake, Maintenance medication: Stool softener and laxative for 14 weeks. Amount of laxative will be increased or decreased to maintain stool at 1 cup per day and medium consistency (measured using Bristol Stool Chart) and Patients will fill in an online diary each day. 

At 4 weeks, patients will be randomised to Group A or B. 

Group A (control group) continue current best treatment. Which involves a combination of detailed education and laxative medication for the duration of  8 weeks.
 
Group B (electrical stimulation group) continue with current best treatment (as mentioned above) plus the use of the Transcutaneous Electrical Stimulation (TES) used daily for 1 hour each day,  for the duration of  8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>All subjects receive
 
a/ a disimpaction regime using over the counter stool softener and laxative (similar to bowel washout used before colonoscopy), 

b/ education on how the bowel works
 
c/ controlled diet and fluid intake

d/ Maintenance medication: Stool softener and laxative for 14 weeks. Amount of laxative will be increased or decreased to maintain stool at 1 cup per day and medium consistency (measured using Bristol Stool Chart).

e/ Patients will fill in an online diary each day. 


All patients continue on maintenance medication for 3 months.

Patients continuing on CBT will be known as Group A (control group).

Patients continuing on CBT + TES will be known as Group B (treatment group)

NB: please refer to the Descriptions of Intervention(s) for further explanation on CBT and TES machine use.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laxative: Medication dosage administered to patient to maintain bowel consistency of type 4 Bristol Stool Chart.
(as per IMPACT Paediatric Bowel Care Pathway - Australia) 2006</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of week 8 of CBT+TES/ CBT</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of patients using laxatives at end of 8 weeks of CBT+TES/ CBT</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of week 8 of CBT+TES/ CBT</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to ceasing laxative use</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily collection of laxative use data for the full term of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients ceasing laxative use</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily collection of laxative use data for the full term of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Defecation episodes/day</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily collection of patient diary data for the full term of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>soiling episodes/day</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily collection of patient diary data for the full term of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - PAC qol, PAC sym questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before starting trial, post disimpaction (pre CBT commencing), Post 8 weeks CBT+TES/ CBT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consistency of stool- as per Bristol Stool Chart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily collection of patient diary data for the full term of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children (4-18yrs) with treatment-resistant Anorectal Retention constipation confirmed by Nuclear Transit Study. Patients with faecaloma will be included.

For entry patients will be assessed for anorectal retention by
a/ History and presence of palpable faecaloma
b/ Confirmation by radio-nuclear transit study (scintigraphy)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>4</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Has a heart pacemaker, neurological defects (including slow transit constipation, epilepsy), cochlear implant or ventricular-peritoneal shunt inserted.
2. Hormonal/metabolic disorder, bowel surgery, cancer or pregnancy.
3. Previous TES therapy.
4. Unable to access the internet each day to login to the computer program for medication dose and to send copies of paper diary Charts.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited at Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne, Australia. Participation in the trial will be offered to patients attending the Gastroenterology, Surgical (Urology), General Medicine, Continence and Encopresis outpatient clinics and patients referred from community GP practice.

A clinical trial announcement flyer will be provided to potential patient candidates with Trial contact details. Once recruited, the Trial co-coordinator will obtain consent.

Prior to performing any study or procedure (including screening procedures to determine eligibility), a signed consent form will be obtained from each participant and or parent/ guardian.  The consent form will describe the purpose of the study, the procedures to be followed, and the risks and benefits of participation. One of the investigators will conduct the informed consent discussion and will check that the participant and/ or their parent/ guardian comprehend the information provided and answer any questions about the study. Consent will be voluntary and free from coercion. 

The investigator that conducted the consent discussion will also sign the informed consent form. A copy of the consent form will be given to the participant and/or their parent/guardian and the fact that the subject has been consented to the study will be documented in the subject’s record. When all the inclusion and/or exclusion criteria have been addressed and the eligibility of the subject confirmed, the subject will be enrolled into the study.  

A record will be maintained of all participants screened but not enrolled due to ineligibility.  Data collected at screening (specifically, eligibility data) will be recorded on these participants.  

Patients will be randomly assigned to receive CBT or CBT+TESIC.  The number participants in each group will be roughly equal with a minimum of 50 completing the protocol in each group.

Treatment A and B wil be randomised. The treatment will be assigned a number and then placed in a numbered envelope and sealed. The envelopes in numerical order will be assigned to each patient after disimpaction.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation was performed by our statistics unit using computer generation. Treatments were randomised in variable block sizes. Allocation was placed into sealed numbered envelopes by the statistics unit. Envelopes were supplied to the trial staff and given to patients in numerical order.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>119</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5
The Royal Children's Hospital 
50 Flemington Road
Parkville, 3052
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will assess if a safe non-invasive transcutantous electrical stimulation can treat chronic constipation from the anorectal retention sub-group (the most common type of chronic constipation). 
Hypothesis
TESIC can increase large bowel motility and defecation to overcome chronic constipation in children with AR, and is more effective than current best treatment (CBT, laxatives, diet, toilet timing and posture, education about brain-gut axis) alone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.healthybowelstrial.org.au (pending - to be activated)</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>32014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Bridget Southwell</name>
      <address>Surgical Research Group, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, 
Level 5 East, The Royal Childrens Hospital,
50 Flemington road,
Parkville.
Victoria
3052</address>
      <phone>61 3 9345 5069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bridget.southwell@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Bridget Southwell</name>
      <address>Surgical Research Group, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, 
Level 5 East, The Royal Childrens Hospital,
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria
3052</address>
      <phone>61 3 9345 5069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bridget.southwell@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Bridget Southwell</name>
      <address>Surgical Research Group, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, 
Level 5 East, The Royal Childrens Hospital,
50 Flemington Road,
Parkville Victoria
3052</address>
      <phone>61 3 9345 5069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bridget.southwell@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bridget Southwell</name>
      <address>Surgical Research Group, Murdoch Childrens Research Institute, Level 5 East, The Royal Childrens Hospital, 50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 5069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bridget.southwell@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>