<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371719">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001499471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A clinical trial  measuring  a new clinical psychology intervention on improving outcomes for people with schizophrenia and distressing voice hallucinations.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single blind randomised controlled clinical trial testing the effectiveness of a  clinical psychology intervention on improving the distress associated with auditory hallucinations in schizophrenia as measured by the Revised Beliefs About Voices Questionnaire.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>VHT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>schizophrenia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Name and description of the investigational product  Clinical Psychology Intervention for Voice Hallucinations (CPV) 

CPV is at least one 45 minute individual face to face session with a Clinical Psychologist on the Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit (SCGH MHU), involving assessment and linking into community therapy with a clinical psychologist, during a 1 day admission on the SCGH MHU. The maximum time of a CPV is 1 hour 3 times week over a 12 month admission. How many sessions each participant attends is a collaborative decision between the participant, the clinical psychologist and the treating team based on the clinical needs of the patient and length of hospital stay. The clinical psychologist draws from the following 4 modules as required for each patient. The duration and number of sessions taken to complete each of the first three modules is based on the individual needs of each participant and in  collaboration with the clinical psychologist . The minimum duration would be 0 minutes during 1 assessment session of 45 minutes. The maximum would be 1 hour of each module per week for 12 months. This would be unusual. The first 3 modules are a description of how the clinical psychologist might spend the time with the patient on top of assessment and supporting the patient to obtain and negotiate a referral to a suitable clinical psychologist in the community. The 4th module is an education group with the Hearing Voices Network that a patient may choose to attend. It is voluntary, available for 1 hour on the SCGH MHU, once a week and run by a peer support worker who has received in-house training from a non government organisation called Richmond Wellbeing.  Their role in this module is  educator. A clinical psychologist does not attend module 4.

Module 1 is called Coping with Voices and includes a discussion of the strengths and weaknesses of strategies already used; review of a strategy handout about  healthy lifestyle techniques, keeping a balanced perspective, understanding your voices, distraction/interfering techniques and calming/soothing techniques; identification of up to 3 strategies willing to be tried after the group. Module 2 is called  Coping with Voices and Self-esteem. It  includes discussion of the definition of self esteem, how voice hallucination experience influences self-esteem, self-esteem enhancement, and acknowledgement of the participant's positive qualities. Module 3 is called Coping with Voices and Stigma. It includes discussion about participant and public attitudes to mental illness and psychotic spectrum disorders, experiences with stigma, education about common mental illness myths, coping strategies for discrimination and negative attitudes. Handouts from the first 3 modules are available to patients as appropriate 
Module 4 is called Afternoon tea with Hearing Voices network and involves the peer support worker explaining to the group of participants the following principles of the  hearing voices approach: 1) Hearing voices is a real and meaningful experience. 2) Each person's interpretation and beliefs about their experiences deserve respect. 3) Safety and wellbeing should be fostered and enabled. 4) Hope is promoted. 6) Providing help to individuals who hear voices, their family and support network helps them not feel so alone. 7) Belief in each person's capacity to take control of their experience and recover is helpful. 8) Individuals are encouraged to come together and feel safe in sharing their experiences and coping strategies. 9)Working collaboratively and inclusively with other services will develop knowledge and achieve holistic approaches to recovery. 10)Volunteering is encouraged to support the Hearing Voices Network of Western Australia.   An information pack is given with an explanation of its contents. The contents are a leaflet outlining  the principles and  information about on-line services and community support groups, a timetable about community support groups, a leaflet on mindfulness exercises, a leaflet for relatives and friends about how to cope with voice hearing and empower the voice hearer and the names and contact details of psychologists trained in the Hearing Voices Approach in Private Practice .

Adherence to the intervention is monitored by the SCGH MHU clinical psychologists who meet weekly for 1 hour of reflective practice. They will keep a record of the duration, number and date of sessions of an intervention for each patient on the Patient Information Form.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment As Usual (TAU) occurs while the participant is on the SCGH MHU and post discharge during the length of the trial. It  involves medication plus at least a 12 monthly medical check-up with a doctor and a minimum of one other treatment program attendance from the following list: Psychiatrist visit/visits other than the 12 month medical check-up doctor in treatment as usual; General practitioner visit/visits other than the 12 month medical check-up doctor in treatment as usual; Regular pickup of Webster medication packs at pharmacy; Hospital in the Home twice daily nurse visits for 2 weeks; Mental health nurse outreach support; Generic case manager outreach support; Supportive inpatient milieu as required; Inpatient or outpatient occupational therapy group program; Community rehabilitation program; Inpatient alcohol and drug program; Inpatient alcohol and drug brief information pack; Community alcohol and drug rehabilitation program; Nicotine addiction treatment; Drop in centre support; Sheltered work; Supported employment; Volunteer work; Education pathway with support; Education pathway without support; Family meetings; Other type of therapy; Non-government organisation outreach support; Non-government organisation social integration via recreational activities; Recreational group/s; Spiritual group; Regular exercise; Supported accommodation-Psychiatric hostel, group home, supported rental alone or shared, family home, aged care facility.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Revised Beliefs about Voices Questionnaire (BAVQ-R).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 ,3 and 6 months post discharge from the SCGH MHU</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychotic Symptom Rating Scale (PSYRATS) hallucinations section</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1, 3 and 6 months post discharge from the SCGH MHU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Engagement in Community Therapy Questionnaire (ECTQ) will describe the type of community therapy engaged with and the number and dates of attendances.</outcome>
      <timepoint> In the past year at the pre-treatment baseline interview, and since last follow-up interview at 1, 3 and 6 months post discharge from the SCGH MHU.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of schizophrenia spectrum disorder defined by DSM-V; experiencing distressing voice hallucinations; has not previously received or is currently receiving CPV; resident of SCGH Mental Health Unit open ward; plans to reside in Australia for the duration of follow-ups; available for follow-up for at least 6 months; able to comply with requirements of the protocol; able and willing to understand and provide written informed consent; between 18 and 65 years of age. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Woman during the lactation period or pregnant; patient highly dependent on medical care; significant communication barrier. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size and power calculations:
Based on the paper by Leff et al. (2013), the corrected effect size is dCohen=0.438, 95% CI: -0.342  1.218. A power calculation was completed using G*Power, based on the paper by Faul et al. (2009),employing a power of 0.80, to detect a difference between the three groups with an alpha of 0.05, and an effect size of 0.438. Mixed Model Repeated Measures ANOVA requires 30 participants to maintain 0.80 power. In view of known attrition in longitudinal study designs, we make the conservative assumption that some 25% of participants may be lost to follow up after baseline contact, at 6 month follow-up we expect an additional 25% attrition. Therefore, 45 participants will be recruited to maintain appropriate study power.

Data Analysis:
Mixed models repeat measure ANOVAs will be conducted using SPSS v21. The dependent variables are total scores on the PSYRATS hallucinations section, BAVQ-R. The within-subjects factor is time with measurements taken at pre-test, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months. The between-subjects factor is intervention, specifically, the two different treatments conditions 1) CPV + TAU and 2) TAU. Descriptive statistics for each group will also be reported.

References:
1.. Leff J, Williams G, Huchvale MA, Arbuthnot M, Leff AP. Computer-assisted therapy for medication-resistant auditory hallucinations: proof of concept study. The British Journal of Psychiatry 2013; 202: 428-433.
2. Faul F,Erdfelder E, Buchner A, Lang A-G. Statistical power and analyses using G* Power 3.1: Tests for correlation and regression analyses. Behaviour Research Methods 2009. 41: 1149-1160.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>North Metropolitan Health Service -Adult Mental Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 1PO
Claremont
Western Australia
6910</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>North Metropolitan Health - Mental Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 1PO
Claremont
Western Australia
6910</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Western Australia, School of Psychiatry</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
D Block
Verdun Street 
Nedlands
Western Australia
6009</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The trial aims to  Demonstrate a Clinical Psychology Intervention for Voice Hallucinations (CPV) plus Treatment As Usual (TAU) is significantly superior to TAU in improving engagement with community therapy, by patient choice, in patients with distressing voice hallucinations and schizophrenia spectrum disorder at the Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit (SCGH MHU). A secondary aim is to see if the distress associated with the voice hallucinations and the frequency and intensity of voice hallucinations will decrease with improved engagement in community therapy.

 There are observed barriers to engagement with community therapy. The higher cost and effectiveness of CPV in overcoming these barriers, compared to the current standard TAU, needs justification by a comparative clinical trial. 

The Participant group will be  voluntary residents of the SCGH MHU with schizophrenia spectrum disorder and distressing voice hallucinations who meet eligibility criteria.

The clinical trial design is a randomised single blind clinical trial comparing 2 treatments groups: CPV + TAU and TAU.

The outcomes measured will be change in: 1) Engagement in community therapy post discharge measured by the Engagement in Community Therapy Questionnaire (ECTQ).  2) Change in Patients distress associated with the voice hallucinations measured by the revised Beliefs About Voices questionnaire (BAVQ-R). 3) Frequency and intensity of voice hallucinations measured by the Psychotic Symptom Rating Scale (PSYRATS) hallucinations section. Measures will be collected at baseline, 1, 3 and 6 months post discharge by a blinded research officer.

The expected outcomes are that engagement in external community therapy will be significantly better in CPV + TAU than TAU at 1, 3, 6 months. Significant reductions in the total PSYRATS auditory hallucination score and abnormal beliefs about the voice hallucinations in the BAVQ-R score are expected at 6 months in the CPV + TAU group compared to the TAU group. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Metropolitan Health Service - Mental Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gascoyne House
Graylands campus
Locked Bag No 1
PO Claremont 
Western Australia
6910</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>01_2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ann Solar</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit
Verdun street 
Nedlands
Western Australia
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63831000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ann.Solar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ann Solar</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit
Verdun street 
Nedlands
Western Australia
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63831000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ann.Solar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ann Solar</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit
Verdun street 
Nedlands
Western Australia
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63831000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ann.Solar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>