<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367357">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000783426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Play Activities Program for nursing home residents with chronic pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cluster randomized-controlled trial of a Play Activities Program
(PAP) for nursing homes residents with chronic pain. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in the experimental group nursing homes will receive the 8-week
Play Activities Program (PAP). The PAP is a protocol-driven intervention which consists of one session per week for a total of 8 weeks. It is conducted in a group format with an emphasis on teamwork and learning various pain management techniques via game activities.  Participants are encouraged to sit together in small groups of 5 to 6 for group activities in every session so as to create social bonding. The PAP will be carried out in the multi-function room, preferably with comfortable chairs, adequate lighting, and comfortable ventilation.

Each session lasts for 60 minutes. At the beginning of each session, participants will
complete 10 minutes of physical exercises including towel dancing; correct body posture and alignment; stretching of arms, legs, and body muscles performed together under the supervision and monitoring of the research team. Then follow by 40 minutes play activities and 10 minutes of portfolio entry. 

Research assistant with nursing or health-care background will facilitate in the sessions. Examples of the play activities include: 
Session One:  Participants will will watch a series of photographs of the natural environment displayed by a projector for 10 minutes. They will be asked to choose the
photographs that they like the most.
Session Two:  Each participant will be given a piece of paper and a few balls of cotton wool; the cotton wool balls will be placed on top of the participants sheet of paper. The participants need to blow the cotton wool onto the paper of the next person. 
Session Three: The participants will be asked to hold a piece of cloth (6 feet x 3
feet in size) using both hands and to move a light ball from one side of the cloth
to the other side. There will be several holes in the cloth and the participants will have to work together to prevent the ball from falling into these holes.
Session Four: The participants will be given colourful paper, and  they will make paper flowers and leaves.
Session Five:  All participants will be seated in a big circle and together they will hold a 6-metre parachute. They will work together, using both hands to throw the parachute in the air and then release their hands, so that the parachute will stay up for 2-3
seconds before coming down;
Session Six: All participants will sit in a big circle. One person will be invited to stand in front of the group for 30 seconds. The person will then hide in a secret place and
modify his/her look. This person will return to the group and the participants will point out the changes that were made.
Session Seven:  Each participant will be given a small handbag made of plain cloth
and will be invited to decorate their handbag with stickers.
Session Eight: The final session will be a summary of the previous sessions. The participants will play with the parachute (as in Session Four) and avoid pain traps (as in
Session Three). They will be encouraged to bring out their flowers and handbags as a reminder to shine like flowers and lead a pain-free life (as in Session Seven).

To ensure the adherence and compliance to protocol content and process, regular meetings will be held among the research team and nursing home staff; also, we shall carefully recruit, thoroughly train, provide ongoing and onsite supervision of research personnel. The consistency of research personnel training will be provided by the principal investigator. Register of attendance at each session will be done; </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group nursing homes will gather together once a week for 8
weeks and listen to talks presented by the research team on diseases that are common among older adults and choices of healthful snacks and meals. Each seminar will last for 40-50 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>current pain intensity and pain interferes as measured by Brief Pain Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at week 8 and at week 20</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain self-efficacy as measured by Chinese version of the Pain Self-efficacy Questionnaire (PSEQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at week 8 and at week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Happiness level as measured by Subjective Happiness Scale (SHS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at week 8 and at week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life as measured by the 12-item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at week 8 and at week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the PAP as measured by self-developed open-ended questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each PAP session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective assessment of pain as measured by saliva biomarkers including alpha-amylase, cortisol and beta-endorphin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at week 8 and at week 20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- aged 65 or above
- able to speak and understand Cantonese
- willing and able to sign a consent form
- experienced pain in the last 3 months of intensity score &gt;=3
- with Chinese Mini Mental State Examination (CMMSE) score &gt;=20 and Hong Kong Montreal Cognitive Assessment (HK-MOCA) &gt;=19</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- with a current or past history of a psychotic disorder
- lack of or inability to participate
- with moderate to severe dementia status
- with a history of acute stroke or acute myocardial infarction, severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, recent fractures, or surgery within the previous 2 months
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Mimi Mun Yee Tse</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>FG 425, School of Nursing,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Research Grant Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>7/F., Shui On Centre,
6-8 Harbour Road, Wanchai,
Hong Kong SAR, People's Republic of China.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Paul Hong Lee</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PQ 433, School of Nursing,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Doris Yuet Lan Leung</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Nursing,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Richard Li</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Medicine,
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road,
Chai Wan,
Hong Kong SAR</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Steven J. Linton</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Law, Psychology and Social Work,
Orebro University,
Fakultetsgatan 1,
702 81 Orebro, 
Sweden</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Sweden</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Shamay Sheung Mei Ng</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>ST 506, Physiotherapy section/Department of
Rehabilitation Sciences,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Winnie Wing Sze Wong</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PLAY INFINITY,
Room 1201, Sing Win Factory Building,
15-17 Shing Yip Street, Kwun Tong, Kowloon</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. John Wai Man Yuen</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>HJ 545, School of Nursing,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic pain is common among ageing population. Fifty per cent of older people in
the community and 74%-80% of nursing home residents experience chronic pain.
Chronic pain significantly impairs both physical and psychological well-being. Pain has
never been adequately managed. Due to concerns about the side-effects of continuous
analgesic use, only 20% of older adults take pain-relief medications. Therefore, a creative, innovative, and non-pharmacological Play Activities Program (PAP), focusing on pain management education via group activities, team effort, and creating social attachments is proposed. This study aims to explore the effectiveness and acceptability of the PAP in reducing pain, enhancing self-efficacy, happiness, and quality of life among older adults with chronic pain.

240 nursing home residents will be recruited. Nursing homes will be randomly allocated to experimental (receiving PAP) or control group (health talks and usual care). The PAP, consisting of 60 minutes of play activities, will be offered once a week for eight weeks.

Primary outcome is pain intensity; secondary outcomes include pain self-efficacy, happiness, health-related quality of life and acceptability of the PAP. Salivary biomarkers  as objective assessments of pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Departmental Research Committee, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Z404, Block Z,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HSEARS20141205003</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mimi Mun Yee Tse</name>
      <address>FG 425, School of Nursing,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</address>
      <phone>+852 2766 6541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mimi.tse@polyu.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mimi Mun Yee Tse</name>
      <address>FG 425, School of Nursing,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</address>
      <phone>+852 2766 6541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mimi.tse@polyu.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mimi Mun Yee Tse</name>
      <address>FG 425, School of Nursing,
The Hong Kong Polytechnic University,
Hung Hom,
Kowloon,
Hong Kong SAR</address>
      <phone>+852 2766 6541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mimi.tse@polyu.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>