<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368592">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000899549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Performance and complications of hysteroscopic  adhesiolysis of in women complaining of reproductive failure due to intrauterine adhesions.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of hysteroscopic adhesiolysis in women with intra-uterine adhesions who are trying to become pregnant</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-3308</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>intrauterine adhesions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Hysteroscopy is the method of choice to diagnose, treat and follow up patients with intrauterine adhesions.
steps of hysteroscopic adhesiolysis: the procedure was carried out with senior gynaecological endoscopist. The cervix was dilated to Hegar dilator 6. A forward oblique 30 degree, hysteroscopy was inserted inside the uterine cavity that was distended with 0.9% normal saline at inflow pressure of 6090 mmHg, using a special machine, hysterometer, which was used to adjust the pressure of the flow, the amount of the distension media fluid used and the deficit after the operation. 
The operative hysteroscopy used was 5.5 mm outer sheath diameter that permits the use of 3-5 French diameter semi-rigid scissors to lyse the adhesion at the junction of the adhesion with the endometrium and excise the tissue. 
Duration of hysteroscopy procedure was ranged between 10  52minutes with average time was 29 minutes. </interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pregnancy rate. It was assessed during routine follow up from patients records in endoscopy unit in our hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint> 6 months postoperative.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of pregnancies. It was assessed during routine follow up from patients records in antenatal care clinic in our hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>If pregnancy occurred during 6 months postoperative; the follow up period extended from the diagnosis of pregnancy till the time of birth or termination of pregnancy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>live births rate. It was assessed during routine follow up from patients records in labor ward department in our hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>If pregnancy occurred during 6 months postoperative; the follow up period extended till the time of birth or termination of pregnancy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of number of bleeding days and amount of menstrual blood loss. i.e. the changes in postoperative menstrual pattern. These changes will be assessed by clinical follow up. The patients will be asked about number of bleeding days, number of napkins per day and the degree of soakness using pictoria charts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months postoperative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The need for another hysteroscopic trial for adhesiolysis.  The need for another hysteroscopic procedure will be assessed by using hysterosalpingogram and office hysteroscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intra- and postoperative complications, like pain, fever, bleeding, postoperative adhesions, theses parameters will be assessed by clinical follow up</outcome>
      <timepoint>intraoperative complication assessed during the operative procedure. Early postoperative follow up within first 24 days. late postoperative complications within month.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time lag between the intervention and diagnosis of pregnancy</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the first 6 months postoperative. If pregnancy occurred the follow up period was extended till the day of delivery or termination of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients trying to get pregnant with intra-uterine adhesions that affect their reproductive carrier, with no contraindication for either pregnancy or surgery</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>37</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age more than 37 years old, other causes of amenorrhea or reproductive failure as ovulatory disorder, tubal block, pelvic adhesions diagnosed by laparoscopy, PID or male factors of infertility.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Menstrual and fertility outcomes data were statistically described in terms of range, mean +/- standard deviation (+/-SD), median, frequencies (number of cases) and relative frequencies (percentages) when appropriate. Comparison of quantitative variables between different groups in the present study was done using Mann Whitney U test for independent samples. For comparing categorical data, Chi square test was performed. Exact test was used instead when the expected frequency is less than 5. Accuracy was represented using the terms sensitivity and specificity.
Correlation between various variables were done using Pearson moment correlation and Spearman rank correlation equations. A probability values (p value) less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant. 
All statistical calculations were done using computer programs Microsoft Excel version 7 (Microsoft Corporation, NY, USA), SPSS (Statistical Package for the Social Science; SPSS; Inc., Chicago, IL, USA version 20) and Arcus Quick Stat (Biomedical version, Addison Wesley Longman Ltd, USA) statistical-program. The number of participants was not determined by sample size equation as it is not controlled trial nor diagnostic one.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/10/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>61</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Minia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Minia Maternity University Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Minia-  Minia Maternity University Hospital, Cornish El- Nile Street, Minia Minia Governorate, Postal code: 61111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Minia Maternity University Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> Minia Maternity University Hospital, Cornish El- Nile Street, Minia  Minia Governorate, postal code:61111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aimed to assess the efficacy and safety of hysteroscopic adhesiolysis in patients with bad obstetric outcome due to intrauterine adhesions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>no</trialwebsite>
    <publication>no</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>no</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Scientific ethical committee of the department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Minia Maternity University Hospital, Cornish El- Nile Street, Minia Minia Governorate, postal code: 61111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board of the University Hospital-Quality control unit of the Faculty of Medicine, Minia University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Minia Maternity University Hospital, Cornish El- Nile Street, Minia Minia Governorate, postal code: 61111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Minia Maternity University Hospital, Cornish El- Nile Street, Minia Minia Governorate, postal code: 61111</address>
      <phone>+20 01000222994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Minia Maternity University Hospital, Cornish El- Nile Street, Minia Minia Governorate, postal code:61111</address>
      <phone>+20 01000222994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Minia Maternity University Hospital, Cornish El- Nile Street, Minia Minia, postal code:61111</address>
      <phone>+20 01000222994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ahmad Sameer Sanad</name>
      <address>Mina university, Faculty of Medicine</address>
      <phone>+20 01000222994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asasanad@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>