<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367380">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001222639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating the relationship between mindfulness and self-control related to fruit and vegetable consumption in young adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>"The effect of Mindfulness Training on Trait Self-control and the Intention-Behaviour Relationship in the Theory of Planned Behaviour" in university students, as assessed by daily fruit and vegetable intake (behaviour outcome).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1163-8259</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 4-week behaviour intervention (BI) group designed to increase fruit and vegetable intake in young adults, compared to a combined 4-week behaviour intervention with mindfulness training (BIM) group. Both programs will take place in a classroom setting with one teacher and the group.

The behaviour intervention (BI) program will be developed specifically for this study and will comprise of 4 weekly 1-hour meetings over a one month period, consisting of the following topics:
a)	Week 1: Information on health and behaviour and negative consequences of having an unhealthy diet.
b)	Week 2: Information on others behaviour, seeking approval, and social comparisons.
c)	Week 3: Motivation and instruction on how to successfully perform the behaviour.
d)	Week 4: Tips on overcoming hindrances and issues opposing the desired behaviour.

The Behaviour Intervention and Mindfulness Group (BIM) will consist of the standard behaviour intervention (see above as presented to the BI group), with additional training and set homework exercises in mindfulness to be practiced on a daily basis over the four week period of the BIM intervention. 

These components are based on the mindfulness practices from the 8-week MBSR program, which will be condensed for this purpose into a four week intervention:
a)	Week 1: 40 min Body Scan Exercise and 10 min mindful eating activity
b)	Week 2: 15-20 min Sitting meditation, mindfulness in daily activities instructions
c)	Week 3: 20-30 min Sitting meditation, mindfulness in daily activities, 10 min walking meditation
d)	Week 4: 30-40 min Sitting meditation, walking meditation, and mindfulness in daily activities.

The homework exercises in mindfulness will consist of a daily 20-30 min sitting or walking meditation practice, with ad-hoc practice of mindfulness in daily activities when suitable. A weekly record will be recorded of time/practice during the four-week program. In total, about 3-5 hours of mindfulness meditation practice per week as homework will be expected of participants in the BIM group.
 
The Fruit and Vegetable Consumption questionnaire will be completed on a daily basis by the participants over the four week period for both the BI and BIM intervention programs to monitor behaviour outcome.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The standard behaviour intervention group is the comparator/ control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily Fruit and vegetable consumption as assessed by a daily food diary indicating daily servings of fruit and vegetables consumed, measured in serving size.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trait Self-control assessed by the Self-Control Scale (SCS), a 36-item self-report scale designed to assess trait self-control, developed by Tangney, Baumeister and Boone (2004).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of Mindfulness assessed by the Mindfulness Attention Awareness Scale (MAAS), a 15-item self-report scale designed to assess level of mindfulness, developed  by Brown and Ryan (2003).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Students enrolled at Curtin University.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A psychiatric condition or history of substance abuse. Any personal reasons (spiritual or otherwise) for not wanting to learn meditation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be screened for substance use and psychiatric conditions, or personal objections to learning meditation, by completing a control screening questionnaire. A pre-screening question will be included to ensure participants are naive to meditation practice prior to commencing the study. Participants will be randomly allocated to one of two intervention groups (behaviour intervention or combined behaviour intervention + mindfulness training). Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using coin-tossing.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study will be a between-groups pre-post design.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Structural Equation Modelling (SEM). 

In order to reliably test the SEM, it has been recommended that we have at least 10 participants for each free parameter* in the model - although 20 participants per free parameter is the ideal (Kline, 2005). 

Therefore, a minimum sample size for testing this SEM model is 10[6 + 3 +1] =100 (50 in each group). 

*A free parameter is a parameter that must be estimated from the sample data. The free parameters in this SEM model include the path coefficients (6 parameters), the disturbances of the endogenous variable (3 parameter), and the variances of the exogenous variables (1 parameter). 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>9/03/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6102 - Bentley</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University, School of Psychology and Speech Pathology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building 401
Kent Street, Bentley, Perth WA 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent Street, Bentley, Perth WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to determine the relationship between higher levels of mindfulness on trait self-control and on the intention-behaviour relationship in the Theory of Planned Behaviour. Further, the study will investigate the mechanisms by which mindfulness affects behavioural change outcomes, as indicated by daily fruit and vegetable consumption over a four week period.
The hypothesis is that higher levels of mindfulness will be associated with higher levels of trait self control. Further, higher levels of mindfulness will strengthen the intention-behaviour relationship as demonstrated by increased fruit and vegetable consumption in the behaviour/mindfulness change group, compared to the standard behaviour change group:
H1: There will be a difference between the standard behaviour intervention (BI) group and the behaviour intervention + mindfulness (BIM) group in terms of behaviour outcome (fruit &amp; vegetable intake).
H2: The relationship in H1 will be mediated by trait self-control and levels of mindfulness.
H3: Compared to the BI group, the BIM group will report higher levels of mindfulness, which will result in higher levels of self-control.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anne Murphy</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>annemarie.murphy@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rosanna Rooney</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>R.Rooney@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Barbara Mullan</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 2468</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Barbara.Mullan@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anne Murphy</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>annemarie.murphy@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>