<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373145">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001038381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the efficacy of a brief mental health crisis intervention for adolescents</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the efficacy of a brief community-based intervention for adolescents presenting in crisis to public mental health service</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Suicidal thoughts and behaviours</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition> Self harm</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Suicide</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The research project aims to evaluate the effectiveness of a Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents who present to the Monash Health Early in Life Mental Health Service (ELMHS) with recent suicidal behaviour/plan or deliberate self-harm (within the past 2 weeks). This intervention is offered to young people and their parents/carers as part of routine mental health care by mental health clinicians within the ELMHS Intake, Assessment, Consultation and brief Treatment (iACT) team at the ELMHS Dandenong site - Community Services Building.  

All mental health clinicians within the iACT Team are health practitioners who have training and experience in assessment and treatment of mental health conditions in children, adolescents and youth, including mental health crisis presentations.  These clinicians include certified psychologists, social workers, occupational therapists, medical practitioners, and consultant psychiatrists who are at a Grade 2 category of employment or higher.

Young people (aged 12 to 18 years) and their parents/carers who agree to participate in the Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents as part of the young persons routine care, will also be invited to participate in this research study.  

The primary treatment goals of the intervention are: To reduce reoccurrence of suicidal/self-harm behaviour and to increase coping with stressors that can trigger suicidal crises. 

The iACT brief crisis intervention is provided over a total of 4-5 sessions, with sessions ideally administered on a weekly basis. This intervention consists of initial, middle and end phases of acute treatment. Each session commences with a risk assessment and broad review, so that revisions may be made to the crisis plan as required. 

Sessions will generally be allocated in the following order: 
1.	Assessment Session (90-120 mins)
2.	Initial Treatment phase (1-2 sessions  60-90 mins) 
3.	Middle Treatment Phase (2-3 sessions  60 mins) 
4.	End Treatment Phase (1 session  60 mins) 

Each phase consists of the following core tasks: 
1.	Initial Treatment Phase  Psychoeducation, safety planning and shared narrative/case formulation 
2.	Middle Treatment Phase  Selective individual skill building modules and family intervention modules. 
3.	End Treatment Phase  Relapse prevention 

The iACT brief crisis intervention is a semi-structured treatment. Thus, individual and family modules are collaboratively chosen by the individual, family and clinician at the end of the initial treatment phase. Selection of the modules is based on relevance to the individual formulation and predicted effectiveness regarding risk reduction.

Individual skill building treatment modules from the middle phase of treatment can include: self monitoring skills; emotional regulation skills; problem solving skills (around identified stressors); mobilising social supports; behavioural activation; communication skills; thought-based strategies and goal setting skills.  Family treatment modules include: enhancing parental emotional reflection skills; strengthening family relationships; and family communication skills.  

The relapse prevention focus of the final stage of treatment involves: reviewing the crisis event; reviewing the crisis event with skills learned through current treatment; reviewing future high-risk scenarios and engaging in planning around how these may be most effectively managed; debriefing around the therapy experience and engaging in planning around recommended follow up supports.
 
Family involvement in all aspects of the young person's treatment can be flexibly planned. Therefore, parents may join the young person for parts of their treatment sessions or participate in entire sessions with the young person at the clinicians discretion.  Additional family phone check ins (5-15 minutes per/week) may be offered at clinicians discretion. These will not be considered as treatment sessions. 

Treatment Fidelity/Adherence Measures:
Mental Health Clinicians providing this brief crisis intervention to young people and their carers, as part of the young person's routine mental health care, will have had orientation to the 'Treatment Fidelity ­Guiding Document'.  This guideline aims to define the minimum therapeutic tasks that should be covered in each treatment stage and selected treatment module to support consistency of the intervention. This aims to ensure that the treatment is implemented as planned and that each component is delivered in a comparable manner to all participants

Clinicians who are providing this routine brief crisis intervention package to young people who have consented to participate in the current research evaluation project will complete a Treatment Fidelity Session Checklist at end of each session that helps document therapeutic tasks covered each session.  

Clinicians will also be required to have several of their clients full series of therapy sessions audio recorded, where a research investigator will rate these recorded sessions in relation to treatment adherence.  A random selection method will be utilised for selecting clinicians clients within the study to request consent for this audio-taping process. The number of sessions recorded will equate to 15-20% of the total number of treatment sessions delivered to all participants group. This recording process is voluntary. If a participant does not want their treatment sessions to be recorded, they do not have to be.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study Hypotheses:

Change in the frequency and severity of suicidal thoughts and behaviour, assessed using the Colombian Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS).

Outcome will be measured with the Colombian Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) - 'Baseline-Screening' Version at Timepoint 1 and the C-SSRS- 'Since Last Session' Version at subsequent time points

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: 

1. Before starting the Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents (baseline), 
2. At their final treatment session
3. Phone review completed two months after completing the intervention.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the frequency and severity of deliberate self-harm behaviour, assessed using the Colombian Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS).

Outcome will be measured with the Colombian Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) - 'Baseline-Screening' Version at Timepoint 1 and the C-SSRS- 'Since Last Session' Version at subsequent time points
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: 

1. Before starting the Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents (baseline), 
2. At their final treatment session
3. Phone review completed two months after completing the intervention.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study Hypothesis:

Change in suicide related resilience and coping skills, assessed using the Suicide Resilience Inventory (SRI-25). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints:
1. Before starting the Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents (baseline) 
2. At their final treatment session
3. Phone review completed two months after completing the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusionary criteria:
	Youth aged in between 12-18 years 
	Following recent suicide attempt or deliberate self-harm within last 2 weeks 
	May present with suicidal ideation and plan
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>General exclusion considerations: 
	Psychiatric inpatient admission required
	Significant psychotic component to presentation
	Severe and chronic substance dependence/abuse that is a primary component of presentation
	Severe personality disorder  where brief treatment is not indicated
	Where the carers capacity/availability to engage in intervention with young person is compromised or severe parent-carer relational discord where a brief family-based intervention is contraindicated.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>1. Justification of Sample Size 

A power analysis was performed to determine the sample size required to detect significant differences across time on the primary outcomes measures. Results from a Daniel Soper a priori sample size calculator indicated that a sample size of approximately 64 participants would be adequate, with a medium effect size (Cohens d) = 0.5, desired statistical power = 0.8 and a = 0.05. This study will aim to recruit 65-75 young people and their parents/carers. 

2. Data Analysis 

A one-way repeated measures Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) will be utilized to assess for significant change in the three outcome variables (suicidal thoughts/behaviours severity, self-harm behaviours severity and suicide-related resilience levels) across the three time-points (beginning of treatment, end of treatment and at 2 month post review). 
A mixed-model ANOVA with a 3x2x3 design will also be used to identify any confounding group effects of age, gender or socio-economic status variables on the results. 



</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/08/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>16/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>2</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3175 - Dandenong</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Early in Life Mental Health Service, Monash Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>145 Cleeland Street, Dandenong VIC 3175</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Cairnmillar Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>993 Burke Road, Camberwell VIC 3123</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The research project aims to evaluate the effectiveness of a Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents who present to a community-based, public mental health service with recent suicidal behaviour/plan or deliberate self-harm (within the past 2 weeks). This intervention is offered to young people aged 12 to 18 years and their parents/carers as part of routine mental health care by mental health clinicians within the team. 

The Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents comprises four to five 60-minute appointments that include a beginning, middle and end phase of treatment.  The treatment involves both the young person and their carer/s and covers the following therapeutic tasks: Keeping safe and building a shared story about the young persons crisis situation; Working through selected individual and family treatment modules that have been specifically chosen to build coping skills relevant to the young persons unique situation; and Relapse prevention (i.e. reviewing what has been learned and planning for the future).

Young people and their parents/carers who participate in the Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents as part of the young persons routine care, will also be invited to participate in this research study.  Young people and parents/carers who decide to participate in this study are consenting for the young person's information and outcome measures be included in the evaluation.  The questionnaires will include routine outcome measures given to all families receiving mental health care at this service, in addition to a few specific questionnaires that evaluate the young persons suicidal ideation and behaviours, self-harm behaviours as well as resiliency.   

It is expected that participants who were provided the Brief Crisis Intervention will demonstrate less risk of future suicidal or self-harm behaviours and have gained coping skills to better manage stress experienced in their lives. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Quantified Rate of Improvement:

It is expected that 15-25% of the sample will display improvement following participation in the Brief Crisis Intervention for Adolescents. Improvement in this study is defined as:

a) A significant decrease in the frequency and severity of suicidal thoughts and suicidal behaviour 
b) A significant decrease in frequency and severity of deliberate self-harm behaviour and;
b) A significant increase in suicide related resilience and coping skills.
 
Please Note: The sample improvement range of 15-25% has been estimated based on the results of previous literature. Previous meta-analyses and individual studies measuring the effectiveness of CBT-based interventions for adolescents presenting with recent suicidal or deliberate self-harm behaviour, have tended to use a diverse range of longer follow-up time points. Consequently, no studies till date have assessed change in suicide risk utilising a follow-up period as short as 2 months. Thus, it should be noted that the results of this study may be somewhat different to that of previous studies.

The below papers were used to create an estimation of percentage improvement for the proposed study's sample:

Wood, A., Trainor, G., Rothwell, J., Moore, A. N. N., &amp; Harrington, R. (2001). Randomized trial of group therapy for repeated deliberate self-harm in adolescents. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, 40(11), 1246-1253

Ougrin, D., Tranah, T., Stahl, D., Moran, P., &amp; Asarnow, J. R. (2015). Therapeutic interventions for suicide attempts and self-harm in adolescents: systematic review and meta-analysis. Journal of  the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, 54(2), 97-107.

Sle Slee, N., Garnefski, N., van der Leeden, R., Arensman, E., &amp; Spinhoven, P. (2008). Cognitivebehavioural intervention for self-harm: randomised controlled trial. The British Journal of  Psychiatry, 192(3), 202-211.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Monash Health Ref: RES-17-0000-352A, NMA SSA Reference Number: SSA/17/MonH/333</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Moseley</name>
      <address>Intake, Assessment, Consultation and Brief Treatment (iACT) Team
Early in Life Mental Health Service (ELMHS), Monash Health
Community Services Building
145-151 Cleeland Street, Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9767 8274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.moseley@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Moseley</name>
      <address>Early in Life Mental Health Service, Monash Health
Community Services Building
145-151 Cleeland Street, Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9767 8274</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9767 8244</fax>
      <email>iact@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Moseley</name>
      <address>Early in Life Mental Health Service, Monash Health
Community Services Building
145-151 Cleeland Street, Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9767 8274</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9767 8244</fax>
      <email>iact@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ayushi Gupta</name>
      <address>Early in Life Mental Health Service, Monash Health
Community Services Building
145-151 Cleeland Street, Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9767 8274</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9767 8244</fax>
      <email>ayushi.gupta@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>