<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367059">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000993695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Analysis of the profile of males with hypogonadism in the regional setting of North Queensland.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Retrospective analysis of the profile of males with hypogonadism in a regional hospital of North Queensland,
Australia over the past 10 years</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1161-4621</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypogonadism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We are doing a retrospective chart study on the profile of males who have developed hypogonadism within Mackay Base Hospital over the last 10 years. We will be looking at the patient's demographic profile, previous medical conditions/surgeries/medication, the symptoms that led them to the diagnosis (fatigue, headache, loss of libido, infertility, low mood), previous examination findings (weight/BMI, neurological finidngs, blood sugar, testicular examination) any investigation results (biochemical or radiological and risk factors for developing the disease (alcohol, radiation, drug-usage, smoking history). All information will be gathered from charts (with previous history of hypogonadism) within Mackay Base Hospital , and relevent information will be transferred to the database collection tool. No patient contact is involved. (passed through ethics and public health act).</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil treatment provided as it is a chart study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A validated data collection tool is being used collect data and analyse the profile of males with hypogonadism. This data collecting tool has been  approved by Townsville Human Research Ethics committee and Public Health Act. This data collection tool was made by our own research group. Things that we are looking for whilst analysing data from patient charts include; patient demographics, symptoms that led to the diagnosis, previous medical and surgical history, examination findings, investigation findings (biochemical- serum testosterone, lipids, blood sugars, prolactin, thyroid hormone, and radiological- ct/mri head, ultrasound of testes), and exposure risk factors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>We have been granted approval by  Townsville Human Research Ethics committee and Public Health Act/Mackay Base Hospital to have access to all patients who have developed hypogonadism within the last 10 years. Thus outcomes for each patient are assessed when they contracted the disease. Usually there a few cases annually. This information will be collected  retrospectively from charts.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To look at the complications developed by patients who have suffered from hypogonadism. These include metabolic syndrome, diabetes, hyperlipidemia, depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>It depends on when the patient suffered the complication (usually after diagnosis). This data will be collected from patient charts.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>all patients aged over 18 years with biochemical hypogonadism within Mackay Base Hospital in the period of June 2004-June 2014</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients under the age of 18, severe chronic renal failure, or liver cirrhosis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>As it is a retrospective chart study study, we only needed the patients who have been diagnosed with hypogonadism. We will be using simple demographical statistics (via MICROSOFT EXCEL) with the aid of graphs, and tables to help evaluate and present our statistics</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mackay Base Hospital - Mackay</hospital>
    <postcode>4740 - Mackay West</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Apoorva Saboo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Apoorva Saboo 
James Cook University
PO BOX 6314
Mackay Mail Centre
QLD 4741</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mackay Base Hospital in-kind costs</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>475 Bridge Road, West Mackay, 4740, QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Pirathaban Sivabalan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>2 Griffin Street, Mackay, QLD, 4740
James Cook University</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The rationale of this project is to study hypogonadism in the background of regional north Queensland. In the setting of a small population with a relatively variable socioeconomic status attributed to the mining and farming industry, it is interesting to evaluate the different causes of hypogonadism ranging from pathological causes to lifestyle choices with respect to exogenous steroid intake and a widespread use of complementary and alternative medicines. This study will also be stratifying how the level of testosterone may provide an insight to the primary general practitioner as to the possible causes of hypogonadism and if there is any correlation between the two parameters. Furthermore, a study on males with hypogonadism in regional Australia has not been previously undertaken.

With the knowledge that a low serum testosterone is known to provide various clinical complications such as increased microvascular disease, hyperlipidaemia, osteopenia, fatigue, weakness and psychological distress from impaired libido it is important to conquer these patients early and attempt to find any underlying cause behind these patients hypogonadism.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Apoorva Saboo</name>
      <address>Apoorva Saboo James Cook University PO BOX 6314 Mackay Mail Centre QLD 4741</address>
      <phone>61451045880</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>apoorva.saboo@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Pirathaban Sivabalan</name>
      <address>2 Griffin Street, Mackay, QLD, 4740 (James Cook University- Medical Student)</address>
      <phone>61432472026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pirathaban.sivabalan@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Pirathaban Sivabalan</name>
      <address>2 Griffin Street, Mackay, QLD, 4740 (James Cook University-Medical Student)</address>
      <phone>61432472026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pirathaban.sivabalan@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Pirathaban Sivabalan</name>
      <address>2 Griffin Street, Mackay, QLD, 4740</address>
      <phone>61432472026</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pirathaban.sivabalan@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>