<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366077">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000378628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of Positive Psychology Group Intervention for Chronic Illness Patients with negative emotional states in Primary Care A Prospective Experimental Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of Positive Psychology Group Intervention for Chronic Illness Patients with negative emotional states in Primary Care A Prospective Experimental Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patient with diabetes and/or hypertension with negative emotions screened using DASS-21</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This prospective case studies will conduct a 6-weekly 2-hr session group intervention program for 15 patients with stable hypertension and/or diabetes on regular follow-up at a primary care clinic. The waiting list of 15 patients for this intervention study will be used as the control. This program will adopt multiple component interventions focusing on the several well-studied areas of positive psychology. The multi-skills including noticing the positives, character strength, gratitude, optimism, hope and mindfulness will be conducted in 6 weekly sessions. A Family physician who has training in counselling and positive psychology will administer this intervention</interventions>
    <comparator>15 patients awaiting the 6-weekly 2hrly session of positive psychology intervention will be used as the control</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in DASS-21, Life Satisfaction Scale and Subjective Happiness Index pre and post-intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 week post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>none</outcome>
      <timepoint>none</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria:
1). Patients aged 40 and above with hypertension and/or diabetes mellitus and they are screened to have negative emotional states using Chinese version of Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale DASS-21 
2). They are willing and able to participate in 6-weekly, 2hr/week Positive Psychology Intervention Program
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria : 
1). Patients with history of major psychiatric disorders such as major depression, schizophrenia, panic disorder and etc.
2). Patients currently on psychoactive medications.
3). Patients with cognitive impairment or acute exacerbation of chronic medical illness.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed
Using the Clinical Management System CMS, patients with chronic medical disease will be identified and their appointment dates searched. On day of patient’s appointment, she/he will be screened on voluntary basis for depression, anxiety and stress using DASS-21 Chinese version.  Patients screened to have negative emotional states with scores of Depression &gt;4 and/or Anxiety&gt;3 and/or Stress&gt;7 will be invited to join this intervention. If patient agrees to join the study, informed consent will be signed. A convenient sampling of 30 eligible subjects will be recruited to account for 25% attrition rate. The 6-weekly 2-hr session group intervention will consist of 15 subjects. The other 15 subjects in the waiting list will be the control group.

</concealment>
    <sequence>Convenient sampling and allocation is not randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>According to Browne ( Browne 1995); Lancaster et al ( Lancaster 2002); Ross-McGill et al 2000); Stevinson&amp;Ernst 2000),  a pilot study recruiting at least 30 subjects is suggested to determine initial data for the primary outcome measure, in order to perform a sample size calculation for a larger trial, Thus, we aimed to recruit 30 subjects for this pilot study</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lorna Ng</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Family Medicine and General Out-Patient Clinic
Kwong Wah Hospital
Waterloo Road
Kowloon, Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lorna Ng</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Family Medicine and General Out-Patient Clinic
Kwong Wah Hospital
Waterloo Road
Kowloon, Hong Kong</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title:  Impact of Positive Psychology Group Intervention for Chronic iIllness Patients with negative emotional states in Primary Care A Prospective Experimental Study

Background: With the epidemic of non-communciable diseases, chronic illness such as heart disease, stroke, cancer, chronic respiratory diseases and diabetes, are by far the leading cause of mortality in the world . In Hong Kong, health care reforms have emphasized the importance of chronic disease management with multi-level, multi-disciplinary and multi-sectoral collaboration to achieve better health. There is also abundant evidence showing that patients with chronic medical illness represent a population at particularly high risk of mental disorders ranging from 20%-60%.  The importance of promoting mental wellbeing while taking care of the medical needs of patients with chronic illness should be advocated.  Different psychotherapeutic interventions including positive psychology has been shown to benefit patients with chronic disease. There is presently no published study on the effect of Positive Psychology Group Intervention for chronic illness patients with negative emotional states in primary care. 

Aim: This study will introduce a multi-component Positive Psychology Group Intervention for chronic illness patients with negative emotional states  and the aim is to provide preliminary evidence that Positive Psychology is an effective intervention modality..

Objective: This study attempts to assess whether Positive Psychology Group Intervention will be effective in reducing negative emotional states including depression, anxiety and/or stress, and  enhance positive affect.
Method:  Using the inclusion and exclusion criteria defined by this study, a convenient sampling of 30 adult subjects screened to have negative emotional states using DASS-21 will be recruited on voluntary basis. A pre-and post-intervention inventories including Chinese validated versions of DASS-21, Satisfaction of Life Scale and Subjective Happiness Scale ( SHS)  will be performed. Eligible subjects will receive 6-weekly, 2 hrs per week of Positive Psychology Group Intervention consisting of 15 adults per group. The waiting list of 15 adults will be used as the control.  This program will adopt multiple component interventions focusing on the several well-studied areas of positive psychology. It will include 6 multi-skills and techniques , some specific examples of skill techniques and weekly home assignments including Week 1and 2 :Noticing the positives, Optimism and gratitude journal, Week 3: Focusing on personal strengths, Week 4: Concept of Mindfulness and practice, Week 5: Hope and Teaching acts of kindness, Week 6: recapitulation and review.
Expected Primary Outcomes: Positive Psychology Group Intervention is associated with improvement of  negative emotional states and enhancement of positive affect in patients with chronic medical diseases.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Kowloon West Cluster Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 533, Block J Princess Margaret Hospital
2-10 Princess Margaret Road, Lai Chi Kok
Kowloon
Hong Kong</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>KWC REC 71-35</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Honduras</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lorna Ng</name>
      <address>Family Medicine and General Out-Patient Department
Kwong Wah Hospital
Waterloo Road
Kowloon, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+852 35172310</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ngl@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lorna  Ng</name>
      <address>Family Medicine and General Out-Patient Department
Kwong Wah Hospital
Waterloo Road
Kowloon, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+852 35172310</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ngl@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lorna Ng</name>
      <address>Family Medicine and General Out-Patient Department
Kwong Wah Hospital
Waterloo Road
Kowloon, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+852 35172310</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ngl@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lorna Ng</name>
      <address>Family Medicine and General Out-Patient Department
Kwong Wah Hospital
Waterloo Road
Kowloon, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+852 35172310</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ngl@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>