<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372258">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000315314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Parenting, Eating and Activity for Child Health (PEACH) Queensland: the trial of universal childhood obesity management program for families of primary school aged children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> Queensland Health's Targeted Risk Modification Kids program: a trial of a statewide universal childhood obesity management program to lower BMI z score, improve diet, physical activity and parenting self efficacy,decrease sedentary behaviours and trial models for health service delivery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PEACH QLD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>diet</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>physical activity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>parenting</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The TRIM kids project trialled the universal availability of a childhood obesity management service in Queensland, Australia.  It was the upscaled implemention of the Parenting, Eating and Activity for Child Health (PEACH) program.  The aims of the project were to increase the capacity of families who participated to adopt healthy lifestyles (eating and physical activity and to promote healthy weight through sustainable behavior change.  
Objectives of the project were to:
 1: Successfully deliver the program to 1400 children state-wide.
 2: Refine the PEACH model to ensure maximum retention of participants and further deploy the program to maximise participation state-wide (including regional and rural Queensland).
3: Document new models utilised to deliver the program.
4: Enhance the currently limited evidence-base on the effectiveness of paediatric treatment programs, in particular, in their use with culturally and linguistically diverse (CALD) and Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander populations.
5: Contribute to the Department of Healths vision through contributing to the early detection and appropriate treatment of childhood obesity and secondary prevention of obesity related conditions.
6: Leverage the funding opportunity to invest in the sustainability beyond the project lifecycle.
PEACH targeted families of children aged 5-11 years who were above the healthy weight range for age.
PROCEDURES AND MATERIALS
PEACH was a group-based, 6 month family-focussed lifestyle intervention.   PEACH consisted of nine 90-minute face-to-face sessions (fortnightly or weekly), followed by a final tenth session at 6-months after session one.  Between sessions nine and ten, facilitators made three individualised phone calls (duration varied according to family need).  At each session, content was delivered by the facilitator to a group of parents, emphasising the role of peer-support in behaviour change.  Sessions were held outside of school hours in a variety of tertiary and community based settings, predominantly school venues.  
Topics included parenting styles, nutrition skills, and physical activity. Each of the ten parent sessions had defined objectives, take home messages and a small homework task. Parents were encouraged to set one or two family family-specific goals to work on between sessions, utilising the goal setting and action planning worksheet templates and the planning ahead template (PAT).  Enrolled families received a Parent Handbook and provided additional one-on-one parent facilitator time support via three phone calls between sessions 9 and 10 at a time each parent had identified as convenient for them. Parents received appointment reminder SMS messages before each face-to-face session and twelve weekly motivational messages between sessions 9 and 10 e.g. "routines help children to move from one activity to th enext smoothly and calmly. why not use a PAT to set a healthy routine?    
Concurrently with parent sessions, Children attended separate sessions with a child facilitator during which they participated in games and activities.  Each child session included a brief healthy eating component based on the content corresponding parent session to facilitate family discussion at home. Children sessions were supported with a Child workbook which encouraged at home activities. Siblings of enrolled children were encouraged to participate in the child sessions.
WORKFORCE
Facilitators were health professionals recruited from around Queensland via call for expressions of interest.  Training workshops were conducted via a 2-day face-to-face workshop in Brisbane, Queensland or teleconference meeting in special circumstances. Workshops comprised program information including the background to PEACH and its key objectives, session content role-plays as well as information on the role of the facilitator in program delivery and collection of evaluation data from participants.
ADHERENCE AND MODIFICATIONS
Data regarding fidelity of the intervention was collected using session monitoring booklets. Facilitators recorded the duration of each session and their adherence to the sessions key content. 
The project was implemented over five geographical time limited waves during which one program cycle (ie 6months) was delivered. The number of programs being run increased incrementally with each wave with services from previous waves expected to continue to offer the program in subsequent waves.  Data was reviewed at the end of each wave and informed subsequent waves.  Two key changes were made as a results: After wave 2, the QUT Project Implementation Team undertook a review of the program design and content, and as a consequence of this the intervention was adapted in order to improve retention and engagement. Some of this adaptations were: changed intervention frequency from fortnightly to weekly sessions, within a school term,  reviewed program design and content to better align with families concerns and reasons for enrolment, Introduced SMS reminder messages before sessions, focused on using schools as ideal venues to reduce stigma, and sent motivational SMS messages to families between sessions 9 and 10. Following wave 4, eligibility criteria were changed to include healthy weight children.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of children with increased intake of fruit and vegetable and reduced intake of discretionary foods and/or non-milk sugar sweetened beverages via parent-reported dietary recall and Child Dietary Questionnaire (a validated tool which combines food frequency and dietary behaviours questions)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At six months after starting the program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of parents reporting changes in their children's activity and sedentary behaviours using a parent reported physical activity survey.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At six months after starting the program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of children who achieved a lower BMI z-score and/or a healthier weight status category. Height and weight measured by child facilitators at first and last sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At six months after starting the program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting self-efficacy and confidence as assessed by the parenting self-efficacy questionnaire. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At six months after starting the program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The eligibility criteria for enrolling in the program were modified for wave 5. 

For waves 1 to 4:
&gt;Child is above healthy BMI range
&gt; Child is aged 511 years
&gt; Child resides in Queensland

For wave 5:
&gt; Child is aged 511 years
&gt; Child resides in Queensland</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>For waves 1 to 4:
&gt; Child is within healthy BMI range
&gt; Child is not aged 511 years
&gt; Child does not reside in Queensland

For wave 5:
&gt; Child is not aged 511 years
&gt; Child does not reside in Queensland</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>18/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1513</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove  Queensland 4059  </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Government Department of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>147/163 Charlotte St, Brisbane City QLD 4000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Flinders University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sturt Rd, Bedford Park SA 5042</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of Queensland Health's Targeted Risk Modification Kids (TRIM Kids) program was to contribute to the reduction of the prevalence of overweight and obesity in Queensland children in two ways. Firstly, it sought to increase the capacity of the families who participate in it to adopt healthy lifestyles related to healthy eating and physical activity in the future. Secondly, it intended to promote healthy weight and weight management through sustainable behaviour change.

The intervention delivered by the program was the PEACH program, a six-month parent-focussed
positive parenting and healthy lifestyle group program that has demonstrated effectiveness in reducing the degree of overweight in primary school aged children and maintaining this reduction for more than two years after the program ended. The PEACH program is based on the recognised cornerstones of child weight management, namely diet and activity changes through behaviour modification with parental involvement and support. The delivery through parent-only groups (ie parents as the exclusive agents of change) is based on the work of Golan and colleagues who demonstrated better outcomes when parents alone were targeted and children not included in intervention sessions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.peachqld.com.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>CONFERENCE ORAL PRESENTATIONS

&gt;&gt;Vidgen H. Managing childhood obesity: Learnings
from the implementation of two state-wide programs
(symposium). The Australian and New Zealand Obesity
Society (ANZOS) Annual Scientific Meeting; 2016 Oct
1921; Brisbane, Australia.
&gt;&gt; Miller J, Moores C, Chan L, Daniels L, Vidgen H,
Croyden D. Key learnings from the PEACH program in
Queensland. The Australian and New Zealand Obesity
Society (ANZOS) Annual Scientific Meeting; 2016 Oct
1921; Brisbane, Australia.
&gt;&gt; Love P, Vidgen H, Daniels L, Innes-Hughes C, Rissel C,
Nean J, Innes-Walker K, Baur L, Croyden D. What are
the implementation barriers and enablers for childhood
obesity management services? The Australian and New
Zealand Obesity Society (ANZOS) Annual Scientific
Meeting; 2016 Oct 1921; Brisbane, Australia.
&gt;&gt; Smith M. PEACH Program and Childrens Nutrition 
the Role that Oral Health Practitioners Play. Australian
Dental and Oral Health Therapists Association (QLD)
State Conference; 2016 Oct 1415; Brisbane, Australia.
&gt;&gt; Moores C, Hartley J, Perry R, Vidgen H, Daniels L,
Magarey A. Impact of PEACH Queensland facilitator
training on knowledge, skills and confidence of parent
facilitators to support families with overweight children.
33rd Dietitians Association of Australia Conference;
2016 May 1921; Melbourne, Australia.
&gt;&gt; Moores C, Hartley J, Perry R, Vidgen H, Daniels L,
Magarey A. PEACH Queensland program improved
child eating behaviours and reduced BMI z-score for
overweight children (pilot study). The Nutrition Societies
of Australia and New Zealand Joint Annual Scientific
Meeting; 2015 Dec 14; Wellington, New Zealand.
&gt;&gt; Moores C, Hartley J, Perry R, Vidgen H, Daniels L,
Magarey A. Pilot results from the Parenting, Eating
and Activity for Child Health (PEACH) Queensland
program. Postgraduate and Early Career Nutrition
Conference; 2015 Dec 1; Wellington, New Zealand.
&gt;&gt; Vidgen H. PEACH: Key learnings and challenges from
the state-wide roll out of a child obesity management
project. Australian and New Zealand Obesity Society
Annual Scientific Meeting; 2015 Oct 1517; Melbourne,
Australia.
&gt;&gt; Daniels L, Perry R, Vidgen H, Hartley J, Croyden D,
Williams S &amp; Littlewood R. Translating evidence to
practice: PEACH a case study (workshop). 31st
National Dietitians Association of Australia Conference;
2014 May 1517; Brisbane, Australia.

CONFERENCE POSTER PRESENTATIONS

&gt;&gt; Davidson K, Vidgen H. Why do parents enrol in a
childhood obesity management program? The
Australian and New Zealand Obesity Society (ANZOS)
Annual Scientific Meeting; 2016 Oct 1921; Brisbane,
Australia.
&gt;&gt; Williams S, van Lippevelde W, Moores C, Magarey A,
Vidgen H, Daniels L. Whos getting engaged? Factors
associated with parent engagement when upscaling
the PEACH program. Poster session presented at:
European Obesity Summit; 2016 Jun 14; Gothenburg,
Sweden

&gt;&gt; Hartley J, Perry R, Moores C, Vidgen H, Esdaile E,
Croyden D, Daniels L, Magarey A. Family lifestyle
behaviours: pilot results of Queensland PEACH.
Poster session presented at: 32nd National Dietitians
Association of Australia Conference; 2015 May 1316;
Perth, Australia.
&gt;&gt; Moores C, Perry R, Hartley J, Croyden D, Esdaile E,
Vidgen H, Vincenc S, Daniels L, Magarey A. Metropolitan
and regional enrolments in the family-focussed child
weight management program PEACH Queensland.
Poster session presented at: 32nd National Dietitians
Association of Australia Conference; 2015 May 1316;
Perth, Australia.
&gt;&gt; Magarey A, Moores C, Hartley J, Perry R, Vidgen H &amp;
Daniels L. Impact of participation in the PEACH child
weight management intervention on parenting and
family lifestyle behaviours: pilot results of PEACH
Queensland. Poster session presented at: European
Congress on Obesity; 2015 May 69; Prague, Czech
Republic.
&gt;&gt; Perry R, Hartley J, Daniels L, Vidgen H &amp;
Magarey A. Venturing down the rabbit hole of
translational research: the PEACH child weight
management program. Poster session presented at:
European Congress on Obesity; 2015 May 69; Prague,
Czech Republic.
&gt;&gt; Perry R, Hartley J, Daniels L, Vidgen H &amp; Magarey A.
Efficacy to Effectiveness: the theoretical challenges
of translational research in the nutrition field using
the PEACH Program as a case study. Poster session
presented at: 31st National Dietitians Association of
Australia Conference; 2014 May 1517; Brisbane,
Australia.
&gt;&gt; Croyden D, Vidgen H, Magarey A, Littlewood R &amp;
Daniels L. The practicalities of translating an effective
nutrition research intervention to a community
program: the PEACH experience. Poster session
presented at: 31st National Dietitians Association of
Australia Conference; 2014 May 1517; Brisbane,
Australia.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>results of original PEACH RCT, ie the evidence based for the program delivered to families used in this trial:
Magarey A, Perry R, Baur L, Steinbeck K, Sawyer M, Hills A, et al. A parent-led family-focused treatment program for overweight children aged 5 to 9 years: The PEACH RCT. Pediatrics. 2011;127(2):214-22. 
results of small scale community trial:
Magarey A, Hartley J, Perry R, Golley R. Parenting Eating and Activity for Child Health (PEACH(trademark)) in the Community: (PEACH(trademark) IC): translating research to practice. Public Health Bulletin South Australia. 2011;8(1):58-61.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland children’s Health Services Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street
South Brisbane QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QHC/25</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2 George St, Brisbane City QLD 4000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1300000633</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders University Social and Behavioural Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sturt Rd, Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H13/09-173</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lynne Daniels</name>
      <address>Emeritus Professor
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, 
Faculty of Health
Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove Queensland 4069
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 6139</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l2.daniels@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helen Vidgen</name>
      <address>School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, 
Faculty of Health
Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove Queensland 4069
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 0118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.vidgen@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helen Vidgen</name>
      <address>School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, 
Faculty of Health
Queensland University of Technology
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove
Queensland 4069</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 0118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.vidgen@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>