<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371015">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000896471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot implementation of the Fear Reduction Exercised Early (FREE) approach to low back pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Fear Reduction Exercised Early (FREE) approach to acute low back pain in general practice: a pilot implementation study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-4351</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Fear Reduction Exercised Early (FREE) approach to acute low back pain (LBP). The FREE approach aims to assist GPs to identify and address attitudes and beliefs which may be barriers to recovery from acute LBP, explain back pain to their patients, and to provide patients with a framework which enables patients to resume normal employment and activities of daily living.

General practitioner (GP) participants will be instructed in the FREE approach through an initial four-hour workshop facilitated by an experienced physiotherapist. The workshop will be supported by a booklet, a website, and a module within the practice's electronic patient management system. GPs will then practise using the approach for approximately one-month with any patients who present with acute low back pain. GPs will then attend a one-hour refresher workshop facilitated by a physiotherapist. The refresher workshop will discuss experiences of using the approach and address any barriers identified . GPs will also be provided with a novel information booklet to provide to their patients. This booklet outlines current best practice for acute LBP, supports recommendations from the GP booklet, and addresses commonly held beliefs. It encourages an active approach to managing LBP. The approachwill also be supported by a website. GPs will have access to the website throughout the study and on an ongoing basis following the study. GPs will be able to continue using the FREE approach following the four-month study period in each practice. GPs will be able to personalise the care they provide to any individual patient based on their own clinical reasoning.

A purposive sample of approximately twelve patients who consult GPs who have completed FREE training with a primary complaint of acute low back pain will be interviewed as part of this study. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP beliefs about back pain measured with the Back Pain Attitudes Questionnaire (Back-PAQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months after initial training workshop (also measured at 4 weeks - following the refresher training session)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attitudes to pain and impairment measured with the Health Care Providers Pain and Impairment Relationship Scale (HC-PAIRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months after initial training workshop (also measured at 4 weeks - following the refresher training session)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP Implementation acceptability through items drawn from the Modified Acceptability Of Intervention (AIM) Post-Intervention Survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months after initial training workshop</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Penetration within the primary study general practice population measured by counting the number of GPs who complete FREE training out of a total population of 131 GPs. Please note that this analysis will also draw on data from the parallel RCT involving 60 GPs from within the primary general practice population (through which these 60 GPs will receive FREE training).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Study termination (estimated July 2018)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Routinely collected insurance data will be used to measure the number of patient LBP claims initiated by GPs involved in the implementation study in the twelve months before they receive training, and the twelve months following their refresher training session.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twelve months following the final practice refresher training session (estimated July 2019)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative interviews will be conducted by a research fellow experienced in qualitative research to explore implementation constructs in more depth with purposive samples of both GPs and their patients. These interviews will be semi-structured and audio-recorded. An interview guide with open-ended questions will allow flexibility to discuss issues as these arise. It is anticipated that each interview will last approximately 30 minutes. Additional participants will be interviewed until saturation of major themes is achieved.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the implementation period.  It is anticipated that approximately twelve interviews will be required with GP participants and interviews with patient participants to achieve data saturation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP evaluation of workshop using a purpose developed questionnaire with likert scale and free text response options</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the training workshop</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP evaluation of training using Eight quantitative items selected from the thirteen item Training/Practice Acceptability/Feasibility/Appropriateness Scale scored on a 5-point likert scale and three qualitative items with free text responses
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the refresher training session (4 weeks post initial training workshop)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP reported implementation adoption measured with items drawn from the Adoption of Information Technology Innovation scale and items adapted from the Level of Use instrument</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months after initial training workshop</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP reported implementation appropriateness measured with items drawn from the Parenting Strategies Questionnaire and the Scott Innovation Scale  Behavioural intention subscale</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months after initial training workshop</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP reported implementation feasibility measured through a purpose developed item and items from the feasibility subscale of the Training/Practice Acceptability/Feasibility/Appropriateness Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months after initial training workshop</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Penetration within all practices which receive training will be measured by counting the number of GPs who complete FREE training out of the number of GPs who practice at these sites</outcome>
      <timepoint>Study termination (estimated July 2018)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Routinely collected insurance data will be used to measure the cost of patient claims (and components of these costs) for LBP claims initiated by GPs involved in the implementation study in the twelve months before they receive training, and the twelve months following their refresher training session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twelve months following the final practice refresher training session (estimated July 2019)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Routinely collected insurance data will be used to measure the rates of earnings compensation for LBP claims initiated by GPs involved in the implementation study in the twelve months before they receive training, and the twelve months following their refresher training session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twelve months following the final practice refresher training session (estimated July 2019)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Routinely collected insurance data will be used to measure the rates of patient referral for additional health care for LBP claims initiated by GPs involved in the implementation study in the twelve months before they receive training, and the twelve months following their refresher training session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twelve months following the final practice refresher training session (estimated July 2019)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Routinely collected insurance data will also be used to assess the proportion of patient with LBP claims initiated by GPs involved in the implementation study in the twelve months before they receive training, and the twelve months following their refresher training session. who file another LBP claim in the 12 months and 24 months following their initial claim.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 months following the final practice refresher training session (24 month time point estimated to be achieved at July 2020)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>GP participants will be eligible for the study if they meet the following criteria:
1) New Zealand registered GP
2) Working within the Hutt Valley, Wairarapa, Wellington, or Kapiti regions
3) Have agreed to attend the FREE approach training sessions

Patient participants will be eligible for the study if they meet the following criteria:
1) Attended a GP who has been interviewed as part of the FREE implementation study with a primary complaint of LBP which had been present for less than 6 weeks
2) Over 18 years of age</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>GP participants will not be eligible for the study if they:
1) Have participated in pilot testing
2) Have been participants in a parallel RCT (60/134 GPs in the Hutt Valley)
3) Do not attend the initial FREE training workshop

Patient participants will not be eligible for the study if they:
1) Are unable to communicate in English
2) Have not been exposed to the FREE approach (assessed via Medtech consultation notes and/or patient inquiry related to FREE resources)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size:
One hundred and forty GPs will be invited to participate in the implementation study. This will give good precision for the primary outcome (Back-PAQ measure  no formal power calculated as the study aim is to estimate changes in beliefs, rather than hypothesis testing per se) and also on the penetration measure (coverage of all Hutt Valley GPs undertaking training). 

GP self-reported outcomes:
The mean and standard deviation of the Back-PAQ and HC-PAIRS scores will be calculated pre- and post-intervention. The change score along with its 95% confidence interval will be calculated to estimate the magnitude of any change, using a paired t-test to identify any statistically significant change, with alpha set at 0.05.

Quantitative workshop evaluation data will be analysed with descriptive statistics.

Implementation outcomes:
Implementation measures are single time-point evaluations, so will be reported using descriptive statistics (frequencies, medians and interquartile range).

Penetration will be calculated by dividing the number of GPs who complete FREE training by the total population of GPs in the study region and practices..

Cost-benefit:
The impact of implementation on ACC insurance costs will be calculated for each GP trained in the FREE approach in the Hutt Valley. Data related to ACC insurance claims for the twelve months preceding FREE training will be compared with data for the twelve months following completion of FREE training. These comparisons will be analysed with paired t-tests. Statistical significance will be judged with an alpha of 0.01 to account for multiple comparisons.

Net Benefit will be calculated by subtracting the net cost of implementation from the monetary benefit (adjusted pre-post change in the total cost of claims) on a per-GP basis and a per-10,000 population basis given a range of assumptions regarding GPs/10,000 people aged &gt;18yrs. The net cost of implementation will comprise the initial training and implementation costs.

Qualitative interviews:
Qualitative interviews will be analysed using Thematic Analysis. Recruitment will continue until theme saturation is achieved. Approximately 12 GPs and 12 patients will be interviewed. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>152</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>27/07/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Lower North Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Ben Darlow</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Primary Health Care and General Practice
University of Otago, Wellington
23 Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Accident Compensation Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Justice Centre
19 Aitken Street
PO Box 242
Wellington 6140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the implementation of a new approach to managing acute low back pain. It will train 140 GPs in the approach and investigate if the training changes their knowledge and beliefs about back pain. It will also look at GPs' views of how the new approach was implemented and explore patients' experiences of the approach.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.otago.ac.nz/backpainstudy</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/CEN/77</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Darlow</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Health Care and General Practice
University of Otago, Wellington
23 Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+6449186051</phone>
      <fax>+6443855539</fax>
      <email>ben.darlow@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Darlow</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Health Care and General Practice
University of Otago, Wellington
23 Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+6449186051</phone>
      <fax>+6443855539</fax>
      <email>ben.darlow@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Darlow</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Health Care and General Practice
University of Otago, Wellington
23 Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+6449186051</phone>
      <fax>+6443855539</fax>
      <email>ben.darlow@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Darlow</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Health Care and General Practice
University of Otago, Wellington
23 Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+6449186051</phone>
      <fax>+6443855539</fax>
      <email>ben.darlow@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>