<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365469">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000073606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>How do tasks involving the upper limbs and trunk affect the sternum post-median sternotomy?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>How do tasks involving the upper limbs and trunk affect the sternum post-median sternotomy?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SMaRT- Sternal Management and Review Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiothoracic surgical patients</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sternal micromotion (movement that occurs at the sternal edges)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>MAIN STUDY (Observational study): 
Main outcome measure is sternal micromotion (movement that occurs at the sternal edges) at rest and during five functional tasks (deep inspiration, cough, upper limb elevation (unilateral and bilateral) and sit to stand) at 3 time points (3-7 days, 6 weeks and 3 months post-operation). Ultrasound (Sonosite M-Turbo device) will be used to capture real-time, 2D images of the sternum during each of the above tasks. A software program (MicroDicom) will then be used to measure the amount of sternal micromotion. 

NESTED STUDY (Reliability study): 
Main outcome measure is sternal micromotion (movement that occurs at the sternal edges) at rest and during five functional tasks (deep inspiration, cough, upper limb elevation (unilateral and bilateral) and sit to stand) at 1 time point (3-7 days post-operation). Each task will be repeated three times and the order randomized. Ultrasound (Sonosite M-Turbo device) will be used to capture real-time, 2D images of the sternum during each of the above tasks. Two observers, blinded to the participant and task will then use a software program (MicroDicom) to measure the amount of sternal micromotion. </interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator/control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sternal micromotion (movement that occurs at the sternal edges) using 2D ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-7 days, 6 weeks and 3 months post-operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sternal pain (visual analogue scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-7 days, 6 weeks and 3 months post-operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function (functional disability questionnaire; brief pain inventory- short form)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-7 days, 6 weeks and 3 months post-operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sternal instability (sternal instability scale):
The sternal instability scale is a manual test that measures the stability of the sternum based on a 4-point scale. A score of 0 corresponds to a clinically stable sternum with no detectable motion or separation of the sternal edges, whilst a score of 3 corresponds to a completely separated sternum with marked increased motion or separation of the sternal edges.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-7 days, 6 weeks and 3 months post-operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients:
1. who have undergone an elective or emergency cardiac surgical procedure, involving a median sternotomy.
2. over the age of 18 years.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients:
1. with insufficient English comprehension to provide informed consent, complete simple, written questionnaires and/or understand simple, verbal instructions. 
2. unable to participate in visual testing methods, including VASs and simple, written questionnaires.
3. deemed medically unstable by their respective cardiothoracic surgeons/teams pre-operatively or post-operatively, preventing them from participation in the testing procedures. This includes patients who are hemodynamically unstable, with a heart transplant or ventricular assist device, requiring intra-aortic balloon pump support, in respiratory distress/failure, requiring ongoing intubation or non-invasive respiratory support or who have suffered an acute neurological event, such as a cerebrovascular accident.
4. with impaired cognition or in a confused state thus preventing them from being able to provide informed consent, complete simple, written questionnaires and/or understand simple, verbal instructions. This includes patients with severe dementia, suffering an intellectual disability or diagnosed with an acute delirium.
5. with a physical impairment that prevents them from participating in the upper limb and trunk tasks tested in the ultrasound component. This includes patients who have been diagnosed with severe osteoarthritis, significant rotator cuff injury or who are bed/wheelchair bound.
6. who have undergone cardiopulmonary resuscitation post-operatively.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size (MAIN STUDY): 
The sample size calculation is informed by the results of a previous study conducted by El-Ansary et. al (2007) who found that the mean micromotion of the sternal edges in participants with chronic sternal instability was 11.5mm (with a standard deviation of 2.9 units). This represents a large effect size (f=0.4). Given that the patient population for this study will not have chronic sternal instability, the research team expects a smaller mean micromotion of the sternal edges. Therefore, using a moderate effect size for a one way ANOVA for repeated measures (f=0.25), the research team will need 64 participants at Beta=0.8 and Alpha=0.05. In order to account for a potential participant drop-out rate of 15%, the research team will aim to recruit 75 participants.

Sample Size (NESTED RELIABILITY STUDY of day 3-7 sternal micromotion measures):
For the inter-rater reliability component of the study, the research team expects an intra-class correlation coefficient of 0.90, but will accept a minimum value of 0.70. Therefore, a total of at least 19 participants are required, at Beta=0.2, Alpha=0.05.

Statistical Analysis (MAIN STUDY):
The primary outcome measure of the mean micromotion of the sternal edges as well as the BPI short form and FDQ will be analysed using repeated measures within subjects ANOVA. Additionally, this data will be presented as a mean difference (+/- 95% confidence interval) at each time point. The mean micromotion of the sternal edges data will also be analysed using repeated measures ANCOVA, with mean VAS used as a covariate.  Based on the data collected for the mean micromotion of the sternal edges, the research team will define a cut-off value for whether a participant has sternal instability or not. This cut-off value will be informed by previous research which has found that the mean micromotion of the sternal edges in patients diagnosed with chronic sternal instability is 11.5mm (with a standard deviation of 2.9 units). Values above and below the cut-off value will be used as a nominal dependent variable in logistic regression analysis. The research team will enter up to 5 variables into the logistic regression to assess relationships between sternal instability and risk factors that are significant on univariate analyses. The SIS will be analysed using Friedmans test for within subjects, non-parametric, repeated measures data. Correlation of the BPI short form, FDQ, VAS and SIS with the primary outcome measure will be calculated using Spearmans correlation coefficient. The overall level of statistical significance will be set at a p-value of less than 0.05.

Statistical Analysis (NESTED RELIABILITY STUDY of day 3-7 sternal micromotion measures):
The inter and intra-rater reliability of the ultrasound measures will be examined using intra-class correlation coefficients and Bland-Altman plots. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>12/07/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Melbourne Private Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sulakshana Balachandran</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department, The University of Melbourne
Alan Gilbert Building, Level 7
161 Barry Street, Parkville, Victoria 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>- The median sternotomy remains the gold standard incision for cardiac surgery procedures and involves division of the sternum (otherwise known as the breastbone) to access the heart and surrounding structures.
- After such procedures, patients are routinely asked to follow precautions that restrict upper limb and trunk movements in order to allow the sternum to heal. 
- However, little is known regarding the sternal healing process and how upper limb and trunk movements affect this process following cardiac surgery.
- The primary aim of this research project is to investigate how tasks involving the upper limbs and trunk affect the healing sternum over time. 
- To achieve this, the research team will measure how much movement occurs at the sternal edges during upper limb and trunk movements with the use of a 2D ultrasound machine.
- 75 participants will be recruited to take part in this study. All participants will receive standard pre and post-operative care.
- Nested within the above main study is a reliability study which aims to investigate the inter and intra-rater reliability of ultrasound measures of sternal micromotion during upper limb and trunk movements, in acute patients following cardiac surgery (first time point- 3-7 days post-operation). 
- The first 20 participants recruited to the main study will form the sample for the reliability study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Human Health Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne Health, Office For Research
PO Royal Melbourne Hospital
300 Grattan Street, Parkville, Victoria 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011.240</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alistair Royse</name>
      <address>Royal Melbourne Hospital- City Campus
300 Grattan Street, Parkville, Victoria 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 39342 7000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alistair.royse@heartweb.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sulakshana Balachandran</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, The University of Melbourne
Alan Gilbert Building, Level 7
161 Barry Street, Parkville, Victoria 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 407 834 822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sulakshana.balachandran@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sulakshana Balachandran</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, The University of Melbourne
Alan Gilbert Building, Level 7
161 Barry Street, Parkville, Victoria 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 407 834 822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sulakshana.balachandran@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sulakshana Balachandran</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, The University of Melbourne
Alan Gilbert Building, Level 7
161 Barry Street, Parkville, Victoria 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 407 834 822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sulakshana.balachandran@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>