<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308387">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000715279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Transform-Us!: an intervention promoting children's health.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-setting intervention to reduce sedentary behaviour, promote physical activity and improve children's health.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Transform-Us!</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour in children</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity in children</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease risk in children</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes risk in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 2-year behavioural intervention targeted at reducing sedentary behaviour (SB-I) and increasing physical activity (PA-I) alone or in combination (SB+PA-I) among 8-9 year old children will be delivered through primary schools, with home-based components. A current practice, control arm (C) will serve as a comparison. The materials are based on Social Cognitive Theory, Behavioural Choice Theory and Ecological Systems Theory.

School based component:
 - Teachers in the SB-I program will increase the proportion of class time that children spend continuously active by delivering one lesson (30-minutes per day) of their standard curriculum via an alternative method which requires the children to be standing (eg 30-minute standing lessons) and reducing periods of continuous sitting by including short (2-minunte) standing breaks every 30 minutes during teaching blocks (eg. children stand and discuss the current activity); 
 - Teachers in the PA -I program will increase childrens physical activity during recess and lunch times through increased teacher supervision and encouragement (ie teachers actively encourage children to be active during school breaks); our provision of additional signage in the school grounds (eg ground court markings); and our provision of additional equipment (eg bats and balls).
 - Teachers in the SB +PA-I program will combine the above strategies to both interrupt extended periods of sitting and increase time spent in physical activity during breaks.
 - Teachers in the C schools are will continue their current procedures, policy and practice.

Over the two years, class teachers in the SB-I, PA-I and SB+PA-I groups will also deliver to their students a series of 18 key messages developed by the research team, targeted at their intervention arms relevant behaviours (eg selective viewing, behavioural contracts). The messages are designed to be easily incorporated into the current learning theme. The researchers will provide resources for this component and teachers are encouraged to incorporate them into their current curriculum. 

Home-based component
Teachers will give children regular homework activities which will focus on reducing time spent in sedentary leisure activities at home (SB-I), increasing physical activity at home (PA-I) or a combination of these (SB+PA-I). Ideas and resources will be provided by the researchers and the teachers will be encouraged to adapt their current homework tasks to match the aim of their intervention arm. Examples of such homework include 
SB-I: Switch off the TV ... contracts, or
PA-I:  walking around the neighbourhood tasks that incorporate current learning (eg. counting letterboxes), and 
SB+PA-I: Switch off the computer and go for a family walk tasks.

In addition, parents will receive eight newsletters and will be invited to attend and two parent information nights to provide families with information about the program aims and progress and to reinforce the behavioural changes.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment. Schools will continue with current practices. Eight generic newsletters of equivalent size to those used in the intervention groups will be sent to parents during the 2 years which will contain educational material unrelated to physical activity or sedentary behaviour.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary time and physical activity, objectively assessed using Manufacturing Technology Inc. (MTI) Actigraph Model, AM7164-2.2C accelerometers and activPALs. Children wear the accelerometers and activPALs during waking hours for eight days at each measurement point. Movement count thresholds (based on age-specific energy expenditure prediction equations) will be used to calculate the average time spent being sedentary, number of breaks to sedentary time, and time spent in moderate- and vigorous- intensity activity. Accelerometry data from specific times of the day (eg, after-school hours, during class time) will be extracted to identify when changes in physical activity or sedentary behaviour occurred. A random sample of children will wear an activPAL. Data obtained will be used to identify periods of sitting, standing and walking.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months (mid-intervention), 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioural information on the types of activities in which children participate, collected by a parental proxy-report version of the validated Children's Leisure Activities Study (CLASS) questionnaire which assesses children's participation (frequency and duration) in 30 physical activities (eg, walking to school, playing various sports), and 9 sedentary behaviours (eg, homework, watching TV, reading) during a typical week and weekend. Time spent outdoors will be assessed using a previously validated proxy-report measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months (mid-intervention), 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index (BMI) (kg/m2), obtained via height and weight assessments without shoes, using a portable stadiometer and digital scales, performed by trained research staff privately at school. BMI will be calculated and converted as recommended for analysis of longitudinal adiposity data. Children will also be categorised as healthy weight or overweight/obese based on International Obesity Task Force definitions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months (mid-intervention), 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference, assessed using a flexible tape measure at the level of the narrowest point between the lower costal border and the iliac crest (or the midpoint if not obvious) by trained research staff privately at school. Sex and age-specific waist circumference thresholds for children that correspond to clustering of cardiovascular disease risk factors will be applied.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months (mid-intervention), 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomarkers in a fasting blood sample, collected at school at the beginning of the school day by a paediatric phlebotomist. Levels of insulin, glucose, total cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, calculated low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol, triglycerides, C -Reactive Protein, Vitamin D and insulin resistance (homeostasis model assessment (HOMA)) will be assessed by a commercial pathology laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure, assessed using an A&amp;D Mercury (Model US-767 PC) home blood pressure digital monitor with a paediatric cuff by trained research staff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mediators (how did the intervention work) and moderators (who did the intervention work for) of the intervention, will be determined through parent proxy-report and children's self-report questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months (mid-intervention), 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness of each intervention arm, determined through cost-utility analysis (CUA), whereby outcomes are expressed in terms of '$ cost per Disability-Adjusted Life Year saved'. Cost-effectiveness analysis (CEA) will also be undertaken, where the intermediate results will be expressed as '$ cost per Unit of Body Mass Index (BMI) saved'.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months (mid-intervention), 24 months (post-intervention), 36 months (12-months follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be children entering Grade 3 in 2010 at one of the 22 randomly selected Primary Schools in Metropolitan Melbourne where the study will be conducted.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>On ethical grounds, there will be no exclusion criteria for participants; however, potential confounders will be assessed using parent report of their childs health.

Potential participant Primary Schools will undergo an audit of current policies and strategies targeted at physical activity and sedentary behaviour and those that already have relevant action plans or programs in place will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will occur at the school level in a cluster design. All children in the target year levels (Grades 3 in 2010 and 4 in 2011) at participating schools will receive the intervention arm that the school has been allocated, as the intervention will be embedded in the school curriculum (with previous consent given by the school council). 
Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Schools will be randomised to one of the four groups (three intervention or one control) using computer-generated blocks of 4.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1640</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences
221 Burwood Highway
BURWOOD  VIC  3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC).</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421, Canberra ACT 2601
Level 5, 20 Allara Street, Canberra City ACT</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Schools within a within 50km of Melbourne may be invited to participate.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>None as yet.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00213)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office, Research Services Division, Deakin University, 221 Burwood Hwy, Burwood VIC 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/08/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Jo Salmon</name>
      <address>Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research (C-PAN)
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy Burwood, Vic 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9251 7254</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9244 6017</fax>
      <email>jo.salmon@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Lauren Arundell</name>
      <address>Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research (C-PAN)
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy Burwood, Vic 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9251 7357</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9244 6017</fax>
      <email>lauren.arundell@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Lauren Arundell</name>
      <address>Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research (C-PAN)
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy Burwood, Vic 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9251 7357</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9244 6017</fax>
      <email>lauren.arundell@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>