<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367898">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000180516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>REACH: Multisite randomised trial of Rehabilitation very EArly in Congenital Hemiplegia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multisite randomised trial comparing infant-friendly modified constraint induced movement therapy and infant-friendly bimanual therapy to improve development of reach and grasp, fine motor skills and cognition for infants with asymmetric brain injuries.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>REACH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asymmetric brain injury
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral palsy
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Congenital hemiplegia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Occupational therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Infant-friendly modified constraint induced movement therapy (mCIMT) involves wearing a material glove/sock on the unimpaired hand to encourage use of the impaired hand in play based activity with the impaired arm/hand. mCIMT will be provided in the home by parents/caregivers to the infant by using the glove/sock and engaging the infant in specific play based activities. mCIMT will commence between 3-9 months corrected age, and be provided for 20 minutes per day (can be done in 2 by 10 minute blocks) for 5 days per week up to 6 months of age. Between 6 and 9 months of age, therapy will be provided for 30 minutes per day (can be done in 3 by 10 minute blocks) for 5 days per week.
Between 9 and 12 months of age, therapy will be provided for 40 minutes per day (can be done in 2 by 20 minute blocks) for 5 days per week. Between 12 and 15 months of age, therapy will be provided for 40 minutes per day (can be done in 2 by 20 minute blocks) for 5 days per week. Parents will be supported by an experienced occupational therapist/physiotherapist who do regular monthly home visits and fortnightly Skype calls for 6 months until the infant is 12-15 months of age to ensure that therapy is child and family friendly. Parents will document the intervention in a training log, and therapists will videorecord home visit therapy sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>Infant friendly BIManual therapy (BIM): comprises play-based activity designed to utilise equal activity of both the impaired and unimpaired upper limbs. BIM will be provided in the home by parents/caregivers to the infant by engaging the infant in age appropriate bimanual play activities. BIM will commence between 3-9 months corrected age, and be provided for 20 minutes per day (can be done in 2 by 10 minute blocks) for 5 days per week up to 6 months of age. Between 6 and 9 months of age, therapy will be provided for 30 minutes per day (can be done in 3 by 10 minute blocks) for 5 days per week. Between 9 and 12 months of age, therapy will be provided for 40 minutes per day (can be done in 2 by 20 minute blocks) for 5 days per week. Between 12 and 15 months of age, therapy will be provided for 40 minutes per day (can be done in 2 by 20 minute blocks) for 5 days per week. Parents will be supported by an experienced occupational therapist/physiotherapist who do regular monthly home visits and fortnightly Skype calls for 6 months until the infant is 12-15 months of age to ensure that therapy is child and family friendly. Parents will document the intervention in a training log, and therapists will videorecord home visit therapy sessions.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assisting Hand Assessment (Mini and Small Kids)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At post-intervention between 12-15 months-of-age (Mini AHA) and at 24 months-of-age (Small Kids AHA)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bayley Scales of Infant/Toddler Development (Bayley III)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At post-intervention between 12-15 months-of-age and at 24 months-of-age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hand Assessment of Infant</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study entry between 6-9 months-of-age and at post-intervention between 12-15 months-of-age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pediatric Evaluation of Disability Inventory Computer Adapted Test (PEDI-CAT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At post-intervention between 12-15 months-of-age and at 24 months-of-age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotional Availability-Self Report (EA-SR) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at study entry between 6-9 months-of-age, at post-intervention between 12-15 months-of-age and 24 months-of-age, </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS-21) 
The Maternal Infant Responsiveness Instrument and Maternal Postnatal Attachment Scale have been deleted as the attachment and responsiveness are measured in emotional availability using the Emotional Availability-Self Report.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at study entry between 6-9 months-of-age, at post-intervention between 12-15 months-of-age and 24 months-of-age,  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diffusion MRI: Laterality index of mean diffusivity (MD) and fractional anisotropy (FA) of the cortico-spinal tracts. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention Rating Scale (PRIME-G) </outcome>
      <timepoint>First home visit and at the midway point and end of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hammersmith Infant Neurological Examination (HINE) </outcome>
      <timepoint>At post-intervention between 12-15 months-of-age and 24 months-of-age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be recruited between 3 and 9 months corrected age (+14 days) and have English spoken in the family AND have at least one or more of the following by less than or equal to or 9 months c.a:
1. Asymmetric brain lesion identified on CUS or MRI including asymmetric (one sided or more involved on one side) or unilateral brain injury including preterm or term arterial stroke, grade III or IV intraventricular haemorrhage, asymmetric periventricular leukomalacia or asymmetric deep grey matter (DGM) lesions; AND/OR
2. Absent Fidgety Movements on General Movements Assessment at 12 weeks C.A. by direct video or uploaded using Baby Moves App (2 part consent for screening then recruitment) (including Asymmetric Fidgety whom are often later diagnosed with hemiplegia) AND/OR
3. Abnormal Hammersmith Infant Neurological Examination (HINE) between 18 to 26 weeks AND/OR
4. Asymmetry of upper limb reach and/or grasp on the Hand Assessment of Infants (&gt; 3 point difference) that is congruent with the brain injury (opposite to likely side of the lesion)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>9</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Epilepsy uncontrolled by medication as this would be a confounder.
2. Infants with Retinopathy of Prematurity (ROP) &gt; grade 2 will be excluded.
3. Infants with Cortical blindness will be excluded.
4. Infants with ventriculo-peritoneal shunts will be excluded.
5. Asymmetric lesions that are NOT likely to be affecting the Corticospinal Tract (i.e. not affecting the Posterior Limb of the Internal Capsule or the Pyramids, or the motor cortex), such as tiny lesions of the cerebellum or the occipital pole, etc.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>150 infants with asymmetric brain lesions (identified on cranial ultrasound (CUS) or MRI prior to 12 weeks post term will be recruited and be aged between 3-9 months at study entry. These infants will be identified from neonatal follow-up in several tertiary centres: Lady Cilento Children's Hospital, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Mater Mothers Hospital, Sunshine Coast University Hospital and Gold Coast University Hospital in Queensland; CP Alliance, Westmead Hospital, Royal North Shore Hospital, Liverpool Hospital, Nepean Hospital, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Royal Women’s Hospital, St George Hospital, Blacktown Hospital, Campbelltown Hospital, John Hunter Children’s Hospital, Children's Hospital Randwick and Children’s Hospital at Westmead in Sydney; Royal Children's Hospital and Monash Medical Centre in Melbourne; Princess Margaret Hospital for Children and the King Edward Hospital for Women in Perth and the Australian Cerebral Palsy Register. An information sheet regarding the study will be circulated to therapists and treating clinicians to refer interested families. Potential study participants will be identified by treating clinicians, paediatricians, rehabilitation specialists, neonatologists and allied health professionals who would first contact the family and seek approval for the family to be contacted about the project. The referring clinician would then notify the researchers that they are able to contact the family about the study. Method of randomisation: central concealed random allocation using computer generated numbers.</concealment>
    <sequence>Children will be randomised centrally to receive either mCIMT or BIManual therapy using an electronic allocation system determined by non-study personnel.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary basis for sample size calculation is adequate power for H1 comparison between functional effects of mCIMT compared to BIManual therapy at 12 months c.a. Based on data from a study of 2-3 year olds  (Eliasson et al., 2011) we propose a mean difference of 6 AHA logit points (100-Logit Scale) (Holmefur et al., 2009) as the minimum difference likely to have substantial clinical impact. Data from our large RCT comparing mCIMT and BIM in school-aged children with hemiplegia yielded SD of 12.8 and 12.6 in each group (Sakzewski et al, 2011). A sample size of 144 participants (72 per treatment) will have 80% power to detect 6 unit difference on AHA between groups (2-sided test at p&lt;0.05). We require 150 children (75 in each group) to allow for attrition.

Standard principles for RCTs using two-group comparisons on all subjects on an intention-to-treat basis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>29</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>King Edward Memorial Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>Perth Children's Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Mother's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Coast University Hospital - Birtinya</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Blacktown Hospital - Blacktown</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Sydney Children's Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <postcode>2086 - Frenchs Forest</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>4575 - Birtinya</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2148 - Blacktown</postcode>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre, The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Children's Health Research
62 Graham St
South Brisbane 4101
Queensland, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>
      </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This multisite study will compare infant friendly modified constraint induced movement therapy to infant friendly bimanual therapy for infants with asymmetric brain injuries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Queensland Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centre for Children's Health Research
Level 7, 62 Graham Street
South Brisbane, Queensland, 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QRCH/376</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Medical Ethics Committee
University of Queensland
research and Graduate Studies Office,
St Lucia,
QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015000013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cerebral Palsy Alliance Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>187 Allambie Rd, Allambie Heights, NSW 2100
PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest, NSW 2086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-01-02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Office
Princess Margaret Hospital for Children 
GPO Box D184 
PERTH WA 6840</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015023EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RCH Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Children's Hospital
Level 4, South Building
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria 3052
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SSA/15/RCHM/28</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roslyn Boyd</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre School of Medicine, University of Queensland
Centre for Children's Health Research
62 Graham Street
South Brisbane, Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 7372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.boyd@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roslyn Boyd</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre School of Medicine, University of Queensland
Centre for Children's Health Research
62 Graham Street
South Brisbane, Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 7372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.boyd@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roslyn Boyd</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre School of Medicine, University of Queensland
Centre for Children's Health Research
62 Graham Street
South Brisbane, Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 7372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.boyd@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roslyn Boyd</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre School of Medicine, University of Queensland
Centre for Children's Health Research
62 Graham Street
South Brisbane, Queensland 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 7372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.boyd@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>