<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370149">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000282482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of healthy lifestyle changes on stroke risk in adults with cardiovascular disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of healthy lifestyle changes on stroke risk in adults with cardiovascular disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Risk factors for stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke prevention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants: In this feasibility study we aim to recruit 50 participants via existing networks in GP practices, such as those newly dispensed a medication for cardiovascular disease or those at &gt;15% risk according to the www.cvdcheck.org.au calculator. We intend to liaise closely with the GPs and onsite Pharmacist to access this information.

Life's Simple 7 Intervention: there will be five key aspects to the 6 month service:
1. Education Package and session specific to cardiovascular disease:  This will involve a once off, face-to-face, 2 hour, small group education session, utilising a Chronic Condition Self-Management approach.  This will be conducted by a  physiotherapist trained in chronic condition self-management.  As part of this session, participants will also be provided with a comprehensive educational package based on the American Heart Foundation's program  - Life's Simple 7.  Given the groups will have about 6-8 participants per group, it is envisaged 6-9 groups will be conducted.

2. Motivational interview with identification of 'nudging' strategies to promote and support identified behaviour change:  After the group session a time will be booked to visit each participant and undertake a face-to-face 'assessment', utilising a motivational interview approach.  This assessment will be undertaken by the same physiotherapist who conducted the  group session and is estimated to take about 1.5 hours.  This session will gather data on baseline measures, areas for change, set goals and develop a plan to achieve the participants desired goals.  Part of this plan will involve 'nudging' strategies to help each participant achieve their desired goals through long term behaviour change.

3. Individual sessions ( physiotherapist and GP consultations): Through the 6 month intervention, individual sessions will be scheduled for each participant.  These sessions will involve a combination of phone and in person sessions, based on the aim of the session and participant preferences.  The aim will be to track goals, assist in further motivation/accountability and identify other input that may be required along the way (e.g. dietician, GP review, pharmacist).  The number of individual sessions will be based on each person's unique needs.

4. Longer term monitoring with ongoing new 'nudges', liaison and Health Diary:  A health dairy will be provided to each participant at commencement of this study.  This diary contains vital health information (cardiovascular risk factors) and self-monitoring (nutrition, activity levels, weight, BP, cholesterol, smoking).  Participants complete the diary daily and provide feedback about their progress and goals.  They will be provided with emails, messages, phone-calls to further support them in this, as well as ongoing 'nudges' to help them achieve their goals.  These will be provided dependent on each participants unique needs and what they are trying to achieve at that stage.

5. Health Buddy:  At the beginning of the project, each participant will select a health buddy.  This will be a person they know (e.g. friend, neighbour) that can support them and encourage them along their journey to be a healthy version of themselves.  The health buddy will attend the initial group session, as well as all the face-to-face sessions throughout the 6 months. </interventions>
    <comparator>Feasibility study: no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity - short version IPAQ
</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting Cholesterol assessed by serum assay - completed by patient's GP</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutrition - assessed using Life's Simple 7 Nutrition Score- American Heart Foundation</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting blood pressure assessed using automatic sphygmomanometer- completed by patient's GP </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight - assessed using calibrated digital scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting blood glucose levels - Glucose concentration determined in whole blood sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking status - Self-reported based on questions designed for this study - non-smoker or smoker,  
If smoker measured in packs/day. 
If non-smoker currently, but was a smoker - length of time since quitting will be collected as well as packs/day history prior to cessation of smoking.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Number of groups: 1 (n = 50)
Age range: adults above 18, no upper age limit
Characteristics: those who have been identified by their usual GP as having cardiovascular disease risk factors. Factors taken into account include: those with hypertension, hypercholesterolaemia, taking medications for either of these conditions, and &gt;15% risk of cardiovascular disease according to the www.cvdcheck.org.au calculator
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Adults with known cognitive impairment, inability to provide informed consent. Note we will accept adults with limited English proficiency and provide qualified interpreters for the education and motivational interviewing sessions. Medically unstable </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>22/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Univeristy of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences
City East Campus
Corner of North Terrace and Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Nancy and Vic Allen Stroke Prevention fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Po Box 201 Broadbeach, Queensland 4218.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Our aims of the study are:
1. Increase awareness and adoption of healthy lifestyle factors for people with cardiovascular risk factors, to prevent cardiovascular morbidity and mortality
2. To conduct a feasibility study in the primary care setting to promote the Life's Simple 7 approach, developed by the American Heart Association, for people at risk of stroke
3. To implement a 6 month study to confirm the feasibility, and to provide preliminary data on effectiveness of such an approach.

1. Our overarching hypothesis is that targeted and individualised, longterm support will result in significantly reduced rate of, and risk factors for, morbidity and mortality from stroke and other causes, compared to current practice
2. The 6 month intervention, based on the Life's Simple 7 (LSS) approach, will result in a reduction in stroke risk, measured using the LSS score
3. We hypothesise that the intervention will be feasible, acceptable for participants and we will also collect cost data to determine if the approach is cost effective.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of South Austalia's Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of South Australia
City East Campus
Corner of North Terrace and Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000034694</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle McDonnell</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
 School of Health Sciences
 Internal Post Code CEA-14
 GPO Box 2471 
 Adelaide SA 5001
 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1684</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Michelle.McDonnell@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle McDonnell</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
 School of Health Sciences
 Internal Post Code CEA-14
 GPO Box 2471 
 Adelaide SA 5001
 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1684</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Michelle.McDonnell@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle McDonnell</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
 School of Health Sciences
 Internal Post Code CEA-14
 GPO Box 2471 
 Adelaide SA 5001
 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1684</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Michelle.McDonnell@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Guerin</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
 School of Health Sciences
 Internal Post Code CEA-14
 GPO Box 2471 
 Adelaide SA 5001
 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2509</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.guerin@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>