<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362644">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000643875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Acute effects of nitrate-rich spinach on arterial stiffness in healthy men and women</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Acute effects of nitrate-rich spinach on arterial stiffness in healthy men and women</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vascular function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomised controlled cross-over designed study will be performed. Each participant will complete two visits to the University of Western Australia, School of Medicine and Pharmacology located at Royal Perth Hospital. The acute effects on arterial stiffness and blood pressure of two energy-matched (~2000 kJ) meals will be compared. The meals provided at each visit will contain either:
(1) 250 mg of nitrate derived from spinach (spinach);
(2) &lt;5 mg of nitrate (control). 
The two visits will be administered in random order, one week apart on the same day and at the same time of day as far as possible. Prior to each visit participants will consume a low nitrate meal for dinner (which will not contain green leafy vegatables or beetroot).  Prior to the first visit, participants will document the meal so that they are able to repeat it for the second visit. 
Each visit will begin in the morning between 08:00 and 10:00 with participants having fasted for at least 12 hours. Baseline measurements will be performed prior to the meal. The meal provided will consist of a white bread chicken and cheese sandwich, with or without 250 g of cooked spinach (255 kJ) containing 250 mg of nitrate. The meal will be consumed over a 15 minute period. Nitrate concentrations in vegetables may vary with season, method of cultivation and storage conditions. To account for this, the spinach will be taken from a single batch of frozen spinach from a commercial supplier, and thawed prior to use. Rice milk (100 mL) will be used as the energy matched low nitrate control for the extra energy provided by the spinach. Outcome measurements will then performed again at specific time points up to 240 minutes (4 hours) post meal.</interventions>
    <comparator>Low nitrate meal</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial stiffness measured as pulse wave velocity (PWV) using applanation tonometry (SphygmoCor pulse wave analysis system: AtCor Medical, Sydney, Australia. Model MM3. Software version 9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and then again at 100 min and 200 min post meal</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial stiffness measured as augmentation index (AIx)using applanation tonometry (SphygmoCor pulse wave analysis system: AtCor Medical, Sydney, Australia. Model MM3. Software version 9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and then again at 100 min and 200 min post meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial elasticity/compliance measured as the large artery elasticity index (LAEI) and the small artery elasticity index (SAEI) using pulse contour analysis of the radial artery pulse wave (HDI/Pulse wave CR-2000 instrument: Hypertension Diagnostics, Inc., Eagan, Minnesota, USA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and then again at 140 min and 220 min post meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Office blood pressure , mesured as systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure and pulse pressure (Dinamap 1846SX/P oscillometric recorder: Critikon Inc., Tampa, FL, USA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and then every 30 minutes to 210 minutes post meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salivary nitrate and nitrite concentrations (measured by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and then again at 120 minutes post meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy men and women</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>current smoking; 
BMI &lt;18 or &gt;35 kg/m2; 
systolic blood pressure (SBP) &lt;110 or &gt; 130 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) &lt;65 or &gt; 80 mmHg; 
use of antihypertensive or cholesterol lowering medication;
history of cardiovascular or peripheral vascular disease;
diagnosed type 1 or type 2 diabetes; any major illness such as cancer; a psychiatric illness; 
recent history of asthma, renal, liver or gastrointestinal disease, or gout; 
use of antibiotics within previous 2 months; 
current or recent (within previous 6 months) significant weight loss or gain (&gt; 6% of body weight); 
&gt; 30g/day alcohol consumption; 
woman who were pregnant, lactating or wishing to become pregnant during the study; 
inability or unwillingness to consume foods provided in the trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>There are two treatments in the cross-over design study. The treatment order for eligible individuals will be randomly assigned using computer generated random numbers. The treatment order allocation will be sealed in numbered envelopes. The envelopes will be used for randomisation by opening an envelope, in consecutive order, as participants are entered into the study. The envelopes will be held by an independent person within the University of Western Australia. The study coordinator will contact the independent person to obtain the next available envelope once an individual is deemed eligible. The envelope will be opened and the code will be recorded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated random numbers using Microsoft Excel</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>18/06/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/06/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>26</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council, GPO Box 1421, Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Consumption of foods and beverages rich in nitrate can increase circulating nitrite and nitric oxide, improve endothelial function and lower blood pressure acutely. Effects of dietary nitrate on arterial stiffness have yet to be explored. We aim to assess the acute effects of a single meal containing nitrate-rich spinach on arterial stiffness in healthy men and women. Effects on blood pressure will also be assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Liu AH, Bondonno CP, Croft KD, Puddey IB, Woodman RJ, Rich L, Ward NC, Vita JA, Hodgson JM. Effects of a nitrate-rich meal on arterial stiffness and blood pressure in healthy volunteers. Nitric Oxide 2013; 35:125-130</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Westren Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/4956</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847 Australia</address>
      <phone>61 8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>