<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370184">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000271404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised comparison of how different terminologies for papillary thyroid cancer affect decision making about treatment among an Australian community sample
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised comparison of how different terminologies for papillary thyroid cancer affect decision making about treatment among an Australian community sample
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Thyroid cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Thyroid</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will test how different terminologies used to describe the same diagnosis (papillary thyroid cancer) affect decision making about treatment. This will be done by surveying a population from the Australian community with no history of thyroid cancer and presenting them with 3 hypothetical scenarios that describe a diagnosis of papillary thyroid cancer using various terminology with and without the "cancer" term. The terms presented to participants are papillary thyroid cancer, papillary lesions of indolent course and abnormal cells. Participants will also be given a table with information on the risks and benefits to each treatment option (total thyroidectomy, hemi-thyroidectomy or active surveillance) so that participants are able to make an informed decision about their treatment options.  Each hypothetical scenario and the treatment options presented to participants will be identical with the only difference being the terminology used. 

Participants will be called randomly using random-digit dialing to mobile numbers across Australia by an experienced independent social research company (the Hunter Research Foundation). Participants who agree to participate will be sent a link via email to the online survey. Participants will then complete the survey which includes all 3 hypothetical scenarios at once. It is estimated to take participants 10-15 minutes to complete. 

The aim of this intervention is to assess if the term "cancer" used to describe a diagnosis of papillary thyroid cancer may impact patient treatment preferences (primary outcomes) as well as psycho-social outcomes (secondary outcomes).</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator will be the treatment preference choice. We will be comparing the proportion that choose each treatment option under the two descriptions (cancer term included - papillary thyroid cancer vs. no cancer term included - papillary lesions of indolent course or abnormal cells).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is treatment decision making. This will be measured for each scenario with different terminology presented by participants selecting between 3 treatment options (thyroidectomy, hemi-thyroidectomy, active surveillance).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention (5-10 minutes after participants are presented with the hypothetical diagnosis scenario).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnosis-related anxiety. Measured using a 1-item Visual Analog Scale. 

Davey, HM, Barratt AL, Butow PN, Deeks JJ. A one-item question with a Likert or Visual Analog Scale adequately measured current anxiety. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology 2007;60:356-360.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention (approximately 5 minutes after participants are presented with the hypothetical diagnosis scenario).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment-related anxiety. Measured using a 1-item Visual Analog Scale. 

Davey, HM, Barratt AL, Butow PN, Deeks JJ. A one-item question with a Likert or Visual Analog Scale adequately measured current anxiety. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology 2007;60:356-360.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention (approximately 5 minutes after participants are presented with the hypothetical diagnosis scenario).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General anxiety. Measured using the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory,

Marteau TM, Bekker H. The development of a six-item short-form of the state scale of the Speilberg State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI). British Journal of Clinical Psychology 1992;31:301-306.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention (10-15 minutes after participants are presented with the hypothetical diagnosis scenario).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cancer worry. Measured using a 4-point Likert scale. 

Sutton S, Bickler G, Sancho-Alridge J, Saidi G. Prospective study of predictors of attendance for breast screening in inner London. Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health 1994;48(1):65-73.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention (10-15 minutes after participants are presented with the hypothetical diagnosis scenario).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health literacy. Measured by a 1-item health literacy screening question. 

Morris NS, MacLean CD, Chew LD, Littenberg B. The single item literacy screener: evaluation of a brief instrument to identify limited reading ability. BMC Family Practice 2006;7:21.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention (10-15 minutes after participants are presented with the hypothetical diagnosis scenario).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal/family history of cancer. Multiple choice question.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention (10-15 minutes after participants are presented with the hypothetical diagnosis scenario).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants in this study will be men and women across the Australian community identified through random digit dialing. Participants will be eligible to participate in the study if they are above 18 years of age, are fluent in English and have no history of a thyroid cancer diagnosis. Researchers will try and recruit a 1:1 ratio of male and female participants. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded from the study if they are unable to speak adequate English upon initial contact, if they do not have a valid email address to access the survey, are below the age of 18 years and have been diagnosed with thyroid cancer.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone. Once a participant agrees to take part in the study they will be randomly assigned to be immediately sent one of the versions of the survey. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computerised sequence generation will be used. An independent research organisation (the Hunter Research Foundation) will use their software to administer the randomisation. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size was calculated by simplifying the assumption that if a person does not opt for surgical treatment (active surveillance) when a more serious description is used (ie. papillary thyroid cancer) they will also not opt for surgical intervention when a less serious description is used (ie. abnormal cells) Since we are carrying out multiple comparisons (3 terms analysed separately using McNemars test, alpha=0.05/3=0.01667) we would need 264 participants to detect a 5% change. We also want to analyse men and women separately therefore, we would need 264 men and 264 women (aim to recruit 600 participants total).

Data will be analysed using chi-square tests to compare the treatment choices (primary outcome) between study arms. A univariate analysis of factors (secondary outcomes and demographic characteristics) associated with surgical treatment choice will be used. A multivariate logistic regression model will also be used to assess predictors of surgical treatment choice by terminology used, including diagnosis and treatment related anxiety, general anxiety, cancer worry, health literacy and personal/family history of cancer. 

.All data will be analysed by researchers at the University of Sydney and compiled for publication and dissemination. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>550</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney School of Public Health </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Sydney
NSW 
2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Program Grant 633003</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra, ACT 
2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Prof Juan P Brito</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism, Mayo Clinic
200 1st Street SW
Rochester, MN
55905
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose of the study: This study aims to explore how adults with no history of thyroid cancer would make decisions about treatments based on the terminology used to describe a hypothetical diagnosis of papillary thyroid cancer. 

Who is it for?: You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or more, have no history of thyroid cancer. 

Study details: All participants in this study will be presented with three hypothetical scenarios that describe the diagnosis of papillary thyroid cancer using various terminology with and without the "cancer" term. The order in which these scenarios will be provided is random (by chance). Each hypothetical scenario and the treatment options presented to participants will be identical with the only difference being the terminology used. Following presentation with these scenarios participants will be assessed on treatment preferences and psycho-social outcomes. This research study will contribute to a new body of research aimed at understanding how different terminology for precancerous conditions or early stage cancer affect patients decision making about treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Publication currently under review.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/916</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kirsten McCaffery</name>
      <address>307F Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7220</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kirsten.mccaffery@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kirsten McCaffery</name>
      <address>307F Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7220 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kirsten.mccaffery@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kirsten McCaffery</name>
      <address>307F Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7220</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kirsten.mccaffery@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Brooke Nickel</name>
      <address>127A Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7829</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brooke.nickel@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>