<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372813">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000635369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> Changes in Resting Energy Expenditure with Two Different Schedules of Calorie Restriction</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single-centre centre randomized 6-week parallel group study of two different schedules of caloric restriction on resting energy expenditure in New Zealand men with a BMI &gt;30 kg/m2.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>UTN: U1111-1189-4510</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CREEDS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Brief Name:
Calorie Restriction: Arm 1 Continuous Daily Restriction (CDR)
                                  Arm 2 Intermittent Very Low Calorie Diet (IVLCD) (see comparator group below)

The CDR arm consists of a daily calorie restriction to 77% of estimate daily requirements, this will be observed daily. 

The intervention will be administered as a dietary prescription observed for  duration of 6 weeks.  A dietary prescription tailored to each participants estimated daily energy intake requirements will  be given. Macro-nutrient composition will not be specified.  The prescription consists of several days of set  recipes. This will be based on baseline resting energy expenditure and self reported physical activity using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ). The recipes will be based on the participants pre-intervention food preferences and have been developed by a research dietitian with over 6 years experience.  A 30 minute 1:1 counselling sessions with a member a physician on the research team will be provided at visit 1. 

Participants will be provided with access to calorie counting resources: http://www.caloriecount.co.nz/. This is based on the AUSNUT database from the Food Standards Authority, Australia/New Zealand.   Participants will also be provided a  written guide to reading nutrition labels  prepared by the Food Standards Authority, Australia/New Zealand. 

Attempts to improve adherence will involve providing dietary counselling in relation to calories and the diet types, menus with a pre-specified diet composition and weekly telephone contact during the study. 

Weekly telephone calls of approximately 15 minutes duration, will be made by study by the study physicians. These calls will be performed to confirm ongoing adherence to diet, answer any questions in relation to the diet prescriptions, remind participants about upcoming assessments, to complete instruments prior to their next scheduled visits and to determine if the participants have developed any health problems since last contact.  

The dietary prescription will be adjusted at 3 weeks following repeat energy expenditure measurements and physical activity assessments. 
  
Food diary logs at 1 week, 3 weeks and 6 weeks will be used to assess adherence to the intervention.    

Participants will be asked to avoid implementing any additional weight loss measures, pharmacological or otherwise during the trial period. They will also be asked to maintain their baseline level of physical activity for the entire trial period in so far as possible. They will be asked to limit &amp; record any alcohol intake. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The IVLCD arm consists of an intermittent calorie restriction to 25% of estimated daily requirements on two days per week &amp; 100% of estimated daily requirements on the other days of the week. It will be implemented in an identical fashion to the CDR arm except for the degree and schedule of calorie restriction. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in resting energy expenditure, assessed by canopy hood indirect calorimetry following a daily caloric restriction versus an intermittent caloric restriction. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in resting energy expenditure, assessed by canopy hood indirect calorimetry following a daily caloric restriction versus an intermittent caloric restriction. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in body composition: Lean Mass, Fat Mass, Visceral Adipose Tissue as assessed by Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in body composition: Lean Mass, Fat Mass, Visceral Adipose Tissue as assessed by Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous fasting glucose measured by Glucose Hexokinase Enzymatic Assay (Abbott)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous HbA1C measured by latex agglutination inhibition immunoassay
 (Cobas b101 POC, Roche)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous HDL by photometric transmission measurement (Cobas b101 POC, Roche)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous LDL by photometric transmission measurement (Cobas b101 POC, Roche)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous total cholesterol by photometric transmission measurement (Cobas b101 POC, Roche)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous triglycerides by photometric transmission measurement (Cobas b101 POC, Roche)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH)  (electrochemiluminescence,Cobas e601, Roche)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intevention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous free thyroxine (FT4)  (electrochemiluminescence, Cobas e601, Roche)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous tri-iodothyronine (T3) by Carbonylmetalloimmunoassay method (CMIA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in venous reverse tri-iodothyroinine (rT3) measured by ELISA</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in resting energy expenditure measured by indirect calorimetry on fasting and non-fasting days.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of interventions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in venous Leptin measured by ELISA</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in serum Ghrelin measured by ELISA</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post commencement of intervention
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in concentration of serum adiponectin measured by ELISA</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Satiety assessed by 100mm Visual Analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Satiety assessed by 100mm Visual Analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Hunger assessed by 100mm Visual Analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Hunger assessed by 100mm Visual Analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in self rated energy levels assessed by 100mm Visual Analogue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in self rated energy levels assessed by 100mm Visual Analogue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self reported calorie intake assessed by quantitative 4 day  food diary analysis (Foodworx)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self reported calorie intake assessed by quantitative 4 day  food diary analysis (Foodworx)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 weeks post commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>BMI greater than or equal to 30 kg/m2.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Recent significant weight change &gt; 5 kg over the previous 3 months 
Current medical illness or medications (e.g. steroids) that may, in the view of the investigators, influence resting metabolic rate. 
Current Smoker
Weight &gt; 220kg, the maximum weight limit on the DEXA machine. 
History of any eating disorder. 
History of T2DM requiring  treatment other than metformin or diet (1) OR poorly controlled T2DM with a HbA1C &gt; 8.0%/64mmol/mol OR a fasting plasma glucose &gt; 10 mmol/L(2)*. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealed: Opaque Sealed Envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerized Sequence Generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>ANCOVA will be used to estimate difference in energy expenditure between the intermittent caloric restriction and daily caloric restriction groups. Baseline resting energy expenditure and lean mass will be entered as covariates. Our recruitment target is 36 participants. This number is based on an analysis of energy expenditure per unit body weight in a population of fifteen overweight and obese men &amp; women from our target community. The mean resting energy expenditure per kilogram body weight (REE kg-1 day-1) was 17.93 kcal kg-1 day-1 with a standard deviation of 2.165 kcal kg-1 day-, a drop-out rate of 15%, an alpha of 0.05 and a beta of 0.80. It is conservative and based on two measures of REE, a third measure as planned during our study will reduce the required number of participants. 

An interim analysis of the primary end-point will be performed after 20 participants have been studied will be performed to establish how many remaining participants will be required.   </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>20/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assoc Prof Jeremy Krebs</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington		
Postcode 6242
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Maurice &amp; Phyllis Paykall Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 110008
Auckland Hospital
Auckland 1148 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Brian Corley</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington		
Postcode 6242</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Rosemary Hall</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington		
Postcode 6242</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Patricia Whitfield</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington		
Postcode 6242</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In 2015/2016, 31.6% of all New Zealanders over the age of 15 years were obese. This rising trend in obesity has been observed globally with obesity now affecting more of the worlds population than malnutrition. The World Health Organisation (WHO) estimated a prevalence of T2DM in NZ of 8.5% in 2014. Worldwide the global burden of T2DM is 422 million. Obesity is a disease of energy consumption that exceeds requirements. An individuals daily calorie requirements are composed mainly of their resting energy expenditure (REE) and physical activity associated energy expenditure.

Measurement of energy expenditure allows precise individualized calorie prescriptions to promote weight loss. However, even when a carefully administered calorie reduction is introduced with controlled physical activity, invariably less weight is lost than predicted. This has been ascribed to adaptive thermogenesis (AT) - changes in REE in response to a dietary intervention that occur in order to maintain weight at its baseline level, but are maladaptive if an individual is attempting to lose weight. 
AT is a result of alterations in hypothalamic neuro-hormonal circuitry resulting from obesity. Permanent changes in the regulation of body weight, energy expenditure, appetite, satiety and higher cognitive responses to food occur in the obese individual in response to weight loss. This is mediated by the central melanocortin pathway which interfaces with peripheral organs via the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous system, leptin, adiponectin, ghrelin, insulin, glucagon and thyroid stimulating hormone, amongst others. 
It is not clear whether adaptive thermogenesis in response to calorie restriction requires a period of sustained dietary restriction to develop or will occur with even very brief energy restriction. 
An intermittent or interrupted schedule of fasting, compared with a regular schedule of daily restriction, may attenuate the development of adaptive thermogenesis in response to a calorie restricted diet. 

Primary Objective: To compare changes in resting energy expenditure in response to 6 weeks of intermittent or continuous calorie restriction.

Secondary Objectives: To compare changes in the following parameters between treatment arms over the 6-week intervention period: fasting glucose, HbA1C &amp; fasting lipids, weight, body composition, TSH, FT4, FT3, leptin, adiponectin, ghrelin, satiety, hunger, dietary adherence, physical activity level &amp; diet composition. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Ethics ref: 16/NTA/208</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jeremy Krebs</name>
      <address>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902
Postcode 6242
</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8062140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jeremy.krebs@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brian Corley</name>
      <address>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Wellington
Private Bag 7902
Postcode 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8062140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brian.corley@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brian Corley</name>
      <address>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Wellington
Private Bag 7902
Postcode 6242</address>
      <phone>+ 64 275858589</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brian.corley@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brian Corley</name>
      <address>Endocrine Diabetes and Research Centre
Wellington Hospital
Wellington
Private Bag 7902
Postcode 6242</address>
      <phone>+ 64 275858589</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brian.corley@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>