<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367946">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000423516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>mDiabetes  a Large Diabetes Prevention Text Messaging Initiative in India</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adult consumers in India, does receiving text messages, when compared to not receiving messages, improve health behaviors known to prevent diabetes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes Prevention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Over 62 million individuals have been diagnosed with diabetes in India, creating a significant public health problem. India, a country with approximately 900 million mobile phone subscribers, is an optimal location to test effects of large-scale mHealth interventions to address burdensome chronic diseases. Arogya Worlds mDiabetes program, a diabetes prevention text-messaging program among one million consumers from all over India, looked at the effectiveness of text messages in encouraging health behaviors known to prevent diabetes. 

The current study employs a non-randomized, prospective, parallel cohort design to test the impact of text messages on health behavior change.  The study had two arms   Experimentals and Controls. Experimentals were about 900 Nokia mobile phone users who opted in  to receive 56 diabetes prevention text messages in their choice of 12 languages, while Controls (N=900)  received no text messages or contact during the 6 month intervention period.  

The frequency of text messages was as follows - one a day for the first 6 days, then twice a week for the rest of the weeks, up to 6 months.  The content of the messages was different - some described how big a problem diabetes was in India, others  that there were medical studies that showed that diabetes was preventable with lifestyle changes, that healthy living included increasing physical activity and improving diets.  And the messages went on to cover how to incorporate physical activity into everyday lives, and also encouraged consumers to eat more fruits and vegetables and limit oily and sugary foods.  

All participants were surveyed by phone at baseline and 6 months to assess a selection of health behaviors.

The study showed encouraging results - 35% of the experimental group compared to 21% in the control group reported positively changing more than one health behavior (p&lt;.001). 

This study shows that large-scale text message based diabetes prevention interventions have the potential to be an effective option for population level health behavior change. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Consumers from all over India who had non-Nokia mobile phones and did not get our text messages</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in adoption of healthy lifestyles, known to prevent diabetes, as measured by comparing self reported behavior change in Experimentals and Control parallel cohorts of adult consumers in India

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Health behaviour in both Experimentals and Controls was assessed before intervention began and at six months, when intervention was completed, by asking 600 plus responders from each group, a set of questions. For eg - What foods they ate. How many fruits and vegetables they ate a day. Whether they exercised regularly.  And whether they consistently avoided eating fried foods etc.    </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Among non-responders, do text messages improve intent to change behavior?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Health behaviour in both Experimentals and Controls was assessed as mentioned above, before intervention began and at six months, when intervention was completed, by asking 600 plus responders from each group, a set of questions and then further questioning the non-responders about when they intended to make the change.  

For eg - For those who answered No to the question - Do you exercise currently, we asked the question -Are you considering beginning to exercise or starting any physical activity? And gave them choices of 
i. yes, in 30 days, 
ii. yes in six months 
iiii. not very soon.  

Those who answered yes, in 30 days, were then included in further analysis for intent to change behavior.    
   </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Are there any differences in responses to text messages among rural versus urban consumers, and North Indian versus South Indian consumers?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Health behaviour in both Experimentals and Controls was assessed as mentioned above, before intervention began and at six months, when intervention was completed, by asking 600 plus responders from each group, a set of questions about the foods they ate and the physical activity they engaged in.  

The data were then subsequently further analyzed by location ie based on whether the responder came from a rural location or an urban location, or North or South India.   
 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Experimental  Having Nokia mobile phone  (series 30 or 40) with Nokia Life Platform and opting-in for Diabetes channel

Controls  Adult consumers with non-Nokia mobile phones  
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Consumers below age 18 years were excluded.  Non-subscribers of Nokia Life Health channel were also excluded.   </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The current study was designed to detect a 10% difference between groups with 80% power and  90% confidence . In absence of reliable estimates on the indicators of interest, a p value of 50% was assumed which produced a sample size estimate of 384 for each group. Assuming about a 15% rate of being lost to follow up and to distinguish differences between a rural and urban sample, the objective was to recruit at least 450 participants for each group.  We doubled the number to be able to study rural and urban consumer responses.  

All participant survey results collected at baseline were included in the analyses. Post-intervention surveys were matched to baseline surveys on phone number and demographic data. All surveys were included in the baseline analyses, but only matched surveys were included in the longitudinal analysis. 

Chi-square tests were performed to detect group differences in baseline measures and retention as well as group differences in the ability to reach a level of behavior change during the intervention. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>8/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/07/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1800</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Arogya World </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>23W651 Hobson Rd, Naperville IL 60540</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arogya World </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>23W651 Hobson Road
Naperville IL 60540</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Johnson &amp; Johnson (Lifescan Inc.)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>One Johnson &amp; Johnson Plaza
New Brunswick, New Jersey 08933</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Aetna </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Aetna International | 151 Farmington Ave, Hartford, CT 06156</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Nokia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress> # 2A, 5th Floor, Jupiter Block, Prestige Technology Park, Kadabeesanahalli, Marathalli-Sarjapur Outer Ring Road, 
Bangalore - 560103 

Nokia India used to be at this address when we did our study.  The mobile phone business was subsequently sold to one company and the Nokia Life business to yet another.   </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>India</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Emory University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Emory University

1518 Clifton Rd NE

Atlanta, Georgia 30322</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Public Health Foundation of India </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>ISID Campus
4 Institutional Area
Vasant Kunj
New Delhi  110070</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>India</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Madras Diabetes Research Foundation</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>No 4, Conran Smith Road, 
Gopalapuram,
Chennai - 600 086</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>India</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In India, there are more than 900 million mobile subscribers.

 m-health, defined as integration of mobile telecommunication technology in the health arena, has been successfully used as a behavior change communication medium in India : health related information delivered in the form of text messages via short message service (SMS), or as pictures through mobile phones, has effectively altered the knowledge, attitudes and behaviors of participants in fields  such as for breast self-examination, oral health or HIV/AIDS.

This mobile phone based text messaging intervention is designed to address the benefits of changing lifestyle to prevent diabetes and to impact processes of change with greatest attention for people in the 'contemplation' to 'action' stages. This trial aims to test the efficacy of an SMS campaign to bring about behavior change known to prevent diabetes.  The text messages are to be delivered in 12 languages over 6 months to about 900 participants (urban and rural) who have Nokia mobile phones and have subscribed to Nokia Life Health channels.  Behavior change will be assessed by pre-post comparisons in those who received the text messages as well as those (controls) who did not.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Late breaking abstract and poster presented at World Diabetes Congress, December 2013.  
http://arogyaworld.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/IDF_2013_mDiabetes_Poster.pdf 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Centre for Chronic Disease Control Institutional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Tower #4, C-9 Commercial Complex, 
Vasant Kunj, New Delhi 110070</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CCDC_IEC_12_2012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>India</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Monika Arora</name>
      <address>Monika Arora, Ph.D.
Director: Health Promotion
&amp;
Adjunct Associate Professor
Public Health Foundation of India
ISID Campus
4 Institutional Area
Vasant Kunj
New Delhi  110070


</address>
      <phone>Phone: +91 11 49566000; </phone>
      <fax>Fax: +91 11 49566063,</fax>
      <email>Monika.arora@phfi.org</email>
      <country>India</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nalini Saligram</name>
      <address>Arogya World 
23W651 Hobson Road
Naperville IL 60540</address>
      <phone>+1 630 637 8923</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nalini@arogyaworld.org</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sandhya Ramalingam</name>
      <address>34B, Dream Meadows Layout, 
ITPL Road   Bangalore - 560 0066</address>
      <phone>+91 988 606 1600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sandhya@arogyaworld.org</email>
      <country>India</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nalini Saligram</name>
      <address>23W651 Hobson Road
Naperville IL 60540</address>
      <phone>+1 630 637 8923</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nalini@arogyaworld.org</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>