<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368051">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000249550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Antibiotics in acute diverticulitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised double-blind placebo-controlled trial to evaluate the effect of antibiotics on length of hospital stay in uncomplicated acute diverticulitis in a tertiary hospital setting.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-5630</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute diverticulitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will receive intravenous antibiotics followed by oral antibiotics.

Intravenous regimen (to commence following CT confirmation of uncomplicated AD, until afebrile for 24 hours)
Cefuroxime 750mg intravenous, every 8 hours
Metronidazole 500mg intravenous, every 8 hours

Oral antibiotics (on discharge or once afebrile for 24 hours)
Augmentin 625mg per oral, three times a day for 5-7 days
-patients will be telephoned at 30 days and adherence will be examined at this time</interventions>
    <comparator>Initial intravenous placebo (containing lactose for colour), followed by tablet placebo (placebo manufactured by external laboratory)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge from index admission</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient symptom score (Global Symptom Score) and pain scores (on a scale of 1-10 as recorded by nursing staff)
-from patient medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 48 hours in hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Readmission
-from patient medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for repeat imaging (CT scan)
-from patient medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout index admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality
-from patient medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>During index admission and 1 month following</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>serum markers of inflammation
-from patient medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout index admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of complications (need for operation or percutaneous drainage)
-from patient medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout index admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Age &gt; 18 years.
2.	Current inpatient under the General Surgery service
3.	Diagnosed with uncomplicated acute diverticulitis on CT scan within 24 hours of admission
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Pregnancy.
2.	Previous allergic reaction with cefuroxime, metronidazole or amoxicillin/clavulanic acid use
3.	Steroid or immunomodulator use for more than 5 days prior to presentation
4.	Greater than 1 week of regular,  non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug use prior to presentation
5.	Inflammatory bowel disease
6.	ASA of 4 or greater
7.	CT evidence of complicated disease
8.	Meets criteria for a diagnosis of SIRS
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrollment - Upon confirming the diagnosis of AD, brief review of the patient’s notes will be undertaken to ensure that the patient is eligible based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria. Potential study participants will be approached in person by the study investigator and if convenient, a brief summary of the intended research will be given. If the patient is open to taking part in the study, a more detailed overview will be given. 

Allocation will occur centrally at the hospital pharmacy.</concealment>
    <sequence>Screened patients who consent to enrolment in this study will be randomised, with the aim of allowing allocation to the antibiotic and placebo groups in a 1:1 ratio. The actual process of patient randomisation will be achieved using a computer-based random number generator. Heterogeneity will be dealt with by the randomisation process, and post hoc stratification analyses will be undertaken as a secondary outcome.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study investigators have undertaken a retrospective review to enable a well-informed power calculation for this randomised control trial. This review examined all admissions for AD at Auckland City hospital over an 18 month period. There were 204 cases of uncomplicated cases of AD during this time, with a mean length of stay of 88.9hrs (SD 70.6) per episode. 20 of these patients were subsequently found to have had poor outcomes (longer hospital stay or need for procedural intervention). We aim to identify the patients who are at high risk for poorer outcomes through our exclusion criteria, which will slightly reduce our pool of potentially eligible patients.
Using these data, a power calculation was performed in order to determine the number of participants required in order to determine non-inferiority of the intervention. The distribution of these data was symmetric under a logarithmic (base 10) transformation (with SD 0.245).
A change in length of stay of 24 hours would be clinically significant for the patient and for hospital services. Assuming a non-inferiority margin of 24 hours, an independent-samples t-test on log-transformed length of stay data and common SD of 0.245 it was determined that 89 patients would be required in each arm to achieve 80% power and one-sided alpha-error of 0.025 . 
We expect the rate of participation to be modest given that this is a trial of acutely unwell patients. After taking rate of participation and the potential for patients to drop-out into account, we aim to recruit 94 patients in each arm  188 patients in total. As the retrospective study of a single centre carried out over 18 months yielded 204 potentially eligible patients, this is a feasible number to recruit over the same study duration over 3 centres, even after accounting for patients who will be excluded for being at increased risk of poorer outcomes.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>188</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ground Floor, 89 Grafton Road
P O Box 110139, Auckland Hospital
Auckland 1148</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Colorectal Surgical Society of Australia and New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 6, 9 Church Street, Hawthorn, VIC 3122, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Auckland City Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>2 Park Road, Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim
To determine whether the administration of an intravenous and oral antibiotic regimen is more effective than a placebo for reducing length of hospital stay, pain and symptoms of uncomplicated AD.

Hypothesis
That patients given the placebo will have a similar resolution of symptoms (as measured by patient reported scores) as those treated with antibiotics without an increase in recurrence or complications.

Primary Objective
To determine whether antibiotic administration results in a difference in length of hospital stay when compared to a placebo.

Secondary Objectives
To determine whether antibiotic administration results in a difference in; patient-reported symptom scores, length of stay, occurrence of complications, readmission within 30 days, symptoms of AD, and serum markers of inflammation when compared with patients receiving placebo. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 1010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Bissett</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
University of Auckland
ACH Support Building
Level 12, Room 12.085
Park Road, Grafton
Auckland 1023
</address>
      <phone>+64 21 347 442</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>i.bissett@auckland.ac.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebekah Jaung</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
University of Auckland
ACH Support Building
Level 12, Room 12.085
Park Road, Grafton
Auckland 1023
</address>
      <phone>+64 21 134 4600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebekahjaung@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebekah Jaung</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
University of Auckland
ACH Support Building
Level 12, Room 12.085
Park Road, Grafton
Auckland 1023
</address>
      <phone>+6421 134 4600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebekahjaung@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>