<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370046">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000128493p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validation Of A Circadian Heart Rate Monitoring Device For Use To Measures Stress Levels In A Convenience Sample of Healthy Adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Validation Of A Circadian Heart Rate Monitoring Device For Use To Measures Stress Levels In A Convenience Sample of Healthy Adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Aim to assess whether a currently available heart rate monitoring device worn over a 24 hour period thus measuring circadian heart rate (CHR) patterns, can provide objective indications of stress. The heart rate monitoring device is a small device worn with a strap covering the skin over the chest region. CHR will be monitored on 4 separate occasions: twice in the first week and twice again after an interval 2-3 weeks. At each assessment point the device is worn for 24 hours. Measures of CHR will be compared with data obtained from self-report mood and stress tools to evaluate consistency of results, and cross-sectional and predictive validity. Participants will be asked to download an App that contains the self-report questionnaires and provides feedback on the heart rate recordings.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of stress levels using CHR patterns derived from a participant ECG data file recorded on the 'Zephyr HxM Smart Heart Rate Monitor'. This device records the participants posture, accelerometer data, and ECG signal. The participant wears this device for up to 24 hours at each assessment point. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline measurement involves 2 participant recordings with ECG data file obtained from the Zephyr Monitor. Another two recordings 3 weeks after first assessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-report levels of stress through DASS-21 and the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS; Cohen, 1988)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants current emotional wellbeing assessed using the Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-being Scale (Tennant et al., 2007)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>User acceptability of App assessed by 5-point Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Screening for major depressive disorder, panic disorder, psychotic disorders, generalised anxiety disorder and posttraumatic stress disorder with the M.I.N.I. International Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I.). Participants who score in the severe range for stress, depression or anxiety on the DASS-21, as well as randomly selected participants (for a total n=50) will be asked to attend another face-to-face meeting for this screening interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity assessed using the Brief Physical activity assessment scale (Marshall et al., 2005)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleeping patterns assessed using the Bergen Insomnia Scale Pallesen et al., 2008)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotional resilience assessed using the Brief Resilience Scale (Smith et al., 2008)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood symptoms assessed using DASS-21 (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety assessed using the DASS-21 (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comfort of wearing Zephyr Monitor using a 5-point Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Physically healthy individuals aged 18 years and older
Access to a smartphone:
1) Android version 4.4 or later	
2) iOS 8 or later</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Individuals who have difficulty reading and understanding English
2) Regular/severe alcohol and/or other substance abuse.
3) Prescribed medication with a recognized cardiac effect (e.g. beta-blockers, thyroxine, clozapine)
4) History and/or evidence of coronary heart disease
5) Physical illness with a recognized effect on heart rate
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>In Calculating the degrees of freedom (df) we have:
the observation  - algorithm result which has 3 levels (normal-mild, moderate, and severe)
the expected  expert rating which has 3 levels (normal-mild, moderate, and severe)
For Chi-squared, df = (3-1) x (3-1) = 4

In Calculating the effect size we need to observe the hypothesised difference between subjects with moderate stress compared to those with severe stress (10% versus 25%) as opposed to (33% versus 33%) which would require an effect size of 0.46. 

Given this medium effect size, in conjunction with an alpha of 0.05 and power of 0.95, with 4 degrees of freedom would require a sample size of 88.

As these 88 participants represent only 35% of the general population, in order to achieve appropriate power for delineating between stress groups, requires a sample size of 88 x 1/0.35 = 251.4. Therefore this study requires a sample of 252 participants, which we expect to lose 10% to natural attrition, and 10% due to unusable data due to ECG recording artifact, we request permission to recruit up to 300 participants.


The circadian heart rate output metrics will be compared with self-report data as follows:

1.	Cross-sectionally against the measures of stress depression and anxiety (quantitative discrete variables), using agreement statistics for dichotomous variables and ROC curves for continuous variables. The analysis would include a comparison of two quantitative variables  with the algorithm providing a measure of the degree of variation from normal (ie. A continuous variable with a true zero) and compare this to the outcome from the self-reports (DASS-21 etc)- (quantitative discrete variable). This would permit analyses using correlation or regression models.

2.	For categorical algorithm outputs (Normal-mild, Moderate, Serious) and self-report measures are quantitative then we could employ ROC curves to identify appropriate cutoffs with the self-report tools. This will allow us to maximize the predictive ability of the algorithm by identifying which cutoffs give the best results in regards to the sensitivity and specificity for the each of the levels.

3.	For categorical algorithm outputs and MINI categories (interview) we will complete Chi Sqd  goodness of fit, or a multinomial logistic regression.

4.	Longitudinally by validating changes in the participants CHR status with changes in self-reported symptoms via scales such as the DASS-21. As we will have continuous algorithm output, we complete a correlation/regression analysis.

5.	General demographic questions - factors such as age and gender will be analysed with ordinary parametric tools.

6.	User acceptability, feedback response and comfort ratings will be collected through questions embedded in the App.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medibio Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Medibio Ltd. 
Suite 605, Level 6
50 Clarence Street
Sydney NSW 2000
[GPO Box 4492, Sydney NSW 2001] </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medibio Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Medibio Ltd.
Suite 605, Level 6
50 Clarence Street
Sydney NSW 2000
[GPO Box 4492, Sydney NSW 2001] </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>According to the most recent Stress and Wellbeing Survey, 35% of Australians experience a significant level of distress in their lives and just over a quarter report having moderate to extremely severe depression symptoms. Unfortunately, the majority of sufferers do not seek help for their stress. When they do, Australians are tend to approach family and friends, and only 15% report seeking help from a psychologist or other mental health specialist. Some of the reluctance to engage in help-seeking is related to the stigma of the perception of not coping, whilst some is also related to the perception of malingering or feigning illness.
There is a key issue in this context. Whilst the use of pen and paper/technology based questionnaires is commonplace to screen for stress there are concerns over their false positive rate and predictive ability. Measures of heart rate variability (HRV), the beat-to-beat temporal changes in the heart rate (HR), may provide an alternative for stress assessment. These beat-to-beat changes are commonly used as a quantitative marker depicting the activity of the autonomic nervous system (ANS), thus related to mental stress. It has been suggested that changes in HR over 24 hours, or circadian heart rate (CHR) changes, may present adjunct information for stress assessment as circadian dysregulation is present in varying degrees in all psychiatric illnesses. As such, it has been proposed that HR profiling algorithms might provide an objective and predictive measure of stress and inform the likelihood of stress becoming a clinical illness.
This study aims to assess whether a currently available HR monitoring device, worn over 24 hours, thus measuring CHR, can provide objective indications of stress. CHR will be monitored 4 times: twice in the first week and twice again after 2-3 weeks. Measures of CHR will be compared with data obtained from self-report measures to evaluate consistency of results and cross-sectional and predictive validity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road 
Eastwood 
South Australia 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Player</name>
      <address>Medibio Ltd
MLC Centre
Suite 36, Level 56 
19-29 Martin Place,
Sydney, NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 419 906 999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.player@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Player</name>
      <address>Medibio Ltd
MLC Centre
Suite 36, Level 56 
19-29 Martin Place,
Sydney, NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 419 906 999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.player@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Player</name>
      <address>Medibio Ltd
MLC Centre
Suite 36, Level 56 
19-29 Martin Place,
Sydney, NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 419 906 999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.player@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Ariane Dahlheimer</name>
      <address>MLC Centre
Suite 36, Level 56 
19-29 Martin Place,
Sydney, NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 422077914</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.dahlheimer@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>