<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370727">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000855426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of anesthetic management using bispectral index monitorization on postoperative agitation in pediatric anesthesia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of anesthetic management using bispectral index monitorization on postoperative agitation in pediatric anesthesia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>postoperative agitation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions> The standard anesthesia protocol  will consist of oral premedication with midazolam (0.5 mg/kg) followed by an inhaled induction with sevofurane 8% and placement of a peripheral IV cannula. Fentanyl 1 to 1.5 microgram/kg and rocuronium 0.5 to 0.6 mg/kg will be given before intubation. After intubation, the patients will be allocated into two groups randomly. Maintenance of anesthesia will be accomplished by titrating sevofurane (between 0.5% to 3.0%) in a background of 50% air in O2. The patients in Group 1 will receive routine anesthasia while the ones in Group 2 will receive anesthesia in an adjusted manner, with the BIS values between 45-55. Patients in Group 2 will be monitored with use of bispectral index and the level of anesthesia will be adjusted according to the results of the measurements. BIS monitorization will be carried out by the same anesthetist with minimum 5 years experience in pediatric anaesthesia, Bispectral Index Scale monitoring is used to prevent intraoperative awakening or awareness and to provide an accurate titration of the anesthesia agents to promote faster recovery from anesthesia.  BIS monitoring involves for participants,  small monitoring device placed across participant's forehead throughout procedure.  Many clinical studies have shown that the administration of anesthetic agents under the guidance of BIS monitoring
has allowed for more effective drug use, faster recovery from anesthesia, shorter time to extubation, and better recovery.. The BIS is displayed number between 0 and 100, with 4555 being suitable for surgical anesthesia. Treating anaesthetist decides based on their clinical discretion how and by how much anaesthesia will be titrated if the BIS value drops out of the range of 45-55 Only patints in group 2 will be assessed with BIS. </interventions>
    <comparator>Deepness of anesthesia will be monitored traditionally for patients in Group 1, regarding the clinical findings (blood pressure, heart rate, pupil diameter, absence or presence of spontaneous respiration).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agitation, assessed using Faces, Legs, Activity, Cry and Consolability (FLACC) </outcome>
      <timepoint>The time period for development of agitations, 
FLACC will be assessed at 1st, 5th, 10th, 15th, 30th, 45th and 60th minutes after completion of anesthesia.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioral Pain Assessment Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Behavioral Pain Assessment Scale will be assessed at 1st, 5th, 10th, 15th, 30th, 45th and 60th minutes after completion of anesthesia.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative Agitation Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative Agitation Scale will be assessed at 1st, 5th, 10th, 15th, 30th, 45th and 60th minutes after completion of anesthesia.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total time to stay in postoperative care unit will be recorded by using review of patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Total time to stay in postoperative care unit will be recorded at discharge from postoperative care unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The patients who will undergo elective surgery under general anesthesia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>7</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who undergo adenoidectomy and toncillectomy
Patients with mental retardation or neurologic disorders

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Afyonkarahisar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Serdar Kokulu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Afyon Kocatepe University, School of Medicine, Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation 
Afyon Kocatepe Universtitesi Tip Fak端ltesi Ali Cetinkaya Kampusu Afyon-Izmir karayolu 8.km 03200 Afyonkarahisar Turkey</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Afyon Kocatepe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Afyon Kocatepe University, Ali Cetinkaya Kampusu Izmir Karayolu Street Number 41 03200 Afyonkarahisar</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One hundred patients (aging 2-7 years) to undergo elective surgery under general anesthesia will be included in the study. The patients will be randomly allocated into two groups. Both patients will be anesthetised using standard methods. In Group 1, deepness of the anesthesia will be measured regarding the heart rate and arterial blood pressure. Doses for inhalation anesthetics will be adjusted according to the vital findings of the patients. In Group 2, deepness of anesthesia will be determined using Bispectral Index monitorization (BIM). Doses for inhalation anesthetics will be determined according to the findings obtained in BIM. Postoperative agitation levels of the patients will be assessed using the Face, Legs, Activity, Cry and Consolability (FLACC) scale and the Postoperative Agitation Scale. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Isparta Suleyman Demirel University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>SERDAR KOKULU</name>
      <address>Afyon Kocatepe University School of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Afyon Kocatepe Universitesi Tip Fak端ltesi Ali Cetinkaya Kampusu Afyon-Izmir karayolu 8.km 03200 Afyonkarahisar Turkey</address>
      <phone>+90 272 2345112</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serdarkokulu@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Serdar Kokulu</name>
      <address>Afyon Kocatepe University School of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Afyon Kocatepe Universitesi Tip Fak端ltesi Ali Cetinkaya Kampusu Afyon-Izmir karayolu 8.km 03200 Afyonkarahisar Turkey</address>
      <phone>+90 272 234 5112</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serdarkokulu@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Serdar Kokulu</name>
      <address>Afyon Kocatepe University School of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Afyon Kocatepe Universtitesi Tip Fak端ltesi Ali Cetinkaya Kampusu Afyon-Izmir karayolu 8.km 03200 Afyonkarahisar Turkey</address>
      <phone>+90 272 2345112</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serdarkokulu@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>