<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82673">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/03/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000198325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Global body posture in temporomandibular joint (TMJ) disorder patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Relationship between global body posture in temporomandibular joint disorder patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>TMJ DISORDERS</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ten subjects were interviewed about presence of parafunctional habits, signs and symptoms, through a questionnaire and the use of the Visual Analogue Scale for pain. Postural body alignment was evaluated in anterior, posterior and both lateral views, and this evaluation was confirmed with the use of digital images. Footprints measurement was obtained using a Harris Mat and characteristics of the longitudinal plantar arches were obtained, all during one assessment. These datas were compared to a control group - sixteen healthy volunteer women, with matched age, weight and height.</interventions>
    <comparator>no treatment / comparing with subjects without any TMJ disorder</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of postural deviation on pelvis, lumbar and thoracic spines, head and mandibulae on the TMJ disorder group, observed  through postural evaluation in anterior, posterior and both lateral views, and with the use of digital images.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After answering the interview for signs and symptons, in a single assessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of local pain on TMJ on the TMJ disorder group, through a signs and symptons interview and with the use of the Visual Analogue Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Signs and symptoms (including pain) was checked through the interview, during the single assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>There were no diferences on parafunctional habits evaluation, checked through the interview, neither on footprints measurements, using a Harris Mat.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Presence of parafunctional habits was checked through the interview. Footprints measurement was obtained right after the postural evaluation. All datas were taken in a single assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>presence of unilateral anterior disc dispacement diagnosed by a pos-graduated student dentist.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any trauma history, anatomical deformities and fractures on the skeletal system, hormonal alterations, orthopaedics or rheumatic diseases already diagnosed, three months pregnancy or more, neither previous TMD treatment in a period of 15 days before this initial assessment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sao Paulo - School of Dentistry</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>R Lineu Prestes, 2227 -  Cidade Universitaria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sao Paulo - School of Medicine</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>R Cipotanea 51 - Cidade Universitaria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study was to identify the relationship between the temporomandibular joint disc displacement and the global posture (plantar arches, lower limbs, pelvis and shoulder girdle, vertebral spine, head and mandibulae). The secondary purpose of the study was to identify the common signs and symptoms of TMJ disorder patients. The study hypothesis was that, on the group with temporomandibular disorder, the presence of postural deviations, signs and symptoms would be more evident,  which suggests a relationship between the disorder and the global posture. This data is important either for orthodontic or for physical therapy treatments.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paula Marie Hanai Akashi</name>
      <address>R Dr Martins de Oliveira 529 ap124B - Sao Paulo</address>
      <phone>55 11 30918426</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.akashi@usp.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paula Marie Hanai Akashi</name>
      <address>R Dr Martins de Oliveira 529 ap124B - Sao Paulo</address>
      <phone>55 11 30918426</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.akashi@usp.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>