<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335276">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000953033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ALPhA Study: Active Living and Physical Activity as modifiers of postprandial lipaemia and other risk factors of cardiovascular disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of continuous and intermittent physical activity on postprandial lipaemia in sedentary men and women</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ALPhA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postprandial Lipaemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>inflammation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Postprandial Glycaemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomized cross over study, in which, participants will  complete the following three, 9 h trials, each separated by at least 7 days: 1) Physical Activity (PA) trial: participants will walk  on the treadmill at 60 % of maximal oxygen consumption (VO2max) for 30 min prior to consuming the first meal replacement beverage (MRB) then remained seated for the remainder of the trial; 2) Active Living (AL) trial:  participants will walk on the treadmill at the same speed and incline as PA, for 1 min and 40 s every 30 min throughout the trial; and 3) Sedentary (SE) trial: participants will remain seated for the duration.  In each trial participants will be fed three MRBs, each providing 0.46 g fat, 0.54 g protein and 1.12 g carbohydrate per kg at 60, 240 and 420 min.</interventions>
    <comparator>No physical activity -The sedentary trial is the control condition.  Participants will remain seated for the duration of the 9 hr trial, and be fed three meal replacement beverages each providing 0.46 g fat, 0.54 g protein and 1.12 g carbohydrate per kg at 60, 240 and 420 min.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial triglyceride response will be assessed by collecting blood samples at the time points listed below.  Concentrations of triglycerides will be measured in each of these samples using enzymatic colorimetric methods</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30, 45, 60, 120, 180, 210, 225, 240, 300, 360, 420, 450, 465, 480, 540 min after consumption of the first meal</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial glucose response will be assessed by collecting blood samples at the time points listed below.  Concentrations of blood glucose will be measured in each of these samples using enzymatic colorimetric methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30, 45, 60, 120, 180, 210, 225, 240, 300, 360, 420, 450, 465, 480, 540 min after consumption of the first meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial insulin response will be assessed by collecting blood samples at the time points listed below.  Concentrations of blood insulin will be measured in each of these samples using an electrochemiluminescent immunoassay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 30, 45, 60, 120, 180, 210, 225, 240, 300, 360, 420, 450, 465, 480, 540 min after consumption of the first meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure will measured using a sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 60, 120, 180, 240,  300, 360, 420, 480, 540 min after consumption of the first meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Substrate utilization will be measured by indirect calorimetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 60, 120, 180, 240,  300, 360, 420, 480, 540 min after consumption of the first meal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy men and women who do not regularly undertake more than 3 hours of physical activity a week.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previously diagnosed cardiovascular disease, diabetes, metabolic disease, high cholesterol or high blood pressure
Resting blood pressure greater than 140/90
History of venous thrombosis or any abnormality of blood clotting
Smoking
Medication known to influence lipid or carbohydrate metabolism</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will initially attend a screening visit at which blood pressure and fasting lipid will be measured.  If blood pressure and lipids are within the acceptable range participants will complete an aerobic capacity test (VO2max).  Participants will then complete the three trial conditions in a predetermined randomized order. The randomization code will be sealed in opaque envelopes.  An envelope will be opened prior to each participant's first session, and the code contained within will dictate the order the interventions will be completed by that participant</concealment>
    <sequence>STATA software will be used to generate the randomization sequence for the order the interventions will be performed for each participant.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/04/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>4/10/2010</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/10/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>65</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tracy Perry</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
New Zealand
9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nancy Rehrer</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
New Zealand
9054</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Prolonged elevation of fat (triglyceride) concentrations in the blood after a meal increases the risk of developing cardiovascular disease.  Moderate to vigorous physical activity is highly effective at lowering the concentration of fat in the blood after a meal.  However, studies in rats suggest that frequent sessions of low level activity performed throughout the day may be just as effective as a single session of more intense exercise at lowering the concentration of fat in the blood after a meal.  
The aim of this study is to compare the effects of one session of 30 minutes of moderate intensity physical activity, to the effects of performing one minute and 40 seconds of low-level physical activity every 30 minutes throughout the day on concentrations of triglyceride, glucose and insulin</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>M C Peddie, J L Bone, N J Rehrer, C M Skeaff, A R Gray, and T L Perry (2013) Breaking prolonged sitting reduces postprandial glycemia in healthy, normal-weight adults: a randomized crossover trial. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 98 (2); 358-366</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
New Zealand
9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/09/0239</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tracy Perry</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
New Zealand
9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7508</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tracy.perry@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Meredith Peddie</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
New Zealand
9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5673</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meredith.peddie@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Meredith Peddie</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin
New Zealand
9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5673</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meredith.peddie@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tracy Perry</name>
      <address>Department of Human Nutrition University of Otago PO Box 56 Dunedin New Zealand 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7508</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tracy.perry@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>