<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336249">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000119998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Characterising the nature, and clinical significance of body and limb movements during adult sleep using multi-site accelerometry</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Characterising the nature, and clinical significance of body and limb movements during adult sleep using a continuous multisite accelerometry system (CMAS) versus standard polysomnogram indices in patients undergoing diagnostic polysomnograms</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Periodic leg movement syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive sleep apnoes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>insomnia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>parasomnia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A continuous multisite accelerometry system will be applied in addition to conventional polysomnogram channels, for the duration of a overnight polysomnogram (typically 6-9 hours). 

Each of the 50 participants will be studied for the duration of a single overnight polysomnogram. 

The duration to complete all 50 studies is anticipated to be approximately 12 months.

The continuous multisite accelerometry system consists of 3 separate units, each containing a digital triaxial accelerometer:
 - One located on the patients wrist. This unit also has a lead with an additional accelerometer which will be taped to the participants middle finger
- One located on the participants  ankle. This unit also has a lead with an additional accelerometer which will be taped to the participants middle finger
 - One located on the participants chest (just below sternal notch) 

Each unit continuously measures acceleration, and transmits data via a low power radio link to a logging PC.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between amplitude of movement detected using accelerometry with amplitude of movement using tibialis anterior EMG</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of PSG (T=0)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between amplitude of movement detected using accelerometry with amplitude of movement using piezo electric movement sensors</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of PSG (T=0)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under ROC curve for predicting arousal based on movement observed using accelerometry, compared to clinician scored arousal based on full PSG</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of PSG (T=0)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Area under ROC curve for predicting periodic leg movement based on movement observed using accelerometry, compared to clinician scored using EMG and piezo gauges</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of PSG (T=0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Clinician identification of movement artefact in PSG channels will be compared with prediction of movement artefact using accelerometry data alone</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of PSG (T=0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Indicies derived from accelerometry will be compared to standardised surveys and PSG based measures (sleep efficiency) in their ability to estimate quality of sleep</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of PSG (T=0)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients referred to The Prince Charles Hospital Sleep Service for an overnight diagnostic polysomnogram for any reason</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Women who are pregnant
- People who are highly dependant on medical care
- Perople with degenerative neuromuscular disorders such as Parkinson's hisease and Huntington's chorea where a resting involuntary tremor is present
-People, who as observed on the PSG, have an uninterpretable EEG</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4032</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane, Queensland, 4072
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland New Staff Research Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane, Queensland, 4072
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road, Chermside, Queensland, 4032</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The general aim of this research is to investigate whether continuous tri-axial accelerometry is a usfull tool for the qunatification, and characterisation of movements during sleep in a clinical diagnosis setting. This research targets:
- Movements as a consequence of movement disorders (Such as Periodic Leg Movements During Sleep),
- Movements as a consequence of arousals during the night
- Movements as a conqequence of respiratory events during the night

50 adults attending The Princel Charles Hospital Sleep Service for a Diagnostic Polysomnogram (sleep study) will be recruited. In addition to the standard physiological channels recorded in a sleep study, Multiple accelerometers will be strategically placed on each subject (ankle and big toe, wrist and middle finger and central thorax).

Data will be analysed to determine whether:
- The amplitude of movements observed using accelerometry predict cortical arousal
- Continuous triaxial accelerometry may be used to automatically classify sleep from wake more accurately than commercial actigraphs
- Multisite accelerometry allows primary limb movements to be distinguished from gross body movements as a consequence of arousal or other events
- Indices of movement events correlate with qualtiy of life measures</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Rd., Chermside, Queensland, 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QPCH/27</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane, Queensland, 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010000961</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Philip Terrill</name>
      <address>The School of IT and Electrical Engineering
The University of Queensland
Brisbane, Queensland, 4077</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 8328</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33654 999</fax>
      <email>p.terrill@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Philip Terrill</name>
      <address>The School of IT and Electrical Engineering
The University of Queensland
Brisbane, Queensland, 4077</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 8328</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33654 999</fax>
      <email>p.terrill@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Philip Terrill</name>
      <address>The School of IT and Electrical Engineering
The University of Queensland
Brisbane, Queensland, 4077</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 8328</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33654 999</fax>
      <email>p.terrill@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>