<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371181">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001347459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> Does nutrition counselling combined with a cooking program improve blood vessel function for patients with vascular disease?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Creating efficiencies while improving effectiveness: A pilot evaluation of a student-led nutrition service for delaying progression of peripheral vascular disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral vascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomised to the intervention arm will attend a  student led nutrition service. The nutrition care process will be delivered in four stages, (1) an initial assessment (for both intervention and control), (2) an individualised 30 minute education session (intervention only), (3) a cooking skills and education program delivered via six sessions over 12 weeks (intervention only), and (4) review and discharge (for both intervention and control). 

The assessment will incorporate anthropometry (e.g. height, weight, waist circumference) and a diet history. Students will report their findings at a team meeting and then an individualised education session that focusses on realistic dietary modification to improve diet quality consistent with established evidence for preventing progression of PVD will occur. 

A cooking skills and education program will be delivered by a dietetic student under the supervision of an Accredited Practicing Dietitian, using a small group format (6-10 participants per group) fortnightly over 12 weeks with hands-on interactive sessions focussed on cooking skills, cooking methods, dietary fat and fibre, dietary sodium, antioxidants and the benefits of seasonal produce, energy balance and label reading, and dietary supplements.  Each session will be 2-3 hours duration and will consist of an education session followed by a hands-on cooking session and will finish with participants gathering to eat what has been cooked during the session, 
Attendance will be recorded for all cooking sessions, baseline and post-intervention clinic visits.
The cooking skills and education program will be evaluated post-program for changes in cooking skills, knowledge and confidence 

The review and discharge session will incorporate a review of improvements made, any questions arising from the cooking skills and education program will be addressed and strategies discussed to make changes long term and sustainable. The assessment, individualised education session and review/discharge session will be supervised by an academic Accredited Practising Dietitian of Flinders University who will progressively reduce their input as student competence increases. The cooking skills program will be supervised by an Accredited Practising Dietitian employed by SPROUT cooking school. 
Follow up
Peripheral vascular disease progressions will be monitor in all participants through a medical record audit. Any data on hospital admissions, revascularisation procedures and other related examinations and procedures (e.g. blood tests and angiogram results) will be extracted from medical records. 

1.	Laboratory assessment.
Fasting blood samples will be collected by a trained phlebotomist. Samples will be analysed for High Density Lipoprotein (HDL), Low Density Lipoprotein (LDL), triglycerides, total cholesterol, C-reactive protein, absolute neutrophils and lymphocytes. LDL-C concentrations will be calculated using the Friedewald equation.
2.	Other assessment (e.g. radiological).
Blood pressure (systolic and diastolic blood pressure) measurements will be taken using a sphygmomanometer. Flow mediated dilation tests will be conducted using a sphygmomanometer and ultrasound equipment. Both measurements and tests will be conducted by a trained researcher.  
3.	Monitoring adverse effects (e.g. emotional, psychological and physical): 
Staff will be required to undergo full immunisation screening and criminal history check to ensure no risk is placed to this vulnerable population group. Staff and participants will undergo an induction, consisting of occupational health and safety training prior to the cooking and nutrition classes at Sprout cooking school. As there is no pharmacological drug being tested in this research study, there are negligible chances of any adverse effect. Any harm to a participant should be reported to a member of the research team immediately. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the control group will undergo the initial assessment and the review and discharge as per the intervention group.  Apart from this, controls will receive standard/usual care which is an optional 30 minute group education session with a dietitian covering healthy eating for CVD and the provision of a list of available community-based cooking programs.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in flow-mediated dilatation which will be measured via ultrasound of the brachial artery following 5 minutes of occlusion. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diet quality will be assessed using a 7-day diet history collected by the student dietitian.  Dietary intake will be compared to the Australian Guide to Healthy Eating recommendations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>blood pressure will be measured using an electronic blood pressure monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in body weight will be assessed by weighing the patient using a stand-on electronic scales in light clothing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events.  Potential adverse events from the intervention include injuries sustained during the cooking program such as burns and cuts. These will be assessed using self-report from the participant and records kept in a diary by the research staff conducting the cooking program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Lipid Levels via venapuncture by a trained phlebotomist and analysed by the local pathology service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>C-reactive protein, Absolute neutrophils and lymphocyte count will be measured via venapuncture by a trained phlebotomist and analysed by the local pathology service to assess the inflammatory status of the participant</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clinical history consistent with Intermittent Claudication as determined by ABPI </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Lower limb ischaemic rest pain 
2. Clinical evidence of tissue loss e.g. ulcers 
3. Undergone arterial intervention in the proceeding 12 months 
4. Incompetent to provide own consent e.g. dementia, confusion, delirium
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the primary outcome of FMD, a sample size of 130 (66 per group) is estimated based on our own pilot data, previous literature and clinical experience that an absolute change of 2% in FMD is clinically meaningful. We aim to recruit 30% of the estimated sample size for this pilot feasibility study, n=40 (20 per group). Primary analysis for this study will be undertaken using intention-to-treat principles. Independent samples t-tests, Mann-Whitney U tests and Chi-square tests across the two groups will be undertaken as appropriate. Statistical significance will be set at p= 0.05. Feasibility outcomes will be reported as frequency (%) and qualitatively.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>28/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/01/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Repatriation Hospital - Daw Park</hospital>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5041 - Daw Park</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Michelle Miller</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Nutrition and Dietetics
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide
SA
5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Flinders University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2100
Adelaide
South Australia
5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Ian Spark</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dept Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park
SA
5042</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with peripheral vascular disease are a nutritionally vulnerable group of patients and current management strategies for addressing nutritional health are sub-optimal. The importance of good nutritional health in achieving optimal clinical outcomes is well established. 
This project will therefore implement an established student-led model of nutritional care to manage the unique nutritional requirements of patients with peripheral vascular disease.
 Our evaluation of this model of care in other patient groups has demonstrated improved satisfaction and outcomes from a student, clinician and patient perspective. Transferring this model of care to those with peripheral vascular disease has the potential to have similar outcomes and we have designed this project to specifically identify improvements in cardiovascular health. 
The primary aim of this pilot RCT is to determine the feasibility of implementing a 12 week student-led nutrition service, for adults with PVD attending the Southern Adelaide Local Health Network (SALHN) Vascular Surgery Claudication Clinic and observe any clinically and statistically significant improvements in the cardiovascular health and quality of life of participants who receive individualised nutritional advice compared to usual care. 
1.	Study design: 
This intervention will be a Randomised Controlled Trial, where participants will be allocated to either an intervention (n=20) or control group (n=20). 

Participants in the control group will receive usual care, where patients typically receive general nutrition advice from Vascular Surgery Consultant or Registrar and the option of attending a 30 minute group seminar by a Dietitian. 
The study will be of 12 weeks duration. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Research and Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park
SA
5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michelle Miller</name>
      <address>Nutrition and Dietetics
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide
SA
5001</address>
      <phone>61 409870065</phone>
      <fax>61 8 82046406</fax>
      <email>michelle.miller@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>michelle Miller</name>
      <address>Nutrition and Dietetics
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide
SA
5001</address>
      <phone>61 409870065</phone>
      <fax>61 8 82046406</fax>
      <email>michelle.muller@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michelle Miller</name>
      <address>Nutrition and Dietetics
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide
SA
5001</address>
      <phone>61 409870065</phone>
      <fax>61 8 82046406</fax>
      <email>michelle.miller@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jolene Thomas</name>
      <address>Nutrition and Dietetics
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide
5001</address>
      <phone>61 08 72218857</phone>
      <fax>61 08 8204 6406</fax>
      <email>jm.thomas@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>