<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373016">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000817347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>App-Based Supplemental Exercise During Inpatient Orthopaedic Rehabilitation Increases Activity Levels: A Pilot Randomised Control Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>App-Based Supplemental Exercise During Inpatient Orthopaedic Rehabilitation Increases Activity Levels: A Pilot Randomised Control Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1197-0568</utrn>
    <trialacronym>AERO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Joint Replacement
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Individuals admitted for orthopaedic rehabilitation randomised to either usual care orthopaedic program or to usual care with an App-based supplemental exercise program, delivered via an App downloaded to a tablet device (PTPal).

The intervention group receive supplementary exercise program designed by their treating therapist and uploaded to PTPal and accessed via a tablet device in addition to usual care. Participants  allocated to the intervention group were provided with a tablet device for the duration of their inpatient program. Both intervention and control group receive supplemental exercises but intervention group uses an app based program for delivery and monitoring of these exercises.

Exercise programs for the intervention participants were individually designed by the treating therapist. 

PTPal is a care delivery App that allows clinicians and therapists to send participating individuals digital prescriptions of exercises, activities and surveys, directly to the a  mobile or tablet device. 

Participants had a de-identified login created by the research team and an individualised exercise program was uploaded to a Royal Rehab Apple iPad Air 2 that was provided to the participants for the duration of their admission. The set programs for orthopaedic conditions were designed by the principal physiotherapy researcher in conjunction with the treating physiotherapy team. Exercise programs included the following exercise types; range of motion, stretching, strengthening and practice of everyday tasks e.g. walking or standing up. The time that participants logged onto their exercise account, repetitions undertaken and difficulties encountered were remotely monitored by the treating therapist and principal investigators. After allocation, the intervention participants received one session at the commencement of their program to learn to use the App and ongoing support to both groups was provided, as needed, to the participants by the research assistant.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group received usual care in addition to scheduled therapy. This included encouragement to undertake supplemental exercise, either with instructions on paper or verbally if the therapist chose to prescribe this. All control participants received a paper diary to record the amount and number of repetitions of supplemental exercise from the research team, which was collected by the research assistant on discharge. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative data obtained from survey designed specifically for this study and administered at the completion of inpatient rehabilitation to assess satisfaction with the App.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation unit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite quantitative data from App from intervention participants and diaries from controls regarding the amount of time, and number of repetitions in supplemental exercise.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation unit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6MWT</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total length of stay as assessed from a review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from inpatient rehabilitation unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>10MWT</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission and discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time Up and Go</outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission and discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total amount of inpatient therapy hours as assessed  from a review of inpatient physiotherapy timetables</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants were included if they were inpatients undergoing usual-care orthopaedic rehabilitation, aged over 18 years of age, able to consent, had been admitted with an orthopaedic diagnosis, and were willing to use or be educated on the use of the tablet device and had no medical contraindications to a supplemental exercise program. If the individual was unable to provide consent due to cognitive impairment defined as a Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) score less than 24/30, they were not approached to take part in the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Cognitive impairment
medical contraindication to supplemental exercise program</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants randomised according to a number drawn from a concealed box </concealment>
    <sequence>Consecutive numbers drawn from concealed box</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Independent T-Tests </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/01/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>17/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>24/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Rehabilitation Hospital - Coorabel/Moorong - Ryde</hospital>
    <postcode>2112 - Ryde</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Rehab Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>235 Morrison Rd Ryde NSW 2112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Rehab Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>235 Morrison Rd Ryde NSW 2112</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Macquarie University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences
G815 75 Talavera Rd
Macquarie University
NSW, 2109, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: To investigate whether an App-based supplemental exercise program in orthopaedic rehabilitation will be feasible and acceptable to participants, increase activity levels and improve functional outcomes.
Design: Single-centre, single-blind pilot randomised control trial 
Setting: Inpatient private general rehabilitation unit
Participants: Twenty individuals admitted for orthopaedic rehabilitation over four week duration. 
Intervention: Participants were randomised to receive supplemental exercise via an App (PTPalTM) on a tablet device additional to usual care or usual care alone. 
Main Outcome Measures: Primary outcome measures were participant satisfaction with App-based supplemental exercise, total repetitions of each activity and time in supplemental exercise programs. Secondary measures were 10 Metre Walk Test (10MWT); 6 Minute Walk Test (6MWT); Timed Up and Go (TUG); Functional Independence Measure and length of stay assessed by a blinded assessor. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>NSLHD Research Office
Level 13, Kolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/HAWKE/444</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373016-Letter - HREC FINAL approval - HREC Exec meeting OSS 12 December 2016 - RESP16297 (1).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tram Bui</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd Ryde NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9808 7215</fax>
      <email>tram.bui@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tram Bui</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd Ryde NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9808 7215</fax>
      <email>tram.bui@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tram Bui</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd Ryde NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9808 7215</fax>
      <email>tram.bui@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tram Bui</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd Ryde NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9808 7215</fax>
      <email>tram.bui@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>