<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372347">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000245392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of early motivational interviewing on post-stroke depressive symptoms: a pilot randomised controlled trial of the Good Mood Intervention program.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of early motivational interviewing on post-stroke depressive symptoms: a pilot randomised controlled trial of the Good Mood Intervention program.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil known</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Good Mood Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group patients will receive early motivational interviewing (MI), provided by facilitators (nurses or social workers) during the acute in-patient hospitalisation after presentation with stroke. Facilitators will have completed a full-day workshop and completed an online training module.
MI will comprise 3, 30-minute individual sessions, performed prior to hospital discharge from the acute episode.. Generally, the sessions will occur on 3 separate and consecutive days. The rationale for using multiple sessions is (a) due to the complexity of the problems of stroke and depression, and (b) there is a significant positive relationship between the amount of MI a person receives and treatment outcomes.
A summary of the 3 sessions follows:
1: Setting agenda and encouraging patient to talk about adjustment to stroke;
2: Eliciting realistic goals for recovery, and barriers to achieving goals; and,
3: Identifying ambivalence about achieving goals; supporting patients optimism and self-efficacy, and identifying solutions to problems.
Fidelity will be assessed for all facilitators on an individual basis after review of recorded interviews. Further training will be provided for facilitators who do not demonstrate appropriate technique for MI.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment is defined as the routine care provided by nursing, medical and allied health staff. Patients ordinarily receive, on an ad-hoc basis, technical brochures regarding depression after stroke from nurse clinicians.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Anxiety levels using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale.
Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale. Acta Psychiatricia Scandinavica 1983;67:361-70.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to intervention.
One-month and 3-months post-intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Depression levels using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale and Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ9).
Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale. Acta Psychiatricia Scandinavica 1983;67:361-70.
Kroenke K1, Spitzer RL, Williams JB.The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure. J Gen Intern Med. 2001 Sep;16(9):606-13.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to intervention.
One-month and 3-months post-intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Quality of Life using the Quality of Life Index.
Ferrans CE, Powers BR. Quality of Life Index: development and psychometric properties. Advances in Nursing Science 1985;8:15-25.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to intervention.
One-month and 3-months post-intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in activities of daily living using the Modified Rankin Scale,
Mahoney FI, Barthel DW. Functional evaluation: the Barthel Index. Maryland State Medical Journal 1965;14:61-65.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to intervention.
One-month and 3-months post-intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>acute presentation after an acute stroke (cerebral infarction/intracerebral haemorrhage); cognitively alert;
aged 18 years and over;
patients who could speak and read English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>subarachnoid haemorrhage;
subdural haematoma;
severe cognitive/communication problems such as significant dysphasia or aphasia; mental health conditions including depressive symptoms requiring professional support one month prior to stroke;
concurrent neurological disease/trauma; and,
myocardial infarction. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>To avoid selection bias and secure allocation concealment, codes will not be revealed to the Research Assistant.
Allocation was concealed by sealed opaque envelopes.
Intervention group participants will be assigned to a facilitator (multi-disciplinary stroke team member including nurse or allied health staff member), who will not be involved in initial assessment, randomisation or assignment of patients to them for MI.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by a computer</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Not applicable</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Summary statistics were used for demographic characteristics and baseline and follow-up time-point measures.
Participant characteristics were compared using chi-square test (including Fishers Exact test for fields with n&lt;5) and T-Test using SPSS.
General Linear Model with Repeated-measures was performed to explore predictors of treatment response, with statistical significance set at p&lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>34</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>3/11/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray - Footscray</hospital>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Debra Kerr</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>College of Health and Biomedicine
Victoria University
PO Box 14428
Melbourne
Victoria
8001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victoria University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 14428
Melbourne
Victoria
8001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Stroke Foundation (Victoria)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7
461 Bourke St
Melbourne
Victoria
3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Not applicable</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Depression is a frequent consequence of stroke that affects recovery adversely and can lead to greater mortality; however, it is often undetected or treated inadequately. While antidepressants can be used to treat post-stroke depression (PSD), they increase the risk of side-effects which complicate recovery. This randomised controlled trial evaluates a new brief intervention, the Good Mood Intervention program. The aim of the study is to investigate if motivational interviewing (MI) improves patients mood post-stroke. It will be conducted at the Stroke Unit, Western Hospital, Melbourne and will recruit inpatients with acute stroke.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>1. Kerr D, McCann T, Wijeratne T, Mackey E. Effects of the Good Mood Intervention after stroke: A qualitative perspective. Stroke Society of Australasia, Annual Meeting. Melbourne, 2015.
2. Kerr D, McCann T, Wijeratne T, Mackey E. Early motivational interviewing on post-stroke depressive symptoms: The Good Mood Intervention Program  Pilot RCT. Stroke Society of Australasia, Annual Meeting. Melbourne, 2015.
3. Kerr D, McCann T, Wijeratne T, Mackey E. Early motivational interviewing on post-stroke depressive symptoms: Pilot randomised controlled trial of the Good Mood Intervention program. Stroke Society of Australasia, Annual Meeting. Hamilton Island, 2014.
4. Kerr D, McCann T, Wijeratne T, Mackey E. Early motivational interviewing on post-stroke depressive symptoms: Pilot randomised controlled trial of the Good Mood Intervention program. World Stroke Congress, Istanbul, 2014. International Journal of Stroke. 2014. 9: 39-40.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Hospital Low Risk Ethics Panel</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sunshine Hospital
Furlong Rd
St Albans
Victoria 
3021</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/WH/9</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Debra Kerr</name>
      <address>Deakin University
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>61 3 5227 2501</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.kerr@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Debra Kerr</name>
      <address>Deakin University
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>61 3 5227 2501</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.kerr@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Debra Kerr</name>
      <address>Deakin University
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>61 3 5227 2501</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.kerr@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Debra Kerr</name>
      <address>Deakin University
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>61 3 5227 2501</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.kerr@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>