<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366539">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000789662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating a new drug (AUY922) for controlling prostate cancer cell growth using laboratory based outcomes in men with high risk prostate cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised controlled Phase II trial of the pharmacodynamic effects of the heat shock protein 90 (Hsp90) inhibitor AUY922 in high-risk, localised prostate cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>AUY922 administered via a 60 minute intravenous infusion at 70 mg/m2 on days 1, 8, 15 and 22 over a 28 day cycle</interventions>
    <comparator>Best standard care - no study drug administered prior to prostatectomy surgery </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine the effect of AUY922 on tumour cell proliferation (frequency of a 50% reduction in the Ki-67 proliferation index from the pre-treatment prostate biopsy compared to that present in prostate cancer tissue from radical prostatectomy)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After four weeks of treatment or at radical prostatectomy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hsp90 inhibition demonstrated by immunohistochemistry and ELISA induction of Hsp 70 </outcome>
      <timepoint>After four weeks of treatment or radical prostectomy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apoptotic cell death by increase in caspase-3 immunohistochemistry </outcome>
      <timepoint>After four weeks of treatment or radical prostectomy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in serum or tumour levels of PSA</outcome>
      <timepoint>After four weeks of treatment or radical prostectomy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pathological regression defined by cancer cell atrophy</outcome>
      <timepoint>After four weeks of treatment or radical prostectomy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of adverse events as reported by either the treating oncologist or surgeon. Examples of adverse events include fatigue, diarrhoea or nausea. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During treatment and 30 days after last dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Males with localised prostate cancer  and at least clinical stage T3a Or Gleason score of between 8 and 10 Or Preoperative PSA greater than or equal to 20 ng/ml AND planned for radical prostatectomy
2.	Age  greater than or equal to 18 yrs
3.	ECOG performance 0-1
4.	Histological confirmation of prostate cancer via a pre-treatment diagnostic transrectal ultrasound (TRUS) biopsy.
5.	Adequate bone marrow function with platelets greater than or equal to 100 x 109/L, neutrophils greater than or equal to 1.5 x 109/L and haemoglobin greater than or equal to 90 g/L;
6.	Adequate hepatic function with serum total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x upper limit of normal range and ALT/SGPT and SGOT/AST less than or equal to 2.5x upper limit of normal range (or less than 5.0 times ULN with documented liver metastases), serum albumin greater than 25 g/L. alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 5x upper limit of normal range, and INR less than or equal to 1.5
7.	Adequate renal function (with calculated creatinine clearance greater than 50 ml/min based on the Cockcroft-Gault method, 24 hour urine or GFR scan) and serum creatinine greater than 1.5 x Upper Limit of Normal range (ULN); 
8.	Serum calcium, potassium and magnesium within normal range or corrected with supplements 
9.	Study treatment both planned and able to start within 7 days of randomisation. 
10.	Willing and able to comply with all study requirements, including treatment and biospecimen collection
11.	Signed, written informed consent (main study and biospecimen banking)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Major surgery less than or equal to 2 weeks prior to enrolment or who have not recovered from side effects of such therapy. Transrectal ultrasound (TRUS) biopsy is not considered major surgery in this study. 
2.	Known hypersensitivity to the study drug or its excipients
3.	Patients with known disorders due to a deficiency in bilirubin glucuronidation (e.g. Gilberts syndrome)
4.	Diarrhoea greater than or equal to CTCAE grade 2
5.	Impaired cardiac function, including any one of the following:
a.	History (or family history) of long QT syndrome
b.	Mean QTcF greater than or equal to 450 msec on baseline ECG
c.	History of clinically manifested ischemic heart disease less than or equal to 6 months prior to study start
d.	History of heart failure or left ventricular (LV) dysfunction (LVEF less than or equal to 50%) by MUGA 
e.	Clinically significant ECG abnormalities 
f.	History or presence of atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter or ventricular arrhythmias including ventricular tachycardia or Torsades de Pointes
g.	Other clinically significant heart disease (e.g. congestive heart failure, uncontrolled hypertension, history of labile hypertension, or history of poor compliance with an antihypertensive regimen)
h.	Clinically significant resting bradycardia (less than 50 beats per minute)
i.	Patients who are currently receiving treatment with any medication which has a relative risk of prolonging the QTcF interval or inducing Torsades de Pointes and cannot be discontinued or switched to an alternative drug prior to commencing start of treatment.
j.	Obligate use of a cardiac pacemaker
6.	Patients who have received prior antineoplastic therapy for advanced disease. 
7.	Prior treatment with an Hsp90 inhibitor 
8.	Patients receiving chronic or high dose corticosteroids therapy (Inhaled steroids and short courses of oral steroids for anti-emesis or as an appetite stimulant are allowed)
9.	Significant infection, including chronic active hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or HIV. Testing for these is not mandatory unless clinically indicated.
10.	Serious medical or psychiatric conditions that might limit the ability of the patient to comply with the protocol.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment> central randomisation by phone/fax/computer</concealment>
    <sequence> Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>3:1 randomisation in favour of treatment</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A two-stage minimax design will be used to test the primary hypothesis about the frequency of pharmacodynamic (PD) responses in treated patients, with a response defined as 50% or greater decrease in Ki-67 expression in the paired prostate biopsy baseline sample compared with the radical prostatectomy sample. 

If fewer than 3 responses are observed in the first 25 treated patients then consideration will be given to modifying or stopping the study. The regimen will be considered to have sufficient activity (greater than or equal to 30% response rate) if at the end of the study at least 8 patients among the 41 treated patients achieve a response.
Fourteen untreated men will be enrolled in the control group to provide estimates of PD biomarkers as a basis for comparison giving a total sample size of 55 patients.


Analysis of efficacy endpoints (i.e., response, biomarkers) will include only evaluable patients. Analysis of safety endpoints (i.e., toxicity) will be according to treatment received, including only patients who received at least 1 dose of the experimental treatment. Where appropriate p-values will be two tailed. A nominal significance level of 0.05 will be applied. Analysis will be performed when evaluable tissue is available from 25 participants treated with AUY922 and at study completion.
Adverse events will be assessed at the interim analysis and at the completion of the study. Serious adverse events will be monitored by the trial management committee on an ongoing basis to ensure that the rate of these events remains acceptable for the study.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>19/09/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>55</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Chris O’Brien Lifehouse - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Missenden Road</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 3, STRAWBERRY HILLS NSW 2012</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the effects of a drug, AUY922 which inhibits heat shock protein 90 and may disrupt cancer cell growth in men with high-risk, localised protate cancer.

You may be eligible to join this study if you are male, aged 18 years or over and have been diagnosed with prostate cancer and scheduled for a prostectomy surgery.

The majority of men diagnosed with prostate cancer have disease confined to their prostate and surgery and/or
radiotherapy offers a potential cure. However many men can have the cancer return within 5 - 7 years. Treatments for
these men with recurrent prostate cancer are limited. The purpose of this study is to answer the question if treatment with a new drug called AUY922 (a 60 minute intravenous infusion at 70 mg/m2 on days 1, 8, 15 and 22 over a 28 day cycle) can stop the growth of prostate cancer cells. Prostate cancer cell growth can be measured by a protein called Ki67. 

Prostate tissue from biopsies from men with prostate cancer will be collected before treatment with AUY922. All men approached will be having a prostatectomy. After patients have received treatment, their prostate tissue will be collected at surgery evaluated for expression of
Ki67. It is hypothesised that Ki67 expression will be 50% lower compared with before treatment. If there is sufficient activity in the first 25 men who receive treatment, the study will continue to a full experimental cohort of 41 patients. Fourteen (14) patients will be recruited to be a control group with no treatment prior to prostatectomy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00113</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Lisa Horvath</name>
      <address>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse
119-143 Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61285140149</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hsp90@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hsp90 inhibitor study coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Chris O'Brien Lifehouse
119-143 Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61295625000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hsp90@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Lisa Horvath</name>
      <address>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse
119-143 Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61285140149</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hsp90@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hsp90 inhibitor study coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Chris O'Brien Lifehouse
119-143 Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61295625000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hsp90@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>