<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362647">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000645853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study investigating the impact of micronutrients on children with Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigation into the effect of micronutrients on mood and behaviour in children with Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD): a study using single case ABAB design.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>ADHD</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>ABAB design (on-off-on-off) using a vitamin and mineral formula (EMPowerplus) for the treatment of ADHD in children. Empowerplus contains 36 ingredients: 14 vitamins, 16 minerals, 3 amino acids and 3 antioxidants. A list of the ingredients can be found on the companys website, www.truehope.com. Participants first take 8 pills a day for 4 weeks; if there is no response, the dose is increased to 15 pills a day for another 4 weeks. After 8 weeks taking pills, participants are taken off for 4 weeks, put back on at the optimal dose for 8 weeks and then taken off again for 4 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Clinical Global Impressions Severity (CGI-S) and Improvement (CGI-I) Scales which are clinician rated questions assessing the severity of the illness (e.g., mild, moderate, severe) and any changes that have occurred since the last visit (e.g. no change, much improved, very much improved)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every visit (once every two weeks) through out the 24 week trial period and follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ADHD rating scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conners Parent and Teacher Rating Scales completed at switch points and a short version completed every two weeks throughout the 24 week trial period and at follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) is a brief screening questionnaire for child mental health problems that is suitable for parents and teachers to fill out</outcome>
      <timepoint>Switch points of ABAB design as well as baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children's Global Assessment Scale (CGAS). The CGAS is used to by the clinician to assess the overall severity of disturbance in children. The CGAS is a single numerical scale from1 through 100 that is separated into 10-point sections indicating the child's level of functioning.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every visit (once every two weeks) throughout the 24 week trial period and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Depression Rating Scale (CDRS) is a 16-item measure, used for children aged 6-12 years old, measuring the severity of depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every visit (once every two weeks) throughout the 24 week trial period and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Young Mania Rating Scale assesses manic-like behaviours in children and adults</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every visit (once every two weeks) throughout the 24 week trial period and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Mania Rating Scale, Parent Version (CMRS-P)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every visit (once every two weeks) throughout the 24 week trial period and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Conners Continuous Performance Test (CPT-II). The CPT-II  (Connors, 2000) is used as a measure of complex cognitive functioning, including attention, visual-motor speed, visual-motor integration, hyperactivity and impulsivity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Switch points of ABAB design as well as baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Participants are between 8-12 years of age.
2.	Each participant must have a level of understanding sufficient to complete the questionnaires and examinations required by the protocol and be considered reliable and compliant with the protocol (including the ingestion of as many as 15 capsules/day).
3.	Participants must be able to eat at least a snack three times per day, so that the capsules will not be ingested on an empty stomach.
4.	Participants meet criteria for ADHD as assessed by the K-SADS (Kaufman, et al., 1997), the Conners Rating Scales (score greater than 70 on either parent or teacher form; (Conners, 1997).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Neurological disorder involving brain or other central function (e.g., epilepsy, MS, narcolepsy). Purely peripheral neurological problems are not excluded (e.g., Raynauds, peripheral diabetic neuropathy).
2.	Any serious medical condition for which major medical interventions are anticipated during the duration of the trial.
3.	Any patient known to be allergic to the ingredients of the intervention (including ginkgo biloba, germanium sesquioxide, or grape seed) will be excluded.
4.	Evidence of untreated or unstable thyroid disease (thyroid testing will occur at baseline).
5.	Any known abnormality of mineral metabolism (e.g., Wilsons disease, haemochromatosis).
6.	Any other medication with primarily central nervous system activity, including mood stabilizers. Participants must have been off of these medications for a minimum of four weeks prior to the trial.
7.	Patients will be excluded temporarily if they have taken an oral antibiotic in the previous 6 weeks. 
8.	Any type of nutritional or herbal supplement, known to have a centrally-acting effect, will result in a patient's exclusion. However, patients who have been taking supplements such as echinacea, chondroitin, or glucosamine may enter the study if a) they have been taking these agents for at least one month prior to the study, and b) they continue on these agents throughout the study. We will permit people to take as much as 1 g/day of EPA and DHA combined.  
9.	Any subject judged clinically to be at serious risk for suicide or violence in the opinion of the researchers.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>14</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Psychology, University of Canterbury</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Vic Davis Memorial Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Vic Davis Memorial Trust
PO Box 793
Whakatane 3158</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Psychology, University of Canterbury</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is a chronic illness that affects 3-5% of the population. It is associated with many other conditions and is a risk factor for continued mental health problems. While many medications are widely used for this condition, the side effects and lack of long-term efficacy data cause many families to seek out alternative options. Micronutrients (vitamins and minerals) are receiving growing recognition as a promising treatment for many psychiatric disorders, including bipolar disorder, depression and ADHD. This study plans to investigate the impact of micronutrients on ADHD and mood symptoms in children using a pilot single case on-off-on-off design.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.mentalhealthandnutrition.co.nz</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Gordon, H. A., Rucklidge, J. J., Blampied, N. M., &amp; Johnstone, J. M. (2015). Clinically Significant Symptom Reduction in Children with Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder Treated with Micronutrients: An Open-Label Reversal Design Study. Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology, 25(10), 783-798. doi: 10.1089/cap.2015.0105
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Lower South Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Ministry of Health
Level 2, Reception
1-3 The Terrace
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HEC 2011/44</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Julia Rucklidge</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch, Canterbury
8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3642987 ext. 7959</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3642181</fax>
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Julia Rucklidge</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch, Canterbury
8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3642987 ext. 7959</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3642181</fax>
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Julia Rucklidge</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch, Canterbury
8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3642987 ext. 7959</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3642181</fax>
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Julia Rucklidge</name>
      <address>Private Bag 4800
Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Christchurch
8140</address>
      <phone>+6433642987</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julia.rucklidge@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>