<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365837">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000500651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Identifying deficient colonic bacterial fermentation in patients with ulcerative colitis in remission</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Colonic bacterial fermentation profiles in patients with Ulcerative Colitis (UC) following high vs low indigestible carbohydrate diets: biomarkers and implications for future   therapies
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ulcerative colitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Individuals with ulcerative colitis in remission will be supplied with two diets differing in high or low amounts of indigestible carbohydrates over a 12-hour period. The diets will consist of only two meals, an evening meal the night before and a breakfast meal the morning of ingesting the pH-motility device. The evening meal will comprise of legumes, grains and starchy vegetables varying in indigestible carbohydrates whereas the breakfast meal will consist of a muesli bar. The HIGH arm will contain 10g fermentable carbohydrate per meal. 

Compliance to the study diets will be assessed by food diaries, return of food containers and breath hydrogen tests. For the rest of the study period, participants will be following their usual diets. 

Following the first dietary arm, there will be a 3-day washout period before participants cross over to the other study diet.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control diet will be the low indigestible carbohydrate diet and as mentioned in the intervention description, will be provided in 2 meals over a 12-hour period prior to ingesting the pH-motility device. The indigestible carbohydrate content in the LOW indigestible carbohydrate arm will be &lt;2g per meal.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of fibre that is utilised or fermented (broken down by bacteria) in the large bowel will be analysed by measuring the stool content of starch and non-starch polysaccharides (NSP).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome will only be measured at baseline (prior to administering the interventional diets) and then used to categorise the subjects into good fibre utilisers or poor fibre utilisers for comparisons with the secondary outcomes. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraluminal pH profiles of the large intestine will be calculated over time using a wireless pH-motility device that records pH data as it travels from the right to the left side of the colon. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Gastrointestinal pH will be measured in the time period following ingestion of the morning meal on the first dietary arm until the device is passed from the gastrointestinal tract and then again 3 days later, after ingesting the morning meal of the 2nd dietary arm. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The passage rate of fibre through the large intestine will also be measured by the wireless pH-motility device. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Passage rate of fibre through the colon will be measured from the time period immediately following ingestion of the morning meal on the first dietary arm until the device is passed from the gastrointestinal tract and then again 3 days later, during the 2nd dietary arm. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Individuals with ulcerative colitis in remission
- on stable medical or drug therapy for &gt; 1 month

OR 

(2) Healthy volunteers 

Both groups must be aged 18-75 years old and have not taken any antibiotics in preceding 3 months </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Individuals with Crohn's disease, indeterminate colitis or have undergone surgical removal of partial or all of the colon
or 
- individuals taking topical rectal therapies in preceding three months
or
- those taking medications affecting bowel function in preceding four weeks
or
- women who are pregnant or breastfeeding

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>12/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School, Monash University
The Alfred Centre
Level 6, 99 Commercial Rd,
Prahran 3004 VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ferring Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO BOX 135, Pymble NSW 2073</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Gastroenterology, The Alfred Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 1, The Alfred, 99 Commercial Rd, Prahran 3004 VIC</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ulcerative colitis (UC) is a chronic and relapsing inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) characterised by inflammation in the lining of the large bowel. Recent studies of the bacterial populations that normally reside in the large bowel (gut microbiota) have shown abnormalities (i.e., dysbiosis) in the faeces of patients with UC. Our research group has found evidence that the ability of the gut microbiota to ferment carbohydrates may be markedly defective and this cannot be corrected by simply providing more dietary fibre. Such fermentation is an important function of the microbiota as it delivers breakdown products that include short-chain fatty acids such as butyrate to the lining cells of the colon. Butyrate is the major source of nutrition for those cells and also has anti-inflammatory and anti-tumour-producing effects. This observation has potentially large implications for how we manage UC. If it is true, then manipulation of the bacteria and of the specific carbohydrate substrates they see by, for example, dietary manipulation of the types of carbohydrates they eat might have therapeutic benefit. Furthermore, such fermentation lowers acidity (pH) in the bowel and this lowering is utilised for the activation of some drugs commonly used in UC (e.g. mesalazine). Defective fermentation might lead to poor activation of those drugs and lack of effectiveness.

The major problem with studying fermentation in the large bowel is that most occurs in the proximal part of the large bowel  i.e., the part furthest away from the anus - and we have only been able to study it indirectly. Using swallowed capsule technology that transmits information to a transmitter worn by the patient (as used by the pill-camera), a new wireless pH-motility device, has been developed. This device is able to capture measurements for transit (speed of passage through the gut) and pH in real time and in a non-invasive manner as it travels along the entire gut. It is the pH measurement that provides our first way of examining fermentation in the intact colon.

We propose to measure the pH profiles in the gut of 10 healthy volunteers and of 20 patients with UC who do not have active disease after both a large and a minimal load of indigestible, fermentable carbohydrates. This will be achieved by controlled food intake over the 12 hours prior to the capsule being swallowed. This will give us a range of pH profiles related to high and low levels of fermentation in the gut. We will then be able to determine if the fermentation capability of patients with UC is truly deficient. The pH-motility device will also permit us to examine transit through the regions of the gut and provide mechanistic information on the role of gut transit in any abnormalities found. We anticipate variation in responses of patients (but not in healthy volunteers). In order to be able to identify patients with abnormal fermentation, we will also collect, prior to the investigations with a wireless pH-motility device, dietary intake information and faeces to determine if these indices provide the correlations with the pH profile. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics and Research Governance Office
Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion
55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004

OR 
Ethics and Research Governance Office
The Alfred 
PO Box 315
Prahran VIC 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>121/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee (MUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University Clayton</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF14/2107 - 20140001086</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Gibson</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Prahran 3004 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61399030271</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.gibson@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>CK Yao</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Prahran 3004 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61399030270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chu.yao@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>CK Yao</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Prahran 3004 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61399030270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chu.yao@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>CK Yao</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Prahran 3004 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61399030270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chu.yao@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>