<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363571">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000340730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can Amino Acids in Combination with Exercise Training Improve Metabolic Flexibility and Cardiovascular Health in Type-2 Diabetics?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can Combined Amino Acid And Exercise Therapy For Type-2 Diabetes Improve Cardiovascular Health and Metabolic Flexibility?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>The trial has no secondary ID</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-insulin dependent type-2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomised to the AA + EX group will underake a 10-week weekday morning small-group mixed-mode exercise program and consume a pre- and post-exercise supplement. All sessions willl be supervised by exercise physiologists. The exercise program entails 3 days of 20 minutes of interval cycling on an ergometer for 20 minutes at 30% and 60% of maximal work capacity, and 2 days of 30 minutes of upper-body resistance circuit training at 60% of 1 repitition maximum plus core exercises (plus warm up and cool down exercises). Maximal cycling work capacity and maximum strength on resistance exercises will be reassesed fortnightly and workloads adjusted to maintain prescribed intensities. The treatment is a 200ml pre-packaged drink containing 15g whey protein, 3g leucine, 15g carbohydrate, and 5g of fat.  Drinks will be consumed immediately before and after exercise and at the same time by participants in the supplement only group. </interventions>
    <comparator>1. Participants randomised to the AA group will not attend exercise sessions but will consume the leucine-enriched milk-protein drink at the same time as participants in the exercise groups for 10 weeks.
2. Participants randomised to the EX group will attend exercise sessions for 10 weeks and consume a pre- and post-exercise isocaloric placebo of similar taste containing 33g of carbohydrate and 5g of fat.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whole-body glucose disposal rate during hyperinsulinemic euglycaemic clamp </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Flow mediated dilation of the brachial artery by ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial stiffness at the brachial artery by pulse wave analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HOMA from fasting plasma glucose and insulin concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mitochondrial capacity at the Vastus Lateralis muscle by near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Microvascular blood flow at the Vastus Lateralis muscle by NIRS</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic flexibility by respiratory exchange ratio during breath by breath gas analysis </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: before and during clamp; before and during exercise
Repeated after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skeletal muscle capillary density via immunocytochemistry</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin stimulated skeletal muscle capillary recruitment at the Vastus Lateralis via NIRS</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline: before and during clamp
Repeated after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skeletal muscle tissue fibrosis via endomysium cross-sectional area (immunocytochemistry) and hydroxyproline concentration (ELISA assay) </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skeletal muscle mitochondrial function 1) density via electron microscopic densitometry 2) mitochondrial enzyme activity (citrate synthase, cytochrome c oxidase and 5 subunits, beta-hydroxyacyl-CoA-dehydrogenase via immunoblot</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total and sarcolemmal glucose transporter 4 content via immunoblot</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline: before and during clamp
Repeated after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intramyocellular lipid content via electron microscopy densitometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin stimulated GLUT4 translocation associated signaling protein activity via immunoblot of phosphorylated IRS, PI3K, AS160, and akt, in Vastus Lateralis muscle</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline: before and during clamp
Repeated after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skeletal muscle growth via immunocytochemistry of myocellular volume and bioelectrical impedance of total lean body mass</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aerobic capacity via breath by breath gas analysis during an incremental maximal cycle ergometer test</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal strength via 1 repetition max test on leg press and smith machine bench press</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentration of cholesterol, triglycerides, and high-density lipoproteins </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after week 10</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whole-body fat mass via bioelectrical impedence</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concentration of myostatin and associated regulators (follistatin, FLRG, activin-receptor) in skeletal muscle via immunoblot </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Genetic adaptation to support other outcomes via gene array and epigenetic analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline: before and after clamp
Repeated after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional health and well-being via psychometric assessment using SF36</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and after 10 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Non-insulin dependent Type-2 diabetics (T2DM)diagnosed for a minimum of 1 year, HbA1c between 7 and 9%, BMI 25-32, stable weight and non-participation in regular exercise in past 6 months. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Use of beta-blockers, moderate to severe retinopathy, nephropathy and neuropathy, history of cerebrovascular or cardiovascular diseases, or evidence of other clinical contraindications preventing moderate to high-intensity exercise, including cardiac irregularities that may appear during baseline maximal aerobic testing.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through advertising and through medical centres in Wellington NZ, based upon database records identifying them as meeting the eligibility criteria. 
After baseline testing, a researcher not involved in the study will randomly allocate participants to treatment and control groups. The experiment is semi-blinded. Researchers involved in the study and participants will be blind to allocation of treatment and placebo to the exercise groups, but will not be blind to participants allocated to the AA (supplement-only) group.
</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomization sequence will be generated using the following internet source (http://www.randomizer.org/form.htm). The randomization sequence (i.e. AA = supplement only; EX = exercise only; AA+EX = supplement plus exercise) will be placed in a sequentially numbered envelope (from 1-36) based on the derived sequence generated by the website</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The between group effect of treatment will be analysed using mixed linear models via the Proc Mixed utility in SAS (SAS, Cary, NC). Fixed effects within the linear models with polynomial contrasts if warranted will be group (treatment) and time. Random effects (covariance matrix) will be subject, amino acid therapy; additional random effects may be added following evaluation of other sources of variability. The baseline values will be added as a covariate to adjust for between-subject variability. Parametric data will be log-transformed prior to analysis, which allows for changes to be expressed as percents and manages heterscedasity to meet the requirements normally-distributed data. Clinical inference and inference to mechanisms outcomes will be via the method of magnitude-based inference.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Massey University Wellington </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>63 Wallace St
Mt Cook, Wellington. 6021 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Masssey University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Massey University
Tennent Drive 
Palmerston North 4474
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Capital and Coast District Health Board
Endocrine, Diabetes and Research Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Capital and Coast District Health Board
Endocrine, Diabetes and Research Centre
Level 5, Grace Neill Block, Wellington Regional Hospital.
Newtown, Wellington NZ. 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In both human and animal studies combined amino acid plus exercise interventions have improved outcomes associated with cardiovascular health (Yoshizawa 2010) and metabolic flexibility above either therapy alone (D'Antona 2010, Sasai 2011, Kim 2011). The purpose of this study is to determine the effect of combined amino acid and exercise therapies on cardiovascular health, glycaemic control and mechanisms important to insulin sensitivity in the skeletal muscle of non-insulin dependent type-2 diabetics.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
 No 1 The Terrace
 PO Box 5013
 Wellington Central 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Kim Gaffney</name>
      <address>School of Sport and Exercise, College of Health, Massey University
63 Wallace St
Mt Cook, Wellington, 6021 </address>
      <phone>+64 4 8014994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimgaffney@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Kim Gaffney</name>
      <address>School of Sport and Exercise, College of Health, Massey University
63 Wallace St
Mt Cook, Wellington, 6021 </address>
      <phone>+64 4 8014994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimgaffney@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Kim Gaffney</name>
      <address>School of Sport and Exercise, College of Health, Massey University
63 Wallace St
Mt Cook, Wellington, 6021 </address>
      <phone>+64 4 8014994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimgaffney@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Kim Gaffney</name>
      <address>School of Sport and Exercise, College of Health, Massey University
63 Wallace St
Mt Cook, Wellington, 6021 </address>
      <phone>+64 4 8014994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimgaffney@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>