<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370916">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000866404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised control trial of Social Skills Training (SCIT) in those diagnosed with psychosis. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised control trial on the effect of Social Cognition Interaction Training (SCIT) on social functioning in those diagnosed with psychosis.  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Schizophreniform psychosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Delusional disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychosis not otherwise specified</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will include 128 individuals diagnosed with psychosis who will be randomised to either a befriending program (comparison group) or the SCIT program (intervention). Participants will attend weekly, 2 hour face-to-face group sessions (2 facilitators, 6-8 participants) for 12 weeks at an inner city community mental health clinic.  This will be in addition to participants' normal routine care. 

Mental health clinicians (psychiatrists, psychologists, social workers and mental health nurses) with specialised training in both SCIT and befriending programs will facilitate programs. External, blinded clinicians (psychologist, mental health nurses) will complete assessments at designated time-points. Facilitators will use the SCIT manual to complete the program. The manual first summarizes the rationale and theoretical underpinnings of SCIT. Next, it distinguishes SCIT from other psychosocial treatments for psychosis. Following this, it provides an overview of the SCIT intervention, along with notes pertinent to its implementation. Then it concludes with a description of the links between the specific intervention activities and the underlying theoretical model.  

Social cognition training (SCIT) is a non- invasive, manualised talking therapy with a purpose of improving social cognition and social functioning for individuals with schizophrenia. It is comprised of three phases (i.e. Introduction and Emotions, Figuring out Situations and Checking it Out) administered in a group format. Participants enrolled in this program will be given a workbook comprising of the above sections to complete. During this completion process they will role-plays, games and technology activities (e.g. watching DVDs) as guided by each section. They will also be asked to complete out of session tasks where they will describe their mood and / or situations they become involved with to debrief at the next session. The session are divided into 2 parts with a short break in between to assist maintenance of concentration and to practice socialising within the group.

Face to face clinical assessments will be at baseline (week 0) and weeks 12 (end-point) and 24 (post end point) , Intermittent phone contact will occur in between face to face visits and at Week 6 to monitor participants' wellbeing and discuss any concerns the participant may raise. Participants will be given Coles / Myer gift vouchers for participating in the trial ($50 at baseline, $50 at end-point, $50 at follow-up) and when needed, transported to and from the clinic.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>The study will include 128 individuals diagnosed with psychosis who will be randomised to either a befriending program (comparison group) or the SCIT program (intervention). Participants will attend weekly, 2 hour face-to-face group sessions (2 facilitators, 6-8 participants) for 12 weeks at an inner city community mental health clinic.  This will be in addition to participants' normal routine care. 

Mental health clinicians (psychiatrists, psychologists, social workers and mental health nurses) with specialised training in both SCIT and befriending programs will facilitate programs. External, blinded clinicians (psychologist, mental health nurses) will complete assessments at designated time-points. 

Befriending therapy is designed to be used as a control interaction for clinical trials of psychotherapy. It entails a series of conversations with a client of clients that are similar to those with whom you have a social acquaintance with. Specifically, it involved an ongoing discussion of everyday topics and / or events in a friendly way without any problem solving or exploration of emotions and feelings. Participants in this program will complete also be given a workbook to complete however this workbook will not compromise of section leading towards an overall goal. Instead it will describe the group format for each session e.g. check-in, ice-breaker exercises, activity 1, break, activity 2 etc. Similar to the SCIT group, sessions are divided into 2 parts with a short break in between to assist maintenance of concentration. 

Face to face clinical assessments will be at baseline (week 0) and weeks 12 (end-point) and 24 (post end point) , Intermittent phone contact will occur in between face to face visits and at Week 6 to monitor participants' wellbeing and discuss any concerns the participant may raise. Participants will be given Coles / Myer gift vouchers for participating in the trial ($50 at baseline, $50 at end-point, $50 at follow-up) and when needed, transported to and from the clinic.  
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bell Lysacker Emotion Recognition Task (BLERT) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0)
End point (week 12)
Post study (week 24) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Skills Performance Assessment </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0)
End point (week 12)
Post study (week 24) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Meta Cognition Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0)
End point (week 12)
Post study (week 24) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Functioning Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0)
End point (week 12)
Post study (week 24) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hinting Task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0)
End point (week 12)
Post study (week 24) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Internal, Personal and Situational Attributions Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0)
End point (week 12)
Post study (week 24) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CogState BRIEF Battery </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline - 0 Weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged between 18 and 65 years (inclusive).
2. Fulfil the DSM-IV criteria practice for broadly defined early psychosis, based on the Diagnostic Interview for Psychosis. This includes diagnoses such as schizophrenia, schizophreniform psychosis, delusional disorder, bipolar disorder, psychosis not otherwise specified. 
3. Have a premorbid functioning IQ of 71 or above 
4. Have a social functioning scale - communication score below 105
5. Have an educational attainment of Grade 4 or above 
6. Agree to participate, has capacity to consent and able to follow the study instructions and procedures.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have a premorbid functioning IQ of 70 or below
2. Have a social functioning scale - communication score above 106
3. Have an educational attainment of Grade 3 or below
4. Being unable to understand study demands and therefore not being able to consent appropriately. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment was completed by central randomisation, using a computer generated randomization table on a 1:1 basis (SCIT to BT). </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be carried out using a computergenerated randomization table on a 1:1 basis (SCIT to BT).  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All data will be analysed using SAS 9.4. We will compare demographic and clinical differences between the groups at baseline (Fisher exact test for nominal variables and Mann-Whitney test or independent sample t test for continuous variables). Efficacy will be assessed according to standard Intention to Treat (ITT) analytic procedures (i.e. for those who do not complete the 24 week study period, we will carry forward their last observation on the study outcomes). Mean changes in clinical assessment will be assessed using mixed-model repeated-measure (MMRM) methods with treatment, week, and treatment-week interaction as fixed effects and intercept as the only random effect; baseline value will be the covariant. The MMRM analyses will be performed using the SAS PROC Mixed procedure. P values will be based on 2-tailored tests with significance levels of 0.05.

Previous pilot studies using a modified emotional training protocol have yielded large effect sizes on emotion identification of 1.60 and .94 respectively. Based an expected 2.2-point difference between baseline to post-test, a change score standard deviation of 2.6, and a baseline-post-test correlation of .50, a sample of 56 participants has 80% power to reject the null hypothesis. We estimate a dropout rate of 15-20% (from treatment to 6-month follow-up) resulting in a final sample size of approximately 128 participants who complete the study.  This estimate is based on the dropout rates from our outpatient pilot study, which had retention rate of 83%, as well as our experience with group RCT research.  


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Lucia, QLD, 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Centre for Health Services Innovation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
Queensland University of Technology
60 Musk Ave Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The social cognition training (SCIT) is a groupbased therapy that has a goal of improving thinking skills about social situations for individuals with psychotic disorders. Two trained therapists deliver the group over 12 weekly sessions, with each session lasting approximately 2 hours. Participants will be able to attend one of the sites convenient to where they live. The therapy involves education about emotions and social interaction using games and technology such as watching DVDs. Participants will be asked to attend a clinical assessment at three times points (beginning of the study, end of study and 3 months post study)that will take approximately 2 hours of their time. The clinical assessment will include tests of thinking and problem solving skills, and questions about how people think in social situations and skills in identifying emotions from photographs of people. At the completion of the entire study, a summary of the results will be sent out to participants informing them of the outcomes of the study. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00167)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC Office  Centres for Health Research Level 7 Translational Research Institute Building Princess Alexandra Hospital Ipswich Road Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QPAH/98</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Dark </name>
      <address>Macgregor Community Mental Health 
519 Kessels Rd, Macgregor, QLD, 4109</address>
      <phone>+61731678333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Frances.Dark@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Baker</name>
      <address>Level 3, Dawson House
The Park Centre for Mental Health 
Corner Ellerton Drive and Wolston Park Road
Wacol Queensland 4076</address>
      <phone>+61732718660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrea_baker@qcmhr.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Dark</name>
      <address>Macgregor Community Mental Health 
519 Kessels Rd, Macgregor, QLD. 4109</address>
      <phone>+61731678333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Frances.Dark@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Baker </name>
      <address>Level 3, Dawson House
The Park Centre for Mental Health 
Corner Ellerton Drive and Wolston Park Road
Wacol Queensland 4076</address>
      <phone>+61732718660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrea_baker@qcmhr.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>