<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335286">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000405011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>This study is examining the safety and tolerability of a new drug (Everolimus) in combination with chemotherapy in the treatment of relapsed adult acute lymphobastic leukaemia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase 1 study investigating the safety and tolerability of RAD001 (Everolimus) in combination with chemotherapy for treatment of relapsed adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group -ALL7</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>acute lymphobastic leukaemia (ALL)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients suffering from ALL in first or subsequent relapse will start oral RAD001 (everolimus) treatment (either 2.5mg or 5mg depending on which study cohort is open) once daily on day 1 for a total of 18 doses in 18 days in conjunction with the HyperCVAD regimen. Patients achieving complete remission by day 21 of the preceding chemotherapy cycle can proceed with subsequent cycles of the same RAD001 dose and HyperCVAD up to a total of 4 cycles.

The first cohort of 6 patients will receive 2.5mg dose of RAD001. The data of each cohort will be reviewed to assess whether or not subsequent cohorts of patients can be given 2.5mg or 5mg dose of RAD001 or whether the trial should be closed.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety of RAD001 given in combination with the Hyper CVAD regimen in patients with relapsed ALL. The primary measure of safety will be the duration of myelosuppression, as measured by time to recovery to grade 2 neutropenia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily evaluations from start of treatment until day 42 of each chemotherapy course</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document the duration of severe thrombocytopenia defined as platelets &lt;50x10e9/L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily evaluations from start of treatment until day 42 of each chemotherapy course</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document and review the incidence of Grade 3 and 4 non-hematological toxicities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily until day 18 following last study treatment and again at day 42 after last study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To provide estimates of the complete remission (CR) rate, duration of remission and leukemia-free survival (LFS) and overall survival (OS) in patients treated with this combination as assessed by medical investigations consistent with standard of care</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years after patient was registered to trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Morphologically and immunophenotypically confirmed diagnosis of precursor B ALL, negative for Philadelphia chromosome/ bcr-abl fusion transcripts, in first or subsequent relapse more than 6 months after starting treatment with a standard combination chemotherapy protocol.

Has provided written informed consent

Must be surgically sterile or female and postmenopausal (ie &gt;12 mths since the last menstrual cycle) or, if capable of parenting a child, must be using medically acceptable and adequate method of contraception while undergoing protocol treatment and until 90  days after the last treatment.

Adequate renal, hepatic and cardiac functions at Screening as defined by:
Serum bilirubin   &lt;2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN)
Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5ULN, unless medically correctable
Adequate cardiac function with left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt;40% and no major left ventricular dysfunction

An Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 2 or less at Screening</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with other immunophenotypic variants of ALL (precursor T, mature B)

Women who are pregnant or lactating. Women of child-bearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test at Screening.

Patients who have relapsed after an allogeneic transplant

Systemic chemotherapy, immunotherapy, approved proteins/antibodies or any investigational agent within 4 weeks prior to commencing study treatment

Radiotherapy within 14 days of commencing study treatment.

Prior therapy with mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitors (sirolimus, temsirolimus, everolimus)
Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus 

CYP3A4 enzyme inducing anti-convulsant medication (eg phenytoin, phenobarbital, or carbemazepine), rifampin and rifabutin, and St. Johns Wort less than or equal to 14 days prior to study treatment 

Ketoconazole less than or equal to 7 days before study treatment (Note: interaction with topical ketoconazole cannot be excluded).

Known cirrhosis, chronic active hepatitis, or chronic persistent hepatitis

Unresolved toxicities from prior systemic therapy or radiotherapy that, in the opinion of the investigator, does not qualify the patient for study treatment.

Patients with known interstitial lung disease or severely impaired lung function (spirometry and diffusional capacity lung carbon monoxide (DLCO) 50% or less of normal and oxygen saturation of 88% or less at rest on room air).

Patients who have a history of another primary malignant disease, apart from non-melanotic skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of the uterine cervix or any other cancer treated with curative intent &gt;2 years previously without evidence of relapse.

Any uncontrolled clinically significant cardiac disease, arrhythmias or angina pectoris
Active inflammatory bowel disease or other bowel disease causing chronic diarrhoea (defined as common terminology criteria (CTC) grade 2)

Chronic treatment with immunosuppressives

Patients who, in the opinion of the Investigator, have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or infections that may compromise study data

Untreated or symptomatic Central Nervous System (CNS) leukaemia

Previous adverse reaction to trial drug(s)

Patients with a known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) seropositivity
Uncontrolled Hepatitis B or C infection. Patients positive for Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) (Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBs Ag) that is not due to vaccination, or HBV deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)) should undergo prophylactic antiviral therapy for 2 weeks prior to the first dose of RAD001, and for 4 weeks following the last dose of RAD001.

Participation in other therapeutic studies in the last 30 days except for studies with a non-medical intervention. Documented evidence of receiving placebo will be required.

Unable to receive treatment at an affiliated Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group (ALLG) centre

Medical or psychiatric conditions that compromise the patients ability to give informed consent or to complete the protocol

Presence of any psychological, familial, sociological or geographical condition potentially hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule. This condition must be discussed with the patient prior to signing consent and registration in the trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central registration</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/04/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/04/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>No data analysis planned</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ground Floor, 35 Elizabeth Street * Richmond, VIC 3121</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis Pharmaceuticals Australia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>54 Waterloo Road
North Ryde, NSW, Australia, 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with relapsed ALL will receive 18 days of oral Everolimus (RAD001) in combination with HyperCVAD therapy. The first 6 patients will receive 2.5mg dose of RAD001. The data of these 6 will be reviewed to assess whether or not subsequent patients can progress to 5mg dose of RAD001, or the trial should be closed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Westmead Hospital, Westmead, NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/WMEAD/198  SSA/11/WMEAD/77</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/05/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ken Bradstock</name>
      <address>Westmead Hospital, Westmead, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9181 4614</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kbradstock@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ken Bradstock</name>
      <address>Westmead Hospital, Darcy Rd, Westmead, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9181 4614</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ken.bradstock@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Delaine Smith</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 3 8373 9701 </phone>
      <fax>61 3 9429 8277</fax>
      <email>delaine.smith@allg.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ken Bradstock</name>
      <address>Westmead Hospital, Westmead, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9181 4614</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kbradstock@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>