<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373239">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001192370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A phase I/IIa study to assess safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetic, pharmacodynamic effects and exploratory efficacy of two doses of AGMG0201 in patients with essential hypertension.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase I/IIa study to assess safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetic, pharmacodynamic effects and exploratory efficacy of two doses of AGMG0201 in patients with essential hypertension.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Essential Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This will be a dose escalation study of AGMG0201 delivered at two doses (high and low) in up to 24 volunteers.

Each participant will be randomised to receive either low dose AGMG0201 (0.2 mg plasmid DNA and 0.25 mg Angiotensin II-KLH conjugate), high dose AGMG0201 (0.2 mg plasmid DNA and 0.5 mg Angiotensin II-KLH conjugate), or placebo (saline) according to the study randomisation schedule. Each dose will be administered as a single intramuscular injection to the deltoid muscle. 

A booster vaccination will be administered 30 days after the first vaccination, providing there are no contraindications to a booster dose at Visit B0 in accordance with the pre-defined eligibility criteria (defined below), as determined by the PI or delegate:
- Mean systolic blood pressure (SBP) &lt; 180 mmHg and/or mean diastolic blood pressure (DBP) &lt;110 mmHg.
- No orthostatic hypotension
- No use of antihypertensive medications since Visit V0.
- No new clinically significant changes to participants health that would contraindicate administration of the booster dose.

Participants receiving the booster dose will receive the same treatment (i.e. AGMG0201 or placebo) administered at their first vaccination.

All participants enrolled in the study will receive a single dose of AGMG0201 (high or low dose) or placebo at Visit V0 and will be required to remain in the clinical unit until 24 hours post vaccination. Participants will attend outpatient visits for study procedures at 7, 14 and 30 days post-vaccine. At Visit B0, 30 days after receiving the first vaccine, participants will be re-assessed according to pre-defined eligibility criteria, and those who remain eligible will be administered a booster vaccine of the same treatment administered at Visit V0, then monitored for adverse events during a second 24 hour post-vaccination confinement period. Participants will return for additional outpatient visits at 7, 14, 30, 60, 90, 180 and 360 days after the booster vaccination. Participants who receive the first vaccine but are not eligible for the booster dose will receive no further IP but will be followed intention-to-treat (ITT), i.e. will undergo all scheduled assessments as per the protocol, unless consent is withdrawn.

Up to 24 participants will be enrolled in two groups of 12 participants: Group 1 (low dose or placebo) and Group 2 (high dose or placebo). In Group 1, two sentinel participants will receive study drug (1 active: 1 placebo) administered a minimum of 7 days prior to study drug administration in the remaining 10 participants in Group 1 (8 active: 2 placebo). The remaining participants in Group 1 will receive their first vaccination after review of 7 days post-dose safety data from both sentinel participants.

Dose administration for the 12 Group 2 participants (high dose 9: placebo 3) will not commence until Group 1 participants have completed study procedures up to 30 days post-booster vaccination (Visit B30). There will be no sentinel dosing in Group 2.

An interim analysis will be performed for each participant group at 90 days following the last study vaccination (Group 1 and Group 2, respectively). The study will then be unblinded, and any placebo participants still active in the study will no longer be required for follow up. Participants randomised to AGMG0201 will continue in the study as per the schedule of assessments.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo controlled treatment: 0.9% saline injection </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of AGMG0201 vaccine administered as an intramuscular injection in adult participants with essential hypertension at two dose levels (low dose; high dose) compared with placebo.

Primary endpoints: 
- Solicited AEs (local and systemic reactogenicity events) collected for 14 days following vaccination.

- Unsolicited events collected for 90 days following vaccination.

- Safety and clinical laboratory parameters (biochemistry, haematology, coagulation, and urinalysis).

- Vital signs, ECG measurements and physical examination findings.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at baseline (screening), and measured at 7, 14 and 30 days after the first vaccination of AGMG0201, and at 7, 14, 30, 60, 90, 180 and 360 days after a booster vaccination of AGMG0201.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the Immunological response to AGMG0201 vaccine administered as an intramuscular injection in adult participants with essential hypertension at two dose levels (low dose; high dose) compared with placebo, as determined by changes to Angiotensin II titer from baseline (pre-dose). Serum samples will be collected for pharmacodynamic analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (pre-dose) and 7, 14 and 30 days after the first vaccination of AGMG0201, and at 7, 14, 30, 60, 90, 180 and 360 days after a booster vaccination of AGMG0201.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whole blood samples will be collected to analyse pharmacokinetic changes to AGMG0201 vaccine administered as an intramuscular injection in adult participants with essential hypertension at two dose levels (low dose; high dose) compared with placebo, as measured by changes to plasmid DNA concentration from baseline (pre-dose).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at baseline (pre-dose), and at 1, 7 and 14 days after each vaccination of AGMG0201.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma samples will be collected to analyse pharmacodynamic changes to hormone levels of renin, aldosterone, angiotensin I, and angiotensin II measured from baseline (screening). The hormone levels mentioned above are composite secondary outcomes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at baseline (screening), and measured at 7, 14 and 30 days after the first vaccination of AGMG0201, and at 7, 14, 30, 60, 90, 180 and 360 days after a booster vaccination of AGMG0201.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma samples will be collected to analyse pharmacodynamic changes to metanephrine hormone levels measured from baseline (screening). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at baseline (screening), and measured at 30, 60 and 90 days after the booster vaccination of AGMG0201</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the efficacy of AGMG0201 vaccine administered as an intramuscular injection in adult participants with essential hypertension at two dose levels (low dose; high dose) compared with placebo, by assessing changes to 24 hour blood pressure measurements as measured by Ambulatory Blood Pressure Monitoring (ABPM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at baseline (pre-dose), and at 30, 60, 90 and 180 days after booster vaccination of AGMG0201.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the efficacy of AGMG0201 vaccine administered as an intramuscular injection in adult participants with essential hypertension at two dose levels (low dose; high dose) compared with placebo, by assessing changes to clinic BP measurements </outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at baseline (pre-dose), and at 1, 7, 14, 30 days after vaccination of AGMG0201, and at 1, 7, 14, 30, 60, 90, 180 and 360 days after the booster vaccination of AGMG0201.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the efficacy of AGMG0201 vaccine administered as an intramuscular injection in adult participants with essential hypertension at two dose levels (low dose; high dose) compared with placebo, by assessing time to commencement of rescue medication for treatment of hypertension or hypotension assessed by participant self reporting which is confirmed by the PI or delegate. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured by time to return to conventional antihypertensive therapy.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Provided voluntarily written informed consent. Willing and able to comply with protocol, and attend all study visits
2. Males or females of non-childbearing potential, aged more than or equal to 18 years and less than 80 years. 
3. Body Mass Index (BMI) less than or equal to 35 kg/m2
4. Adequate venous access 
5. Mild to moderate hypertension, defined as mean systolic blood pressure (SBP) 140-179 mmHg AND/OR mean diastolic blood pressure (DBP) of 90-109 mmHg (inclusive), who are either not currently using antihypertensive medications or are willing to discontinue current antihypertensive medications. No clinically significant abnormalities that would contraindicate participation
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>79</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants with any of the following will not be eligible:
1. Using two or more antihypertensive medications (excluding ACEi + CCB, ACEi + diuretic, ARB+ CCB or ARB + diuretic) or unable to safely discontinue antihypertensive medications. 
2. Any history of intolerance to ACE inhibitors or Angiotensin II antagonists
3. African descent
4. Renal insufficiency, or serum potassium &gt; upper limit of normal (ULN).  Proteinuria or hematuria or AST/ALT &gt; 3 times ULN at screening
5. Mental health conditions requiring pharmacological treatment
6. History or presence of macrovascular complications from type II diabetes, allergic symptoms such as bronchial asthma, HIV, hepatitis (B or C), immunosuppressive disease, clinically significant autoimmune disease or unstable chronic conditions.  
7. Presence of CNS or cardiovascular diseases, including  QTcF more than or equal to 450 milliseconds at screening. 
8. Systemic steroid use in the last 3 months
9. Participation in another clinical study. Donation of blood within 12 weeks prior to first vaccination. Planned administration of a non-study vaccine 
10. Current consumption of alcohol. Current smokers 
11. Participants who the Principal Investigator deem unsuitable 
12. Participants on medications that could affect blood pressure 
13. Unwilling to use appropriate contraception 
14. Severe, orthostatic or secondary hypertension </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AnGes, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5-20-14, Shiba
Minato-ku, Tokyo 108-0014</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Japan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AnGes, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5-20-14, Shiba
Minato-ku, Tokyo 108-0014
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Japan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetic, pharmacodynamic effects, and exploratory efficacy of AGMG0201 vaccine administered as an intramuscular injection in male and female participants with essential hypertension at two dose levels (low dose; high dose) compared with placebo.

You may be eligible to join this study if you are of non-childbearing potential, between 18 and 79 years of age, and have mild to moderate hypertension

This is a placebo controlled, dose escalation study. Each participant will receive a single injection to the deltoid muscle, followed by a second injection to the deltoid muscle, in the same arm, 30 days later. 

A vaccine for hypertension could potentially reduce or halt the use of antihypertensive drugs and reduce long-term medical expenses. Although current antihypertensive drugs appear to fulfill the unmet medical needs of hypertensive patients, there are still serious issues (e.g., daily dosage of the medication, often for life) that may be a significant financial burden, particularly in developing countries. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-04-319</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sepehr Shakib</name>
      <address>CMAX Clinical Research Pty Ltd 
Level 5, 18a North Terrace
Adelaide
SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>(+61) 8 7088 7900</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 8 7088 7999</fax>
      <email>sepehr.shakib@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Tetsuya Ishihama </name>
      <address>AnGes, Inc. 
5-20-14, Shiba
Minato-ku, Tokyo 108-0014
</address>
      <phone>+81-3-5730-2488</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tishihama@anges.co.jp</email>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sepehr Shakib</name>
      <address>CMAX Clinical Research Pty Ltd 
Level 5, 18a North Terrace
Adelaide
SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>sepehr.shakib@health.sa.gov.au</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sepehr.shakib@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>