<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335084">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000193077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Differential effects of saturated &amp; unsaturated fats on satiety and energy intake</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of fatty acid saturation on satiety &amp; energy intake in healthy male adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight/obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomised, 3 treatment cross-over trial designed to measure the differential effects of saturated &amp; unsaturated fats on satiety &amp; energy intake when delivered as part of a high fat breakfast test meal.  The high-fat test breakfasts (2.0 MJ) containing 26g lipid are given to 18 healthy, lean Body Mass Index (BMI) 18-25 kg/m2) men, each treatment separated by a washout period of at least 3 days. The washout period was not to be greater than 28 days. Participants scheduled their visits as per their availability taking into account the washout period. The breakfasts are high in saturated (SFA, 65% of total fat), polyunsaturated (PUFA, 76%) or monounsaturated (MUFA, 76%) fatty acids, and comprise 2 savoury muffins.  Participants rate appetite sensations using visual analogue scales (VAS) to assess palatability immediately following the meals, and hunger and fullness throughout the day.  
A venous cannula is inserted for sequential collection of blood samples throughout the morning to measure a number of factors thought to be associated with weight control. The test breakfast is served at 0830h and participants are asked to consume the test-meal in full but at their own pace within a 15 minute period. No further foods are allowed throughout the morning until an ad lib lunch meal is served 215 minutes later, at 1205h, to assess energy and macronutrient intake.

High-fat test breakfasts:
The 3 breakfast treatments are High Fat (HF) (50 en% fat) and isoenergetic (2.0 MJ), comprising 2 savoury muffins (ingredients: flour, skimmed milk powder, eggs, tomato, ham, test lipid). The lipids are included as an integral part of the recipe and baked into the muffins. The test breakfast is served at 0830h, co-presented with 300ml water. The treatments differ in fatty acid composition and are (i) high-SFA (from butter fat), (ii) high-PUFA (from safflower oil) or (iii) high-MUFA (from olive oil).</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Energy Intake at ad libitum lunch meal. Lunch items are weighed pre- and post-meal, and energy, fat, carbohydrate (CHO) and protein intake calculated using the dietary program Foodworks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>t=215mins</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) scores for hunger and fullness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time points: t= -15, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90,120, 150, 180, 210, 270, 330, 390 mins</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood analyses:
Response of circulating hormones and other factors associated with appetite regulation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time points: t= -15, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90,120, 150, 180, 210, 270, 330, 390 mins</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- men, aged 18-65y
- lean (BMI&lt;25kg/m2)
- healthy, as ascertained by self-report
- desire to participate in clinical trial</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- type I or II diabetes mellitus
- other endocrine, cardiovascular or metabolic disease
- smoking
- overweight/obesity</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a randomised, cross-over trial. Randomisation is carried out using a Latin square design, whereby the next patient registered is allocated to the sequential randomisation code. The Latin square that determines the order of treatments is made prior to any participant being enrolled into the study. The order by which participants are enrolled into the study determines the order by which they will complete the arms of the study. Allocation is not concealed to research staff</concealment>
    <sequence>A Latin square will be used to randomise the subjects to each of the 3 intervention arms. Each participant is randomized to complete all 3 intervention arms. The order by which treatments are recieved is determined by the order in which participants are enrolled into the study. The first person enrolled will complete the treatments in the order of the first line of the Latin square, the second subject enrolled will complete the treatments as per the order on the second line etc</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/03/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lactopharma</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Fonterra Centre, 9 Princes Street, Private Bag 92032, Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lactopharma</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Fonterra Centre, 9 Princes Street, Private Bag 92032, Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Auckland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Human Nutrition Unit, The University of Auckland, 18 Carrick Place, Mt Eden 1024</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A critical factor in the regulation of energy balance is the control of energy intake. Long-term reduction in intake is likely to result in parallel reduction in body weight and adiposity. Increased consumption of high satiety foods may lead to the subconscious reduction in energy intake and loss of body weight. 
Whilst lipids are commonly associated with poor satiety and weight gain relative to other dietary macronutrients, there is some evidence of a hierarchy within the lipid group itself and that specific lipid groups or lipid components may provide useful tools through which higher satiety food products may be developed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3rd floor, Unisys Building 650 Great South Rd Penrose Private Bag 92-522, Wellesley St Auckland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/05/07/090</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2005</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sally Poppitt</name>
      <address>Human Nutrition Unit, the University of Auckland, 18 Carrick Place, Mt Eden 1024
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 630 5160</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 630 5764</fax>
      <email>s.poppitt@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sally Poppitt</name>
      <address>Human Nutrition Unit, the University of Auckland, 18 Carrick Place, Mt Eden 1024
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 630 5160</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 630 5764</fax>
      <email>s.poppitt@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katy Wiessing</name>
      <address>Human Nutrition Unit, the University of Auckland, 18 Carrick Place, Mt Eden 1024
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 630 3744</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 630 5764</fax>
      <email>k.wiessing@uniservices.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>