<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367843">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000166572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing a brief and standard  parenting intervention for toddler externalising and aggressive behaviours</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating improvements in families who are randomised to receive a brief parent discussion group versus a standard group parenting program (both Triple P- Positive Parenting Program), as compared to a waitlist control group on child externalising and aggressive behaviour, dysfunctional parenting, parenting efficacy, parent relationship satisfaction and parental adjustment.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil known</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ToPP (Toddler Positive Parenting) Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Toddler aggressive behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Toddler externalising behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Standard duration parenting intervention is the 8 session Group Triple P Program. This behavioural family intervention involves 2-hour group sessions held once a week for four weeks, followed by 20-minute individual telephone sessions, also once a week for four weeks. The four group sessions focus on the following topics: positive parenting, helping children develop, managing misbehaviour and planning ahead for high risk situations. These four sessions cover 17 core positive parenting strategies. The group program involves active skills training to teach parents these key parenting strategies, including videotaped modelling of skills, roleplay, rehearsal and feedback. The group sessions are followed by telephone discussions to assist parents to implement the skills learnt in the program. This intervention will be facilitated by a registered psychologist who is also an accredited Triple P Practitioner.

The brief duration parenting intervention is the Triple P Parent Discussion Group focussing specifically on how to manage fighting and aggression.  This intervention involves a single two-hour group session followed by 20-minute telephone sessions, held once a week for two weeks.  The group session covers 8 positive parenting strategies and involves videotaped modelling of key parenting skills and some roleplay, but does not include the extensive roleplay, rehearsal and feedback of the standard duration intervention. This intervention will be facilitated by the same registered psychologist and Triple P Practitioner as for the standard intervention.
 </interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control group - Families in the waitlist control group wait for an 8 week period before choosing which parenting intervention to participate in. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child aggressive behavior problems as measured by the parent-rated Physical Aggression Scale for Early Childhood (PA-SEC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysfunctional parenting as measured by the three subscales of the Parenting Scale parent-report measure: Laxness, Overreactivity and Verbosity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting self-efficacy as measured by the Parenting Tasks Checklist parent-report measure: Behavioural self-efficacy scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental negative affect as measured by the DASS-21 parent-report questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent relationship satisfaction as measured by the parent-rated Quality of Marriage Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Observed child disruptive behavior as measured by the percentage of intervals with disruptive child behavior from a 20 minute clinic videotaped parent-child observation, coded in 10 second intervals by trained coders who were blind to condition .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Observed parent aversive behavior as measured by the percentage of intervals with aversive parent behavior from a 20 minute clinic videotaped parent-child observation, coded in 10 second intervals by trained coders who were blind to condition.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents or carers of a child aged two or three years who are concerned about their child's aggression, and the child scores one standard deviation above the mean on the Physical Aggression Scale for Early Childhood. Parents need to be living in Sydney and able to attend group sessions at the University of Sydney.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>3</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Parents are excluded from participating if they had previously participated in a Triple P Program; if they are receiving (or planning to receive) parenting assistance from another professional; if parents are not able to complete the questionnaires in English; and if the child has a developmental delay (other than a language delay), disability or chronic illness. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation is concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Families are randomly assigned to one of three conditions using the next sequential opaque envelope technique (Doig &amp; Simpson, 2005). The method of sequence generation was simple randomisation using a randomisation table.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis of covariance and multivariate analyses of covariance
A power calculation was conducted using G*Power 3.1 (Faul, Erdfelder, Lang &amp; Buchner, 2007). A sample size of 72 families (24 per group) was estimated to be sufficient to detect a large effect size for 3 group analysis of variance (power=0.80; alpha = 0.05).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/10/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>69</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lucy Tully</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
The University of Sydney
Camperdown NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology
Camperdown, NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Caroline Hunt</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology
The University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomized controlled trial compared the efficacy of a brief parenting intervention with a standard parenting intervention and a waitlist control group, for reducing toddler aggressive behaviour, dysfunctional parenting and related aspects of family functioning. It was hypothesized that both interventions would show superior improvements relative to the control group in child aggressive behaviours and other child and family outcomes, but that the brief and standard interventions would not differ significantly from one another at post-assessment or 6-month follow-up. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Tully, L.A &amp; Hunt, C. (2013). Extending the reach and impact of parenting interventions for toddler externalizing and aggressive behaviour. Paper presented at the 8th International Conference on Child and Adolescent Psychopathology, London.

Tully, L.A. &amp; Hunt, C. (2014). A randomized controlled trial of Triple P Discussion Groups versus Group Triple P for reducing toddler externalizing and aggressive behaviour. Paper presented at 16th International Helping Families Change Conference, Sydney.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building - G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12989</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Caroline Hunt</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, University of Sydney
Camperdown, Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 439723814</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroline.hunt@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lucy Tully</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, University of Sydney
Camperdown, Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 439723814</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lucytully56@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lucy Tully</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, University of Sydney
Camperdown, Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61439723814</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lucytully56@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lucy Tully</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, University of Sydney
Camperdown, Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>lucytully56@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>