<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373230">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001005347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Emergency Lung-Protective Ventilation Implementation Strategy (ELVIS) for mechanically-ventilated patients in the emergency department: a before and after study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Emergency Lung-Protective Ventilation Implementation Strategy (ELVIS) project for mechanically-ventilated patients in the emergency department: a before and after study to compare ventilation parameters, pulmonary complications and clinical outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>n/a.</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The ELVIS Project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mechanical ventilation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Emergency Lung-protective Ventilation Implementation Strategy guideline aims to standardise the mechanical ventilation of intubated Emergency Department patients in a metropolitan tertiary referral hospital. The guideline encourages accurate calculation of 'ideal body weight' (IBW) through measurement of patient height &amp; aims to ventilate patients at 6-8mL/kg of IBW, whilst maintaining a plateau pressure of less than 30cmH2O. It also mandates prescribed ventilation &amp; oxygenation targets empowering bedside nursing staff to adjust ventilator settings or seek early medical assistance in providing finessed, patient-specific, lung-protective ventilation.

It is a quality improvement initiative designed by Emergency Medicine and Intensive Care physicians and approved for implementation by Executive members of both departments. 

ELVIS will be introduced as a quality improvement initiative to senior medical staff (specialist Emergency Physicians and senior registrars), Clinical Nurse Educators and resus- trained nurses via formal in-services. Implementation will take place once 75% of these staff have been educated and signed off for use.

Following the implementation of ELVIS, all patients aged greater than or equal to 16 years, who are mechanically ventilated in emergency department (with the exception of those excluded by clinician discretion, eg. life-threatening asthma) will have their ventilation strategy optimised by the ELVIS guideline. Prospective data will be collected on all mechanically ventilated patients for one year following implementation to ensure quality improvement outcomes are being reached.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a before and after observational study. The comparator group in this trial is the cohort of intubated and mechanically ventilated patients treated in the same facility over the prior two years (2015-2016), before ELVIS implementation. </comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the percentage of mechanically ventilated patients who receive a lung protective strategy (tidal volumes of 6-8mL/kg of IBW whilst maintaining a plateau pressure of less than 30cmH2O) in the emergency department following implementation of the ELVIS guideline and compare this to rates of lung protective ventilation that occurred prior to this implementation (by review of medical records).</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post commencement of mechanical ventilation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the percentage of patients receiving lung-protective ventilation who develop pulmonary complications (eg. atelectasis, pneumothorax or ventilator-associated pneumonia) during their hospital stay, and compare this to rates that occurred prior to this implementation (by review of medical records and radiology reports).</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 30 days of mechanical ventilation or intensive care length of stay (whichever occurs first).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the percentage of patients receiving lung-protective ventilation who reach their predetermined physiological targets (oxygenation and ventilation) (by review of medical records).</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post commencement of mechanical ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the percentage of patients receiving lung-protective ventilation who reach acute lung injury or acute respiratory distress syndrome criteria during their hospital stay, and compare this to rates that occurred prior to this implementation (by review of medical records and radiology reports).</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 30 days of mechanical ventilation or intensive care length of stay (whichever occurs first).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the total ventilator days in patients receiving lung-protective ventilation and compare this to durations that occurred prior to this implementation (by review of medical records).</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 30 days of mechanical ventilation or date of extubation (whichever occurs first).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the hospital length of stay in patients receiving lung- protective ventilation and compare this to durations that occurred prior to this implementation (by review of medical records).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of hospital discharge or one year from admission date (whichever occurs first).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Mechanically ventilated patients (including those intubated prehospital).
Age greater than or equal to 16 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Age less than 16 years
2. Underlying clinical condition or lung pathology not conducive to lung-protective ventilation (at discretion of treating physician).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Following a twelve month trial period, clinical data will be formally reviewed to establish the effectiveness of this strategy including patient demographics, intubation details, physiological observations, ventilation parameters, blood gas results and rates of ventilator-associated pneumonia and acute lung injury. This data will be collated and compared to our current, pre-ELVIS ventilation practices (2015-16 data). 

All analyses will be supervised by a senior biostatistician. 

Normally distributed outcomes will be reported as means (SD) and non-normal data will be reported as medians (IQR). Categorical data will be reported as count and proportions. A two-sided p-value of 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. Multivariable logistic regression with propensity score adjustment will test the hypothesis that ED lung-protective ventilation decreases the incidence of pulmonary complications. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/08/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>24/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Liverpool Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>7103 Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 2170</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Liverpool Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>7103 Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 2170</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>South Western Clinical School, University of New South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Goulburn St
Liverpool NSW 2170</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A small number of patients who are brought to the emergency department need a general anaesthetic. This lets us help them by keeping their airway open, improve their oxygen levels and breathe for them on a mechanical ventilator. Some of these patients have injured or severely diseased lungs. In these patients, a protective ventilator setting (small volumes of breath at lower pressures) reduces rates of death and time on a ventilator. Other patients have normal lungs initially, but are at risk of developing lung disease whilst on a ventilator. The use of the same protective ventilator settings on these patients can reduce the development of severe lung disease, including infections and lung collapse.

Currently, the ventilator settings in our emergency department are set by the bedside, treating clinician. These may not always be with protective settings.

We aim to improve the quality of our care of our ventilated patients by optimising ventilator settings and increasing the frequency by which protective settings are used. This will be done by implementing a guideline (called ELVIS) designed to prompt clinicians and bed-side nursing staff to set the ventilator to patient-specific, protective values whilst promoting frequent reassessment of these targets and adjusting settings on a regular basis to meet the patients needs. This guideline has been developed by both Intensive Care and Emergency Medicine specialists.

The ELVIS guideline will be used on all ventilated patients in the emergency department, unless the clinician believes an alternate method is safer based on their underlying lung disease. For example, asthmatic patients do not need a protective strategy and will not have the guideline used.

Most ventilated patients are transferred from the emergency department to the intensive care unit. These protective ventilator settings will be continued in intensive care.

This study aims to compare clinical data, ventilation settings and outcomes of patients ventilated according to the ELVIS guideline to those who were ventilated during the subsequent two years (2015-2016).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Western Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 7279
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373230-EMERGENCY LUNG-PROTECTIVE  VENTILATION  IMPLEMENTATION STRATEGY v2.0.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373230-ELVIS CASE REPORT FORM.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Partyka</name>
      <address>Liverpool Hospital
Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</address>
      <phone>+61287383950</phone>
      <fax>+61287383984</fax>
      <email>Christopher.Partyka@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Partyka</name>
      <address>Liverpool Hospital
Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</address>
      <phone>+61287383950</phone>
      <fax>+61287383984</fax>
      <email>Christopher.Partyka@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Partyka</name>
      <address>Liverpool Hospital
Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</address>
      <phone>+61287383950</phone>
      <fax>+61287383984</fax>
      <email>Christopher.Partyka@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Partyka</name>
      <address>Liverpool Hospital
Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</address>
      <phone>+61287383950</phone>
      <fax>+61287383984</fax>
      <email>Christopher.Partyka@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>