<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368851">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000805572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Chiropractic for Adolescent Low back pain including Manipulation/Manual Therapy. The CALM Study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Chiropractic for Adolescent Low back pain including Manipulation/Manual Therapy compared to a sham treatment for pain and disability. A randomised controlled trial pilot study. The CALM Study. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-7170 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>CALM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adolescent Low Back Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The chiropractic clinicians will deliver usual chiropractic care in the form of massage, mobilization, manipulation, and exercise prescription. 

1. The patient participants will receive four consultations, of about 15-30 minutes each, of which two will be delivered in the first week, and the other two at subsequent weekly intervals. 

2. The participants will receive the following interventions:

Manipulation
For the purpose of this study lumbo-pelvic manipulation is defined as a localised force of high velocity and low amplitude thrust directed at a spinal joint often resulting in joint cavitation or a cracking sound and/or   

Mobilisation
For the purpose of this study lumbo-pelvic mobilisation is defined as gentle, controlled movements of the spinal joints within the normal ranges of movement and  

Advice to stay active
This is general advice given to the participant to remain active and continue with normal duties within tolerance and as possible. This is as opposed to bed rest and/or

Specific back exercises
Tailored exercises provided to an individual participant by the treating chiropractor for their back pain or

General exercise
Advice to undertake general exercise such as walking or other low impact aerobic activity for 30 minutes on at least 5 days per week and

Modification of activities
Advice to modify daily activities that are likely to worsen the condition or retard recovery

3. A home exercise and other treatment diary will be administered to monitor compliance with exercises and utilization of other treatments for back pain.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Sham group : participants will receive de-tuned ultrasound (no intensity) and de-tuned Activator Trademark treatment that provides a very small impulse provided by a hand held device delivered through a tongue depressor (see: http://www.activator.com/) by the chiropractor to the regions where spinal pain is experienced. To increase the perceived hands on credibility, the chiropractor will be trained to gently place one hand on an area adjacent to the participants spine while delivering the ultrasound and Activator therapies. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome is pain using a visual analog scale for pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be measured one week, two weeks, and four weeks after chiropractic care/sham commences .</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome is disability using a Roland Morris instrument for disability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be measured one week, two weeks, and four weeks after chiropractic care/sham commences .</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of feasibility of conducting a larger, fully-powered, randomized controlled trial. The feasibility of the main study will be determined by assessing the following criteria during the pilot study:
1. all chiropractor clinicians recruited within two weeks
2. 20 patients recruited within four weeks of placing recruitment notices 
3. 100% of recruited patients allocated to assigned group
4. 90% of patients complete baseline measures within 30 mins
5. 85% of patients receive all assigned treatments within three weeks
6. 95% of consultations adhere to treatment protocol 
chiropractors ability to successfully deliver the usual and sham intervention, assessed qualitatively through brief survey instrument/telephone interviews
7. 100% of treatments deemed safe, in that reported adverse events are benign and transitory
complete follow-up in at least 90% of all recruited subjects
8. Treatment costs will be assessed

This is a composite primary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be measured one week, two weeks, and four weeks after chiropractic care/sham commences .</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General Health using the SF-36</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be measured at four weeks after chiropractic care/sham commences</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures of well-being using the EQ-5D-5L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be measured four weeks after chiropractic care/sham commences</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged between 13 and 17 years (inclusive) who have experienced non-specific low back pain in the last month for at least 14 of those days; and have a Visual Analogue Scale for low back pain of at least 3 out of 10 in the previous 24 hours.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known pathology causing their low back pain (for example, fracture, spinal infection, neoplastic disorders); clinical signs and symptoms of a lumbar disc herniation; a history of spinal surgery; not fluent and/or literate in the English language; currently receiving care for low-back pain from any other healthcare provider, or are unable to consent to treatment. Young people will also be excluded if they have previously received manipulation as previous experience of manipulation may affect successfully maintaining blinding. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A registered chiropractor will administer the inclusion and exclusion criteria by way of questionnaire and examination. Suitable participants will be provided information about the study and then offer a consent form. Parents will also provide consent. If admitted to the study, participants will be randomised using block randomisation sequence and a set of numbers sealed in opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>A statistician will generate the block randomisation sequence and then place the allocation (A or B). The sequence will be allocated by a phone call to a blinded Research Assistant who holds the envelopes; this will allow each participant to enter the trial into either the chiropractic care or sham group in a random manner.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a feasibility study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We will analyze feasibility and not effect sizes in this pilot study.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>4</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 South St, Murdoch
6150 WA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>90 South St, Murdoch
6150 WA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A feasibility study for a larger, randomized, controlled trial investigating chiropractic treatment for adolescent low back pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>facebook.com/CALMstudy</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Murdoch University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>90 South St, Murdoch WA
6150 WA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Human Ethics Permit 2015/216.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Walker</name>
      <address>Room 1.011 Building 461 
90 South St
Murdoch University, Murdoch 6150 WA</address>
      <phone>61893601297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Bruce.Walker@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Walker</name>
      <address>Room 1.011 Building 461 
90 South St
Murdoch University, Murdoch 6150 WA</address>
      <phone>61893601297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Bruce.Walker@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Walker</name>
      <address>Room 1.011 Building 461 
90 South St
Murdoch University, Murdoch 6150 WA</address>
      <phone>61893601297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Bruce.Walker@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>