<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365313">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001259730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of self knee taping versus therapist knee taping  in people with patellofemoral osteoarthritis </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of  self taping on pain and function in people with mild to moderate radiographic severity patellofemoral knee osteoarthritis </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SKTPO: Self knee taping for Patellofemoral Osteoarthritis</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Isolated Patellofemoral osteoarthritis or co-existed with tibiofemoral osteoarthritis.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: Commercially hypoallergenic knee tape (Hypafix) will be tested. The knee tape will be used to induce medial gliding of knee patella. Tape will be applied by   physiotherapist 1 in Arm 1. In Arm 2, Tape will be applied by patient after getting detailed instructions from physiotherapist 2. In order to improve adherence from patients in arm 2, Patients will be required to report date and time of taping sessions, and return of unused tape. Patients in both groups will be contacted  every 3-4 days to confirm appointment date (arm 1) or ensure ability to apply self taping. An independent  investigator (observer 1) will open the sealed opaque envelope indicating whether patient will be allocated in arm 1 or arm 2. In addition, he will collect questionnaires after final treatment from observer 2.
The outcome investigator (observer 2)  will remain blinded to test condition (therapist taping vs. Self taping) for the study duration. He will be responsible for distribution and collecting questionnaires at baseline and post-treatment and send them to observer 1.

Arm 1: Therapeutic tape will be applied by Physiotherapist 1 

Arm 2: Therapeutic tape will be applied by patient himself with supervision by physiotherapist 2. 

Exposure: The tape will be applied for 6 weeks starting from first treatment session. Tape will be replaced every 3-4 days at clinic for arm 1. Subjects in arm 2 will be supplied with pre-cut tape to apply at home with detailed instructions. 



</interventions>
    <comparator>The  effects of the self knee tape (treatment group) on pain and function will be compared with therapist-applied knee taping (comparator group) at baseline and after 6 weeks of continuous treatment. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome:  Visual Analogue Score (VAS) of  knee pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>VAS 
Time point: 0 minutes (baseline), 6 weeks post-treatment for arm1 and arm2 groups.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain, function and symptom sub-scores of Knee objective outcome score (KOOS) will be collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>KOOS 
Time point: 0 minutes (baseline), 6 weeks post-treatment for arm1 and arm2 groups.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i) Confirmed diagnosis of Mild to moderate of isolated Patellofemroal or co-existed with tibiofemoral knee osteoarthritis; ii) aged at least 35 years at the time of treatment; iii) pain during aggravating activities present on most days during the past month; and v) radiographic OA severity of greater than or equal to 2 on Kellgren and Lawrence grading (Kellgren, 1957).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i) concomitant pain from hip or lumbar spine; ii) recent knee injections (3 months); iii) planned lower limb surgery in the following 6 months; iv) knee or hip arthroplasty or osteotomy; v) Any history of skin problems prevent application of patellar taping; vii) inability to understand written and spoken Arabic/English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following provision of informed consent, Patients at first treatment session will be allocated randomly by sealed opaque envelopes to either arm 1 or arm 2 groups. This concealed allocation will be performed by independent investigator (from outside of physiotherapy clinic). The assessor will remain blinded group allocation until all analyses have been finalized.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple computer generated randomization</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <state>Eastern Province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>King Khaled General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>King Khaled General Hospital
Hafr Albatin 31991
Eastern Province 
Saudi Arabia </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>King Khaled General Hospital
Hafr Albatin</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hafr Albatin
Hafr Albatin 31991
Eastern Province</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Saudi Arabia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoarthritis (OA) is a global problem, commonly developed in the knee joint. The prevalence of radiographic tibiofemoral osteoarthritis (TFOA) in elderly American subjects is about 44% in those 80 years or older, whereas it is only 27% in those younger than 80 with a slight higher percentage in women than men . The prevalence of patellofemroal osteoarthritis (PFOA) is approximately at same percentage, in patients with degenerative changes of the knee; about half has arthritis in patellofemoral joints. McAlindon, Snow et al. (1992) was among the firsts who investigated the prevalence of PFOA in UK and worldwide; authors reported that 19% of men and 34% of women over the age of 55 have radiographic degenerative changes isolated to the patellofemoral joint in a community based British study. Davies, Vince et al. (2002).

Therapeutic taping (clinical-based) has been used extensively in physiotherapy practice. However, with no availability of cure and progressive nature of patellofemroal osteoarthritis, there is urgent need to test whether simpler and easier to apply taping technique are effective or not. Self taping is a cost-effective and easier to apply technique comparing to clinical-based patellar taping.

This clinical trial aims to explore whether this technique (self patellar taping ) able to produce similar effects compared with commonly used therapeutic taping or not.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical Comittee at KKGH.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>King Khaled Geneal Hospital,
Hafr Albatin, 31991
Eastern Province
Saudi Arabia
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Saudi Arabia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ameer Almubarak</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, King Khaled General Hospital, Hafr Albatin 31991, Eastern Provice</address>
      <phone>+966558877635</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaalmubarak@moh.gov.sa</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ameer Almubarak</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, King Khaled General Hospital, Hafr Albatin 31991, Eastern Provice</address>
      <phone>+966558877635</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaalmubarak@moh.gov.sa</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ameer Almubarak</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotehrapy, King KHaled General Hospital, Hafr Albatin 31991</address>
      <phone>+966558877635</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaalmubarak@moh.gov.sa</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>