<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369795">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000130460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Training students in effective communication strategies via telehealth</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of using people with aphasia to train healthcare students in effective communication strategies over the internet</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1177-7004 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>aphasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group 1: The students will participate in a theoretical lecture about strategies to communicate effectively with people with aphasia. The lecture will be delivered face-to-face by a fully qualified speech pathologist for no more than 1 hour in duration. Following the lecture, all students will have a conversation with 1-2 people with aphasia. The conversations will occur up to one week after the lecture. The students will be in groups of 1-2 students per conversation. The conversations will be conducted over the internet using eHAB software, with the students being at The University of Queensland while the people with aphasia will be at the Princess Alexandra Hospital. The conversations will run for approximately 10 minutes and involve 5 minutes of general conversation followed by 5 minutes of clinical questioning. During the clinical questioning, the students will ask the people with aphasia up to 5 questions to obtain information (e.g., what is your address? How many stairs do you have at home?). Following the conversation, the people with aphasia will provide the students with verbal and visual feedback about their use of conversation strategies. The students then will complete a reflective note about their learning experience before they complete the final outcome measures. To monitor adherence to the study a register of attendance at the lecture and conversation will be kept.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in control group will attend the same training as the intervention group, however, at the completion of the training program, participants in the control group will not receive any feedback from the people with aphasia. The students in control group will participate in a theoretical lecture about strategies to communicate effectively with people with aphasia. The lecture will be delivered face-to-face by a fully qualified speech pathologist for a maximum duration of one hour. Following the lecture, all students will have a conversation with 1-2 people with aphasia. The conversations will occur up to one week after the lecture. The students will be in groups of 1-2 students per conversation. The conversations will be conducted over the internet using eHAB software, with the students being at The University of Queensland while the people with aphasia will be at the Princess Alexandra Hospital. The conversations will run for approximately 10 minutes and involve 5 minutes of general conversation followed by 5 minutes of clinical questioning. During the clinical questioning, the students will ask the people with aphasia up to 5 questions to obtain information (e.g., what is your address? How many stairs do you have at home?). Following the conversation, students will not be provided with feedback about their conversation with the people with aphasia, nor will they watch a reflective video of their conversation. However, the students will complete a reflective note about their learning experience before they complete the final outcome measures. To monitor adherence to the study a register of attendance at the lecture and conversation will be kept.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in confidence when communicating with people with aphasia using a customised 100mm visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately before receiving the training and then immediately after the training.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in knowledge about effective strategies for communicating with people with aphasia (in the form of an open-ended content question)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately before receiving the training and then immediately after the training.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis of the students conversations with people with aphasia according to the Kagan scales (the students skill in providing support for the person with aphasia during the conversation and the level of participation of the person with aphasia in the conversation) (Kagan et al., 2004). The analyses will be conducted by a research assistant who is trained in using the scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the conversations with the people with aphasia.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The students effectiveness communicating during the conversations will be also rated according to Compass Assessment in Speech Pathology (COMPASS) Professional Competency Unit 2 Communication Element 2.1 (Use of interpersonal communication skills to facilitate the effective practice of speech pathology) by the members of the project team. COMPASS is the psychometrically validated competency-based assessment tool used to evaluate student performance on clinical placements Australia-wide, including at UQ and on UQ-organised industry placements (Speech Pathology Australia, 2014). </outcome>
      <timepoint>During the conversations with the people with aphasia.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The students abilities to use the telehealth technology will be evaluated through observational checklists developed by the project team.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the conversations with the people with aphasia.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis of the students conversations with people with aphasia according to conversation breakdowns and repairs (Cunningham &amp; Ward, 2003). This analysis will be conducted by a research assistant who is trained in using the approach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the conversations with the people with aphasia.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standardised Patient Interview Rating Scale (SPIRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the conversations with the people with aphasia.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Students (Intervention and control groups): Students who are in the second or third year of study in the speech pathology program and are currently attending lectures about aphasia at The University of Queensland.

People with aphasia: diagnosed with aphasia by a speech pathologist prior to their inclusion in the study with no other neurological or developmental conditions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Students (Intervention and control groups): inadequate English skills to consent and participate in the program; history of neurological conditions.

People with aphasia: inadequate English skills to consent and participate in the program; history of other neurological or developmental conditions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A computerised random number generator will be used to determine group allocation, which will be concealed at the time of recruitment using opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computerised random number generator</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power calculations for a medium effect size (0.26) with an alpha level of 0.05, power of 0.80 for a repeated measures ANOVA with within-between interactions indicated that a sample size of 32 participants is required. To allow for participant drop out and the fact that not all students enrolled in the course will wish to participate in the project, all students enrolled in the course (n = 100) will be approached about potential participation in the study. 

The students' confidence when communicating with aphasia according to a 100mm visual analogue scale will be recorded before and immediately after the conversations with the people with aphasia. Changes in conversation ratings between the 2 groups at these time point will be analysed using a repeated measures ANOVA (or non-parametric equivalent if the data are not normally distributed).

The students knowledge of effective communication strategies for communicating with people with aphasia before and after the conversations using a written free recall question (i.e., List strategies for communicating with a person with aphasia) will be analysed using repeated measures ANOVAs (or non-parametric equivalent if the data are not normally distributed).

The students videotaped conversations with people with aphasia will be analysed according to: (a) the Kagan scales (the students skill in providing support for the person with aphasia during the conversation and the level of participation of the person with aphasia in the conversation) (Kagan et al., 2004) and (b) conversation breakdowns and repairs (Cunningham &amp; Ward, 2003). Potential differences between the groups on these measures will be compared descriptively.

The students effectiveness communicating during the conversations will be also rated according to Compass Assessment in Speech Pathology (COMPASS) Professional Competency Unit 2 Communication Element 2.1 (Use of interpersonal communication skills to facilitate the effective practice of speech pathology) by the members of the project team. COMPASS is the psychometrically validated competency-based assessment tool used to evaluate student performance on clinical placements Australia-wide, including at UQ and on UQ-organised industry placements (Speech Pathology Australia, 2014). Potential differences between the groups on these measures will be compared descriptively using differences in ratings.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Emma Finch</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland, St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ashley Cameron</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba
Queensland 4102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Jennifer Lethlean</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba
Queensland 4102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kyla Hudson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Tanya Rose</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Jennifer Fleming</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>David Copland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deborah Theodoros</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Steven McPhail</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Functioning and Health Research
Metro South Health
Suite 304
Level 3, Buranda Village
Cnr Ipswich Road and Cornwall Street
Buranda QLD 4102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There has been an increasing move by healthcare providers towards telehealth services (i.e., the remote delivery of healthcare services over the internet). In the university environment the use of telehealth technology has the potential to enable healthcare students to interact with patient populations and build valuable clinical communication skills without leaving the university campus. Research has suggested that while speech pathology students have the theoretical knowledge to treat aphasia (an acquired language disorder often resulting from stroke) they are not confident communicating with this clinical population. Our project will develop and evaluate a telehealth program to train speech pathology students in strategies for communicating effectively with patients with aphasia, and evaluate the clinical useability of telehealth for student clinical learning. The effects of different types of feedback on learning will also be investigated. While targeting speech pathology students in this current application, the intention is to develop a model to be used for other student cohorts who interact with other clinical populations with a range of communication difficulties. This will contribute to the development of new telehealth-driven approaches to clinical education.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QPAH/329</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011000801</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>