<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308314">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000758202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assesment of antioxidant status in vivo and in vitro of guarana (Paullinia cupana).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of  ingestion of a beverage made with guarana powder on plasma and low density lipoprotein (LDL) susceptibility to oxidation  and on antioxidant enzymes status in overweight adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Plasma and LDL susceptibility  to oxidation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Antioxidant acitivity of the Enzymes Superoxide Dismutase, Catalase and Glutathione Peroxidase.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Twelve (12) overweight volunteers will be instructed to gradually  reduce the ingestion of coffee, tea, red wine, chocolate and other foods that contain guarana before 15 days before the visit for the blood collection and during the intervention. Consumption of juice fruits may not exceed 300ml per day and alcoholic beverage will be required to be avoided at least 2 days before each visit. Vollunteers will be asked to avoid taking any antioxidant suplement for 2 weeks beforetheir first visit and throughout the ensuing study periods. They will have their blood  drawn on a twelve-hour overnight fast (T=1) and one hour after guarana consumption the second blood sample will be collected (T=2).  Fifteen days after drinking the beverage made with guarana powder (3g) diluited in cold 300 ml water, two blood samples will be collected: one on a twelve-hour overnight fast (T=3) and other after the fisrt hour of drinking the beverage (T=4). Lipid profile of the volunteers will be evaluated  on the begging and in the end of the intervention. Plasma and LDL at the four moments will be submitted to oxidation by copper (Cu+2) and after that the kinetics of diene conjugate generation and thiobarbituric acid reactive substance (TBARS) will be evaluated as well antioxidant activity of the enzymes gluthatione peroxidase (GPx), superoxide dismutase (SOD), and catalase (CAT) in erythrocites. Antioxidant Total Status of the plasma will be determinated. The Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) damage will be analyzed in blood lymphocytes using the Comet Assay. The Comet assay  successfully assess interactions of
antioxidants with genotoxicants  and it has also proved a valid
technique to evaluate whether antioxidant/micronutrients are
able to protect the integrity of the genetic material.</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects will be their own controls. Each one will have their parameters compared before and after the intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will evaluated plasma total antioxidant status (TAS), the kinetics of diene conjugate generation, and thiobarbituric acid reactive substance (TBARS) contents in plasma, as well as antioxidant activity of gluthatione peroxidase (GPx), superoxide dismutase (SOD), and catalase (CAT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>A baseline blood sample will be collected on a twelve-hour overnight fast (T=1) and after one hour guarana consumption the second blood sample will be collected (T=2). 15 days after drinking the beverage, another blood sample will be collected one on a twelve-hour overnight fast (T=3) and other after one hour of drinking the beverage (T=4).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Commet Assay in lymphocytes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A baseline blood sample will be collected on a twelve-hour overnight fast and 15 days after drinking the beverage, another blood sample will be collected one on a twelve-hour overnight fast.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Body Mass Index (BMI).: 24.90 kg/m2 &lt; BMI&gt; 29.90 Kg/m2 (overweight)
tryglicerides: &lt; 400mg/dl
total cholesterol: &lt;200 mg/dl
LDl cholesterol:  from 100 to 159 mg/dL</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Vegetarian diet,   pregnant , smoking, obesity, diabetes, hypertension,chronic heart disease (CHD) history, hepatic desease, regular use of supplements or drugs, sensibility to caffeine or any other chronic desease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be enroled at Incor - Heart Institute (Clinical Hospital) in Sao Paulo (Brazil) by the ambulatory of chronic coronary disease.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Carolina de Aguiar Martins</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Av. Dr. Arnaldo, 715 - Cerq. Cesar - CEP: 01246-904  - Sao Paulo/SP - Brasil</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The State of Sao Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>R. Pio XI, 1500 - Alto da Lapa - CEP 05468-901 - Sao Paulo/SP - Brasil</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Elizabeth Aparecida Ferraz da Silva Torres</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Av. Dr. Arnaldo, 715 - Cerq. Cesar - CEP: 01246-904  - Sao Paulo/SP - Brasil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Heart and Coffee research group, linked to the Unit of Chronic Coronary disease of the Heart Institute-InCor, HC-FMUSP.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Av. Dr. Eneas de Carvalho Aguiar, 44. Cerqueira Cesar. CEP: 05403900 - Sao Paulo, SP.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Brazil</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to investigate a short and a long term effects of the consumption of a beverage made with guarana powder (3g) and water (300ml) on the inhibition of lipid peroxidation on plasma and LDL of overweigth subjects as well as the antioxidant activity of the enzymes  Superoxido Dismutase, Catalase and Gluthatione Peroxidase in erytrocitys.
Comet Assay will be also perfomed to assess Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) volunteers lymphocytes damage before and after the intervention wiht guarana.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethic Committee of The Public Health - COEP Sao Paulo University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av. Dr. Arnaldo, 715  academic advising
CEP: 01246-904  Sao Paulo  SP</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>166/08
approval number: 1817</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elizabeth Aparecida Ferraz da Silva Torres</name>
      <address>Av. Dr. Arnaldo, 715. Cerqueira Cesar. CEP: 01246-904 - Sao Paulo</address>
      <phone>55 11 30617857</phone>
      <fax>55 11 3061-7130</fax>
      <email>eatorres@usp.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolina de Aguiar Martins</name>
      <address>Av. Dr. Arnaldo, 715. Cerqueira Cesar. CEP: 01246-904 - Sao Paulo.</address>
      <phone>55 11 30617748</phone>
      <fax>55 11 3061-7130</fax>
      <email>carol_nutriusp@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolina de Aguiar Martins</name>
      <address>Av. Dr. Arnaldo, 715. Cerqueira Cesar. CEP: 01246-904 - Sao Paulo</address>
      <phone>55 11 30617748</phone>
      <fax>55 11 3061-7130</fax>
      <email>carol_nutriusp@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>