<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365315">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000450617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Developing an Australian-first recovery model for parents in Victorian mental health and family services.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised control trial of Lets Talk About Children on the mental health recovery of parents with a mental illness.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-642</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mental health
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Let's Talk About Children is an intervention that is applied by adult mental health clinicians to engage with and support parents who have a mental illness in relation to their families and children.  Within the 2-3 session intervention the clinician assists the parent to chart the developmental progress of their children, monitor their wellbeing and to talk to their children about the illness and possible impacts on them and the family. The program provides training for clinicians to, talk to parents, who have a mental illness, about their children, discuss with parents the impact of the mental illness on the children and assist parents in supporting their children to better understand and cope with parental mental illness.  The intervention is implemented in 3 sessions however with clinician and parent agreement this is reduced to 2 sessions based on their judgement that the 3rd session is not required.  Sessions are implemented for 60 minutes once per week.  Clinicians are trained in the intervention by completing 4 online modules (1 hour each) along with a follow up 4 hour face to face training session. The face-to-face clinician training is undertaken within 2 weeks of completing the online modules and the intervention is implemented with parents within 1 month.  The face-to-face training is facilitated by a trained experienced clinician.</interventions>
    <comparator>The wait list control group will be offered the intervention after 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery as measured by the Australian Quality of Life - 8D scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting as measured by the Parenting Stress scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family functioning as measured by the family assessment device</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clients of the participating services
Diagnosed mental illness
Parent living at least some time with children
Over 18 years of age
Capable of giving informed consent as identified by their treating practitioners</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-english speaking clients
Non-custodial parents
Parents deemed too unwell by the clinician to participate in the study (where it is deemed by the practitioner for involvement to do harm to the client) or to be able to provide consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Parent-clients on the caseload of trained Let’s Talk (LT) practitioners will be advised of a research project into recovery by their treating practitioner. They will also receive a brief introduction to the research containing a consent form to be contacted for further information. If potential parent-clients are interested in receiving more information about the study, the parent-client will complete the contact details form and forward to the researchers (by fax, email or reply paid envelope).  The researchers will then contact the parent-client to provide a detailed verbal and written description of the research and to determine their willingness to consent to being involved in the study.

All parent-clients agreeing to participate in the study will be sent a questionnaire pack containing survey measures on recovery, parenting stress and family functioning. A reply paid envelope will be provided with the questionnaire pack for the parent-client to complete and post themselves, or the parent-clients can nominate to be called by the researchers for completion over the phone if they wish. Parent-clients will also complete questionnaire packs (as above) at two later time frames – 6 weeks after completing LT below (or equivalent time frame - an estimated 10 weeks after pre questionnaires) for wait list controls and then a third identical questionnaire package at follow-up (6 to 12 months post LT).

Following the completion of the first questionnaire package all participating parent-clients will then be randomised to either: (1) wait list control group or (2) Let’s Talk (LT) intervention group. The researchers will initially be blind to the allocation of the participant at the collection of informed consent and collection of the baseline data. Following this, an independent admin officer will be contacted to allocate the participant based on the computer generated random sequence allocation that they will maintain. The researcher will advise the practitioner of the outcome of the allocation and from this point on the research assistant who will remain blind to the allocation will collect the post and follow-up questionnaire data. At this stage, parent-clients allocated to the LT group will be advised of the intervention by their treating practitioner and asked if they would like to participate in the intervention. The practitioner will undertake the intervention according to agreement with their parent- client.  If there is agreement the parent client will receive the two to three session LT intervention from their practitioner.  If the parent- client declines the LT intervention they will continue with treatment as usual with their practitioner. Participants will also be advised that they can decline the intervention but continue to participate in the research study or be involved in the intervention and decline to be involved further in the research. 

The intervention involves a discussion between the parent-client and their practitioner about their children, to discuss with parents the potential impact of the mental illness on the children and to assist parents in supporting their children to better understand and cope with parental mental illness. The intervention includes charting the developmental progress of their children, monitoring their well-being and supporting the parent to talk to their children about the illness and possible impacts on them and the family. 

Both intervention and wait list groups will continue to complete the questionnaires at post and follow up data collections as indicated above.  The control group will continue to receive ‘treatment as usual’ from their clinician and will be informed about (and offered) LT as they complete the final follow up questionnaire. Of those parents who also consented to be interviewed they may be invited to participate in a semi-structured interview approximately 10 weeks after completing the first questionnaire package.  Primarily the interview aims to ascertain their experience of the intervention and any impact it may have had on them and their family.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be developed by computer generation of random number sequences via SPSS by the project manager prior to commencing the project, and maintained by the admin officer.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Mixed models repeated measures models 

Participant numbers were initially determined by a power calculation indicating a minimum n equals 54 participants with Crit F equal to 2.46 (using GPOWER 3.1, assuming 3 sectors and 3 repetitions, a small effect size, an alpha of 5% and power of 95%) to be required. However 72 participants will be engage in the study to account for parent and family dropout. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Road
Clayton
Victoria 3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Department of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Lonsdale Street
Melbourne, 
Victoria 3000 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>none</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>La Trobe University
</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Bouverie Centre, 
8 Gardiner St 
Brunswick 
Victoria 3056 

</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Parenting Research Centre </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>5/232 Victoria Parade, 
East Melbourne 
Victoria 3002</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Grattan St, 
Parkville 
Victoria 3010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deakin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>221 Burwood Highway, 
Burwood, 
Victoria 3125</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>SANE</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 226
South Melbourne 
Victoria 3205</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Family Life – SHINE</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Suite 2, 
450 Nepean Highway, 
Chelsea, 
Victoria 3196</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Eastern Health Mental Health Service</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Davey Drive, 
Ringwood East
Victoria 3135</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Northern Area Mental Health Service</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Grattan Street
Parkville 
Victoria 3050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Neami Psychiatric Disability Rehabilitation and Support Service</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>247-249 Rosanna Road
Rosanna 
Victoria 3084</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>beyondBlue</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 6100 
Hawthorn West
Victoria 3122</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research examines the utility of Lets Talk About Children intervention for its application in Australian mental health services. The objectives of the project are to determine the effectiveness of the Lets Talk program, an innovative, evidence-based program which involves training clinicians in talking to mental health clients about their children.  The research will investigate the impact of Lets Talk on parenting confidence and family functioning along with aspects of recovery (e.g. self worth, relationships, independent living) and quality of life, as compared to a control group receiving standard treatment.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Clayton Campus
Wellington Road
Clayton
Victoria 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF13/3300120130017</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/365315-monash-medicine DOHMinisterAug2013final.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Darryl Maybery</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe 
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 429358470</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dmaybery@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Clare Plozza</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe 
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5128 1000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5128 1080</fax>
      <email>clare.plozza@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Darryl Maybery</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe 
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 429358470</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5128 1080</fax>
      <email>dmaybery@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Darryl Maybery</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe 
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 429358470</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 51281080</fax>
      <email>dmaybery@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>