<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365786">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000311651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An evaluation of the treatment efficacy and comfort of a modified Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare (FPH) ICON continuous positive airway pressure device to treat obstructive sleep apnea. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An evaluation involving an in-lab assessment and an in-home trial comparing a modified continuous positive airway pressure device to a comparable market-released continuous positive airway pressure device in terms of treatment efficacy for treating Obstructive Sleep Apnea and comfort.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>1111-1151-3251</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CIA-115 (Internal company naming procedure). Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The investigation device is a modified humidified continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) device (Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare ICON). The modification will include a form of pressure relief, to improve patient comfort. This investigation will focus on fixed CPAP only.

The clinical investigation device will be supplying continuous positive airway pressure with humidity and pressure alleviation to the patient via a hose and mask (mouth/nose). The device will be monitoring the flow signal of the patient in order to detect apnea, hypopnea and flow limitations. In Auto-PAP mode these events will trigger the device to adjust the pressure in order eliminate sleep disordered breathing events. In fixed-CPAP mode this pressure will be fixed to the pressure that the patient was prescribed by a sleep physician. 

For the in-lab portion of the trial, the investigation device will be used for half the night before they are switched over to the control treatment for the rest of the night, or vice versa (randomised). Subjects will undergo a full polysomnograpy (PSG) 

For the in-home portion of the trial, the investigation devices (investigation and control) will be used by the patient at home for a period of 2 weeks, after which they will cross-over to the alternate device. The washout period will serve as the first week on the new device, meaning that only the second week's data (in both arms)will be used for analysis. 

Adherence to therapy is measure by an in-built hours used counter in the CPAP device (as is normal practice for CPAP therapy). As such, there are no additional strategies required for monitoring adherence in the study. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatment comparative to the intervention is the treatment provided by a continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) devices available on the market, designed to deliver the same therapy. 

For this investigation we compare the performance, safety, patient preference and treatment efficacy provided by the investigation device to a market-released comparable CPAP device.

Objective data will be collected by the PSG, the devices, and an additional pressure-flowmeter. The patients will be presented with a custom questionnaire which will gather their subjective data in regards to their perception of the treatment provided by both devices.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This investigation is to inform product development teams of the performance, safety, reliability and patient preference in regards to the investigation device. The efficacy will be scored by the PSG (Apnea-Hyponea index, AHI, the number of times the subject's airway collapses per hour), the device reported efficacy (AHI) and the independent pressure-flow meter. Subjective patient data will also be gathered in the form of a questionnaire which will ask patients about their experience with the investigation device.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>One night of therapy (in-lab). Subjects will be monitored continually throughout the night by a PSG technician, and questionnaires will be completed in the morning immediately following the study. Recorded PSG studies will be scored and assessed after the night of therapy. 

4 weeks at home (2 x 2 weeks). Subjects will take the investigation device home for a designated amount of time to use as their primary treatment device. Interviews at crossover and completion of the trial will include subjective patient data, as well as device reported efficacy and independent pressure-flow measurements. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome of this trial would be to inform product development of potential errors and bugs before the device progresses further along the development cycle.  Potential errors could include the device failing to maintain therapeutic pressure, ineffective pressure relief or a hardware failure during treatment. These bugs/errors will be logged automatically on the CPAP device, and all bugs/errors will be reviewed during the course of the clinical trial by representatives from product development and clinical research. </outcome>
      <timepoint>One night of therapy (in-lab) and/or 4 weeks of therapy as the patient's primary device in a typical home setting. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18+
Diagnosed with OSA by a practicing sleep physician
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients that have used CPAP with pressure relief in the last two years, to prevent bias towards their current device. 

Patients with a known history of Cerebrospinal fluid leak, abnormalities of the cribriform plate, head trauma and/or pneumocephalus

Patients with pathologically low blood pressure, pneumothorax, a previous history of pneumothorax, or for patients who have an increased risk of pneumothorax, such as those with bullous lung disease

Patient with bypassed upper airway

Patients with COPD or respiratory failure

Patients that require supplemental oxygen with their CPAP device

Patients with implanted electronic medical devices (e.g. cardiac pacemakers), to prevent interfernce with/by trial machine</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be selected from our New Zealand internal patient database. Patients will be randomised into two groups - to receive device A or B first. Randomisation will be completed using a randomised number sequence generated by computer - allocation is not concealed to the investigators.  

Anyone diagnosed with OSA is able to join our patient database, a separate ethics application exists for enrolling new patients into our database.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be completed using a randomised number sequence generated by computer - allocation is not concealed to the investigators.  </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As it is a study for the purpose of product development no statistical methods will be used for choosing a sample size. The Sample size is based on previous similar trials we have undertaken. Once the proof of concept is complete, validation tests will be completed (under a different trial) which will have statistical methods employed.

Results will be compared using paired sample t-tests. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hanie Yee</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hanie Yee (Clinical Research Manager)
Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare
Stewart Building
15 Maurice Paykel Place
East Tamaki
Auckland
2013</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15 Maurice Paykel Place
East Tamaki
Auckland
2013</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a common sleep breathing disorder affecting up to 7% of the adult population and characterized by periodic collapse of the upper airway during sleep. Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) is the primary treatment for patients with OSA. Despite the effectiveness of CPAP in abolishing upper airway obstruction, compliance with therapy has been sub optimal at best. Pressure relief was developed to improve patient comfort by reducing the pressure when therapeutic pressure is not required. This trial is a randomised and unblinded study comparing a prototype device with a market released device, and will compare the two based on device efficacy and patient comfort.

This trial will be conducted as a combination of in-lab (at Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Sleep Laboratory,  Auckland) and in-home (where the participant takes the trial device and uses it as their primary therapy for a set duration of the trial). 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disabilities Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Vicars</name>
      <address>Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Stewart Building 15 Maurice Paykel Place East Tamaki Auckland 2013</address>
      <phone>+645740123 Ext. 7759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachel.vicars@fphcare.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Vicars</name>
      <address>Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Stewart Building 15 Maurice Paykel Place East Tamaki Auckland 2013</address>
      <phone>+645740123 Ext. 7044</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CPAPTrial@fphcare.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Vicars</name>
      <address>Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Stewart Building 15 Maurice Paykel Place East Tamaki Auckland 2013</address>
      <phone>+645740123 Ext. 7759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CPAPTrial@fphcare.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Vicars</name>
      <address>Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare Stewart Building 15 Maurice Paykel Place East Tamaki Auckland 2013</address>
      <phone>645740123 Ext. 7759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CPAPTrial@fphcare.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>