<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363746">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000339752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Single Centre Phase II Study Of Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation (HSCT) for Severe Auto-Immune Diseases.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single Centre Phase II Study Of the safety and efficacy of Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation For Severe Auto-Immune Diseases.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Auto Immune disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients are assessed using inclusion and exclusion criteria, some of which are specific for the underlying auto-immune disease, in order to determine whether they are eligible for an Autologous Stem cell transplant. If eligible, all patients are given Cyclophosphamide 2g/m2 as per standard practice on a Saturday or Sunday, followed by G-CSF 10mcg/kg for the next 10-12 days until the following Monday when stem cells are collected. Minimum target CD34+ stem cell collection will be 2 x 10^6/kg. 

Patients will be admitted into hospital for their autologous stem cell transplant within 4-8 weeks of stem cell collection. Patients with all autoimmune diseases (except multiple sclerosis) will then undergo chemo-immunotherapy. This consists of Cyclophosphamide 50mg/kg administered via a central venous line on days -5, -4, -3, and -2. Anti-thymocyte Globulin (ATG - Horse, ATGAM) 10mg/kg will be administered on Days -6, -5, -4 and -3 after a test dose is administered on Day -6. A minimum of 2 x 10^6/kg CD34+ cells without manipulation will be infused on Day 0. 

Patients with multiple sclerosis will undergo BEAM therapy combined with Horse ATG (Atgam). Such a procedure is reported in the guidelines of the cooperative group European Bone Marrow Transplantation (EBMT) and European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR). This includes administration of  carmustine 300mg/m^2 on Day -6; then cytosine arabinoside 200mg/m^2 /day and etoposide 200mg/m^2 /day on Days -5, -4, -3, -2; then Melfalan 140mg/m^2 on Day -1. Reinfusion of stem cells occurs on Day 0. This is followed by methylprednisolone 5mg/Kg /day and horse antithymocyte globulin 20mg/Kg /day on Days +1 and +2.

Standard supportive measures including hydration, antiemetics, and antimicrobial prophylaxis are followed as per institutional protocols.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety, as measured by transplant related mortality (TRM) by day 100. This is defined as death upto 100 days post transplant, not due to the original disease. </outcome>
      <timepoint>day 100</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of HSCT in various auto-immune conditions that are refractory to standard therapies. This will be assessed using standardised clinical and laboratory criteria, specific for each auto-immune disease.</outcome>
      <timepoint> 3 months, 6months, 12months then yearly up to 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion of Systemic Sclerosis patients who have attained a 25% reduction in skin scores, using Modified Rodman Skin score at pre-mobilisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3, 6, 12, 24 months and subsequently yearly up to  5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of Multiple Sclerosis who become wheel chair bound (EDSS 7) at pre-mobilisation. This will be determined clinically and with reference to medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3, 6, 12, 24 months and subsequently yearly up to  5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of Multiple Sclerosis paitents who have improvement in their T2 lesion on MRI at pre-mobilisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 24 months and subsequently yearly up to  5 years </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate whether remission and disease activity correlates with immunological parameters, including immune reconstitution and auto-antibodies. This will be assessed using blood tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-mobilisation and at 12, 24 months and subsequently yearly up to  5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>assess Quality of Life and Health Assessment of patients post HSCT using QOL questionnaires and HAQ forms </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-mobilisation and at 3, 6, 12, 24 months and subsequently yearly up to  5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adequate organ function as measured by: Cardiac LV Ejection Fraction &gt; 45%, total Lung Capacity &gt;60%, Pulmonary artery pressure &lt; 50mmHg, DLCO greater than or equal to 50%.
Negative serology for HBV, HCV and HIV.
Negative pregnancy test.
Able to provide informed consent and the absence of mental and cognitive deficits which can interfere with the capability of providing the informed consent.
Absence of severe chronic infection.
Severe auto-immune disease less than 7 years duration (excluding Multiple Sclerosis) OR Multiple sclerosis of any duration unresponsive to multiple standard therapies including corticosteroids.

Sperm collection or ova cryopreservation is to be offered prior to HSCT in those of child-bearing age

Specific Inclusion Criteria for each disease:
1.Systemic Sclerosis: 
Early, rapidly progressive inflammatory diffuse scleroderma with truncal skin involvement and/or involving lungs and/or heart (myocarditis) which has failed to stabilize with monthly intravenous cyclophosphamide and other anti-rheumatic agents. Ideally patients will also have signs of ongoing disease-related inflammation immediately prior to ASCT. Early disease is defined as disease in which the timing from second symptom onset to ASCT was 7 years or less

2. Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE): 
Diagnosis according to ACR-criteria with  antinuclear antibodies positive on at least two successive tests at three months interval plus disease duration &lt;7 years since the diagnosis or first time of intensive immunosuppressive drugs. Unresponsive to multiple therapies including at least 6 months of the best standard local therapy using prednisone, intravenous cyclophosphamide or mycophenolate mofetil either alone or successively with or without anti CD 20 (Rituximab). Major organ damage (eg: cerebritis, nephritis, pulmonary, cardiac or skin vasculitis) is present despite optimal immunosuppression. 

3. Multiple Sclerosis (MS):
MS clinically defined and supported by laboratory tests (eg:MRI). Patients should have an EDSS between 3.5 and 6.5 at screening evaluation and the presence of one or more enhancing lesion on MRI. Previous Treatment with Nataluzimab is allowed but a minimum of 3 months MUST have elapsed since completion of treatment.

The forms of MS eligible for HSCT include:
a) Secondary Progressive form of MS with or without relapses, with recent worsening of disease in the previous year despite immunomodulating therapy (interferon beta or glatimer acetate) and/or immunosuppressive therapy
b) Relapsing remitting form of MS with recent worsening of disease or accumulation of disability in the previous year despite immunomodulating therapy (interferon beta or glatimer acetate) and/or immunosuppressive therapy.
c) Relapsing-remitting forms of MS who do not accumulate disability but who have at least two relapses per year, in spite of immunomodulating therapy (interferon beta or glatiramer acetate, where approved) or immunomodulating and immunosuppressive therapy and presence of one or more enhancing areas at MRI (possible repetition of MRI within three months). 
d) Secondary progressive form of MS with or without relapses or relapsing-remitting MS form who accumulate disability between relapses (relapsing-progressive) with a worsening documented by EDSS during the last year in spite of the immunomodulating therapy (interferon beta or glatiramer acetate, where approved) or immunomodulating and immunosuppressive therapy, even in the absence of contrast enhancing areas at MRI. 

4. Other Auto-Immune Conditions:
Diseases such as vasculitis, Chrohns disease, Behcets disease refractory to all available therapies and in the opinion of the referring physician, HSCT is a valid therapeutic option for that patient. These patients will require an independent physician to assess the patients suitability for HSCT.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>if specific auto immune disorders does not meet the individual eligibilty criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>open label
Specific conditioning regimens are used dependent on AutoImmune disorder</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/12/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Diseases such as Scleroderma, Multiple Sclerosis (MS), Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE), vasculitis, Chrohns disease, Behcets disease refractory to all available therapies and in the opinion of the referring physician, HSCT is a valid therapeutic option for that patient. These patients will require an independent physician to assess the patients suitability for HSCT. Patients will undergo GSCF stimulated stem cell collection following chemotherapy. Patients are readmitted for autlogous transplant and will have specific  high dose immunosuppresssive therapy depending on their disorder followed by  stem cell re infusion </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/12/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>svhcancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>svhcancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>svhcancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>