<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364861">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001025729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of Partial Body Weight-Supported Treadmill Training (PBWSTT) Compared with Overground Walking Practice on Endurance and Walking Speed in Children with Cerebral Palsy (CP): A Randomised Controlled Trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of Partial Body Weight-Supported Treadmill Training (PBWSTT) Compared with Overground Walking Practice on Endurance and Walking Speed in Children with Cerebral Palsy (CP): A Randomised Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Partial Body Weight-Supported Treadmill Training (PBWSTT) in children. This is a method used in neurological rehabilitation of adults and children that provides task-specific gait training with multiple repetitions and active participation of the client, which has been demonstrated to enhance motor learning.
Partial body weight is facilitated via the use of a harness.  sessions will be administered 2xper week over an 8 week period, each session lasting up to 30 minutes.  Sessions will be administered by the physiotherapists at the school where the study will take place.  Participants will be encouraged to increase their duration and / or walking speed, and / or decrease the amount of body weight support over the duration of the 8 week study as deemed appropriate by the treating physiotherapist.

The number of  sessions and duration of each session will be recorded.  In the event that a participant misses a session they will be provided with a catch up session in the next week.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be provided with the same number of physiotherapy sessions, again lasting up to 30 minutes, over the 8 week period.  the control group will be trained by overground walking, and will be encouraged to increase their speed / duration as deemed appropriate by the treating physiotherapist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in endurance as measured via a Six Minute Endurance Walk (6 MWT) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), immediately after training (week 4) and after completion of training (week 8). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking speed as measured by the 10 metre wlak test (10mwt)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) week 4 and week 8</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in function as measured by the Gross Motor function (88)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), immediately after training (week 4) and after completion of training (week 8).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Students will be included with:
(i) a diagnosis of CP and aged between 6 and 18 years.
(ii) Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) Levels II (walks without assistive mobility devices but has limitations walking outdoor and in the community) and III (walks with assistive mobility devices but has limitations walking outdoors and in the community).
(iii) an ability to follow verbal directions for standardized testing.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Students will be excluded if they had:
(i) visual impairment that could compromise the performance of the tasks.
(ii) a concurrent medical condition such as severe cardio respiratory disease or uncontrolled epilepsy that will pose a risk to their safety during training.
(iii) lower limb orthopaedic surgery or botulinum toxin injections in the 6 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Students will be randomly allocated to the intervention or control group by a block randomisation method according to Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) levels, gender and age (6-12y or 13-18y).</concealment>
    <sequence>For each stratum, the allocation sequence will be generated from a random numbers table with assignments sealed in sequentially number opaque envelopes. After the enrolment, the participants will be assigned to a group by opening the next envelope. This process will be administered by a team member not known to any of the parcitipants and not involved in recruitment or the training programs.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The obtained data will be subjected to statistical analysis using SPSS software to determine the:
1. baseline differences between the groups using independent t tests.
2. effects of training at week 4 and week 8 by ANCOVA.
3. significance between groups using independent sample t tests.
As per the profiling of the students, done for the purpose of database by the school, there is higher number of boys in GMFCS Level II and III with better cognitive abilities as compared to girls. Henceforth, the study will include 20 boys and 10 girls. 


The clinically accepted improvement in gait speed is 0.1m/s.  Using data from Dodd and Foley (2007), who had 2 groups with 7 participants each, the average SD for walking speed at baseline was 0.09m/s.  A power calculation using 0.09 as the SD and a mean change of 0.1, with an alpha of 0.05 and power of 0.8, 14 participants per group are required.  We propose a recruitment target of 30 to cover the possibility of a drop out in each group.

Additionally, a similar study by Willoughby et al (2010) conducted a power calculation using their own pilot data and suggested that 15 participants in each group (30 total) would be sufficient to detect a significant difference for an 80% power at the 0.05 level.  While their results did not reach statistical difference, they recruited a more functionally disabled group (GMFCS III and IV).  The number, duration and frequency of intervention is also clinically feasible in the setting the study will take place in.


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders University of SA</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C Block, Repatriation General Hospital, Daws Road, Daw Park SA 5041 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>None </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>None</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cerebral Palsy Alliance Singapore</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cerebral Palsy Centre, 65 Pasir Ris Drive 1, Singapore 519529</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Singapore</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To investigate the change in endurance, walking speed and function after Partial Body Weight Supported Treadmill Training (PBWSTT) in children with Cerebral Palsy with Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) Level II and III. To compare the result obtained with the overground walking in children with CP. It is hypothesised that children in the treatment group (PBWSTT) will have greater endurance, walking speed and function. 
 
In Singapore there has been a dearth of study to investigate the effectiveness of Partial Body Weight Supported Treadmill Training (PBWSTT) in children with Cerebral Palsy, hence this study will allow the clinician to select appropriate intervention for children with Cerebral Palsy and as well as to investigate the evidence supporting Treadmill Training (TT) with PBWSTT.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Flats G5 - Rooms 3 and 4
flinders Drive
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>317.13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chris Barr</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation, Aged &amp; Extended Care
C Block
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1103</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1130</fax>
      <email>chris.barr@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chris Barr</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation, Aged &amp; Extended Care
C Block 
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1103</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1130</fax>
      <email>chris.barr@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chris Barr</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation, Aged &amp; Extended Care
C Block 
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1103</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1130</fax>
      <email>chris.barr@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Marnie Joyce</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation, Aged &amp; Extended Care
C Block 
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1103</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8275 1130</fax>
      <email>marnie.joyce@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>