<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83240">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/10/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000580370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does the High Intensity Functional Exercise Group program improve clinical outcomes in older people in the sub-acute setting?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The short term effects of a High Intensity Functional Exercise (HIFE) group on mobility in older people in the sub-acute setting.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mobility in older adults</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Activity levels of older inpatients </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients allocated into the intervention will be encouraged to attend the HIFE group three times a week as well as individual therapy aimed twice a week for the duration of their hospital admission. HIFE exercises will be prescribed by the treating therapist according to a previously described, standardised protocol (Littbrand 2006) which includes weight bearing functional exercises for strength and balance targeted at different levels of mobility. The HIFE group sessions will be aimed at least 20 minutes duration. Participants will be encouraged to perform at least 2 balance and 2 strength exercises at a high intensity and the treating therapist will increase the difficulty as appropriate. To maintain a high intensity, strength exercises will be aimed at 8-12 repetition maximum (RM) performed as 2-3 sets, and balance exercises to challenge the participants postural stability. To ensure safety of all group participants, the maximum number of participants in the HIFE group will be limited to 6. All exercises will be performed at a set of rails in the ward gymnasium with one physiotherapist or allied health assistant taking the group. An additional physiotherapist may also assist in the running of the group if the therapist feels another person to assist is indicated e.g. any of the participants require more than the assistance of one person to stand from a chair. Individual therapy sessions may range from 5 minutes to one hour, as deemed appropriate by the treating physiotherapist. The type of exercises in the individual therapy sessions will be determined by the treating therapist as appropriate - these may include strengthening, balance, cardiovascular and range exercises. 
The duration of the trial is anticipated to 3+ years. 
Those who are allocated to the intervention will also be invited to participate in an interview about their experiences of the group physiotherapy.  If consent is obtained for this interview and for it to be audiorecorded, it will take place after participants have taken part in several group sessions. It is anticipated that the interview will take approximately 20 minutes. We aim to continue to invite participants to be interviewed until no new themes emerge from interviews.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control Treatment: 'usual care' inpatient individual physiotherapy sessions, aimed at 5 times per week until discharged from hospital.  They will not participate in the HIFE group program. Therapy session length will be determined by the treating therapist, influenced by the ability of each patient.  It may vary between 5 minutes and 60 minutes and therapy is determined by the treating therapist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Elderly Mobility Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At  baseline (admission to the study) and on discharge if discharge is to their premorbid residence. If the patient is to be discharged into residential care then the final measurement will be taken when the multidisciplinary team have determined the patient has reached a plateau.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Berg Balance Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (admission to the study) and discharge if discharge is to their premorbid residence. If the patient is to be discharged into residential care then the final measurement will be taken when the multidisciplinary team have determined the patient has reached a plateau.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls Rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during hospital admission and totalled upon discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of Stay (days)</outcome>
      <timepoint>On discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Discharge Destination</outcome>
      <timepoint>On discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight (kg)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (admission to the study) and discharge if discharge is to their premorbid residence. If the patient is to be discharged into residential care then the final measurement will be taken when the multidisciplinary team have determined the patient has reached a plateau.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mini-Mental State Examination</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>perspectives of those participating in group exercise on group exercise. A single, semi structured interview will be conducted with a number of participants with a researcher. The interview will be guided by a number of open ended questions and interviews audiorecorded and transcribed verbatim 24 hours after each interview. </outcome>
      <timepoint>after participating in at least 2-3 group exercise sessions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activity levels - time spent upright, sitting, lying down, walking, overall activity levels.
Participants will wear a Positional Activity Logger 2 (PAL2) accelerometer over a 5 day period, comprising 3 week days and 2 week end days. This is attached to their leg and worn 24 hours per day (excluding for showering/hygiene purposes)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days during admission: 3 weekdays and 2 weekend days. This will occur during their admission, after they have participated in at least one exercise group (if in intervention) or anytime if in the control arm. It will be at least 5 days prior to their expected date of discharge. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 65 and older</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those with contraindications to exercise
Premorbidly non-ambulant &gt; 1 month
Palliative Care
Known Length of stay &lt; 7 days
Mini-Mental State Examination &lt;10
Those who require more than minimal assistance of one person to stand from a standard chair with arm rests.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once deemed eligible for the study, an independent clinician who is not in a dependent/therapeutic relationship with the patient will seek informed consent – those with Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) 24/30 or less will have their next of kin contacted for third party acknowledgement.  Patients declining to participate will receive usual assessment and physiotherapy as appropriate.  Those who consent will have their baseline measures assessed and recorded for the study by their treating therapist.  Patients will then be randomised to one of two physiotherapy treatments by a non-treating therapist who is independent of the study team. The randomisation will occur by opening a sequentially numbered opaque envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation by use of a computer generated sequence to create a randomisation table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Baseline measures will be asessed by the treating physiotherapist prior to randomisation.  Outcome measures on discharge will be assessed by a blinded assessor.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>468</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>468</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Caulfield General Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>260 Kooyong Road 
Caulfield 
Victoria 3162</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Caulfield General Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>260 Kooyong Road 
Caulfield 
Victoria 3162</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine the short term effects of a High Intensity Functional Exercise (HIFE) group program on clinical outcomes in older people in the sub-acute setting.  Clinical outcomes include mobility, balance, length of stay and discharge destination.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Raymond, M. J., Burge, A. T., Soh, S. E., Jeffs, K. J., Winter, A., &amp; Holland, A. E. (2016). Experiences of older adults in a group physiotherapy program at a rehabilitation hospital: A qualitative study. J Hosp Med, 11(5), 358-362.
Two abstracts have been accepted for oral presentations at the upcoming World Congress on ACtive Ageing (Melbourne) June-July 2016 on clinical outcomes as well as the qualitative outcomes as above. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria
3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/08/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>190/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe Faculty of Health Sciences Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>La Trobe University
Melbourne
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>FHEC 09/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/01/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Melissa Raymond</name>
      <address>Caulfield General Medical Centre
260 Kooyong Road 
Caulfield 
Victoria 3162</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 6000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.raymond@cgmc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Melissa Raymond</name>
      <address>Caulfield General Medical Centre
260 Kooyong Road 
Caulfield 
Victoria 3162</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 6000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.raymond@cgmc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Melissa Raymond</name>
      <address>Caulfield General Medical Centre
260 Kooyong Road 
Caulfield Victoria 
3162</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 6000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.raymond@cgmc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Melissa Raymond</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Dept, Caulfield Hospital
260 Kooyong Road Caulfield Vic 3162</address>
      <phone>+61390766000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.raymond@cgmc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>