<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364075">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000461796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of pacemaker on cardiac function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of permanent pacemaker implantation with lead in right ventricular apex (RVA) versus right ventricular outflow tract (RVOT) on cardiac function in patients requiring pacemakers due to heart block</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>“SELECT SITE” STUDY </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Block</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pacemaker lead implantation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Consecutive patients with AV block, scheduled to undergo dual chamber pacemaker implantation will be recruited into the study. Patients will be randomised to RVOT (Intervention arm) or RVA (Control arm) pacing groups according to a computer generated randomisation schedule.
Patients who are randomised to intervention arm will have the pacemaker lead implanted in the right ventricular outflow tract (RVOT). These patients will be followed up 6 monthly for the period of study i.e 36 months and will have investigations as per schedule .
The total duration of the procedure will be 60-90 minutes.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the control arm will have pacemaker right ventricular lead implanted in Right ventricular apex (RVA). Rest of the procedure will be same in both arms. These patients will be followed up 6 monthly in the pacemaker clinic and will have investigations as per schedule for the period of study i.e 36 months.
The total duration of the procedure will be 60-90 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Investigate the effect of apical and septal right ventricular site pacing on left ventricular structural change and ejection fraction using cardiac MRI in RVA group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months, 24 months and 36 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life( QOL) Assessed by 
*New York Heart Association Functional class
*subjective validated patient scoring algorithm (SF36/ MLWHF)
* 6 min walk test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12,24,36 MONTHS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect on cardiac Biomarkers assessed by :
N-terminal pro-hormone brain natriuretic peptide (NT pro-BNP), High sensitivity C reactive Protein (HsCRP)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12,24,36 MONTHS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New-onset atrial tachyarrhythmia assessed by pacemaker check
</outcome>
      <timepoint>AT 12,24,36 MONTHS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Effect of cardiac remodeling on its hemodynamics assessed by 6 min walk test,cardiopulmonary VO2 Max test and Echo parameters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12,24,36 MONTHS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lead-related complications such as lead dislodgement, myocardial perforation, lead integrity failure</outcome>
      <timepoint>12,24,36 MONTHS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The impact of ventricular pacing site to right ventricular and atrial remodelling by cardiac MRI and Echocardiogram </outcome>
      <timepoint>12,24,36 MONTHS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomarkers of myocardial fibrosis e.g. MMP-9, TIMP-1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12,24,36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New onset heart failure, heart failure related hospitalizations. CRT-P, CRT-D or AICD upgrade from History</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12,24,36 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age &gt;18 years old
Patients with high grade AV block 
Able and willing to comply with all pre-, post- and follow-up testing, and requirements 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients indicated for an Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillator or Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy.
Myocardial Infarction, Bypass surgery or Valve replacement within 3 months prior to enrollment.
Patients where a right ventricular lead cannot be placed i.e. complex congenital heart disease.
Patients with hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy.
Patients with acute coronary syndrome, unstable angina, severe mitral regurgitation and/or hemodynamically significant aortic stenosis.
Known permanent atrial fibrillation prior to enrollment.
Terminal conditions with a life expectancy of less than two years.
Participation in any other study that would confound the results of this study.
Psychological or emotional problems that may interfere. 
Pregnant patients.
Musculo- skeletal disease hampering the realization of a 6-minute walk-test.
Previous non MRI compatible device
Renal Dysfunction with eGFR &lt; 60ml/min
Any contraindication for MRI
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutive patients with AV block, scheduled to undergo dual chamber pacemaker implantation will be recruited into the study.Enrolment into the study will be made by independent research nurse if the patient meets the inclusion and exclusion criteria. This nurse will not be involved in randomisation of the patient and will be done by investigators.  Patients will be randomised to RVOTS or RVA pacing groups according to a computer generated randomisation schedule. The total number of patients screened to obtain the sample, and reasons for their exclusion, will be recorded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation will be used</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The statistical methodology for the study has been determined in consultation with the Data Management and Analysis Centre, University of Adelaide. The primary endpoint of the study is time to development of LV systolic dysfunction in RVA group. 
All analyses will be based on the intention to treat principle. The primary outcome of time to development of LV systolic dysfunction in RVA group will be compared between randomised groups using a Cox proportional hazards model. Differences between the groups will be expressed using a hazard ratio and 95% confidence interval. Key secondary outcomes such as rates of atrial or ventricular arrhythmia episodes will be analysed using either Cox proportional hazards models or Fine and Gray competing risks regression as appropriate. Continuous secondary outcomes such as the 6-minute walking distance, SF36 scores, MLWHF score will be compared between randomised groups over time using linear mixed effects models.
All continuous variables will be reported as mean +/- standard deviation where normally distributed. Mixed effects modelling will be employed to evaluate the difference in LV ejection fraction as a primary endpoint between the two groups. Statistical significance will be two-sided and will be established at p&lt;0.05. 
Echocardiographic, haemodynamic, and CMR outcomes for patients will be evaluated as described above. Symptomatic outcomes will be evaluated by NYHA classification and by SF36 and MLWHF score. Objective change in functional capacity will be measured by 6-minute walk distance and by VO2 PEAK . 
The outcomes of the study groups will be compared by mixed effects modelling to determine the effect of pacing modality on the primary endpoint.

Power Calculation : The patient numbers have been selected based on previous published literature evaluating the change in LV ejection fraction using RVA pacing versus RVOTS pacing. Ninety patients are required in each group to find a 5% difference in follow-up LV ejection fraction with a power of 90% and a significance level set at 0.05 assuming a common baseline LVEF of 60% with standard deviation of 10%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5001 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5086 - Manningham</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Adelaide, Centre for Heart Rhythm Disorder</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 
5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia
5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Medtronic
Cardiac Rhythm Disease Management External Research Program</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clinical Research Manager, CRDM
Medtronic Australasia Pty Ltd.
97 Waterloo Road ; North Ryde, NSW 2113 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Introduction: Right ventricular apical (RVA) pacing results in abnormal left ventricular (LV) electrical and mechanical activation and is associated with adverse effects on left ventricular systolic function. The comparative effects of right ventricular outflow tract septal (RVOTS) pacing on cardiac structural remodeling are unknown. Our aim is to therefore examine the long-term effects of septal RVOT versus RVA pacing on ventricular and atrial structure and function using cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR).
Methods/Design: A multicenter randomised controlled trial in which 180 patients with an indication for ventricular pacing using a permanent pacemakers (PPM) will be randomized to pacing either from the RVA or RVOT septum. All patients will have a baseline CMR, Echocardiogram, 6-minute walk test, quality of life scoring e.g. SF36, Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Score (MLWHF) and blood tests such as NT pro-BNP, HsCRP and biomarkers of myocardial fibrosis e.g. MMP-9, TIMP-1. The tests will be repeated at 12 months, 24 months and 36 months. The following clinical outcomes will be used:
Primary Endpoint: 
Investigate the effect of apical and septal right ventricular site pacing on left ventricular structural change and ejection fraction using cardiac MRI.
 
Secondary Endpoint:
 
Clinical Parameters: 
New York Heart Association Functional class, Quality of life assessed by a subjective validated patient scoring algorithm (SF36/ MLWHF), 6 min walk test.

Biologic Parameters: 
N-terminal pro-hormone brain natriuretic peptide (NT pro-BNP), High sensitivity C reactive Protein (HsCRP), Biomarkers of myocardial fibrosis e.g. MMP-9, TIMP-1.

Combined clinical end point: 
New-onset atrial tachyarrhythmia, new onset heart failure, heart failure related hospitalizations. CRT-P, CRT-D or AICD upgrade.
The Effect of cardiac remodeling on its hemodynamics.
Lead-related complications such as lead dislodgement, myocardial perforation, lead Will integrity failure
The impact of ventricular pacing site to right ventricular and atrial remodeling.

Conclusion: 
The results of the study will provide new information about the potential benefits in mechanical function and consequent clinical endpoint(s) of septal versus apical pacing.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Human Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA
Adelaide
5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/RAH/174</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorder
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Prash.Sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorder
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Prash.Sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorder
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Prash.Sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rajeev Pathak</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorder
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rajeev.Pathak@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>