<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372513">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001531303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does intranasal oxytocin enhance emotions in dementia?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study: Intranasal oxytocin administration as a potential symptomatic intervention treatment to improve emotion recognition in patients with dementia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vascular dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this 1 week, double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled crossover trial, all participants will be randomised to either an intranasal administered oxytocin (72 IU; One 36 IU doses of oxytocin/placebo per nostril twice daily) or placebo nasal spray (one dose per nostril twice daily) for one week. This is followed by a one week washout period and a further one week crossover period with the alternative medication.

Intervention adherence will primarily be monitored using a chart completed by the carer of the participant living with dementia, after each administration. Additionally, participants will be required to return empty medication packets at the end of each intervention week whereby the investigators will measure nasal-spray bottle weight to elucidate drug adherence</interventions>
    <comparator>The participants in the placebo group will self-administer a saline mist nasal spray (one dose per nostril) twice daily for one week. The placebo saline mist nasal spray will be placed in an identical bottle to the active drug but only contain glycerol (2%); sorbitol crystaline powder (2 %); benzyl alcohol (0.9 %) and distilled water. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The ability to infer mental states with the Reading the Mind in the Eyes Test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration; between 45 and 90 minutes post single dose administration; and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants perspective-taking as assessed by the carer version of the Interpersonal Reactivity Index. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants empathic concern as assessed by the carer version of the Interpersonal Reactivity Index. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Speed and emotion recognition as assessed by the Facial Speed and Recognition Task.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration; between 45 and 90 minutes post single dose administration; and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotion recognition as assessed using the Emotion Evaluation Test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotion discrimination as assessed using the Emotion Discrimination Test.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in patient-carer relationships as reported by the carer on the Intimate Bond Measure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in patient apathy as reported by the carer on the Apathy Evaluation Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in caregiver burden as reported by the Zarit Burden Interview.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in the participants quality of life as reported by the WHO (Five) Well-Being Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the participants sleeping habits as reported by the carer on the HBA Sleep Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the participants behaviour as reported by the carer on the Socioemotional Dysfunction Scale.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the participants cognitive and behavioural changes as assessed by the Carer-Report Functional Decline Scale.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the carers mood as assessed by the 15-item Geriatric Depression Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the participants behaviour (e.g., aggression, apathy, disinhibition, irritability) and mood (e.g. depression, dysphoria, anxiety, elation) as assessed by the Neuropsychiatric Inventory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in participant's neuropsychological status as measured by a neuropsychological test battery comprising the following domains: Memory (Hopkins Verbal Learning Test); Reaction Time (Trail Making, Part A); Executive Functioning (Trail Making Part B, Verbal Fluency, Stroop); and Working Memory (WAIS-III Digit Span).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in the participant's blood levels of oxytocin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>in-vivo brain changes associated with intranasal oxytocin administration via magnetic resonance spectroscopy in the first 15 randomised participants who are eligible and consent to undergo a brain MRI scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at the first 1 week treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in the carers' quality of life as reported by the WHO (Five) Well-Being Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre single dose administration and at 1 week for each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible participants must:
1. 60 to 90 years of age
2. Have a diagnosis of mild AD, Vascular Dementia or mixed AD / Vascular Dementia 
(MMSE &gt; 21)
3. Have a carer who will be able to live with the participant during the study
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they:
1. Have prior history psychiatric disorders (e.g. major depression, schizophrenia, bipolar disorder)
2. Have a score of =&lt; 40 on the Benton Facial Recognition Test
3. Have a score on the 18-item Hamilton Depression Rating Scale greater than 16
4. Prescribed an anticholinesterase medication for less than three months or are experiencing side effects secondary to this class of medication. 
5. Currently prescribed any of the following classes of medications: non-anticholinesterase medications for dementia, antipsychotics, antidepressants, benzodiazepines, sedatives, and hypnotics
6. Have prior history of neurological disorder (e.g., head injury, stroke or transient ischemic attack, epilepsy)
7. Have a diagnosis of another neurodegenerative disease (e.g., Dementia with Lewy Bodies, Frontotemporal Dementia, Parkinson Disease Dementia)
8. Have an intellectual disability
9. Have a current history of substance abuse
10. Has a history of a myocardial infarction within the last two years or congestive heart failure
11. Current uncontrolled hypertension
12. Current bradycardia (rate &lt; 50 beats per minute/bpm) or tachycardia (rate &gt; 100 bpm)
13. Has a diagnosis of long QT syndrome
14. Current use of prostaglandins and their analogues
15. Current use of any anaesthetic (inhalation or caudal)
16. Known allergies to oxytocin or to preservatives in the nasal spray
17. Participants with severe nasal obstruction/blockage
18. Participants with severely compromised hepatic function
19. Participants with severely compromised renal function</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is "off-site" (Royal Prince Alfred Pharmacy, Sydney Camperdown, NSW) to the central administration site. Participants will be enrolled "on-site" at the central administration site (Brain and Mind Centre, University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW).

</concealment>
    <sequence>Prior to study enrolment, all participants will be provided with a sequential screening number. This screening number will identify the participant up until eligibility and enrolment is confirmed. Following enrolment, the participant will be allocated the next available unique randomisation ID. All randomisation IDs will be generated through randomisation software, using a random block size that is not available to staff who enrol participants. Regardless of treatment allocation (oxytocin or placebo), the first 15 randomised participants who are eligible and consent will be offered to undergo a brain MRI scan.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Men and women aged 60-90 years with a diagnosis of early Alzheimer's disease and/or Vascular dementia (MMSE &gt; 21) will be referred from the Healthy Brain Ageing Clinic, at the Brain and Mind Centre. Once consent is obtained and eligibility is confirmed by a Geriatric medical practitioner along with the Trial Coordinator, the participant will be enrolled in the study. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This study is a pilot study to determine an overall effect size to fund larger trials. Based on previous similar studies, it is estimated there will be &gt;80% power to determine a medium to large effect size with this sample of 40 participants (and crossover design).

Repeated measures ANOVAs will be used to model change in all primary social cognition outcome variables and all secondary outcome variables over time as functions of treatment (oxytocin and placebo).  All analyses will be two-tailed with an alpha of 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Brain and Mind Centre - University of Sydney - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2006 - The University Of Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brain and Mind Centre, University of Sydney
100 Mallett Street
Camperdown,
NSW, 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Judith Jane Mason &amp; Harold Stannett Williams Memorial Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ANZ Trustees
Level 4, 100 Queen Street
Melbourne Vic 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alzheimer's Australia Dementia Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>42 Macquarie St,
 Barton ACT 2600
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with dementia often experience difficulty in recognising the emotions of other people, such as fear, anger and sadness. This can impact upon relationships and social interactions thus causing distress for the individual living with dementia as well as for family members and friends. This study investigates whether a naturally occurring hormone in the body, oxytocin, can help people with Alzheimer's disease and/or Vascular dementia recognise the emotions of other people better. It is hypothesised that patients who receive the oxytocin nasal spray will demonstrate improved accuracy of emotion recognition, following a single dose and repeated administration over one week. Furthermore, it is also hypothesised carers of patients who receive the oxytocin nasal spray will report improved interactions and reduced caregiver burden. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics and Governance Office, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office (REGO)
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital,
Camperdown, NSW, 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X15-0255 &amp; HREC/16/RPAH/638</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sharon Naismith</name>
      <address>The Brain &amp; Mind Centre
Healthy Brain Ageing Program, 
94 Mallett St, Camperdown
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2050 AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61293510781</phone>
      <fax>+61293510551</fax>
      <email>sharon.naismith@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Johannes Michaelian</name>
      <address>The Brain &amp; Mind Centre
Healthy Brain Ageing Program, 
94 Mallett St, Camperdown
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2050 AUSTRALIA

</address>
      <phone>+61293510621</phone>
      <fax>+61293510551</fax>
      <email>johannes.michaelian@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Johannes Michaelian</name>
      <address>The Brain &amp; Mind Centre
Healthy Brain Ageing Program, 
94 Mallett St, Camperdown
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2050 AUSTRALIA
</address>
      <phone>+61293510621</phone>
      <fax>+61293510551</fax>
      <email>johannes.michaelian@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Johannes Michaelian</name>
      <address>The Brain &amp; Mind Centre
Healthy Brain Ageing Program, 
94 Mallett St, Camperdown
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2050 AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61293510621</phone>
      <fax>+61293510551</fax>
      <email>johannes.michaelian@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>