<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369930">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000094471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Long term impact of targeted drug counselling intervention on medication adherence in Inflammatory Bowel Disease patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Long term impact of targeted drug counselling intervention on medication adherence in Inflammatory Bowel Disease patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-5327</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients are given two screening questionnaires to determine if they are adherers or non-adherers  
The Medication Adherence Rating Scale (MARS) is a validated questionnaire that represents medication adherence comprising of 4 simple questions. A score below 17 represents medication non-adherence. 
The Beliefs about Medication Questionnaire (BMQ) is a validated questionnaire assessing a subjects perception of necessity of medications and concerns about medications. This questionnaire helps guide the direction of the counselling / educational intervention.  
Patients identified as non-adherers are assigned to the intervention group and will receive a ONCE off personal (one on one) drug counselling session with an experienced IBD pharmacist lasting approximately 20 minutes. 
Further questionnaires are given out on a 3 monthly basis to monitor for changes in adherence and to detemine the effectiveness of the intervention</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients who were screened with the two questionnaires and not assigned to the non-adherers group were assigned to the adherers group as a control. 

Controls, as they have good adherence at baseline, do not require intervention. However, they will be followed up to ensure their adherence remains optimal. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in adherence assessed by the Medication Adherence Rate Scale(MARS) score </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3,6,9,12,15,18,21,24 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in medication Acceptance as determined by Beliefs about medications questionnaire (BMQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3,6,9,12,15,18,21,24 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in medication necessity as determined by Beliefs about medications questionnaire (BMQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3,6,9,12,15,18,21,24 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in medication concerns as determined by Beliefs about medications questionnaire (BMQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3,6,9,12,15,18,21,24 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Confirmed diagnosis of IBD
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not taking medications at the time of screening
Incomplete questionnaires at screening.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>N./A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Non-adherers will receive the educational counselling. 
Adherers do not require educational counselling as they already take their medication, but will be followed up to determine whether adherence is dynamic and changes over time. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Preliminary studies determined the Cohens effect size value to be (d=0.99) suggesting a large effect size difference between adherers and non-adherers. With a two-sided alpha level of 0.05, a sample size between 24 to 54 non-adherers was required to provide a statistical power of 80%. As non-adherence in IBD patients is approximately 35-45% , a target sample size of 120 was calculated to be sufficient to gather the required amount of non-adherent patients and adherers..

 Missing data were replaced by the last-observation-carried-forward (LOCF) method for patients who could not be contacted or refused further follow up. All analyses were performed on the basis of the intention-to-treat principle. Non parametric test such as the Mann-Whitney test was used for continuous variables and chi-square test for categorical variables. Analyses were performed with SPSS software, version 20.0.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>12/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>21/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>116</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Bankstown-Lidcombe Hospital - Bankstown</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2200 - Bankstown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Rupert Leong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept of Gastroenterology and Liver Services
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2139</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Concord Repatriation General Hospital Dept of Gastroenterology and Liver Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Dept of Gastroenterology and Liver Services
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2139</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Psychological factors are often underrepresented although important in medication adherence. Interventions geared towards education may help facilate adherence.

Two questionnaires were administered to screen IBD patients. The Medication Adherence Rating Scale (MARS) questionnaire screened for non-adherence and consisted of four questions on a Likert-type scale. The Beliefs about Medications Questionnaire (BMQ) addressed necessity and concerns. The BMQ consisted of ten questions on a 5-point Likert scale  The first five questions addressed patient necessity towards medications and the last five questions addressed patient concerns regarding medications totalling a maximum of 25 points per domain. High necessity and concerns was determined with a score of &gt;15/25 in each corresponding domain. Patients with MARS scores below 17 were classified as non-adherers and were offered a structured personalised counselling session with an IBD pharmacist addressing misperceptions, concerns, risk and other queries. Adherers were recruited as controls. All patients were followed up with the MARS and BMQ questionnaire on a three-monthly basis for a maximum of two years or until the study period had elapsed. The primary outcome was adherence measured by the MARS score. Secondary outcomes were medication necessity, concerns and acceptance. Medication acceptance was defined as high necessity &gt;15/25 and low concerns score &lt;16/25. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee - CRGH</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Concord Repatriation General Hospital(CRGH)
Hospital Road
Concord NSW 2139</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11/217</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rupert Leong</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Liver Services
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital,Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61297676111</phone>
      <fax>+61297676767</fax>
      <email>rupert.leong@swsahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rupert Leong</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Liver Services
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital,Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61297676111</phone>
      <fax>+61297676767</fax>
      <email>rupert.leong@swsahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rupert Leong</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Liver Services
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital,Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61297676111</phone>
      <fax>+61297676767</fax>
      <email>rupert.leong@swsahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rupert Leong</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Liver Services
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital,Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>61297676111</phone>
      <fax>61297676767</fax>
      <email>rupert.leong@swsahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>