<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367173">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001093673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does giving antibiotics or not after draining acute perianal abscess in adult patients affect further anal fistula formation? A prospective randomized controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison between giving antibiotics and not giving antibiotics after draining acute perianal abscess in adults in terms of anal fistula formation. A prospective randomized controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peri Anal Abscess</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will be operated in Lithotomy position. Anaesthesia whether spinal or general will be determined by the patients and anaesthetist preference and according to patientss general condition. Examination under anaesthesia will be done first, the area of the abscess will be cleaned with povidone iodine. An alcohol swab will be used to disinfect the area of aspiration. A 10 cm syringe will be used for aspiration of a sample from abscess contents and will be sent for culture and sensitivity study after which abscess will be incised and drained.Patients will be allocated randomly (using closed envelope technique) into two groups: Group A for patients who will receive oral metronidazole (500mg, three times daily TDS for for 3 days , then same antibiotic may be continued for another 4 days or different antibiotic may be given based on results of culture and sensitivity of aspiration sample) as post operative antibiotic. Type of antibiotic  will be changed after three days according to the results of the culture and sensitivity of the pus sample taken from the abscess. Patients will be followed up at 1,3,6, and 12 months to detect anal fistula formation.</interventions>
    <comparator>group B for patients  will not receive postoperative antibiotics. Patients will be followed up at 1,3,6, and 12 months to detect anal fistula formation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anal Fistula formation</outcome>
      <timepoint>By examination by the doctor (blinded) in outpatient clinic at 1,3,6,and 12 months post operatively and diagnosis will depend on creation of anal fistula at the same site of preexisting perianal abscess. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All adult patients complaining of perianal abscess presented to ER department of Aseer Central Hospital and Najran Hospital will be included in this study. Diagnosis of peri anal abscess will be on clinical bases. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Patients with already formed anal fistula (as the outcome will not be valid)
*Patients with pelvi-rectal abscess (as the approach of surgery is different)
*Patients with known compromised immune state as DM, malignancy or receiving steroid therapy (as these people require antibiotic coverage to prevent serious complications)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>closed envelope technique</concealment>
    <sequence>One hundred opaque envelope will contain 50 group A and 50 Group B will be prepared and shuffled (in each hospital 25 for each group).  An operative nurse with no relation to the research will choose an envelope and inform a resident (not involved in the research) who will prescribe the post operative treatment for the patient without informing the surgeon</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size was calculated to be 44 patients (90% power). It was determined  based on the Epi info Statcalc version 6(1993) statistical program  with a assuming incidence of fistula formation  from 38%-50%.
t test will be used to compare between the two groups</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>88</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <state>Abha/Najran</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>King Khalid University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Greiger 
Zip: 61421
P.O.: 641
Abha
Saudi Arabia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Aseer Central Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>King Abdullah Road
PO Box 34
Zip: 62523
Abha
Saudi Arabia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Perianal abscesses are common and important clinical problems. Previous studies have reported that the development of fistula after perianal abscess formation is related to the bacteriology of the abscess and that accurate microbiological analysis of the abscess was very useful in predicting an underlying anal fistula. There was, however, little data concerning the prevention of fistula formation in patients with a perianal abscess without identified fistula.The present study aims to assess if making culture and sensitivity of pus swab and treating the patient with the specific antibiotic following incision and drainage of perianal abscess has any significant impact on surgical outcome in terms of fistula formation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Walid Abd El Maksoud MD, MRCS</name>
      <address>King Khalid University, Abha, Saudi Arabia Faculty of Medicine Department of General Surgery	Zip: 61421 P.O.: 641</address>
      <phone>+966543128555</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr.waleedmaksoud@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Walid Abd El Maksoud MD, MRCS</name>
      <address>King Khalid University, Abha, Saudi Arabia Faculty of Medicine Department of General Surgery	Zip: 61421 P.O.: 641</address>
      <phone>+966543128555</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr.waleedmaksoud@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Walid Abd El Maksoud MD, MRCS</name>
      <address>King Khalid University, Abha, Saudi Arabia Faculty of Medicine Department of General Surgery	Zip: 61421 P.O.: 641</address>
      <phone>+966543128555</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr.waleedmaksoud@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>