<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347847">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/12/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001280998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of acceptance-mindfulness therapy in children with anxiety: a controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of Acceptance and Commitment Therapy versus Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for anxiety disorders in children and adolescents.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-3789</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Acceptance and Commitment Therapy group-based manualised therapy program delivered as 10 x 1.5 hour sessions over 10 weeks, involving up to 8 children and their caregivers in each group. The ACT program will involve the 'Cool Mind' and 'Mindchill' programs, developed at The Childrens Hospital at Westmead, for children aged 7-11 years and 12-17 years, respectively. They are both ACT-based adaptations of Cool Kids and Chilled programs, described below, and were designed to conform to the overarching structure of these programs for comparison purposes. These ACT programs were developed on the basis of ACT-consistent protocols adapted from Lee and Semples (2008) Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy for Children protocol;  Murrell and Wilsons Acceptance and Commitment Therapy Adapted for Children (Murrell &amp; Wilson, 2003), Cayouns MiCBT protocol (Cayoun, 2009), and Harris ACT Mindfully Workshops (Harris, 2007). This program incorporates all six ACT core therapeutic processes that target psychopathology (as described above) including Acceptance, Being Present/Mindfulness, Valued directions, Committed Action, Self-as-context and Cognitive Defusion. In Mindchill, adolescents will learn skills to manage the distress associated with anxious thoughts and feelings. For example, rather than the CBT approach to fighting anxiety and being in control, this program will concentrate on anxiety management via supporting adolescents to identify their values and behave in a value-consistent way, whilst encouraging acceptance of anxious thoughts and feelings that may arise in the process of doing so.

Arm 2: Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT) group-based manualised therapy program delivered as 10 x 1.5 hour sessions over 10 weeks, involving up to 8 children and their caregivers in each group. The CBT program will entail the Cool Kids and Chilled (Registered Trademark) programs - for children aged 7-11 years and 12-17 years, respectively - developed at Macquarie University (Rapee et al., 2006). Cool Kids and Chilled (Registered Trademark) assist children to learn skills to recognise their emotions and combat anxiety, encouraging brave behaviour and gradual engagement with feared situations. One section of the Chilled (Registered Trademark) Program worry wave will be omitted from the program for the purposes of this research as it was considered to have mindfulness components more consistent with an ACT approach. This is a small component of the overall program.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 3: Waitlist control group. After being waitlisted for a period of 10 weeks, children and their caregivers in this group will commence the Arm 2, The CBT program</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of DSM-IV Anxiety disorder as measured by the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule (ADIS-IV) (Albano &amp; Silverman, 1996)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, 3 months post-treatment and 2 years post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinically significant change in anxiety severity as measured by either ADIS-IV, Multidimensional Anxiety Scale for Children (MASC; March, 1997) and/or Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, 3 months post-treatment and 2 years post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mechanisms of change (adolescent participants only) as measured by changes in experiential avoidance, cognitive fusion, acceptance and valued living</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression symptoms as measured by the Child Depression Inventory and/or Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, 3 months post-treatment and 2 years post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life and self-efficacy	as measured by the Childrens Anxiety Life Interference Scale Child Form (CALIS-C)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, 3 months post-treatment and 2 years post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Aged between 7-17 years 
2) Meet criteria for a primary diagnosis of a Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV) anxiety disorder (including panic disorder and/or agoraphobia, obsessive compulsive disorder, specific phobia, social anxiety disorder or generalised anxiety disorder)
3) Available/able to attend The Childrens Hospital at Westmead for pre-treatment, immediate post-treatment and three month post-treatment assessments as well as attending a minimum of 80% of therapy sessions 
4) Have a parent/caregiver who is willing to attend and participate in the assessment as well as a minimum of 80% of therapy sessions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Developmental or language delay, as reported by parent/caregiver
2) Non-English speakers
3) Complex mental health problems such as psychosis, conduct disorder or active suicidality
4) Complex medical conditions with a high degree of medical dependence that would prevent them from being able to attend at least 80% of sessions
5) Attention deficit disorder with hyperactivity that is not well controlled
6) Medicated with an anxiolytic/antidepressant for less than 2 months
7) Post-traumatic stress disorder (due to the potential distress caused to other participants in the group and the specialised treatment required for this disorder)
8) Completed &lt; 80% of sessions or dropped out of treatment  Those who become lost to follow-up will be placed in the intention to treat category</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following referral to the Department of Psychological Medicine, The Children's Hospital at Westmead (CHW) the parents/carers of potential child participants are briefly screened over the phone to determine suitability for baseline assessment using a checklist developed for this study. If deemed suitable at this point, they will be sent an information pack about the study including consent forms, and a battery of questionnaires to be completed by both the child and parent as part of the baseline assessment. Eligible participants and their parents/caregivers will be randomised to one of three conditions, Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT), Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT) or a waitlist control group for a period of 10 weeks.</concealment>
    <sequence>This is a block randomised controlled trial, with the participant serving as the unit of randomisation. Randomisation will be undertaken via a freely available computer random assignment software application, ‘Graphpad’ (for more information and to access see: www.graphpad.com/quickcalcs/randomize2.cfm). The researchers conducting baseline assessments will be blinded to the treatment type to reduce potential bias and will only become aware of the group allocation upon commencement of the relevant program. The researcher who determined if a participant was eligible for inclusion in the trial was blind to the group allocation process, at the time of allocation. Allocation was performed at a central administration site.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The ACT and CBT treatments are completed as parallel assignment. However, those initially allocated to waitlist control will receive the CBT arm of the intervention after completion of the 10 week waitlist period.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Children's Hospital Westmead, Department of Psychological Medicine</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine
Children's Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Hospital Westmead, Department of Psychological Medicine</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Psychological Medicine
Children's Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Newcastle</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology
The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Over the last 15 years mindfulness and acceptance therapies have taken hold in psychology as a new era of
treatment. Acceptance-mindfulness therapies differ from traditional cognitive behavioural therapies (CBT) in that
rather than attempting to change the content, frequency and form of thoughts and feelings, acceptance or
mindfulness-based therapies seek to change the functions of thoughts, feelings and physical sensations so as to
minimise their impact.
While there is growing empirical support for the utility of acceptance-mindfulness treatments for adults with anxiety
and other psychological problems, very little research has been conducted on children evaluating its effectiveness
despite the growing use in children and adolescents. This study aims to conduct a controlled clinical trial evaluating
the efficacy of acceptance-mindfulness therapy for children with anxiety disorders. Children aged 7-17 years will be
randomly allocated to one of 3 groups: acceptance-mindfulness integrated with cognitive behavioural therapy,
cognitive behavioural therapy only, and a waiting list control group. Repeated measures of psychological outcomes will
be taken pre, immediate post and 3 months post-treatment. Parents will also undertake group therapy sessions while the children are undergoing therapy to assist children transfer the skills to everyday life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Alexandra Hospital for Children Ethics Committee (EC00130)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Development
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd and Hainsworth St
Westmead NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/CHW/4</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/01/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Karen Hancock</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
The Children's Hospital Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street, 
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98450408</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9845 0413</fax>
      <email>Karen.hancock@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Karen Hancock</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
The Children's Hospital Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street, 
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98450408</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9845 0413</fax>
      <email>Karen.hancock@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jessica Swain</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine
The Children's Hospital Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street, 
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98450406</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9845 0413</fax>
      <email>jessica.swain@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>