<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="307977">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000491268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Pathways for Acute Coronary Syndromes in China - phase 2: implementation and evaluation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with acute coronary syndromes admitted to urban hospitals in China, are clinical pathways effective for improving the quality of care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CPACS-2</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Coronary Syndromes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Clinical pathways in this study are standardized algorithms for the treatment of acute coronary syndromes that aim to optimize and streamline patient care. They are established according to American Heart Association (AHA) and American College of Cardiology (ACC) guidelines to promote the use of evidence-based treatments for high risk patients and ultimately, improve clinical outcomes. The clinical pathways are designed to accompany the patients medical record and available in printed copy. In this study after baseline data collection, the printed clinical pathways as a reminder of guideline adherence will be added in front of patients medical record in relevant departments in the participating hospitals. The clinical pathways will be used for at least 24 month in participating hospitals. Its impact will be evaluated periodically (every 6 months) by comparing a series of key performance indicators, e.g. average door-to needle time and average door-to-balloon time for patients with ST elevated myocardial infarction.</interventions>
    <comparator>1. Randomized comparison: hospitals will be selected to implement the clinical pathways early and to implement 12 month later.   Approximately one-half of the 75 participating hospitals will be allocated (at random, stratified by hospital size and level) to commence the study in the first year of the full program (Group A), while the remaining one-half (Group B) will commence during the second year. This staggered commencement will be necessary from a logistic viewpoint, but will also provide the opportunity to make a randomized evaluation of the intervention program on the key performance indicators (12 month data for Group A vs. baseline data for Group B).
2. Non-randomized comparison: a before-after comparison in key performance indicators among all 75 hospitals will be conducted from up to 3750 patients (50 patients from each of the 75 hospitals) at each 6-month interval with baseline and the previous 6-month time periods. After 24 months, summary data will be available for over 15000 patients to examine overall trends in key performance indicators.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of ST elevated myocardial infarction patients arriving at hospital within 12 hours of symptom onset who receive thrombolysis or primary percutaneous coronary intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with final diagnosis (unstable angina pectoris or myocardial infarction) consistent with biomarker findings (blood test results for Creatine Phosphokinase and Triponin)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Door-to-needle time for ST elevated myocardial infarction patients undergoing thrombolysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of high-risk patients undergoing coronary angiography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of low-risk patients (no ongoing symptoms, persistently normal Electrocardiography, persistently normal serum Creatine Phosphokinase and Triponin value) undergoing functional testing (exercise test and stress echocardiography)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients discharged on appropriate medical therapy for secondary prevention (antiplatelets, beta-blockers, Angiotensin-Converting Enzymeinhibitors (ACE) inhibitors and statins being prescripted when patients are discharged )</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean length-of-stay in hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Door-to-balloon time for ST elevated myocardial infarction patients undergoing primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PCI) (where primary PCI is offered)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hospitals routinely admitting patients with acute coronary syndromes are included in the study; patients over 17 years old and being hospitalised due to acute coronary syndromes are included in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Hospitals currently admitting fewer than 100 patients with suspected acute coronary syndromes per year will be excluded from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The randomisation was performed at hospital level. Allocation of hospitals to early or later commencing group was concealed by central randomisation by computer. Allocation is not concealed at individual patient level.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sanofi-Aventis (China)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Floor 32, No.1266
Nanjing West Road
Shanghai, 200040</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sanofi-Aventis (China)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Floor 32, No.1266
Nanjing West Road
Shanghai, 200040</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Coronary heart disease is now a leading cause of disease in China. The strategies for managing acute coronary syndromes (ACS) are well-recognised, however, anecdotal reports suggest that many patients do not receive recommended therapies. This study aims to develop, implement and evaluate quality improvement initiatives (using clinical pathways) throughout selected hospitals in China, to increase the use of recommended treatments and reduce the use of expensive and unnecessary investigations and treatment. Over the long term, this could lead to substantial reductions in the rates of disability and death due to ACS.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The university of sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building G02
The University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09-2007/10276</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fiona Turnbull</name>
      <address>Level 10, King George V Building
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
Sydney NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9993 4563</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>FTurnbull@george.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ye Rong</name>
      <address>Level 10, King George V Building
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
Sydney NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8507 2523</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rye@george.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>