<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369647">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000062426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using people with aphasia to train health professionals in effective communication strategies over the internet</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of using people with aphasia to train health professionals in effective communication strategies over the internet</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1177-1850 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Aphasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Health professionals from a variety of disciplines will be randomly allocated to groups (internet vs. face-to-face). All health professionals will attend an initial assessment session, a training session, and then a follow-up session. The initial assessment sessions will be held up to one week before the training session, while the follow-up session will occur approximately one week later. At the initial and follow-up assessment sessions, the health professionals will complete survey measures about their confidence when interacting with people with aphasia and knowledge about communication strategies. During the training session the health professionals will learn and implement communication strategies via a single 1 hour lecture by a speech pathologist and then a 15 minute conversation with a person with aphasia followed by feedback. The conversations will involve 1-2 health professionals paired with 1-2 people with aphasia in a small group format. The internet group will receive the training over the internet (this will involve watching a pre-recorded version of the training session online and then having a real-time conversation in a small group format with a person with aphasia (via Skype or a similar program) to practically implement the strategies. A register of attendance will be kept to monitor adherence to the intervention.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Health professionals in the control group will attend an initial assessment session, a training session, and then a follow-up session. At the initial and follow-up assessment sessions, the health professionals will complete survey measures about their confidence when interacting with people with aphasia and knowledge about communication strategies. During the training session the health professionals will learn and implement communication strategies via a single 1 hour lecture by a speech pathologist and then a 15 minute conversation with a person with aphasia followed by feedback. The control group will receive the training in the traditional face to face format delivered by a speech pathologist physically present in the room with participants. During the conversation, the people with aphasia will be physically present in the room with the health professional.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in confidence when communicating with people with aphasia using a customised 100mm visual analogue scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately before receiving the training and then immediately after the training.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in knowledge about effective strategies for communicating with people with aphasia (in the form of an open-ended content question)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately before the training and immediately after receiving the training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-rated success of the communication partner training program by the person with aphasia on a customised 100mm visual anologue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the person with aphasia has participated in the conversation with the health professional</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be Health professionals from a variety of allied health disciplines employed at the Princess Alexandra (PA) Hospital (Brisbane, Queensland). The people with aphasia will be currently attending an outpatient communication group at the Princess Alexandra Hospital. The people with aphasia will all be diagnosed with aphasia by a speech pathologist prior to their inclusion in the study and will not have any other neurological or developmental conditions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Health professionals - inadequate English skills to consent and participate in the program; history of neurological conditions. People with aphasia - inadequate English skills to consent and participate in the program; history of other neurological or developmental conditions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A computerised random number generator will be used to determine group allocation, which will be concealed at the time of recruitment using opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>A computerised random number generator</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The visual analogue scale data will initially be analysed using descriptive statistics (mean, SD, range). The confidence visual analogue data will be analysed using repeated measures ANOVAs (or non-parametric equivalent) with between group comparisons (internet, face to face) and time (pre, post) as the repeated measure. The people with aphasia visual analogue scale data will be analysed using independent samples t tests (or non-parametric equivalent) (internet, face to face). The knowledge questions will be analysed descriptively using thematic analysis. Sample size calculations were based primarily upon current clinical numbers and feasibility. A sample size calculation for this project is somewhat speculative in the absence of pilot data. The study requires 54 complete data sets (90% completion rate from the 60 participants) to achieve 80% power to detect a between group difference of 7.9mm on the primary outcome visual analogue scale (assuming a standard deviation of 14mm, 1:1 allocation ratio, and 0.68 correlation between baseline and follow-up assessments). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>29/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>55</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Emma Finch</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba
Queensland 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Stroke Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>461 Bourke Street
Melbourne, Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Research Support Scheme Postgraduate Scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba, Brisbane 
Queensland 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ms Ashley Cameron</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba
Queensland 4102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kyla Brown</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Steven McPhail</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Functioning and Health Research
Metro South Hospital and Health Service</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Jennifer Lethlean</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Jennifer Fleming</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The communication difficulties associated with aphasia can create a significant barrier to the involvement of people with stroke in healthcare decisions. Our research team has previously demonstrated that people with aphasia can train health professionals to effectively communicate with individuals with aphasia. The current project will extend this research by investigating the effectiveness of delivering the training over the internet to cater for rural clinicians. The project will be a pre-post intervention study with random allocation of health professionals to groups (internet vs. face-to-face). During the study, 60 health professionals will attend a training session where they learn and implement strategies for communicating with people with aphasia (via a 1 hour lecture on communication techniques and then a 15 minute conversation with a person with aphasia). The health professionals will be randomly allocated to either training using the traditional face-to-face format, or training over the internet. The proposed project will provide valuable evidence about whether communication partner training programs for health professionals involving people with aphasia can be delivered over the internet, and will be used as pilot data for a multisite RCT. It is anticipated that the program has the potential to increase the participation of people with aphasia in healthcare decisions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QPAH/329 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
St Lucia Campus QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011000801</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.finch@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>