<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363209">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001154897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A workplace-based exercise intervention to prevent and reduce the economic and personal burden of non-specific neck pain in office personnel</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A workplace-based exercise intervention to prevent and reduce the economic and personal burden of non-specific neck pain in office personnel aged 18-65 years.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-4579</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-specific neck  pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: Employees will receive an individualised best practice ergonomic assessment based on a comprehensive assessment conducted by a registered health professional. In addition, they will receive a progressive exercise program to condition the muscles of the neck/shoulder girdle supervised by a registered health professional. These exercises will be performed in the workplace for 20 minutes, three times per week for 12 weeks. A standard sequence of exercise will be prescribed to all employees but their implementation and progression will be within the specific capabilities of the individual. Employees will perform shoulder girdle exercises using dumbbells (single arm rows, bilateral shoulder shrugs, upright rows, reverse flyes, bilateral arm lateral arm raise to 90-degrees shoulder abduction) progressing from unresisted to resisted exercise utilising variable resistance bands. Training load for each individual will be based on their one-repetition maximum (1-RM) that will be regularly re-evaluated to ensure exercise is progressed accordingly. Each training session will commence with a warm up of ten repetitions at a load of 50% of 1-RM for each exercise. This will be followed by 2 to 3 sets of 10-15 repetitions of each exercise at 60-80% of their 1-RM. Progression of the exercises will be within the guidelines suggested for the principle of periodisation and progressive overload. Neck exercises (cervical flexion and extension exercises) that incorporate the coordinated function of the deep and superficial muscle layers will be included and progressed from unresisted to resisted exercise utilising variable resistance bands. Twelve weeks of this training schedule has been shown to be a sufficient intervention period to achieve significant adaptations.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator/Control: Participants will receive an individualised best practice ergonomic intervention ONLY. As per the intervention arm the assessment will be conducted by a registered health professional. There are no anticipated adverse events or risks for the individual employee as it is standard practice for employees to receive ergonomic advice regarding their workstation and work practices. As the control arm will not recieve the exercise, intervention and to ensure parity in time with those in the intervention group, employees will be invited to attend health promotion sessions for one hour per week for 12 weeks. Topics will include information on healthy eating, stress management, weight loss, relaxation, cessation of smoking and safe drug and alcohol guidelines using resources provided by the Queensland Health Department.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Productivity Loss measured in monetary units calculated using the World Health Organisation Health and Productivity Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediate and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of Neck Pain measured using a 10-point scale ranging from 0 (no pain) to 9 (worst possible pain)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediate and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The personal burden of Neck Pain will be measured using the 10-item Neck Disability Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediate and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength (Newtons) and endurance (time to task failure at 50% of maximal strength) of the neck and shoulder girdle will be evaluated using a portable digital dynamometer at the three time points.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediate and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Related Quality of Life will be measured with the Assessment of Quality of Life Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediate and 12 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of workers' compensation claims will be evaluated by one question: Have you received worker's compensation because of neck trouble in the past 12 months?"</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 12 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychosocial workplace factors will be evaluated using the Job Content Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Job satisfaction will assessed with a single item: Overall how satisfied are you with your job?, scored on a seven point Likert scale where 1 was extremely dissatisfied   and 7 was extremely satisfied.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels will be measured using the valid and reliable short-form International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) with data expressed as a continuous variable in MET-min per week</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health beliefs will be assessed using three questions from the Fear-Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire. Employees will be considered to hold fear-avoidance beliefs if they agree with the statements: Physical activity should be avoided when in pain and I should not do physical activities which (might) make my pain worse (dichotomous Yes/No variable).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible employees will be any office worker, aged 18-65 years, who work more than 30 hours/week in predominantly sedentary office work.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria are pregnancy, health conditions such as previous trauma or injuries to the neck, specific pathologies (e.g., congenital cervical abnormalities, stenosis) or inflammatory condition (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis), any history of cervical spine surgery or if exercise is contraindicated. Employees who anticipate any prolonged absence from work during the study's follow-up period will also be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An invitation to participate will be sent via the onsite liaison. Interested employees will be directed to a web-based questionnaire with information about the research, consent form, as well as questions to determine eligibility and their location to establish clusters. The project coordinator will determine eligibility for inclusion in the study and allocate eligible employees to a cluster (de-identified) until the required number is reached for each intake (6-8/year for 3 years).  A cluster is defined as a group of 6 people located on the same floor, work group or building.  Allocation will be based on clusters and allocation
concealment will be at the cluster level. A statistician who is based off-stie and blinded to the identity of the individuals will assign the clusters by simple random allocation (computer generated random number sequence) to either the control or intervention group. The project coordinator who will determine subject eligibility for inclusion in the trial will be unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the subject would be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>A statistician blinded to the identity of the individuals will assign clusters by simple random allocation to either the control or intervention group using computer generated random number sequence. A cluster is defined as a group of 6 people located on the same floor, work group or building.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study design incorporates clusters where all workers in a work team or floor are randomised to the same intervention</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>640</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/o Dr Susan O'Brien
Manager, Sponsored Research (Health and Biomedical Initiatives)
Research Management Office
UQ Research and Innovation
The University of Queensland
Brisbane Queensland 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra City ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Health and Medical Research Council</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra City ACT 2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Non-specific neck pain is a major burden in industry in terms of lost productivity (reduced work performance, lost days) and personal suffering (pain, disability, reduction in quality of life and reduced job satisfaction). Non-specific neck pain is a particular threat to productivity at work due to its tendency for chronicity and its recurrence. With more than 50% of office workers experiencing neck pain at some stage of their working life, significant resources have been allocated to improve the individuals ergonomic working environment aimed at primary prevention of this problem. Emerging evidence supports the effectiveness of ergonomic interventions in reducing absenteeism and improving productivity, but to date it has shown minimal impact in preventing or reducing neck pain in the workplace. In contrast, a workplace neck strengthening exercise protocol has demonstrated effectiveness for reducing the severity of neck pain in office workers but its impact on productivity has not been explored. Due to the recognised link between health and productivity, health initiatives at the workplace are gaining momentum. We propose that best practice ergonomic intervention combined with neck specific exercise is the optimal approach to minimise productivity losses and neck pain in the workplace. This project will test the impact of a workplace-based best practice combined ergonomic and exercise intervention on work productivity and severity of neck pain in a population of office personnel.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UQ Research &amp; Innovation
Cumbrae-Stewart Building (72)
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC number is 2012001318</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Venerina Johnston</name>
      <address>Level 7, Therapies Building 84A
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences 
The University of Queensland QLD 4072 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2124</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>v.johnston@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Venerina Johnston</name>
      <address>Level 7, Therapies Building 84A
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences 
The University of Queensland QLD 4072 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2124</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>v.johnston@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Venerina Johnston</name>
      <address>Level 7, Therapies Building 84A
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences 
The University of Queensland QLD 4072 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2124</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 1622</fax>
      <email>v.johnston@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Venerina Johnston</name>
      <address>Level 7, Therapies Building 84A
School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
The University of Queensland
St Lucia 4072</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 33652124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>v.johnston@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>