<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363747">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001054707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An innovative home-based internet health service project to improve outcomes for Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant survivors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An innovative home-based exercise and stress management program to improve outcomes for Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant survivors using the internet</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Allogeneic  Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant  patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Supervised home based training sessions on exercise and stress management techniques will be conducted over 4-6 weeks by a trained physiotherapist and psychologist using the internet. The exact number of sessions will be determined by ongoing individual needs. 
The Proposed exercise intervention will be supervised home based training for aerobic and resistance exercises with stretching and resistance/strength training. The programme includes a goal attainment scale (GAS) to aid adherence and as an objective end point measurement. 
Patients will be given recommendations for daily practice. The initial consultation includes 6 minute walk test. Following the initial consultation, 3-4 reinforcement sessions will be conducted over 4-6 weeks, duration of each session maybe between 15 -30 mins. This will be followed by assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6,  and 12 months after the training sessions.
All participants will undergo an initial 1 hour face-to-face assessment session conducted by a Clinical Psychologist to screen for psychosocial risk factors and levels of anxiety and depression. All patients will complete a 1.5 hour psycho-education session with a psychologist that will include a discussion and training in general stress management techniques as well as provision of written materials on stress management strategies and audio recordings of the relaxation technique . All sessions will be one on one, and face to face using the internet.
Participants will undergo live training over the internet using Skype with the physiotherapist and psychologist. 
The recommended Australian immunisation guidelines following HSCT will be used to check participants' medical records for evidence of post-transplant vaccination. Vaccination status will also be assessed using serology (on blood tests) to specified pathogens at baseline. Any deficiencies in vaccination will be addressed with re-immunisation. </interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine the feasibility of delivering exercise, psychological and re-vaccination programmes to patients at home utilising telecommunication technology, assessed clinically and by ongoing reviews of programme. Assessment is done by both patient and staff on how compliant the patient is during the study-  How many continue the programme, drop out of the programme.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6, and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine the feasibility of web-based and self-assessment tools and supervision of these programmes using telecommunication technology, assessed clinically and on an individual patient basis. After the initial training period, the participant will provide information on whether the programs were useful to them, changed their habits, and wether the methods of program delivery were appropriate using 5-point Likert Scales and open responses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessment at end of the training period only</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the outcome of these programmes in regards to their acceptability, utility and benefits. This will be assessed using standardised assessment tool, 6-minute walk test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6, and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the outcome of these programmes in regards to their acceptability, utility and benefits. This will be assessed using standardised assessment tool - Goal Attainment Scale, </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6, and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the outcome of these programmes in regards to their acceptability, utility and benefits. This will be assessed using standardised assessment tools including:  Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6, and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the outcome of these programmes in regards to their acceptability, utility and benefits. This will be assessed using standardised assessment tool,  Rating of Perceived Exertion. The patient rates their perceived rate of exertion at each timepoint, basic assessment ratingsuch as easy or hard the level of activity was, this is giving a rating and monitored/compared to  the previuos / baseline level.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6, and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the outcome of these programmes in regards to their acceptability, utility and benefits. This will be assessed using standardised assessment tool, Karnofsky Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6, and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Allogeneic HSCT patients, &gt; 6 months post-transplant with no severe GVHD or other medical issues that requires regular clinic visits, no physical or mental impediments to carry out the programmes or assessment tasks,</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>has cardiac disease including arrhythmia,living alone and not approved by the patients haematologist.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>open label</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>26/07/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>21</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ARROW Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Leichhardt St, Darlinghurst, NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients will be assessed for suitability for this study and then invited to participate. All participants will then undergo an initial face-to-face session by the investigators on matters related to methodology and technical requirements on conducting home-based internet programmes on exercise and stress management techniques. Following this initial session, supervised home based training sessions will be conducted over 4-6 weeks. This will be followed by assessment at end of the training period and then at 3, 6, and 12 months after the training sessions. . </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>No publications were done, A funding report was provided to Arrow Foundation </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent'sHospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LNR/12/SVH/240</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Ma</name>
      <address>Kinghorn Cancer Centre
St Vincent'sHospital, Sydney
370 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>6 12 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>svhcancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Patricia Plenge</name>
      <address>Kinghorn Cancer Centre
St Vincent'sHospital, Sydney
370 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>6 12 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>svhcancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Ma</name>
      <address>Kinghorn Cancer Centre
St Vincent'sHospital, Sydney
370 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>6 12 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>svhcancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>