<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336542">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000215921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of an internet-based depression treatment program: Depression Online</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Depression Online: An RCT evaluation of Self-Monitoring versus a Fully Automated online treatment program for people with Depression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-5206</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The-DO-Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>The trial will only be registered with ANZCTR.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The effect of an online intervention study on depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This project will evaluate the effectiveness of Depression Online (DO) an
internet-based treatment program for consumers who experience depressive symptoms or receive a diagnosis of a depressive disorder by implementing a randomised controlled trial (RCT). Consumers of Depression Online will complete 12 CBT-based modules that provide
information and strategies for the treatment of depression. Consumers who participate in the trial will be randomly assigned to one of two conditions: (1) Fully Automated - DO (FA-DO) or (2) Self-monitoring waitlist control (SMWLC).  A brief description of each condition follows.
The DO Program is an automated, self-help program that consists of 12 evidence-based modules. Each participant will be required to complete one module per week over a 12-week period. The program will provide participants with information about Depression and strategies on how to address thoughts, feelings and behaviours that contribute to or maintain Depressive Disorders. Participants who are allocated to the Self Monitoring Waiting List control are required to monitor their mood for a 12 week period before they are given access to the Depression Online program. A therapist will monitor a participant to determine whether there is any deterioration in mood that requires action. Participants who monitor their mood over a 12 week period are then invited to participate in the DO program. 

A participant's involvement in the study depends on which condition they have been allocated to. For participants allocated to the Depression Online (DO) program, participation is required for a 12 week period. During this time, the DO program involves approximately 1 hour of online reading and approximately 1 hour of offline activities per week. Questionnaires at each of the time points (baseline, week 4, week 8 and week 12 ) will take approximately 30 to 60 minutes to complete. Six (6) moths after completing the DO program (follow-up), participants are invited back to complete a number of questionnaires that should take approximately 60 minutes. For participants allocated to the Self-Monitoring (Waiting List Control), they are required to monitor their mood for a 12 week period (on a weekly basis). The Self-Monitoring task should take no more than 5 minutes to complete. Once the 12 week period has lapsed, participants commence the DO program and follow the same protocol described above.</interventions>
    <comparator>The Self Monitoring Waiting List Control (SMWLC) will commence the Fully Automated (FA-DO) intervention immediately after completing the self-monitoring task (i.e. after week 12).  During the SMWLC condition, the student-researcher will be in email-contact with participants if they do not provide their mood data for two weeks. If this occurs, the researcher will email-contact participants and prompt them to either: re-commence monitoring their mood, direct them to the exit survey if they decide to withdraw from the study or notify their General Practitioners if participants to not respond to the student-researcher email.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in depressive symptomatology or remission of depressive disorder as measured by online psychological assessment instrument (e-PASS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After randomisation has occurred: week 1 (baseline, pre-intervention) and after week 12 (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in Centre for Epidemiological Studies-Depression (CES-D) and Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale - 21 (DASS-21) scores on depression and distress </outcome>
      <timepoint>After randomisation has occurred: week 1 (baseline), month 1, month 2, month 3 (post intervention), month 6 (follow-up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in Dysfuctional beliefs Scale (DAS) score of people experiencing depression</outcome>
      <timepoint>After randomisation has occurred: week 1 (baseline), month 1, month 2, month 3 (post intervention), month 6 (follow-up)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants are eligible to participate in the study if they experience depressive symptoms or a depressive
disorder. In this sense mental illness is strictly defined as those participants identified by the e-PASS
assment tool as experiencing depressive phenomenon. The e-PASS assessment tool will provide
participants with details as to the type and severity of their psychological symptoms or disorders and provide
appropriate recommendations for addressing their problem/s. It will also help determine whether participants
meet eligibility for the Depression Online (DO) program.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if the e-PASS program finds that they do not experience depressive symptoms
(no depression diagnosis  clinical or subclinical) or they experience any of the following disorders as
primary or conditions: (a) a concurrent medical condition that is contributing to their depression (b) an
organic or psychotic problem (c) a primary substance abuse disorder (d) an eating disorder or (e) a bipolar
disorder. If consumers are unable to complete the required online depression-specific assessment measures
and/or are unable consent to the treatment protocol they will also be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The student-researcher will be blind to whether participants will be allocated to either the experimental or control conditions. All participants will be randomly allocated to either condition by using a computer generated 'randomisation table'.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participant randomisation will be occur by a 'computer-generated random numbers table table' held by an
independent person associated by the National e-Therapy Centre. When a new participant is recruited, the
independent person will inform the researcher what condition the participant has been allocated to.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swinburne University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC  3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Swinburne University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC  3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to examine the effectiveness of an internet-based treatment program for depression. This will be achieved by comparing the Depression Online (DO) fully automated self help treatment program to a person who monitors their mood (self monitoring or waitlist control) over a 12 week period. The aim of this comparison is to will determine how effective the DO program is in the treatment of depression. 

The importance of the treatment of depression has become a focus for many researchers because the World Health Organisation has predicted that depression would be the worlds second biggest cause of death by 2020. A recent survey (The Australian National Mental Health Survey) found that only a third of respondents who reported experiencing a depressive or anxiety disorder sought professional assistance and only 10 percent consulted a psychologist or psychiatrist for specialised face-to-face treatments. Given the high prevalence of the disorder, the online environment provides an elegant solution to meet the largely unmet needs of depressed (and anxious) people by providing them with relatively easy access to efficacious treatments.

Internet-based psychological treatments (eTherapies) have been vigorously evaluated over the past decade and many have been shown to be effective, safe and acceptable forms of mental health treatment. As eTherapies have a broad reach capacity, they enable the delivery of specialist psychological support far beyond the capability of traditional face-to-face services. Depression Online is one of the programs that aims to do this.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.anxietyonline.org.au

Depression Online is one of the programs offered by 'anxietyonline'.</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University's Human Research Ethics Committee (SUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Officer
Office of Research and Graduate Studies (H68)
Swinburne University of Technology
PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC  3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010/289</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Michael Kyrios</name>
      <address>Professor Michael Kyrios 
Faculty of Life and Social Sciences
Swinburne University of Technology
PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC  3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 4886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mkyrios@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Michael Kyrios</name>
      <address>Professor Michael Kyrios 
Faculty of Life and Social Sciences
Swinburne University of Technology
PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC  3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 4886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mkyrios@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gabriel Notarianni</name>
      <address>1301 Burke Rd
Kew, VIC, 3101</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9817 7778</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9817 7766</fax>
      <email>psychology@1301burkerdkew.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>