<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369396">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001058561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of an intervention to improve the implementation of food service nutrition guidelines in  childcare centres that provide food to children </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of a training intervention versus usual care on compliance with food service nutrition guidelines in long day care services. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Childhood overweight and obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 6 month intervention to improve childcare service implementation of nutrition guidelines will be delivered. The intervention will consist of: cook and service manager training to improve knowledge and skills in regards to the menu planning (service managers and service cooks will be provided with a single one-day menu planning workshop, delivered by experienced dietitians and health promotion staff).; provision of resources including a resource manual, menu planning checklists and recipe ideas;  review of service menus and feedback at one month following the workshop. </interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment, standard care  participating services randomised to the wait list control group will receive the intervention after follow-up data collection.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in proportion of services who have a two week menu that is compliant with nutrition guidelines (provides 50% of recommended serves as specified by the Australian dietary guidelines).Menu audits will be undertaken by a dietitian blinded to intervention allocation.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, end of intervention (6 months post-baseline) and 6 months post intervention (12 months post -baseline)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in proportion of services who are compliant with the nutrition guidelines for individual Australian Guide to healthy Eating food groups ((1) Vegetables and legumes/beans; (2) Fruit; (3) Wholegrain cereal foods and breads; (4) Lean meat and poultry, fish, eggs, tofu, seeds and legumes; (5) Milk, yoghurt, cheese and alternatives; and (6) Discretionary foods).
As per the sector nutrition guidelines services are required to provided: 2 serves of the vegetable and legumes/beans food group; 1 serve of the fruit food group; 2 serves of the wholegrain cereals and breads food group; 0.75 serve of Lean meat and poultry, fish, eggs, tofu, seeds and legumes food group; 1 serve of Milk, yoghurt, cheese and alternative food group and; 0 serves of discretionary foods, per child each day. A service will be deemed compliant with a food group if their planned menu provides the recommended serve of the food group for each child on everyday across the 2 week menu (10 days),
Menu audits will be undertaken by a dietitian blinded to intervention allocation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, end of intervention (6 months post-baseline) and 6 months post intervention (12 months post -baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Long Day Care Services: For a service to be eligible, it will be located within the Hunter New England region of NSW Australia, provide all meals (at least one main meal and two mid-meals) to children while they are in care, and open for at least 8 hours per day. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Long Day Care Services: Services that do not prepare and provide meals to children onsite or do not have a cook with some responsibility for menu planning will be excluded from the study. Further, services catering exclusively for children requiring specialist care, mobile preschools and family day care centres will also be excluded from the study] 
A sample of 70 services in the Hunter New England  Region (n=111) will be randomly approached to participate in the trial
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Study information and consent forms will be mailed to services approximately one to two weeks prior to a telephone call from a research assistant requesting consent to participate in data collection. Random allocation to groups will be conducted by an independent statistician, at a centralised location. </concealment>
    <sequence>Consenting childcare services will be randomly allocated to an intervention or control group in a 1:1 ratio via block randomisation using a random number function in SAS statistical software following baseline data collection. Allocation of services will be undertaken by a statistician who will otherwise have no involvement in the study. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/10/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>47</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter New England Population Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Longworth Avenue, Wallsend, NSW 2287</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter New England Population Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Longworth Avenue, Wallsend, NSW 2287</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Newcastle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University Drive, Callaghan NSW 2308</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Supporting centre based childcare services to provide healthy food can make an important contribution to promoting health of young children at a critical stage in their development.  This study aims to assess the effectiveness of a large scale intervention aiming to increase childcare service implementation of menu nutrition guidelines. The study will recruit 60 long day care services that will be randomised to receive the intervention to support nutrition guideline implementation, or a usual care wait list control group. The intervention will consist of multiple strategies including staff training, executive support, performance feedback, resources and ongoing support.  Menu assessments before and after the intervention will be conducted to assess the effectiveness of the initiative in improving compliance with setting nutrition guidelines. We hypothesis that childcare service's implementation of nutrition guidelines will improve as a result of the intervention. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1, New Lambton NSW 2305]</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/07/26/4.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Meghan Finch </name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend, New South Wales 2287
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6131</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6215</fax>
      <email>Meghan.Finch@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Meghan Finch</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend, New South Wales 2287
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6131</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6215</fax>
      <email>Meghan.Finch@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Meghan Finch</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend, New South Wales 2287
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6131</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6215</fax>
      <email>meghan.finch@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>