<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367092">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001034628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Rapid Induction Analgesia: Audio recordings of hypnosis for induced pain in a student sample</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of rapid induction analgesia by hypnosis recording compared to relaxing music on pain intensity and distress associated with acute pain in a sample of university students</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Rapid Induction Analgesia is a 20-minute hypnosis procedure with suggestions for relaxation and pain mediation. The intervention will be given as an audio recording that lasts for 20 minutes. There will be two experimental conditions, one where participants listen to the recording two days, then one day before and during a testing session and one where they just listen during the testing session. In the testing session pain will be induced using capsaicin applied to their forearms. Participants will then listen to the recording, or relaxing music,  and then rate pain distress and intensity in response to several mechanical stimuli applied to the forearm. Mechanical stimulation will be applied using an algometer which measures pressure, a temperature simulator that will apply heat of approximately 43C and a Neuropen that will produce a sharp pricking sensation. The testing session will take approximately one hour.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will listen to relaxing music for 20 minutes after capsaicin has been applied and before rating pain distress and intensity in response to mechanical stimulation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain intensity associated with physical stimuli on capsaicin application site in experimental group versus control group as assessed on a scale of 1-10. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Before capsaicin application and 30 minutes after capsaicin application</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress associated with physical stimuli on capsaicin application site in experimental group versus control group as assessed on a scale of 1-10.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before capsaicin application and 30 minutes after capsaicin application</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sharpness, using a neuropen applied to the forearm, with participant ratings of sharpness on a 1-10 scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before capsaicin application and 30 minutes after capsaicin application</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure pain threshold will be measured using an algometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before capsaicin application and 30 minutes after capsaicin application</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heat intensity will be assessed using a thermal simulator applied to the forearm. Participants will rate heat intensity on a scale from 1-10</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before capsaicin application and 30 minutes after capsaicin application</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults 18 and over
Generally good physical and mental health</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of a dissociative disorder, major depression, any anxiety condition with severe anxiety symptoms, schizophrenia
Diagnosis of a chronic pain condition
Pregnancy
Breastfeeding
Identified allergy to chilli or capsaicin</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through poster advertisements placed on notice boards throughout the campus. The student researcher will attend psychology lectures as approved to personally recruit participants, and hand out poster advertisements. Poster advertisements will outline the process for signing up for the study, which will involve an email or telephone call to the student researcher and/or signing up to the Murdoch Psychology Subject Pool website. 

Willing participants will contact the researcher and go through a brief screening interview to rule out exclusion criteria. They will then be randomly allocated to the experimental or control condition. Allocation will not be concealed. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Random number generator</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In a similar study using hypnosis for pain management (Wright and Drummond, 2001), 58 participants were recruited for three conditions (attention control, assessment during rapid induction analgesia, assessment after rapid induction analgesia). As this sample size (approximately 20 per condition) was sufficient to identify significant effects of rapid induction analgesia in that study (indicating a large effect size), we will also recruit approximately 20 subjects in each condition in the present study.

Differences in the mean values of several measures of the three groups on several measures of pain experience will be compared using analysis of variance.


Wright, B. &amp; Drummond, P. (2001). The effect of rapid induction analgesia on subjective pain ratings and pain tolerance. International Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hypnosis. 49:2. 109-122
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/04/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A Variety of research suggests that hypnosis can be used successfully to treat acute pain (Patterson and Jensen, 2003; Wright and Drummond, 2001). Specifically, it has been demonstrated that hypnosis can reduce the intensity of pain experienced by patients with burn injuries during treatment (Wright and Drummond, 2000). Hypnosis also appears to have unique effects above and beyond other pain management treatments, such as opioid analgesics and relaxation training (Patterson, 2010). 

Despite this, it appears that hospitals do not routinely use hypnosis or other psychological pain management strategies with their patients. One reason for this may be that hospitals are not well resourced with clinical psychology staff, and thus their time is taken up with high priority issues such as post trauma psychological symptoms. Another reason may be a lack of education amongst medical staff of the benefits of hypnosis for pain management. 

It has been suggested that nurses are well positioned within a hospital environment to use hypnosis for pain management (Valente, 2006). Nurses spend more time with patients than other clinicians, and are often present during painful procedures. However, nurses have a demanding role and may not have time amongst their general duties, or specialist training, to work through hypnosis protocols with patients. It has been suggested that nurses may have time to administer and reinforce an audio recording of a hypnosis protocol, and that this may have similar benefits to protocols administered directly by a practitioner. 

The aim of this study is to trial an audio recording of a Rapid Induction Analgesia (RIA) hypnosis protocol with a student sample, as a pilot study, to determine if a larger scale study at the burns unit at Fiona Stanley hospital may be worthwhile in 2015. The effects of hypnosis on students experience of pain will be examined.  

References

Patterson, D (2010). Clinical Hypnosis for Pain Control. Washington: American Psychological Association. 

Patterson, D., &amp; Jensen, M. (2003). Hypnosis and clinical pain. Psychological Bulletin, 129:4, 495-521

Valente, S. (2006). Hypnosis for pain management. Journal of Psychosocial Nursing, 44:2, 2-9

Wright, B. &amp; Drummond, P. (2000). Rapid induction analgesia for the alleviation of procedural pain during burn care. Burns, 26, 275-282

Wright, B. &amp; Drummond, P. (2001). The effect of rapid induction analgesia on subjective pain ratings and pain tolerance. International Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hypnosis. 49:2. 109-122
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Murdoch University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Chancellery Building
South Street
MURDOCH WA 6150
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/164</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Drummond</name>
      <address>Social Sciences Building room 1.020
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch WA 6150
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9360 2415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>P.Drummond@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn James</name>
      <address>Social Sciences Building room 1.020
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 458620032</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate@go.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Drummond</name>
      <address>Social Sciences Building room 1.020
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9360 2415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>P.Drummond@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn James</name>
      <address>Social Sciences Building room 1.020
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 458620032</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate@go.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>