<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369883">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000091404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study of a novel Sternal Protection Device to evaluate its safety in 12 patients requiring a cardiothoracic surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study evaluating the safety of a Novel Sternal Protection Device for cardiac surgery involving a median sternotomy incision</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-2964</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>01025-00014</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Jupiter 101</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sternal bleeding resulting from cardiothoracic surgery requiring median sternotomy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sternal fractures resulting from cardiothoracic surgery requiring median sternotomy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Jupiter sternal protection device (SPD) is supplied sterile for single use and consists of 2 identical components (a left and a right component). Each component has 2 sides, a soft, foam cushioned fabric intended to contact the sternal medulla and a medical-grade fabric supported by a frame designed to contact the retractor. After the median sternotomy incision but prior to insertion of the sternal retractor, a SPD component is placed over each of the hemi-sternal sections by the cardiothoracic surgeon. The special design of the frame enables the SPD to take the shape of hemi-sternal section and holds it firm. The surgeon will visually inspect the adherence of the SPD and will position a SPD compatible retractor over the SPD as per standard surgical practice. Once in place, the SPD will remain in-situ during the procedure and is removed immediately after the retractor is removed and prior to performing sternal closure.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of Sternal Protection Device will be evaluated during the cardiac surgery, assessed by the number and severity/seriousness of adverse device events. These assessments are made continuously throughout the surgical procedure by the cardiothoracic surgeon.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From placement of SPD to time of removal of SPD</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability of the SPD to protect the sternum from trauma will be evaluated. This will be visually assessed by the cardiothoracic surgeon post removal of the sternal protection device and rates according to a 4-point Likert scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutes after removal of SPD</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability of the SPD to protect the sternum from blood loss during the period of the device is in situ will be evaluated. This will be visually assessed by the cardiothoracic surgeon at various required time-points during the surgery and rates according to a 4-point Likert scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 mins prior to insertion of SPD; 5 and 10 mins after insertion of IMA; 5 and 30 mins after insertions of Sternal retractor; 5 mins after protamine administered; 5 mins after removal of SPD</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of use of the SPD during the cardiac surgery will be evaluated. This will be rated by the surgeon using a 5-point Likert scale at various stages of the surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutes after insertion, 5 minutes after retractor insertion, 5 minutes after removal of SPD</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Patients must be assessed as requiring cardiac surgery via a median sternotomy incision by a cardiothoracic surgeon 
2) Site personnel must obtain written informed consent from the patient prior to any study procedures (including screening procedures)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Patients who require emergency cardiac surgery
2) Patients who have undergone previous surgery via a median sternotomy incision
3) Patients who have any significant thoracic deformity including pectus excavatum, pectus carinatum
4) Patients where the sternal length (including the manubrium and body of the sternum and excluding the xiphisternum) is &lt;= 130mm or =&gt; 175 mm (using an external skin preoperative measurement) 
5) Patients who weigh =&gt; 110kg
6) Patients with a known bleeding disorder or abnormal coagulation profile
7) Patients who have taken an anti-platelet agent (other than aspirin) or other anticoagulant within 7 days of surgery
8) Concurrent enrolment in another investigational drug or device study, or use of any experimental or investigational drug or device within 30 days of cardiopulmonary bypass support
9) Any other medical condition which in the view of the Investigator is likely to interfere with the study or put the participant at risk</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>22/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Protego Medical Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 9, 278 Collins Street
Melbourne
Victoria-3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Protego Medical Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 9, 278 Collins Street
Melbourne
Victoria-3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nine</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this first in-man, non-comparative study, is to evaluate the safety of the novel Sternal Protection Device developed by Protego Medical Pty Ltd during cardiac surgeries that require median sternotomy. The device has two identical components, each one will be placed over a hemi-sternal section after the median sternotomy incision but prior to insertion of the Internal Mammary Artery or sternal retractor. The device will kept in situ during the procedure and removed immediately prior to sternal closure.

This will be conducted at the Alfred Hospital in just 12 patients. The other objectives of the study are evaluation of ability of this device to protect the sternum from trauma and bleeding, and its ease of use during the surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Road,
Prahran, VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>4/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Silvana Marasco</name>
      <address>The Alfred,
Department of Cardiothoracic Surgery
55 Commercial Rd,
Prahran, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.marasco@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Pablo Solis</name>
      <address>Level 9,
278 Collins Street,
Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96570718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pablo.solis@protegomedical.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Pablo Solis</name>
      <address>Level 9,
278 Collins Street,
Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96570718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clinical.studies@protegomedical.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Pablo Solis</name>
      <address>Level 9,
278 Collins Street,
Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96570718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pablo.solis@protegomedical.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>