<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335890">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000766011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can diagnostic assessment using an Accelerated Pathway reduce hospital admissions for chest pain in New Zealand?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study to compare the effectiveness, when applied to clinical practice of an accelerated chest pain diagnostic pathway, against the standard investigative process for adults presenting with possible cardiac chest pain at Christchurch Hospital.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Chest Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Accelerated Arm - Diagnostic assessment using an accelerated chest pain pathway. The pathway incorporates using (i) a risk stratification tool, Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction Risk Score (TIMI score), (ii) Electrocardiographs (ECGs) AND (iii) troponin blood test over a 2 hour time period from presentation to the hospital.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control Arm - Conventional diagnostic assessment pathway according to hospital guidelines involving ECGs and troponin blood test on hospital presentation and a further troponin blood test 8 to 12 hours after pain onset from presentation to the hospital.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be the proportion of patients successfully discharged home after Emergency Department (ED) assessment (without admission under another medical specialty to an in-patient ward). Sucessfully discharges is defined as discharged home within 6 hours of arrival at ED and have no serious adverse events. Serious adverse events include;
Death
Cardiac Arrest
Cardiogenic Shock
ST segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI)
non-ST segment myocardial infarction (NSTEMI)
Ventricular Arrhythmia
High Level  atrioventricular (AV) Block
The research nurses will track the patient's in-hospital progress in real time and use direct questioning of clinicians and patient records in order to record management decisions at initial attendance and admission, extract resource use data and identify subsequent attendances, admissions, and serious adverse events up to three months</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge home within 6 hours of arrival at ED. - Discharge with no serious adverse event during the following 30 days as determined by follow-up at three months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay (LOS) in hospital. The research nurses will track the patient's in-hospital progress in real time and use direct questioning of clinicians and patient records in order to record management decisions at initial attendance and admission, extract resource use data and identify subsequent attendances, admissions, and adverse events  up to three months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the 3 months following initial presentation to ED.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Re-attendance at and/or re-admission to hospital. The research nurses will track the patient's in-hospital progress in real time and use direct questioning of clinicians and patient records in order to record management decisions at initial attendance and admission, extract resource use data and identify subsequent attendances, admissions, and serious adverse events  up to three months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 30 days and at 3 months following initial presentation to ED.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serious Adverse Events
Death
Cardiac Arrest
Cardiogenic Shock
ST segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI)
non-ST segment myocardial infarction (NSTEMI)
Ventricular Arrhythmia
High Level  atrioventricular (AV) Block
The research nurses will track the patient's in-hospital progress in real time and use direct questioning of clinicians and patient records in order to record management decisions at initial attendance and admission, extract resource use data and identify subsequent attendances, admissions, and serious adverse events up to three months</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 months following initial presentation to ED.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of admitted patients ultimately diagnosed as having Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI) by the European Society of Cardiology/American College of Cardiology (ESC/ACC) criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>in-patient time over 3 months following initial presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness
The primary form a cost comparison will be the use of hospital inpatient days in each arm.
A secondary cost comparison will be possible using costs of investigation used and re-attendance to hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months following initial presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health utility measured using the EQ-5D self-complete questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after initial attendance at ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with care using a modified Group Health  Association of America questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month after initial attendance at ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Adults &gt; 18 years of age
2.	Presenting acutely to Christchurch hospital ED with chest pain (or discomfort) suggestive of AMI for whom, following initial clinical assessment, the attending clinician(s) intends to perform serial Cardiac Troponin (cTns), as part of the current chest pain investigation pathway for possible AMI.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. ST Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction (STEMI) present on any ECG.
2. Aged less than 18 years old
3. Proven or suspected non-coronary pathology as the cause of chest pain
4. Patients who will require admission regardless of a negative cTn, due to other                      medical conditions, need for other investigations or social considerations.
5. Transfers from other hospitals
6. Chest pain episode began over &gt; 12 hours ago and still persisting pain
7. Subjects previously enrolled in this study
8. Patient (or Legal Representative) unable or unwilling to provide informed consent.
9. Anticipated problem with follow-up e.g. resident outside New Zealand
10. Researcher does not feel that recruitment is appropriate (e.g. terminal illness)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research nurses will randomise individual patients using a web–based program (allocation concealed) after screening and obtaining consent</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Blinding of patients and clinical staff will not be clinically possible, however the primary objectives will be determined by investigators blind to study group assignment and the analyses will be performed by investigators blind to study group assignment.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Canterbury District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Princess Margaret Hospital
Cashmere Road
Cashmere
PO Box 1600
Christchurch 8140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3
110 Stanley Street
Auckland 1010
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canterbury District Health Board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Princess Margaret Hospital
Cashmere Road
Cashmere
PO Box 1600
Christchurch 8140
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Emergency Care Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o Dr Martin Than
Emergency Department
Riccarton Avenue
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8011</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Martin Than</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Emergency Department
Riccarton Avenue
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8011</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The research will provide an innovative and workable change to the medical decision making involved in the investigation, and service delivery for patients presenting acutely to Emergency Departments (EDs) with possible cardiac chest pain. It is a randomised trial comparing current care with a new fast-track pathway. This research will support research knowledge translation by proving the effectiveness in real-time clinical practice, of the findings of recent, promising, cutting edge, New Zealand research. This research suggests that for significant numbers of patients, an accelerated chest pain pathway can rule-out Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI) sooner, enabling earlier progression to the next phase of chest pain investigation(s) and, importantly, allow early discharge from ED, without hospital admission. It is beneficial for the health service, which avoids unnecessary admissions, duplication of staff activities and pressure upon urgent care services.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Upper South A Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
4th Floor
250 Oxford Terrace
PO Box 3877
Christchurch 8011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/07/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>URA/10/06/045</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Martin Than</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Christchurch Hospital
Riccarton Avenue
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8011</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3640 640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.than@cdhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Martin Than</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Christchurch Hospital
Riccarton Avenue
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8011</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3640 640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.than@cdhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>MARTIN THAN</name>
      <address>Emergency Department Christchurch Hospital Riccarton Avenue Private Bag 4710 Christchurch 8011</address>
      <phone>+6433640270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martinthan@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>