<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336915">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000506998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Epirubicin-Paclitaxel-Cyclophosphamide Methotrexate Fluorouracil (E-T-CMF) versus Epirubicin-Cyclophosphamide Methotrexate Fluorouracil  (E-CMF) as adjuvant chemotherapy in high risk patients with operable breast cancer. A phase III study conducted by the Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group (HE10/97)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>High-risk patients with operable breast cancer treated with Epirubicin followed by Paclitaxel followed by Cyclophosphamide-Methotrexate-Fluorouracil (E-T-CMF) or Epirubicin followed by Cyclophosphamide-Methotrexate-Fluorouracil (E-CMF) as adjuvant chemotherapy to investigate the effect of the treatment on disease-free survival and overall survival.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>high-risk operable breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>epirubicin [110  milligram/square meter (mg/m2) intravenously infused over 30 minutes] every 2 weeks for 3 cycles followed by 3 cycles of paclitaxel (250 mg/m2, intravenously infused over 3 hours) every 2 weeks and 3 cycles of CMF (cyclophosphamide; 840 mg/m2, methotrexate; 57 mg/m2 and fluorouracil; 840 mg/m2 intravenously infused over 30 minutes) every 2 weeks</interventions>
    <comparator>epirubicin (110 mg/m2, intravenously infused over 30 minutes) every 2 weeks for 4 cycles followed by 4 cycles of CMF (cyclophosphamide; 840 mg/m2, methotrexate; 57 mg/m2 and fluorouracil; 840 mg/m2, intravenously infused over 30 minutes) every 2 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-Free Survival (DFS). 
DFS was measured from randomization until local recurrence, distant relapse or death from the disease without relapse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years from study initiation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Translational Research of Human Epidermal growth factor Receptor 2 (HER2) status and other biomarkers like: basal marker, angiogenesis, BRCA1 etc.
We collect paraffin embedded tumor tissue at baseline.
The samples are assessed by immunohistochemistry, Fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH), Chromogenic In Situ Hybridization (CISH), polymerase chain reaction (PCR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Results are correlated with outcome at 5 years and 8 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS). 
OS was measured from the date of randomization until death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years from study initiation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute toxicity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Toxicity is assessed by laboratory evaluation of hematology and biochemistry, physical examination etc. 
1 month since the last administration of chemotherapy for acute toxicity</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life. We use the EUroQol (EQ-5D) evaluation questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline-End of Chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Histologically-confirmed epithelial cancer of the mammary gland. -Premenopausal patients with T1 to T2 classification with histologically-confirmed invasion of axillary lymph nodes (N1 classification) or T3 and N0 or N1 classification. -Postmenopausal patients with T1 to T2 classification and &gt; 4 positive axillary nodes or T3 and N0 or N1 classification. - White Blood Cells (WBC) &gt;4x10^9/litre, platelets &gt;100 x10^9 /litre. -Serum creatinine, Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT), serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (SGPT), gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase (gamma-GT), serum bilirubin &lt; = 1.3 milligram/milliliter (mg/ml) or inside the normal range of the participating hospital. -Performance status (World Health Organization) 0 or 1. -Age &gt;= 18 years. -Previous surgical treatment: Either radical surgery (i.e. total, radical or modified radical mastectomy), or, for a partial mastectomy, a histologically confirmed sane margin of 2 cm or more and the results of the axillary node dissection available. -Time from surgery 2 to 4 weeks -Informed consent of the patient according to the dispositions of the Helsinki convention and its Tokyo and Venice amendments and to individual institutional policy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Previous antitumor chemotherapy or radiation
- History of myocardial infarction within the previous 12 months or heart failure (including cardiac insufficiency controlled by digitalis and diuretics) or arrhythmias requiring medication or uncontrolled arterial hypertension (Blood Pressure&gt;= 200/110 millimetres of mercury (mmHg). In high risk patients a normal baseline  left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) should be demonstrated by Multi Gated Acquisition Scan (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram (ECHO).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/06/1997</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/06/1997</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/11/2000</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hatzikostandi 18, 11524, Athens</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Greece</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hatzikostandi 18, 11524, Athens</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Greece</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this phase III, randomized study was to explore the effect of dose-dense sequential chemotherapy with or without paclitaxel primarily on disease-free survival (DFS) and secondarily on overall survival (OS) in patients with high-risk operable breast cancer. Acute toxicity and quality of life were also investigated. Translational research studies were also performed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Postoperative dose-dense sequential chemotherapy with epirubicin, followed byCMFwith or without paclitaxel, in patients with high-risk operable breast cancer: a randomized phase III
study conducted by the Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group
G. Fountzilas, D. Skarlos, U. Dafni, H. Gogas, E. Briasoulis, D. Pectasides, C. Papadimitriou, C. Markopoulos, A. Polychronis, H. P. Kalofonos, V. Siafaka, P. Kosmidis, E. Timotheadou, D. Tsavdaridis, D. Bafaloukos, P. Papakostas, E. Razis, P. Makrantonakis, G. Aravantinos, C. Christodoulou and A.M. Dimopoulos
Annals of Oncology 16: 17621771, 2005

Evaluation of the prognostic and predictive value of p53 and Bcl-2 in breast cancer patients participating in a randomized study with dose-dense sequential adjuvant chemotherapy
V. Malamou-Mitsi, H. Gogas, U. Dafni, A. Bourli, T. Fillipidis, M. Sotiropoulou, D. Vlachodimitropoulos, S. Papadopoulos, O. Tzaida, G. Kafiri, V. Kyriakou, S. Markaki, I. Papaspyrou, E. Karagianni, K. Pavlakis, T. Toliou, C. D. Scopa, P. Papakostas, D. Bafaloukos, C. Christodoulou and G. Fountzilas
Annals of Oncology 17: 15041511, 2006

Evaluation of the prognostic value of HER-2 and VEGF in breast cancer patients participating in a randomized study with dosedense sequential adjuvant chemotherapy
Ioannis Kostopoulos, Petroula Arapantoni-Dadioti, Helen Gogas, Savvas Papadopoulos, Vasiliki Malamou-Mitsi, Chrisoula D. Scopa, Sofia Markaki, Evangelia Karagianni, Vasiliki Kyriakou, Anastasia Margariti, Elisavet Kyrkou, Kitty Pavlakis, Thomas Zaramboukas, Anna Skordalaki, Antonia Bourli, Christos Markopoulos, Dimitrios Pectasides, Meletios A. Dimopoulos, Dimosthenis Skarlos, and George Fountzilas
Breast Cancer Research and Treatment 96: 251261, 2006


Evaluation of the prognostic and predictive value of HER family mRNA expression in high-risk early breast cancer: a Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group (HeCOG) study.
Koutras AK, Kalogeras KT, Dimopoulos MA, Wirtz RM, Dafni U, Briasoulis E, Pectasides D, Gogas H, Christodoulou C, Aravantinos G, Zografos G, Timotheadou E, Papakostas P, Linardou H, Razis E, Economopoulos T, Kalofonos HP, Fountzilas G 
British Journal of Cancer 99(11): 1775-85, 2008


Gene expression of estrogen receptor, progesterone receptor and microtubule-associated protein Tau in high-risk early breast cancer: a quest for molecular predictors of treatment benefit in the context of a Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group trial.
Pentheroudakis G, Kalogeras KT, Wirtz RM, Grimani I, Zografos G, Gogas H, Stropp U, Pectasides D, Skarlos D, Hennig G, Samantas E, Bafaloukos D, Papakostas P, Kalofonos HP, Pavlidis N, Fountzilas G
Breast Cancer Research and Treatment 116(1):131-43, 2009


Prognostic utility of beta-tubulin isotype III and correlations with other molecular and clinicopathological variables in patients with early breast cancer: a translational Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group (HeCOG) study.
Pentheroudakis G, Batistatou A, Kalogeras KT, Kronenwett R, Wirtz RM, Bournakis E, Eleftheraki AG, Pectasides D, Bobos M, Papaspirou I, Kamina S, Gogas H, Koutras AK, Pavlidis N, Fountzilas G 
Breast Cancer Research and Treatment 127(1):179-93, 2011


Triple-negative phenotype is of adverse prognostic value in patients treated with dose-dense sequential adjuvant chemotherapy: a translational research analysis in the context
of a Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group (HeCOG) randomized phase III trial
P. Skarlos, C. Christodoulou, K. T. Kalogeras , A. G. Eleftheraki , M. Bobos , A. Batistatou , C. Valavanis, O. Tzaida, E. Timotheadou, R. Kronenwett, R. M. Wirtz, I. Kostopoulos, D. Televantou, E. Koutselini, I. Papaspirou, C. A. Papadimitriou, D. Pectasides, H. Gogas, G. Aravantinos, N. Pavlidis, P. Arapantoni, D. V. Skarlos, G. Fountzilas
Cancer Chemotherapy and Pharmacology 69(2): 533-46, 2012


HER2 and TOP2A in high-risk early breast cancer patients treated with adjuvant epirubicin-based dose-dense sequential chemotherapy
George Fountzilas, Christos Valavanis, Vassiliki Kotoula, Anastasia G Eleftheraki, Konstantine T Kalogeras, Olympia Tzaida, Anna Batistatou, Ralf Kronenwett, Ralph M Wirtz, Mattheos Bobos, Eleni Timotheadou, Nikolaos Soupos, George Pentheroudakis, Helen Gogas, Dimitrios Vlachodimitropoulos, Genovefa Polychronidou, Gerasimos Aravantinos, Angelos Koutras, Christos Christodoulou, Dimitrios Pectasides and Petroula Arapantoni
Journal of Translational Medicine 2012, 10:10


Improved Outcome of High-Risk Early HER2 Positive Breast Cancer With High CXCL13-
CXCR5 Messenger RNA Expression
Evangelia Razis, Konstantine T. Kalogeras, Vassiliki Kotoula, Anastasia G. Eleftheraki, Nikitas Nikitas, Ralf Kronenwett, Eleni Timotheadou, Christos Christodoulou, Dimitrios Pectasides,
Helen Gogas, Ralph M. Wirtz, Thomas Makatsoris, Dimitrios Bafaloukos, Gerasimos Aravantinos, Despina Televantou, Nicholas Pavlidis, George Fountzilas 
Clinical Breast Cancer 12(3): 183-93, 2012


Prognostic significance of UBE2C mRNA expression in high-risk early breast cancer. A Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group (HeCOG) Study.
Psyrri A, Kalogeras KT, Kronenwett R, Wirtz RM, Batistatou A, Bournakis E, Timotheadou E, Gogas H, Aravantinos G, Christodoulou C, Makatsoris T, Linardou H, Pectasides D, Pavlidis N, Economopoulos T, Fountzilas G
Annals of Oncology 23(6): 1422-7, 2012


The prognostic and predictive value of mRNA expression of vascular endothelial growth factor family members in breast cancer: a study in primary tumors of high-risk early breast cancer patients participating in a randomized Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group trial.
Linardou H, Kalogeras KT, Kronenwett R, Kouvatseas G, Wirtz RM, Zagouri F, Gogas H, Christodoulou C, Koutras AK, Samantas E, Pectasides D, Bafaloukos D, Fountzilas G
Breast Cancer Research 14(6):R145, 2012


Prognostic significance of RACGAP1 mRNA expression in high-risk early breast cancer: a study in primary tumors of breast cancer patients participating in a randomized Hellenic Cooperative Oncology Group trial.
Pliarchopoulou K, Kalogeras KT, Kronenwett R, Wirtz RM, Eleftheraki AG, Batistatou A, Bobos M, Soupos N, Polychronidou G, Gogas H, Samantas E, Christodoulou C, Makatsoris T, Pavlidis N, Pectasides D, Fountzilas G
Cancer Chemotherapy and Pharmacology 71(1):245-55, 2013
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof. George Fountzilas, MD</name>
      <address>"Papageorgiou" Hospital, Nea Efkarpia, 564 29, Thessaloniki</address>
      <phone>+30 2313323959</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fountzil@auth.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Eleni Papakostaki</name>
      <address>18, Hatzikostandi str, 11524, Athens</address>
      <phone>+30 2106912520</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e_papakostaki@hecog.ondsl.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Maria Moschoni</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>m_moschoni@hecog.ondsl.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>George Fountzilas, MD</name>
      <address>"Papageorgiou" Hospital, Nea Efkarpia, 564 29, Thessaloniki</address>
      <phone>+30 2313323959</phone>
      <fax>+30 2313683136</fax>
      <email>fountzil@auth.gr</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>