<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373305">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001082392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating the risk of adverse maternal and infant perinatal outcomes following vaccination during pregnancy, Australia 1994-2015.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Retrospective cohort analysis to investigate the risk of adverse maternal and infant perinatal outcomes following vaccination during pregnancy, Australia 1994-2015.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Maternal vaccination</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory illnesses</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Retrospective cohort analyses of four separate datasets where data collection is complete.
Written, informed consent was obtained from each individual participant in each study. 
1. 'FluMum' (NHMRC Project Grant no.APP1020035, HREC Reference Number: 2012-1744) . Data collection occurred from 01 April 2012- 30 June 2015.
2.'PneuMum' (HREC Reference Number: 05-52). Data collection occurred from August 2006 and January 2011. Exact dates of data collection not provided due to potentially identifiable information of Indigenous participants. 
3. '1+1HS' (HREC Reference Number: 2016-2710) studies. Data collection occurred from  2004-2006 and 2009-2011. Exact dates of data collection not provided due to potentially identifiable information of Indigenous participants. 
Participants were interviewed by trained research staff using a detailed structured questionnaire at birth and then at 6 months post-partum.
Exposures will be inactivated influenza, dTpa(pertussis) and 23v polysaccharide pneumococcal vaccines in pregnancy compared to unvaccinated pregnant women.</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical NT birth cohort of de-identified perinatal data from 1 Jan 1984-31 Dec 2014 based on an NHMRC funded probabilistically linked study 'Partnership Project Grant'
HREC Reference number: 2017-2749.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Congenital anomalies between infants of vaccinated and unvaccinated mothers up until 6 months post-partum as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review. For international consistency, congenital anomalies will be identified using ICD-10 coding and will be classified according to the Brighton Collaboration working group definitions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>low birthweight in infants of vaccinated and unvaccinated mothers as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review. For our study, low birthweight is defined as an infant at term weighing less than 2500grams.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>preterm birth in infants of vaccinated and unvaccinated mothers as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review. For our study preterm birth will be define as less than 37 completed weeks gestation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=Small for gestational age (SGA) in infants of vaccinated and unvaccinated mothers assessed by calculation using validated algorithm of infant birthweights and gestations at birth (self-reported and medical record review). Our study defines SGA as birth weight below the 10th percentile of the Australian population birth weight versus gestational age greater than or equal to 20 weeks gestation, by sex.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=Maternal deaths as assessed by medical record review </outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=All cause maternal hospitalisations as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review </outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>COMPOSITE SECONDARY OUTCOME= Maternal co-morbidities and risk factors for infection as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review. For our study, a co-morbidity and risk factor for infection is anything other than a normal viable pregnancy from 20 weeks gestation until 6 months post-partum</outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=Stillbirths as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>at birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=Pregnancy complications as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review. For our study a pregnancy complication is one that involves anything other than a normal viable pregnancy greater than 20 weeks gestation resulting in a live infant born at term.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=infant morbidities as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review. For our study, an infant morbidity will be defined as any illness requiring medical attention or review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=infant deaths as assessed by medical record review </outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=All cause infant hospitalisations as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review </outcome>
      <timepoint>up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRIMARY OUTCOME=Birth complications as assessed by maternal self-report and medical record review. For our study a birth complication is one resulting in anything other than a normal vaginal birth of a live infant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up until 6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i.	Mothers  any pregnancy greater than or equal to 20 weeks gestation
ii.	Infants born greater than or equal to 20 weeks gestation and/or weighing greater than or equal to 400grams
iii.	Singleton infants from singleton pregnancies
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i.	Non-pregnant women 
ii.	Multiparous pregnancies (pregnancies where the woman is carrying more than one fetus)
iii.	Infants who are a twin, triplet or other multiple birth 
iv.	Participants in the FluMum, PneuMum and 1+1HS datasets where maternal vaccination status is unknown
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Effect estimates from univariable and multivariable logistic regression models will be presented as adjusted odds-ratios, accounting for clustered data where applicable. Expected incidence rates (IRs) of adverse maternal and infant perinatal outcomes will be calculated using an historic, largely unvaccinated 20-year population birth cohort (19942014), and compared with the observed incidence rates (IRs) in maternally vaccinated (influenza, pertussis, pneumococcal) and unvaccinated pregnant mothers. Standardised incidence ratios (SIR) will be calculated using Poisson regression with 95% confidence intervals. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>85000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>85000</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>10/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,NT,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname> Menzies School of Health Research </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1,147 Wharf Street 
Spring Hill, Brisbane 
QLD, 4000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> Charles Darwin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ellengowan Drive, Casuarina NT 0810</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Retrospective descriptive analysis of the safety of maternal vaccination utilising 4 datasets: FluMum, PneuMum, 1+1HS and a population based de-identified NT birth cohort. Combined datasets ~85,000 mother-infant pairs, of which ~30% identify as Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander. There is no active participant recruitment, no blood tests or specimen collections and no direct contact with any participants. Results will be presented as large aggregate data with no potential for identifying information. Results will contribute novel information on adverse maternal and infant perinatal outcomes over a 21 year period (1994-2015) .We will calculate Observed-to-Expected ratios to describe the risk of an adverse outcome occurring following maternal vaccination in pregnancy with influenza, pertussis or pneumococcal vaccines.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Menzies School of Health Research Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee of the NT Department of Health and Menzies School of Health Research PO Box 41096, Casuarina NT 0811.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-2015-2333</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lisa McHugh</name>
      <address>Menzies School of Health Research, Charles Darwin University
Level 1,147 Wharf Street 
Spring Hill, Brisbane 
QLD, 4000
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3169 4209 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.mchugh@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lisa McHugh</name>
      <address>Menzies School of Health Research, Charles Darwin University
Level 1,147 Wharf Street 
Spring Hill, Brisbane 
QLD, 4000
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3169 4209 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.mchugh@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lisa McHugh</name>
      <address>Menzies School of Health Research, Charles Darwin University
Level 1,147 Wharf Street 
Spring Hill, Brisbane 
QLD, 4000
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3169 4209</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.mchugh@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lisa Mchugh</name>
      <address>Menzies School of Health Research, Charles Darwin University
Level 1,147 Wharf Street 
Spring Hill, Brisbane 
QLD, 4000
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3169 4209</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.mchugh@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>