<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366748">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000834651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Variation of the respiratory volumes in the asthmatic subject after the rotation sitting impulse technique of the dorso-lumbar junction.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Variation of the respiratory volumes in the asthmatic subject after the rotation sitting impulse technique of the dorso-lumbar junction.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1159-0943</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Osteopathic treatment: Rotation sitting impulse technique of the dorso-lumbar junction bilaterally
technique of high velocity, low amplitude in the dorso-lumbar junction known in osteopathy as "Fryette modified technique for dysfunction in T12 ERS." The aim of the technique is to increase lung volumes by restoring mobility at this level, where the diaphragmatic pillars are originated. 
Subject Position: Sitting, hands placed like lift-off technique. Therapist position: forward to a side of the subject. 
Contacts: pectoral contact on the outside of the upper side of the subject, locking the trunk. The previous hand contact on the back of the shoulder encircling the trunk of the subject and the elbow raised to rest his forehead. The back hand takes a pisiform contact ulnar border of the hand on the nested facet of T12
The technique is administered on a single occasion, but bilaterally
The duration of the tecnique is less than a minute (30 seconds approximately)

</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo. 
The same position of the subject and the osteopath, the same parameters and principles of the technique applied to the experimental group, but without impulse.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Possible variations of respiratory volumes FVC, FEV1, FEV1/FVC ratio and PEF assessed by spirometry, using a MIR Spirobank Registered Trademark  USB spirometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, 1 minute post-intervention, 30 minutes post-intervention and 1 week post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Possible variations of MiniAQLQ quality of life questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention and 1 week post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Having diagnosed the disease "asthma" for over 1 year 
Aged between 20 and 49 years inclusive 
Sign the informed consent. 
Do not submit any exclusion criteria</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>49</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>COPD 
Lung Cancer 
Emphysema 
Pulmonary edema 
Heart failure 
Pulmonary hypertension 
Smooth muscle disorders and / or striated 
Surgical lung and / or chest 
Use of inhaled beta 2 agonists in the 24 hours prior to the study 
Rates of asthma medication in the last 6 weeks or during the study 
Hospitalization for acute crisis, and / or oral corticosteroids in the last month or during the study 
Anxiety 
Depression 
Respiratory infection in the last month 
Osteopathic treatment in the last month 
Osteopathic treatment for asthma in the last 5 years 
Contraindication to performing maneuvers study: fractures and / or dislocations, tumors, infections, inflammatory rheumatism, birth defects, osteoporosis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The method of allocation concealment used wwas central randomsation by computer.
Subjects were randomly assigned to study groups using a table of random numbers generated by a computer, once it was found that the subject met the inclusion and exclusion criteria for participation in the study. 
6 sequences encoded characters (A, B) replacing the random numbers, in which A represents the experimental group and B represents control group were used. The randomization sequence was guarded at all times by the principal investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization using a randomisation table generated by a computer</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To calculate the sample size formula for estimating proportions was used. The study population was 63,566 subjects (estimated from prevalence data of 4.4% between the ages 18-44 years in Madrid population). An error of 13.5% and a confidence interval of 95% was assumed. The formula for calculating the sample size has the following mathematical expression: 

       k(2) * P *Q      1,96(2) * 0,5 * 0,5
n = --------------- = -------------------------- = 52,71   52
             e(2)                   0,135(2)

where: 
k = constant for 95% = 1.96 
P = proportion of individuals that possess the property of the population = 0.5 
Q = 1 - P = 1 to 0.5 
e = MPE = 13.5% 
Therefore, the appropriate sample size for the study was 52 subjects.

Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS version 19.0 program. There has been a statistical description of the bulk sample, and one each of the study groups. The Kormogorov-Smirnov test was used to verify whether or not data fit a normal distribution. 
In the intragroup analysis, as proof of hypothesis testing for comparing scores pre-intervention and post-intervention Student t test for related samples was performed for both GE and GC. For the intergroup analysis, the Student t test for independent samples, where the differences between the post-intervention measures were contrasted minus pre-intervention between GE and GC measures. A confidence interval of 95%, so that is considered statistically significant values are those established as p &lt;0.05</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>26/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Escuela de Osteopatia de Madrid</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>San Felix de Alcala Street, 4
28807 Alcala de Henares
Madrid</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>David Nunez Fernandez</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Estrasburgo II Avenue, no 77
28514 Nuevo Baztan 
Madrid (SPAIN)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objectives: To assess the possible variations of FVC, FEV1, FEV1/FVC ratio, PEF and MiniAQLQ quality of life questionnaire after the application of the rotation sitting impulse technique of the dorso-lumbar junction in asthmatic subjects.

Hypothesis: The application of the rotation sitting impulse technique of the dorso-lumbar junction in asthmatic subjects produces statistically significant changes on spirometric values for forced vital capacity (FVC), forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1), FEV1/FVC ratio, peak expiratory flow (PEF) and MiniAQLQ quality of life questionnaire. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Experimentation Ethics Committee of the University of Seville</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pabellon de Brasil
Paseo de las Delicias s/n 
41013 Sevilla 
SPAIN</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366748-Questionnaire for evaluation by experimentation ethics committee of the University of Sevilla.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366748-Report approved by the Ethics Committee for Experimentation of the University of Seville.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366748-Blank clinical record forms.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366748-Informed consent for study participation.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366748-Data confidentiality.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Nunez Fernandez</name>
      <address>Escuela de Osteopatia de Madrid
Avenida Estrasburgo II, no 77
28514 Nuevo Baztan
Madrid</address>
      <phone>+34 669927288 </phone>
      <fax>+ 34 91 8725532</fax>
      <email>davidnunezfernandez@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Nunez Fernandez</name>
      <address>David Nunez Fernandez
Escuela de Osteopatia de Madrid
Avenida Estrasburgo II, no 77
28514 Nuevo Baztan
Madrid</address>
      <phone>+ 34 669927288</phone>
      <fax>+ 34 91 8725532</fax>
      <email>davidnunezfernandez@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Nunez Fernandez </name>
      <address>David Nunez Fernandez
Escuela de Osteopatia de Madrid
Avenida Estrasburgo II, no 77
28514 Nuevo Baztan
Madrid</address>
      <phone>+ 34 669927288</phone>
      <fax>+ 34 91 8725532</fax>
      <email>davidnunezfernandez@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Nunez Fernandez</name>
      <address>David Nunez Fernandez
Escuela de Osteopatia de Madrid
Avenida Estrasburgo II, no 77
28514 Nuevo Baztan
Madrid</address>
      <phone>+ 34 669927288</phone>
      <fax>+ 34 91 8725532</fax>
      <email>davidnunezfernandez@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>