<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366486">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000629639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Carbohydrate dependence during endurance exercise (The effect of Nicotinic acid on endurance performance in trained cyclists)  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of Nicotinic acid on endurance performance in trained cyclists </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>endurance exercise performance in healthy trained athletes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Using a repeated measures design, we will test our hypothesis in 10 well-trained cyclists who will each perform six maximal, all-out cycling time-trials (over 60, 90 and 120 min duration), three under conditions where lipolysis and fat oxidation are blocked and three under normal conditions (control). Lipolysis will be blocked via orally administered nicotinic acid.

1a) The dose administered for the the 60 min trial will be 20 mg/kg BM
The dose administered for the 90 min trial will be 25 mg/kg BM
The dose for the 120 min trial will be 30 mg/kg BM
b)Doses 1x10 mg/kg BM dose 30 mins before trial, 1x5 mg/kg dose 15 min before trial, and 5 mg/kg BM after completion of  every 30 min of trial.
2)TT's will be conducted on a stationary bike.
3) wash out period will be at least 72 hr between trials</interventions>
    <comparator>Control conditions will be the same conditions as the experimental group but instead of taking the nicotinic acid participants will be orally administered small doses of glucose powder (placebo)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to complete time trial</outcome>
      <timepoint>compare time trial times under nicotinic acid conditions to control/placebo conditions</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory Exchange Ratio values. assessed using a Parvomedics metabolic cart. </outcome>
      <timepoint>compare values attained during nicotinic acid conditions with values attained during control/placebo conditions. These outcome will be assessed at the completion of all trials from all subjects </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: 
 Aged 18-35 years
 Participants must be engaged in cycling training &gt; 200km/week.
Participants must have at least 2 years of competitive cycling experience.
VO2max of greater than 60 mL/ (kg BM/min). 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: 
Current or prior use of anabolic steroids or other prohibited substances.
Contraindications to strenuous physical activity as indicated by cardiovascular risk factor questionnaire.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Initially telephone interviews, e-mail or a face to face meeting will assess suitability and if subjects comply with inclusion/exclusion criteria. Subsequently, participants will attend a physiological testing session to assess suitability for the study. The selected participants will then be informed about all the details of the study and the risks and benefits involved. A signed Informed consent document approved by the Human Ethics Committee at the Australian Catholic University will be obtained prior to any experimental trials. 

</concealment>
    <sequence>trial conditions will assigned a number (1, 2, 3, 4, 5 or 6) with each number only being used once. These 6 numbers will then be entered into a random code generator of which 10 combinations will be selected for the 10 participants. each participant will then be allocated a code and that is the order that they will complete the trials.

the method of allocation concealment we will use is numbered containers</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>9</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Catholic University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>115 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Institute of Sport</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> Leverrier Crescent, Bruce ACT 2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Institute of Sport</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress> Leverrier Crescent, Bruce ACT 2617</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One of the major adaptations of muscle to endurance training is a slower utilization of carbohydrate stored in the muscle (muscle glycogen) and blood glucose and  greater reliance on fat oxidation during low intensity exercise. . These adaptations are thought to play an important role in the large increase in the ability to perform prolonged strenuous exercise that occurs in response to endurance exercise training. However, the results of early studies demonstrate carbohydrate dependence during prolonged endurance events (i.e. marathon running) lasting up to 3 hours, with little (&lt;10%) contribution from fat to the total fuel requirements of exercise. Using a pharmacological agent Nicotinic acid(also known as Niacin or Vitamin B3) to block the breakdown and liberation of free fatty acids into the bloodstream(lipolysis) and impair rates of fat oxidation during exercise, we will test the hypothesis that carbohydrate is the predominant (&gt;90% of total energy requirements) fuel for muscle oxidation during cycling time trials  lasting from 60-120 min. Using a repeated measures design, we will test our hypothesis in 10 well-trained cyclists who, after a standardised diet/exercise control, will each perform six maximal, all-out cycling time-trials (over 60, 90 and 120 min duration), three under conditions where lipolysis and fat oxidation are blocked and three under normal conditions (control). We hypothesise that there will be no differences in the time-trial performance for any duration, and that carbohydrate oxidation will be the major fuel for oxidative energy production. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Torrens, S.L., Areta, J.L., Parr, E.B., Hawley, J.A. Carbohydrate dependence during prolonged simulated cycling time trials. 2016, 116(4): 781-90.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Manager, Ethics
c/o Office of the Deputy Vice Chancellor (Research)
Australian Catholic University
North Sydney Campus
PO Box 968
NORTH SYDNEY, NSW 2059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014 51V</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Daniel Mannix Building
Level One
office 1.32
115 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9953 5552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>John.Hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Daniel Mannix Building
Level One
office 1.32
115 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9953 5552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>John.Hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Hawley</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Daniel Mannix Building
Level One
office 1.32
115 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9953 5552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>John.Hawley@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>