<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372832">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000647336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A bike pedalling based protocol after total knee replacement surgery compared to a standard multi-exercise physiotherapy program: a randomised control trial.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A bike pedalling based protocol after total knee replacement surgery compared to a standard multi-exercise physiotherapy program: a randomised control trial.

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Total Knee Replacement</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Intervention or "Pedalling" group will be given a modified physiotherapy protocol with the main exercise being stationary pedalling on a set of floor pedals, it will also include gait retraining and walking as well as a knee extension (straightening) stretch. A senior orthopaedic physiotherapist will be delivering both the Intervention and Control group physiotherapy protocols. In the hospital setting, the twice daily 20-minute physiotherapy session will consist of 2 exercises (pedalling and a knee extension stretch, gait retraining &amp; aid prescription and practice of functional activities such as transfers and stair climbing. 8 minutes will be dedicated to the bike pedalling activity, 2 minutes to the extension stretch, and the other 10 minutes towards gait retraining and achievement of functional goals for discharge such as independent transfers and mobility. Once discharged the patient will continue with this home exercise program twice daily for 20 minutes and will be given a diary to tick off daily to calculate compliance, they are asked to return the diary to the assessor at their 2-week review.  As patients will be independent with transfers and mobility on discharge, an increased time can be spent on their home exercise program which consists of the same exercises in hospital and should be split, 10 minutes on pedalling, 5 minutes of knee extension stretching, and 5 minutes spent on gait training with an emphasis on heel-toe strike.

Both the Intervention and Control groups will commence physiotherapy on the day of surgery and undergo the same twice daily inpatient physiotherapy sessions post total knee replacement surgery, the time of each session will be approximately 20 minutes. This is no different than the standard frequency and duration of current inpatient physiotherapy sessions. Patients are instructed not to see an outpatient physiotherapist between discharge and their 2 week follow up assessment.</interventions>
    <comparator>The Control or "Multi-exercise" group will be given a standard multi­-exercise physiotherapy program which includes seated knee bends, Inner range knee strengthening exercise and functional strength exercises such as mini squats and calf raises. The control group will also be given the knee extension stretch and gait­ retraining, however, they will not be given any stationary pedalling exercises. A senior orthopaedic physiotherapist will be delivering both the Intervention and Control group physiotherapy protocols. The 20 minute session for the control group will consist of 10 minutes dedicated to the mult-exercise handout which is the same as their on-going 2 week home exercise program. The other 10 minutes will be spent on gait retraining and achievement of functional goals for discharge such as independent transfers and mobility. Once discharged the patient will continue with this home exercise program twice daily for 20 minutes and will be given a diary to tick off daily to calculate compliance, they are asked to return the diary to the assessor at their 2-week review. As patients will be independent with transfers and mobility on discharge, an increased time can be spent on their home exercise program which consists of the same exercises in hospital and should be split, 15 minutes on multi-exercise handout and 5 minutes spent on gait training with an emphasis on heel-toe strike. 


Both the Intervention and Control groups will commence physiotherapy on the day of surgery and undergo the same twice daily inpatient physiotherapy sessions post total knee replacement surgery, the time of each session will be approximately 20 minutes. This is no different than the standard frequency and duration of current inpatient physiotherapy sessions. Patients are instructed not to see an outpatient physiotherapist between discharge and their 2 week follow up assessment.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>10 meter timed walk test
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 days, 12 days and 4 months post TKR surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 minute walk test </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 days, 12 days, and 4 months post TKR surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EuroQol 5 Dimensions (EQ5D) Health Outcome Measure Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 days, 12 days, and 4 months post TKR surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed Up and Go 3 meter walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 days, 12 days and 4 months post TKR Surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxford Knee Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 days, 12 days and 4 months post TKR Surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee flexion ROM</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 days, 12 days and 4 months post TKR Surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analgesia Consumption, recorded by review of the medication chart from the patient's hospital medical record. Specifically, Oxycodone which is prescribed for "breakthrough" pain relief, and is prescribed as "PRN" or "as needed".</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of TKR surgery to discharge from acute hospital ward</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Threshold self-reported Likert Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 days post TKR Surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Satisfaction with Physiotherapy self-reported Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 12 days post TKR Surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>"Time at which the patient is deemed safe for discharge" this is routinely decided by the orthopaedic physiotherapist at our institution and is dependent on the achievement of the following functional goals:
Independent transfers 
Independent mobility (with aid for discharge)
Completed stairs practice
Achieved 90 degrees knee flexion at any point during post-operative hospital stay

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured in days from day of surgery to day of discharge from the acute hospital setting. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients of one particular Orthopaedic Surgeon at our Institution undergoing primary unilateral total knee replacement surgery with a primary diagnosis of osteoarthritis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they have a history of a mental illness or a condition which would interfere with the patients ability to understand the requirements of the study. This may include, but is not limited to, a history of dementia or short-­term memory impairment. Participants will also be excluded if they have a predisposition to be discharged to an inpatient rehabilitation (or hostel) facility due to lack of social support (for example, the patient would otherwise return home with no carer availability) or other physical impairment that would mean they could not perform a home exercise program without hands­on assistance. 
Participants will also be excluded if they have a physical condition following surgery that makes them unable to participate in testing, i.e an extreme nauseous reaction following anaesthesia or a severe medical complication that would limit mobility such as a pulmonary embolism, or syncopal event.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelope, carried out by Surgeon's practice Nurse, who is otherwise not involved in any other aspect of this trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised Sequence Generation: Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>60 participants (30 in each group) is based on the existing research publication "The immediate and long­term effects of a walking­ skill program compared to usual physiotherapy care in patients who have undergone total knee arthroplasty (TKA): a randomised controlled trial" (Bruun­Olsen V, Heiberg KE, Wahl AK, Mengshoel AM. The immediate and long­term effects of a walking­skill program compared to usual physiotherapy care in patients who have undergone total knee arthroplasty (TKA): a randomised controlled trial. Disabil Rehabil.2013;35(23):200815. 
doi: 10.3109/09638288.2013.770084.) 
In total, this study included 57 patients in its analysis, 29 in the walking­skill group and 28 in the usual physiotherapy care group, in the primary outcome measure, 6MWT, a statistically significant difference in change scores between the two groups was seen. In addition, further sample size estimates will be calculated using G­Power, utilising the appropriate primary outcome measure.

The quantitative data will be analysed using the Statistical Package SPSS. A repeated measures ANOVA (analysis of variance) will be utilized to assess the relevant and specific outcome measures across the data collection time points of 3 days, 12 days, and 4 months postoperatively. Additional post hoc comparisons and analysis will be utilised where appropriate.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>20</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Pindara Private Hospital - Benowa</hospital>
    <postcode>4217 - Benowa</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Larissa Sattler</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Senior Orthopaedic Physiotherapist
Pindara Private Hospital
Allchurch Avenue
Benowa 4217 QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bond University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>14 University Dr, Robina QLD 4226</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bond University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>14 University Dr, Robina QLD 4226</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a research investigation into physiotherapy treatment after Total Knee Replacement surgery. This trial is specifically designed to compare two different types of physiotherapy exercise groups, to evaluate whether they provide equal benefit to patients in regards to both physical measures and patient reported satisfaction.

The treatment group will be given a modified physiotherapy protocol with the main exercise being stationary pedalling, it will also include gait retraining and walking as well as a knee extension (straightening) stretch. The control group will be given a standard multi­exercise physiotherapy program which includes seated knee bends, Inner range knee strengthening exercise and functional strength exercises such as mini squats and calf raises. The control group will also be given the knee extension stretch and gait ­retraining, however, they will not be given any stationary pedalling exercises. 
A selection of outcome measures will be recorded at 2 days, 12 days and 4 months post-operatively in conjunction with the participant's Orthopaedic surgeon review.
Outcome measures will include: 
Time of which the patient is deemed safe for discharge from hospital by the treating physiotherapist 
Timed Up &amp; Go test functional measure test 
10 Meter timed walk test 
6-minute walk test 
Knee Range of Motion Measurement 
Subjective measurement tools including the EQ5D survey (incorporating a VAS pain scale), and the Oxford Knee Score.

The significance of the results of this study would be to provide evidence for substituting a standard physiotherapy protocol, which includes a variety of treatment modalities and exercises, with a simplified one which can be mostly patient driven. If the results of the simplified bike pedal group are better than or no different than the standard multi­exercise physiotherapy group then there would be implications for greater time efficiency for treating physiotherapists and an overall cost benefit associated with this.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bond University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>14 University Dr, Robina QLD 4226</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15631</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Greenslopes Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Greenslopes Private Hospital
Newgate St. Greenslopes QLD 4120</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/49</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372832-BUHREC Approval Letter.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372832-PARTICIPANT EXPLANATORY FORM (Final).docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372832-PARTICIPANT INFORMED CONSENT FORM (Final).docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Larissa Sattler</name>
      <address>Senior Orthopaedic Physiotherapist
Pindara Private Hospital 
Allchurch Avenue, Benowa
QLD 4217
</address>
      <phone>+61755889125</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sattlerl@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Larissa Sattler</name>
      <address>Senior Orthopaedic Physiotherapist
Pindara Private Hospital 
Allchurch Avenue, Benowa
QLD 4217</address>
      <phone>+61755889125</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sattlerl@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Larissa Sattler</name>
      <address>Senior Orthopaedic Physiotherapist
Pindara Private Hospital 
Allchurch Avenue, Benowa
QLD 4217</address>
      <phone>+61755889125</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sattlerl@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Larissa Sattler</name>
      <address>Senior Orthopaedic Physiotherapist
Pindara Private Hospital 
Allchurch Avenue, Benowa
QLD 4217</address>
      <phone>+61755889125</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sattlerl@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>