<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363024">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000991819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Patients with non-functioning pituitary tumours: Are there differences between gender in post-operative hormone outcomes and does this relate to the pressure within the tumours?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Participants with non-functioning pituitary macroadenomas: Intrasellar pressure measurement at the time of operation and pituitary hormone deficiencies. Do gender differences exist?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1134-5769</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non functioning pituitary adenomas</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hormone Deficiencies</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1) Observational data of hormone deficiencies pre and 6 months post operatively for surgically treated non functioning pituitary adenomas. 
2) Measurement of pressure within the pituitary adenoma at the time of surgery
3) Quality of life questionnaire pre and 6 months post surgery</interventions>
    <comparator>No camparator or control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>That Premenopausal females have fewer hormone deficiencies compared to males and postmenopausal females post-operatively for treatment of non functioning pituitary macroadenomas. This will be assessed by the collection of biochemical hormone blood test. The hormonal assessment is routine part of clinical management of this condition. We aim to collect this data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>That Intrasellar pressure measured at the time of operation is lower in premenopausal females compared to males and postmenopausal females. This measurement of intrasellar pressure will be measured at the time of surgery using a commercial kit - Codman Intracranial Pressure Monitoring Kit (Camino Laboratories San Diego CA). At surgery, dura is exposed by removal of the bony sella floor, and a 1.5mm dural opening made allowing insertion of the fiberoptic transducer tip into the pituitary tumour with minimal chance of tumour extravasation. When a stable waveform is present on the pressure monitor, mean ISP is recorded and the catheter removed, with surgery proceeding as usual. This procedure will take 3-5 minutes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the time of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The measurement of Quality of life of participants pre and 6 month post surgery: that quality of life remains unchanged. This will be undertaken by a a validated questionnaire SF36- 4 week recall. Participants will undertake the questionnaire pre-operatively and 6 months post-peratively, with each participant acting as their own control</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively and 6 months post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All adult patients who require surgery for non functioning pituitary adenomas having surgery at the study hospitals will be eligible for inclusion in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to give consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>93</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Carmela Caputo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Vincent's Hospital,
35 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy, 3065
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>35 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy, 3065,
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The pituitary gland is an important gland that assists in control and release of hormones in the body. Abnormal growths in the gland, called pituitary tumours or adenomas can occur. The most frequent type requiring surgery is the non-functioning pituitary macroadenoma (NFPMA), which are tumours that dont produce any excessive hormones but can be associated with hormone deficiences. 
At St Vincents Hospital, we have reviewed our own historical series of NFPMA.  Between 1995 and 2010, 141 cases of NFPMA  were operated on. It was observed that males were more likely than females to be to have 2 or more hormonal deficiencies at presentation.  Post-operatively,  2 or more hormone deficiencies occurred more frequently in males and postmenopausal females but rarely in premenopausal females. So it appears that premenopausal females to have better hormonal outcomes. 
We have hypothesed that it may be related to lower pressure within tumours of premenopausal females. High pressure in the tumour is postulated to reduce blood flow to the pituitary gland and leads to death of normal hormone producing cells, thus less ability for hormonal recovery.  
This current project has been designed to confirm if gender differences in hormone deficiencies do occur after surgery. Also to demonstrate that pressure within tumours of premenopausal females in lower than males and postmenopausal females. 
These findings are important as they contribute to the understanding of hormonal differences in genders, which has not been fully examined before.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2012 Aug 13. doi: 10.1111/cen.12009. [Epub ahead of print]

Gender differences in presentation and outcome of non-functioning pituitary macroadenomas.

Caputo C, Sutherland T, Farish S, McNeill P, Ng KW, Inder WJ.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincents Hospital Research and Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-A 028/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carmela Caputo</name>
      <address>4th Floor Daly Wing
Department of Endocrinology
St Vincent's Hospital, 
35 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy, 3065
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 3579</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9288 3590</fax>
      <email>carmela.caputo@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carmela Caputo</name>
      <address>4th Floor Daly Wing
Department of Endocrinology
St Vincent's Hospital, 
35 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy, 3065
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 3579</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9288 3590</fax>
      <email>carmela.caputo@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carmela Caputo</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne,
4th Floor Daly Wing
Department Endocrinology and Diabetes
35 Victoria Parade,
Fitzroy 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carmela.caputo@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>