<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364115">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000472774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The PEBBLES study: Prevention of Eczema By a Barrier Lipid Equilibrium Strategy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does twice daily application of a ceramide dominant cream (EpiCeram) for the first six months of life reduce the incidence of eczema by six months of age, when compared to standard skin care, in infants who have a family history of allergic disease </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1142-2705</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PEBBLES</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ACTR12609000727246: The PEBBLES Pilot Study</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>eczema</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Twice daily use of a ceramide dominant cream (EpiCeram) to infants skin. Ingredients in the formulation are Capric Acid, Cholesterol, Citric Acid, Conjugated Linoleic Acid, Dimethicone, Disodium EDTA, E. Cerifera (Candelilla)
Wax, Food Starch Modified Corn Syrup Solids, Glycerin, Glyceryl Stearate, Hydroxypropyl Bispalmitamide MEA
(Ceramide), Palmitic Acid, PEG-100 Stearate, Petrolatum, Phenoxyethanol, Potassium Hydroxide, Purified Water,
Sorbic Acid, Squalane, Xanthan Gum. Approximatly six grams will be applied twice per day. Duration of treatment is 6 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>The study staff will not provide any directions to parents in the control arm on how to manage their child's skin. No attempt will be made to alter or influence parents treatment of their child's skin in this arm of the study. This is defined as standard skin care. Duration of care is 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of eczema as assessed using the UK working party criteria for eczema</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks and 6 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Transepidermal water loss (TEWL) as assessed using Vapometer on the infants forearm and forehead </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks and 6 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of eczema, as assessed using the UK working party criteria for eczema, six months post cessation of study treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Probable eczema, as defined by diagnosis of eczema by medical practitioner that was not verified by the study investigators.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During treatment period (0 to 6 months), and for six months (7 to 12 months of age) post cessation of treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eczema severity as measured by SCORing Atopic Dermatitis (SCORAD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months &amp; 12 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin prick test reactivity to six common food (cows' milk, peanut and hens egg) and areo-allergens (house dust mite, rye grass and cat dander), defined as a wheal of 3mm or greater than the negative saline control.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomechanical properties of the skin (pH, hydration, oiliness) assessed using a Skin-pH-Meter (PH905), Coneometer (CM 825), and Sebumeter (SM 815) from Courage + Khazaka electronic</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 and 12 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Either mother and/or father has a self reported history of:
- asthma and/or
- eczema/atopic dermatitis and/or
- hayfever/allergic rhinitis and/or
- food allergy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>3</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- A parent who has a known hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients of EpiCeram.
- Multiple births (twins, triplets etc.)
- Premature infants (&lt;36 weeks)
- Infants with major birth or early life medical complications that require admission into a special care nursery.
- Infants whose parents are not able to comply with all protocol required visits and procedures.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The random allocation list will be held by the Royal Children's Hospital (RCH) Pharmacy Department. Pharmacy staff will be independent from the participant recruitment or testing. The allocation list will be concealed from the study co-ordinator and other study investigators who will manage participant recruitment.
The PEBBLES study co-ordinator will call the RCH Pharmacy Department by telephone at the end of the one week-baseline assessment to determine the group of allocation. The study co-ordinator will provide the child's name and this will be recorded on the allocation list. The infant will be allocated to the next study number and assigned to the group corresponding to that unique study identification number</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random allocation list will be generated with variable blocks sizes. Randomisation will be stratified for the number of parents affected by allergic disease (1vs 2). Simple randomisation will be used, with equal numbers of children being allocated to the control and intervention groups</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>With 40 participants per group, we should have sufficient numbers to be able to demonstrate that EpiCeram (Trademark) causes an important reduction in risk of eczema and an increase in the infants skin barrier function. Based on our recent experience with a similar study (Probiotics in the Prevention of Eczema Prevention of Eczema  PEPS) that used a comparable selection criteria and outcome assessment, approximately 35% of infants in the control group will show evidence of eczema at three or six months of age. Given that this is a reasonably intensive treatment, and the substantial impact that EpiCeram has as a treatment for eczema, we expect a large reduction in the symptoms of eczema in the intervention group. 

Due to slower than anticipated recruitment rate, the sample size estimate was re-estimated.  The revised estimate is based on having 80% power to detect a very large difference in eczema at six months (35% in controls, 5% in intervention group). The revised sample size is 34 children per group, or a 80 total to allow for approximately a 15% drop out rate.

If we have 40 infants per group, we will have over 80% power to detect a difference in TEWL of 26 g/cm2/hour for the control group to 19 g/cm2/hour in the intervention group (assuming a sd = 11 and an alpha level of 0.05).

Data will be analysed using the intention to treat principle; that is that regardless of the level of compliance with the study protocol, or if they discontinued use of the EpiCeram treatment, they will be analysed in the group to which they were allocated.

If there are clear differences between the groups on baseline risk factors that are associated with risk of allergic disease (gender, exposure to cigarette smoke, parental level of education) multiple logistic or linear regression models will be used to adjust for these baseline imbalances. Baseline TEWL (at 1 week of age) will also be considered as a potential confounder of the effect of the intervention.

A per-protocol analysis will be performed to determine if a certain amount of compliance (at least an average of three days application, or 36 grams, of cream per week) is required for the treatment to be effective. Both parental report of frequency of administration, and weight of cream used will be used as a potential predictor of risk of eczema values. This will help determine if less frequent (or smaller quantity of) application of the study cream could be sufficient to reduce the risk of eczema.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>4/08/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/07/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Frances Perry House - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Financial Markets Foundation for Children</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 3655
Sydney
NSW  2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Asthma Foundation of Victoria
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>491  495 King Street
West Melbourne   
Vic   3003
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>PuraCap Pharmaceutical LLX</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>1001 Durham Avenue
South Plainfield
New Jersey 
07080
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Asthma affects approximately 20% of children, is a common cause of hospital admissions, and we do not know how to stop children developing it. Infantile eczema is also common, affecting about a third of children. Infants with eczema often later develop asthma. It is hypothesised sensitisation to allergens can occur via damaged skin associated with eczema, which then increases the risk of asthma.
If this hypothesis is correct, it may be possible to prevent asthma by improving the skin barrier function in infants. There is evidence that a ceramide based emollient (which contains the major components of skin) can improve skin barrier function, while current treatments for eczema do not.
This study is aims to determine if twice daily application of a ceramide dominant emollient can improve infant skin barrier function and prevent the development of eczema in high risk children.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>No trial website</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Published pilot study results:
Lowe AJ, Tang ML, Dharmage SC, Varigos G, Forster D, Gurrin LC, Robertson CF, Abramson MJ, Allen KJ, Su J: A phase I study of daily treatment with a ceramide-dominant triple lipid mixture commencing in neonates. BMC Dermatol 2012, 12: 3.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development &amp; Ethics
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road 
Parkville  3052 
Victoria
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>29132</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Ethics Secretariat
The Royal Women's Hospital
Locked Bag 300
Cnr Grattan St &amp; Flemington Rd
Parkville 3052
Victoria </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lowe</name>
      <address>Allergy and Lung Health Unit, Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, University of Melbourne,Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street  VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lowea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lowe</name>
      <address>Allergy and Lung Health Unit, Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, University of Melbourne,Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street  VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lowea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lowe</name>
      <address>Centre for Molecular, Environmental, Genetic, Analytic (MEGA) Epidemiology 
School of Population and Global Health 
The University of Melbourne 
Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street
Carlton VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lowea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lowe</name>
      <address>Centre for Molecular, Environmental, Genetic, Analytic (MEGA) Epidemiology 
School of Population and Global Health 
The University of Melbourne 
Level 3, 207 Bouverie Street
Carlton VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lowea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>