<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371072">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001414404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot intervention for attention, memory, and social problems after an acquired brain injury in children and adolescence.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot intervention program for cognitive and social sequelae following Acquired Brain Injury in childhood and adolescence.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-7768</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Amat-c</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acquired brain injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Amsterdam Memory and Attention Training for children (Amat-c) is a cognitive training program for enhancing childrens attention, memory, and executive functioning (EF) skills. This is a restorative or direct intervention that is designed to treat the consequences of ABI, and requires an initial evaluation to identify impaired abilities. The child is trained, using specific exercises focusing on deficient cognitive abilities, in an attempt to improve these skills, as well as to impact more generally on cognitive functions. 

The task undertaken by the child are presented in three phases:

Phase 1Sustained attention. Training methods focus on learning to concentrate on one task for a period of time. Example: Listening to the clock: The clocks ticking is counted. The distance from the clock is increased and the task repeated until the child is not able to complete the task. The first and the final distance from the clock are measured.

Phase 2Selective attention. Focused (e.g. ignore distraction) and divided attention (e.g. focusing attention quickly and flexibly). Example: ABCDE Method: The Child is taught the ABCDE Method for approaching a task. A, Appreciating; B, Being Critical; C, Concentrating, D, Deep Thinking, E, Evaluating.

Phase 3Mental tracking and memory. Techniques to assist memory, including repetition, coding/sorting and visual imagery. Example: MemoryRepeating and Sorting: The child is involved in tasks that require repetition of information and sorting of information in order to enhance memory skills.

The Amat-c will be administered to participating families in the treatment group for a period of 18 weeks. Each week will be preceded by a 1hour clinician-support session. During these sessions, a clinician will call participating families via a video call to explain the techniques and instructions for the Amat-c activities for that week. The clinician will also address any concerns arising from the previous weeks activities (commencing from week two). 

Following this, the Amat-c program will be delivered by a parent for the rest of the week, in a daily 30 minute session. Parents will coach this session using relevant sections the Amat-c Handbook provided for the respective weeks activities.

Adherence to the intervention will be monitored during the weekly call sessions with the clinician. Here, specific questions will be asked as to whether the exercises were completed and any potential challenges associated with each exercise will be addressed. In addition, we will evaluate adherence to the protocol by assessing the parents responses to questions about their likes and dislikes for each weeks activities, entered in a section of the workbook. All workbooks completed by the parent and child during the weekly activities will be collected at the post-intervention outcome assessment session, and will be another source of evaluation of adherence to the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>An active control group with ABI will be included in this study. This group will be asked to read the content of a psycho-education booklet on common behaviour problems associated with childhood ABI. This booklet is designed for the purpose of this study and will include sections on headache, fatigue, sleep disturbances, dizziness and emotional problems, as well as sections on how parents can assist their child in each of these domains. Parents will be required to read this booklet.

Subsequently, a clinician will conduct a weekly video or audio call to discuss these topics and any potential problems encountered by the family in a given domain. Each weekly call will involve a one-on-one session with the clinician and will be for a maximum of 1hour. 

The control group will only be administered the Amat-c program once all data collection is complete and the feasibility and efficacy of the program is confirmed. Thus, post outcome assessment. This is expected to be approximately 9 months after the intervention group has completed the program. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Memory: assessed using the mean scores on pre-selected subtests of the Childrens Memory Scale) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, immediately post-intervention, and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attention: assessed using the mean scores on pre-selected subtest of the Everyday Attention for Children (TEA-Ch)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening, immediately post-intervention, and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adaptive Behabior: assessed with the Vineland Adaptive Behaviour Scales- Second Edition (Vineland-II) - Parents form</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional memory: measured with selected subtests of the Rivermead Behavioural Memory Test-Third Edition,</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prospective memory, assessed with the Prospective and Retrospective Memory Questionnaire (PRMQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Academic performance: assessed with the Wide Range Achievement Test 4 (WRAT-4)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Affect recognition:  assessed with the Developmental Neuropsychological Assessment-II (NEPSY-II; Affect Recognition subtest)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proxy memory assessment: Assessed using the parent form of the Observer Memory Questionnaire (OMQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavior: Assessed using the parent and teacher forms of the Behaviour Assessment System for Children (BASC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Executive functioning: assessed with the Brief Rating Inventory of Executive Function (BRIEF), parents and teacher forms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qulaity of life: assessed with the Paediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PedsQL) Generic Core Scale- Parent form</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will: 

(a) have an ABI diagnosis.
(b) be between the ages of 8-16 at the time of the intervention.
(c) be a minimum of 1 year post-injury.
(d) have an IQ of 70 or above.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential participants will be excluded if:

They present with no attention and memory difficulties ton the screening tasks.
They do not meet the eligibility criteria during the screening (e.g. IQ below the score of 70).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This trail will include 20 participants each in the intervention and control groups. Based on a priori power estimation on the Childrens Memory and Attention Scale, we estimate that this sample size  will allow us to detect a difference in verbal and visual working memory at a power of 80%. alpha value of 0.05, and an effect size of 0.90.

For each intervention program, repeated measures multivariate planned comparisons, using the SPSS, GLM procedure will compare pre-and-post intervention and 6-month follow-up performance on the outcome measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>4/11/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>25/05/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cathy Catroppa (Asso Prof)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Psychologist/Research Fellow
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria, 3052, 
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Telematics Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Telematics Trust Level 7, 171 Collins Street Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Vicki Anderson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Head of Psychology, RCH Mental Health
Theme Director, Clinical Sciences Research, MCRI
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nicholas Ryan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Provisional Psychologist / MPsych (Clinical Neuropsychology) 
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Edith Botchway</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PhD Candidate, University of Melbourne
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Stefanie Rosema </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Post-doctoral Researcher and Clinician
Sophia Revalidatie Den Haag
Vrederustlaan 180
2543 SW Den Haag</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Netherlands</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Cheryl Soo</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clinical Psychologist and Research Fellow 
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute 
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nikita Tuli</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PhD Candidate, University of Melbourne
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Impairments in memory, attention, and social/psychosocial functioning are common consequences of acquired brain injury (ABI) sustained in childhood and adolescence. However, there exists a dearth of evidence-based interventions that target these difficulties, while only a few studies have evaluated the feasibility of these interventions in an ABI population. 

This study aims to pilot the feasibility and efficacy of the English version of the Amsterdam Memory and Attention Test for Children (Amat-c), with an online clinician support component, in children and adolescents presenting with difficulties in these functional domains post-ABI. The Amat-c is to enhance childrens attention, memory and executive functioning (EF) skills. The child is trained using specific exercises focusing on deficient cognitive abilities, in an attempt to improve these skills, as well as to impact more generally on cognitive functions. 

Parents of participating children will have to engage their children in a daily 30 minutes session for 18 weeks. During these sessions families in the treatment group will complete the Amat-c activities. Those in the control group will complete some psycho-education models, and will be invited to receive the Amat-c intervention after it is found to be efficacious.  Feasibility of this intervention will be assessed immediately and at 6 months post-intervention using neuropsychological and ecologically sensitive measures. Relative to baseline scores, we expect significant improvements in attention, memory, and functional everyday outcomes both immediately and at 6 months post-intervention. 

We anticipate that preliminary support for the feasibility and efficacy of this online clinician-supported program will inform current evidence-based practices and optimize childhood/adolescent outcomes post-ABI. Potentially, this will inspire larger future studies and provide an evidence base for the incorporation of the Amat-c into standard clinical care for children and adolescents with ABI.   

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Current Protocol:

Cathy Catroppa1,2,3,  Celia Godfrey1,2,3, Nicholas Ryan1,3, Edith Botchway1,3, Stefanie Rosema1  &amp; Vicki Anderson1,2,3

A pilot intervention program for attention and memory difficulties following acquired brain injury (ABI) in childhood and adolescence - online clinician support- A Conference on Childrens Rehabilitation. Brisbane, Australia. (16- 18th November 2016).
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics &amp; Governance. The Royal Children's Hospital. Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics &amp; Governance
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road, Parkville,  
3052, Victoria
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>29099 J</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371072-Amat-c ethic approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cathy Catroppa </name>
      <address>Psychologist/Research Fellow
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria, 3052, 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99366638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.catroppa@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Ryan</name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria, 3052, 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 4 37124427 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicholas.ryan@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cathy Catroppa (A/Prof)</name>
      <address>Psychologist/Research Fellow
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria, 3052, 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99366638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.catroppa@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Edith Botchway</name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria, 3052, 
Australia</address>
      <phone>+64 416523586</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>edith.botchway@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>