<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83387">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000032257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does taking the drug thyroxine on an empty stomach or with food significantly alter its absorption in treating patients with hypothyroidism?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does taking the drug thyroxine on an empty stomach or with food significantly alter its absorption in treating patients with hypothyroidism?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Absorption of the drug thyroxine in patients with hypothyroidism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Thyroid disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants who are taking a standard oral dose of the thyroxine tablet manufactured by GlaxoSmithKline (brand name: Eltroxin) will take their thyroxine tablet orally with food (their meal). Their dosage amount will continue to be what has been their regular dose previous to the commencement of the study as prescribed by their General Practitioner, therefore each patient will be taking an individualised dosage amount between 0.05mg - 0.20mg; dosage frequency will be once daily with food. As approximately six to eight weeks is required for any changes in thyroid function (i.e. changes in blood Thyroid Stimulating Hormone levels) to be seen, the duration of the Intervention Treatment for each participant will be six to eight weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>As this is a crossover study, participants will be acting as their own control. Control treatment is active: Participants will take their thyroxine tablet orally on an empty stomach (at least thirty minutes before their meal). Their dosage amount will continue to be what has been their regular dose previous to the commencement of the study as prescribed by their General Practitioner, therefore each patient will be taking an individualised dosage amount between 0.05mg - 0.20mg; dosage frequency will be once daily with food. A 'wash-out' period of 1 day will be given between Intervention and Control Treatments. As approximately six to eight weeks is required for any changes in thyroid function (i.e. changes in blood Thyroid Stimulating Hormone levels) to be seen, the duration of the Control Treatment for each participant will be six to eight weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Thyroid Stimulating Hormone (TSH) level outside the normal range of 0.3 - 4.0mu/L. A blood sample (approximately 5mLs) will be taken from each participant and sent to the Biochemistry Laboratory where TSH level in the blood sample will be measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline; at eight weeks after beginning Intervention Treatment; and at eight weeks after beginning Control Treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight. Each participant's weight will be measured by the health care professionals conducting this research in our clinic here in the hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline; at eight weeks after beginning Intervention Treatment; and at eight weeks after beginning Control Treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart Rate. Each participant's heart rate will be measured by the health care professionals conducting this research in our clinic here in the hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline; at eight weeks after beginning Intervention Treatment; and at eight weeks after beginning Control Treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure. Each participant's blood pressure will be measured by the health care professionals conducting this research in our clinic here in the hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline; at eight weeks after beginning Intervention Treatment; and at eight weeks after beginning Control Treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participant: has been taking thyroxine tablets for hypothyroidism for a minimum of 8 weeks; thyroxine tablet taken is manufactured by GlaxoSmithKline (brand name: Eltroxin); takes a standard daily dose; &gt;18 years; has a blood TSH level within the normal range of 0.4  4.0mu/L at the start of study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participant: has history of other serious illness, for example active cardiovascular disease; is normally non-compliant with medication; is currently taking other medications that could possibly interfere with thyroxine absorption, for example omeprazole, or calcium tablets; has a blood TSH level not within the normal range of 0.4  4.0mu/L at the start of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Dr Patrick Manning</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Endocrinology Research Unit
Dunedin Public Hospital
201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago, Department of Medical and Surgical Sciences</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Medical and Surgical Sciences
Dunedin Public Hospital
201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ahrin Anna Choi</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Endocrinology Research Unit
Dunedin Public Hospital
201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hypothyroidism is one of the most common endocrine disorders, the treatment of which consists of lifelong replacement therapy with the drug thyroxine. Drug company GlaxoSmithKline recently reformulated their thyroxine tablet and now requires the tablet be taken on an empty stomach. To our knowledge however there is no evidence currently to suggest that food affects gastrointestinal thyroxine absorption. As taking medications on an empty stomach makes patient compliance more difficult this project aims to show that taking thyroxine with food will not affect its absorption in any clinically significant manner.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Lower South Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Level 4
229 Moray Place
PO Box 5849
Dunedin 9016</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LRS/08/11/060</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Dr Patrick Manning</name>
      <address>Endocrinology Research Unit
Dunedin Public Hospital
201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4747733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>patrick.manning@otagodhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ahrin Anna Choi</name>
      <address>Endocrinology Research Unit
Dunedin Public Hospital
201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4747733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>choah986@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ahrin Anna Choi</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>