<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365654">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000173695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot Study of Progressive Resistance Training for Sedentary Adults with Charcot-Marie-Tooth</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study to evaluate the effect of progressive resistance training on muscle strength in sedentary adults with Charcot-Marie-Tooth</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CMT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Charcot-Marie-tooth</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The proposed project is for an eight-week RCT on resistance training study in persons with Charcot-Marie-Tooth (CMT), a muscular atrophy disease. Traditionally, people with CMT have been discouraged from performing exercise without strong supporting scientific evidence. The resulting lower activity levels and decreased muscle mass (from the disease process) means persons with CMT population may have increased incidence of metabolic syndrome, diabetes and cardiovascular disease. This pilot study will provide information on the effectiveness of progressive resistance training (PRT) for people with CMT.  This research will provide data for larger studies that answer more specific questions about CMT and exercise. The study is a blinded RCT. The total duration of the study will be approximately 12 weeks with each participant performing pre-tests then being randomized into one of two intervention groups for 8 weeks, followed by post testing. One group will perform 8 weeks of individual power training exercise sessions supervised by an exercise physiologist (Exercise group) and the other group (Control group) will maintain their usual activity levels.

The power training group will require participants to attend three training sessions each week for 8 weeks at University of Sydney, Lidcombe campus. The training sessions would last for 60minutes each session (e.g. 3 x 60 minutes training sessions per week for 8 weeks). The exercises will focus on the upper and lower extremities, using Keiser pneumatic strength training equipment. The exercises will include leg press, chest press, knee extension, Ankle dorsiflexion, Hip abduction, seated row etc. The intensity of the training will be built up over the first few sessions to high intensity (80% 1RM) and then maintained at this intensity level for the remainder of the program. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The Control group will maintain their usual activity levels.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leg Press Muscle strength (Hamstring, gluteals, quadriceps): The 1 Repetition Maximum (1RM) test will be used to determine the dynamic maximal muscle strength. This technique has been used extensively to monitor gains in muscle strength in strength training intervention in older adults and gives a good reliability.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chest Press Muscle strength (Pectoralis, triceps). The 1 Repetition Maximum (1RM) test will be used to determine the dynamic maximal muscle strength.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Baseline and after 8 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition analysis: Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA scan). DXA scan for whole body composition of bone mass, muscle mass and strength ratios.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>only at baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Performance: measured by Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) which involves scores on balance test, sit to stand test, and habitual walking speed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual physical activity and sedentary behaviour: Actigraph
accelerometers set at 10 s epochs will be worn during all waking hours for 7 days on the non-dominant hip as well as on the non-dominant wrist at all times to monitor sleep quality.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking Biomechanics: Surface Electromyography (EMG).  EMG electrodes will be placed on the skin over 8 leg muscles on the dominant leg of the participants. The participants will then be asked to perform standard movements to allow the measurement of a standard value for the muscle activity to be referenced to. The subjects will be asked to walk on a treadmill at a comfortable pace for 1 minute. The treadmill is instrumented with sensors that allow the measurement of walking parameters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Questionnaire: The Short Form (36) Health Survey (SF-36)

SF-36 is a patient-reported survey of patient health and is a measure of health status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Questionnaire: Centre for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale (CES-D).

The CES_D is a widely used 20 item self-report scale which measures the current level of depressive symptomatology in the general population, with an emphasis on depressed mood during the past week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Questionnaire: Current Level of overall body pain measured by Visual analog scale (VAS).

VAS is a psychometric response scale and it is a measurement instrument for subjective characteristics or attitudes that cannot be directly measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Questionnaire: EWART self efficacy Scale (EWART).

This is questionnaire examine the self-efficacy of participants in regards to physical activities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and after 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Questionnaire: Demograhic survey.

This questionnaire attains general information for subject identifications such as gender, residence, education, smoking status, hospital admission etc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stair Climb Power test. The Stair Climb Power Test (SCPT) is a functional test associated with leg muscle power.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 Minute Walk Test. The six-minute walk test (6MWT) measures the distance an individual is able to walk over a total of six minutes on a hard, flat surface.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Handgrip Strength (via Handgrip Dynamometer)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Sixteen individuals with CMT Type 1 or X will participate in this project.The following inclusion criteria enable the volunteer to participate in the CMT Study: 

-Participants will have either type 1 or X CMT. 
-They will be aged between 18-60yrs 
-Be able to walk 100m at a gait speed over 0.4 ms-1 and without an assistive device [ankle-foot orthoses are allowed, no bilateral assistance]
-Participants must be able to get to Cumberland by own transport.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The following conditions permanently exclude the subject from
participation in the CMT STUDY:
- Participants with recent exacerbation of CMT condition
- Those who are not sedentary (i.e. currently participating in structured aerobic or weight training activities)
- Those who have medical conditions that would preclude them from intense exercise.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>To assess subject eligibility for CMT Study, a telephone screening would be administered. The questions on the form were designed to address all inclusion and exclusion criteria. A 30 minute phone call from the interviewer allowed all volunteers to answer the questions and ask any questions the subjects had about the study. After the forms were reviewed by the researchers, all potential subjects were informed of
their eligibility and if further screening was required. Written informed consent will be required prior to any testing or randomisation.

Allocation was concealed using sealed opaque envelopes given to eligible participants after completion of all baseline testing. Participants will be randomised into an intervention group, or a control group following completion of baseline assessments.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will be performed by a researcher, who is not involved in testing and counselling of participants, using computer- generated randomly permuted blocks. Participants will be informed of their group allocation by means of sealed opaque envelopes given to them after completion of all baseline testing.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Charcot-Marie-Tooth Australia Association (CMTAA)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building 22
Concord Hospital
Concord, NSW
2139 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Charcot-Marie-Tooth Australia Association (CMTAA)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Building 22
Concord Hospital
Concord, NSW
2139 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Charcot-Marie-Tooth (CMT) is the most frequently inherited peripheral neuropathy affecting around 1 in 2500 persons. CMT causes slow degeneration of the nerves in the extremities including feet, legs, arms and hands. Typically muscles weaken and atrophy due to the loss of activation by the affected nerves. In the past, persons with CMT have been discouraged from performing exercise and physical activity because clinicians believed that such activity might hasten the disease; these beliefs have never been validated by studies.  However, it is now known that regular exercise or activity helps maintain good health and function in most populations. Inactivity and a poor muscle mass can also lead to metabolic syndrome, increasing morbidity and the risk of developing diabetes and cardiovascular disease. These metabolic diseases may even worsen the symptoms of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease, for example diabetes can worsen CMT symptoms.

More evidence is required on exercise for persons with CMT, especially at moderate to high intensities. Recent research has shown that light and moderate intensity exercise is not detrimental to persons with CMT and offers many of the same benefits to persons with CMT as it does to the general population .  The few previous studies have used home-based low intensity training (i.e. 20-30% maximum lift) for the upper limbs and moderate intensity for the legs (i.e. 40-50% maximum lift). In the neurologically normal population, muscle and strength gains are correlated with the intensity of exercise, i.e. high intensity training develops greater strength and muscle mass. A considerable amount of weakness and muscle atrophy in persons with CMT may be due to secondary disuse due inactivity. Higher intensity training could be beneficial for those with CMT to improve muscle mass, power and strength. The benefits of intense training might also provide persons with CMT from developing secondary metabolic disease or lead to improve functional ability in daily activities.

We propose to conduct a study investigating the benefits of a high intensity training gym-based program (i.e. power training) for individuals with CMT. The proposed project is an eight-week resistance training randomized controlled pilot trial. This pilot study will provide information on the effectiveness of progressive resistance training (PRT) for people with CMT.  We expect power training may benefit individuals with CMT by increasing muscle mass (strength and metabolic benefits) and muscle power (increased function). This research will provide data for a larger National Health and Medical Research Council funding application that will have the statistical power to answer more specific questions about CMT and exercise. 

Recently, many people with CMT have become aware that exercise might be beneficial for them, but do not understand how to accommodate exercise in their lives. Therefore, the results of this pilot study will be promoted to educate Exercise Sports Science Australia (ESSA) and Australian Accredited Exercise Physiologists (AEP) on the benefits of exercise for CMT. In time, we hope that people with CMT will be able to easily contact AEPs in the community for advice on exercise.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/851</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Maria Fiatarone Singh</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney Faculty of Health Sciences Exercise, Health &amp; Performance Faculty Research Group Room K221, 75 East St Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9755</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9204</fax>
      <email>maria.fiataronesingh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nidhi Saigal</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney Faculty of Health Sciences Exercise, Health &amp; Performance Faculty Research Group Room K220, 75 East St Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9138</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9204</fax>
      <email>nidhi.jain@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Maria Fiatarone Singh</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney Faculty of Health Sciences Exercise, Health &amp; Performance Faculty Research Group Room K221, 75 East St Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9755</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9204</fax>
      <email>maria.fiataronesingh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nidhi Saigal</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney Faculty of Health Sciences Exercise, Health &amp; Performance Faculty Research Group Room K220, 75 East St Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9138</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9204</fax>
      <email>nidhi.jain@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>