<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373313">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001246370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of an Internet-based Decision Aid (myAID) for Ulcerative Colitis Patients to Improve Quality of Life, Empowerment, Decision Making and Disease Control</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial of a Decision Aid (myAID) for Ulcerative Colitis Patients: Enhancing Patients Quality of Life, Empowerment, Quality of Decision Making and Disease Control</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>myAID (my Actively Informed Decision) study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ulcerative colitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The overall aim of the project is to improve, through the implementation of a decision aid (myAID), quality of life, empowerment, quality of decision making, and disease control of patients receiving treatment for ulcerative colitis (UC). myAID is an internet-based multimedia decision aid (Emmi Solutions, Chicago) designed to support shared decision making for treatment choices in UC management. Its content was determined following a survey of 460 UC patients from USA and Australia which confirmed that most patients with UC want better understanding about UC and its treatments, and wish to participate in shared decision making with their gastroenterologist when making treatment decisions.

Content: Organised into small chapters that can be viewed repeatedly as necessary, myAID aims to enhance the viewer's understanding of UC including its risks and potential complications, goals of treatment as well as benefits and risks of a range of surgical and medical treatment options available.

Interactivity: myAID can be accessed using any computer by a unique link assigned to the viewer during the study. Study participants will be asked to view myAID in their own time and space. myAID has several interactive components that prompt patients to answer questions about their current symptoms and concerns, allows them to return and skip to a specific chapter of their interest after viewing the entire tool at least once, and to take virtual notes and print these as required to discuss with their doctor. A summary of all the information provided in myAID can also be printed once all the contents have been viewed. 

The intervention will be administered in a two arm, prospective phase III cluster randomised controlled trial involving 18 sites across New South Wales (NSW), South Australia (SA), Victoria (Vic), Queensland (QLD) and Western Australia (WA). Half ie 9 of the sites or clusters will be allocated to the intervention arm where myAID will be made accessible to patients routinely throughout the 12-month study period in addition to usual care.

Consenting patients will be asked to complete a baseline online questionnaire and test for faecal calprotectin before they view myAID and return to their consultant for further discussion about their management. All participants in the intervention arm of the study will be required to view myAID at least once, as they will not be able to progress through the study without viewing it (which will constitute a minimum requirement of the baseline assessment for them). From thereon, they will be encouraged to view myAID as often as necessary to help with their decision making during the entire study period. An online questionnaire will be completed after the initial viewing of myAID to assess the patients perception of the usefulness and acceptability of myAID, and whether the patient used any other information material than myAID. Additional online questionnaires and FC samples will be collected at 2 months, 6 months, and 12 months, all of which can be done from the patients home. The online questionnaires will collect patients demographic and basic clinical information eg hospital admissions, and also ask the patient to complete the following measures: Assessment of Quality of Life-8D, Health Literacy Questionnaire, Health Education Impact Questionnaire, Decisional Conflict Scale, Trust in Physician Scale, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale  Anxiety, Morisky Medication Adherence Scale-8, Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index, and Work Productivity and Activity Index.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients recruited from sites or clusters allocated to the control arm in the study will receive usual care without the use of the decision aid during the 12-month study period. Patients will be reviewed by their respective gastroenterologist (or team) within 2-4 weeks of study inclusion to help with the decision making process, and be asked to complete an online questionnaire to assess whether they used any information material to help in this process. All patients will complete the same online questionnaires and submit FC samples as those in the intervention arm at 2 months, 6 months, and 12 months to allow comparison of designated primary and secondary outcomes during the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life, as measured by Assessment of Quality of Life-8D</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Empowerment, as measured by Health Education Impact Questionnaire 3.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health literacy, as measured by Health Literacy Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of decision making, as measured by Decisional Conflict Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of decision making, as measured by Trust in Physician Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety, as measured by Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale - Anxiety</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Productivity, as measured by Work Productivity and Activity Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication adherence, as measured by Morisky Medication Adherence Scale-8</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease activity and control, as measured by the Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease activity and control, as measured by faecal calprotectin</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease activity and control, as measured by proportion of patients taking steroids (captured through self-report via online questionnnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease activity and control, as measured by proportion of patients requiring surgery (captured through self-report via online questionnnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease activity and control, as measured by proportion of patients requiring unplanned hospital admissions (captured through self-report via online questionnnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the decision aid, as measured by questions specifically developed for the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2-4 weeks of initial viewing of myAID (intervention arm only)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be eligible to participate in the study if they:
a) have a diagnosis of ulcerative colitis (UC);
b) are 18+ years;
c) have failed or are failing oral +/- rectal 5-aminosalicylate (5-ASA) therapy or any therapy beyond 5-ASAs (failure includes non-adherence);
d) are making a new decision about therapy;
e) can communicate in English; and
f) have access to internet and email</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a) patients with no prior exposure to 5-ASAs;
b) inpatients with severe colitis or acute severe UC;
c) post colectomy patients at baseline;
d) patients that do not meet above inclusion criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation using a computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This study is powered to detect a difference of 0.5 SD between the Intervention and Usual Care groups in the primary outcome of QoL using the AQoL-8D measure. The sample size has been adjusted for the design effect due to the clustered design and can accommodate an intra-class correlation coefficient (ICC) as high as 0.05 to achieve 80% power. Adjusting for this ICC, the estimated required sample size for the full study is 238 patients in total (119 per group). Assuming 70% of eligible patients consent to study participation and a loss to follow up rate of 20% at the 12-month end-point, we aim to approach 426 patients in total (213 per group). Across all sites, recruitment and follow up can be achieved in approximately 30 months.
The primary analysis will be conducted for the primary outcome using multilevel models to account for the correlation of outcomes within a cluster (site). For the primary outcome, the dependent variable will be the QoL measure and the exposure variable will be the intervention status (usual care versus intervention). The unit of analysis will be at the patient level to accommodate the weighting required by unequal cluster (site) sizes. Other independent variables will be added to the models if they are independently associated with the QoL measure and/or their inclusion in the model changes the linear coefficient of the intervention effect by more than 20% in absolute value. Multilevel models will also be used to evaluate secondary outcomes.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>426</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>60</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>5/04/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Blacktown Hospital - Blacktown</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Subiaco - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2148 - Blacktown</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Susan Connor</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology 
Clinic 123 Level 1 Liverpool Hospital Liverpool NSW 2170

Psycho-Oncology Research Group, Ingham Institute
Liverpool Hospital, Locked Bag 7103. Liverpool BC NSW 1871 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>South Western Sydney Local Health District Mid-Career Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>South Western Sydney Local Health District Executive Office
Locked Bag 7279
LIVERPOOL BC 1871
NSW
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gastroenterological Society of Australia IBD Clinical Research Grant 2016</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gastroenterological Society of Australia
PO BOX 5359
Pinewood
Victoria 3149
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Afaf Girgis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Psycho-Oncology Research Group, Ingham Institute
Liverpool Hospital, Locked Bag 7103, LIVERPOOL BC NSW 1871 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ingham Institute for Applied Medical Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>1 Campbell Street
Liverpool NSW 2170
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The overall aim of this study is to improve treatment outcomes for patients with ulcerative colitis (UC) primarily focusing on improved patient care and empowerment through patient involvement in the decision making around their disease management. It aims to trial the first decision aid for UC which explains the risks and benefits of treatment in a clear, understandable and balanced way to greatly enhance patient understanding of their disease and management options. This in turn is expected to improve medium-term quality of life by better patient empowerment and quality of decision making in UC. Improvements in anxiety, adherence to chosen therapy, disease outcomes and prevention of complicatons will ideally follow. This will be the first study in the world to trial a decision aid developed to help decision making in UC treatment, making this a highly significant research project with the potential to contribute to routine UC care worldwide.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Poster presentation:

Kim AH, Sechi AJ, Ruban SO, Ng Watson, Girgis A, Andrews JA, Siegel CA, Connor SJ. Australian Gastroenterology Week, Gold Coast 2017. "Feasibility and acceptability of an internet-based decision aid (myAID) for ulcerative colitis patients"

Invited oral presentations:

Kim AH, Sechi AJ, Ruban SO, Girgis A, Andrews JM, Siegel CA, Connor SJ. Patient Experience Symposium, Sydney 2017. Feasibility and Acceptability of an Internet-based Decision Aid for Ulcerative Colitis Patients

Kim AH, Sechi AJ, Ruban SO, Girgis A, Andrews JM, Siegel CA, Connor SJ. Health Beyond Research &amp; Innovation Showcase, Sydney 2016. Feasibility and Acceptability of an Internet-based Decision Aid for Ulcerative Colitis Patients  Results of a Pilot Study</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The following sites are awaiting site-specific approvals from their respective research ethics committees before starting recruitment:
- Blacktown Hospital, Sydney
- Fiona Stanley Hospital, Perth
- Flinders Medical Centre, Adelaide
- Monash Medical Centre, Melbourne
- The Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Adelaide</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SWSLHD Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>South Western Sydney Local Health District Research and Ethics Office
Locked Bag 7103, Liverpool BC, NSW, 1871
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/LPOOL/358</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373313-NEAF Approval 18.10.15.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373313-Site Addition Approval 18.04.17.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373313(v19-08-2017-01-29-02)-SSA Approvals 19.08.17.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373313-Protocol 3.0 and Master PIS 6.0 Approval 21.09.16.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373313-Study Protocol V3 9th September 2016_Clean.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373313-MASTER Patient Information Sheet V6_clean.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373313-Local Liverpool Patient Information Sheet V6_clean.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Connor</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology &amp; Hepatology 
Clinic 123 Level 1, Liverpool Hospital, Liverpool NSW 2170 Australia

Psycho-Oncology Research Group, Ingham Institute
Liverpool Hospital, Locked Bag 7103. Liverpool BC NSW 1871 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8738 4085</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8738 3094 </fax>
      <email>Susan.Connor2@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Kim</name>
      <address>Psycho-Oncology Research Group, Ingham Institute
Liverpool Hospital, Locked Bag 7103, LIVERPOOL BC NSW 1871 Australia
Street: Level 2, Ingham Institute Building, 1 Campbell Street, Liverpool 2170 Australia</address>
      <phone>+ 61 430 540 998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.h.kim@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Kim</name>
      <address>Psycho-Oncology Research Group, Ingham Institute
Liverpool Hospital, Locked Bag 7103, LIVERPOOL BC NSW 1871 Australia
Street: Level 2, Ingham Institute Building, 1 Campbell Street, Liverpool 2170 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 430 540 998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.h.kim@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Kim</name>
      <address>Psycho-Oncology Research Group, Ingham Institute
Liverpool Hospital, Locked Bag 7103, LIVERPOOL BC NSW 1871 Australia
Street: Level 2, Ingham Institute Building, 1 Campbell Street, Liverpool 2170 Australia</address>
      <phone>+ 61 430 540 998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.h.kim@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>