<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="943">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/12/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000161527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised double-blind placebo controlled trial of pyridoxine for prevention of capecitabine induced hand-foot syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised double-blind placebo controlled trial of pyridoxine for prevention of capecitabine induced hand-foot syndrome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Capecitabine induced hand-foot syndrome (HFS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The specific pathophysiologic mechanism of HFS is unclear. The clinical features of HFS are characteristic and evolve in stages. Most patients have their first (92.9%) or most severe (67.9%) episode of HFS within the first two cycles of treatment.11 

Initially, symptoms are very mild with no obvious changes to the hands and feet. Patients may experience a prodrome of about 3 to 5 days, which consists of vague paraesthesias and tingling of the extremities, or painless swelling or erythema (grade 1). If the drug is continued, the syndrome progresses with painful erythema and swelling (grade 2). It may further progress to fissuring, ulceration and desquamation involving the hands and feet, leading to extreme pain when grasping objects or walking (grade 3).11 Resolution of HFS occurs upon discontinuation of capecitabine. Histologically, the condition is marked by hyperkeratosis associated with an inflammatory cell infiltrate and an increase in vascularity of the dermis.                                                           The treatment group will receive oral Pyridoxine 200gm daily for 24 weeks. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive oral placebo for 24 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Grade 2 or greater Hand Foot Syndrome (HFS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed clinically every three weeks, and via phone contact weekly</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity is graded according to Commom Toxicity Criteria for Adverese Events (CTCAE) Version 3 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed clinically every three weeks, and via phone contact weekly</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to onset of grade 2 or higher HFS will be evaluated in days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The duration of treatment is 24 weeks.
Assessment for the primary end-point will occur at clinic visitsand via weekly phone calls from the research nurse.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Commencement of capecitabine at a dose of 800mg/m2 BD every 2 out of 3 weeks either as single agent or combination therapySigned informed consent. Life expectancy greater than 12 weeksConcommitant radiotherapy or steroids permitted</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior capecitabine chemotherapy over the past 30 daysInability to provide informed consentConcommitant administration of drugs that cause HFS eg docetaxel, liposomal doxorubicinConsumption of pyridoxine-containing preparationsAnticipated inability to follow up patient for side effects of chemotherapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Computerised randomisation package with sealed opaque envelopes made up by non research team individual</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>288</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Chris Karapetis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Flinders Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Capecitabine (Xeloda) is an oral chemotherapy agent that has shown to be effective in breast and gastrointestinal cancers. Patients receiving Xeloda tend to experience less severe side effects such as diarrhoea, mouth sores, nausea , hair loss and reduced white blood counts. Hand and foot syndrome (HFS) is a common complication for patients receiving Xeloda. Although it is not a life-threatening complication, it can be disabling in severe cases and affects the treatment course due to the need for dose interuption or reducation. Some previous research has suggested that the addition of Pydidoxine (vitamin B) to the chemotherapy may reduce the incidence and severity of HFS. The study is a double blind study comparing the administration of oral 200mg pryidoxine with an oral placebo for 24 weeks. Neither the patient of the Doctor will know what treatment (active drug or placebo) the patient will be allocated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/02/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>89/045</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Chris Karapetis</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Unit
Department of Medical Oncology
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82048997</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82044997</fax>
      <email>chris.karapetis@fmc.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Alison Richards</name>
      <address>Department of Medical Oncology
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82048997</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82044997</fax>
      <email>alison.richards @fmc.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>