<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368389">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000790549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Curcumin for the treatment of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) - a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Curcumin for the treatment of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) - a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-3930 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Curcumin capsules containing 250-500mg of a proprietary blend of curcumin (BCM-95 'Registered Trademark') will be consumed twice daily for 12 weeks by children diagnosed with ADHD or with significant attentional problems. Adherence to capsule intake will be monitored through capsule return and count.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo, is matched to to the curcumin capsules in terms of taste and appearance, but does not contain any of the active ingredients.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in ADHD score as assessed by the ADHD Rating Scale-IV</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 4, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ). The SDQ is a behavioral screening questionnaire assessing the following areas- emotional symptoms, conduct problems, hyperactivity/ inattention, peer relationship problems and prosocial behaviour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 4, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Child is a healthy male or female aged between 6 and 14 years
2. Child has been diagnosed with ADHD or significant attentional problem, as assessed by investigators
3. Child is willing and able to swallow capsules. 
4. Preferable, but not essential. Childs teacher is willing to complete questionnaires (at the beginning and end of the study)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Current or 12-month history in your child of any psychiatric disorder other than ADHD, oppositional defiant disorder or similar behavioural disorder (moderate-to-high severity). 
2. Child is currently taking any pharmaceutical medication (including ADHD medication), apart from the occasional use (no more than fortnightly) of pain-relievers (e.g., ibuprofen, panadeine).
3. Child is currently taking turmeric/ curcumin supplements and/or other specific herbal products
4. Child has current or history of clinically significant chronic medical condition including cardiovascular disease, organic brain disorder, seizure, diabetes
5. Child currently abuses or is dependent on drugs
6. Child has any learning problem significantly affecting his/her educational achievement
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will respond to advertisements. Participants will then be briefly interviewed to assess eligibility and if meeting eligibility criteria a formal mental health assessment will be conducted (MINI International Neuropsychiatric interview). If the participant meets all eligibility criteria, he/she will be randomly allocated into a placebo or curcumin treatment group. Group allocation will be conducted in a double-blind, randomised fashion. Allocation concealment will occur through the use of numbered containers where both the participant, and primary researcher responsible for conducting the study, will be unaware of its contents.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly allocated into placebo and treatment groups. These groups are named group 1 and group 2 and the primary investigator and participants will be unaware of which treatment these groups represent. Each participant will be allocated a participant number (1 to 60) based on order of inclusion in the study. A computer-generated software will randomly assign the numbers 1 to 60 into either group 1 or 2.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As this is the first time curcumin will be used for the treatment of ADHD the magnitude of treatment effects from curcumin is not known. However, in a previous study using another natural substance (Pinus marinus) positive effects were found when a sample size of 60 children was used. In this study a moderate effect size of 0.75 for the treatment group was identified. Assuming a power of 80% and a type one error rate  (alpha) of 5%, the number of participants per group to find an effect is 29. In the current study we will be using 30 participants per group</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>70</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>29/01/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 South St 
Murdoch WA 6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dolcas-Biotech, LLC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>29 Beacon Hill Drive
Chester, NJ 07930</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a double-blind, placebo controlled study assessing the therapuetic effects of curcumin in 60 youth suffering from ADHD or significant attentional problem. Participants will be randomly allocated into either a curcumin (BCM-95 'Registered Trademark' - 250-500mg twice daily) or placebo group and changes in ADHD symptoms and general behaviour will be measured over a 12-week period. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>No publication has been submitted. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Murdoch University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>90 South St 
Murdoch WA 6150</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/002</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Drummond</name>
      <address>Murdoch University, School of Psychology and Exercise Science, 90 South St Murdoch Western Australia 6150</address>
      <phone> +61 8 9360 2415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> P.Drummond@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lopresti</name>
      <address>Murdoch University, School of Psychology and Exercise Science, 90 South St Murdoch Western Australia 6150</address>
      <phone>+61411969797</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.lopresti@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lopresti</name>
      <address>Murdoch University, School of Psychology and Exercise Science, 90 South St Murdoch Western Australia 6150</address>
      <phone>+61411969797</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.lopresti@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adrian Lopresti</name>
      <address>Murdoch University, School of Psychology and Exercise Science, 90 South St Murdoch Western Australia 6150</address>
      <phone>+61411969797</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.lopresti@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>