<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335557">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000498099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>SCIPA (Spinal Cord Injury and Physical Activity) Full-On:  Intensive Exercise Program After Spinal Cord Injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Intensive Exercise Program After Spinal Cord Injury:  Effectiveness of a comprehensive exercise program compared to a generic upper body strength and fitness training program on neurological improvement in people at least 6 months post spinal cord injury</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SCIPA Full-On</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Cord Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group A - Experimental Group - comprehensive exercise program:  Body weight supported treadmill training (Therastride System, Food and Drug Administration (FDA) registration number 890.5380) allows spinal cord injured patients to stand suspended in a harness by an overhead pulley on a specially designed treadmill for locomotor training. Functional Electrical Stimulation-assisted cycling (RT-300 cycle ergometer) allows spinal cord injured patients to actively exercise using coordinated electrically evoked/enhanced muscle contractions while remaining seated in their wheelchair (fully compliant with 21 Code of Federal Regulations (CFR) Part 820, United States of America (US) FDA Quality Systems Regulations). Trunk and lower extremity exercises will comprise assisted and/or resisted movements aimed at facilitating and strengthening voluntary muscle activity and improving movement quality.  These may be provided in lying (e.g. supine, prone) and in weight-bearing positions (e.g. kneeling, standing).  Task specific practice of functional tasks, involving moving the upper body over and outside the base of support, will also be undertaken.  This comprehensive exercise program will be conducted 2-3 hours per day, 3 times per week for 12 weeks.  Every session will contain all exercises where possible; the amount of time devoted to each component will vary according to a participant's ability and endurance.  The aim is to build up the amount of exercise to three hours per session in total.  The exercise program will be supervised by a physiotherapist with assistance from an exercise physiologist and/or physiotherapy assistants.  The amount of supervision will vary according to the activity, e.g. one-on-one supervision for the trunk and limb exercises, four-on-one for treadmill training.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group B - Control Group - upper body exercise program:  Upper body circuit-based exercise program incorporating resistance and cardiovascular training, focusing on health and wellbeing.  Participants will use standard gym equipment to complete a circuit of exercises as part of a group of 3-4 participants supervised by a physiotherapist or trained exercise instructor.  The program will be conducted 3 times per week for 12 weeks.  The amount of time devoted to each exercise will vary according to the participant's ability and endurance.  The aim is to build up the amount of exercise to three hours per session in total.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint is the change in American Spinal Injury Association classification (ASIA) Motor Score at 12 weeks (Post Intervention Assessment) compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following 12 weeks of treatment compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in ASIA Motor Score at 6 and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months and 12 months post randomisation compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in SCIPA Aerobic Fitness Test at 12 weeks, 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Spinal Cord Independence Measure (SCIM) and measure of trunk function post intervention (12 weeks), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in anthropometry measured using Body Mass Index (BMI), skinfolds and abdominal, chest and leg circumferences post intervention, 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Quality of Life Measures post intervention (Assessment of Quality of Life, Health Utilities Index Mark III and World Health Organisation Quality of Life Questionnaire, brief version (WHOQoL-bref)), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in spasticity (measured using the the Penn Spasm Frequency Scale) post intervention, 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in pain (measured using the Spinal Cord Injury version of the Multidimensional Pain inventory) post intervention, 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in diurnal blood pressure pattern measured using non-invasive ambulatory blood pressure and pulse rate monitoring post intervention, 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in psychological measures (measured using questionnaires:  stress - Perceived Stress Scale, depression - Hospital Depression and Anxiety, health locus of control - Multidimensional Health Locus of Control Scale, self efficacy - Moorong Self-Efficacy Scale, self esteem - Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale) post intervention, 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (Post Intervention), 6 months and 12 months compared to baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be included if they:
1.  Have sustained a traumatic spinal cord injury (SCI) a minimum of 6 months prior to consent and have completed their primary rehabilitation
2.  Are 18 years or older and able to give informed consent
3.  Have a complete or incomplete spinal cord injury between C6 and T12 (as per the International Standardised Neurological Assessment for SCI)
4.  Are able and willing to attend an exercise program 3 times per week for 12 weeks
5.  Are considered by their medical consultant to be fit to undertake the exercise program (documented approval by the medical consultant is required).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will not be included if they:
1.  Have brachial plexus, cauda equina, or peripheral nerve injury
2.  Have had recent  major trauma or surgery within the last 6 months
3.  Have an existing pressure ulcer Stage 3 or 4 according to the National Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel classification
4.  Are post-menopausal at time of injury (females)
5.  Have Body Mass Index (BMI) at injury falling below lower threshold of healthy adult reference range   
6.  Have endocrinopathy or metabolic disorders of bone, such as Pagets disease, lytic or renal bone disease and senile osteoporosis 
7.  have medical history of exposure to medication(s) known to affect mineral ion or bone metabolism
8.  Have chronic systemic diseases, e.g. Hepatitis C (Hep C), Human Immunodeficiency Virus-Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome (HIV-AIDs)
9.  Have significant impairment or disability, including physical, neurological or psychological impairments
10.  Have a history of long bone fracture, or family history of fragility fracture
11.  Have medical fragility, e.g. BMI falling below lower threshold of healthy adult reference range, or history of recurrent hospital readmissions.
12.  Have extensive fixed contractures in upper or lower limbs
13.  Have severe spasticity 
14.  Have uncontrolled neuropathic pain
15.  Are likely to experience clinically significant  autonomic dysreflexia and/or hypotension in response to electrical stimulation or prolonged upright posture
16.  Are unable to attend the 6-month and 12 month follow-up assessments at their treating spinal unit
17.  Have any contraindications to Functional Electrical Stimulation (FES) such as cardiac pacemaker, epilepsy, lower limb fracture or pregnancy
18.  Have intracranial metal implants (for Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) only)
19.  Have any other serious medical condition including malignancies, psychiatric, behavioural or drug-dependency problems, which are likely to influence the participants ability to cooperate or in the opinion of the study investigator would prevent adherence to the Protocol.
20.  Are participating in any other therapy (including alternative therapies) or taking medications (including herbal preparations) that are not considered to be standard care as per the protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will participate in pre-screening, then screening and baseline visits prior to randomisation.  Eligible participants will be randomised to one of two groups:  1.  Group A - Experimental Group - comprehensive exercise program or 2. Group B - Control Group - upper body exercise program.  Randomisation will be stratified by site and injury status (complete/incomplete) and co-ordinated by a central randomisation unit.  Upon completion of all screening and baseline assessments and suitability checks, a participant eligibility checklist will be completed by the Site Coordinator and signed by the Principal Investigator. This checklist will be sent to the central randomisation unit who will notify the Site Coordinator of treatment assignment. This will not be disclosed to the Blinded Assessors.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>188</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>116</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Melbourne, Parkville, VIC 3101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Neurotrauma Intiative</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6, 60 Brougham Street, Geelong, VIC 3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lifetime Care and Support Authority</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 24, 580 George St
Sydney NSW 2000

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main objective of the study is to determine whether the comprehensive exercise program leads to better neurological recovery than the upper body training program.  Both programs are likely to lead to improvements in health and fitness</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Unit
Henry Buck Building
Austin Hospital</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2010/03976</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/05/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Clinical Trials business Unit Royal Perth Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5, Colonial House, Wellington St, Perth</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010/115</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/10/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Terrace, Adelaide</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>101014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/10/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Multi-regional Ethics Commitee New Zealand</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health, 1 The Terrace, Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/10/10/101</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/09/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Central Coast Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Business Unit, Level 2 Building 51, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards, NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/HAWKE/142</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/11/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Royal Park Campus
34-54 Poplar Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melanie Hurley</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Trials Australia (SCIPA / University of Melbourne)
(a business unit within the Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health)
Melbourne Brain Centre - Austin Campus
245 Burgundy Street
Heidelberg VIC 3084
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7235</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2881</fax>
      <email>mhurley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Melanie Hurley</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Trials Australia (SCIPA / University of Melbourne)
(a business unit within the Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health)
Melbourne Brain Centre - Austin Campus
245 Burgundy Street
Heidelberg VIC 3084
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7235</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2881</fax>
      <email>mhurley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Royal Park Campus
34-54 Poplar Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>