<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362989">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000949886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mepitel Film for the prevention of skin ulceration caused by radiation therapy in breast cancer patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of Mepitel Film in preventing radiation-induced moist desquamation in breast cancer patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer patients treated with radiation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acute side effects of radiation therapy for breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who are to be treated with radiation therapy for breast cancer will be invited to particiate in this trial.
At the start of radiation treatment the chest area to be irradiated will be divided into a medial and lateral half (containing the axilla). Each half will be randomized to either the treatment or the control arm. 

Treatment Arm
1. Mepitel Film will be placed on the skin area randomized to the treatment arm by the research radiation therapist. Film will be replaced when necessary (approximately every 1 or 2 weeks). 
2. Radiation therapy will be given through the Film, due to the extremely small bolus effect. 
3. The Film will remain in place for the duration of RT treatment and after completion of radiation therapy treatment until the skin reactions resolve fully. 

Control Arm
1.	Aqueous cream will be applied by the patient twice a day to treat the control skin areas. 

Trial Endpoint: moist desquamation
When moist desquamation occurs in either the Mepitel Film or control patches, the skin will be treated as per department protocol.</interventions>
    <comparator>Aqueous cream will be applied by the patient twice a day to treat the control skin areas for the entire duration of the trial (from the first day of treatment till resolution of all skin reactions).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of moist desquamation. Moist desquamation is when the integrity of the epidermis is lost, leading to ulceration. We will use the RISRAS scale to assess all skin reactions, including moist desquamation. This Radiation-Induced Skin Reaction Assessment Scale was developed specifically for these situations by Noble Adams (Br J Nurs. 1999 Nov;8(19):1305-12) and later adjusted by McBride et al. (Cancer Nurs. 2008 Jan-Feb;31(1):E8-14).We have used this scale in our previous two trials (Diggelmann et al. BJR, 83 (2010), 971?978).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The number of skin patches in the treatment and control arms that develop moist desquamation during the trial.
The trial commences at the time that the patients will get their very first radiation therapy treatment. Treatment usually lasts 5 weeks. Patients will continue to be seen once a week for four weeks after completion of treatment or untill all skin reactions have been resolved.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to developing moist desquamation. Moist desquamation will be assessed under primary outcome 1.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The number of days it takes to develop moist desquamation in skin patches in the treatment and control arms after commencement of radiation treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The severity of the skin reactions which will be determined by RISRAS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>RISRAS scores will be determined three times a week during treatment and once a week after completion of treatment until skin reacyions resolve (usually 4-6 weeks after treatment completion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who receive radiation therapy for breast cancer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous radiation therapy to the chest
Metastatic disease
Inability to attend follow up sessions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>1.	Patients will commence RT treatment after having received information about the trial verbally from the radiation oncologist and research radiation therapist and in the form of the participant information sheet. They will also give written informed consent . 
2.	At the start of treatment the chest area to be irradiated will be divided into a medial and lateral half (containing the axilla). Each half will be randomized to either the treatment or the control arm. 
3.     Randomization will be done by the PI, Dr Patries Herst from the University of Otago, Wellington, using computer generated random numbers, provided by the University’s  biostatistician, Dr James Stanley.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated numbers.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients will act as their own controls. This circumvents confounding patient-related and treatment-related factors. Randomization will circumvent the effect of small dose differences between the areas with dressings and the areas without dressings. In addition, TLDs will be used on all patients to determine the actual dose received by skin areas covered in Film and those treated with aqueous cream.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>80</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>South Island, Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>POBox 7343
Wellington South
Wellington 6242</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Molnlycke Healthcare Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Molnlycke Healthcare
Box 130 80
SE-402 52 Gothenburg
Sweden</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dunedin Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Southern DHB
Private Bag 1921
Dunedin 9054</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Breast cancer is the most common malignancy for women in New Zealand. Severe skin reactions occur in a significant proportion of women who receive radiation therapy for breast cancer. Skin ulceration affects patient quality of life and poses a risk of infection. There is currently no standard treatment for radiation-induced skin reactions. 
We have shown in two trials in New Zealand that  Mepilex Lite dressings decrease the severity of acute radiation-induced skin reactions. Both trials were intra-patient controlled randomized trials, whereby each patient acted as their own control, circumventing the problem of the many confounding treatment-and patient-related factors that affect the severity of such skin reactions.
However, the dressing were not transparent and did not stick well in the armpit and underneath the breast. 
Mepitel Film has all the advantages of Mepilex Lite but is transparent, sticks better and stays on for longer. This study will compare the efficacy of Mepitel Film with that of aqueous cream in reducing the incidence of radiation-induced skin ulceration in 40 women treated for breast cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>The trial has recently been published:
Patries M Herst, Noelle C Bennett, Annie E Sutherland, Ruth I Peszynski, Dean B Paterson &amp; Marieke L Jasperse. Prophylactic use of Mepitel Film prevents radiation-induced moist desquamation in an intra-patient randomised controlled clinical trial of 78 breast cancer patients. Radiotherapy and Oncology. 2014. 110(1) pp. 137-143).</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago
Academic Committees 
PO Box 56,
Dunedin 9054,
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/239</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/362989-Herst et al., 2014.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Patries Herst</name>
      <address>Radiation Therapy
Senior Lecturer
University of Otago
POBox 7343
Wellington South
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 3855475</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3855375</fax>
      <email>patries.herst@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Patries Herst</name>
      <address>Radiation Therapy
Senior Lecturer
University of Otago
POBox 7343
Wellington South
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 3855475</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3855375</fax>
      <email>patries.herst@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Patries Herst</name>
      <address>Radiation Therapy
Senior Lecturer
University of Otago
POBox 7343
Wellington South
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 3855475</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3855375</fax>
      <email>patries.herst@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Patries Herst</name>
      <address>University of Otago POBox 7343 Wellington South Wellington 6242.</address>
      <phone>+64 4 3855475</phone>
      <fax> +64 4 3855375</fax>
      <email>patries.herst@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>