<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81608">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/12/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/03/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000150448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Post-operative pain management following arthroscopic rotator cuff repair. A comparison of inter-scalene block with subacromial bursal infusion</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomised control trial comparing post-operative pain relief after shoulder surgery, using regional anaesthesia inter-scalene block, compared with direct shoulder joint anaesthesia using a breg pump following arthroscopic rotator cuff repair of the shoulder for those patients with rotator cuff arthropathy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rotator cuff tear / arthropathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prospective Randomised Control Trial

Patients undergoing an arthroscopic rotator cuff repair by Simon McMahon with the anaesthetic given by John Hyndman at Mercy Hospital, Dunedin, New Zealand will be eligible for enrolment in the study

After patients have given there consent to being in the study they will be randomised into Group 1 or 2
Randomisation will occur through a random generated number table

Group 2 (CONTROL): Those who will receive a long-acting inter-scalene block + IV/oral analgesia

Bupivacaine 0.375% 20-30mls (depending patients weight)

After patients have given their consent to being in the study they will be randomised
Patients will be asked to record their level of pain by
1. using a visual analogue scale (VAS) on paper

VAS = visual scale 100mms in length with no pain at the left hand side and worst pain ever experienced at the right hand side. Patients will be asked subjectively to place a mark on the line where they feel there level of pain is at there pre-operative assessment, and then 4, 8, 12, 24, 48 hours post-operation.

Any analgesics consumed at these times will also be recorded</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 1 (COMPARATOR): Those patients who will be receiving a short acting inter-scalene block and subacromial infusion (Breg) pump + IV/oral analgesia

Interscalene block dosage:
lignocaine 1.5% 20-30 mls (depending on patients weight)

Subacromial infusion pump:
50mls 0.25% Bupivicaine </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of Pain following surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operation, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours post-operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operation, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 48 hours post-operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other medications used</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operation, 4, 8 ,12, 24 and 48 hours post-operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. All patients with a rotator cuff tear / arthropathy at Mercy Hospital who will2. undergo arthroscopic rotator cuff repair by Simon McMahon 3. be anaesthetised by John Hyndman4. All patients who wish to participate in the study and give consent to being in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those patients not able to give consent. Those patients who are sensitive or allergic to the medications given. Those patients who do not wish to participate and/or who do not give consent to being in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation was concealed by central randomisation by phone</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nigel Hartnett</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mercy Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dunedin Public Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Simon McMahon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>John Hyndman</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rotator cuff surgery ranks in the top 3 procedures performed according to Accident Compensation Commission records. Arthroscopic rotator cuff surgery is becoming more common as surgeons skills and techniques become better.However pain relief following an arthroscopic rotator cuff repair can be problematic. A number of different techniques have been described to overcome this problem. The one conventionally used is an interscalene block whereby the nerves at the base of the neck receive a local anaesthetic injection. The patient is then given IV/oral analgesics once the block has worn off. The main issues are that 1. sometimes the block does not work (ie.. does not provide pain relief/control) and 2. sometimes the patients get concerned that the block fails to resolve (ie.. they are left with a short-term almost paralysis type picture) and makes movements and sensation of the affected arm difficult for the patient.There is no accepted consensus on which technique is best, however, recently devices have become available which infuse the anaesthetic directly into the shoulder joint. The results both locally and internationally although anecdotal (no scientific paper has compared the two techniques) are promising and may lead to better and more effective pain control as well as taking away the patients concern regarding there non-functioning arm.We will be undertaking the first project to compare the traditional technique against a direct local anaesthetic infusion pump. We feel that the potential health outcomes from this new technique for pain control, may change what is now considered standard treatment. It may even become practical for use in other areas of Arthroscopy such as the knee, ankle, elbow or wrist 
Our hypothesis is that there is an advantage in terms of post op pain relief with the use of a Breg Pain Pump with a short acting brachial plexus block compared to a long acting brachial plexus block.
We will be doing this by  using a visual analogue score for the patients to see whether there is any statistical significant difference between group 1 (those who will be receiving a short acting inter-scalene block and subacromial infusion pump) compared with group 2 (those who will receive a long-acting inter-scalene block)</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mercy Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/08/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LRS/06/04/016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Dunedin Public Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/08/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LRS/06/04/016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/08/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LRS/06/04/016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nigel Hartnett</name>
      <address>Orthopaedic Registrar
Orthopaedic Department
Dunedin Public Hospital
Private Bag 1921
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4740999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nigel.hartnett@healthotago.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr. Simon McMahon</name>
      <address>Mercy Hospital
Private Bag 1919
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4672315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mcmortho@paradise.net.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>