<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370004">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000121460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Blood Flow Restriction Exercise for Muscle Health and Physical Function in End-Stage Kidney Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Blood Flow Restriction Exercise for Muscle Health and Physical Function in End-Stage Kidney Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-9379</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>End-Stage Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The trial will examine 2 exercise training interventions among patients with end-stage kidney disease. Both exercise training interventions will be completed intradialytically, 3 times per week, for a period of 3 months.

Intervention 1 will examine the use of blood flow restriction to the lower limbs during cycling exercise training (50% reduction in muscle blood flow) using a pneumatic surgical tourniquet. The pneumatic surgical tourniquet includes two cuffs similar to blood pressure cuffs. It auto-regulates the pressure to which the cuffs are inflated based on settings input into the central machine, this pressure adjusts to maintain constant pressure with muscle contraction under the cuff. The cuffs are placed on the most proximal aspect of the thigh. Intervention 1 will involve 10 minutes of cycling, followed by 20 minutes of rest, and then a second 10 minute bout of cycling. The cuffs will only be inflated during the two 10 minute bouts of active cycling, and deflated during the rest. The intensity of the cycling will be based on patients' subjective rating of perceived exertion (RPE) of between 12 and 15 on Borg's 6-20 scale. Blood flow restriction exercise is known to have higher RPEs than equivalent intensity non-blood flow restriction exercise.

Intervention 2 will examine more traditional cycling, without any blood flow restriction, for 20 minutes continuously. This is more reflective of current aerobic training guidelines for end-stage kidney disease patients. The intensity of the cycling will be based on patients' subjective rating of perceived exertion of between 10 and 12 on Borg's 6-20 scale. This would mark the equivalent absolute intensity to that of intervention 1. This is the lower end of what is commonly recommended, and allows for a direct comparison of training adaptations to intervention 1.

All exercise training sessions will be supervised by study staff to ensure that protocol is adhered to, and that all prescribed training intensities are met.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group used in this study will be usual care haemodialysis, where patients will undergo their normal dialysis routine, without exercising.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee extensor strength measured by one-repetition maximum bilateral knee extension</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing intervention, at 3 months, within 7 days of final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower limb functional strength reflective of activities of daily living using the 30-second sit-to-stand test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing exercise training intervention, and at 3 months, within 7 days of completing the final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower limb dynamic balance and mobility using the Timed Up-and-Go test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing exercise training intervention, and at 3 months, within 7 days of completing the final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait speed, endurance and cardiovascular fitness using the 6-minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing exercise training intervention, and at 3 months, within 7 days of completing the final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>VO2peak during exercise measured using Innocor metabolic system during symptom limited graded cycling test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing exercise training intervention, and at 3 months, within 7 days of completing the final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life and physical activity participation using the CHAMPS questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing exercise training intervention, and at 3 months, within 7 days of completing the final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Regional body composition measured using Dual-Energy X-Ray Absorptiometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing exercise training intervention, and at 3 months, within 7 days of completing the final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thigh musculature sizes measured using peripheral quantitative computer tomography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline within 7 days of commencing exercise training intervention, and at 3 months, within 7 days of completing the final exercise training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stage V kidney disease (end-stage kidney disease); have been undergoing haemodialysis for more than 3 months;</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>symptomatic peripheral vascular disease; amputation, uncontrolled hypertension, inability to complete requirements of physical testing and exercise training sessions; have been hospitalized for non-dialysis reasons within 4 weeks of study commencement; completing more than 150 minutes per week of moderate to vigorous physical activity including resistance training</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Expected effect sizes were ascertained based on previous literature utilising similar aspects of exercise training, and the same primary outcome for knee extensor strength using G-Power 3 statistical software package. To achieve a power of 80% at an alpha level of 0.05, 20 participants per group will be required to detect a difference between the expected means for percentage strength improvement (the size of the variation in means is represented by a standard deviation of 6.24).

Based on the 3 month duration, a conservative attrition rate of 20% will be adopted, as supported by pilot data for a 12 month training study by our research group (demonstrated attrition of 20% over 12 months). Therefore a total of 75 participants will be recruited for this study.

One-way ANOVA for all outcomes comparing baseline to post-intervention data between groups will be used during data analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/08/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>19</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter James Centre - Forest Hill</hospital>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3131 - Forest Hill</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>none</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with end stage kidney disease require renal dialysis to maintain health. These people are attached to dialysis machines for 4 hours at least 3 times per week. Both the kidney disease and the dialysis lead to an accelerated physical deterioration, resulting in decreased strength and reduced capacity to perform activities of daily living.

At present, exercise recommendations suggest moderate to high intensity exercise that incorporates both resistance training and aerobic training. To satisfy this requirement it is recommended that 30-60 minutes of exercise training be completed on both dialysis and non-dialysis days. This is very poorly adhered to by patients undergoing dialysis due to decreased exercise capacity, contraindication to high intensities of exercise training, elevated fatigue, and a preference for not doing exercise training on non-dialysis days.

Blood flow restriction (BFR) exercise training elicits significant muscle size and strength increases with low intensities. BFR with aerobic exercise training produces muscle size and strength that is not commonly achieved with non-BFR aerobic exercise training. This has previously been performed in older adult populations, and also with individuals with stable ischaemic heart disease with promising results and can easily be performed during haemodialysis.

This study aims to measure the effect of 3 months of intradialytic BFR exercise training on lower limb strength, muscle size, physical function, and quality of life.

Participants will be recruited from 4 Victorian outpatient and private dialysis units administered by Eastern Health. Participants will be randomly allocated into 3 groups (20 patients in each). The groups will perform one of: BFR aerobic exercise training (BFR AT), non-BFR aerobic exercise training (AT), or non-exercise controls. The BFR AT group will complete 2 bouts of 10 minutes cycling with BFR applied. The AT group will complete 20 minutes of continuous cycling. and the control group will undergo usual-care haemodialysis with no exercise.

It is expected that the BFR AT group will exhibit greater increases in muscle size and strength, as well as greater levels of physical function compared to the AT group following exercise training intervention. Both the BFR AT and AT group will demonstrate greater muscle size and strength than the usual care control group. This study will demonstrate that BFR is a potential alternative to the burdensome exercise recommendations that are, at present, extremely poorly adhered to, or altogether ignored by dialysis patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill VIC 3128
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>E05-2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Matthew Clakson</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Victoria
3125</address>
      <phone>+61 400 225 116</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mclarks@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Matthew Clakson</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Victoria
3125</address>
      <phone>+61 400 225 116</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mclarks@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Matthew Clakson</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Victoria
3125</address>
      <phone>+61 400 225 116</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mclarks@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Matthew Clarkson</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood, Victoria
3125</address>
      <phone>+61 400 225 116</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mclarks@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>