<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373402">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001132336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparative assessment of the absorption of a generic formulation of 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) capsule against the innovator 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) capsule conducted under fasting condition and at steady state in healthy male and female volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multiple dose, randomized, blinded, bioequivalence study of a test formulation of 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) capsule in a 2 way crossover comparison against the innovator 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) capsule conducted under fasting conditions and at steady state in healthy male and female volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1197-1741</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) is a C5 Controlled Drug indicated in the management of obesity as a short-term adjunct in a medically monitored comprehensive regime of weight reduction.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mutliple dose, crossover study design whereby each participant receives the test formulation of 40 mg 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) capsule on five occasions and the innovator formulation of 40 mg 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) capsule on five occasions with each dose separated by a 10 day washout period. The intervention for this trial is the test capsule formulation.

On study days 1-5 subjects will receive 5 daily doses of one formulation (either the test or innovator) and on study days 15-19 they will receive 5 daily doses of the other formulation (either the innovator or test). 

Each dose (1 x 40 mg) will be taken orally with 240 ml of water at ambient temperature. Medication must be swallowed whole and a mouth check will be conducted to ensure the medication has been taken as directed.

No water is allowed for 1 hour prior to dosing until 1 hour after dosing (except for the water consumed with the dose).

Participants are required not to eat for 4 hours before receiving each dose on study days 1 to 4 and 15 to 18.

On study days 1 and 15 subjects will report to the Zenith Clinical Site for dosing and observation of adverse events and the provision of one blood sample. They are required to stay at the clinical site for 10 hours after dosing. 

On study days 2 to 4 and 16 to 18 subjects will report to Zenith Technology for dosing and the provision of one blood sample.

On study day 5 and 19 no water is allowed for 1 hour prior to dosing until 1 hour after dosing (except for the water consumed with the dose) and subjects are required to fast for 8 hours prior to receiving the dose and approximately 4 hours after receiving each dose. Bathroom visits will be supervised to ensure no unauthorised water or food intake and for personal safety. Participants will be confined at the Clinical Site for 8 hours prior to dosing to ensure compliance can be monitored and for 24 hours after dosing.

Standard meals will be consumed at the Clinical Site on study days 5 and 19 with no additional food intake allowed. Alcohol breath testing will be performed upon each participant reporting to the Clinical Site prior to dosing.

Pre and post study laboratory tests will be completed to assess the health of participants along with HIV, Hepatitis and drugs of abuse testing.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Multiple dose, crossover study design whereby each participant receives the test formulation of 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) (1 x 40 mg) on five occasions and the innovator formulation of 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) (1 x 40 mg) on five occasions with each dose seperated by a 10 day washout period. The comparator/control for this trial is the innovator formulation of 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8).  Both formulations will be given as an oral capsule.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the bioavailability of 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) (as summarised by Cmax(ss) and AUC(ss)) for the two formulations. All plasma samples will be assayed for 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) using a fully validated LC/MS/MS method. Validation will be conducted to comply with EU and FDA guidelines.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to dosing on study days 1-4 and 15-18 and at 0, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 16, 20 and 24 hours after dosing on study days 5 and 19.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to maximum peak concentration (Tmax). Tmax will be the time where the maximum concentration occurred in the sample points. All plasma samples will be assayed for 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) using a fully validated LC/MS/MS method.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to dosing on study days 1-4 and 15-18 and at 0, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 16, 20 and 24 hours after dosing on study days 5 and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy males and Females
Aged between 18 and 55
Non-smoker
BMI between 18 and 33
Normal, healthy individuals as determined by medical history, physical examination, ECG, blood pressure and laboratory tests
Able to provide written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Any history of recent recurrent attacks of bronchitis, asthma, migraine headaches
Concomitant drug therapy of any kind (excluding prescribed hormonal contraceptives
History of depression, anxiety, obsessive-compulsive disorder, or post-traumatic stress syndrome
Pregnant or breast-feeding
Sensitivity to 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8), any antidepressant agents, excipients of 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8)
History of any conditions that might interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of the drug
Smoker (anyone who has smoked in the last 6 months)
History of alcohol or drug abuse or dependency
Participation in a drug study within 60 days of the start of the study or donated blood in the 60 days preceding the study.
Volunteers for whom the Clinical Investigator believes, for any reason, that participation would not be an acceptable risk.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All formulations will be labelled as Formulation A and B. The identification of each treatment will only be known to the Managing Director and the Section Head - Trials and Regulatory Affairs. Randomisation will be performed using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generator).</concealment>
    <sequence>Each participant will be identified by a 3 digit screening number and a 2 digit subject number. the screening number will be issued once the participant has given written consent to participate in the study and the two digit subject number (randomisation number) after acceptance into the study</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Aspen Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>34-36 Chandos St
St Leonards
NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this study is to evaluate the bioequivalence of the test formulation relative to the that of a reference formulation, following oral administration of a combination multiple dose of 40 mg 2-methyl-1-phenylpropan-2-amine (122-09-8) capsule to healthy male and female subjects under fasting conditions and at steady state.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/CEN/112</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Noelyn Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777)
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779669</fax>
      <email>noelyn.hung@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Linda Folland</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777)
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>linda.folland@zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tak Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street (PO Box 1777)
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>tak.hung@zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>