<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347911">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000499886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Research of quality of life trends for Malignant obstructive jaundice patients with different treatment methods</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Research of quality of life trends for Malignant obstructive jaundice patients with different treatment methods</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malignant obstructive jaundice</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Biliary tree (gall bladder and bile duct)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1.Our research group have developed the quality of life scale specific module about malignant obstructive jaundice  patients (QLQ-MOJ11) on the basis of EORTC QLQ-C30 scale. So we apply both EORTC QLQ-C30 and QLQ-MOJ11 scale to evaluation the quality of life for patients with  malignant obstructive jaundice  from admission to three months discharge. The patiernts need to fill with the scale five times over this period. We use the methods of self-evaluation and telephone follow-up to assesment the QOL of malignant obstructive jaundice patients.
2.The purpose of collecting general information on the patient is to  judgment the demographic characteristics and biochemical indicators of the impact on patient quality of life and survival time. So that we can predict the risk factors with death forpatients with malignant obstructive jaundice .</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The patients should fill out the QLQ-C30 and QLQ-MOJ11 scale three times duration of hospital stay, including admission, seven days after treatment, before dicharge. We should collect general data about patients in this timepoint. We can get the influence factors of quality of life for patients with malignant obstructive jaundice.</outcome>
      <timepoint>admission, seven days after treatment, before discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We follow-up patients with malignant obstructive jaundice patients by telephone and outpatient review. Patients shoud still full out the QLQ-C30 and QLQ-MOJ11 scale after discharge, including one month dicharge, three months discharge. We combine the data about patients duration of hospital stay to analysis the trends of quality of life for patients with malignant obstructive jaundice.</outcome>
      <timepoint>admission, seven days after treatment, before discharge, one month discharge, three months discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will measure the survival time and the risk factors of death for  patients with malignant obstructive jaundice by COX proportional hazards model.</outcome>
      <timepoint>the first day after treatment, one month discharge, three months dischare, six months discharge, and so on, till the patients death.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) clinically diagnosed with primary bile duct cancer, gallbladder cancer, duodenal cancer, pancreatic cancer, bile duct cancer and metastatic carcinoma.
2) Serum bilirubin Serum Bilirubin thelarger than or equal to 17.1micromol / L.
3) Imaging studies confirmed the biliary obstruction.
4) informed consent of patients.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) past and current mental illness patients and consolidation of the heart, lungs and other major disorders.
2) can not understand the contents of the questionnaire, and patients with language barrier.
3) have been involved in the survey of patients.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Nursing, Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital,No.225,Changhai road,Yangpu District, Shanghai ,200438.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Second Military Medical University Graduate seedling Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Second Military Medical University,No. 800,Xiangyin road, Yangpu District, Shanghai ,200438.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Second Military Medical University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Second Military Medical University,No. 800,Xiangyin road, Yangpu District, Shanghai ,200438.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The patients with malignant obstructive jaundice in advanced disease have poor quality of life according the  results of literature review and clinical observations,  so the main purpose of this study is the use of the QLQ-C30 scale developed by the European cancer research and treatment organizations, and the group pre-developed in patients with malignant obstructive jaundice specific item pool (QLQ-MOJ11) the class of the patient's quality of life evaluation, and analysis of these patients the survival time and the risk factors for death during hospitalization and late follow-up results, the trend of quality of life drawing class for patients with different treatment methods.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Shanghai Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital,No. 225,Changhai road,Yangpu District,Shanghai,200438.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EHBHKY2012-002-9</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Zhihuizou</name>
      <address>Department of Nursing,Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital,No. 225,Changhai road,Yangpu District , Shanghai,200438.</address>
      <phone>+8615618877623</phone>
      <fax>+86021-81875041</fax>
      <email>zouzhihui1999@163.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lili</name>
      <address>ICU,Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital, No.225,Changhai road,Yangpu District ,Shanghai,200438.</address>
      <phone>+8613817382212</phone>
      <fax>+86021-81875041</fax>
      <email>smallsweetlily@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Zhihuizou</name>
      <address>Department of Nursing,Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital,No. 225,Changhai road,Yangpu District , Shanghai,200438.</address>
      <phone>+8615618877623</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zouzhihui1999@163.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>