<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371677">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001549415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of combining omega-3, vitamin D and protein with exercise on cognition in older people  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-faceted intervention to enhance cognition in older people at risk of cognitive decline: the Protein, Omega-3 aNd vitamin D Exercise Research (PONDER) study </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-8145 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Protein, Omega-3 aNd vitamin D Exercise Research (PONDER)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Frailty</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Age-related cognitive decline</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will take part in a community based exercise program which will be conducted in local leisure centres twice per week for 6 months. Participants will be allocated to either a 6 month multi-modal exercise program combining moderate intensity resistance training or a flexibility, stretching and agility program. The multi-modal exercise program will include 2 sets of 8 resistance exercises, with 8-12 reps completed at an intensity of at least 13/20 on the BORG RPE scale. All exercise sessions will be delivered by qualified personal trainers and each session will last approximately 60 minutes. Participants will also consume a daily supplement drink containing 1.5 grams combined EPA and DHA omega 3 fatty acids, 1000 IU vitamin D3 and 25 grams whey protein for 6 months or a placebo drink. The supplement will be provided in powder form to be mixed with water. Outcomes will be assessed 6 months post-baseline after the exercise program has been completed and at 12 months post baseline to assess the longer term effects of the intervention. Adherence to the exercise programs will be monitored by the personal trainers and recorded on the participants exercise cards. Participants will record supplement intake on calendars which will be reviewed monthly. </interventions>
    <comparator>A placebo drink will be matched for appearance and caloric content. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive function assessed using the CogState battery and the Trail Making Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive function assessed using the CogState battery, the Trail Making Test and the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood as assessed by the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as assessed by the Short Form Health Survey (SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function as assessed by maximal muscle testing, the four metre walk test, the four square step test, the two minute step test, the grip strength test and 30 second site to stand test </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition as assessed by whole body dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Red blood cell omega 3 profile </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep Quality as assessed by the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum Vitamin D</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip to waist ratio</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pulse wave veolcity</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Areal bone mineral density as assessed by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Healthy adults aged 60 to 85 
2. Subjective memory complaints defined as a positive response to the question do you feel like  your memory is becoming worse? and a score of 24 or greater on the Montreal Cognitive Assessment.
3. Fluent in written and spoken English
4. Normal, or corrected to normal vision and hearing
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis of Alzheimers disease or other dementia, parkinsons disease
2 .Past history of brain damage including significant head trauma,  stroke, or
serious neurological disorder  
3. Clinical diagnosis of psychiatric disorder likely to affect cognition 
4. Alcohol or drug dependency within the last 2 years 
5. Existing diagnosed gastrointestinal disorders likely to impact absorption of  fatty acids 
6. Known allergy to fish or any other component in the dietary supplement
7. Insufficient mobility to exercise
8. Body mass index &gt;40
9. Current smokers
10. Participating in progressive resistance training &gt;1 week or more &gt;150 minutes per week of moderate intensity physical activity
11. Daily use of omega-3 rich supplement, or vitamin D supplements &gt;500 IU 
weeks
12. Use of cholinesterase inhibitors, benzodiazepines, antipsychotics, high dose antidepressants, warfarin or high dose blood thinners
13. Resistance hypertension



</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An independent holder of the randomisation schedule who will have no contact with the volunteers or be involved in data analysis, will perform treatment allocation</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated block randomization, stratified for age and gender.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>148</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research
221 Burwood Hwy
Victoria 3125
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ARC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Research Council
GPO Box 2702, 
Canberra ACT 2601, 
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Protein, Omega-3 aNd vitamin D Exercise Research (PONDER) study is a randomised controlled trial which will investigate the effects of combining a structured exercise program with dietary supplements on cognition and muscle mass and function in people aged 60 -85 years. The PONDER study is being run by researchers from the Institute of Physical Activity and Nutrition (IPAN) at Deakin University in Burwood. People who take part in this research will be assigned to one of two exercise programs run in a community based gym. Participants will either receive a dietary supplement drink which contains a combination of protein, omega 3 fish oil and vitamin D, or a placebo. The exercise programs will be run for 6 months in community based gyms under the supervision of qualified trainers. Participants will be asked to attend Deakin University in Burwood on 4 occasions over 12 months to undergo cognitive and health testing and to visit a local pathology centre on 3 occasions for a blood test.  Participants in this study will attend 2 x 60 min supervised exercise sessions per week at a local gym, for a period of six months and will be asked to consume a dietary supplement daily during this time.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee (DUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Deakin Research Integrity
Burwood Campus Victoria
Postal: 221 Burwood Highway
Burwood 
Victoria 3125 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-260</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helen Macpherson</name>
      <address>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition
Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy 
Burwood
Vic 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 5317</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.macpherson@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sarah Brownell</name>
      <address>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition
Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy 
Burwood
Vic 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9246 8660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ponder@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helen Macpherson</name>
      <address>Institute for Physical Activity and Nutrition
Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy 
Burwood
Vic 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 5317</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.macpherson@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>