<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308420">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000769280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised phase II trial of Cimetidine in patients having surgery for bowel cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised, Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Phase II Trial of the Effect of Peri-operative Cimetidine on Relapse and Survival in Early Colorectal Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>U1111-1123-1396</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cimetidine oral tablets 800mg twice daily for 5 weeks starting a week before surgery</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (content not specified) oral tablets 800mg twice daily for 5 weeks starting a week before surgery</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2 year disease-free survival comparison by Kaplan-Meier actuarial survival curves and logrank statistic iin subgroup with positive tumour immunostaining for sialyl Lewis antigens a or x</outcome>
      <timepoint>primary outcome will be analysed when recruited population has been followed for a median of 2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>duration of post-operative inflammatory cytokine elevation, assessed as the time that plasma concentrations of each cytokine (TNF, IL-1B, IL-6, IL-8) are elevated above pre-treatment baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>plasma concentrations of each cytokine will be measured at baseline (prior to starting study medication), the day prior to surgery then at 24 hours and 1, 2 and 4 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of tumour sialyl Lewis antigen a and/or x expression overall (as % of cases scored as positive) and in different ethnic groups, using published immunostaining protocols</outcome>
      <timepoint>post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-free survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>once at 5 years median follow-up from recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>overall survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>once at 5 years median follow-up from recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cimetidine compliance (% of tablets taken of total expected in the period) and safety (proportion of patients with treatment-related adverse events)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Compliance is measured at the end of the first week, at discharge from hospital following surgery and 4 weeks after surgery. 
Safety is assessed at the end of the first week of administration of study medication.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Biopsy-proven colorectal adenocarcinoma planned for resection with curative intent. 
2.	Age at least 18 years
3.	Accessible for treatment and follow up
4.	Written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Clinical T1 tumours such as a pedunculated polyp
2.	Radiological or clinical evidence of unresectable primary tumours or metastatic disease beyond regional nodes
3.	Unable to swallow or absorb study tablets 
4.	Currently taking H2-antagonists (cimetidine, ranitidine, famotidine, nizatidine)
5.	Taking medications during the period of study treatment that have clinically significant interactions with cimetidine (including warfarin, phenytoin, theophylline and nifedipine) 
6.	Significantly impaired renal function (serum creatinine &gt; 1.25 x upper limit of normal)
7.	Significant liver impairment (bilirubin &gt; 30 micromol/l; Alkaline phosphatase (ALP), aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 2 x upper limit of normal)
8.	Other invasive malignancy within 5 years except adequately-treated basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of skin or in-situ carcinoma of the cervix
9.    Pregnant or breast feeding women
10.  Major surgery within prior 30 days, excluding defunctioning colostomy or ileostomy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consenting eligible patients will be enrolled through the Cancer Trials Unit at Waikato Hospital and allocated a subject number. They will be stratified by preoperative therapy (none vs chemoradiation or radiotherapy) and primary tumour site (colon vs rectum), then allocated by the Clinical Trials Pharmacist to cimetidine or placebo treatment using permuted block randomisation. Allocation concealment is achieved by each bottle being labelled with a batch number, expiry date, subject number and an individual bottle number (created from a list of random unique numbers). Batch numbers and expiry dates are the same for all medication bottles.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated random numbers for each stratum</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy prior to, or following, surgery will be administered according to local policies</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/03/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>17/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Waikato Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 3200
Hamilton 3240</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Waikato Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Peter Rothwell Academic Centre
Private Bag 3200
Hamilton 3240</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Society of NZ (Waikato-Bay of Plenty Division)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P.O. Box 134
Hamilton</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is looking at how we can most effectively use Cimetidine, an ulcer-healing drug that has been available for over 30 years, to try to improve the outcome in patients having surgery to remove bowel cancer. This drug can support the immune system to remain fully active following the stress of surgery, and might reduce the risk of cancer cells spreading during and after the operation. However it is not clear how long patients may need to take the drug to gain the maximum benefit, and this study is aiming to clarify that by examining the impact of surgery on immune responses and what effect cimetidine has on them. 

We will randomise patients to take cimetidine or placebo tablets twice a day for 5 weeks, starting a week before the operation, and will look at immune responses in blood tests taken 6 times over those 5 weeks. We will also look at whether patients have any problems taking the tablets, especially immediately after the operation, how well they recover from surgery and whether they have recurrence of the bowel cancer over the next few years.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 1031
Hamilton</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Jameson</name>
      <address>Regional Cancer Centre
Waikato Hospital
Private Bag 3200
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8604</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 839 8778</fax>
      <email>michael.jameson@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Wendy Thomas</name>
      <address>Cancer Trials Unit
Waikato Hospital
Private Bag 3200
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8976</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 858 0940</fax>
      <email>thomasw@waikatodhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Jameson</name>
      <address>Regional Cancer Centre
Waikato Hospital
Private Bag 3200
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8604</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 839 8778</fax>
      <email>michael.jameson@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Jameson</name>
      <address>Regional Cancer Centre Waikato Hospital Private Bag 3200 Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 839 8604</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.jameson@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>