<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365318">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001306707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Sleep-e: an online treatment program for insomnia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of insomnia severity amongst adults with insomnia related sleep difficulties after an online cognitive behavioural therapy intervention, Sleep-e.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Insomnia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An online cognitive behavioural therapy program for insomnia called Sleep-e. Sleep-e is a 7week interactive CBT program for insomnia. It comprises 6 modules including psycho-education about sleep and insomnia (Module 1), stimulus control and sleep restriction (Module 2), sleep hygiene and relaxation (Module 3), cognitive restructuring (Module 4 and 5), and a relapse prevention module (Module 6).

Participants will be asked to complete the first module over two weeks and the remaining modules over one week each. The anticipated duration to complete each module is approximately one hour.  

Strategies used to monitor adherence to the intervention will include online checking of completion of daily sleep entries, date last logged in, page of program last accessed and dates of completion of surveys.
</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no control group for this study as it is an open trial pilot design.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insomnia severity, as measured by the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete the ISI at pre program (0 weeks), mid program (weeks 4-5), post program (weeks 7-9), and at a 3 month follow up (weeks 21-23).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of Insomnia such as difficulty falling or staying asleep, early morning waking, and feelings of unrefreshed sleep. This will be measured by the consensus sleep diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete the consensus diary throughout the duration of the Sleep-e program (Week 0-7). Participants will also complete the sleep diary for an additional two weeks after completion of the program (Week 7-9), as well as at a 3 month follow up (weeks 21-23).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysfunctional sleep related beliefs, as measured by the Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about Sleep Scale (DBAS-16)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete this questionnaire at pre program (0 weeks), mid program (weeks 4-5), post program (weeks 7-9), and at a 3 month follow-up (weeks 21-23).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of stress, such as difficulty winding down, over-reacting to situations and feeling agitated, as measured by Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete the DASS-21 at pre program (0 weeks), mid program(weeks 4-5), post program (weeks 7-9), and at a 3 month follow-up (weeks 21-23).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of anxiety, such as rapid breathing in the absence of physical exertion, trembling, and feelings of panic, as measured by Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete the DASS-21 at pre program (0 weeks), mid program(weeks 4-5), post program (weeks 7-9), and at 3 months follow-up (weeks 21-23).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of depression, such as feeling down and blue as measured by Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete the DASS-21 at pre program (0 weeks), mid program (weeks 4-5), post program (weeks 7-9), and at 3 months follow-up (weeks 21-23).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Program satisfaction as measured by an online survey developed for this study, the Intervention Evaluation Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed post program (weeks 7-9)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a)Clinical or subclinical symptoms of Insomnia (Insomnia Severity Index
score greater than or equal to 8)
b)18 years of age or older
c)Australian resident
d)Access to the internet</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a)Current psychological treatment for insomnia
b)Extremely severe levels of depression, as measured by the Depression
Anxiety and Stress Scales, DASS-21 (A score of 14 or more on the DASS-21)
c)No access to the internet
d)Not able to understand English
e)Under 18 years of age
f)Non-Australian resident</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The project will be advertised on the Mental Health Online website (formerly Anxiety Online) as well as other mental health websites. Clients interested in finding out more will be directed to a website where they can read the full Information Statement and Consent form, and if they wish to proceed, start the pre-assessment questionnaire. Participants will be given the option of contacting the Principal Investigator to ask questions before providing consent.
The Information Statement and Consent form will explain that their clicking on the “start” button will be taken as their consenting to take part in the study. They will be informed that they can leave the website if they do not consent. If they consent they will directed to complete the pre-assessment questionnaire (via online survey), which asks for their email address, basic demographic information and includes the study measures. Participants who meet all the inclusion criteria for the study will be emailed details of how to access the Sleep-e program (including the program URL, a username and their password).
</concealment>
    <sequence>As this is an open trial evaluation of the program, no control group is being recruited and hence participants are not  randomised.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample demographics, questionnaire findings and sleep diary data will be described using descriptive and summary statistics. The study will investigate treatment effects of the Sleep-e program from pre- to post-assessment to follow-up-assessment and pre to follow-up-assessment using Repeated Measures (Within Subjects) ANOVAs and MANOVAs. If significant results are found, pairwise comparisons from pre to post- to follow-up-assessment and pre to follow-up-assessment will be conducted.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/12/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National eTherapy Centre, Swinburne University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>H99
PO Box 218
Hawthorn
VIC 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Barbara Dicker Brain Sciences Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn
VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to investigate the effectiveness of an Australian designed cognitive behavioural therapy intervention for insomnia called Sleep-e. Insomnia is a very common sleep problem but many people do not access available treatment. Online interventions that are delivered via the internet, such as Sleep-e, can increase the  communities access to treatment, and improve health outcomes. 70 participants with insomnia related sleep difficulties will be recruited into the study. Participants will be recruited either through completing the e-PASS online assessment on www.mentalhealthonline.com or through advertisements on mental health websites such as beyondbue and Reconnexion. Participants will initially
complete a range of questionnaires via the internet about their sleep, and also complete sleep diaries outlining their current sleep patterns. Participants will then complete Sleep-e, a 7 week online program based on cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia. Every week, participants
will be asked to read one module, complete homework activities based on the module, and also complete weekly sleep diaries. Participants will be given questionnaires and sleep diaries to re-assess their sleep and insomnia immediately after the program has been completed, as
well as three months following completion. Twenty participants will also be interviewed by telephone regarding their program experiences and satisfaction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn
VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SUHREC 2013/212 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Abbott</name>
      <address>Swinburne University of Technology H99, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9214 5866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmabbott@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Abbott</name>
      <address>Swinburne University of Technology H99, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9214 5866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmabbott@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Abbott</name>
      <address>Swinburne University of Technology H99, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9214 5866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmabbott@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Abbott</name>
      <address>Swinburne University of Technology H99, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9214 5866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmabbott@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>