<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364930">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001016729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The characterisation and correlation of cardiovascular haemodynamics and endothelial function in preeclampsia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An observational study of pregnant women with or without preeclampsia or pre-existing hypertension, examining biomarkers of endothelial and placental function, endothelial function in large and small vessels and echocardiographic parameters during the third trimester and in the post-partum period. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1147-7532 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>preeclampsia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>hypertension in pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational study of cardiovascular function to be performed in the third trimester of pregnancy and 6 months post-partum period. Pregnant women with preeclampsia, pregant women with pre-existing hypertension and pregnant women without hypertension in preganancy will all be prospectively enrolled to this study.
Parameters to be measured include plasma and urine biomarkers of placental and endothelial function, functional measures of small and large vessel reactivity (using aplanation tanometry and laser doppler iontophoresis) and echocardiogaphical parameters of systolic and diastolic function.</interventions>
    <comparator>normotensive pregnant women.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in diastolic function as measured on echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in placental angiogenesis biomarkers (sFLt-1 and P-IPG) measured in maternal plasma samples taken in late preganacy and at 6 months post-partum. This is performed using a commercially available assay. Statistical analysis of the change in plasmsa concentrations of each biomarker over time and between the three groups will be performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in maternal endothelial biomarkers in plasma: hSCRP, ADMA, hydrogen sulfite. These are taken (by venesection) in late pregnancy and at 6 months post-partum. The samples will be analysed using comercially available assays or published methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in maternal vascular function (microvessels and large capacity vessels). These will be measured using applanation tanometry for large vessel capacitance, laser doppler iontophoresis for microvessel reactivity and function. These measurements will be performed in late pregnancy and repeated at 6 months post-partum. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in right heart structure and function as measured on 2D and 3D echocardiography performed in late pregnancy and at 6 months post-partum.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant women more then 32 weeks pregnant. They will be divided into three groups: Those diagnosed with preeclampsia as defined by the "international society for the study of hypertension in pregnancy" guidelines, those with pre-existing hypertension and those who are normotoensive on no antihypertensive medication.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. unable to give informed consent
2. pre-pregnancy cardiovascular disease or diabetes
3. chronic renal disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>1. comparisons between normotensive and hypertensive groups at the two times points will be made by 2 way ANOVA and Chi square testing.
2. correlations will be sought between the placental biomarkers, endothelial biomarkers, measures of vascular reactivity and echocardiographic parameters.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>8</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>27/03/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>110</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Modbury Hospital - Modbury</hospital>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>5092 - Modbury</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cardiology Unit, Lyell McEwin Hospital, Northern Adelaide Local Health Network</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Haydown Rd, Elizabeth Vale, SA 5112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lyell McEwin Hospital special purpose fund for cardiology research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Haydown Rd, Elizabeth Vale, SA 5112</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The incidence of preeclampsia is rising in Australia due to increasing numbers of pregnancies in women at high risk for this condition. Our understanding of the pathophysiology is still unclear and the clinical and pathalogical classifications are inconsistent. In particular, the inconsistency in classification makes the management and follow-up of patients with preeclampsia challenging. Various studies have measured haemodynamic, vascular physiology and biochemical markers individually , however studies correlating these measurements are few. This project will comprehensively characterise the cardiovascular haemodynamic and endothelial function changes that occur in preeclampsia. From this we will correlate these changs to the various clnical presentations of preeclampsia in an attempt to find a better way to classify and risk stratify this life threatening condition. The ultimate aim is to gain a better understanding of the pathophysiology of preeclampsia and translate this into better management strategies in the future.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (TQEH/LMH/MH) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Woodeville Rd,
Woodville South
SA 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Margaret Arstall</name>
      <address>Cardiology Unit
Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road,
Elizabeth Vale
SA
5112</address>
      <phone>+61881829439</phone>
      <fax>+61882820706</fax>
      <email>margaret.arstall@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>York Yann Chow</name>
      <address>Cardiology Unit
Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road,
Elizabeth Vale
SA
5112</address>
      <phone>+61881829439</phone>
      <fax>+61882820706</fax>
      <email>yychow@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Margeret Arstall</name>
      <address>Cardiology Unit
Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road,
Elizabeth Vale
SA
5112</address>
      <phone>+61881829439</phone>
      <fax>+61882820706</fax>
      <email>margeret.arstall@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>York Yann Chow</name>
      <address>Cardiology Unit
Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road,
Elizabeth Vale
SA
5112</address>
      <phone>+61881829439</phone>
      <fax>+61882820706</fax>
      <email>yychow@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>