<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362420">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000471886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does treatment initiated by a Continence Nurse help to improve bladder and bowel problems in people with Multiple Sclerosis?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised Controlled Trial to determine whether nurse-initiated management improves bladder function in people with Multiple Sclerosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1130-1257</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bladder dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of life related to degree of bother and impact on life</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will be screened with a newly developed continence screening tool.  This tool has been trialed as part of a pilot study, and will be refined further by trialing on 50 people with MS, before it is further refined and then re-trialed by two Neurologists and two MS Nurses on ten patients with MS.  The final version will then be drafted. 

The continence screening tool will be administered by the Continence Nurse for the RCT.  It is a one-page double-sided form which will take 5-10 minutes to complete.  A 5-point scale is used for all questions.  Urinary questions pertain to frequency, urgency, intemittency, straining, feeling of emptyness, use of catheter, urinary tract infection, incontinence, near-miss incontinence, fluid intake.  Bowel questions pertain to frequency, consistency using the Bristol Stool Scale, urgency, straining incomplete emptying, need to manually evacuate, faecal incontinence and near miss situations relating to faecal incontinence.  

The two quality of life questions include a four point scale relating to the degree to which bladder and bowel symptoms interfere with life, and a seven point scale relating to how the individual would feel if they had to spend the rest of their life with current level of bladder and bowel symptoms.  There are separate questions for each; a total of four questions.  

All participants will be screened with the continence-screening tool, and if symptomatic (determined by their continence-screen score), will be allocated to one of two study arms.  This is the screening visit.   

ARM 1 (Treatment Group): On the second visit, this group of MS participants will have a more thorough continence assessment and have a management plan outlined by the Continence Nurse.  Follow up will occur at 1, 3(by phone), 6 and 12 months following the initiation of continence intervention.  Intervention follows standard practice, based upon current best-practice guidelines.  This will also involve working closely with the patient's Neurologist and referral to a Medical Clinical Mentor and Continence Physician, as required.  Outcome measures include urinary symptoms and quality of life related to burden and impact.

ARM 2 (Control Group): This group of MS participants will be provided reference material in the form of pamphlets, articles and booklets provided and endorsed by the Continence Foundation of Australia which will be tailored to that individual's particular problems.  It is up to the individual's own discretion as to how they use this information.  This group will also continue to be managed by their regular health care team including their Neurologist, MS Nurse and General Practitioner (GP).  Participants in this arm will be reviewed 6 months after re-screening with the continence-screening tool.  Patients with persistent symptoms will be offered treatment as per ARM 1.</interventions>
    <comparator>ARM 1: Standard continence intervention which has been initiated by a Continence Nurse 

ARM 2: Package of information tailored to the participant's continence issues, plus standard care from the participant's health care team eg Neurologist, MS Nurse or GP</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bladder function symptom score.  Measuring the following symptoms for improvement: UTI, urinary urgency, urinary hesitancy, urinary intermittency, urinary straining, feeling of incomplete emptying and urinary incontinence.

A screening tool, to assess the above-mentioned symptoms, and determine a bladder function symptom score has been trialed and will be refined prior to commencement of randomised control trial. The tool has been based upon the American Urological Association (AUA) Symptom Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following intervention, measurement of bladder function will occur at 1, 3(by phone), 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life measures related to degree of bother and impact of urinary symptoms on life.  The Quality of Life question is part of the American Urological Association (AUA) Symptom Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following intervention, measurement will occur at 1,3,6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Confirmed diagnosis of Multiple Sclerosis.
Able to read English sufficiently to comprehend the study requirements and give informed consent.
Participants with MS attending the Box Hill Hospital MS outpatient clinic.
Willing to undergo serial continence evaluation over a period of 12 months
A score of 10 or more on the Bladder symptom score</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Less than 18 years of age.
No definitive diagnosis of Multiple Sclerosis.
Insufficient English literacy to understand the study information.
Unwilling to give consent to the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients attending the Eastern Health MS Service, Box Hill Hospital in Melbourne Vicoria, Outpatients Service each week will be asked if they would like to participate in the randomised controlled trial.  All patients who agree to be screened and are identified with a continence issue, using the continence screening tool, will be randomly allocated to to one of two arms.  

The following process will occur:
1. A randomisation administrator not involved in the trial and working at a different institution will generate a random sequence of numbers Group 1 and Group 2 using http://www.randomizer.org/form.htm
2. The Continence Nurse will screen all patients
3. The MS Nurse, who is not involved in the trial and who also attends the MS Outpatients Clinic where screening will occur, will allocate the screened patients to either arms of the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated process using http://randomizer.org/form.htm will be used to generate numbers 1 and 2 to correspond with the two treatment arms.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>ARM 1 will receive standard continence care, initiated by a Continence Nurse working in the Eastern HealthMS Service

ARM 2 will receive literature and resource information, including referral information.  They will also be provided standard care by their MS health care team.  At the end of 6 months they will be rescreened, and if they still have continence issues they will be offered care as per protocol in ARM 1</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Eastern Clinical Research Unit
Level 2
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill, VIC. 3128</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Eastern Clinical Research Unit, Eastern Health MS Service is part of the Monash University, located at the Box Hill Hospital Campus of Eastern Health.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 5 Arnold Street 
Box Hill, Vic., 3128</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Eastern Health Service, Box Hill Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nelson Road
Box Hill, VIC., 3128</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bladder dysfunction in people with Multiple Sclerosis is very common, very distressing and can affect the individuals quality of life in many ways.  Although it is strongly recommended that routine, targeted continence assessment be undertaken, this is poorly done by health professionals and inadequately discussed by patients.  By appropriate screening and targeted continence treatment, initiated by a Continence Nurse, it is hoped that symptoms and quality of life will improve.  This will be undertaken by comparing two groups of patients with identifiable continence problems, using a simple one page, double sided continence-screening tool, administered by the Continence Nurse.  Participants in Group 1 will be offered assessment and management in line with standard continence practice by the Continence Nurse.  Follow up will occur at 1, 3(by phone), 6 and 12 months.  Participants in Group 2 will be offered standard care by the patients Health Care Team and tailored information endorsed by the Continence Foundation of Australia.   The patients in Group 2 will subsequently be reviewed by the Continence Nurse following 6 months, and offered treatment as per the patients in Group 1, if symptoms persist.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill, VIC., 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/04/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc Prof Helmut Butzkueven</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology,
Level 4
Royal Melbourne Hospital, city Campus
Grattan Street
Parkville, VIC., 3050</address>
      <phone>+61414881494</phone>
      <fax>+61398999137</fax>
      <email>butz@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Louise Kurczycki</name>
      <address>Level 2
5 Arnold Street
Box Hill, VIC., 3128</address>
      <phone>+61429205127</phone>
      <fax>+61398999137</fax>
      <email>louise.kurczycki@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>