<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362388">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000438853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes of intraocular pressure after photorefractive keratectomy; a comparison between Goldmann applanation tonometry and dynamic contour tonometry</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective  clinical trial to compare changes of intraocular pressure after photorefractive keratectomy obtained by Goldmann applanation tonometry and dynamic contour tonometry</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>myopia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>myopic astigmatism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1-Photorefractive keratectomy: All the participants underwent this operation using the Planoscan method of the Technolas 217z laser platform (Bausch &amp; Lomb, USA) with an optical zone diameter of 6.00 mm, repetition rate of 50 Hz and a flat top-beam profile with spot size of 2.00 mm. After prep and drep (i.e. disinfecting the eyelids and periocular area for 1 minute with povidoneiodine 10% solution, and having the eyes washed out with 20 mL of a balanced salt solution), the epithelium was removed with a hockey knife and photoablation performed. 
2-Goldmann applanation tonometry: The procedure was performed according to the guidelines of the Eye Care Technology Forum. The tear film was stained by placing paper fluorescein strips in the lower conjunctival fornix. Goldmann applanation tonometer (AT 900, HS Inc., USA) was mounted on a slit lamp (YJ-5Z, OcuHealth Plus Inc, New York, USA) and its tonometer was calibrated according to the manufactures instructions. The tonometer tip was brought into contact with the corneal surface and the intraocular pressure was documented after applanating the corneal surface and adjusting knob of the tonometer. Measurements were repeated 3 times at 30 second intervals and the readings averaged. Before each reading, the measuring drum was reset to approximately 2 mm Hg. In the case of fluctuation of IOP during the cardiac pulse cycle, it was measured in the middle of the pulsation amplitude. 
3-Dynamic contour tonometry: Dynamic contour tonometer (Pascal, Swiss Micro Technology, Switzerland) was mounted on the same slit-lamp and IOP measurement was accomplished according to the manufactures guidelines. The tonometer tip of this device, similar to that of the GAT, contacts the corneal surface. However, its correct positioning is indicated by an audible signal that changes in pitch with changes in the pressure detected.  IOP measurement with DCT was repeated if the quality score was greater than 2. 
In all participants, Goldmann applanation tonometry was performed 5 minutes after Dynamic contour tonometry on the same day.</interventions>
    <comparator>active control
standard treatment including photorefractive keratectomy as described before. In eyes in which the ablation depth was greater than 50 micro m, mitomycin-C 0.02% (0.2 mg/mL) was applied for up to 25 seconds. Then the eyes were irrigated with 50 mL of a balanced salt solution and bandage contact lenses were fitted. Postoperatively, ciprofloxacin 0.3% eye drop (Ciplox, Cipla, Mumbai, India) and betamethasone 0.1% eye drop (CIBA VISION, USA) were administered 3 times/day until complete corneal reepithelialization was ensured. Betamethasone 0.1% eye drops were administered 4 times/day for 1 month and then tapered over the next month.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>intraocular pressure by Goldmann applanation tonometry and dynamic contour tonometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and 6 months after operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>central corneal thickness by ultrasonic pachymetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and 6 months after operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>candidates for bilateral PRK to correct myopia or myopic astigmatism  without any history of ocular trauma/surgery or corneal disease</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>history of ocular trauma/surgery or corneal disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>113</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state>Tehran</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Afshin Lotfi Sedigh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sheshkelan Ave., Nikookari Hospital, Tabriz, PO BOX:45395-51546</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Afshin Lotfi Sedigh</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sheshkelan Ave., Nikookari Hospital, Tabriz, PO BOX:45395-51546</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hassan Hashemi</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Valiasr Ave., Zafar, Esfandiar Bulvar, Noor Ophthalmology Research Center, Tehran, Iran, PO Box: 19395-3475</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main objective of this prospective study was to compare intraocular oressure changes before and at 6 months after photorefractive keratectomy (PRK) obtained by Goldmann applanation tonometry and dynamic contour tonometryin patients with myopia or myopic astigmatism in relation to changes of central corneal thickness, as well as to suggest a correcting formula, if applicable.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rohollah F Fouladi</name>
      <address>Golgasht Ave., University of Medical Sciences, Medical Faculty, Tabriz, PO BOX: 51655-118</address>
      <phone>+989144122542</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>medicorelax@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rohollah F Fouladi</name>
      <address>Golgasht Ave., University of Medical Sciences, Medical Faculty, Tabriz, PO BOX: 51655-118</address>
      <phone>+989144122542</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>medicorelax@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Afshin Lotfi Sedigh</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>