<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="334987">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000061033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of an internet-based treatment for comorbidity of alcohol disorders and depressive mood.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluate the efficacy of an internet-based psychological program for people who are concurrently depressed and drinking alcohol at harmful levels.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1113-1485</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>alcohol misuse</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>brief intervention and therapist support - 1 module motivation enhancement plus an additional 5 modules of integrated treatment with email support from therapist.
a) all modules are internet based
b) each module can be done at the client's own pace. they could be completed in one sitting (approximately an hour each) but it is recommended that the client pace themselves and complete the modules on a weekly basis.
c) the overall length of the intervention is 3 months because we ask people to check in weekly for 3 months to complete alcohol use charts and mood monitoring while they continue to implement changes instigated by the programs
d) general topics in the 5 modules are 1) motivation for change and making plans to change 2) mindfullness and activity planning 3) cravings and dealing with risky situations 4) problem-solving and cognitive-behavioural therapy (CBT) 5) building relationships and conflict resolution</interventions>
    <comparator>There are a total of 3 comparison treatment arms in this study: 1) brief intervention only (1 module motivation enhancement)
2) brief intervention + self guided modules (1 module motivation enhancement + 5 modules of self-guided integrated treatment)
3) brief intervention + therapist support.
group 1 (brief intervention) is an online module that could be completed in one sitting of approximately one hour, but it can be done at whatever pace the client feels comfortable with.
group 2 (BI + 5 modules) again could be completed in one sitting taking approximately one hour per module, but it is recommended that the modules are attempted on a weekly basis. both groups are given up to 3 months to complete the intervention while also completing weekly mood monitoring and alcohol use questionnaires.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>alcohol use - measured by Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) + patient report on past month of alcohol use</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>depressed mood - measured by Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS) and Hamiliton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to predict therapeutic alliance, satisfaction, number of treatment modules accessed and number of tools completed from self-guided versus therapist-support, treatment response in the first month and baseline demographic and disorder-related variables. Satisfaction and treatment response will be assessed via the Working Alliance Inventory (Short Form) and self-report from 1-100 "How useful did you find this program?"</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to test whether alcohol and depression outcomes from internet treatment are moderated by therapeutic alliance, treatment expectancy, disorder independence, number of modules accessed or tools completed or gender. Treatment expectancy will be measured on a scale of 1-100 in response to questions such as "How likely do you think it is that this treatment will help you reduce your drinking?" Disorder independence will look at which of the disorders became apparent first, e.g., did the depression lead to substance abuse or vice versa?</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to examine the relative unit cost of the treatments by comparing outgoing costs for each of the treatment arms (e.g., therapist time etc)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) reported weekly alcohol consumption of more than 14 units/week over the last month
2) score more than 8 on the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test
3) score at least 14 on the Depression scale of the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (e.g., 'moderate' depression)
4) sufficient english to complete treatments and assessments without translation
5) able and willing to access internet/email/text messages</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) use of injectable drugs in the previous month
2) daily use of an illicit substance
3) history of psychosis lasting more than 2 days
4) diagnosis of bipolar disorder
5) acutely suicidal
6) highly dependent on alcohol</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>participants will view www.ontrack.org.au in response to a referral or advertising and will be guided to complete some screening questionnaires online. after completing the quizzes participants receive feedback and, if appropriate, referral to the alcohol and depression program, where they register to receive a screening call. During the call they are given information about the research. If they're interested in participating the screening information sheet is read over the phone and the participant provides verbal consent for screening. If they meet screening eligibility requirements they are sent an email link that takes them to the consent form and online assessment questionnaires. Following this they receive a baseline assessment phone call. Once all baseline assessments are completed they are randomly allocated to one of the three treatment groups and provided with a username and password to access the online program. Allocations are computer generated and occur automatically once the person's access is activated.  The assessor has no way of controlling or predicting assignment.</concealment>
    <sequence>random permutations of 6 and 9 - computersised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>60 Musk Ave, 
Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra, ACT, 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>e-Therapy Unit, Swinburne University of Technology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study aims to evaluate the efficacy of an internet based psychological program for people who are concurrently depressed and drinking alcohol at harmful levels. This study is a randomised controlled trial with 3 comparison treatment, each with 200 participants who will be followed up for 12 months.

The 3 treatments to be compared are:
1) brief intervention (BI) (1 module of motivation enhancement)
2) BI + self-guided modules (SG) (1 module of motivation enhancement + 5 modules of self-guided integrated treatment
3) BI + therapist-support (TS) (1 module of motivation enhancement + 5 modules of integrated treatment with email support from a therapist)

Primary predictions are that 1) TS and SG interventions will have superior alcohol and depression outcomes at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months compared with BI and 2) TS will elicit greater client satisfaction and completion rate than SG, but SG will have similar treatment outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ontrack.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2434, Brisbane QLD 4000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/05/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00171</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof David Kavanagh</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, Queensland University of Technology, GPO Box 2434, Brisbane QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3138 6143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.kavanagh@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennifer Connolly</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, Queensland University of Technology, GPO Box 2434, Brisbane QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3138 0048</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.connolly@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Danielle Graber</name>
      <address>e-Therapy Centre
Faculty of Life and Social Sciences
Swinburne University 
PO Box 218
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 5867</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dgraber@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>