<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368966">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000866505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Do artificial sweeteners influence intestinal glucose absorption in humans?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial to determine whether diet supplementation with non-caloric sweeteners alters the rate of intestinal glucose absorption in healthy individuals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Royal Adelaide Hospital Protocol Number: 150605</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Healthy subjects will be screened then undergo 2 study day visits in a randomised, double-blinded manner. Study day 1 will occur prior to diet supplementation, with study day 2 immediately following 2 weeks of diet supplementation with placebo capsules or capsules containing a combination of non-caloric sweeteners (sucralose, 92 mg + acesulfame K, 52 mg).  Single capsules will be consumed immediately prior to meals, three times daily. Adherence to the intervention will be monitored by capsule return.

On each study day, fasted unsedated subjects will have an intravenous cannula inserted into a forearm vein in one arm for blood sampling and a small diameter (5.3 mm) video endoscope placed in position in the second part of the duodenum via an anaesthetised nostril. Five mucosal biopsies will be collected via endoscope forceps, then an intraduodenal glucose infusion commenced for 30 min via the endoscope channel (30 g glucose, together with 3 g of the non-metabolisable glucose analogue 3-O-methy-glucose (3-OMG) dissolved in water to a total volume of 150 mL, infused at 5 mL/min; 4 kcal/min). An additional 5 biopsies will be collected post-infusion; bloods will be collected regularly over 2 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo capsules (hydroxypropyl methylcellulose)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportional differences in incremental area under the curve, peak and/or time-to-peak for serum 3-OMG levels (absorption) for sweetener vs. placebo supplementation during intraduodenal glucose infusion (composite outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = -10, 0 (commencement of intraduodenal glucose infusion), 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 90 and 120 min</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportional differences in incremental area under the curve, peak and/or time-to-peak for plasma incretins for sweetener vs. placebo supplementation during intraduodenal glucose infusion (composite outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = -10, 0 (commencement of intraduodenal glucose infusion), 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 90 and 120 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in baseline or post-infusion expression of transcript (RNA) and/or protein for glucose sensing and transport/uptake pathway molecules in mucosal biopsies (composite outcome)

Targets assessed include sweet taste receptors (T1R2, T1R3), G-protein (alpha-gustducin), ion channels (Kir6.2, TRPM5) and glucose transporters (SGLT-1, GLUT2).</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = -2 (immediately prior to commencement of intraduodenal glucose infusion) and 30 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identification of glucose sensing, signalling and transport/uptake pathway molecules in functionally activated (glucose-responsive) cells within mucosal biopsies (composite outcome)

Targets assessed include sweet taste receptors (T1R2, T1R3), G-protein (alpha-gustducin), ion channels (Kir6.2, TRPM5), glucose transporters (SGLT-1, GLUT2) and cell markers (5-HT, GLP-1, GIP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = 30 min, where T=0 is the start of glucose infusion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Non-diabetic, healthy volunteers matched as closely as possible for sex and body mass index; Body mass index 20-30 kg/m2; HbA1c less than or equal to 7.0%</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant illness including impairment to cardiovascular or respiratory function that would limit a subjects activity and therefore would represent a risk to undertaking endoscopy safely (American Society of Anaesthesiologists Grade 3 or more); History of gastrointestinal disease, including significant upper gastrointestinal symptoms (assessed by a validated gastrointestinal symptom questionnaire), pancreatitis, or previous gastrointestinal surgery (other than uncomplicated appendectomy or cholecystectomy); Diffuse mucosal disease involving the upper gastrointestinal tract, including Crohns disease, coeliac disease, or ischaemic changes, evident either macroscopically or on histopathological examination of mucosal biopsies; Haemoglobin below the lower limit of the normal range (ie. below 135g/L for men and 115g/L for women), and ferritin below the lower limit of normal (below 20ng/mL for women and 30ng/mL for men); Impaired renal or liver function (as assessed by calculated creatinine clearance &lt; 90 mL/min or abnormal liver function tests, &gt; 2 times upper limit of normal); Body mass index &gt; 30 kg/m2 or &lt; 20 kg/m2; Donation of blood within the previous 3 months; Participation in any other research studies within the previous 3 months; Subjects requiring the use of anticoagulant drugs, antiplatelet agents or NSAIDS; Subjects with known coagulopathy; Presence of mucosal abnormalities at endoscopy; Subjects requiring medication that may influence gastrointestinal function; Evidence of drug abuse, consumption of more than 20 g alcohol or 10 cigarettes per day; Female patients not using appropriate contraceptive method (ie oral contraceptive pill, diaphragm, DepoProvera hormonal contraceptive injection, intrauterine device (IUD), Norplant method); Vegetarian, lactation or pregnancy (verified by urine testing in women of reproductive age; in these subjects, study will be completed during the follicular phase of the menstrual cycle); habitual consumption of &gt;500 mL of artificially sweetened drink, or food equivalent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be screened for medical and diet history, medications and lifestyle as well as assessed for blood haemoglobin, ferritin, HbA1c, renal and liver function. Study participants will provide written, informed consent and will be randomised and blinded to placebo or sweetener capsules. Study capsules will be identical in size, colour and weight.

Allocation concealment by schedule will be undertaken and held by pharmacy staff of the Royal Adelaide Hospital; allocation will be blind to staff and subjects involved in this project.

</concealment>
    <sequence>computer-generated random number table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample sizes are calculated for alpha=0.05 and beta=0.2 from a priori data on the primary outcome measures. The effect size for glucose absorption, the most variable outcome, is 1.052; subject dropouts are incorporated at 15%. All variables will be assessed using ANOVA, with treatment and time factors. Post hoc tests, adjusted for multiple comparisons, will be performed for significant effects. Relationships between transcript expression and other factors will be compared using Pearson correlation coefficient; area-under-the-curve data will be compared using 2-tailed paired Students t-tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite increasing use of non-caloric sweeteners in western diets, it is not known whether habitual high intake alters glucose absorption in healthy subjects. This is critical knowledge, as an increased risk of developing type 2 diabetes may occur in regular, heavy consumers of non-caloric sweeteners, potentially due to increased uptake of glucose in the intestine. The outcome of this diet supplementation study will, accordingly, be of enormous public health interest as it determines whether intestinal sensors for sugars and artificial sweeteners (intestinal sweet taste receptors) set absorptive capacity in humans.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/RAH/223, Protocol 150605</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>