<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347597">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001092987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of EMA401 and biomarkers in the treatment of pain due to nerve damage following chemotherapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2 open label biomarker study of angiotensin II type 2 receptor antagonist EMA401 for the treatment of pain in patients with chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Protocol number EMA401-005</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chemotherapy induced peripheral neuropathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>EMA401 100mg orally twice a day for 28 days</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the efficacy of EMA401 100 mg orally twice daily for 28 days, in reducing spontaneous neuropathic pain, from baseline to Week 4 of treatment, in patients with chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy.

This will be assessed using patient pain scores (on a scale of 0 to 10, where 0 = no pain and 10 = pain as bad as you can imagine).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 28 days treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the efficacy of EMA401 100 mg orally twice daily for 28 days in restoring nerve fibre phenotype in skin punch biopsies.

This will be assessed by examing changes in biomarkers on slides taken from biopsy samples pre and post treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 28 days treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the efficacy of EMA401 100 mg orally twice daily for 28 days in reducing evoked pain in patients with chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy.

This will be assessed by change in area of evoked pain from using brush, monofilaments, pin prick, thermal thresholds, and contact heat evoked potentials (CHEPS), patient pain scores, patient ratings of change, and the Short Form - McGill Pain Questionnaire (SF-MPQ-2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 28 days treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of EMA401 100 mg orally twice daily for 28 days in patients with chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy.

This will be assessed by incidence and severity of adverse events, and changes and findings in laboratory parameters, physical and neurological examinations, vital signs, and ECG.  All adverse events that occur will be measured by recording details of the event including description, start and stop dates, severity, seriousness, and relationship to study drug</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 28 days treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to give voluntary written informed consent to participate in the study.

18 to 80 years old inclusive.

Previously received taxane and/or platinum based chemotherapy for any type of cancer and are not expected to receive further chemotherapy for the study duration.

Signs and symptoms of sensory peripheral neuropathy of the lower limbs which have been clinically stable for at least 8 weeks prior to Screening.

History of spontaneous pain in the lower limbs for at least 8 weeks prior to Screening.

Moderate to severe spontaneous neuropathic pain in the lower limbs.

Female of non-child-bearing potential, or if of child-bearing potential, must have used adequate contraceptive precautions for 30 days prior to Screening, and must agree to use two approved methods of contraception for the duration of the study and for one month after administration of the last dose of study medication
OR
Are male and agree to use two approved methods of contraception for the duration of the study and until one month after administration of the last dose of the study medication.

Able to read and understand English.

Have a telephone.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant or breast-feeding.

Do not and cannot comply with the protocol concomitant medication restrictions.

Participated in an investigational medical product study within the past 3 months prior to Day 1.

Exposure to more than 3 new chemical entities within 12 months prior to Day 1.

Previously received EMA401.

Known to be allergic to EMA401 or any of the excipients.

History or evidence of any other clinical neuropathy.

Any other pain condition or injury that may confound the self-evaluation of pain due to peripheral neuropathy.

History of clinically significant cardiac arrhythmias or the presence of clinically significant abnormalities on electrocardiogram (ECG) at screening.

Resting supine blood pressure &lt; 165/95mmHg.

Resting pulse rate &gt;100 or &lt;50 beats per minute (bpm) on two consecutive measurements at least 10 minutes apart.	
Calculated creatinine clearance (using Cockroft and Gault formula) of less than 50 mL/min at Screening.

Serum aspartate transaminase (AST), gamma glutamyl transaminase (GGT) or alanine transaminase (ALT) levels greater than 3.0 x the upper limit of normal or have total bilirubin concentrations greater than 2.0 x the upper limit of normal at Screening.

History of or current hepatitis B (HBV), hepatitis C (HCV) or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection.

Other than the condition under study, have a history of or current active medical condition including allergic, skin, cardiovascular, psychiatric disease, drug or alcohol abuse, or laboratory finding, that in the opinion of the investigator precludes participation in the study, or may interfere with the study objectives / results.

Pacemaker or implanted brain or cord stimulators.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/09/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>46</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Spinifex Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Corporate One, Suite G5
84 Hotham St
Preston, VIC, 3072
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Spinifex Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Corporate One, Suite G5
84 Hotham St
Preston, VIC, 3072
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Peripheral neuropathy is caused by damage to nerves.  Current therapy needs to be improved as a significant proportion of neuropathic pain patients dont respond to current therapy and these treatments have dose-limiting side effects.

EMA401 is an angiotensin II type 2 (AT2) receptor antagonist, a class of molecules that offers an innovative approach to the treatment of neuropathic pain. EMA401 has shown efficacy in a number of relevant models and good human safety and pharmacokinetics in Phase 1 studies. 

This study will look at whether EMA401 reduces pain in patients who have peripheral neuropathy caused by cancer chemotherapy drugs, whether it has an effect on biomarkers of pain, and whether it is well tolerated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Not applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>London Bridge Committee of the National Research Ethics Service, National Research Authority, National Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Committee (REC) Centre Charing Cross, Room 12, 4th Floor West, Charing Cross Hospital, London W6 8RF.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11/LO/2042</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>United Kingdom</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tom McCarthy</name>
      <address>Corporate One, Suite G5
84 Hotham St
Preston, VIC, 3072
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9863 6820</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tom.mccarthy@spinifexpharma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tom McCarthy</name>
      <address>Corporate One, Suite G5
84 Hotham St
Preston, VIC, 3072
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9863 6820</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tom.mccarthy@spinifexpharma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Praveen Anand</name>
      <address>Hammersmith Hospital
Peripheral Neuropathy Unit
Du Cane Rd
London
W12 0NN
United Kingdom</address>
      <phone>+44 (0)20 3313 3319</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.anand@imperial.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>