<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82871">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000301369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Metabolic and Neurobiological changes after Continuous Positive Airway Pressure treatment for Obstructive Sleep Apnea</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Metabolic and Neurobiological changes after Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) treatment for Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MANPAP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Blinded Continuous Positive Airway Pressure for 12 weeks followed by open-label CPAP treatment for 12 weeks. 
The subjects will undergo a 3 night home-titration using an auto-titrating machine. The machine will then be set to the 90th percentile on a fixed pressure for the remainder of the study. We are using an identical Sham machine. A trained CPAP technologist who had been involved in other similar sham-controlled trials is responsible for the allocation of the CPAP machines for this and all other studies. Only this person has access to the sham machines, which she stores separately from the effective CPAP machines. This person will have no direct contact with the subjects.
This is a 24 week study. For the first 12 weeks of the study, Week 0 to Week 12, the subject is randomised to use either therapeutic CPAP or sham CPAP every night for the entire 12 weeks. This first 12 weeks is blinded.
From Week 12 to Week 24 every subject is changed to receive open-label therapeutic CPAP every night for the entire 12 weeks. They will return the blinded machine they used from Week 0 to Week 12 and will receive a new therapeutic machine.</interventions>
    <comparator>Sham Continuous Positive Airway Pressure
The technical details are propriety and are therefore not available to us. However, this device has been used worldwide as a state of the art sham device and we are currently using this device in a currently approved protocol. In brief, the sham device does not deliver effective pressure to the patient through two mechanisms:
·   An internal release valve (inside the machine, so it cannot be detected by the casual observer) releases pressure and hence therapeutic pressure is not delivered to the patient 
·   A swivel is attached to the CPAP mask, which has an opening through which air escapes which again prevents effective pressure being delivered to the patient.
The pressure delivered by the sham device is actually slightly higher than atmospheric pressure (ie 0.5 cm H2O).
The subjects are randomised to either therapeutic or sham CPAP in the first 12 weeks (Week 0 to Week 12). No matter what machine they are assigned to (they will not be aware as is blinded) they will use the machine every night while sleeping for the entire 12 weeks (Week 0 to Week 12). 
At week 12 each subject will return the blinded machine (either sham or therapeutic). Everyone will receive a open-label therapeutic CPAP machine which they will use every night for the entire next 12 weeks (Week12 to Week24)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Abdominal Visceral Fat
Single slice 3D Computerised Tomography (CT) scan of the abdomen. The single slice is taken in relation to a bony landmark (eg T12/L1 or L4/L5 in the axial plane) and hence is reproducible serially.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after Randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Total Body Fat and Muscle Mass
- Dexa scan and bioimpedence</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Insulin Sensitivity
- Insulin sensitivity will be assessed by modified minimal model (MINMOD) analysis of multiple measurements of c-peptide (at 0, 10, 20, 30, 60, 90 and 120 after a 75g oral glucose load)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Arterial Stiffness and Central Blood Pressure
- Peripheral and central blood pressure will be assessed by non-invasive tonometry with a brachial sphymomanometer. This is a measurement of arterial stiffness using pulse wave analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 and 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Physical Activity
- Physical activity and will be assessed by questionnaire (IPAQ) and objective assessment (Actigraphy). The subject will complete a diary containing questions relating to sleep, such as bed time and time of awakening, while undertaking Actigraphy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 and 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Blood Hormones</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 and 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in sleep and breathing parameters
- Sleep will measured by the gold standard Polysomnograph which requires the attachment of leads to the subject in order to measure chest and abdominal movement, airflow at the mouth and lips, blood oxygen level, muscle tone, eye movements, heart rate and electrical activity in the brain. The subject will be required to sleep with these leads attached. The study is scored using standard criteria.
 
In addition, a functional assessment of the effects of sleepiness will be used. These are validated questionnaires (FOSQ) which assess the impact of sleepiness on multiple activities of daily living (36). The Epworth Sleepiness Scale and assessment of functional outcomes of sleep and neurocognitive function will also be assessed using a 60 minute computer program performed in conjunction with the sleep study. Other measures of sleep at each visit are validated questionnaires and tests (Functional Outcomes of Sleep, Sleepiness scales, driving simulation test).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 and 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in vascular reactivity and repair (as measure by peripheral arterial tonometry (PAT) and endothelial progenitor cell counts)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Bone Turnover Markers (Osteocalcin, CTX, P1NP, Vitmain D and PTH) and Renal Function (urinary albumin)  (blood and urine)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 and 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Erectile Dysfunction as measured by the modified International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF) and an erectile function survey (EFS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 and 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in abdominal subcutaneous fat Single slice 3D Computerised Tomography (CT) scan of the abdomen. The single slice is taken in relation to a bony landmark (eg T12/L1 or L4/L5 in the axial plane) and hence is reproducible serially.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Anthropometry measurements (weight, height and waist, neck, hip, mid-arm and mid-thigh circumferences)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 and 12 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>TERTIARY OUTCOME: All the above measured outcomes during the open-label CPAP period (12-24 weeks after randomisation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 24 weeks after randomisation (if collected only at 12 weeks)
at 18 and 24 weeks (if collected at 6 and 12 weeks)
except for vascular reactivity and repair which were not collected during the open-label period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Males aged 18 years or above. 
2. Moderate to severe obstructive sleep apnea with respiratory disturbance Index (RDI) =20/hr and inclusive of =3% desaturation (RDI &gt;=20 and ODI &gt;=15)
3. Written informed consent
4. Good general health as defined as men who are community dwelling, with no significant uncontrolled medical problems who are independent in activities of daily living.
5. Medical history and physical examination indicating no clinical evidence for significant and uncontrolled cardiovascular (ischemic, hypertension), diabetes, renal, liver, prostate or any other disease.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Severe OSA (minimum oxygen saturation &lt; 65% or RDI &gt; 80)  requiring immediate treatment due to severity or increased associated risk (eg Transport worker)
2. Psychiatric disorders or drug abuse unless well controlled
3. Chronic medical conditions likely to interfere with or influence study treatment or safety unless well controlled
4. Contradictions to CPAP therapy 
5. Any other condition likely, in the judgment of the investigator, that makes the patient unable to complete safely, or otherwise unsuitable for the study
6. Shift workers</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After written consent patients will be enrolled in a randomised order sham-controlled crossover double blind study. At the end of the baseline visit patients will be randomly assigned, by equal chance, to either CPAP or Sham-CPAP (1:1 basis) for 12 weeks. All patients will then receive 12-weeks open-label therapeutic CPAP.
A separate co-ordinator will be responsible for the allocation of machines and will have no direct contact with the subjects. The sham devices are identical in appearance to commercially available therapeutic CPAP equipment which will ensure blinding.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney South West Area Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>431 Glebe Point Rd Glebe</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to investigate nasal Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) therapys efficacy to improve important intermediate markers of cardio-metabolic health (visceral fat, insulin sensitivity, central blood pressure, arterial stiffness).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Services (SSWAHS) Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Development Office
Level 8, Building 14
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>X08-0043</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Peter Liu</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research, PO Box M77, Missenden Rd, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0459</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>pliu@mail.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Camilla Hoyos</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research, PO Box M77, Missenden Rd, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0449</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>camillah@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Camilla Hoyos</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research, PO Box M77, Missenden Rd, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0449</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>camillah@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>