<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83065">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/08/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000462381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective randomised cross-over trial of regional citrate with heparin for anticoagulation and additional albumin prime in continuous venovenous haemofiltration in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Paediatric Haemofiltration priming and anticoagulation methods - does additional heparinsed albumin priming, citrate or heparin anticoagulation produce the longest circuit lifetimes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute renal failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The randomised cross over trial will aim to determine if additional priming of a haemofilter circuit with 5 u/ml heparinised 4% albumin increases circuit life (compared to only 5 u/ml heparinised saline).  This additional priming will be performed before the circuit is connected to the patient.
The study will also determine if there is a difference between regional citrate and global heparinised anticoagulation on circuit life.  The dose of citrate (in the form of ADC-A) will be titrated with a calcium chloride infusion to maintain circuit calciums of less than 0.3 mmol/L and a patient calcium of 1.0-1.3 mmol/L.
Upon recruitment all participants will be randomly assigned to one of 8 sequences of varying anticoagulation and priming methods as recommended for a four period crossover design with 2 factorial treatments.  Their first 4 circuits will consist of two heparin and two citrate circuits, one of each will be primed with heparinised saline and the other with an additional heparinised albumin prime, with the order of the treatments determined by their pre-assigned randomised sequence.
As hemofiltration is necessary to maintain these patients there will be no intentional "wash out" period as with holding treatment may be detrimental to the patient.
Each circuit will run until TMP (Transmembrane Pressure) reaches 280mmHg, treatment needs to be interrupted for longer than two hours or a significant adverse event occured.  The participant will be in the trial for a maximum of eight circuits.</interventions>
    <comparator>Each participant is their own control</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of the trial is haemofilter circuit duration, a TMP (Transmembrane Pressure) of 280mmHg determines end of circuit life. The data will be analysed using Kaplan-Meier plots, stratified log rank test and Cox proportional hazard regression of time to circuit failure, censoring circuits that are stopped for other reasons at the time of cessation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A TMP (Transmembrane Pressure) of 280mmHg determines end of circuit life, circuits ceased for other reasons will be sensored</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes to be analysed will be adverse events, such as excessive bleeding (assessed by medical and nursing staff by the bedside), thrombocytopenia, metabolic acidosis and hypocalcaemia (assessed by regular blood tests) using x2 tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be assessed as they occur and at a quarterly review (depending on numbers) for the duration of the trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any patient requiring Continuous Veno-venus Haemofiltration (CVVH) in the unit will be eligible for the trial.  Parental consent will be obtained before the patient is recruited.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with liver failure defined for the purpose of this trial as INR (international normalized ratio) &gt;3 despite clotting factor replacement (these patients often have the problems of metabolizing heparin and citrate and more severe coagulopathy) or known sensitivity to heparin (i.e. heparin-induced thrombocytopenia) will be excluded from the trial. Patients with significant risk of bleeding (those with intra cranial, cerebral or pulmonary haemorrhage or stroke)  will also be excluded, however, coagulopathic or thrombocytopenic patients without significant bleeding will be included.
If parental consent cannot be obtained or is not given the child will not participate in the trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Upon recruitment all participants will be randomly assigned to one of 8 sequences of varying anticoagulation and priming methods as recommended for a four period crossover design with 2 factorial treatments.  
Before the trial opaque randomisation envelopes will be created and drawn as each patient is recruited.</concealment>
    <sequence>The sequence generation will use a simple randomisation using a randomisation table generated by a computer program.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Childrens' Hospital Mebourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Childrens' Hospital Mebourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The trial aims to determine if heparin and citrate anticoagulation in venovenous haemofitration provide equivalent circuit lifespan in paediatrics.  It also aims to determine if additional albumin priming effects circuit lifespan.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Childrens' Hospital Mebourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>27108A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Rosemary McRae</name>
      <address>Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9345 5218</phone>
      <fax>+613 9345 6840</fax>
      <email>rosemary.mcrae@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Rosemary McRae</name>
      <address>Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9345 5218</phone>
      <fax>+613 9345 6840</fax>
      <email>rosemary.mcrae@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rosemary McRae</name>
      <address>Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9345 5218</phone>
      <fax>+613 9345 6840</fax>
      <email>rosemary.mcrae@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rosemary McRae</name>
      <address>50 Flemington Rd 
Parkville 3052 VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 5218</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rosemary.mcrae@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>