<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347515">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001028998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of the suboccipital muscle inhibition technique in craniocervical posture and greater occipital nerve mechanosensitivity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Immediate effects of the suboccipital muscle inhibition technique in craniocervical posture and greater occipital nerve mechanosensitivity in subjects with a history of orthodontia use: a randomized trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Forward head posture</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nerve Mechanosensitivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Suboccipital muscle inhibition technique (SMI technique)

With the patient supine, the therapist sits at the head of the table and places the palms of her hands under the subject's head, her fingers contacting the occipital condyles.  Then, the therapist locates with the middle and ring fingers of both hands the space between the occipital condyles and the spinal process of the second cervical vertebra.  Then, with the metacarpophalangeal joints in 90degrees flexion, she rests the base of the skull on her hands and exerts a constant, but not painful, pressure ventrally, maintaining the index, middle, and ring fingers of both hands extended and together.  A very slight traction can be added cranially to decongest the suboccipital zone.  During the SMI technique, the subject is asked to keep his eyes closed to avoid eye movements affecting the suboccipital muscle tone. 

We set an intervention time of four minutes. The intervention procedure will be performed only once in order to assess the immediate effects of the technique</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo manouvre consisted in the therapist placing her hands under the patient's skull with the finger tips in contact with the occipital base for four minutes, without any kind of pressure or therapeutic intention.  The aim was to provide a manual stimulus as similar as possible to the suboccipital muscle inhibition technique. The subject will be asked to keep his eyes closed as in the intervention techique.

The intervention time for the placebo technique is four minutes and it will be performed only once.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>IMPROVEMENT OF CRANIOVERTEBRAL ANGLE IN AT LEAST 10%

The craniovertebral angle (CVA) is measured to be that between a horizontal line that crosses the body of the seventh cervical vertebra (C7) and the line from the tragus of the ear to the spinal apophysis of C7.  Two lateral photographs are taken of the subject seated and standing still. For the first photograph, the subjects are asked to sit with their arms on their legs, and to rest their back and buttocks on the back of the chair, with both feet on the ground.  The examiner instructs them to fix their gaze on an imaginary point on the wall directly in front.  For the second photograph, the subjects stand still in a posture as natural as possible, with arms resting along the body, and directing their gaze as in the previous case.</outcome>
      <timepoint>AFTER INTERVENTION</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DECREASE IN GREATER OCCIPITAL NERVE MECHANOSENSITIVITY

Measurements will be made with a Model FPX 25 digital algometer (Wagner Instruments Greenwich, CT), using a 1cm2 area contact head, and applying a pressure gradient of approximately 1kg/cm2/s.  For the palpation of the Greater Occipital nerve, we will follow the indications described by Loukas et al. and Mosser et al. locating it laterally with a finger, and approximately one finger's length caudally from the external occipital crest.  The reference points on both sides of the head will be labelled with a marker, and three measurements will be made at each one with a resting period of 30 seconds between each measurement.  All the subjects are instructed identically: "Let me know when the sensation of pressure becomes uncomfortable or painful".</outcome>
      <timepoint>AFTER INTERVENTION</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) older than 18 years old
(ii) a history of having used orthodontics</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) a history of whiplash injury; 
(ii) a history of degenerative disorders of the central and/or peripheral nervous system; 
(iii) a history of cranial vault, craniofacial, temporomandibular joint, or any level of spinal fractures and/or surgery; 
(iv) suffering or having suffered osteitis, or cranial-vault, craniofacial, or temporomandibular joint rheumatic or tumoural diseases; and 
(v) consumption of analgesics or anti-inflammatory drugs within 48 hours prior to data collection</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using  coin-tossing</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>42</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Sevilla</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sevilla</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Physiotherapy.
Faculty of Nursing, Physiotherapy and Podiatry.

C/ Avicena s/n 41009 Sevilla (Spain)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sevilla (Spain)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Physiotherapy.
Faculty of Nursing, Physiotherapy and Podiatry.

C/ Avicena s/n 41009 Sevilla (Spain)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Spain</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We hypothesized that, in correcting tooth alignment, orthodontic treatment will affect the normal resting position of the jaw and the entire Cranio-Cervico-Mandibular Unit, favouring extension of the high cervical segment and the tendency to prognathism, so leading to a Forward Head Posture. This correlates with a retraction of the suboccipital muscles and a decreased pressure pain threshold of the greater occipital (GO) nerve, a threshold which we shall find to be improved following application of the Suboccipital muscle inhibition technique. Thus, the objective of the study was to determine and analyze the differences in head posture and in the PPT of the GO nerve following an intervention by a SMI technique among asymptomatic subjects with a history of having used orthodontics As suggested by Saiz LLamosas et al. the study of the potential effects and benefits of myofascial induction techniques should be started in pain-free subjects to avoid any sensitization.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Part of the trial has been published in Journal of Manipulative and Physiological Therapeutics

Heredia-Rizo AM, Oliva Pascual-Vaca A, Albornoz Cabello M, Rodriguez Blanco C, Pina Pozo F, Luque Carrasco A. Immediate effects of the suboccipital muscle inhibition technique in craniocervical posture and greater occipital nerve mechanosensitivity in subjects with a history of orthodontia use: a randomized trial. J Manipulative Physiol Ther 2012; 35(6): 446-53. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2012.06.006</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>COMITE DE EXPERIMENTACION DE LA UNIVERSIDAD DE SEVILLA</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Paseo de las Delicias s/n

41013 Sevilla</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NONE</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/01/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ALBERTO MARCOS HEREDIA RIZO</name>
      <address>C/ AVICENA S/N

41009 SEVILLA</address>
      <phone>(+34) 954 48 65 07</phone>
      <fax>(+34) 954 48 65 28</fax>
      <email>amheredia@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ALBERTO MARCOS HEREDIA RIZO</name>
      <address>C/ AVICENA S/N

41009 SEVILLA</address>
      <phone>(+34) 954 48 65 07</phone>
      <fax>(+34) 954 48 65 28</fax>
      <email>amheredia@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>ALBERTO MARCOS HEREDIA RIZO</name>
      <address>C/ AVICENA S/N

41009 SEVILLA</address>
      <phone>(+34) 954 48 65 09</phone>
      <fax>(+34) 954 48 65 28</fax>
      <email>amheredia@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alberto Marcos Heredia-Rizo</name>
      <address>C/ Avicena s/n 41009, University of Sevilla</address>
      <phone>(+34 954486507)</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amheredia@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>