<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363320">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000162718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving medication adherence in patients with chronic diseases</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Targeted and tailored interventions to improve medication adherence compared to standard care in patients with chronic diseases </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dyslipidaemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type II Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Other cardiovascular diseases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Interventions to improve medication adherence tailored to the identified patient reasons for non-adherence. 

These interventions may include implementing dose administration aids, telephone reminders, health coaching or motivational interviewing. The selected intervention will depend on the patient's reasons for non-adherence.

Dose administration aids as an intervention will be implemented by explaining to the patient what a dose administration aid looks like and how it works, which will take approximately 10 minutes. If the patient agrees the patient will be referred onto the pharmacy to initiate dose administration aids for this patient. The pharmacy will create a medication profile for the patient by liaising with the patient's general practitioner. The patient's prescriptions will be kept by the pharmacy and dispensed. Dose administration aids will be packed on a fortnightly basis and patients will pick up the packs as needed. (This is the standard procedure of dose administration aids in a pharmacy and the delivery of these packs will be the responsibility of the pharmacy). From the researcher's own experience in packing dose administration aids, the initiation of the dose administration aid will take several hours. 

Telephone reminders will be implemented by initiating fortnightly phone calls discussing medication-taking behaviour after baseline.

Health coaching or motivational interviewing will involve setting goals of medication-taking behaviour, which will be conducted at baseline and 3 and 6 months if appropriate. This will be facilitated in the private counselling area of the pharmacy and will involve a 20 minute one-on-one interview with the researcher (who is also a pharmacist).

These interventions will be implemented at baseline and if necessary 3 and 6 months after baseline. The interventions will be implemented over the total trial duration of 6 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment: patients will receive standard pharmacist counselling on their medication and medical condition at baseline by the researcher/pharmacist and when they have prescription refills for an overall duration of 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication adherence as assessed by mean MAQ (Medication Adherence Questionnaire) scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3 and 6 months after implementation of intervention at baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in adherence behaviour over time as assessed by individual mean MAQ scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3 and 6 months after implementation of intervention at baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Patients attending one of the study pharmacies
- Patients  over 18 years of age
- Diagnosed with at least one of the following chronic    diseases: hypertension, type 2 diabetes, dyslipidaemia or cardiovascular disease 
- Patients taking a medication for one of the above chronic diseases from the following drug groups: ACE-inhibitors, calcium channel blockers, beta-blockers, oral hypoglycaemic drugs, lipid lowering agents
- Patients with a newly initiated medication (from above) within the previous four to twelve weeks
- Consent to participate in the study
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Patients who do not adequately understand the study information (in the opinion of the researcher)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The proposed trial will screen patients attending a number of community pharmacies within Brisbane and surrounding suburbs to identify patients with chronic disease(s) newly initiated on a medication. These patients will be screened to identify their adherence behaviour using a validated adherence scale (MAQ). Based on their adherence, patients will be assigned into one of three groups: adherent, intervention or control. Patients who are identified as non-adherent will be randomised into the intervention or control group.  

ALLOCATION IS NOT CONCEALED</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/02/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence
20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence
20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the study is to identify patients with poor medication-taking behaviour and implement personalised interventions to improve medication-taking behaviour.

We hope to learn about changes in medication-taking behaviour over time and to determine the degree to which improvements in this behaviour are sustained. We also want to learn if using the MAQ and Beliefs about Medicines Questionnaire - Specific was helpful to improve medication-taking behaviour.

We hypothesise that:
- Personalising interventions to patients known to have poor medication-taking behaviour will improve medication-taking behaviour at three months.
- Improvements in medication-taking behaviour at three months will not be sustained at six months.
- Medication-taking behaviour, and the reasons for poor medication-taking behaviour, will change over time in all groups studied. 


</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland School of Pharmacy Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Thi-My-Uyen Nguyen</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence
20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3346 1996</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.nguyen63@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Thi-My-Uyen Nguyen</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence
20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3346 1996</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.nguyen63@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Thi-My-Uyen Nguyen</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence
20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3346 1996</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.nguyen63@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Thi-My-Uyen Nguyen</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Australia Centre of Excellence
20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3346 1996</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.nguyen63@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>