<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363526">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000101785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Research Study of Injections of Testosterone in an Oil Vehicle for men with Androgen Deficiency:  Reandron (Testosterone Undecanoate) will be administered  subcutaneously and intramuscularly.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pharmacokinetics of Subcutaneous Injection of Testosterone in an Oil Vehicle: A  Randomised crossover study of Reandron (Testosterone Undecanoate) given subcutaneously and intramuscularly in hypogonadal men.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Male Hypogonadism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Testosterone Undecanoate (TU) 1000mgs in 4 mL oil vehicle. 
Arm 1, 
Administered as a single subcutaneous (SC) injection under the abdominal skin.
Arm 2,
Administered as a single intramuscular (IM) injection into the buttock.
Participants will be randomised to one of the two arms. Then after 12 weeks will  receive treatment in the second arm.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Testosterone Undecanoate (TU) 1000mgs in 4 mL oil vehicle administered as a single intramuscular (IM) injection into the buttock. (Standard treatment)
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time profile of serum testosterone concentrations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post each testosterone injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time profile of serum  DHT, estradiol, LH and FSH concentrations</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient preference will be measured by self administered  Likert scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of the study (24 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient acceptability will be measured by self administered  Likert scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after both SC and IM injections and at the completion of the study (24 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient pain will be measured by self administered  Likert scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the injections (SC and IM) and 24 hours post injections.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Already receiving regular testosterone treatment.
*Written, informed consent &amp; willing to comply with study requirements</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Contraindication to testosterone 
*History of major psychiatric disease or psychological condition that may limit understanding and compliance with study requirements
*Regular medications that interfere with absorption, metabolism or action of testosterone which may require dosage change during the study
*Taking medications for antiplatelet or anticoagulant therapy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment by computer randomisation.
Then sealed in opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Calculate non-compartmental PK parameters according to Gibaldi &amp; Perrier. The primary descriptive and not comparative but will examine the data on a non-inferiority basis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW, 2139</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Concord Repatriation General Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW, 2139</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Although intramuscular (IM) injections of androgen's are known to be effective, they result in varying degrees of pain at the injection site that may last for a day or two. These injections need to be given into a precise location of the buttocks and require staff with expert training. 

Unlike many other injections these cannot be self-injected due to the difficulty of safely injecting into the buttocks. A SC injection, if effective, may be given by yourself in your own home, which would be more convenient to avoid extra medical visits as well as saving GP and hospital resources.

Many men who require androgen replacement therapy may have bleeding disorders or are on medications that may intentionally slow the ability of their blood to clot. These men have a theoretical risk of bleeding and a very large bruise deep in an important muscle may later become infected and cause significant disability. As a result men using these anti-clotting drugs are usually prescribed other forms of androgen replacement therapy that are not always optimal. A subcutaneous (SC) injection, if effective, may be used in these men.
This is a randomised crossover study of testosterone Undecanoate given subcutaneously and intramuscularly in patients receiving testosterone replacement therapy. Each participant will receive a single IM injection and a single (SC) injection of TU. An IM injection is standard of care and duration of action is approximately 12 weeks. It is expected a SC injection will have a duration of action of 12 weeks. Thus the study will take 24 weeks for each participant  to complete both arms.

This is the second stage of a 2 stage research study. This is stage 2 of study ACTRN12613000068763</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This is a randomised crossover study of testosterone Undecanoate given subcutaneously and intramuscularly in patients receiving testosterone replacement therapy.
This is the second stage of a 2 stage research study. The study will take each participant 12 weeks to complete each arm of the study and thus 24 weeks to complete the entire study.
Stage 1 is registered. Trial ID is ACTRN12613000068763</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee( Concord Repatriation general Hospital Zone (EC00118)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Concord Repatriation General Hospital, Hospital Road,Concord, NSW 2139</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/CRGH/158</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Handelsman</name>
      <address>The Andrology Department Hospital Road Concord Repatriation General Hospital Concord, NSW, 2139</address>
      <phone>612 97677222</phone>
      <fax>612 97677221</fax>
      <email>djh@anzac.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Leo Turner</name>
      <address>The Andrology Department Hospital Road Concord Repatriation General Hospital Concord, NSW, 2139</address>
      <phone>612 97677222</phone>
      <fax>612 97677221</fax>
      <email>lturner@anzac.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Handelsman</name>
      <address>The Andrology Department Hospital Road Concord Repatriation General Hospital Concord, NSW, 2139</address>
      <phone>612 97677222</phone>
      <fax>612 97677221</fax>
      <email>djh@anzac.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Leo Turner</name>
      <address>The Andrology Department Hospital Road Concord Repatriation General Hospital Concord, NSW, 2139</address>
      <phone>612 97677222</phone>
      <fax>612 97677221</fax>
      <email>lturner@anzac.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>