<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83302">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/10/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000568314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase 3, duble-blind, randomized, parallel study to evaluate the efficacy of glucosamine sulfate and meloxicam administered in combination or glucosamine sulfate and meloxicam administered separately to subjects with mild to moderate osteoarthiritis of the knee or hip</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase 3, duble-blind, randomized, parallel study to evaluate the efficacy of glucosamine sulfate and meloxicam administered in combination or glucosamine sulfate and meloxicam administered separately to subjects with mild to moderate osteoarthiritis of the knee or hip</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Not aplicable</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild to moderate osteoarthrits</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Combination of Glucosamine sulfate 1.500mg and Meloxicam 15mg, administration daily orally, during 12 weeks (84 days). 1 powder packet, diluting in water, once a day.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group 1: Glucosamine sulfate 1.500mg + Meloxican placebo (pill - the same substances except for Meloxicam), administration daily orally during 12 weeks (84 days). 1 powder packet ( diluting in water) and 1 tablet, once a day. Control group 2: Meloxicam 15mg + Glucosamine sulfate placebo (Packet - the same subtances except for Glicosamine sulfate) , administration daily orally during 12 weeks (84 days). 1 tabelt and 1 powder packet (diluting in water) once a day.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity evaluation measured by WOMAC (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluation will be measured in baseline - visit 2 (randomization day), visit 3 (week 2), visit 4 (week 4), visit 5 (week 6), visit 6 (week 8), visit 7 (week 10), visit 8 (week 12 - end of treatment period)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety measured by patient adverse event reports (serious and non serious adverse event). Glucosamine sulfate and meloxicam can presents skin alergy reaction, gastric problems and headaches but this symptoms are rare. However, every single adverse event presented during the study (15 weeks - screening, baseline, treatement period and follow-up period) will be followed. The adverse events will be assessed by patients reports during each visit and/or patient contact at any time. Non serious adverse events will be recorded at the Case Report Form (CRF) and serious adverse events will be recorded on a special adverse event report form (e.g. Council for international Organizations of Medical Sciences - CIOMS).

Safety will be also measured by laboratory exams performed in visits 1 (screening), 4(week 4), 6 (week 8) and 8 (week 12) to check if it is still normal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse event - during all study (15 weeks): screening - time =0, baseline - 1 week, treatment period - 12 weeks and follow up period - 2 weeks

Laboratory exams - visits 1 (screening), 4(week 4), 6 (week 8) and 8 (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Patients between 40 and 60 years old
- Knee or hip osteoarthritis radiologic and clinical diagnosis
- lesion intensity should be mild to moderate (level 2 or 3 in Kellgren-Lawrence classification)
- normal laboratory exams
- informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- not used corticosteroids during the last 30 days
- not used non steroidal antinflamatory during the last 7 days
- immunomodulators previous use
- intrarticular medication during the last 6 months
- previous surgery in knee or hip and prosthesis use
- pregnant
- organic disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>270</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zodiac Produtos Farmacêuticos S.A.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Praça Prof. José Lannes, 40 - 15 andar
Sao Paulo</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Zodiac Produtos Farmaceuticos S.A.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Praca Prof. Jose Lannes, 40 - 15 andar
Sao Paulo</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Arthritis is a generic term that refers to the inflammatory process that occurs in one or more joints. Among the causes of arthritis, the osteoarthritis (OA), also called osteoarthrosis, its the most frequent one (Myers e cols., 2007).
Previously considered to be a degenerative disease, OA is known today as a metabolically dynamic disease, with repairing mechanisms that involve the cartilage and the underlying bone tissue of the joints (Jones &amp; Doherty, 1995).
OA is a result of mechanical or biological events that interfere with the delicate balance between production and degradation of the cartilage tissue and the bone immediately beneath it. It attacks all the joint tissues and it is characterized by morphological, biochemical, molecular and biomechanical changes.
Over the last few years, the possible treatments for OA have been largely studied all over the world. All these studies strive to provide a drug or a therapeutic combination that brings more comfort to the patient and improves his or her quality of life. In this sense, the ultimate goal is to alleviate symptoms of pain (acute or chronic), increase functional physical capacity and help repair the affected cartilage.
Pre-clinical studies had shown that orally absorbed glucosamine helps restitute the components lost during natural degradation of OA and increases production of proteoglicans by the chondrocytes when associated with Meloxicam.
Combination of an anti-inflammatory / analgesic drug and a cartilage regenerator like SYSADOA (SYmptomatic Slow-Acting Drugs in Osteoarthritis) is the objective for a more complete approach in the treatment of OA.
The proposed therapy with this new association aims to keep work capacity in young adults (40 to 60 years old) that have the chronic and potentially incapacitating form of the disease.
The purpose of this study is to compare, after 12 weeks of double-blind oral administration of this therapy, the physical activity rate achieved by the subjects assigned to the different therapeutic branches, which will be analyzed by the WOMAC (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index) questionnaire filled out by individuals with knee or hip OA of mild to moderate intensity and not exposed to previous treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CEP da Faculdade de Medicina do ABC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Santo Andre</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/02/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tatiana Ferian da Fonseca</name>
      <address>Rua Borges Lagoa, 1080 - cj101
São Paulo</address>
      <phone>55 11 5904 4454</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tatiana@newcotrials.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tatiana Ferian da Fonseca</name>
      <address>Rua Borges Lagoa, 1080 - cj101
São Paulo</address>
      <phone>55 11 5904 4454</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tatiana@newcotrials.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tatiana Ferian da Fonseca</name>
      <address>Rua Borges Lagoa, 1080 - cj101
São Paulo</address>
      <phone>55 11 5904 4454</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tatiana@newcotrials.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>