<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364810">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000958785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>What is the efficacy of therapist-guided internet-treatment, self-guided internet-treatment with pre-treatment contact, and purely self-guided internet-delivered for older adults (60+) with symptoms of anxiety and depression?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial of the effects of guided internet-treatment vs. self-guided internet-treatment with pre-treatment contact vs. purely self-guided internet-delivered treatment on symptoms of anxiety and depression in Australian older adults (60+). </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>WBPRCT3</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this trial Australian older adults (60+) with symptoms of anxiety and depression will be randomly allocated to one of three groups.

The three groups are:
Group 1: Purely self-guided - treatment. Participants in this group will complete the treatment in a purely self-guided format, that is, without pre-treatment contact or weekly support from a therapist.
Group 2: Self-guided with pre-treatment contact. Participants in this group will complete the treatment in a self-guided format, that is, with pre-treatment contact but no weekly support from a therapist.
Group 3: Guided - treatment. Participants in this group will complete the treatment in a guided format, that is, with pre-treatment contact as well as weekly telephone or email support from a therapist.

Pre-treatment contact will occur via a brief 5 - 10 minute telephone call with one of the two clinicians running the Course. The pre-treatment contact will involve a brief discussion about the Course requirements, orienting the participant to the Course structure and online treatment.  

Weekly contact will be conducted via a brief 5 - 10 minute telephone call by one of two clinicians running the treatment groups. The weekly contact will involve answering participants' questions about the treatment materials, orienting participants to the upcoming treatment materials, encouraging practice of self-management skills, and answering queries about practicing the skills in the Course.

Over the 8 weeks, all participants will be directed to read 5 online lessons about management of symptoms. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 14 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to read. Participants will also have access to summaries and homework assignments for each lesson, and will read stories about people with similar symptoms, taking a further 20 minutes per week.

Participants in all groups will also receive automatic emails providing reminders about the course and encouragement to continue.

Study questionnaires will be administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 3 months post-treatment. These will take about 10-15 minutes to complete. Participants will also complete brief measures of mood and anxiety before each lesson. The treatment materials include cognitive behavioural treatment (CBT) skills.</interventions>
    <comparator>This 3 group (purely self-guided vs. self-guided with pre-treatment contact vs. guided) RCT does not have a formal control group, as it compares active treatments. However, data from historical controls will be obtained and compared from similar studies conducted by this research team over the period 2007-2012. These studies include:

Titov, N., Dear, B.F., Johnston, L., Lorian, C., Zou, J., Wootton, B., Spence, J., McEvoy, P., Rapee, R.M. (In Press). Improving adherence and clinical outcomes in self-guided internet treatment for anxiety and depression: randomised controlled trial. PLoS ONE.

Titov N, Dear BF, Schwencke G, Andrews G, Johnston L, Craske M, McEvoy P. (2011). Transdiagnostic Internet treatment of anxiety and depression: A randomised controlled trial. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 49; 441-452.

Titov N, Andrews G, Schwencke G, Robinson E, Peters L, Spence J. (2010). An RCT of Internet CBT for social phobia with and without motivational enhancement strategies. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry;44:938-945.

Titov N, Andrews G, Johnston L, Robinson E, Spence J. Transdiagnostic Internet treatment for anxiety disorders: A randomized controlled trial, Behaviour Research and Therapy (2010), 48:890-899. doi:10.1016/j.brat.2010.05.014

Titov N, Andrews G, Choi I, Schwencke G, Johnston L. (2009). Randomized controlled trial of web-based treatment of social phobia without clinical guidance. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry;43:913-919.

Titov N, Andrews G, Johnston J, Schwencke G, Choi I. (2009). The Shyness program: Longer term benefits, cost-effectiveness, and acceptability. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry;43:36-44.

Titov N, Andrews G, Robinson E, Schwencke G, Johnston L, Solley K, Choi I. (2009). Clinician-assisted Internet-based treatment is effective for generalized anxiety disorder: A randomized controlled trial. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry;43:905-912.

Titov N, Andrews G, Schwencke G, Solley K, Johnston L, Robinson E. (2009). An RCT comparing two types of support on severity of symptoms for people completing Internet-based cognitive behavior therapy for social phobia. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry;43:920-926.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of anxiety are measured by the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7 Item Scale (GAD-7)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, prior to each Lesson in the course, at post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of low mood/depression are measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, prior to each Lesson in the course, at post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of low mood typified in an older population are measured by the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured with the Kessler-10 item (K-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability is measured by the Sheehan Disability Scales (SDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Life satisfaction is measured by the Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Positive adaptive behaviours are measured by the Things You Do Questionnaire (TYDQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 3 months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Australian resident
(2) 60+ years of age
(3) Not currently participating in CBT for target symptoms
(4) Provides informed consent
(5) Reliable internet access 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Severe depression (i.e. score &gt; 23 on PHQ-9), suicidal intention or plan 
(2) Principal problem not anxiety or low mood/depression
(3) Self-reported suicide intent or plan
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online, and those who meet inclusion criteria are randomly allocated to one of two groups. Allocation concealment will not be required, as applications are date stamped, and allocation is automatically assigned. The validity of this process will be checked daily by the CI.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized using a permuted block sequence using a list generated prior to the study via a software program (www.randomizer.org). The list will then be transcribed into an electronic format and merged with the online application system, such that eligible applicants are automatically assigned the next number in the sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A total sample size of 450 participants is sufficient to observe the expected differences. With power at 80% and alpha of 0.05, 150 participants in each intervention group will allow detection of between-intervention group effect size differences of 0.3, the smallest effect size considered of clinical importance.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/02/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>450</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>434</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>eCentreClinic, Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue: the national depression initiative</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West
Victoria 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is part of a research program funded by beyondblue to develop and evaluate Internet based treatment programs for older adults (60+) with anxiety and depression. This project examines the relative efficacy of guided and self-guided internet delivered treatment. Additionally, the study aims to examine the effect of a pre-treatment interview upon treatment outcomes for self-guided interventions.

We expect that the guided intervention will result in superior outcomes to the self-guided interventions. Additionally, we expect that the self-guided intervention which includes a pre-treatment interview will result in superior outcomes when compared to the self-guided intervention without the interview.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ecentreclinic.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication>1. Dear, BF., Zou, J., Titov, N., Lorian, C., Johnston, L.,  Spence, J.,  Anderson, T., Sachdev, S., Brodaty, H., Knight, RG. (2013). Internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy for depression: A feasibility open trial for older adults. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry, 47, 169-176.

2. Titov, N., Dear, B. F., Johnston, L., Lorian, C., Zou, J., Wootton, B., McEvoy, P. M., Rapee, R. M. (2013). Improving adherence and clinical outcomes in self-guided internet treatment for anxiety and depression: randomised controlled trial. PLoS One, 262873.

3. Zou, B.J., Dear, B.F., Titov, N., Lorian, C.N., Johnston, L., Spence, J., Knight, R.G., Anderson, T., Sachdev, P. (2012).  Brief internet-delivered cognitive behavioral therapy for anxiety in older adults: A feasibility trial. Journal of Anxiety Disorders, 26, 650-655.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201300458</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Building/Room C3A 724 Macquarie University North Ryde NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Building/Room C3A 724 Macquarie University North Ryde NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Building/Room C3A 724 Macquarie University North Ryde NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address> Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Building/Room C3A 724 Macquarie University North Ryde NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>