<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373114">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000961347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of physical activity and text-messaging on exercise levels in obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can physical activity intervention and/or text messaging improve functional exercise capacity and self-efficacy in adults with OSA?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1197-7314</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive sleep apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a three-arm intervention as follows: 
Group 1 will attend a 1 hour supervised group exercise session, once/week for 12 weeks,
Group 2 will attend a 1 hour supervised group exercise session once/week for 12 weeks and will receive 5-7 personalised text messages each week for those 12 weeks, followed by a gradually reducing number for an additional 12 weeks.
Group 3 will be provided with an individual exercise programme to follow unsupervised for 12 weeks and receive 5-7 personalised text messages each week for those 12 weeks, followed by a gradually reducing number for an additional 12 weeks.  In groups 2 and 3, the number of text messages will be reduced by one every fortnight, resulting in a single text message being sent in the final two weeks of the study (weeks 23 and 24).
Participants will be encouraged to undertake all physical activity at a moderate intensity, working at level 4-6 on the modified Borg RPE scale.  The group exercise will be supervised by an experienced physiotherapist with at least 10 years experience, and comprise both aerobic and resistance exercises including, but not limited to, static bike, rower, free weights and resistance bands.  Exercise prescription, in terms of duration, resistance, repetitions and number of sets, will be specific to the individual participant.  The group exercise will be conducted at a University gym facility.  Participants in all groups will be encouraged to exercise at moderate intensity throughout the study duration.   Those participants undertaking unsupervised exercise will be encouraged to aim for NZ Ministry of Health guidelines of two and a half hours of moderate physical activity spread throughout the week (e.g. 30 minutes, 5 days a week), and muscle strengthening activities at least two days a week.
Personalised text messages will be motivational in nature and the content will be determined by participant information provided at baseline assessment.  These will be uni-directional with no response required from participants.  If participants require advice/extra support, a contact phone number will be provided at commencement of the study.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator group is group 3 who will receive no supervised exercise intervention.  They will, however, receive tailored text messages at the same frequency, and over the same time period, as Group 2.  Participants in group 3 will be provided with information regarding the current NZ Ministry of Health guidelines for physical activity and a personalised physical activity plan,  They will be encouraged to walk 5 days a week, at moderate intensity, aiming for a cumulative total of 150 minutes and will be provided with suggestions on how best to achieve this.  Each participant will also be provided with an upper limb strengthening programme (10 repetitions of each exercise x 3 sets) to be carried out twice a week.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional exercise capacity as measured using the six minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moderate-vigorous physical activity behaviour as measured by 7 days of accelerometry data</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as measured by the following questionnaires: Short Form 36 (SF-36) and Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep duration/disturbance as measured using overnight accelerometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait speed measured over a 10 metre walking distance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength using a handheld dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive symptoms as measured using the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at  6 weeks, 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of self-efficacy as measured by the General Self-Efficacy Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary time as measured by accelerometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 12 weeks and 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults referred to the Dunedin Sleep Clinic with symptoms indicative of OSA and with an Epworth Sleepiness Scale score of 11 or greater, and able to walk independently with or without a walking aid
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	An overnight sleep study result with no diagnosis of OSA (excluded from study data analysis)
	Uncontrolled hypertension or unstable angina 
	Inability to participate in exercise-based physical activity
	Inability to provide informed consent  
	Inability to complete health related questionnaires independently and in English
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>With a MCID of 40, using an SD of 27.2, we calculated we would need n=45 per group (total = 135).  Allowing for 10% attrition, this requires a total sample size of 149.  This calculation assumes a significance level of 0.05 and power of 0.8.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>14/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/04/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Physiotherapy, University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Physiotherapy, University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) often exists in people with high blood pressure, heart disease, obesity and/or diabetes. Poor sleep quality, daytime sleepiness, fatigue, and physical inactivity are commonly associated with OSA.  A graduated physical activity programme, prescribed at a level appropriate to the individual, has been shown to improve energy levels and reduce associated health risk factors; motivational text messaging may also assist. 

The study will focus on engaging adults with OSA over a 12-week period involving either a physical activity programme, motivational texting or both, with the primary purpose being:
	To investigate the effects of a 12-week physical activity intervention on physical activity behaviour and a range of relevant health outcomes.
	To compare activity levels and sedentary time during a physical activity programme with and without tailored text messaging intervention.
	To compare physical activity behaviour in those undergoing CPAP treatment with those who are not. 
	To objectively measure physical activity levels at three time points (baseline, 12 and 24 weeks) in conjunction with a supervised exercise intervention and compare levels with current World Health Organization weekly recommendations.

Participants will be allocated to one of three groups - ( 1) once weekly supervised exercise group, (2) once weekly supervised exercise group plus tailored text messaging, or (3) tailored text messaging only.  

Individuals will be provided with a device for measuring activity levels (Actigraph accelerometer) at initial assessment and asked to wear this for seven days and nights, to provide baseline physical activity levels, sedentary time and sleep quality and duration. Wearing of the accelerometer will be repeated for another seven-day period for comparison at 12 weeks, and 24 weeks.  In addition, various measurements such as height, weight, blood pressure and waist circumference will be take at each of the three time points.  Various questionnaires related to quality of life and self-efficacy will be undertaken at baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.

The weekly supervised group exercise will comprise both aerobic and resistance exercises, and be supervised by a physiotherapist.    Those in the text messaging groups will receive personalised text messages sent between five and seven times a week throughout the initial 12 weeks, and for 12 weeks afterwards at a decreasing rate. 

Expected outcomes will be: (1) Analysis of the effects of a 12-week physical activity intervention on physical activity behaviour and a range of relevant health outcomes and comparison with World Health Organisation weekly recommendations; (2) Comparison of activity levels and sedentary time between groups participating in a physical activity programme with and without tailored text messaging intervention; (3) Comparison of physical activity behaviour in those undergoing CPAP treatment with those who are not.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee NZ</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373114-PhD study protocol 18062017.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sarah Rhodes</name>
      <address>University of Otago
School of Physiotherapy
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7460</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.rhodes@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sarah Rhodes</name>
      <address>University of Otago
School of Physiotherapy
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7460</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.rhodes@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Margot Skinner</name>
      <address>University of Otago
School of Physiotherapy
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7466</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>margot.skinner@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>