<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363116">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001073897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD) Program - A Randomised Controlled Trial comparing clinician-assisted Internet based treatment for OCD vs. a waitlist control condition on severity of symptoms of OCD.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing clinician-assisted Internet based treatment for Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD) vs. a waitlist control condition on severity of symptoms of OCD.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The OCD Program</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive Compulsive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two groups: 1) Treatment with clinician-assisted Internet based Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD), or 2) Waitlist control. All participants will meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for OCD. All group 1 participants will separately complete 6 lessons of Internet based treatment about the management of symptoms of OCD. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 14 days (it will become available after the preceding lesson has been completed, with a minimum of 7 days between lessons and a maximum of 14 days). Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Group 1 participants will have access to summaries of each lesson, homework exercises, extra resources, weekly reminder emails, and one-on-one contact with the Clinician (Clinical Psychologist) by telephone or email in the first 2 weeks, then as required. The duration of the program is 8-10 weeks, but participants will be contacted 3 months post program and asked to complete follow-up questionnaires. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, at 3 months post-treatment, and the K10 pre-each lesson. These will take about 20 minutes to complete. The treatment materials are based on cognitive behavioural techniques.</interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control group. These participants remain on the waitlist until the treatment groups have completed their treatment (10 weeks). At that time (10 weeks) the waitlist group will receive the same treatment as Treatment Group 1.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Obsessive Beliefs Questionnaire (OBQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dimensional Obsessive Compulsive Scale (DOCS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured by the Kessler-10 (K-10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered before each lesson, at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalised Anxiety Disorder is measured by the Generalized Anxiety Disorder - 7 Item (GAD-7) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to lessons and homework.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before each lesson (lesson must be completed and homework downloaded before patient advances to next lesson).

The slides of a lesson must be clicked through from start to finish before the homework for that lesson can be downloaded, and the next lesson will not become available until the homework has been downloaded. Our admin system will notify us whether or not the homework has been downloaded.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of the American Psychiatric Association-4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for Obsessive Compulsive Disorder, Internet access + printer access, Australian citizen.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current substance abuse/dependence, Psychotic mental illness (Bipolar or Schizophrenia), Current or planned psychological treatment during study duration, previous iCBT for OCD, Change in medications during last 1 month or intended change during study duration, use of Benzodiazepines, Suicidal .</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply on line, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI 5.0.0), a structured diagnostic interview. Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study. Allocation concealment will occur in the following way: A staff member not involved in the clinical trial will generate the sequence using computer software, and place each choice in a sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed and stapled envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation list will be generated prior to the study using computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>86</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We have recently developed an online cognitive behavior therapy program involving exposure and response prevention for people with OCD. This study will examine the programs effectiveness in reducing symptoms of OCD and related symptoms of anxiety, depression, distress, and disability. We will also assess how acceptable the program is to participants.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.virtualclinic.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Behav Res Ther. 2014 Oct 7;
Internet cognitive behavioural treatment for obsessive compulsive disorder: A randomised controlled trial.
Mahoney AE, Mackenzie A, Williams AD, Smith J, Andrews G.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital HREC
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/SVH/239</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jessica Smith</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>jessica.smith@svha.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Level 4, O'Brien Centre
390-394 Victoria Street
St Vincent's Hospital 
Darlinghurst
NSW
2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>