<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368330">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000538549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of lumbar anaesthesia on sympathetic activity below the level of the block</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Area under curve of the photoplethysmographic signal as the evaluation measure for sympathetic activity during lumbar epidural anaesthesia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-1192</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>sympathetic activity during lumbar epidural anaesthesia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Only one group of patients was included in the study. 0.5% bupivacaine was injected in the L3/L4 level by the qualified anaesthesiologist and Biopac SS4LA Pulse Plethysmograph. Photoplethysmography recordings were taken before lumbar epidural anaesthesia procedure was done, as well as during the whole surgical procedure and during the post-anaesthesia recovery (until all of the sensoric functions of the lower limbs were recovered). Transducer was used for photoplethysmography recording. Amplitude (maximum PPG sygnal), pulse transit time and area under the curve were recorded.</interventions>
    <comparator>Only one group of patients was included in the study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation of epidural anaesthesia success (meaning clinically successful: the degree of reducement of the pain caused by the surgical procedure ; no tools were used for assesing the pain because the patients were subjected to painful surgical stimulus ; that means that in all of the patients which were included in the study, the pain was reduced to the level of feeling no pain at all during surgical stimulation) with the area under the curve of the photoplethysmographic signal which is measured by the Biopac SS4LA Pulse Plethysmograph Transducer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Few minutes after lumbar epidural anaesthesia application.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>No secondary outcomes</outcome>
      <timepoint>No secondary outcomes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>40 patients aged 18-45 which underwent surgical procedure under epidural anaesthesia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>pulses of the arteria tibialis posterior and arteria dorsalis pedis are not palpable
perspiration of the feet is not maintained
abnormal growth and transparency of the nails 
changes which indicate pathological alteration of the blood vessels of the lower extremities</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Differences between two measurements of the single parameters of the same examinees will be tested by the nonparametric test for dependent samples (Wilcoxon Matched-Pairs Test). Differences between three or more measurements of the single parameters of the same examinees will be tested by the nonparametric analysis of the variance for dependent samples (Friedman ANOVA). As the statistically significant limit, p&lt;0,005 was chosen. Statistical analysis will be done on PC computer, in program Statistica 6. Number of 40 patients was chosen as objective number for the study due to clinical experience in giving successful epidural anaesthesia. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <state>City of Zagreb, Clinical Hospital Center Zagreb</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Hospital Center Zagreb</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kispaticeva 12, 10000 Zagreb, Croatia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Croatia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department for Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care Medicine, Clinic for Surgery, Clinical Hospital Center Zagreb, Zagreb, Croatia
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kispaticeva 12, 10000 Zagreb, Croatia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Croatia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Photoplethysmographic signal reflects sympathetic activity under the level of epidural block. The height of sensory block during epidural anaesthesia reflects the height of sympathetic block. Area under the photoplethysmographic curve (AUC) depends on variability of the photoplethysmographic signal strenght and duration. Our hypothesis is that change in any parameter, due to the sympathetic block, will change the area under the curve of the photoplethysmographic signal.
40 patients with epidural anaesthesia will be included in the research. 0.5% bupivacaine will be injected in the L3/L4 level and Biopac SS4LA Pulse Plethysmograph Transducer will be used for photoplethysmography recording. Amplitude (maximum PPG sygnal), pulse transit time and area under the curve will be recorded. Our goal is to test sympathetic activity using variabilities, shapes and characteristics of  the PPG curve (area under the curve) during 0.5% bupivacaine epidural anaesthesia. 


</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Slobodan Mihaljevic</name>
      <address>Clinical Hospital Center Zagreb, Obstetrics and Gynecology Clinic
Petrova 13
10000 Zagreb, Croatia
</address>
      <phone>+385915024223</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smsmihaljevic@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kresimir Reiner</name>
      <address>Clinical Hospital Center Zagreb, Obstetrics and Gynecology Clinic
Petrova 13
10000 Zagreb, Croatia</address>
      <phone>+385917615364</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kresimirovichmd@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kresimir Reiner</name>
      <address>Clinical Hospital Center Zagreb, Obstetrics and Gynecology Clinic
Petrova 13
10000 Zagreb, Croatia</address>
      <phone>+385917615364</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kresimirovichmd@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>