<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368929">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000782538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised, double blind, placebo controlled comparative trial of Ceramide Cream and Ceramide Cleanser in the management of moderate eczema in adults </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, double blind, placebo controlled comparative trial of Ceramide Cream and Ceramide Cleanser in the management of moderate eczema in adults </scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1172-1554</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Eczema</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The will investigate the efficacy of two cosmetic products, a  ceramide-dominant physiological lipid-based hydrating cleanser and moisturiser. The Cream will be applied liberally to the whole body twice a day, while the Cleanser will be used on the whole body once a day. Duration of use will be for 28 days.  Compliance will be monitored by weighing the products at each study visit. Both products are regulated as cosmetics, and as such do not have 'active' ingredients. Both products contain ceramides, cholesterol and physiological lipids in a 3:1:1 ratio.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo cleanser will contain a blend of surfactants, while the placebo cream will contain a blend of emulsifiers, fatty alcohols and thickeners. These placebo products are the intervention products with the ceramide components removed. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary efficacy endpoint will be the percentage change from baseline in EASI score at Day 28 for both the PP and ITT populations. The outcome to be assessed by the EASI score is eczema severity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage change from baseline in the EASI score. The outcome to be assessed by the EASI score is eczema severity.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7, 14 and 21</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage change from baseline in trans epidermal water loss (TEWL). TEWL is determined by the use of a hand held Tewameter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7, 14, 21 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage change from baseline in skin hydration. Skin hydration is determined by the use of a handheld Corneometer. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7, 14, 21 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in DLQI from baseline. The DLQI, Dermatology Quality Index Survey, will be used to assess changes in quality of life. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 14 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction survey. This survey has been designed for this study and will be used to assess subject attitudes towards the test products. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 14 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of Zatamil Hydrogel used as rescue medication. The amount of Zatamil Hydrogel used will be determined by weighing the product at each assessment visit.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7, 14, 21 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type of adverse events, and their relationship to the investigational products. The most common type of adverse events from topical cosmetic cleansers and creams is irritation. This may present as itch and/or rash. These will be assessed via subject self reporting and medical observation/queries at each clinical visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7, 14, 21 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of adverse events, and their relationship to the investigational products.  Adverse events from cosmetic cleansers and creams are rare. These will be assessed via subject self reporting and medical observation/queries at each clinical visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7, 14, 21 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of adverse events, and their relationship to the investigational products. Adverse events from cosmetic cleansers and creams are usually mild. These will be assessed via subject self reporting and medical observation/queries at each clinical visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7, 14, 21 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male or females over 18 years of age.
2. A confirmed diagnosis of eczema according to the criteria of Hanifin &amp; Rajka for at least one year, with moderate severity (score of 10-20) as evaluated with the EASI.
3. Free of any dermatological or systemic disorder which could interfere with the results, at the discretion of the Investigator.
4. Free of any acute or chronic disease that may interfere with or increase the risk of study participation.
5. Completed a preliminary medical history form.  
6. Have read, understood and signed an informed consent document relating to the specific type of study they are subscribing.
7. Able to cooperate with the Investigator and research staff, willing to have the test materials applied according to the protocol, and complete the full course of the study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Individuals under 18 years of age.
2. History of allergies or adverse reactions to moisturisers or the components of the specific products being tested.
3. Use of other moisturising products or other topical eczema therapies in the week prior to participation in this trial.
4. Use of other moisturising products or other topical eczema therapies during the trial.
5. Individuals taking any medication (topical or systemic) that may mask or interfere with the test results, i.e. calcineurin inhibitors, oral corticosteroids.
6. A history of any acute or chronic disease that may interfere with or increase the risk of study participation.
7. Excessive hair on the test sites.
8. Individuals diagnosed with chronic skin allergies.
9. Pregnant or nursing females.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment is achieved using numbered containers. Trial product will be randomised and labelled/numbered by the Sponsor. When a subject is enrolled they will be assigned the next randomisation number and given the matching products.  </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be generated by using SAS 'Registered trademark' statistical software.  The randomisation will be constructed to ensure balanced assignment to the study products as time progresses. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To determine the number of subjects needed a power analysis was used. This power analysis has shown that assuming an alpha (a) of 0.05, power (1-ß) of 0.8, a difference between group means of 12% and a standard deviation of 20, approximately 50 subjects per group are required.

The Students t-test will be used to test if there is a statistically significant difference in EASI score, TEWL, skin hydration, DLQI and quantity of Zatamil Hydrogel used in the active and placebo groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ego Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>21-31 Malcolm Road
Braeside Vic 3195</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ego Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>21-31 Malcolm Road
Braeside Vic 3195</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine if two cosmetic products, a cleanser and a moisturiser, containing ceramides can be of benefit for those with moderate eczema. It is hypothesised that daily use of such products will be of benefit as part of the maintenance regimen for those with moderate eczema.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limtied</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-04-270</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stephen Shumack</name>
      <address>St George Dermatology and Skin Cancer Centre
Belgrave St Unit Trust
Level 3, 22 Belgrave Street
Kogarah 
New South Wales 2217
</address>
      <phone>+61295874277</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> sshumack@iinet.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fabrizio Spada</name>
      <address>Ego Pharmaceuticals
21-31 Malcolm Road
Braeside Vic 3195</address>
      <phone>+61395868874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fabrizio.spada@egopharm.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fabrizio Spada</name>
      <address>Ego Pharmaceuticals
21-31 Malcolm Road
Braeside Vic 3195</address>
      <phone>+61395868874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fabrizio.spada@egopharm.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>