<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372040">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000703303p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A novel bundled intervention (4Ds) to improve adherence with phosphate control in people receiving haemodialysis for end stage kidney disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Nurse-led teach back intervention to improve adherence with phosphate control in people receiving haemodialysis for end stage kidney disease. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1196-1365</utrn>
    <trialacronym>‘Taking control of your phosphate ‘4Ds’.</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic kidney disease </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention was guided by the behavioural theory Social Cognitive Theory. It consists of six (30-45 minutes) individual face to face educational sessions with the aid of a PowerPoint presentation via a laptop, teach-back and a booklet. Four initial educational sessions are in weeks one, two, three, four; and two booster sessions in weeks eight and 12. Both the educational topics and the booklet was developed following a systematic review and in consultation with an expect peer  panel review. The educational topics and the booklet covers information on i) dietary phosphate control, ii) phosphate binder medications to reduce intestinal phosphate absorption, and iii) haemodialysis prescription to promote removal of phosphate. The teach-back method is used as a teaching method to ensure understanding of information provided during the educational session. Participants will also be encouraged to use the booklet during teach-back and at home to guide their self-management goals.  An experience haemodialysis nurse will deliver the intervention to participants during their haemodialysis treatment times. </interventions>
    <comparator>The standard procedure at all three locations involves, an elevated serum phosphate level (&gt;1.6mmol/L) triggering additional general phosphate control education (provided by nurses), review of phosphate binder medications and potentially the dose and/or type of binder altered by either medical practitioner (nephrologist or registrar) or nurse practitioner, and referral to the renal pharmacist.  The role of the pharmacist is to provide education on the amended and/or new phosphate binder prescription (e.g. how, when, dose and side effects). If on the following monthly blood review, the same patient continues to have an elevated serum phosphate level &gt;1.6mmol/L, a referral to the renal dietitian occurs. The dietitian provides general education on diet and drinks high in phosphate to avoid, and low phosphate diet and drinks to consume more frequently. At the end of the study participants in the control group will receive the booklet from the Principal researcher.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome
Serum phosphate levels obtained from clinical laboratory results</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point  2 = week 4, Time point 3 = week 8, Time point 4 = week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General knowledge on phosphate control methods measured with a 20 item self-report instrument adapted from Ford, Pope, Hunt, &amp; Gerald, 2004. The instrument has been validated in the study population.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1: Baseline
Repeated measurement: - Time point 3: week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of adherence to diet and drinks measured with a seven item self-report instrument adapted from Karavetian &amp; Ghaddar, 2013. The instrument has been validated in the study population.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point 3: week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of adherence to drugs (phosphate binder medication) measured with a eight item self-report instrument adapted from Morisky, Ang, Krousel-Wood, &amp; Ward, 2008. The instrument has been validated in the study population.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point 3: week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of adherence to haemodialysis  attendance (skipping and shortening behaviours) measured with a nine item self-report instrument adapted from Kim, Evangelista, Phillips, Pavlish, &amp; Kopple, 2010 and information from electronic medical records. The instrument has been validated in the study population.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point 3: week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy for managing chronic disease measured with a six item self-report instrument adapted from Lorig, et al., 2001. The instrument has been validated in the study population.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point 3: week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum corrected calcium levels obtained from clinical laboratory results</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point  2 = week 4, Time point 3 = week 8, Time point 4 = week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum haemoglobin levels obtained from clinical laboratory results.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point  2 = week 4, Time point 3 = week 8, Time point 4 = week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum potassium levels  obtained from clinical laboratory results</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point  2 = week 4, Time point 3 = week 8, Time point 4 = week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum albumin levels obtained from clinical laboratory results</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1= Baseline
Repeated measurement: Time point  2 = week 4, Time point 3 = week 8, Time point 4 = week 12 (intervention conclusion) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age (18 years and over)
End stage kidney disease undergoing in-centre haemodialysis (three times per week) for at least three months
Able to speak English language
Elevated average serum phosphate levels of &gt;1.6mmol/L for the previous three months before   the study  
Willing to participate
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Malnourished (as protein intake takes precedence over phosphate control)
Receiving or under going home haemodialysis
Diagnosed with functional psychosis or organic brain disorder
Living in a nursing home as it is difficult for them to self-manage
Receiving palliative treatment
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation done by a computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Not applicable </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size estimation was based on figures derived from a previous study that used serum phosphate level as a physiological index of adherence to dietary phosphate and phosphate binder medication (Shi, et al., 2013). The sample size was calculated assuming 80% power (1-beta= 0.8), a type 1 error rate (alpha) of 5% (two-tailed) and an effect size of 0.5 (Standard Deviation = 0.39 mmol/L). Based on these parameters, using the online calculator 
http:/biostat.mc.vanderbilt.edu/wiki/Main/PowerSampleSize version 3.1.2, 2014, a sample size of 21 participants per group is needed. 
However, the sample size was inflated by a design effect of 0.03 which assumes a moderate intra-cluster correlation and an approximate cluster size of 21 participants. The calculation was further inflated by 20% to compensate for attrition and also by a further 15% to account for the possibility of non  normality of data forcing for non-parametric statistics. It was estimated a total sample of 60 participants per group (total=120) would be required to detect a meaningful difference of 0.39 mmol/L in serum phosphate level between groups. Three clusters are in each group; therefore 60 participants in the control group will mean that there are 20 participants per haemodialysis unit per shift.
Data analysis conducted on intention-to-treat basis. Measurements with only one measure - mean and Standard deviations utilising unpaired t-test if normal distribution. If non-parametric then Mann-Whitney test performed.
For repeated measures - paired t test.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Redcliffe Hospital - Redcliffe</hospital>
    <hospital>North Lakes Day Hospital - North Lakes</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>4020 - Redcliffe</postcode>
    <postcode>4509 - North Lakes</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Nursing 
Queensland University of Technology 
Kelvin Grove,
 QLD 4059 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> Royal Brisbane and Women’s Hospital Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Metro North Hospital and Health Board, Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital Research  Foundation
Corner Butterfield Street and Bowen Bridge Road
Herston
Queensland 4029
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Health and Medical Research Unit
Queensland Health
GPO Box 48
Brisbane QLD 4001, </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test the effectiveness of an innovative educational intervention 4D. The intervention integrates all four methods of phosphate control, incorporating teach-back as a teaching strategy to improve adherence behaviours to phosphate control in adults receiving haemodialysis, with a target to maintain a serum phosphate level at near normal level between 0.7  1.6mmol/L.  The anticipated study out comes will be reduced serum phosphate levels, increased  knowledge on phosphate control methods, increased adherence to diet, phosphate binder medication and haemodialysis and increased self-efficacy for managing chronic disease
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>none</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp;Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC Office
Royal Brisbane &amp;Women's Hospital
Level 7
Block 7
Butterfield street
Herston
Queensland 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UHREC - Queensland University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Ethics &amp; Integrity
Level 4, 88 Musk Avenue
Kelvin Grove 4059
Queensland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Molly  Milazi</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology
N Block, 
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove 
Queensland 4059</address>
      <phone>+61-4010209084</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>molly.milazi@hdr.qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Molly Milazi</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology
N Block, 
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove 
Queensland 4059</address>
      <phone>+61-4010209084</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>molly.milazi@hdr.qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Molly Milazi</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology
N Block, 
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove 
Queensland 4059</address>
      <phone>+61-4010209084</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>molly.milazi@hdr.qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Molly Milazi</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology
N Block, 
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove 
Queensland 4059
</address>
      <phone>+61-4010209084</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>molly.milazi@hdr.qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>