<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83433">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001077257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>'A multi-centre phase II trial of early treatment intensification with R-ICE (rituximab  ifosfamide, carboplatin, etoposide) chemotherapy followed by BEAM ( BCNU(BCNU is Carmustine), etoposide, ara-C (ara-C is Cytarabine), melphalan) high dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation for patients with poor prognosis diffuse large B-cell lymphoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>This is a multi-centre phase II trial of early treatment intensification with R-ICE (rituximab  ifosfamide, carboplatin, etoposide) chemotherapy followed by BEAM ( BCNU(BCNU is Carmustine), etoposide, ara-C (ara-C is Cytarabine), melphalan) high dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation for patients with poor prognosis diffuse large B-cell lymphoma as identified by interim-treatment PET/CT (Positron emission tomography - computed tomography) performed after four cycles of R-CHOP-14 (rituximab and Cyclophosphamide, Doxorubicin, Vincristine, Prednisone - CHOP - every 14 days) chemotherapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ALLG NHL21</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with CD20+ diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL) with low intermediate, high intermediate, or high risk disease or low risk disease with bulky tumour (&gt; 7.5 cm) who are considered fit and eligible for high dose chemotherapy (HDCT) with Z-BEAM ( Zevalin - BEAM ( BCNU(BCNU is Carmustine), etoposide, ara-C (ara-C is Cytarabine), melphalan) and autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - High grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will receive 4 cycles of R-CHOP (rituximab Cyclophosphamide, Doxorubicin, Vincristine, Prednisone administered every 14 days (R-CHOP-14) and supported with Pegfilgrastim.  Cycle 5 of R-CHOP-14 will be delayed one week, and an interim PET/CT scan will be performed as close as possible (ie, day 17 to day 20) to the planned 5th cycle of R CHOP-14.  Patients who have metabolically inactive disease (PET/CT-negative) will proceed to complete a further two cycles of R-CHOP-14 (total of 6 cycles) plus two doses of rituximab.  Patients who display metabolically active disease (PET/CT-positive) will then receive treatment intensification with rituximab, Ifosfamide, Carboplatin and Etoposide (R-ICE) supported by Pegfilgrastim or Filgrastim for 3 cycles at intervals of 21 days.  Peripheral blood stem cells will be collected following one of the cycles (typically the second or third) of R ICE. Subsequently, responding patients will undergo High Dose Chemotherapy (HDCT)  with Zevalin-BEAM ( Z-BEAM) and autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT).Dose is based on the individual patient Body Surface Area (BSA) calculation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active - PET+ patients recieve R-ICE and Z-BEAM Transplant. whereas the PET- patients will recieve R-CHOP chemotherapy only.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary objective and endpoint:
The primary objective is to demonstrate an absolute improvement of 25% in two-year progression-free survival (PFS) from 20% to 45% in those patients with advanced stage DLBCL who have been identified with a positive interim-treatment PET/CT scan and switched to early treatment intensification using R-ICE chemotherapy followed by HDCT/ASCT in comparison with historical outcomes.

The primary endpoint for this trial is progression-free survival (PFS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>progression-free survival (PFS). PFS is defined as the time from the interim PET/CT scan (after the 4th cycle of R-CHOP-14) to the first observation of disease progression or death from any cause.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary objectives and endpoints:
Event-free survival (EFS). measured for all patients who have a positive interim PET/CT scan after the 4th cycle of treatment. Also using complete metabolic response(CMR), or non-CMR or partial metabolic response, using qualative and semi-qualitative analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post completion of treatment regimen</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete remission rates. disappearance of all detectable clinical evidence of disease and disease-related symptoms if present prior to therapy by a PET scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post completion of treatment regimen</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse rates. by a PET scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post completion of treatment regimen</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival rates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post completion of treatment regimen</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria
1.	Age 18 - 70 years
2.	Male and female patients
3.	Diagnosis of CD20-positive diffuse large B-cell lymphoma on biopsy
4. 	Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-3
5. 	Low-intermediate, high-intermediate, high risk, or low risk disease with bulk (&gt;7.5 cm)
6. 	Previously untreated (except for corticosteroids if required)
Patients considered suitable for dose-intense chemotherapy with R-CHOP-14 with Pegfilgrastim support
Eligible and fit for high dose chemotherapy with Z-BEAM and autologous stem-cell transplantation
Signed informed consent form
A positive baseline fluorodeoxyglucose(FDG) positron emission tomography(PET)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria
1.	Life-expectancy &lt; 3 months
2.	Transformed NonHodgkin lymphoma (NHL) or types of NHL other than DLBCL
3.	Primary Central Nervous System (CNS) or gastrointestinal Mucosa-Associated Lymphoid Tissue (MALT)lymphoma
4.	CD20-negative NHL
5. 	Documented Human Immunodeficiency Viris (HIV)  
6. 	Seropositivity for Hepatitis B [Either 1. HbsAg (surface antigen) positive or 2. HbcAb (core antibody) positive and HbsAb (surface antibody) titre of &lt; 100 iu/ml] unless clearly due to vaccination 
7.	Patients with good prognosis low risk disease (IPI = 0, 1) plus absence of bulk (= 7.5 cm).
8.	Hypersensitivity to components of Zevalin including ibritumomab tiuxetan, Yttrium chloride, other murine proteins, or to any exipients
9.	Pregnant woman
10.	Previously treated lymphoma
11.	Any serious active disease or co-morbid medical condition (according to investigators decision)
12.	Non-compensated cardiac failure
13.	Chronic lung disease with hypoxaemia
14.	Severe psychiatric disease
15.	Poor renal function (creatinine &gt; 150 micromol/L), poor hepatic function (total bilirubin level &gt; 30 mmol/L, transaminases &gt; 2.5 maximum normal level) unless abnormalities are related to the lymphoma
16.	Poor bone marrow reserve as defined by neutrophils &lt; 1.5 x 109/L or platelets &lt; 100 x 109/L, unless related to bone marrow infiltration
17.	Any history of cancer during the last 5 years, with the exception of non-melanoma skin tumours or stage 0 (in situ) cervical carcinoma
18.	Treatment with any investigational drug within 30 days before planned first cycle of chemotherapy and during the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/07/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/12/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>162</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>162</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/07/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group (ALLG)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 10 St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
3002
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group (ALLG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 10 St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
3002
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at the effectiveness of early treatment intensification with R-ICE chemotherapy followed by high dose chemotherapy (HDCT) and autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT) if positive PET/CT, or a further 2 cycles of R-CHOP-14 if negative PET/CT in patients with lymphoma which is classified as CD20 positive diffuse large B cell type who have received an initial 4 cycles of R-CHOP-14 chemotherapy. 

Who is it for? 
You can join this study if you:  have lymphoma which is CD20 positive diffuse large B cell type (DLBCL) have either low intermediate, high intermediate, or high risk disease, or low risk disease with bulky tumour (&gt; 7.5 cm)  are considered fit and eligible for high dose chemotherapy(HDCT) and autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT)  have not received previous treatment for lymphoma. 

Trial details 
All participants will receive treatment with R-CHOP-14 chemotherapy every fourteen days over four cycles. They will then undergo PET/CT scanning. Participants who have scans that show the disease remains active will have their treatment intensified with R-ICE chemotherapy followed by HDCT with Z-BEAM (a special chemotherapy regimen) and ASCT. If the scans show that the cancer is no longer active, they will receive a further two cycles of the R-CHOP-14 chemotherapy. The study aims to monitor participants to see the effectiveness of this new treatment, particularly in relation to an expected increase in the number of patients who remain disease free after two years.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.petermac.org/allg/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>1)  Early treatment intensification with R-ICE and 90Y-ibritumomab tiuxetan (Zevalin)-BEAM stem cell transplantation in patients with high-risk diffuse large B-cell lymphoma patients and positive interim PET after 4 cycles of R-CHOP-14. M. Hertzberg et. al., (2017). Haematologica, 102:  356-363;  doi:10.3324/haematol.2016.154039 

2)  Early Treatment Intensification with R-ICE Chemotherapy Followed By Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation (ASCT) Using Zevalin-BEAM for Patients with Poor Risk Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma (DLBCL) As Identified By Interim PET/CT Scan Performed after Four Cycles of R-CHOP-14: A Multicenter Phase II Study of the Australasian Leukaemia Lymphoma Study Group (ALLG). M. Hertzberg et. al., (2015). Blood, 126: 815. American Society of Hematology, oral presentation.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Mark Hertzberg</name>
      <address>Department of Haematology
Westmead Hospital
Westmead 
2145
New South Wales</address>
      <phone>+610298456274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark_hertzberg@wmi.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Delaine Smith</name>
      <address>Level 2, 10 St Andrews Place 
East Melbourne
3002
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96563656</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 96561420</fax>
      <email>delaine.smith@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Delaine Smith</name>
      <address>Level 2, 10 St Andrews Place 
East Melbourne
3002
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96563656</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 96561420</fax>
      <email>delaine.smith@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>