<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371189">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001481460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of physiotherapy intervention in symptoms of dysmenorrhea.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of physiotherapy intervention in symptoms of dysmenorrhea.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition> dysmenorrhea.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Menstruation and menopause</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Suboccipital inhibition technique: Subject supine, physiotherapist sitting at the bedside with his elbows on the surface of the table. The physiotherapist places both hands below the patients occipital  with his palms facing up. The occipital is placed first on the palms of the hands and the fingers take on a position at right angles so that clearly pointing anteriorly for 5 minutes of pressure. The fingertips touch the bottom edge of the occipital.
3 sessions will be performed, respectively on the 7th, 14th and 21st day of the menstruation. Participants will receive two cycles of treatment</interventions>
    <comparator>Uterus external manipulation technique: Subject supine with the lower limb triple flexion, physiotherapist standing next to the patient. The physiotherapist hand picks patients knees and puts hand head above patients lower abdominal area, taking with thumb and index finger ends uterus fundal. The technique involves slow exert transverse movements to mobilize and slide the uterus and its fascia, for a time of 3 minutes per fundal. In while moving toward the opposite side the lower limbs of the patient to be able to reach all the ROM.
3 sessions will be performed, respectively on the 7th, 14th and 21st day of the menstruation. Participants will receive two cycles of treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the impact of physical therapy in improving the symptoms of dysmenorrhea  by subjective symptoms (Lattinen Index), using an inhibition suboccipital technique and an external manipulation of uterus. Lattinen Index is an instrument of measurement widely used in the area of the treatment and investigation of the chronic pain. We used also the Lattinen scale composed of 5 categories: pain intensity, patient activity, pain frequency, use of analgesics, and hours of sleep. Each category comprises 5 items scored from 0 (better) to 5 (worse). Maximum score of the Lattinen scale is 20; a decrease in score indicates an improvement in patient status. Pain alleviation scores on the scale of 0 to 4 were: 0 (no alleviation), 1 (slight alleviation), 2 (moderate alleviation), 3 (considerable alleviation), 4 (complete alleviation).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, last day of treatment and first two days of menstruation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the impact of physical therapy in improving the symptoms of dysmenorrhea by  the pain related to the vertebral pressure on the uterine innervations trigger points by algometer, using an inhibition suboccipital technique and an external manipulation of uterus.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, last day of treatment and first two days of menstruation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the impact of physical therapy in improving the symptoms of dysmenorrhea  by  pain location with a graphic, using an inhibition suboccipital technique and an external manipulation of uterus.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, last day of treatment and first two days of menstruation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the impact of physical therapy in improving the symptoms of dysmenorrhea by  the index scale of pain, using an inhibition suboccipital technique and an external manipulation of uterus.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, last day of treatment and first two days of menstruation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria will be nulliparous women aged between 18 to 35, with dysmenorrhea for at least 3 months, BMI &lt;30, informed consent signed.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects presenting the following could not participate in the study: 
(i) Previous surgery in the lumbar-pelvic area. (ii) Previous serious injuries (&lt;3 months). (iii) Cervical arthrosis / instability of the cervical ligament. (iv) Vertebrobasilar artery syndrome. (v) physiotherapy-osteopathic pretreatment (&lt;1 month). (vi) IUD use. (vii) Thyroid problems. (viii) Infection and inflammation in acute stage.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>26</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Camilo Jose Cela</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/ Castillo de Alarcon, 49
Urb. Villafranca del Castillo
28692 Madrid</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Camilo Jose Cela</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>C/ Castillo de Alarcon, 49
Urb. Villafranca del Castillo
28692 Madrid</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dysmenorrhoea is defined as the presence of pain during the menstrual cycle. The objective of our study will be to determine the impact of physical therapy on the improvement of this condition, using a suboccipital inhibition technique and an external manipulation of the uterus.  Well enrol patients aged between 18-35 years old, nulliparous and presented with dysmenorrhoea. We`ll divide them into two groups: group 1 received the suboccipital inhibition technique and group 2 an external manipulation of the uterus. Three sessions were performed, respectively on the 7th, 14th and 21st day of the menstruation. The outcomes will be evaluated before and after the intervention and collected in the first two days of menstruation. The variables analysed will be: the subjective symptoms, the pain location, the Lattinen test, the index scale of pain and the pain related to the vertebral pressure on the uterine innervations trigger points. 12 patients will receive two cycles of treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Camilo Jose Cela University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/ Castillo de Alarcon, 49
Urb. Villafranca del Castillo
28692 Madrid</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sara Fiscon</name>
      <address>Camilo Jose Cela University
C/ Castillo de Alarcon, 49
Urb. Villafranca del Castillo
28692 Madrid</address>
      <phone>+39 3383074797</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarafiscon@hotmail.it</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ELENA RODRIGUEZ LOPEZ</name>
      <address>Camilo Jose Cela University
C/ Castillo de Alarcon, 49
Urb. Villafranca del Castillo
28692 Madrid</address>
      <phone>+34679336394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>esrodriguez@ucjc.edu</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ELENA RODRIGUEZ LOPEZ</name>
      <address>Camilo Jose Cela University
C/ Castillo de Alarcon, 49
Urb. Villafranca del Castillo
28692 Madrid</address>
      <phone>+34679336394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>esrodriguez@ucjc.edu</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>