<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83670">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000586213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the effectiveness of 4 disposable supraglottic airway devices and one reusable Laryngeal Mask Airway (LMA) classic for use in flexible bronchoscopy in children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of the effectiveness (in terms of ease of manipulation of the scope and resistance encountered) of 4 disposable supraglottic airway devices and one reusable Laryngeal Mask Airway (LMA) classic for use in flexible bronchoscopy in children with acute and chronic lung disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>bronchiectasis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>recurrent cough</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>recurrent lower respiratory tract infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>4 Disposable LMAs : Unique (Polyvinyl Chloride (PVC) construction) similar in form to the LMA Classic, Portex soft seal(PVC construction also similar form to the LMA Classic), Ambu Aura Once (green preformed curve PVC construction with an inflateable cuff similar to the LMA CLassic), Boss systems (disposable silicone construction very sinilar in construction to the LMA CLassic) are compared to the Classic LMA (high grade medical silicone construction) in an randomised clinical trial in children below the weight of 50Kg.  Each child is randomised to one of the disposable LMAs, which is inserted into the airway under general anesthesia for a duration of approximately 10minutes and a flexible bronchscopy is performed via the LMA.  The LMA Classic is inserted in the same patient either preceding or following the disposable LMA (during the same general anaesthetic) depending on randomisation order. Bronchoscopy is performed via the LMA Classic also for a duration of approximately 10 minutes.  Observations are made throughout both processes and the final LMA removed prior to recovery from general anesthesia.</interventions>
    <comparator>The LMA company 'Classic LMA' is a medical grade silicone contructed supraglottic airway inserted into the mouth and resting above the larynx in the supraglottic space.  It is used for maintaining a clear airway during general anaesthesia.  Thois particular design is considered a gold standard for supraglottic airway devices due to the number of safety and efficacy trials in the literature. The Classic LMA is inserted for half of the time required to complete the flexible bronchscopy study (generally 10 minutes)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>difference between each disposable LMA and the Classic LMA with regard to resistance encountered to scope manipulation 1. in the LMA 2. at the vocal cords 3. below the vocal cords 4. overall impression of ease of use.  These are all subjectively scored on a 10cm line by the bronchoscopist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately following attempted bronchoscopy with each Laryngeal mask</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cuff pressures when inflated within manufacturers guidelines</outcome>
      <timepoint>pressures are measured with a pressure manometer immediately following inflation of the laryngeal mask cuff and pressure reduced immediately to 20cmH2O</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cuff volumes measured using a syringe to extract the air in the cuff following removal of the laryngeal mask from the child's airway (cuff pressure while in te airway was standardised at 20cmH2O</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately following removal of laryngeal mask</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>leak pressures with cuff inflated to 20cm water are measured by increasing the pressure release valve for the anaesthetic cicuit to 30cmH2O and observing the highest pressure obtained in the circuit (determined by the pressure at which the air leaks aound the laryngeal mask and out of the child's mouth</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately apon measuring the leak pressure during the general anaesthetic</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>all children presenting for flexible bronchoscopy at Starship Children's Health between March 2008 and April 2009 or until 100 patients are recruited</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>weight &gt;50kg
children with previous difficult bronchoscopy
children deemed too unwell to use an LMA or change an LMA during the procedure
patient or caregiver or physician refusal
allergy to any material used for the study
family or child refusal</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>randomised by computer generated programme to one of the 4 disposable LMAs and every child received the Classic LMA.  The order in which the 2 LMAs are inserted is also randomised.  The respiratory physician who enrolled their patient in the study was unaware of the randomisation result.  The anaesthetist performing the anaesthetic was aware of the randomisation result only after the patient was enrolled.  The holder of the randomisation schedule was on-site (although outside the clinical area) approximately 50% of the time and off site the other 50%. Contact was made to obtain randomisation details only following enrollment.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated randomisation programme</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>no</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Katharine Brunette (Young)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 28478 Remuera Auckland 1541</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland Hospital Anaesthetic Department Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 92019
Victoria Street West
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 92019
Victoria Street West
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Paul Baker</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 28478 Remuera Auckland 1541</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Catherine Byrnes</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 28478 Remuera Auckland 1541</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Laryngeal masks (LMAs) are ideally suited to support flexible bronchoscopic examination and lavage of the airways.  Recently at Starship Childrens Health, concerns arose with a move from reusable LMAs, which have potential infective risks, to a disposable version.  Increased resistance to the bronchoscope increases the difficulty and duration of the procedure.  This can necessitate additional lubrication and/or the use of scissors to modify the mask- neither measure is ideal.  Our goal is to compare available disposable LMA devices (LMA unique, Portex Soft Seal, Boss , AMBU) with the reusable classic LMA for efficiency and effectiveness in the paediatric flexible bronchoscopy service.  Our bench testing of various LMAs in mannequins allowed selection of those most appropriate to assess in clinical practice.  Caregivers of the children on the fortnightly bronchoscopy list will be invited to take part.  Children will be randomised to 1 of the disposable devices, and the reusable LMA.  The respiratory paediatrician will grade each device for resistance to scope manipulation, laryngeal view and overall ease of use.  A formal prospective study would be helpful to assist our own, national and international decision making as recommendations move towards using disposable items where possible.  No company is sponsoring this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 1031 Hamilton 3240</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NYT/07/12/134</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katharine Brunette</name>
      <address>PO Box 28478 Remuera Auckland 1541</address>
      <phone>+6421309315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katiejess@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katharine Brunette</name>
      <address>PO Box 28478 Remuera Auckland 1541</address>
      <phone>+64 9 376 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katiejess@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katharine Brunette</name>
      <address>PO Box 28478 Remuera 1541 Auckland</address>
      <phone>+6421309315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katiejess@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>