<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365850">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000233628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluate changes in physical activity levels in the weeks following left ventricular assist device implantation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of left ventricular assist device implantation on physical activity levels in patients with chronic heart failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic heart failure </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Stable participants with left ventricular assist devices (LVADs) support will be assigned to the intervention group and chronic heart failure participants with current NYHA functional class III/IV heart failure symptoms, but without LVADs will be allocated to the control group. All participants in both intervention and control groups will have to complete 2 questionnaires (heart disease self-efficacy scale &amp; SF-36). They will then undergo an exercise test on a treadmill to measure their peak VO2. After the end of the assessment session, all participants will be given accelerometers (Actiheart) to measure their physical activity levels. Participants will be instructed to wear the Actiheart for 7 days and not to alter their usual physical activity during the assessment week. The assessment will be carried out individually at home. During the 7 days of assessment period, they will also receive follow up phone calls from the investigators.   </interventions>
    <comparator>Chronic heart failure participants with current NYHA functional class III/IV heart failure symptoms, but without LVADs will be allocated to the control group (as mentioned above). All participants in the control group will receive standard treatment where they will be taking routine heart failure management pharmaceutical therapy. 

A subgroup of participants in the control group will also be provided with an additional physical activity monitor (Fitbit) that provides feedback to participants about their physical activity levels. The use of Fitbit will help to determine whether feedback about activity levels via mobile phone influences the amount of activity a person undertakes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the physical activity levels in stable participants on left ventricular assist device support, compared to chronic heart failure participants on optimal pharmaceutical management alone.

Actiheart is a small portable device that will be used during physical activity assessment. It measures heart rate, accelerometry or combination of both to calculate ones body energy expenditure (BEE). However, we are relying on accelerometry function alone for this study. 

The accelerometry data collected will be analysed using SPSS, version 21. If the data is normally distributed, unpaired t test will be used to compare the physical activity levels between LVAD and control group. The data not conforming to a normal distribution will be either transformed or analysed using non-parametric statistical test such as Mann-Whitney test. The level of statistical significance will be set at P&lt;0.05.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 7 days of assessment period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the association between the physical activity levels, exercise self-efficacy, quality of life and aerobic capacity in participants on left ventricular assist device support and chronic heart failure participants on optimal pharmaceutical management alone.  

The heart disease self-efficacy scale to be used in the proposed study describes ones ability or confidence to begin, continue and complete a task under several specific circumstances. It consists of 16 statements, each describing a different physical act ranges from 0 to 100 (0 describes an activity that a person cannot do at all and 100 is an activity a person rate as absolutely certain I can do). 

SF-36 questionnaire is a generic instrument that is frequently used to measure ones quality of life relating to a variety of health states. It consists of 36 questions, grouped into 8 health-related aspects of ones life: physical function; social function; physical role; emotional role; mental health; energy; pain and general health perceptions. The score for each of the eight health concepts ranges from 0 (worst health status) to 100 (best health status). 

Cardiopulmonary exercise testing is a non-invasive tool that measures the maximum amount of oxygen consumed by an individual. 12 ECG electrodes will be used to monitor heart rate and rhythm. Participants will be required to breath through a mouthpiece and asked to rate their perceived exertion and dyspnoea using Borg scale.

If the data is normally distributed, Pearson correlation will be used to determine the correlation between physical activity level with self-efficacy, quality of life and aerobic capacity in participants with LVADs support and CHF participants. The data not conforming to a normal distribution will be either transformed or analysed using non-parametric statistical test such as Spearman correlation. The level of statistical significance will be set at P&lt;0.05. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After 7 days of assessment period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Intervention group will have a confirmed history of NYHA functional class III/IV heart failure symptoms (where class III heart failure symptoms is characterised by shortness of breath during low level of activity and class IV heart failure symptoms is characterised by shortness of breath at rest), have been clinically stable on left ventricular assist device for at least 3 months and will be an outpatient. The control group will have NYHA functional class III/IV heart failure symptoms and will be taking routine heart failure management pharmaceutical therapy. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants with co-morbidities that may influence the ability to undertake physical activity (eg. severe renal, pulmonary or hepatic dysfunction, active uncontrolled systemic infection, several mitral or aortic valve insufficiency and severe musculoskeletal disease will be excluded from the study. Participants who receive a cardiac transplant during the physical assessment period will be withdrawn from the study. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>1</followup>
    <followuptype>Weeks</followuptype>
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Case control</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Perth Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>197 Wellington St, Perth CBD WA 6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent Street, Bentley WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Curtin University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Kent Street, Bentley WA 6102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Left ventricular assist devices (LVAD) are pump that are implanted into the heart of patients with impaired heart function (heart failure) to assist in the pumping of blood around the body. An important objective of LVADs is to enable patients to achieve a more active lifestyle. Furthermore, physical activity and exercise are important components of the rehabilitation of patients with LVADs. The aim of this study is to compare the physical activity levels of stable patients with LVAD support (intervention group) compared with patients with advanced heart failure receiving optimal pharmaceutical management, but without LVAD support (control group). </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>197 Wellington St, Perth CBD WA 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REG 13-122</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
GPO Box U1987 Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+618 92242681</phone>
      <fax>+618 92241464</fax>
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987 Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+618 92242681</phone>
      <fax>+618 92241464</fax>
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987 Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+618 92242681</phone>
      <fax>+618 92241464</fax>
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sylvia Liew Wang Ying</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
GPO Box U1987 Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61414817977</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.liew1@student.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>