<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364299">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000614796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of bright light therapy to improve mood in residential care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of bright light therapy to improve mood in residents in residential aged care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1143-3342 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depressive symptoms
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive decline</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will spend 1 hour in a room fitted with bright lights that provide 2000-3000 lux at eye level. Light intensity will be measured using a calibrated light meter.  The room has space for six residents and one staff member, with a central table and toilet facilities located adjacent to the room.  The bright light exposure period will be from 10am-11am, Monday to Friday for two weeks.  While in the room, a staff member will be present and will provide residents with morning tea and conduct social activities or assist residents as needed.  Residents will be encouraged to remain in the room for the one hour period; however if they wish to leave they will not be prevented from doing so.  The residential aged care facility has 2 floors with the same living room on each floor to be used for the study - on one floor the room is fitted with bright lights for the intervention group. This will also enable bright light and usual light groups to occur at the same time.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will spend 1 hour in a room fitted with standard lights (300-500 lux at eye level). Light intensity will be measured using a calibrated light meter.  The room has space for six residents and one staff member, with a central table and toilet facilities located adjacent to the room.  The usual light exposure period will be from 10am-11am, Monday to Friday for two weeks.  While in the room, a staff member will be present and will provide residents with morning tea and conduct social activities or assist residents as needed.  Residents will be encouraged to remain in the room for the one hour period; however if they wish to leave they will not be prevented from doing so.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression as measured by a score of 5 or more on the Geriatric Depression Scale - 15 item version.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the week following the intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ADL status: Modified Barthel Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the week following the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression in Dementia: Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the week following the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognition: Standardised Mini Mental State Examination</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the week following the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: Six Dimensional Assessment of Quality of Life tool (20 item)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the week following the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuropsychiatric Symptoms: Neuropsychiatric Inventory  Nursing Home version</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the week following the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Vasey RSL Brighton East residents.
-Residents with low mood who have capacity to consent, or who have a person responsible who is able to provide consent.  
-Residents who are able to be transported to the light therapy room or equivalent and able to remain in the room for a one hour period.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Residents who are receiving palliative care
-Residents with severe eye disease
-Residents who require a secure facility</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Residents identified by staff as having low mood will be invited to participate. Consent will be sought from the resident and/or person responsible. Following the baseline assessment, participants will be randomised to the intervention or control group. Allocation will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is off-site from the residential aged care facility. </concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random number sequence will determine group allocation and project staff will be informed.  Randomisation will occur in blocks as the intervention can only be conducted with a limited number of people at a time. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome measure will be the GDS.  Based on a reduction in the presence of depression (as defined by a score of 5 or more on the GDS) to 60% in the intervention group, and no change in the control group, 15 participants in each group will be required (80% power, alpha 0.05, 2 tailed).  Allowing for drop-outs, 18 people in each group need to be recruited. All data will be analysed using intention to treat analysis.  The difference in the presence of depression between the control group and intervention group will be analysed using chi-square analysis.  To analyse the effect of the intervention on secondary outcomes, linear regression will be used for continuous variables, and logistic regression used for categorical variables. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3187 - Brighton East</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Ageing Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital 
Victoria 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lord Mayors Charitable Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1851
Melbourne 
Victoria 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Vasey RSL Care</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>172 Burwood Road
Hawthorn 
Victoria 3122 </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many older people in residential aged care settings receive reduced levels of bright light. Bright light is essential for maintaining the body clock (circadian rhythm). This project is a randomised controlled trial to investigate whether bright light therapy can help reduce depressive symptoms in older people living in residential care. Residents from Vasey RSL Brighton East will be randomised into an intervention or control group. The intervention group will spend time in a lounge room equipped with bright lights (of at least 2,000 lux) for one hour each morning, Monday to Friday for 2 weeks. The control group will spend time in a room equipped with normal lights (300-500 lux) for one hour each morning, Monday to Friday for 2 weeks. Depressive symptoms will be measured using the Geriatric Depression Scale before and after the treatment period. Secondary outcomes to be investigated include cognition, behaviour and quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Level 6 East, Main Building
300 Grattan Street
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  VIC  3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2013.131</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kirsten Moore</name>
      <address>National Ageing Research Institute
PO Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>61 3 8387 2200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.moore@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kirsten Moore</name>
      <address>National Ageing Research Institute
PO Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>61 3 8387 2200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.moore@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kirsten Moore</name>
      <address>National Ageing Research Institute
PO Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>61 3 8387 2200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.moore@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Batchelor</name>
      <address>National Ageing Research Institute
PO Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>61 3 8387 2383</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.batchelor@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>