<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373518">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001323314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot phase for the Tension-type HeadAche Prevention Project (HAPPy Too) to investigate in a double-blind, randomised trial whether treatment with low-dose blood pressure (BP) lowering therapy on top of standard care will reduce tension-type headache compared to placebo and standard care.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigator initiated, multi-centre, randomised, double-blind placebo controlled study to assess the effectiveness and tolerability of low-dose combination blood pressure lowering therapy in patients with tension-type headache .</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HAPPy Too</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tension-type Headache</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The HAPPy Too trial is a double-blind randomised controlled trial in participants with frequent episodic tension-type headache (TTH). The duration of the trial is 16 weeks in total (12 weeks of treatment + 4 weeks of observation) with an additional 4-week screening period prior to randomisation.
The 4-week screening period will record number of headache days in that month and laboratory test results to confirm eligibility to receive study treatment. All eligible participants will be randomised and followed for a period of 16 weeks. The treatment period will be for 12 weeks. Unblinding will be avoided by using a uniform medication procedure for all groups. Randomised participants who deviate from the protocol/ and or discontinue allocated BP intervention will still be followed up to 16 weeks as their data will be analysed on the intention to treat principle. The 13 and 16 week follow ups will assess for rebound headache and hypertension.
During the 12-week treatment period, participants will be randomised to one of two arms: low-dose combination of telmisartan (20mg), amlodipine (2.5mg) and indapamide (1.25mg) OR placebo. Participants will take one capsule orally, daily. The capsule will either be a low-dose combination (telmisartan + amlodipine + indapamide) or placebo. 
To maximise participants adherence to the study medications the following processes will be implemented:
	Participant education during all visits on the importance of taking study medication, including timing, storage and what to do in the event of a missed dose
	Participants will be instructed to return unused capsules at each follow up visit (visit 3-5), and returned capsules will be counted by the study team.
	Reminder text messages to commence study treatment after randomisation 
	Participants will be encouraged to contact a member of the study team if for any reason they are unable to continue their study medication or have missed multiple doses and are unsure whether to continue.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - commonly used excipients (to be determined) received via blinded study capsules</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change from baseline in mean monthly TTH days at 12 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Headache diary to be completed by participant; reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change from baseline in mean monthly hours with TTH</outcome>
      <timepoint>Headache diary to be completed by participant; reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects with at least a 50% reduction from baseline in monthly TTH days </outcome>
      <timepoint>Headache diary to be completed by participant; reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in monthly TTH medication treatment days
(Medication treatment day is defined as any day in which the patient takes medication other than study medication to treat their TTH.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Headache diary to be completed by participant; reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in monthly lost productive work days due to TTH</outcome>
      <timepoint>Headache diary to be completed by participant; reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in the number of reduced productivity work hours per month</outcome>
      <timepoint>Headache diary to be completed by participant; reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in health-related quality of life (HRQoL) - assessed through the use of Headache Impact Test-6 (HIT-6)</outcome>
      <timepoint>HRQoL will be assessed through the use of Headache Impact Test-6 at Baseline (0 weeks), 12 and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in DBP and SBP</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood pressure (DBP and SBP) will be recorded at screening (-4 weeks), baseline (0 weeks), 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability - Difference between groups in potentially-related side-effects (dizziness, blurred vision, syncope/ collapse/ fall, ankle oedema, skin rash, itching, gout, hyperkalaemia, hypokalaemia, hyponatraemia, rebound hypertension)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks.
Participants will be asked (self-reported) if they have experienced any of the potentially-related side effects at all visits. These adverse events of special interest (AESIs) will be monitored and recorded as new or ongoing and reported to the CCC regardless of seriousness or severity</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Percentage with any severe adverse event (SAE)
Self reported by participants during follow up visits.
An SAE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence that at any dose:
	Results in death
	Is life threatening in the opinion of the attending clinician (i.e. The patient was at risk of death at the time of the event; it does not refer to an event that might hypothetically have caused death had it been more severe)
	Requires inpatient hospitalisation or prolongation of existing hospitalisation (any hospitalisation that was planned prior to randomisation will not meet sae criteria. Any hospitalisation that is planned post-randomisation will meet the SAE criteria)
	Results in persistent or significant disability or incapacity
	Results in congenital anomaly or birth defect (note that the females in the study population are likely to be post-menopausal)
	Is an important medical event in the opinion of the attending clinician that is not immediately life-threatening and does not result in death or hospitalisation but which may jeopardise the patient or may require intervention to prevent one of the other outcomes listed above
</outcome>
      <timepoint>An adverse event that meets the above categories between when the informed consent form is signed and the 1 month post study visit at week 16 will be reported as an SAE. All SAEs are required to be reported to TGI within 24 hours of the study team first becoming aware of the event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication Adherence: Self-reported measures - participants will inform study personnel if they have missed any doses or misplaced any capsules. Participants will be instructed to return unused capsules at each follow up visit (visit 3-5), and returned capsules will be counted by the study team.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability - Difference between groups in participant withdrawals from treatment </outcome>
      <timepoint>Reviewed every 4 weeks, patient follow up: 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>	Frequent episodic TTH according to the diagnostic criteria of the IHS
	2-14 days per month with headache averaged over past 3 months (90-days), as self-reported by subject
	Headache must have been present for &gt;=1 year prior to enrollment in the study.
	Onset of symptoms must have occurred before the age of 50 years
	Adults between 18 and 65 years
	Office SBP &gt;=130mmHg and/or DBP &gt;=80 mmHg 
	No definite contraindications to any of the study medications at the doses used in this trial. (Subjects can be taking other preventive and therapeutic medications as long as they do not contraindicate study medication. Patients will not be eligible if they are taking medications from the same class as the study treatments)
	Is medically stable as determined by the Study Investigator
	If the patient has concomitant migraine attacks, he/she must be able to differentiate between TTH and migraine. The frequency of migraine attacks must not exceed one attack per month during the preceding year.
	Is able to take oral medication, adhere to the medication regimens, and perform study procedures over the study duration.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Contraindication to any of telmisartan, amlodipine, indapamide, or placebo
	Concomitantly taking an ARB, ACE-I, CCB, or diuretic.
	Definite indication to any one or more of the study medications
	Subject has history of cluster headaches
	Medication overuse headaches according to HIS criteria
	Female patients who are pregnant, nursing, or those not using adequate birth control, if capable of bearing children.
	Chronic medical illnesses (e.g. lupus) that could potentially affect frequency of headache as determined by the Study Investigator
	Alcohol or substance abuse within the last year
	Any concurrent medical or psychiatric condition which, in the investigator's judgment, may interfere with study conduct or which contraindicates participation
	Abnormal creatinine or electrolytes on screening.
	Inability to provide informed consent
	Participation in an interventional medical investigation or clinical trial currently or within the past 3 months.  Subjects in observational, natural history and/or epidemiological studies not involving an intervention are eligible.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The randomisation allocation will be blinded to all participants and study team members except the primary study statistician and the manufacturer of the investigational products. All individual medications will be over-encapsulated and concealed by identical packaging, labelling and administration scheduling.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute for Global Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 10, King George V Building
Missenden Road
Camperdown, NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The George Institute for Global Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 10, King George V Building
Missenden Road
Camperdown, NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recurrent headache is a common, disabling condition affecting millions of Australians.  TTH has a lifetime prevalence in the general population ranging between 30 and 78%. It affects approximately 1.4 billion people globally or 20.8% of the population. Headaches are a leading cause of lost work productivity, with reduced performance rather than absence from work being the main cause of lost productive time.
Therefore, there would be considerable value in a simple, highly tolerable preventive therapy for the large number of people suffering from frequent TTH.  This trial aims to assess a novel low-dose BP lowering combination in this regard.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee (Royal Prince Alfred Hospital (RPAH) Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road, CAMPERDOWN, NSW, 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/RPAH/161</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anthony Rodgers</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, Australia
Level 10, King George V Building, 83-117 Missenden Rd, 
Camperdown NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4375</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>arodgers@georgeinstitute.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ruth Freed</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, Australia
Level 10, King George V Building, 83-117 Missenden Rd, 
Camperdown NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4522</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rfreed@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cheryl Carcel</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, Australia
Level 10, King George V Building, 83-117 Missenden Rd, 
Camperdown NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4508</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ccarcel@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Grace Balicki</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, Australia
Level 10, King George V Building, 83-117 Missenden Rd, 
Camperdown NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8052 4811</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gbalicki@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>