<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82718">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000165381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Detecting injury to the heart after emergency orthopaedic surgery by means of a blood test (called Troponin I) and determining if care by the cardiology unit can improve mortality at one year compared to usual care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Troponin rise after emergency orthopaedic-geriatric surgery randomised to standard care versus cardiology care and its associaton with one year mortality</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myocardial injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All recruited patients will have troponin blood tests and electrocardiographs (ECGs) done on post-operative days 1,2 and 3.  Patients with a post-operative troponin rise will then be randomised to either standard care or cardiology care (the intervention).  The  cardiology care protocol involves a "total package" of care.  This involves transfer to the coronary care unit for 24hours, review by a cardiologist and consideration for catheterisation if symptomatic.  If not for catheterisation or if asymptomatic cardiology treatment will involve medical management with aspirin, beta blocker, statin +/- Angiotensin Converting Enzyme (ACE) inhibitor.  All medications will be given orally with the dose and frequency at the discretion of the cardiologist.  Duration of medication treatment will be for at least the duration of hospitalization with ongoing medication treatment at the discretion of the cardiologist.  Patients randomised to coronary care will also have cardiac investigations including serial ECGs, chest x-ray, lipid profile, echocardiogram.  All patients randomised to coronary care will also receive outpatient follow up by a cardiologist and a functional cardiac study (either dobutamine stress echocardiography or thallium stress test, only if they are a candidate for catheterisation in the future).</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients with a troponin rise who are randomised to standard care will continue to receive usual ward care from the orthopaedic-geriatric unit.  The usual care for patients after an orthopaedic operation at The Northern Hospital is to be reviewed by both the orthopaedic and geriatric units for the duration of the hospital admission. Patients who develop cardiac symptoms will still be elligible for cardiology review (including coronary care) if the treating team feel it is appropriate as this is part of standard ward care for symptomatic patients (eg. chest pain, arrhythmia, haemodynamically unstable, cardiac arrest).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>all cause mortality at one year</outcome>
      <timepoint>one year after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>all cause mortaliy</outcome>
      <timepoint>in hospital and at 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cardiac events (eg.Myocardial infarction, ischaemia, heart failure, major arrhythmia, cardiac arrest)</outcome>
      <timepoint>in hospital, 6 months, 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ECG changes and correlation with troponin rises</outcome>
      <timepoint>in hospital, 6 months, 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>functional status measured by barthels index</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 6 months, 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Investigations and medications ordered by the cardiologist in comparison to standard care</outcome>
      <timepoint>in hospital, 6 months, 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients over 60 admited under the orthopaedic unit who undergo emergency surgery</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Elective surgery, die before surgery, admitted under a different unit, patients with an estimated mortality of less than 1 year (eg. terminal cancer), nursing home patients.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment using pre-sealed tamper-evident evelopes will be used to enrol subjects (pre-sealed by an individual not involved in the trial).  Envelopes will be opened in order of patient recruitment and signed by two people.</concealment>
    <sequence>A statistical program will be used to generate block randomisation with variable block sizes.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/04/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>154</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3076</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Carol Chong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Northern Hospital
c/o Northern Clinical Research Centre
185 Cooper Street
Epping, 3076
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will determine whether standard care or cardiology care improves survival for patients undergoing emergency orthopaedic-geriatric surgery with a troponin rise.
A pilot study conducted at The Northern Hospital in 2006 revealed that at one year mortality rate was 21% in this population and those with a troponin rise were more at risk of dying.  Therefore, this RCT is proposed to see if cardiology care is any better than standard care to improve survival.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Northern Hospital
185 Cooper Street
Epping, 3076
Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Carol Chong</name>
      <address>The Northern Hospital
c/o Northern Clinical Research Centre
185 Cooper Street
Epping, 3076
Victoria</address>
      <phone>03 8405 2008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carol.chong@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Carol Chong</name>
      <address>The Northern Hospital
c/o Northern Clinical Research Centre
185 Cooper Street
Epping, 3076
Victoria</address>
      <phone>03 8405 2008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carol.chong@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>