<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364015">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001099516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Haemodynamic Effect of Intravenous Paracetamol during and after Cardiac Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Haemodynamic Effect of Intravenous Paracetamol during and after Cardiac Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiopulmonary bypass</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intravenous paracetamol (Actavis, North Adelaide, SA)

Paracetamol is one of the most commonly used medications in the world. The intravenous format is the preferred method of administration in the intraoperative and immediate postoperative periods. 

In 100mL of solution for infusion, intravenous paracetamol contains the following:

Paracetamol = 1g
Mannitol = 3.91g

Cysteine hydrochloride monohydrate
Dibasic dihydrate sodium phosphate
Sodium hydroxide
Hydrochloric acid
Water for injections

The insertion of a pulmonary artery catheter (PAC) is required for routine anaesthesia treatment during cardiac surgery. Haemodynamic measurements will be monitored via the PAC. After insertion of the PAC, 100mL paracetamol (containing 1g paracetamol and 3.91g mannitol) will be administered intravenously. 

Volume of paracetamol to be administered:
Actavis (North Adelaide, SA) recommends 1g of paracetamol per administration with a maximum of 4g of paracetamol per day. The minimum dose interval is 4 hours. The duration of infusion is 15 minutes. 

In this trial, a 1g of paracetamol will be administered every 6 hours, for 3 consecutive doses, which is in line with the manufacturer's recommendations.  The first dose will be administered on arrival to the operating room, prior to induction of anaesthesia. The second dose will be administered 6 hours after the first, which may be  near completion of surgery or in the intensive care unit. The final dose will be 6 hours later in the intensive care unit. The duration of each infusion will be set at 15 minutes.

Paracetamol will be administered in addition to standard care analgesia.  In accordance with strict hospital protocols, all doses of paracetamol administered will be recorded or logged on the participants analgesic chart. </interventions>
    <comparator>Normal saline 0.9% is an intravenous fluid solution that provides maintenance and replacement of deficits of extracellular fluid. It is commonly used throughout the world as an infusion proving water for hydration for patients undergoing major surgery. 

For this clinical trial 100 ml Normal Saline 0.9% will be administered every 6 hours over a 15 minute period, for 3 consecutive doses. The first dose will be administered on arrival to the operating room, prior to induction of anaesthesia. The second dose will be administered 6 hours after the first, which may be  near completion of surgery or in the intensive care unit. The final dose will be 6 hours later in the intensive care unit. The duration of each infusion will be set at 15 minutes.

In accordance with strict hospital protocols, all doses of saline administered will be recorded or logged on the participants fluid balance chart. 

All patients will also receive standard postoperative analgesia.  </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is a composite outcome using pressure based haemodynamic variables, namely systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, mean arterial blood pressure. These will be recorded from a arterial line inserted as part of standard care that measure continuous systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, and mean arterial blood pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome will be measures at the following peri-operative timepoints using the measurements from the arterial line. 

1. Baseline (BL) just after pulmonary artery catheter insertion
2. 5 minutes (T5)
3. 10 minutes (T10)
4. 15 minutes (T15)
5. 30 minutes (T30)
6. Pre-cardiopulmonary bypass
7. Rewarming
8. ICU arrival (ICU 1)
9. ICU 6 hours (ICU 6)
10. ICU 12 hours (ICU 12)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac output will be measured by a bolus thermodilution technique using a Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary outcome will be measured at the following peri-operative timepoints using the measurements from the Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter:

1. Baseline (BL) just after pulmonary artery catheter insertion
2. 5 minutes (T5)
3. 10 minutes (T10)
4. 15 minutes (T15)
5. 30 minutes (T30)
6. Pre-cardiopulmonary bypass
7. Rewarming
8. ICU arrival (ICU 1)
9. ICU 6 hours (ICU 6)
10. ICU 12 hours (ICU 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac index will be measured by a bolus thermodilution technique using a Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary outcome will be measured at the following peri-operative timepoints using the measurements from the Swan-Ganz pulmonary artery catheter:

1. Baseline (BL) just after pulmonary artery catheter insertion
2. 5 minutes (T5)
3. 10 minutes (T10)
4. 15 minutes (T15)
5. 30 minutes (T30)
6. Pre-cardiopulmonary bypass
7. Rewarming
8. ICU arrival (ICU 1)
9. ICU 6 hours (ICU 6)
10. ICU 12 hours (ICU 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma paracetamol levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Plasma paracetamol levels will be measured at the following peri-operative timepoints:  

1. Baseline (BL) just after pulmonary artery catheter insertion
2. 5 minutes (T5)
3. 10 minutes (T10)
4. 15 minutes (T15)
5. 30 minutes (T30)
6. Pre-cardiopulmonary bypass
7. Rewarming
8. ICU arrival (ICU 1)
9. ICU 6 hours (ICU 6)
10. ICU 12 hours (ICU 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary end point of renal biomarkers, which will include including serum and urine NGAL and cystatin C. These renal biomarkers are sensitive indicators of renal injury and inflammation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Serum and urine NGAL and cystatin C levels will be measured at the following peri-operative timepoints:  

1. Baseline (BL) just after pulmonary artery catheter insertion
2. 5 minutes (T5)
3. 10 minutes (T10)
4. 15 minutes (T15)
5. 30 minutes (T30)
6. Pre-cardiopulmonary bypass
7. Rewarming
8. ICU arrival (ICU 1)
9. ICU 6 hours (ICU 6)
10. ICU 12 hours (ICU 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma (blood) levels of Pro-inflammatory effects using TNF-a, IL-6 and IL-10.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Plasma levels of TNF-a, IL-6 and IL-10 will be measured at the following peri-operative timepoints:  

1. Baseline (BL) just after pulmonary artery catheter insertion
2. 5 minutes (T5)
3. 10 minutes (T10)
4. 15 minutes (T15)
5. 30 minutes (T30)
6. Pre-cardiopulmonary bypass
7. Rewarming
8. ICU arrival (ICU 1)
9. ICU 6 hours (ICU 6)
10. ICU 12 hours (ICU 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Core body temperature will be measure via an electronic  nasal probe temperature transducer that will be inserted 8-10cm into the nasopharyngeal area.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Core body temperature will be measured at the following peri-operative timepoints:  

1. Baseline (BL) just after pulmonary artery catheter insertion
2. 5 minutes (T5)
3. 10 minutes (T10)
4. 15 minutes (T15)
5. 30 minutes (T30)
6. Pre-cardiopulmonary bypass
7. Rewarming
8. ICU arrival (ICU 1)
9. ICU 6 hours (ICU 6)
10. ICU 12 hours (ICU 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first postoperative request for opioid treatment, which will be assessed by review of the medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This timepoint will commence at the completion of surgery until  the first request for opioid treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount of opioid adminstered during stay in ICU, which will be assessed by review of the medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This timepoint will commence at the completion of surgery until  the end of ICU stay.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of inotrope use, which will be assessed by review of the medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This timepoint will commence at the completion of surgery until  the end of ICU stay.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount of fluids used, which will be assessed by review of the medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This timepoint will commence at the completion of surgery until  the end of ICU stay.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type of surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be collected from the medical records. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total volume of administered CPB prime fluids will be collected from the perfusion medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of cardiopulmonary bypass which will  commences when full cardiopulmonary bypass flows are established and concludes once the patient has separated from bypass and spontaneous circulation has been achieved. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Baseline EuroSCORE</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be collected from the medical records.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Baseline Parsonnet indices. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be collected form the medical records.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of ICU stay. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be collected form the medical records.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of hospital stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be collected from the medical records. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Renal failure assessed using the international RIFLE criteria for Acute Kidney injury </outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of hospital stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pneumonia that will be assessed using the international criteria of raised white cell count in addition to focal changes on an x-ray. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of hospital stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Adult surgery patients (age &gt;18 years)
2. Cardiac surgery requiring cardiopulmonary bypass
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Paracetamol use 24 hours prior to surgery (in paracetamol only or in combination therapy)

Pregnancy

Chronic renal impairment (creatinine &gt;250 umol/L)

Chronic liver disease (ALT &gt;200IU/L)

Morbid obesity (BMI &gt;35kg/m2)

Known allergic reaction to IV paracetamol 

Consumption of caffeine (e.g. coffee or energy drinks), consumed within 10 hours of surgery</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients undergoing cardiac surgery are evaluated preoperatively at the cardiac surgery and anaesthesia
pre-admissions clinic at least 4 weeks prior to surgery. Patients will be identified for study entry by the
investigators or an anaesthetist or research co-ordinator acting on behalf of the principle investigators by
surveillance of patients in the pre-admissions clinic.

Allocation concealment will be by sealed opaque envelopes. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two groups using a computer generated
random number allocation system with permuted blocks prior to the commencement of the
study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We will recruit 50 patients in total, 25 patients in the paracetamol group and 25 patients in the control group. This is in keeping with realistic power calculations used in other studies evaluating the haemodynamic effects of IV paracetamol in patients undergoing major surgery.

Sample size for the study was calculated based on our pilot data evaluating patients undergoing cardiac surgery at Austin hospital. With an average blood pressure of 120mmHg, and a SD of 10 mmHg, if we were to demonstrate a mean difference between the paracetamol group and control group of 10mmHg, with a power value of 80%, we require a minimum of 18 patients to be recruited into each group. We will therefore recruit 25 patients in each arm, a total of 50 patients.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>7/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/11/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/11/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Intensive Care
15 Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084

Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Intensive Care
15, Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There are currently no double-blinded, randomised controlled trials that assess the haemodynamic effects of paracetamol in patients undergoing cardiac surgery. The effects of cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) on paracetamol pharmacokinetic are also poorly understood. 

This study will add to a growing body of evidence evaluating the safety and efficacy of paracetamol use in patients undergoing cardiac surgery.

Hypothesis: Paracetamol (1g IV) has adverse effects on blood pressure in patients undergoing cardiac surgery. 

No of patients: 50

No of recruiting hospitals: 1

Randomisation:  Patients will be randomised in a 1:1 fashion via a computer generated randomisation program to either paracetamol IV formulation (N=25) or control treatment (normal saline 0.9%) (N=25). 

Blinding: This is a double-blinded clinical trial. Surgical teams, intraoperative and postoperative nursing staff, and patients will be blinded to assignment of treatment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Research Ethics Unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Health Research Ethics Unit
Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria, 3084 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2013/05006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia Austin Hospital, 15 Studley Road Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax> +61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia Austin Hospital, 15 Studley Road Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax> +61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia Austin Hospital, 15 Studley Road Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax> +61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia Austin Hospital Studley Road Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria </address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax> +61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>