<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366795">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000845639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Blackcurrant supplementation on sporting performance in adolescent hockey players</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of blackcurrant supplement consumption on physical performance, mental acuity and health in adolescent hockey players over an 8-week training period; possible involvement of mitochondrial adaptation?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-1776</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Exercise performance </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Health and fatigue </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive performance </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this nutritional intervention study, we aimed to examine how timed blackcurrant supplementation prior to each training session or game influenced the health, physical and cognitive performance parameters of adolescent field hockey players over an 8-week training period. The blackcurrant (freeze-dried powder) supplement used in this study was enriched with anthocyanins (30%) and was from a commercial supplier (Just-the-Berries, Nelson, New Zealand). The participants were given the blackcurrant extract (equivalent 150 mg anthocyanins) as a small opaque gelatine capsule and asked to consume the supplement 1 hr prior to each training session (4 per week) or hockey game (1-2 per week) over the 8-week period. Compliance was monitored by (i) providing particpants with only enough capsules (placebo or blackcurrant) for a week to ensure that the treatments are being taken (ii) notify the trial co-ordinator by text each time they took their treamtent, and (iii) trial coordinator reminded the particpants. In this study, the trial coordinator for this trial was also a hockey coach and so monitored the participants closely. Participants were asked to maintain their normal eating habits but to omit dietary supplements high in antioxidants over the 8-week period. In addition, trial participants were assessed (a) prior to and after an 8-week training periods and (b) weekly (on the same day each week) for their (i) fitness, (ii) cognitive smart game skills, and (iii) health.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatment comprised of a opaque gelatin capsule containing the equivalent fruit sugar (fructose and glucose) present in the blackcurrant extract given to the particpants. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical performance parameters</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fitness assessment by measuring VO2max was performed prior to the start of the trial and then again at the end of the 8-week training period. VO2 max was assessed on a cycle ergometer. The method used required the subject to cycle at incrementally increasing wattage until volitional fatigue.  At the commencement of the VO2 max test, participants were instructed to cycle at a work rate of 50 W for 2 min followed by incrementally increasing target workload (i.e. 1 W every 2 sec) until volitional fatigue. In addition we performed a series of performance measures weekly. These included (a) Yoyo "bleep" performance test, (b) hand grip strength using a hand grip dyanometer and (c) leg muscle strength using a timed squad against a wall.   </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive performance </outcome>
      <timepoint>This was measured before the start of the 8-week study and then every week on the same day for 8-weeks. Cognitive performance was assessed using a mixture of tests looking at psychomotor skills (Perdue pegboard and finger maze) and a series of 8 short computerized "brain games" on iPads, commerically known as "joggle". </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Innate immunity biomarkers </outcome>
      <timepoint>Innate immune biomarkers were measured before the start of the study and then every week over the 8-week period of the study. Plasma IL-6, IL-10, C-reactive protein and TNFa and salivary B-defensins, cortisol and IgA  were measured using commercially available ELISA kits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived energy, fatigue and motivation </outcome>
      <timepoint>At each weekly training session, changes in perceived energy, fatigue and motivation were assessed at the start and then again at the end.  This was assessed using visual analogue scales (VAS) forms.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxidative stress and antioxidant status </outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes in oxidative stress parameters were measured at the beginning and end of the each weekly training session.  We specifically measured plasma oxidative stress parameters, (a) radical oxygen species using fluorescence assay using hydrolysed DCF, (b) superoxide and (c) nitric oxide using commercially available assay kits (Abcam). In addition, we assessed changes in superoxide dismutase, catalase and GPx activity in PBS washed (x2) erythrocytes using in house colorimetric bioassays and plasma total antioxidant capacity measured using hydrolysed fluorescent probe DCF and H2O2 as the pro-oxidant stimulus.   </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for participation in this study include written informed consent. Participants had to be member of the Hamilton Boys High School hockey squad and aged between 16-19 yrs. All participants were in good general health, free of injury. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>19</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria included the inability to provide written informed consent to take part in the study. Unable or unwilling to comply with study procedures, including only consuming the treatment at the appropriate time. Individuals were also be excluded if they were known to have experienced  hypersensitivity to blackcurrants or berryfruits or their health situation changes that they became unable to train, e.g. injury, heart and/or breathing problems. Individuals were also not able to take part if they have any of the following health conditions; blood borne diseases (e.g. hepatitis), clinically diagnosed high/low blood pressure, recent bacterial or viral illness or vaccinations, chronic illness that affects their immune system (e.g. lupus) or are taking medication that affects the properties of blood, e.g. clotting. 

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>(a) Participants were only recruited from Hamilton Boy’s High School hockey squad. Recruitment was done in consultation with parents/guardian and hockey coaches.  
Subjects interested, together with coaches and parents or guardians, were given a presentation about what they could expect in the study and were allowed to ask questions and given an information sheet and health questionnaire. If interested they made an appointment with the trial co-ordinator (Robyn Wells) to discuss the study in detail. They were given two weeks to decide whether they wish to take part in the study. Once informed consent and the health questionnaired had been assessed against the study' inclusion and exclusion criteria by an independent occupational health service, they were recruited. 
(b) This is a two-arm parallel study. Participants were allocated into one of two groups; blackcurrant extract or placebo. Study investigators and participants were blinded from the dietary intervention given to participants.  THis allocation process was undertaken by a fellow scientist who is not involved in this study. Participant treatment allocation is held concealed until completion of the trial and analysis of the data is finished (on-going). Furthermore, participants were given their dietary treatments as an opaque gelatin capsule, which masked the colour of the blackcurrant extract or placebo. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation of participants into the two treatment groups were performed using a spreadsheet random function.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power analysis. The fitness level, VO2 max measurement on cycle ergometer, from a previous trial was used to calculation of the minimum sample size likely to show an effect in this study. Using this parameter, a sample size of 10 has a desired statistical power level of 0.8 with a probability level of 0.05.  This is calculated on an anticipated effect size (Cohenss d) of 1.159 based on paired SD for a difference in VO2 max L/min. 
Data will be analyzed using Statistical Analysis Software (SAS) 9.1 for Windows (version 5.1.2600). Using a repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA), comparison between conditions over time for each measure (independent variable) will also be determined, providing levels of significance for trial effect, treatment effect, and interaction effect between treatment and trial. In some situation, i.e. cognitive testing, the raw data may be appropriately transformed to allow for participant variation, prior to statistical analysis. Data will be expressed as mean  + / - standard error of the mean. In addition, post-hoc tests may be performed to identify significant differences at each time point. Values will be presented as means + / - standard deviation (or standard error) at a 95% significance level (p = 0.05). Pearsons Product Moment Correlation Coefficients may also be assessed using SPSS 15.0 for Windows to investigate if there are any relationships between certain variables by giving an R-value between 0.0 and 1.00 (or -0.0 and -1.00).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton, Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand Institute for Plant &amp; Food Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92169, 
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand Institute for Plant &amp; Food Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 92169, 
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Assoc. Prof. John Podd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology
Massey University
Private Bag 11-222
Palmerston North 4442</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Eating fruit as part of your diet keeps you healthy. Recent studies show certain fruits contain compounds that boost the bodys natural defences. Hockey training is very demanding for young athletes. Finding a fruit that may help them keep healthy, recover quickly after injury, and play better during the hockey season would be helpful.  The pricipal question being asked by this study is does the regular consumption of a blackcurrant supplement prior to each hockey practice and game facilitate sporting performance (physical and mental) and maintain the health of young hockey players over an 8-week period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Minstry of Health 
No. 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/CEN/45</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Hurst</name>
      <address>New Zealand Institute for Plant &amp; Food Research Ltd., Private Bag 11600, Palmerston North 4442</address>
      <phone>+64 (6) 355 6231</phone>
      <fax>+64 (6) 351 7050</fax>
      <email>suzanne.hurst@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Robyn Wells</name>
      <address>New Zealand Institute for Plant &amp; Food Research, Ruakura campu, Private Box 3123, Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 (7) 959 4490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Robyn.Wells@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Hurst </name>
      <address>New Zealand Institute for Plant &amp; Food. Ltd., Private Bag 11600, Palmerston North 4442</address>
      <phone>+ 64 (6) 355 6231 </phone>
      <fax>+64 (6) 355 6231</fax>
      <email>suzanne.hurst@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Hurst</name>
      <address>New Zealand Institute for Plant &amp; Food Research, Private Bag 11600, Palmerston North 4442</address>
      <phone>+64 (6) 355 6231</phone>
      <fax>+64 (6) 351 7050</fax>
      <email>suzanne.hurst@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>