<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343217">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000767909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of thrombolysis on communication and swallowing outcomes following stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of thrombolysis on communication and swallowing recovery in patients with an ischaemic stroke compared with non-thrombolysed patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-0259</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will investigate the effects of thrombolysis using recombinant tissue plasminogen activators (rt-PA) on communication and swallowing recovery after ischaemic stroke. During the study we will record patient communication and swallowing outcomes through observational measures at different time points along the recovery continuum (the first week post-stroke, and then 3 and 6 months later). We will compare the recovery patterns between patients who are lysed and patients who are not lysed. No thrombolytic drugs will be administered during the study (ie. Participants will be lysed on admission to hospital by the hsopital medical team as per the hospital thrombolysis guidelines prior to entry into the study).</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will consist of patients who were not thrombolysed on admission to hospital. During the study we will record patient communication and swallowing outcomes through observational measures at different time points along the recovery continuum (the first week post-stroke, and then 3 and 6 months later).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in communication and cognitive function as measured by standardised assessments (Western Aphasia Battery, Measure of Cognitive-Linguistic Abilities, and CogniSTAT) for participants according to study group (thrombolysis vs. control) and according to stroke site (left vs. right stroke)</outcome>
      <timepoint>First week post-stroke, 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in swallowing function as measured by the RBHOMS for participants according to study group (thrombolysis vs. control) and according to stroke site (left vs. right stroke)</outcome>
      <timepoint>First week post-stroke, 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in general physical function as measured by observational measures (Functional Independence Measure, Motor Assessment Scale) for participants according to study group (thrombolysis vs. control) and according to stroke site (left vs. right stroke)</outcome>
      <timepoint>First week post-stroke, 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will have been admitted to hospital following an ischaemic stroke. Participants will have English as their primary language and will not have previously received thrombolysis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any individuals with other neurological conditions, a hisotry of previous stroke or head injury, or a NIHSS score of greater than 22 will be excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/07/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Emma Finch</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Kathy Clark</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kathryn Hayward</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Building 84A (Therapies building)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke is currently the second highest cause of death in Australia and a leading source of disability (National Stroke Foundation, 2010). Some strokes are caused by a blockage in a blood vessel within the brain. Evidence suggests that thrombolysis (i.e., administering a drug to dissolve the blockage) shortly after a stroke may reduce some of the neurological damage (Wardlaw, Murray, Berge, &amp; del Zoppo, 2009; Williams et al., 2009). One such drug is called recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (rt-PA). Very little is known about the effects of rt-PA on the recovery of communication or swallowing function. This has significant implications for patient rehabilitation, as it is unknown whether patients who receive rt-PA will respond differently to traditional behavioural rehabilitation methods post-stroke or improve at different rates. It is also unknown whether the effects of rt-PA on post-stroke recovery differ according to stroke location. As a result, the proposed study will investigate the effects of thrombolysis on the recovery of communication and swallowing function after stroke. Increasing our knowledge in this area will assist in the development of effective patient rehabilitation programs to maximise quality of life post-stroke.  

Aims
The overall aim of the project is to investigate the effects of thrombolysis on the recovery of communication and swallowing function after ischaemic stroke. Specifically, the project will investigate whether patients who receive rt-PA following an ischaemic stroke differ from patients who do not receive the drug with respect to language, speech and swallowing function. The project will also investigate whether these communication and swallowing recovery patterns differ following rt-PA over the first 6 months post-stroke. Finally, given the difference in communication disorders resulting from stroke location, the study will investigate whether there is a difference in the effects of rt-PA on communication and swallowing outcomes according to whether patients experienced a left or right sided stroke.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Finch, E., Fleming, J., Clark, K., &amp; Hayward, K. (in press). Interdisciplinary rehabilitation outcomes following thrombolysis for acute ischaemic stroke: A case series. Neurorehabilitation: An interdisciplinary journal

Finch, E., Hayward, K., Fleming, J., &amp; Copland, D. (2013). Identifying implications of thrombolysis for stroke rehabilitation: Knowledge gaps in current research. Disability and Rehabilitation.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health Services District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/QPAH/293</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.whiting@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.whiting@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.whiting@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Emma Finch</name>
      <address>Speech Pathology Department
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3896 3133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.whiting@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>