<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367772">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000208505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of shift work on human health and metabolism; a preliminary study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>shift workers and non-shift workers; their gut bacteria  and metabolites</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1165-8430</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gut disorders due to  disruption of sleep schedule</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational study to evaluate gut microbiota and metabolism of shift workers and non- shift workers. 
At the Initial screening participants will fill out two questionnaires. 
1. Pittersburg Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)
2. Gut health questionnaire
The duration of the observation will be 7days, where participants of both groups (shift workers and non-shift workers) will maintain a sleep log (7 days) as well as a diet record (only for the last 3 days of the observational period). Participants will fast overnight on the 7th day and will provide a faecal, a urine and a blood sample on the following morning. </interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator group will be non-shift workers.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantification of  blood and urinary chemical metabolites by liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry </outcome>
      <timepoint>On the Day 8; after 8 hour fasting </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in faecal bacteria by next generation gene sequencing</outcome>
      <timepoint>On the Day 8; after 8 hour fasting</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantification of circadian markers in blood by gene expression</outcome>
      <timepoint>On the Day 8; after 8 hour fasting</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessing  sleep quality by 7 day sleep log used by Sleep Wake Research Institute/Massey University</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each day during the  observational period (7 days)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary intake using 3 day Diet record used by Plant and Food Research</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 3 days (i.e. days 5,6, and 7) before the sample donation day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gut health assessment  using a gut health questionnaire used by Plant and Food Research designed by Plant and Food Research with input from external collaborators.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the initial screening</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult (18-65 years) with a BMI between 18.5-29  will be considered. 
For the purpose of this study, shift workers are defined as people who have undertaken  shift work duties for at least 1 year on permanent night or rotating shifts with at least 2 nights per week. Night shift is defined as  at least 3 hours work between midnight and 5am.
Non-shift workers are defined as people who are on permanent work schedules  during the day time  with no  shift work history over the last 1 year and do not suffer from sleep disruption on a regular basis (no more than 1 sleep disruption episode during one week).  

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Candidates who suffer from chronic disease (cancer, diabetes, cardiovascular or gastrointestinal disorders, neurological conditions (e.g. multiple sclerosis, spinal cord injury, and stroke).  
Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding will also be excluded. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>There is no published data available regarding the effect of shift work on intestinal microbiome or blood and urinary metabolites in humans. However,  quantitative changes in gut microbiome in two individuals before, during and after jet lag has been reported  (Thaiss et al., 2014). This is an acute study with only one episode of sleep disruption, unlike our proposed trial which studies the long term effects of sleep disruption. In another study,  the shiftworkers were found to consume significantly lower percentage of carbohydrate and higher percentage of fat than non-shiftworkers, with changes in proteins that are linked to fat metabolism and inflammation   (Crispim et al., 2012).  There is no other study on long term changes in the gut microbiome or metabolites of shiftworkers as compared to non-shiftworkers, so we are unable to perform power calculations.  Therefore our study is a preliminary study to investigate long term effects of shift work on gut microbiome and metabolic patterns. 

Thaiss, Christoph A., Zeevi, D., Levy, M., Zilberman-Schapira, G., Suez, J., Tengeler, Anouk C., Abramson, L., Katz, Meirav N., Korem, T., Zmora, N., Kuperman, Y., Biton, I., Gilad, S., Harmelin, A., Shapiro, H., Halpern, Z., Segal, E., Elinav, E., 2014. Transkingdom Control of Microbiota Diurnal Oscillations Promotes Metabolic Homeostasis. Cell 159, 514-529. DOI 10.1016/j.cell.2014.09.048.


Crispim, C.A., Padilha, H.G., Zimberg, I.Z., Waterhouse, J., Dattilo, M., Tufik, S., de Mello, M.T., 2012. Adipokine Levels Are Altered by Shiftwork: A Preliminary Study. Chronobiology International 29, 587-594. DOI 10.3109/07420528.2012.675847.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>8/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>7/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The New Zealand Institute for Plant and Food Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private bag 11 600, Palmerston North, 4442</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The New Zealand Institute for Plant and Food Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private bag 11 600, Palmerston North, 4442</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sleep Wake Research Institute, Massey University, Wellington</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Drummond Street, Mount Cook, Wellington 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Circadian rhythm or body clock refers to the 24 hour  cycle that controls physiological functions such as sleep/wakefulness, eating, hormonal and metabolic functions.  When we sleep for 7 to 10 hours, our bodies get adequate rest resulting in stabilisation of our metabolic pattern and immune defenses. Irregular sleep patterns are increasingly common in industrialised countries and many years of shift work increases the chances of metabolic disorders by about 50 to 60%. Shift work disorder may result in excessive sleepiness or insomnia associated with reduction of total sleep time and it may affect 10-38% of shift workers.  

Irregular exposure to light or disruption of sleep as commonly experienced in shift work or jetlag results in circadian disruption with behavioural consequences such as disturbed sleep patterns, increased food intake, and the hormonal system is unable to cope with excessive nutrients  resulting in metabolic shifts towards diabetes and obesity.  Gut health can also be compromised with a higher prevalence of Irritable Bowel Syndrome among rotating shift workers, which was directly associated with disruption of the circadian clock. Also, evening shift and widely varying work start and end times may increase risks for gastrointestinal disturbances.

Gut microbial balance is known to play an important role in metabolism of food, gut health and obesity. A recent study with just two volunteers showed an increase in faecal Firmicutes following jet lag, which was then reversed to normal pattern after 2 weeks. 

Our hypothesis is that shiftwork, especially over a prolonged period of time,  may disrupt circadian rhythm, resulting changes in  metabolism and the  gut microbial balance.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Heath and Diabaility Ethics commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shanthi Parkar</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Private Bag 11600
Palmerston North
4442</address>
      <phone>(+64) 6 9537737</phone>
      <fax>(+64) 6 3517050</fax>
      <email>Shanthi.Parkar@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christine Butts</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Private Bag 11600
Palmerston North
4442</address>
      <phone>(+64) 4 3556147</phone>
      <fax>(+64) 4 3517050</fax>
      <email>Chrissie.Butts@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shanthi Parkar</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Private Bag 11600
Palmerston North
4442</address>
      <phone>(+64) 6 9537737</phone>
      <fax>(+64) 6 3517050</fax>
      <email>Shanthi.Parkar@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Thanuja Herath</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Private Bag 11600
Palmerston North
4442</address>
      <phone>(+64) 6 355 6122</phone>
      <fax>(+64) 6 3517050</fax>
      <email>Thanuja.Herath@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>