<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369800">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000198426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Different training strategies to improve turning performance, functional mobility and brain activity in individuals with Parkinsons disease
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To investigate the effects of different training strategies on turning performance, functional mobility and brain activity in individuals with Parkinson's disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neurodegenerative diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in each group received one-on-one 30 minutes of specific exercise, turning-based treadmill training, or control exercise, respectively, followed by a 10-minute turning/walking training on a level surface for a total of 12 sessions over a 46-week period by a physiotherapist. All subjects needed to register of attendance at each session to monitor adherence.
Specific exercise: Our previous study found that balance ability and lower extremity muscle strength correlated significantly with turning performance in individuals with PD. Therefore, participants in the specific exercise group received specific exercise training that included 20 minutes of balance exercises and 10 minutes of muscle strengthening exercises. The balance exercises focused on both static and dynamic standing balance training. For instance, standing on the ground composed of different materials and bases of support, and single leg stance were treatment programs for static balance training. For dynamic balance training, catching/throwing a ball, the ring toss game, and forward reaching to different directions were included. The strengthening training focused on hip extensors, abductors, and knee extensors, which were highly correlated with turning performance. Training intensity began from 50% of maximal voluntary contraction (MVC) for 10 repetitions, and the intensity increased to 75%80% of MVC progressively. After the individual muscle strengthening exercises, participants performed squatting, stepping up/down in the standing position, and bridging and hip circle activities in the supine position. Normal breathing was emphasized during the training session.
Turning-based training: Participants in the turning-based training group received the 30 minutes turning training on a rotational treadmill. This rotational treadmill (Rmax Science &amp; Technology Co., Ltd., New Taipei City, Taiwan) was designed to provide turning-based (task-specific) training. The basic design principle of this rotational treadmill is similar to the regular treadmill except for its circular, running motor belt. The small radius (0.8 m) forces participants to perform a turning action rather than walking straight.
Following the above-described, 30-minute exercise training for each group, a 10-minute over-the-ground turning program was carried out. This program included S-shaped, 8-shaped, square-shaped, and oval-shaped turning walking with verbal cues for gait correction.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control exercise: Participants in the control group received 30 minutes of trunk exercises combining upper limb movements in the sitting position that minimally challenged standing balance and lower extremity muscle strength. These exercises included trunk flexion, extension, rotation, and side bending with different arm movements (i.e., shoulder flexion, extension, abduction, rotation, and diagonal lifting and chopping).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Turning performance:step/quick turn (SQT; Balance Master Registered Trademark system, NeuroCom International, Inc., Clackamas, OR, USA) </outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome was measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measured brain activity by using EEG (Electroencephalogram, EEG, QuickAmp amplifier, Brain Products GmbH, Munich, Germany).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome was measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unified Parkinsons Disease Rating Scale, UPDRS


</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcomes were measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life scale (the Parkinsons disease questionnaire-39 item, PDQ-39)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome was measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensory integration ability was assessed by the sensory organization test (SOT) of the Balance Master Registered Trademark System.
</outcome>
      <timepoint> All outcomes were measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional gait assessment (FGA)</outcome>
      <timepoint> All outcomes were measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength was evaluated using a handheld dynamometer (Power Track II; Jtech Medical Industries Inc., Herber City, UT, USA). The muscle groups tested were trunk flexors/extensors, hip flexors/extensors/abductors/adductors, knee flexors/extensors, and ankle dorsiflexors/plantar flexors. The make test method was used during which the examiner held the handheld dynamometer stationary while the subject exerted a maximal force against it; the testing position for each muscle followed standard protocols. </outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcomes were measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freezing of Gait questionnaire, FOGQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcomes were measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic balance ability was assessed by the Tinetti balance scale and the limit of stability (LOS) test of the Balance Master Registered Trademark System.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcomes were measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fall efficacy scale international, FES-I
</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcomes were measured the day before intervention (pre), the day after completing the intervention (post), and on the 30th day after completing the intervention (follow up) by the same rater blinded to group assignment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Hoehn and Yahr stage I to III
2. ability to walk independently
3. stable medication usage
4. a score of at least 24 on the mini-mental state examination (MMSE)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. unstable medical conditions
2. history of other neurological, cardiopulmonary, or orthopedic diseases known to interfere with participation in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical Package for the Social Sciences 20.0 software was used for data analysis. Descriptive statistics were generated for all variables, and distributions of variables were expressed as the mean +/- standard deviation. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) or Chi-square analysis was used to evaluate the intergroup differences among baseline characteristics. Change values were calculated by subtracting the baseline data from the post-training data or by subtracting the baseline data from the follow-up data. To analyze intergroup differences, the change values were analyzed using a one-way ANOVA by group as a factor, followed by the Tukey post hoc test. Statistical significance was set at p&lt;0.05. The effective sample size in this study was 60 based on the primary outcome effects observed (turning performance) of our previous study. Using an effect size Eta-squared of 0.19, a type I error of 0.05, an 80% power, at least 20 patients in each group were required for identifying statistically significant differences in turning performance (one-way ANOVA). However, after recruited 36 patients, the effect size  Eta-squared for turning performance were 0.19 to 0.21, and the power were 80% to 84% which had reached the statistical target. Finally, a total of 36 patients were included in the study</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>8/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>36</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Yang-Ming University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No. 155, Li-Nong Street Section 2, Pei-Tou District, Taipei, Taiwan 112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Science and Technology </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>106, Sec. 2, Heping E. Rd., Taipei 10622, Taiwan, R.O.C.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cheng Hsin General Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>112. No.45,Cheng Hsin St.,Pai-Tou,Taipei</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Chang Guan Memorial Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>No.5, Fuxing St., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname> Mackay Memorial Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>No.92, Sec. 2, Zhongshan N. Rd., Zhongshan Dist., Taipei City 104, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>More than 50% of people with Parkinsons disease (PD) have difficulty in turning while walking. However, there is a lack of effective training programs for improving turning performance. Balance control and lower extremity muscle strength influence turning performance in individuals with PD. On the other hand, specific tasks have been proposed as contemporary training strategies for functional improvement. In this study, two different training strategies were designed and investigated for improving turning performance in individuals with PD.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Boards of Taipei City Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>8F., No.10, Sec. 4, Renai Rd., Daan Dist., Taipei City 106, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>TCHIRB-1000101</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Boards of Chang Gung Medical Foundation</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>102-3920A3</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Boards of Mackay Memorial Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No.92, Sec. 2, Zhongshan N. Rd., Zhongshan Dist., Taipei City 104, Taiwan (R.O.C.)
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14MMHISO58</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ray-Yau Wang</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University, 112. No. 155, Sec 2, Li Nong St., Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886228267210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ray-Yau Wang</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University
112. No. 155, Sec 2, Li Nong St., Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886228267210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ray-Yau Wang</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University
112. No. 155, Sec 2, Li Nong St., Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886228267210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>