<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83140">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001057077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Rehydration with Intravenous Fluid and Oral Glycerol in Athletes: Effects on Cardiovascular, Hormonal, Thermoregulatory, Metabolic and Performance Variables</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In athletes, is intravenous fluid with oral glycerol comparable to either intervention alone or placebo, for rehydration</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1118-3236</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HMS06/2303/4</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dehydration</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All subjects completed all four experimental trials in a randomised crossover sequence: (1) 100% oral fluid without glycerol (oral); (2) 100% oral fluid with oral glycerol (oral with glycerol); (3) 50% oral fluid, 50% intravenous (IV) fluid (0.9% NaCl), without glycerol (IV); and (4) 50% oral fluid, 50% intravenous fluid (0.9% NaCl) with oral glycerol (IV with oral glycerol). Trials were conducted at least two weeks apart.

In each experimental trial, subjects were initially dehydrated via cycling exercise in the heat (35oC, 70% relative humidity) to -4% bodyweight. The interventions (oral [control trial], oral with glycerol, IV and IV with oral glycerol) were then provided during rehydration over a two hour period. The total volume of rehydration was 150% of the bodyweight lost. In the first hour, subjects were given 100% of the bodyweight lost, with a further 50% provided in the second hour of rehydration.

Glycerol (1.5 g/kg bodyweight) was provided orally in a sports drink (Gatorade) solution during two hours of rehydration (after being dehydrated by -4% bodyweight) in the oral with glycerol and IV with glycerol trials. The overall dose was provided in two fluid boluses containing 1.0 g/kg and 0.5 g/kg during the first and second hours of rehydration, respectively.

Intravenous fluids (0.9% NaCl) were administered in the IV and IV with oral glycerol trials. In these trials, half the rehydration volume was IV fluid and the other half was oral fluid.</interventions>
    <comparator>Water and sports drink (Gatorade) are provided in combination as the control/placebo (oral) rehydration condition. 

Subjects were initially dehydrated via cycling exercise in the heat (35oC, 70% relative humidity) to -4% bodyweight. The placebo solutions (water and Gatorade) were then provided during rehydration over a two hour period. The total volume of rehydration was 150% of the bodyweight lost. In the first hour, subjects were given 100% of the bodyweight lost, with a further 50% provided in the second hour of rehydration.

Intravenous fluids were only provided in the IV and IV with oral glycerol trials)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma volume (measured using changes to heamoglobin/heamatocrit and Dill and Costal equations) to monitor hydration status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dehydration, -1% bodyweight, -2% bodyweight, -3% bodyweight, post-dehydration, post-first hour of rehydration, mid-second hour of rehydration, post-second hour of rehydration, mid-equilibration, post-equilibration and following 15 min, 30 min, 10 km, 20 km, 30 km and 40 km of an exercise performance test.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise performance assessed as time to complete a 40 km time trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following 10 km, 20 km, 30 km and 40 km of a 40 km time trial.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in aldosterone concentration (measured using a high-performance liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometric method) to reflect hydration status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dehydration, -1% bodyweight, -2% bodyweight, -3% bodyweight, post-dehydration, post-first hour of rehydration, mid-second hour of rehydration, post-second hour of rehydration, mid-equilibration, post-equilibration and following 30 min, 20 km and 40 km of an exercise performance test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cortisol concentration (measured using a high-performance liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometric method) to reflect stress response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dehydration, -1% bodyweight, -2% bodyweight, -3% bodyweight, post-dehydration, post-first hour of rehydration, mid-second hour of rehydration, post-second hour of rehydration, mid-equilibration, post-equilibration and following 30 min, 20 km and 40 km of an exercise performance test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma osmolality (measured using vapour pressure osmometer)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dehydration, -1% bodyweight, -2% bodyweight, -3% bodyweight, post-dehydration, post-first hour of rehydration, mid-second hour of rehydration, post-second hour of rehydration, mid-equilibration, post-equilibration and following 15 min, 30 min, 10 km, 20 km, 30 km and 40 km of an exercise performance test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) male aged 18  40 yrs; 
2) experienced cyclist; 
3) high endurance training status (VO2max &gt; 55 mL · kg-1 · min-1); and 
4) consistently high training volumes for at least the preceding two months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) a history of current or previous renal, hepatic, cardiovascular, thermoregulatory or endocrine disorders; 
2) contraindications to exercising in the heat; 
3) any current or chronic health problems or injuries; 
4) the use of any diuretic during the preceding four weeks; and 
5) having made a blood donation in the preceding three months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4067</postcode>
    <postcode>4068</postcode>
    <postcode>4064</postcode>
    <postcode>4103</postcode>
    <postcode>4121</postcode>
    <postcode>4520</postcode>
    <postcode>4072</postcode>
    <postcode>4113</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Human Movement Studies
Blair Dr, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane 
QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Human Movement Studies
Blair Dr, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane 
QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Queensland Academy of Sport</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Queensland Sport and Athletics Centre (QSAC)
Kessels Road
Nathan QLD 4111</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The major aim of this study is to assess whether rehydration in athletes can be improved by the use of intravenous fluids and/or oral glycerol, compared to oral fluids alone. It was hypothesised that both intravenous fluids or oral glycerol would improve rehydration, but that a combination of intravenous fluids and oral glycerol together would improve rehydration more than either of the interventions alone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentations:
1.	van Rosendal SP, Strobel NA, Osborne MA, and Coombes JS. (2008) The effect of intravenous fluid and oral glycerol on rehydration and exercise performance in a hot/humid environment. ACSMS: Sports Medicine Australia National Conference, 16th-18th October, Hamilton Island Aus, 2008. Personal funding.

2.	van Rosendal, S.P. Rehydration techniques for subsequent endurance performance in a hot/humid environment: The effect of glycerol and IV fluid. Griffith University Seminar Series: Invited speaker, Griffith University, Gold Coast 2008. No funding required.

3.	van Rosendal SP, Strobel NA, Osborne MA, and Coombes JS. The effect of intravenous fluid and oral glycerol on rehydration and exercise performance in a hot/humid environment. Annual Human Movement Studies Postgraduate Conference, Gold Coast, 2008. Funding School of Human Movement Studies and personal.

4.	van Rosendal, S.P., Natalie A. Strobel, Mark A. Osborne, and Jeff S. Coombes. (2008) The effect of glycerol on IV and oral rehydration techniques and subsequent endurance performance in a hot/humid environment. Annual Renal Research Meeting, Royal Brisbane Hospital, 2008. Personal funding.

5.	van Rosendal, S.P., Ward, L.C., Osborne, M.A. and Coombes, J.S. Measuring and Optimising Rehydration. DSO Singapore Military Laboratories and Singapore Sports Council seminar series: Invited speaker, Singapore, 2008. Funding UQ Graduate School Research Travel Grant (GSRTG).

Publications - journal articles:
Taylor, P.J., van Rosendal, S.P., Coombes, J.S., Gordon, R. and Stowasser, M. Simultaneous measurement of aldosterone and cortisol by high-performance liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry: application to dehydration-rehydration studies. J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci. 2010;878(15-16):1195-8.

Publications - published abstracts:
1. van Rosendal SP, Strobel NA, Osborne MA, and Coombes JS. The effect of intravenous fluid and oral glycerol on rehydration and exercise performance in a hot/humid environment. ACSMS: Sports Medicine Australia National Conference, 16th-18th October, Hamilton Island Aus, 2008.

2. van Rosendal SP, Ward LC, and Coombes JS. (2008). Skin and subcutaneous water content as indices of dehydration. 8th International Symposium on In vivo body composition studies, 9th-12th July 2008, New York, USA. Int J Body Comp Res 6: 72.

3. van Rosendal SP, Strobel NA, Osborne MA, and Coombes JS. (2008). The effect of intravenous fluid and oral glycerol on rehydration and exercise performance in a hot/humid environment. Annual Human Movement Studies Postgraduate Conference, Gold Coast, 2008.

4. Paul J. Taylor, Simon van Rosendal, Jeff S. Coombes, Richard Gordon, Michael Stowasser. (2009). Simultaneous Measurement of Aldosterone and Cortisol in Plasma by HPLC-Tandem Mass Spectrometry: Application to Sports Medicine Studies. 11th International Congress of Therapeutic Drug Monitoring &amp; Clinical Toxicology, Montréal, Québec, Canada, 2009.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee
St Lucia Campus
Cumbrae Stewart Building
The University of Queensland
ST. LUCIA QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/02/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HMS06/2303/4</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gary Wilson</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
University of Queensland
Blair Dr, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane 
QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6445</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gwilson@hms.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Simon van Rosendal</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
University of Queensland
Blair Dr, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane 
QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 421856932</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simon.vanrosendal@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Simon van Rosendal</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
University of Queensland
Blair Dr, St Lucia Campus
Brisbane 
QLD 4072</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>simon.vanrosendal@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>