<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368257">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000928516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nurse-led atrial fibrillation management- the NEAT study. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For patients with atrial fibrillation, will a nurse-led clinic facilitated by the use of a guidelines-based EDS system and compared to standard treatment, improve lifestyle risk factors and health related quality of life. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NEAT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is 3 months in duration for each study participant. There will be 2 face-to-face visits at the beginning and completion of the intervention, with 4 phone consultations in between. It is expected that the face-to-face visits will take approximately 30 minutes in duration. 

The intervention is a nurse-led support package which contains the following components: 

1. An electronic decision support (EDS) tool 

A mobile enabled web app  designed to facilitate a discussion between the nurse and study participant and to build an individual patient profile. The app will be used by the nurse to take the participant through potential risk factors, lifestyle factors and medication options. The profile is based on the their stroke risk (using the CHAD2S2-VASc score), their medication adherence (using Morisky medication adherence score) and their cardiovascular risk factors and lifestyle choices. The app will be used at baseline and at the 3 month face-to-face follow up visit. 

2. Health counselling and goal setting 

At the baseline visit, the nurse will provide education and the pathophysiology of AF, its symptoms and possible complications. The nurse will discuss rate and rhythm control as well as prophylactic vascular therapy (including strict anti-coagulation monitoring) and information about knowing when to report to hospital. Each study participant randomised to the intervention arm will also receive a booklet entitled Living with Atrial Fibrillation. 

At the baseline visit the nurse will provide behaviour change support, through motivational interviewing principles (Miller &amp; Rollnick, 2012) and use the EDS tool to facilitate the discussion about HR-QoL encouraging patients to set realistic goals in line with their priority and motivation. 

3. Three-month telephone-based support and follow up

The study participant will receive regular telephone support (minimum of four phone calls in the intervention period) and the nurse will continue to provide psychosocial support and educational interventions as offered at the baseline visit. The length of each phone call will be recorded in the Case Report Form (CRF). 

The final face-to-face visit (3 months after the baseline visit) will collect the same individual patient data as collected as baseline including but not limited to vital sign measures, quality of life measures, and medication adherence. </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care for their cardiovascular health, comprising in-patient treatment including diagnostic and interventional procedures, pharmacotherapy, and lifestyle counselling, as determined by their usual doctors. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- health related quality of life as measured by the SF-12 questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured at baseline and at three months after randomisation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Resting systolic blood pressure, using Microlife BP A200 Afib blood pressure monitor.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured 3 months after randomisation  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication adherence - measured using the Morisky Medication Adherence Scale (MMAS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured at baseline and at 3 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health literacy - measured using the Rapid Estimate of Adult Literacy in Medicine - short form (REALM- SF). </outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured at baseline and at three months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognition - measured using the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured at baseline and at 3 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity level - measured using the Global Physical Activity Questionnaire (GPAC). </outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured at baseline and at 3 months after randomisation . </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol consumption - measured using the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured at baseline and at 3 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking status - self reported measure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at baseline and at 3 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index (BMI) assessed according to international standards by measuring weight on calibrated scales, and height with a stadiometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>- measured at baseline and at 3 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria are as follows: 
- Participants must be over the age of 18 years, 
- living independently, 
- have a primary and secondary diagnosis of AF, confirmed by a 12-lead ECG. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Age &lt; 30 years; 
2) Home address outside the catchment area of the hospitals; 
3) Inability to provide informed consent; 
3) Absence of ECG documentation of AF during index presentation; 
4) Patients with end stage heart failure (NYHA class IV, LVEF &lt; 35%); 
5) Cardiac surgery &lt; 2 months prior to index presentation; 
6) Terminal (life expectancy &lt; 1 year and/or palliative care) and/or active malignancy (undergoing current chemo or radiotherapy; secondary diagnosis or via patient self-report; or via interrogation of notes after patient consent)
7) Documented thyrotoxicosis or acute pneumonia at the time of index presentation; 
8) poor English literacy; 
9) non-independent living. 
10) End-stage renal dysfunction (Hx of dialysis; secondary diagnosis coding of renal failure or via patient self-report; or via interrogation of notes after patient consent)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants identified by medical physicians will be invited by the study team to attend a study visit. At the baseline visit participants will receive detailed information about the study and sign informed consent if willing to proceed. All consented participants will have the following information collected: review against inclusion/exclusion criteria, documented diagnosis of AF, relevant vital sign measures (heart rate, blood pressure) and cardiovascular risk factor measure (BMI, smoking status, alcohol consumption, physical activity level). All participants will be randomised via a central computer generated randomisation process. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to either control or intervention group with a 1:1 allocation as per a computer generated randomisation schedule using permuted blocks of random sizes. The block sizes will not be disclosed, to ensure concealment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary analyses will be conducted using SPSS for Windows. Continuous variables will be reported as mean plus/minus standard deviation (SD), and categorical variables as numbers and percentages. Within subject differences between baseline and follow-up will be analysed using Wilcoxon signed ranks tests for non-parametric variables. Between group comparisons will be analysed using Student's t-test, the Mann Whitney U test (for non-normally distributed continuous data) and the chi-squared test (with calculation of odds ratios and 95% CIs) where appropriate. SF12 data will be analysed using software by OptumInsight. 
Process evaluation interviews will be analysed using an inductive approach. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Charles Perkins Centre, Sydney Nursing School, University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building D17, Johns Hopkins Drive, University of Sydney, 
Camperdown 2006 NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Vanguard Grant - Heart Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 80 William St East Sydney NSW 2011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bayer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>875 Pacific Hwy
Pymble NSW 2073</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is a single blind randomised controlled trial to determine whether a nurse-led clinic which uses a mobile enable web app (a computer program that also works on a smartphone or tablet) to guide discussion between the nurse and patient, can improve lifestyle risk factors and health related quality of life (HR-QoL) in participants with AF. The study aims to provide evidence of feasibility with the intention to seek funding for a larger study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD - Concord Repatriation General Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2139</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/CRGH/57</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lis Neubeck</name>
      <address>Room 4.B.29, Sighthill Campus, 
Edinburgh Napier University 
Sighthill Court, Sighthill 
Edinburgh  EH11 4BN 
</address>
      <phone>+44 7491 522 050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Neubeck@napier.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lis Neubeck </name>
      <address>Room 4.B.29, Sighthill Campus, 
Edinburgh Napier University 
Sighthill Court, Sighthill 
Edinburgh  EH11 4BN 
</address>
      <phone>+44 7491 522 050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Neubeck@napier.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lis Neubeck </name>
      <address>Room 4.B.29, Sighthill Campus, 
Edinburgh Napier University 
Sighthill Court, Sighthill 
Edinburgh  EH11 4BN </address>
      <phone>+44 7491 522 050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Neubeck@napier.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jessica Orchard</name>
      <address>Level 2, Charles Perkins Centre (D17)
University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61286271664</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.orchard@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>