<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362062">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000179831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise and postprandial lipemia - The effect of exercise and bioactive nutrients on vascular and metabolic response to postprandial lipemia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of exercise and bioactive nutrients on vascular and metabolic response to postprandial lipemia in healthy young males</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vascular problems related to a high fat meal</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will consist of three sessions; each session will be separated by a one week wash-out period. In Session 1, subjects will consume a high fat meal (HFM). The fat-rich meal will be in milkshake form and will consist of 270 ml of whipping cream and 65 g of specialty ice cream. The meal will provide 4.1 MJ (980 kcal; 0.05 MJ/kg body weight), 100 g fat (1.1 g/kg); 66.5 g saturated, 29.5 monounsaturated, 4.0 g polyunsaturated, 17 g carbohydrate (0.2 g/kg), and 3 g protein (0.03 g/kg). This meal has been successfully used in previous studies to induce postprandial lipemia. All measures will be assessed at pre and post consumption of a HFM. In Session 2, a combination of a HFM and green tea capsules (GTC) will be consumed by subjects; all measures then will be assessed at pre and post consumption of a HFM and GTC combined. The green tea extract will be in capsule form (3 capsules), which will contain 375 mg of epigallo catechin gallate (EGCG). In Session 3, subjects will consume a HFM and GTC, then 2 hours post consumption of a HFM and GTC subjects will undergo a single bout of exercise. All measures will be assessed at pre and post consumption of a HFM and GTC capsules and post acute exercise. The acute exercise protocol will consist of 30 min of steady state exercise on a stationary Monark bike at 60% of subjects VO2peak. During exercise, subjects will be supervised and their heart rate will be monitored every 2 min by the tester/researcher.</interventions>
    <comparator>All subjects will receive the same treatment. They will consume a high fat meal (HFM) only, a HFM and green tea capsules (GTC)combined, and a HFM and GTC combined followed by acute exercise.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular function and blood markers following a high fat meal (HFM) assessed at pre and post consumption of a HFM. Vascular function will be assessed using Hokanson Plethysmography and lipid profiles will be assessed using Cholestech casette.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In Session 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular function and blood markers following a high fat meal (HFM) combined with green tea capsules (GTC)assessed at pre and post consumption of a HFM and GTC combined. Vascular function will be assessed using Hokanson Plethysmography and lipid profiles will be assessed using Cholestech casette.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In Session 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular function and blood markers following a high fat meal (HFM) combined with green tea capsules (GTC)assessed at pre and post consumption of a HFM and GTC combined as well as post acute exercise. Vascular function will be assessed using Hokanson Plethysmography and lipid profiles will be assessed using Cholestech casette.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In Session 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Young healthy individuals with a normal body mass index (BMI) of between 18-25kg.m2. Free of medications and diseases</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>BMI&gt;25kg.m2; smoker, use of medications; hypertension; diabetes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>All subjects will receive the same treatment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>High Street
Randwick, NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Consumption of a high fat meal (HFM) can lead to increased risk of cardiovascular disease. Ingestion of a HFM  not only increases  the fat level in the blood but also damages  blood vessels, which overtime can lead to many health problems. Thus, the purpose of the study is to examine the effect of consumption of a HFM alone and the effect of a HFM consumption followed by a combined exercise and green tea ingestion on vascular function. It is predicted that exercise and green tea ingestion will reduce the severity of vascular problems related to a HFM.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HREC University of New Soutch Wales</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>High Street
Randwick, NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yati Bouthcer</name>
      <address>School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
University of New South Wales
High Street, Randwick, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9385 2419</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>y.boutcher@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yati Bouthcer</name>
      <address>School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
University of New South Wales
High Street, Randwick, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9385 2419</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>y.boutcher@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yati Bouthcer</name>
      <address>School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
University of New South Wales
High Street, Randwick, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9385 2419</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>y.boutcher@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>