<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372002">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000280303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Advance Care Planning for Patients with advanced illnesses attending hospital outpatient clinics study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Advance Care Planning (ACP) on health resources utilisation and quality of care for patients with advanced illnesses attending hospital outpatient clinics</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1191-0560</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>advance care planning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>palliative care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>chronic disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>aged care</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Informational materials:
1. ACP brochure produced by NSW Health (v6)  contains basic information about ACP and where to get assistance if interested;
2. ACP workbook endorsed by NSW Health;
3. Enduring guardianship NSW booklet  produced by the Public Guardian Office of the NSW Government Department of Attorney General &amp; Justice.
4. Consensus Plan  - utilised for families to develop a plan (when the person is unable to develop an ACD).

Procedures, activities, processes used:
1. Provision of personalised information on ACP;
2. Facilitation of ACP discussions with patients, caregivers, family and relevant health professionals; 
3. Assistance in completing appropriate ACP documents
4. Referral to relevant local legal services for witnessing as required
5. Organising and facilitating meetings and/or teleconferences with clinic staff, GPs, and other health care professionals involved in patients care to discuss the patients care and their wishes;
6. Assistance with dissemination of ACP documents on completion that may include upload to Local Health District record system and national eHealth record (contingent on LHD and national eHealth improvements during the study period), and forwarding the document to patients GP.

Who will deliver the intervention: 
ACP trained clinical nurse consultants, ACP trained outpatient clinics staff 

Mode of delivery: 
Individually, face to face 

Number of times the intervention will be delivered:
Depending on the needs of the patients and carers, one or more facilitated ACP discussions, each lasting min. 20 mins.
Duration of the intervention period for each participant = up to 6 months.
There is no maximum number of sessions, but we would not expect more than 6 to be required over a 6 month period.

Location:
Outpatient clinics </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group patient participants will be given written information on Advance Care Planning. This represents the current standard care. 
The written information will consist of:
1. ACP brochure produced by NSW Health (v6)  contains basic information about ACP and where to get assistance if interested;
2. ACP workbook endorsed by NSW Health;
3. Enduring guardianship NSW booklet  produced by the Public Guardian Office of the NSW Government Department of Attorney General &amp; Justice. 
4. Consensus Plan  - utilised for families to develop a plan (when the person is unable to develop an ACD); a companion guide is being finalised.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of unplanned hospital admissions as assessed by chart audit of patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ambulance services calls as assessed by data linkage to NSW Ambulance Data Collection
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergency Department presentations as assessed by data linkage to NSW Emergency Department Data Collection
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of hospital admissions as assessed by data linkage to NSW Admitted Patient Data Collection
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Date, place and causes of death as assessed by data linkage NSW Mortality Data
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resuscitation attempts as assessed by data linkage to NSW Emergency Department Data Collection, NSW Admitted Patient Data Collection, NSW Ambulance Data Collection
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intensive Care Unit admissions as assessed by data linkage to NSW Admitted Patient Data Collection</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data collected from patient participants: PACIC - Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care, SF-20 - 20-Item Short Form Health Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Audit of ACP discussion sessions (intervention group only). For each session: time taken; number of attendees and their categories (e.g. patient, facilitator, family member, other health care professionals); number and types of documents completed; number and types of documents distributed; referrals made (if any). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data collected from caregiver participants; SF-20 - 20-Item Short Form Health Survey, ZBI-12 - Zarit Burden Short Form Interview.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data collected from clinical staff working in the outpatient clinics: 
There are pre- and post- surveys on ACP knowledge. These were used by the investigators previously in non-research contexts. They have generic names: Staff questionnaire: knowledge of ACP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data collected from clinical staff working in the outpatient clinics: 
There are pre- and post- surveys on ACP attitudes. These were used by the investigators previously in non-research contexts. They have generic names: Staff questionnaire: attitudes to ACP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Audit of advance care directives. These audits aim to measure the output of Advance Care Planning as indicated by (a) the number and duration of discussion sessions; (b) documents created as a result of Advance Care Planning; (c) number of stakeholders participating in discussions; and (d) communication of the output to external stakeholders.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data obtained from data linkage with Medicare and PBS, including Medicare items and medication items accessed by the patient during the 6 months prior to and 6 months following patient enrolment in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Attending an outpatient clinic of participating clinical services in the study.
2. Identified by Supportive &amp; Palliative Care Indicators Tool (SPICT Trademark) as potentially having supportive and palliative care needs and at risk of dying in the next 12 months.
3. Identified by the ACP screening tool as not having a current Advance Care Directive / Plan or an enduring guardian AND is interested in engaging in further Advance Care Planning discussions.
4. Willing and able to give written informed consent and willing to participate to and comply with the study (or if the person lacks decision making capacity then the person responsible is willing to provide informed consent).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Less than 18 years of age.
2. Pregnant.
3. Identified by the ACP screening tool as having both an enduring guardian and an Advance Care Directive / Plan or is not interested in Advance Care Planning discussions.
4. Current inpatient.
5. Patient (or if patient lacks decision making capacity, guardian or person responsible) is unable or unwilling to provide informed consent.
6. Permanent resident of residential aged care facility. 
7. Unable to provide informed consent and participate in ACP conducted in English due to difficulties in understanding and speaking English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).
Stratification according to study site and according to number of hospital admissions in the past 6 months (&lt;2 versus 2 or more).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation: 
n=288 (control = 144, intervention = 144).
We assume an alpha of 0.05, power of 0.8 to detect at least 25% reduction (IRR 0.75) in unplanned hospital admissions over 6 months (from an average of 2.2 over 6 months to 1.65 admissions over 6 months assuming the number of admissions follows a Poisson distribution in each group). Based on these assumptions, we will need to recruit 100 people in each group who will have the full 6 month follow-up, so that the number of hospitalisations in the groups are 220 (control) and 165 (intervention).  However, given that we expect a death rate in the 6 months of the trial of up to 35% of people, we will need to recruit 122 people in each arm of the trial.  If we also expect a drop-out rate (withdrawal, loss to follow-up) of 15% we will need 144 people in each arm of the trial. 

Statistical Analysis Plan: 	
The primary outcome will be the number of unplanned hospital admissions during follow-up.  A Poisson regression model, including follow-up time as an offset will be fitted to compare the mean number of admissions between the trial arms.  The analysis will also adjust for the variables used in stratification in the randomisation (number of admissions in 6 months prior to the trial, and the study site). The secondary outcomes will be analysed similarly to the primary outcome; as well as using descriptive statistics and linear regression adjusting for stratification variables. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>288</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>The Sutherland Hospital - Caringbah</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>War Memorial Hospital - Waverley</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Health Care Sydney Ltd - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2229 - Caringbah</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2024 - Waverley</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Geriatric Medicine
Prince of Wales Hospital
High St
Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Ministry of Health: Translational Research Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NSW Ministry of Health
Level 5
73 Miller St
North Sydney NSW 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sydney Local Health District</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Geriatric Medicine
Concord Hospital
Building 12
Hospital Road
Concord NSW 2139</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of New South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity
University of New South Wales Sydney
UNSW SYDNEY NSW 2052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Notre Dame</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Medicine, Sydney
The University of Notre Dame
160 Oxford Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sydney University of Technology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Health
235 Jones Street
Ultimo NSW 2007</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Wollongong</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Graduate Medicine
University of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Advance Care Planning (ACP) is a process of reflection, discussion and communication that enables a person to plan for their future medical treatment and other care, for a time when they are not competent to make, or communicate, decisions for themselves. ACP could significantly improve the quality of care provided to patients with advanced illnesses. ACP allows patients to have a voice, to receive patient-centred care, in the setting of their choice, and avoid unwanted hospitalisations and inappropriate treatments.
The importance of ACP in patient care has been widely recognised. The Australian Government National Health and Hospitals Reform Commission (2009) recommended the implementation of a national program of ACP in Australia. ACP has been widely endorsed by a large number of professional groups, specialist colleges, peak bodies and patient advocate groups.
The NSW Healths policy on ACP is outlined in the 2013 document Advance Planning for Quality Care at End of Life: Action Plan 2013-18. Among others, it shows that NSW Healths priority is to: (i) incorporate ACP into routine care; (ii) educate health professionals in both conducting and responding to ACP; and (iii) improve collaboration between NSW clinical services and community and primary care health professionals. The policy also noted deficiencies that currently exist in NSW Health clinical services in identifying and recognising patients who might be at risk of dying in the near future.
The intervention is informed by the Diffusion of Innovation Theory. This theory states that for innovation to be taken up, five conditions need to be met - relative advantage, compatibility, complexity (how difficult the innovation appears), trialability and observability (whether positive outcomes of the innovation can be observed). This means that didactic education sessions alone are unlikely to be sufficient to lead to significant increase in ACP undertaken by health professionals. This intervention will allow clinical services to see a few, do a few, and teach a few, thereby embedding ACP firmly into routine care of patients. GPs of participating patients will be exposed to ACP documents and information material; the chance of them engaging with the educational material is significantly increased because they relate to their own patients.
This research aims to trial and evaluate on patients attending NSW hospital clinics with advanced illnesses identified as potentially having supportive and palliative care needs, a model of ACP that seeks to: (i) increase the uptake of ACP by patients; and (ii) encourage NSW Health clinical services and GPs and other health professionals providing care for the patients to incorporate ACP into routine care. This study seeks to determine if this model of ACP will reduce acute health resources utilisation; improve the quality of care for patients and caregivers/family; and result in improved understanding and uptake of ACP by health professionals.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney LHD Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office
 G71, East Wing 
 Edmund Blacket Building
 Prince of Wales Hospital
 Randwick NSW 2031 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NEAF Ethics Approval 16-321</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Joel Rhee</name>
      <address>School of Medicine, Sydney
The University of Notre Dame
160 Oxford Street, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8204 4485</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.rhee@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karolina Krysinska</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity
University of New South Wales Sydney
UNSW SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 1506</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.krysinska@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karolina Krysinska</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity
University of New South Wales Sydney
UNSW SYDNEY NSW 2052 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 1506</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.krysinska@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karolina Krysinska</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity
University of New South Wales Sydney
UNSW SYDNEY NSW 2052 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 1506</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.krysinska@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>