<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336476">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000129987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intra-examiner reproducibility of probing pocket depth using four types of manual periodontal probes, in vivo</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Intra-examiner reproducibility of probing pocket depth with four manual probes types in healthy volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diagnosis of periodontal disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Periodontal probing depth with four types of manual probes in healthy volunteers 
One trained examiner will measure PD in 20 patients to determine the intra-examiner reproducibility with four types of manual periodontal probes in two times measurements by each patient and each probe (Baseline and repeated measurement) as follows: FIRST DAY: PD on Patient 1 (Baseline), SECOND DAY: PD on Patient 2 (Baseline), THIRD DAY: PD on Patient 3 (Baseline), FOURTH DAY: PD on Patient 4 (Baseline), FIFTH DAY: PD on Patient 5 (Baseline) and Patient 1 (repeated probing), SIXTH DAY: PD on Patient 6 (Baseline) and Patient 2 (repeated probing), SEVENTH DAY: PD on Patient 7 (Baseline) and Patient 3 (repeated probing), EIGHTH DAY: PD on Patient 8 (Baseline) and Patient 4 (repeated probing), the sequence will continue at the  same manner until reach the patient number 20. PD is defined as the measurement in millimeters from the gingival margin to the bottom of the gingival sulcus. The study will use a Williams manual periodontal probe (1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 8, 9 and 10 mm Hu-Friedy), Colorvue periodontal probe (3, 6, 9 and 12mm Hu-Friedy); PDT Sensor Probe 2M-12 (2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12mm Pro-Dentec, Batesville AR), and UNC 15/23 manual probe (1 to 15mm Paradise Dental Technologies). The examiner will introduce each probe in the interior of the gingival sulcus and following the length of the tooth until resistance will be felt by the penetrating probe. Each patient will have six sites probed per tooth (mesial buccal, buccal, distal buccal, mesial lingual, lingual and distal lingual), excluding third molars. The PD measurements will do using the following criteria: all measurements will be round to the closest 0.5 mm (up or down), when the PD measurements are exactly between two marks on the probe the closest millimeter immediately above the mark will recorded. Each patient will have a minimum of six teeth per quadrant in order to be included in the study. The perfect squares formula will be used to random distribution of probes and areas to will be probed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intra-examiner reproducibility by duplicated measurements of probing pocket depth with four types of manual periodontal probes on healthy patients</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: 
Assess the inter-examiner reproducibility on clinical register of probing pocket depth in healthy patients (without periodontal disease) using different measurement tools (four types of manual periodontal probes).</outcome>
      <timepoint>During a period of three months, the examiner selected subjects who will participate in the study based on exclusion and inclusion criterions (participants selection). From June to August 2008.
After subjects selection, during a period of 6 months, the examiner worked on calibration process until demonstrate that he was calibrated (in subjects that were not part of the experimental group) according to parameters: Substantial kappa values, 90% measurements agreement not bigger or smaller than 1mm and an exact agreement in 75% of the PD repeated measurements. From September 2008 to February 2009.
Once the examiner demonstrates that has been trained within the abovementioned parameters, the study will be initiated. Finally, 6 months to collect and assess the datas.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with four types of manual periodontal probes on mesial tooth surfaces vs. distal tooth surfaces</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with four types of manual periodontal probes on anterior vs. posterior mouth areas.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with four types of manual periodontal probes on buccal vs. lingual tooth surfaces.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with four types of manual periodontal probes on superior vs. inferior dental arch.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy patients: No signs of periodontal destructive disease (loss of clinical attachment).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who have received treatments of fixed or partial prosthetics, individual crowns or orthodontia; surgical or non-surgical periodontal treatments in the last eight months; been taking antibiotics; or be pregnant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>El Salvador</country>
      <state>San Salvador</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Roberto Antonio Andrade Acevedo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centro de Salud Integral, 5 calle poniente 4212, colonia Escalon, San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>El Salvador</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>None</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>None</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The periodontal probe remains as the best clinical diagnostic tool to collect information regarding the health status and the attachment level of periodontal tissues. The aim of the present study is to evaluate the intra-examiner reproducibility of probing pocket depth (PPD) measurements with a four types of manual periodontal probes. Methods: Previously accepted by an Ethical Committee and after informed consent, 20 subjects without periodontal disease were selected if they presented at least 6 teeth per quadrant without antibiotic therapy in the last 8 months. One calibrated examiner (k&gt;0.6), will assess PPD from all teeth at 6 sites/tooth with Williams (1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 8, 9 and 10 mm), Colorvue (3, 6, 9 and 12mm); PDT Sensor Probe 2M-12 (2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12mm), and UNC 15/23 (1 to 15mm) manual periodontal probes from the gingival margin to the bottom of the periodontal sulcus (rounded to the next 0.5mm). Initial (Baseline) and repeated measurements will performed by one trained examiner.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CIE. Institutional Ethics Comite of Evangelic University of El Salvador. UEES.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Universidad Evangelica de El Salvador. First Building, Third floor. Prolongacion Alameda Juan Pablo II, Calle El Carmen, San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>Certificate assessment of clinical study n0 9</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>El Salvador</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Roberto Antonio Andrade Acevedo. Titular Professor in Periodontics. Evangelic University of El Salvador. San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America.</name>
      <address>Centro de Salud Integral 4212. Colonia Escalon, San Salvador, Central America.</address>
      <phone>+(503) 2264 6321 (for San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America)</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robertoandrade_periodoncia@yahoo.com.br, robertoandrade67@yahoo.com.br, acevedoroberto@hotmail.com.</email>
      <country>El Salvador</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Roberto Antonio Andrade Acevedo. Titular Professor in Periodontics. Evangelic University of El Salvador. San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America.</name>
      <address>Centro de Salud Integral 4212. Colonia Escalon, San Salvador, Central America.</address>
      <phone>+(503) 2264 6321 (for San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America)</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robertoandrade_periodoncia@yahoo.com.br, robertoandrade67@yahoo.com.br, acevedoroberto@hotmail.com.</email>
      <country>El Salvador</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>