<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82556">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000226303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A double-blind, placebo controlled, randomised trial to prove the therapeutic concept and to determine the pharmacokinetic profile of ATL1102 (VLA-4 antisense oligonucleotide) by subcutaneous injections in patients with relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blind, placebo controlled, randomised trial to prove the therapeutic concept and to determine the pharmacokinetic profile of ATL1102 (VLA-4 antisense oligonucleotide) by subcutaneous injections in patients with multiple sclerosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients receive 200 mg ATL1102 (VLA-4 antisense oligonucleotide) by subcutaneous injection three times in the first week, then twice weekly for the next seven weeks. The patients are monitored for a further eight weeks following completion of dosing.</interventions>
    <comparator>1.3 ml placebo comprising sodium chloride and colorant by subcutaneous injection three times in the first week, then twice weekly for the next seven weeks. The patients are monitored for a further eight weeks following completion of dosing.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative number of new active lesions on Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), corrected for the number of enhancing lesions at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4, 8 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative volume of gadolinium-enhancing lesions on MRI, corrected for the volume of enhancing lesions at baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4, 8 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males and females aged 18 to 55 years
Diagnosis of Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis (RRMS)
At least 9 T2 lesions or at least 4 if one is gadolinium-enhancing
Last relapse in the previous 12 months
No relapse in the previous four weeks
Score of EDSS 0 to 6.0
Reliable contraception (e.g. surgical sterilisation, oral contraceptives) 
Written informed consent to participate in the study by signature on the Patients Consent Form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Administration of any investigational drug within the previous 2 months before enrolment (4 months if the previous drug was a new chemical entity).
Progressive disease.
Concomitant clinically relevant other findings on MRI that may interfere with outcome assessment.
Previous treatment with VLA-4 antibodies, anti-CD4 antibodies, or other monoclonal antibodies.
Total lymphoid irradiation at any time.
Treatment with immune-modulating drugs in the previous two months or treatment with immune-suppressive drugs in the previous six months.
HIV positive patients.
Detectable levels of JC Virus in the blood measured by quantitative PCR.
Patients with renal impairment with serum creatinine greater than or equal to 2,0 mg/dl.
History of clinically relevant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, endocrine, haematological, metabolic, neurologic (other than multiple sclerosis (MS)) and psychiatric disease.
Patients with infections (lymphocytes greater than 3000/microL).
History of any bleeding.
History of coagulation abnormalities.
Concomitant medication acetyl salicylic acid (greater than 300 mg/day) and phenprocoumon.
Clinically relevant abnormalities in physical findings at screening examination if interfering with the study objective.
Pregnant or breast-feeding women.
History of drug or alcohol abuse.
Epileptics.
Suicidal subjects.
History of drug allergy and/or known drug hypersensitivity.
Inability to communicate or cooperate with the Investigator due to language problem, poor mental development or impaired cerebral function.
Any medical condition which, in the judgement of the Investigator, might interfere with the objectives of the study.
Repeated participation in this study.
Contraindication for application of study drug.
Corticoid-treatment in the previous six weeks and during the study period, exceptions are corticoid-treatment before the study period (not in the previous six weeks) and of relapses during the study period: Relapses are characterised by the occurrence of neurological dysfunction symptoms, appearing after a 30-day period of stability or improvement and lasting for more than 24 hours (no infection, no fever). 
A 5-day methylprednisolone treatment 1000 mg intravenous (i.v) is allowed in this case followed by a reducing procedure.
Corticoid-treatment if applied locally (e.g. inhaled products) is allowed.
Additionally MRI exclusion criteria: Metal residing in the body (e.g. implants), Cardiac pacemaker, valves, cochlear implants, CNS vascular clips.
Contrast medium allergy Gadolinium Diethylenetriamine Penta-Acetic Acid (Gd-DTPA).
No MRI exclusion criteria but caution is advised in case of: Cardiovascular disease including coronary heart disease, Immune deficiency, Haematologic disorder.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/02/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovakia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bulgaria</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Antisense Therapeutics Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>10 Wallace Avenue, Level 1
Toorak
Vic 3142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Antisense Therapeutics Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10 Wallace Avenue, Level 1
Toorak</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Antisense oligonucleotides (ASOs) are an innovative new class of drugs that inhibit the expression of proteins by sequence-specific binding to the proteins mRNA. ATL1102 is a 2nd generation antisense inhibitor of CD49d, a subunit of Very Late Antigen 4 (VLA-4) which plays a key role in cell adhesion to vessel walls. VLA-4 blockade, as shown by monoclonal antibodies such as natalizumab, prevents activated lymphocytes from migrating into the CNS and significantly reduces disease activity in MS.

Objective: To evaluate VLA-4 Antisense (ATL1102) in the treatment of RR-MS

Methods: Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled multicenter Phase-IIa trial. 77 patients with RR-MS were treated for 8 weeks with either 200mg of ATL1102 or placebo subcutaneously twice weekly and evaluated for 16 weeks. MRI scans were performed at screening, and then monthly over 16 weeks. Primary efficacy variable: cumulative number of new active lesions (CNNAL; new gadolinium-enhancing T1 lesions (T1-Gd), new or enlarging T2 lesions) on MRIs taken at weeks 4, 8 and 12. Secondary efficacy variable: cumulative volume of T1-Gd lesions (CVT1L) on MRIs taken at weeks 4, 8 and 12. 

Results: ITT population: 74 patients with a valid baseline MRI and at least one post-baseline MRI scan after first injection of study medication (n=39 placebo, n=35 ATL1102). ATL1102 showed a significant reduction, 54.4%, in CNNAL (6.2 placebo, 3.0 ATL1102; p=0.01). A reduction of 66.7% (p=0.002) was observed in the cumulative number (weeks 4,8,12) of new T1-Gd lesions with ATL1102. A reduction in CVT1L was also observed under ATL1102 but did not reach significance (589.4 mm3 placebo, 358.0 mm3 ATL1102; p=0.1068). Adverse events that were more frequent under ATL1102 included mild to moderate injection site reactions and a tendency for decreased platelet counts which were reversible after treatment interruption.

Conclusions: This proof-of-concept study of a drug designed to inhibit VLA-4 mRNA showed a significant reduction of the cumulative number of new active lesions in RR-MS patients following 8 weeks of treatment. These promising results warrant further investigation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>VLA-4 Antisense  An Oligonucleotide targeting VLA-4 mRNA (ATL1102) significantly reduces new active lesions in patients with RR-MS. Volker Limmroth, Frederik Barkhof, Nuket Desem, for the ATL1102 Study Group 
Presented at the World Congress on Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis in Montreal Canada on 20 September 2008 and at the American Academy of Neurology (AAN) 61st Annual Meeting in Seattle, Washington USA on 29 April 2009 by the Principal Investigator of the trial, Volker Limmroth MD PhD.
 
ATL/TV1102, an oligonucleotide targeting VLA-4 mRNA, significantly reduces new active lesions in patients with relapsing remitting multiple sclerosis.
Volker Limmroth, Frederik Barkhof, Nuket Desem
Presented at the New York Academy of Sciences Annual Meeting of the Oligonucleotide Therapeutics Society, Boston Massachusetts, USA on 18 October 2008 by Dr Christopher Wraight, Research Director, Antisense Therapeutics Ltd. 
 
ATL1102, an Antisense Drug Targeting VLA-4, Significantly Reduces the Development of Active Lesions in Relapsing-Remitting Multiple Sclerosis.
Volker Limmroth, Frederik Barkhof, Nuket Desem
Presented at the Keystone Symposia scientific conference entitled Therapeutic Modulation of RNA Using Oligonucleotides, in Alberta Canada on 13 February 2009 by Nuket Desem, Development Director, Antisense Therapeutics Ltd.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, University of Duisburg-Essen, University Clinic Essen</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Robert-Koch-Str. 9-11 45147 Essen</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/08/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Idnr: 04-2508</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the State Chamber of Physicians of the Federal State of Hessen</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Im Vogelsang 3 60488 Frankfurt am Main</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>E 258/2004MC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Chamber of Physicians of the Federal State of Lower Saxony, Corporation under Public Law</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Berliner Allee 20 30175 Hannover</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/10/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Grae 212/2004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Chamber of Physicians of the Federal State of Mecklenburg-West Pomerania at the University of Rostock, Institute of Forensic Medicine</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Postfach 100888 18055 Rostock</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/10/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>II SV 68/2004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the State Chamber of Physicians of Thuringia, Corporation under Public Law</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Im Semmicht 33 07751 Jena</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/10/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>kl/1117/04112</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Chamber of Physicians of Berlin, Corporation under Public Law</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Friedrichstrasse 16 10969 Berlin</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/01/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Eth-012/05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Medical University of Hannover</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Carl-Neuberg-Str. 1 30625 Hannover</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Nr. 3884</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the State Chamber of Physicians of Rhineland-Palatinate, Corporation under Public Law</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Postfach 2926 55019 Mainz</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>837.253.06 (5351)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Chamber of Physicians of Hamburg, Corporation under Public Law</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Postfach 760109 22051 Hamburg</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/08/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>M-206/06</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, University of Witten/Herdecke</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred-Herrhausen-Str.50 D58448 Witten</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Antragsnr. 33/2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Germany</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>MHAT "Tzaritza Ioanna" Ltd Local Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Byalo more Str. Sofia 1504, 8</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>231/25.10.2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Bulgaria</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Local Ethics Committee at SHATNP "Sv. Naum</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>4 km Tsarigradsko shose Blvd.1113 Sofia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/18.10.2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Bulgaria</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Local Ethics Committee at SHATCVD</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sofia, 65 Konyovitsa Str</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/18.10.2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Bulgaria</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>MHAT "St. Marina" Ltd. Varna Local Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 Hristo Smirnenski Str. 9010 Varna</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/10.10.2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Bulgaria</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee FN Olomouc</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>I.P. Pavlova 6 77520 Olomouc</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>174/06 MEK 44</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Czech Republic</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of Slezska Nemocnice Opava</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Olomoucka 86 Opava, 74601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Czech Republic</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Commitee of FNKV</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Scrobarova 50 100 34 Praha 10</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Czech Republic</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of District Hospital Pardubice</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kyjevska 44 53203 Pardubice</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Czech Republic</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee at FNsP Bratislava Ruzinov Facility</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ruzinovska 6 82606 Bratislava</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006-004736-79</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Slovakia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee at FNsP BratislavaSt.cyril and Method Hospital pracovisko Petrzalka</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Antolska 11 85107 Bratislava</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Slovakia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics committee at University Hospital Nitra</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Spitalska 6 PP41C 95001 Nitra</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Slovakia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bioethical Committee of Medical University of Lodz</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Al. Kosciuszki 4 90-419 Lodz</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RNN/4/07KE</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ministry of Health National Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av. Sanatescu 48 sector 1 Bucharest</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Nr. 4302</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Romania</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nuket Desem</name>
      <address>10 Wallace Avenue, Level 1, Toorak, Vic 3142</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9827 8999</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9827 1166</fax>
      <email>nuket.desem@antisense.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mark Diamond</name>
      <address>10 Wallace Avenue, Level 1, Toorak, Vic 3142</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9827 8999</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9827 1166</fax>
      <email>mark.diamond@antisense.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nuket Desem</name>
      <address>10 Wallace Avenue, Level 1, Toorak, Vic
3142</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9827 8999</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9827 1166</fax>
      <email>nuket.desem@antisense.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>