<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362206">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000380897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised trial of a novel model of diabetes care for adults in the community through multidisciplinary collaboration and integration across the primary and tertiary interface</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of a novel model of community care versus usual care on glycaemic control in adults with type 2 diabetes: a randomised trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This intervention is based on a novel concept which incorporates the principle of General Practitioners (GPs) with special interests around a multidisciplinary and coordinated approach to diabetes care in the community. This model of care includes a specialist doctor (endocrinologist), who acts in a consulting capacity to the GP, to endorse the GPs patient management plan. The intervention is delivered face to face with their advanced GP as well as with a diabetes nurse educator. This intervention will include follow up appointments which will be approximately every 6 weeks and will continue until 12 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care for patients with complex type 2 diabetes is in an endocrinology and diabetes outpatients settings at a secondary or tertiary hospital. Typically patient care is delivered prodominantly by a consultant doctor (an endocrinologist).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>glycaemic control (as measured by HbA1c)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cholesterol and cholesterol fractions</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of patients ceased smoking, collected by patient self-report on questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>foot complications including presence of diabetic ulcers/sores, partial or total foot amputation, charcot joint, delayed healing times for injured skin, neuropathic symptoms, pulses present in right and left foot  (determined by assessment from podiatrist)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>retinopathy complications (determined by patient medical records data)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>microalbuminuria (determined by urine analysis to calculate albumuria to creatinine ratio and compared to reference range)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>serum creatinine</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hospitalisations for diabetic related complications (determined by data linkage to external database Queensland Hospital Admitted Patients Data Collection (QHAPDC))</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of patients achieving clinical target for HbA1c (at less than or equal to 7%) measured by blood pathology testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of patients achieving clinical target for blood pressure (at less than or equal to 130/80 mm/Hg) measured in seated position with digital sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of patients achieving clinical target for low density lipoprotein (at less than or equal to 2.5 mmol/L) measured by blood pathology testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>greater than 18 years
type 2 diabetes
referred to secondary/tertiary hospital diabetes outpatients for care
residing in the geographical area of interest in Brisbane, Australia
able to provide informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>patients without hypoglycaemic awareness
pregnancy
receiving haemodialysis
patients with terminal illness with life expectancy less than 2 years</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The person who determines if a patient is eligible to participate is unaware of the allocation group at the time of enrolment. Randomisation to group is conducted after eligibility is confirmed and consent has been provided from the patient. 

Allocation to treatment group is done off site by the study statistician who is removed from the screening of participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will use a weighted control of 3 intervention to 1 control. The randomisation will be done via web based computer randomisation, which is set up by the study statistician remotely. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>multi site</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>352</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Claire Jackson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Discipline of General Practice
School of Medicine
The University of Queensland
Level 8, Health Science Building 
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston QLD 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
 GPO Box 1421
 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Anthony Russell</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology
Princess Alexandra Hospital
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Diabetes is a chronic disease where the primary care physician has a central role to play. Historically, evidence has supported the role of diabetes teams in hospital settings being able to provide better care compared with primary care but it has been argued whether this relates to improved systematic and organised care, compared to increased expert knowledge. With appropriate support and recall systems, delivery of diabetes care in general practice can be as good as hospital outpatient care. Recognising this, the United Kingdom has seen the introduction of diabetes clinics conducted by general practitioners with special interests (GPSIs) with demonstrated favourable improvements in HbA1c, cholesterol and blood pressure. To date, Australia has not adopted GPSIs into clinical practice. However, the Australian health care system is facing significant reform aimed at shifting the focus from tertiary and secondary hospital health care to primary health care, including the move towards GP superclinics.

This research project focusses on the care of patients with complex T2DM who have been referred by their GPs for specialist diabetes care. This research is based on a novel concept which incorporates the principle of GPs with special interests around a multidisciplinary and coordinated approach to diabetes care in the community. Important to this model is the role of the specialist Endocrinologist in a consulting capacity to review and endorse the advanced skill GPs (GP Clinical Fellows) management plan. Few studies have investigated the staged devolution of diabetes services from secondary/tertiary care to primary care through increasing the capacity of primary care to meet the needs of patients who would otherwise use hospital outpatient services.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Askew DA, Jackson CL, Ware RS, Russell A. Protocol and baseline data from The Inala Chronic Disease
Management Service evaluation study: a health services intervention study for diabetes care. BMC Health Services
Research 2010;10:134.

Jackson, Claire, Tsai, Jane, Brown, Cathy, Askew, Deborah and Russell, Anthony (2010) GPs with special
interests impacting on complex diabetes care. Australian Family Physician, 39 12: 972974.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/04/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Claire Jackson</name>
      <address>Discipline of General Practice 
The School of Medicine
The University of Queensland
Level8, Health Sciences Building
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston 4029 QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5381</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 5178</fax>
      <email>c.jackson@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Maria Donald</name>
      <address>Discipline of General Practice 
The School of Medicine
The University of Queensland
Level8, Health Sciences Building
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston 4029 QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 5135</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 5178</fax>
      <email>m.donald@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Maria Donald</name>
      <address>Discipline of General Practice 
The School of Medicine
The University of Queensland
Level8, Health Sciences Building
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston 4029 QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 5135</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3346 5178</fax>
      <email>m.donald@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Claire Jackson</name>
      <address>Discipline of General Practice The School of Medicine The University of Queensland Level8, Health Sciences Building Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Herston 4029 QLD </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.jackson@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>