<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365360">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001371785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Helping Health Anxiety: Evaluation of a pure self-help treatment program for Health Anxiety     </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adults with Health Anxiety, is the self-help program of Helping Health Anxiety effective in improving health anxiety, anxiety sensitivity and general stress, depression and anxiety.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1150-6830</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Health Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will involve a Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) based self-help program called Helping Health Anxiety developed by the Centre for Clinical Interventions (CCI).   There are nine modules providing the following intervention components: psychoeducation; attention training; worry postponement; thought diaries; reducing unhelpful checking and reassurance seeking; challenging avoidance and safety behaviours (exposure); adjusting health rules and assumptions; healthy living; and self- management planning  (Anderson, Saulsman, &amp; Nathan, 2011).  Each week, over nine weeks, one module will be sent to the participants via email.  Each module takes approximately 1 hour to complete, plus any time the participant spends on doing the associated practice tasks throughout the week.  Each week the  participants are required to complete a questionnaire via email, before they are sent the module, in order to tracks their Health Anxiety.  
Their experience of the modules will also be explored during the follow-up interview (a month after the intervention is completed).</interventions>
    <comparator>An A-B (pre-post) single case experimental design series will be implemented.  The study aims to evaluate if there are positive reliable changes as well as clinically significant changes between pre-test and post-test in terms of health anxiety, anxiety sensitivity and general anxiety, depression and stress.  Post-test (post-intervention) scores will be compared to each individual's Pre-test (pre-intervention) scores.  </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Anxiety Score as assessed by the Short Health Anxiety Inventory (Salkovskis, Rimes, Warwick, &amp; Clarke, 2002)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week before the commencement of treatment, each week of the treatment and one month after treatment completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety Sensitivity as measured by the Anxiety Sensitivity Index (Peterson, Gursky, &amp; McNally, 1986)</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week before treatment commences, the first week of treatment, the final week of treatment and one month after the final week of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General levels of depression, anxiety and stress as measured by the Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale Short Form (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>A week before the commencement of treatment, the first week of treatment, the final week of treatment and one month after treatment completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feedback on the self-help program and it's effects using a semi-structures interview</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month after the completion of the program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Have health anxiety as the primary problem as assessed using diagnostic and questionnaire measures of: a semi-structured intake interview, the Short Health Anxiety Inventory and the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants excluded if they meet criteria for psychosis, substance misuse, bipolar disorder, or are at high risk for self-harm or suicide.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>4</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Rebecca Anderson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
Kent Street, Bentley WA 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent Street, Bentley WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Timea Zalanyi</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University
Kent Street, Bentley WA 6102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project is a case series looking at the effectiveness of a series of self help modules for the treatment of health anxiety.  The self-help modules are based on evidence-supported intervention and were developed by expert clinical psychologists.  The project will entail the recruitment of four participants whose primary condition is health anxiety and their assessment.  The selected participants who meet the selection criteria and consent to the participation will be emailed these modules weekly.  The project aims to investigate if pure self-help is an effective treatment for health anxiety by assessing if the participants demonstrate reliable and clinically significant change.  If so, this will improve treatment accessibility and affordability for individuals who suffer from this problem. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, W.A. 6845 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR 100/2013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Anderson</name>
      <address>Curtin University
Kent St
Bentley, WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3012</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.anderson@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Timea Zalanyi</name>
      <address>Curtin University
Kent St
Bentley, WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61411116260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>timea.zalanyi@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Anderson</name>
      <address>Curtin University
Kent St
Bentley, WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3012</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.anderson@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>