<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366173">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000490673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of eccentric exercise on calf muscle contracture in people with multiple sclerosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In people with multiple sclerosis, do eccentric exercises, compared with routine stretching, reduce contracture in ankle joint and calf muscle?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ankle joint contracture</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Multiple sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in intervention group will be exercising under supervision at a university-based gym two times each week for twelve weeks. Each exercise session will last about 45-60 minutes. The exercise involves walking backwards and downhill on a treadmill. This type of exercise is known to produce muscle soreness - the same sort of soreness that people normally experience after they participate in unaccustomed physical activity. We expect that, if participants in intervention group will experience muscle soreness. However, the  soreness will gradually be less and less over the 12-week period. To minimize this muscle soreness, participants will be trained at low intensity at start and gradually increased intensity over the first 8 sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>home-based exercises, including stretching the ankle, to practice at home for 20-30 minutes at least 2 times per week over the 12 week treatment period. Home-based exercises will involve strengthening exercises for affected muscle groups (e.g. hip flexors, knee flexors or ankle dorsiflexors). Participants will learn these exercises at base line testing. The exercises will be either recorded on participant's smart phone or on papers if they do not use smart phones. Adherence to exercises will be monitored monthly by phone calls.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>passive ankle dorsiflexion range of motion of the affected leg at 12Nm using a Cybex equipment (Humac Norm)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before training) and at completion of 12-week training (or 24 sessions)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The passive mechanical properties of the gastrocnemius muscle including: passive slack length of the gastrocnemius muscle-tendon unit, passive muscle fascicle slack length as well as lengthtension curves of the muscle fascicles and tendons. The outcomes are derived from using ultrasound in combination with measurements of passive ankle torques at difference knee angles (Hoang et al, 2007).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before training) and at completion of 12-week training (or 24 sessions)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility capacity (10-meter  and 6-minute Walk tests) 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before training) and at completion of 12-week training (or 24 sessions)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait parameters (step length and gait symmetry) using  Gaitrite mat</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before training) and at completion of 12-week training (or 24 sessions)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of accidental falls during the intervention and 3 months after completion. Incidents of falls are collected by using Falls diary: participants in both groups will be given 6 monthly calendars and 6 "reply paid" envelopes. Participants will be asked to record date and time falls (defined as inadvertently ended on the ground during daily activities) and consequences if any (e.g. bruise, broken bones). Calendars are sent back to investigators monthly.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During 12-week training and 3 month follow-up after completion of training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* A definite diagnosis of multiple sclerosis (MS), confirmed by neurologists
* Less than 90 degrees of ankle dorsiflexion range of motion when a dorsiflexion torque of 12 Nm is applied to the relaxed ankle 
* Have EDSS scale between 1 and 5
* Able to understand spoken English and follow instructions during testing and exercise
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Being unable to give informed consent, or
* Have received a Botox injection for their calf muscles in the past 6 months or expect to receive a Botox injection for their calf muscles in the subsequent 12 weeks
* Have been advised by a medical doctor not to do exercise
* Had a relapse (or attack) of MS in the previous 30 days 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly allocated to one of two groups - an Eccentric Training group or a Control group - using a simple (unrestricted) allocation procedure.  The allocation schedule will be drawn up by a person who is not otherwise involved in the trial. This will be concealed from the researchers involved in recruitment, consent and assessment procedures. After potential participants have given consent and baseline measures have been taken the allocation will be determined by contacting the person holding the allocation sequence. The participant will be considered to have entered the trial when the allocation is divulged.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neuroscience Research Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Street Address:
NeuRA
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neuroscience Research Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Street Address:
NeuRA
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Multiple Sclerosis Research Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Street address:
Level 26, Northpoint, 100 Miller Street, North Sydney NSW 2060</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people with MS develop ankle contractures (a stiffening of the ankle joint) that can impact on normal movement at a very early stage. There is moderate-to-high quality evidence that stretch, the first line of intervention for prevention and treatment of joint contracture in physiotherapy, does not have clinically useful immediate, short-term or long-term effects on joint range of motion. This study will investigate whether exercise that stretches the calf muscle while they contract (eccentric exercise) can be used to treat ankle contractures in people with MS. 40 people with MS who have developed ankle contractures will be randomly allocated either to receive or not receive a 12-week program of eccentric exercise of calf muscle. Ankle joint range of motion, calf muscle properties and parameters of gait and mobility will be measured before and after the 12-week period.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australia Catholics University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Street address:
25A Barker Rd, Strathfield NSW 2135</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013 312N</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Street address:

High St, Kensington NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366173-Approval from ACU.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366173-Previous UNSW Ethics Approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366173-HC14073 Letter from 01 Apr2014 Meeting-1.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phu Hoang</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street Randwick Sydney NSW 2031 

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1832</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.hoang@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phu Hoang</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street Randwick Sydney NSW 2031 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1832</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.hoang@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phu Hoang</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street Randwick Sydney NSW 2031 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1832</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.hoang@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phu Hoang</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street Randwick Sydney NSW 2031 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1832</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>