<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364819">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000972729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving Vitamin D status and related health in young women: The Safe-D study  Part B </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Females aged between 16 and 25 years residing in Victoria, Australia, with 25 OHD levels between 25-74 nmol/L randomised to a behavioural intervention group (receiving the Safe-D m-Health mobile-based app), a pharmacological intervention (receiving Vitamin D3, 1000IU, daily by mouth) or a control group (general advice in the form of a pamphlet) for a period of 12 months, aiming to determine the effectiveness of the behavioural intervention to improve 25 OHD levels. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Safe-D</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vitamin D deficiency </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>3-arm trial comparing the effectiveness of a behavioural intervention with a pharmacological intervention and a control group to improve 25 OHD levels in young women at 4 months and 12 months.
The two intervention groups are:
 - a pharmacological intervention group, receiving 1000 IU Vitamin D3, daily, oral consumption, for 12 months; weekly reminders will be sent to participants to take the tablets; compliance will be measured at 4 months and 12 months with a manual medication count.
 - a behavioural intervention group, receiving a mobile-based app that provides both personalised and general advice about methods to improve Vitamin D levels, for 12 months; the app will be provided to participants and they will be informed on the ways it can be used; usage will be monitored though use of the app will be at the participants' discretion.</interventions>
    <comparator>1 control group, receiving a pamphlet from SunSmart, explaining methods to improve Vitamin D levels</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure the effectiveness of a (1) behavioural and (2) a pharmacological intervention to increase circulating 25 OHD levels, compared with usual care; a blood test will be performed to obtain this information and tested using a highly sensitive assay, liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare effectiveness of the two interventions to increase circulating 25 OHD levels; a blood test will be performed to obtain this information and tested using a highly sensitive assay, liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LC-MS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure compliance to the interventions by: manual medication count for those in the pharmacological intervention group; measuring app usage in the behavioural intervention group</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure changes in UV exposure and 'SunSmart' behaviour; this will be measured using a UV dosimeter, worn by particpants' for 14 days   </outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Residing in Victoria, Australia
Own and use a smartphone
25 OHD levels between 25 and 75 nmol/L</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Currently taking Vitamin D supplements over 800 IU daily
Unable to give informed consent
Currently pregnant, breastfeeding or planning to conceive during the study timeframes
Plan to move outside of Victoria during the study
Have ever had a melanoma or 1st degree relative diagnosed with melanoma
Health problems that may put participants at greater risk, or that may confound study results (sun sensitivity conditions, malabsorption conditions)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participant will be allocated using opaque envelopes, prepared by a statistician external to the study. Block allocation will be used. Both researcher and participant will not know the group the participant will be allocated to until the time of allocation. The researcher will be blinded to the endpoints throughout the duration of the study.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Block stratified randomisation (Stratum 1: 25 OHD - 25-49 nmol/L; Stratum 2: 25 OHD 50-75nmol/L).
Allocation sequence determined by statistician external to the study. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size was determined through an extensive literature review which found an increased 25 OHD concentration of ~12 nmol/L for each 100 IU per day of supplemental vitamin D. Assuming average supplementation of 1000 IU vitamin D/day, we expect changes in 25 OHD concentration of ~10-20 nmol/L in the pharmacological intervention group. A sample size of 62 per arm at 4 months (corresponding to 78 per arm at baseline) will give us 85% power to detect a difference between groups in the change in vitamin D level of 15 nmol/L (assuming a standard deviation of 25 nmol/L and total level of significance of 0.05), using intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis to test Hypothesis 1. This gives us 80% power to detect a 15 nmol/L difference in per protocol analysis, assuming 85% adhere to the protocol.

To test Hypothesis 2, we expect to be able to include 48 participants per arm (n = 56 for ITT analysis) in the 12-month per protocol analyses (accounting for attrition and non-compliance), giving us 80% power (85% in ITT) at 5% significance level to detect a 9-10 nmol/L difference in change from baseline between the two intervention arms (assuming a lower S.D. of 20 nmol/L due to seasonal matching).  

Main analyses will be conducted on an intention-to-treat basis to compare the intervention arms against the control group at 4 and 12 months, using various imputation strategies to account for missing data arising from sample attrition.
Due to the possible protocol violations (e.g, non-compliance with the prescribed treatment), secondary per protocol analysis designed to adjust for non-compliance will be undertaken at 4 and 12 months and results will be compared to the ITT analysis</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>234</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Grattan Street,
Parkville
Vic 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Safe-D study aims to determine the effectiveness of a mobile-based intervention to improve vitamin D levels in a cohort of young women, aged 16 to 25 years, residing in Victoria. 
The effectiveness of the mobile-based app will be compared with standard vitamin D supplementation (1000 IU daily, by mouth, capsule form) and general advice (in the form of a pamphlet).

The study team hypothesise that the behavioural intervention will be as effective in correcting mild vitamin D deficiency within this cohort at 4 months as the standard pharmocological treatment. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>To be activated upon commencement of study
http://www.safedstudy.org/ </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research
Level 6 East
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan Street
Parkille
Vic 3052
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2013.215</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John D Wark</name>
      <address>Level 4 Clinical Sciences Building Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital) The University of Melbourne Parkville Vic 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jdwark@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Karen Gillett</name>
      <address>Level 4 Clinical Sciences Building Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital) The University of Melbourne Parkville Vic 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 5178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.gillett@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John D Wark</name>
      <address>Level 4 Clinical Sciences Building Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital) The University of Melbourne Parkville Vic 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jdwark@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Karen Gillett</name>
      <address>Level 4 Clinical Sciences Building Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital) The University of Melbourne Parkville Vic 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 5178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.gillett@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>