<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336790">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000443998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the LenSx Laser System for Performing Anterior Capsulotomy, Phacofragmentation, and Corneal Arc Cuts/Incisions in Patients Undergoing Cataract Surgery for Removal of the Crystalline Lens</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the LenSx Laser System for Performing Anterior Capsulotomy, Phacofragmentation, and Corneal Arc Cuts/Incisions in Patients Undergoing Cataract Surgery for Removal of the Crystalline Lens</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CPT-002m</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cataract</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The objective of this evaluation is to observe the performance of the Femtosecond Cataract Laser (LenSx Alcon) by assessing the performance of the following applications; laser created anterior capsulotomy, phacofragmentation, and/or corneal incisions, as well as to compare standard visual outcomes and commercial experience between laser and traditional manual cataract surgery procedures.

The laser procedure is assisting the removal of cataracts. Cataracts cause visual loss. Previous studies have shown that removing the cataract and implanting a new intraocular lens rehabilitate the patient's vision and may increase the patients quality of life.

The LenSx (Registered Trademark) Laser works by creating incisions through tightly focused femtosecond laser pulses that cut tissue with micron-scale precision. Further laser pulses are able to create the capsule and break up the existing or natural lens. The Laser replaces a combination of equipment including a blade to create the manual incisions, a needle to help open the capsule which then allows for the lens/cataract to be removed by the use with an external phaco emulsification unit.

In this study each patient will undergo each available application in order to fully assess the impact on safety and accuracy that the LenSx may provide in comparison to the manual (control) technique. 

The duration of the Femtosecond laser is approximately 3 minutes. The subsequent removal of the lens and replacement by the new artifical lens commonly takes approximately 10 further minutes although there is a break to transport the patient across to the operating suite.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Manual Cataract extraction procedure

The standard manual cataract procedure takes approximately 15 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome: 

1. Lens fragmentation is complete. Complete segmentation is achieved without requiring use of ultrasound energy or sharp nuclear crackers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately  following surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Anterior capsulotomy is complete. Complete capsular edge separation without residual tags requiring separation with capsulorhexis style tearing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. Corneal incision(s) are complete.  Entry wounds fully and easily open using a blunt spatula</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and incidence of surgical related complications compared to manual surgical procedures.

Surgical complications may include:
Capsular tear
Corneal abrasion or defect
Pain
Infection
Bleeding
Damage to intraocular structures
Anterior chamber fluid leakage, anterior chamber collapse

These complications may occur throughout surgery and will be assessed and treated as required. At 1 day and 3 months following surgery the patient will be seen by the ophthalmologist and assessed on the slit lamp microscope to note the abscence (or presence) of any complications occuring after the initial surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and at 1 and 3 months following surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy compared to manual cataract removal achieved by assessment of postoperative visual outcomes. 

Visual Outcomes include visual acuity both with and without optical aids compared to baseline levels. This will be completed by the use of standard visual acuity charts (Snellen). The patient will also undergo a refraction to assess the level of pre and postoperative prescription. This will further assist the evaluation of the success of the procedures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and at 1 and 3 months following surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Subjects must be eligible to undergo cataract extraction by phacoemulsification with primary intraocular lens implantation in at least 1 eye.
2.	Subjects must be willing and able to return for scheduled follow-up examinations.
3.	Subjects must sign and be given a copy of the written Informed Consent form.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>24</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Subjects who have undergone previous intraocular or corneal surgery of any kind, including any type of surgery for either refractive or therapeutic purposes in either eye.
2.	Subjects who are pregnant, lactating, or planning to be pregnant during the course of the study.
3.	Subjects with known sensitivity to planned study concomitant medications.
4.	Subjects participating in any other ophthalmic drug or device clinical trial during the time of this clinical investigation.
5.	Subjects presenting any contraindications to cataract surgery.
6.	Hypotony, glaucoma, or the presence of a corneal implant.
7.	Presence of blood or other material in the anterior chamber. 
8.	Residual, recurrent, active ocular or eyelid disease, including any corneal abnormality (for example, recurrent corneal erosion, severe basement membrane disease).
9.	A history of lens or zonular instability.

Exclusion For Laser Group Only
10.	Corneal disease that precludes applanation of the cornea or transmission of laser light at 1030 nm wavelength.
11.	Corneal opacity that would interfere with the laser beam.
12.	Descemetocele with impending corneal rupture.
13.	Poorly dilating pupil, such that the iris is not peripheral to the intended diameter for the capsulotomy.
14.	Conditions which would cause inadequate clearance between the intended capsulotomy depth and the endothelium (applicable to capsulotomy only).
15.	Previous corneal incisions that might provide a potential space into which the gas produced by the procedure can escape.
16.	Corneal thickness requirements that are beyond the range of the system (&gt;1500 microns).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Vision Eye Institute Chatswood</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3 270 Victoria Avenue
Chatswood NSW 2067</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alcon LenSx</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>33 Journey, Suite 175, Aliso Viejo, CA 92656</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Vision Eye Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 270 Victoria Avenue
Chatswood NSW 2067</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alcon LenSx</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>33 Journey, Suite 175, Aliso Viejo, CA 92656</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The LenSx laser system is a femtosecond laser that has received 510(k) clearance (USA FDA) for anterior capsulotomy during cataract surgery, laser phacofragmentation during cataract surgery and for use in the creation of a single and multi-plan  arc cut/incisions  in the cornea.

During cataract surgery, the LenSx Laser creates corneal incisions to allow the surgeon to enter the anterior chamber of the eye. It also creates a circular incision on the anterior capsule at a pre-programmed diameter to allow the surgeon to remove the cataractous lens. Lastly, the laser creates incisions within the cataractous crystalline lens to create fragmented pieces that are easy to manipulate, emulsify and aspirate with a phacoemulsification device.

The objective of this study is to observe the performance of the cleared 510(k) device by assessing the laser created anterior capsulotomy, phacofragmentation, and/or corneal incisions when attempted, as well as to compare standard visual outcomes and commercial experience between laser and manual completion of standard cataract surgery procedures.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil at this point</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Aspire IRB</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>9340 Fuerte Drive, Suite 210 La Mesa CA 91941</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2011-03-144</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chris Hodge</name>
      <address>Vision Eye Institute Chatswood
Level 3 270 Victoria Avenue
Chatswood NSW 2067</address>
      <phone>61 2 9424 9999</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9410 3000</fax>
      <email>christopher.hodge@vgaustralia.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chris Hodge</name>
      <address>Vision Eye Institute Chatswood
Level 3 270 Victoria Avenue
Chatswood NSW 2067</address>
      <phone>61 2 9424 9999</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9410 3000</fax>
      <email>christopher.hodge@vgaustralia.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chris Hodge</name>
      <address>Vision Eye Institute Chatswood
Level 3 270 Victoria Avenue
Chatswood NSW 2067</address>
      <phone>61 2 9424 9999</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9410 3000</fax>
      <email>christopher.hodge@vgaustralia.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>