<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366038">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000211561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized controlled trial of daily aerobic exercise for inpatient cannabis withdrawal</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, parallel-group randomized controlled trial comparing an exercise versus control intervention across a range of cannabis detoxification outcome measures during a 7-day inpatient admission</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cannabis Withdrawal</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will compare a behavioural intervention (exercise) with a control (stretching) regime during standard inpatient detoxification for cannabis withdrawal.

All participants will present with 1 known CVD risk factor (current smoker or have quit within the past 6 months). It is therefore likely that the majority of participants will be classified as moderate risk (2 or more CVD risk factors). As such, participants will be screened and the exercise intensity will be maintained at low  moderate intensity in accordance with American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM) guidelines. Participants assigned to the exercise condition will complete 7 individual consecutive daily sessions of submaximal aerobic training, specifically 35 minutes of static cycling at 60% VO2 max. This will take place in dedicated rooms in each of the withdrawal facilities, equipped with a Kaiser M3 exercise bicycle, computerised cognitive testing equipment, and standard venepuncture facilities. Exercise or control interventions will occur in supervised sessions (sessions will be supervised by either an Exercise Physiology student or by a Registered Nurse who will be trained by CIC Dr Kieron Rooney, or a Nurse who is trained by a trained nurse) at the same time each day (11-12.30 pm) approximately 3 h after a standardized breakfast. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomized to the control group will experience identical duration and timing of daily sessions to the exercise group, but with a series of 7 low intensity stretch exercises over a 35 min period. Each major muscle group will be trained including chest, shoulders, abdomen, back, hips, legs and arms for 2  4 sets. The stretching regime is specifically designed so that it does not stimulate the specific metabolic effects of increased lipolysis hypothesised to come from aerobic exercise. Controls will have blood collected on Days 1, 3 and 7 and will receive cognitive testing and withdrawal assessment as per the exercise group. Participants and researchers cannot be blinded given the obvious differences in the two interventions, but one participant will take part per week and thus will not be aware of the alternative intervention. Additionally, as many of the primary outcome measures are objective (e.g. plasma assays), or involve automated tests (i.e. cognitive tests) they are unlikely to be affected by the lack of blinding. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of completion of the 7 day inpatient detoxification regime</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day of discharge from the 7 day inpatient stay</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily measures of cannabis withdrawal severity using the Cannabis Withdrawal Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during the 7 day inpatient detox</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily measures of cannabis cravings using the Marijuana Cravings Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during the 7 day inpatient detox</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma measures of THC, THC-COOH, 11-OH-THC, CBD, lipolysis, anandamide, 2-AG, and BDNF pre- and post-exercise </outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 3 and 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily urinary cannabinoid levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during the 7 day inpatient detox</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre-post exercise measures of cognitive function and psychomotor performance using computerised cognitive performance measures (RAVLT, Erickson flankers task,	Stop-Signal Task, Rapid Visual Information Processing, 	Digit symbol substitution)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 3 and 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any adverse events during the 7 day admission such as an unexpected reaction to exercise regime </outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during the 7 day inpatient detox</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 day follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported measures of drug use (days used Timeline Followback)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28-day follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>psychosocial functioning (SF-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 day follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient ratings of global improvement </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 of inpatient stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(a)    At least 18 years of age, 

(b)	meets ICD-10 criteria for cannabis dependence, 

(c)	reports significant cannabis withdrawal symptoms in previous periods of abstinence,
 
(d)	capacity to tolerate moderate exercise, and
 
(e) willing and capable of providing informed consent to the study procedures.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(a) Alcohol dependence (and associated alcohol withdrawal sequel by clinical assessment); 

(b) Regular use of other drugs (excluding caffeine, alcohol, and tobacco) or injecting drug use more than once per week on average in previous 28 days; 

(c) Any Drug and Alcohol treatment in the last 28 days;

(d) Significant medical conditions impacting upon exercise capacity, metabolism and excretion of cannabinoids, or assessment of cognition and performance (including severe cardiovascular, neurological, hepatic, renal, respiratory and endocrine disorders; or haematological conditions: 

(e) Active and severe psychiatric disorders that warrant immediate psychiatric treatment (outside of experimental trial conditions), impact upon capacity for consent, or assessment of outcomes, such as psychosis, suicidality, delirium and severe affective disorders (mild or moderate levels of depression or anxiety not excluded); 

(f) Use of medications that may impact upon the metabolism and excretion of cannabinoids (e.g. CYP450 enyzme inducers/inhibitors), or may impact upon measurement of withdrawal features (e.g. mood stabilisers, sedatives); and 

(g)	Pregnancy (plasma hCG screen in women of child bearing potential). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligibility tests for the trial will be performed by people unaware of the allocation group for said participant. ELigibility is assessed in a two stage process, by telephone screen first, then by in person medical assessment. Participant treatment allocation is only released to the study/treatment team by the offsite independent statistician on day 1 of the inpatient stay, when the participant arrives at the hospital, after all screening steps have been completed. If eligible for the study subjects will be randomised upon presentation to the inpatient detoxification service, after they sign informed consent.

The randomisation schedule will be made available to all participating staff but not to the participant. As such it is a single blinded trial.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified for each trial site and by gender and BMI, treatments are balanced within blocks (to achieve approximately 1:1 ratio between conditions), and block size is randomised to improve blinding procedures.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Active (stretching) control</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 40 subjects per group is required to detect a statistically significant difference in cannabis craving scores (used as a proxy for withdrawal scores here) between exercise and control groups with 90% power and a = 0.05. This calculation assumes that the change in craving scores over the week is 1 (SD 3) unit on the Marijuana Craving Questionnaire (MCQ) in the exercise group (33) and 0 (SD 1.8) in the control group (56), giving an anticipated effect size, Cohens f, of 0.3.

The primary comparison will be severity scores on the Cannabis Withdrawal Scale and the Marijuana Cravings Questionnaire between each treatment group, compared across groups using a Mixed Model for Repeated Measures (MMRM), with main effects of time in treatment, treatment group, and their interaction. The model will assume a linear link function and account for within subject correlations with a first order Autoregressive correlation structure. The model will be used to incorporate data from blood analyses (endocannabinoid and THC levels) as covariates to assess biomarkers fit to behavioural observations, as well as any other interesting covariates. 

Secondary analyses will explore the mechanistic reintoxification questions posed in this study with the use of a series of MMRM models with cognition indicators and blood analysis results as dependent variables: THC, THC-COOH, endocannabinoid levels, BDNF, with time, treatment and their interaction as predictors. The effects of exercise induced lipolysis on the time to 1st drug free urine will be determined using survival analysis. The impact of the intervention on post detoxification outcomes will compare changes in self-reported cannabis use (Time-line Followback) and urine THC-COOH levels at baseline and at one month follow up between the groups using MMRMs. Family-wise error corrections (e.g. Bonferroni) will control for Type 1 errors where multiple comparisons are being performed.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>18/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>14/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>46</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>19/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Sydney Hospital and Sydney Eye Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Surry Hills</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is a prospective, parallel-group randomized controlled trial comparing an exercise versus control intervention across a range of cannabis detoxification outcome measures during a 7-day inpatient admission, with follow-up at 28 days post-discharge. Specifically, the study will compare severity of cannabis withdrawal and cannabis cravings, detoxification completion rates, and adverse events between the two conditions in an intention-to-treat analysis. Mechanisms by which exercise affects cannabis withdrawal will be assessed through the analysis of markers of endogenous cannabinoids, and plasma and urine THC levels. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.psych.usyd.edu.au/forms/exercise-study/
</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/RPAH/59</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Lintzeris</name>
      <address>The Langton Centre, 
591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills, NSW, 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9332 8702</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicholas.lintzeris@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anjali Bhardwaj</name>
      <address>The Langton Centre, 591 South Dowling Street Surry Hills, NSW, 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7665</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anjali.bhardwaj@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Allsop</name>
      <address>Psychopharmacology Laboratory
School of Psychology
University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7665</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.allsop@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anjali Bhardwaj</name>
      <address>Psychopharmacology Laboratory
School of Psychology
University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7665</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anjali.bhardwaj@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>