<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372573">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000414314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised trial comparing two new types of nerve repair (Neurowrap and Neuragen) to the conventional type of nerve repair among patients with finger nerve injury.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of direct digital neurorrhaphy; direct digital neurorrhaphy within a collagen nerve wrap; and short gap neurorrhaphy using a collagen conduit on sensibility at one year following digital nerve laceration: a randomised trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Digital nerve laceration
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will undergo a surgical procedure by a hand surgeon in an operating theatre to repair a lacerated nerve. 

Arm 1. Direct digital neurorrhaphy within a collagen nerve wrap (Neurowrap). In this procedure the nerve laceration will be identified during surgery and then repaired using microsurgical suturing. In addition the nerve wrap will be placed around the repair site to protect the repair site during healing
Arm 2. Short gap neurorrhaphy using a collagen conduit (Neuragen). In this procedure the nerve laceration will be identified during surgery and then the 2 ends of the severed nerve are secured inside the nerve conduit intentionally leaving a 2mm gap between the nerve ends within the conduit. This is performed using similar microsurgical techniques as Arm 1.

Both procedures would take approximately 60 minutes to perform </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group go patients will also undergo a surgical procedure by a hand surgeon in an operating theatre to repair a lacerated nerve. 

They will undergo a Direct digital neurorrhaphy (with no conduit or nerve wrap)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Touch/pressure threshold </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Static two point discrimination </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moving two point discrimination </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 week, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months and 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain at rest was measured using a 100 mm visual analogue scale, with 0 mm representing no pain and 100 mm representing worst pain imaginable.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cold intolerance measured using a likert scale. The participant will be provided with a definition of cold intolerance, and asked to indicate their current cold intolerance intensity and this will be converted to an ordinal score (none/minor = 3, moderate = 2, disturbing = 1, and hinders function = 0).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hyperaesthesia measured using a likert scale. The participant will be provided with a definition of hyperaesthesia, and asked to indicate their current hyperaesthesia intensity and this will be converted to an ordinal score (none/minor = 3, moderate = 2, disturbing = 1, and hinders function = 0).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total active range of motion for the injured digit will be calculated as the difference between composite flexion and composite loss of extension (ASSH, 1990) with any hyperextension (beyond 0 deg) denoted as 0 deg for the purpose of the calculation. Measurements will be taken using dorsal placement of a hand-held finger goniometer (Rolyan, Patterson Medical Holdings Inc, Bolingbrook, Illinois USA) and reported in deg, with the shoulder, elbow and wrist positioning standardised.. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall recovery will be measured using the global estimation of recovery (GER), a 100 mm visual analogue scale, with 0 mm representing not at all recovered and 100 mm representing fully recovered (Rosen, 1996). Participants will be asked to quantify their degree of recovery by placing a vertical mark on the line.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participation in work or usual roles will be measured via direct questioning. Participants will be questioned as to whether they have returned to their work or usual role/s and, if so, whether they are undertaking their full duties or modified duties. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age between 18 to 65yo                                                      
Male or Female                                                      
Treated within 14 days of injury.                                                     
Laceration  to  digital  nerve  where  gap  closure  can  be achieved  by  flexion  of  the  extremity  and  the  nerve  can be held together by a single 9-0 nylon suture                                                      Lacerations from proximal end of A1 pulley to trifurcation of nerve distally amenable to  primary repair under minimal tension                                                      
Patients  with  associated  injuries  such  as  tendon  and/or artery injury                                                      Signed informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with nerve injuries at more than one level                                                     Communication  problems  due  to  language  or  severe psychiatric issues                                                      Nerve  gaps  requiring  bridging  with  grafts  or  where  the nerve  cannot  be  held  together  by  a  single  9-0  nylon suture                                                      
Known allergy to bovine derived products                                                      
Disorders known to affect the peripheral nervous system (PNS)  such  as  diabetes  mellitus,  chronic  heavy  alcohol use or toxic nerve lesions                                                      
Associated fracture or amputation                                                      
Receiving  immunosuppressive  or  antineoplastic agents within 7 days of the study                                                       Actively infected wound                                                      
Uncooperative or unsuitable for completion of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A suitable subject requiring surgical repair of their nerve injury and who have also given consent to a part of the study will be randomised using sealed opaque envelopes in the operating theatre at the time of surgery. The person recruiting the patient into the study is unaware of which group the patient will be in at the time of surgery</concealment>
    <sequence>The  sequence  of  allocation  will  be computer  generated  using “Research  Randomiser” (Urbaniak,  G.C,  &amp;  Plous,  S. (2013).  Research  Randomizer  (version  4.0)  [Computer  software].  Retrieved  on May  19,  2016,  from  http://www.randomizer.org/)  by  a  member  of  the  research team  who  is  not  involved  in  recruitment.  This  allocation  will  be  concealed  in numbered,  sealed,  opaque  envelopes.  These  envelopes  will  be  numbered  and opened in sequential order and kept safe in a locked cabinet in theatre, only to be accessed  by   the   operating   consultant/registrar   when   the   patient   who   has consented to be part of the study is on that day’ s theatre list. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sydney Hospital and Sydney Eye Hospital - Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>John Tawfik</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street
Sydney NSW 2000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Hospital Hand Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sydney Hospital
8 Macquarie Street
Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Lauren Miller</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street
Sydney NSW 2000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Timothy CB Heath</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street
Sydney NSW 2000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Anand K Deva</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street
Sydney NSW 2000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Elaine Leahy</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street
Sydney NSW 2000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Javariah Siddiqui</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street
Sydney NSW 2000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Peripheral  nerve  repair  still  remains  a  challenging  problem  for  surgeons. Despite  improvements  in  microsurgical  techniques,  the  sensory  recovery remains  suboptimal.  With  the  advancement  in  molecular  biology and  tissue engineering  techniques  there  has  been  further  development  in  the  realm  of nerve repair using various synthetic and biological materials to develop nerve wraps and conduits. It is now vital to be able to compare these newer repair techniques with conventional methods to determine whether they provide an improvement in outcome in the form of sensory recovery.  The  aim  of  this  study  is  to  compare  outcomes  between  3  types  of digital nerve  repair  techniques  following  digital  nerve  laceration  where  primary neurorrhaphy  is  possible.  These  3  arms  are  direct  end  to  end  repair  of severed  nerve  ends,  direct  end  to  end  repair  with  protection of  site  using  a collagen nerve wrap and short gap neurorrhaphy using a collagen conduit.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SESLHD HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room G71 East Wing
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/104</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John Tawfik</name>
      <address>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street 
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 7350</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john@tawfik.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John Tawfik</name>
      <address>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street 
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 7350</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john@tawfik.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John Tawfik</name>
      <address>Sydney Hospital Hand Unit
Macquarie Street 
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 7350</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john@tawfik.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>