<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365572">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000114640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Evaluation of Malvatricin in the Reduction of Microorganisms Associated to Oropharynx Infections </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Malvatricin is Tested in Patients with Oropharynx Infections Compared to Placebo in order to Reduce the Microorganisms</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1151-7907</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pharyngitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: The solution ready-to-use contains quinosol 1 mg/ml and tyrothricin 0,1 mg/ml. It is necessary to rinse 20 ml of the solution in the mouth for 60 seconds just a single time. 
Arm 2: The tablet contains quinosol 0,7 mg/tablet, tyrothricin 1,0 mg/tablet and benzocaine 5,0 mg/tablet. It is necessary to dissolve one tablet in the mouth just a single time.
Arm 3: The spray contains quinosol 2,0 mg/ml, tyrothricin 0,1 mg/ml and lidocaine chloride 4,0 mg/ml. It is necessary to perform 3 spray applications in the mouth in a single time.
Each pharmaceutical form was compared to its respective placebo. 
No strategies were used to monitor adherence to the treatment because the intervention is realized in just one visit followed by sub-investigator/investigator.</interventions>
    <comparator>The solution placebo is mainly composed of ethyl alcohol, glycerol, menthol and water. The tablet placebo is mainly composed of silicon dioxide. The spray placebo is mainly composed of ethyl alcohol, mint oil and sorbitol. All of these types are used in the same dose, duration, and mode of administration related to the respective interventions.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is the reduction of the level of microorganisms after rinsing with the tested products. Two oropharynx swabs are collected in the timepoints 0 - before the use of the medicine, and 30 minutes later. Sowings in the media are done and after counting of microorganisms, we obtain a relation between the beta-hemolytic bacteria and the total Estreptococcus from the material collected and we convert it to a UFC/cm2 number of the tonsilar area.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two oropharynx swabs are collected in the timepoints 0 - before the use of the medicine, and 30 minutes later. The timepoint is one week after the swabs collection, when it's possible to determine the effect of the intervention due to the outcome of the microorganisms counting.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement of the pharyngitis by clinical evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The timepoint is one week after the swabs collection.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects presenting complaining of odinophagy from varied etiology,with up to 48 hours of evolution, recruited in private clinics of Otorhinolaryngology and invited to participate in the clinical trial after being attended and received medical assistance.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant women and patients with malignant tumors of the oral cavity and pharynx.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio de Janeiro</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Laboratorio Daudt Oliveira Ltda</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>57, Simoes da Mota
Turiacu, Rio de Janeiro/ RJ
Zip code: 21540-100</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Laboratorio Daudt Oliveira LTDA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>57, Simoes da Mota
Turiacu, Rio de Janeiro/ RJ
Zip code: 21540-100</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The use of antiseptics for the treatment of oropharyngeal infections have been reported in the scientific literature, and many products have the efficacy assessed by clinical studies. Conditions of the oropharynx as pharyngitis and odinofagias, and oral cavity, such as periodontal disease, mouth ulcers, stomatitis, and its symptoms, can be attenuated with the use of products containing antiseptics, antibiotics and anesthetics. The adjunctive use of these products, followed by professional treatment, is a valuable tool in the treatment of these conditions, and randomized clinical trials, double-blind, and controlled with placebo should be used to prove the effectiveness of these products. The objective of this study is to evaluate the clinical efficacy of Malvatricin 'Registered Trademark' (Lab Daudt de Oliveira, RJ) in the reducing of microorganisms associated to oropharynx infections.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The Malvatricin 'Registered Trademark' is a mouthwash registered in Brazil for more than 50 years. It is consolidated in brazilian market. This study is necessary for the revalidation process in our regulatory agency - ANVISA.
There are no risks involved in this study, even because there is no evidenced adverse effect.
Related to the study, the mouthwash containing placebo is necessary in order to compare the level of reduction of microorganisms with the experimental group. Immediately after rinsing and collecting material through the oropharynx swabs, all patients will begin a treatment prescribed by an otorhinolaringologist specialist for each clinical condition presented.
</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Ethics Committee in Research of the University of HUPE-UERJ</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>77, Boulevard 28 de setembro
Vila Isabel, Rio de Janeiro - RJ
Zip code: 20.551-030</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eduardo Muniz Barretto Tinoco</name>
      <address>Universitary Hospital Pedro Ernesto/ UERJ
524, Sao Francisco Xavier
Maracana, Rio de Janeiro - RJ
Zip code: 20550-013</address>
      <phone>+55 21 2247-7493</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>embtinoco3@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Michele Vieira Espindola</name>
      <address>Laboratorio Daudt Oliveira Ltda
57, Simoes da Mota
Rio de Janeiro - RJ
Zip code: 21540100</address>
      <phone>+55 21 3369-8552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michele.espindola@daudt.net</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eduardo Muniz Barretto Tinoco</name>
      <address>Universitary Hospital Pedro Ernesto/ UERJ
524, Sao Francisco Xavier
Maracana, Rio de Janeiro - RJ
Zip code: 20550-013</address>
      <phone>+55 21 2247-7493</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>embtinoco3@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nathalia Vianna da Silva</name>
      <address>Laboratorio Daudt Oliveira Ltda
57, Simoes da Mota
Rio de Janeiro - RJ
Zip code: 21540100</address>
      <phone>+55 21 96711-2780</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nathalia_silva4@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>