<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308221">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000634279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind trial to assess the safety and glucose-lowering efficacy of VVP808 in participants with Type 2 diabetes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind trial to assess the safety and glucose-lowering efficacy of VVP808 compared to placebo in participants with Type 2 diabetes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>VVP808-002 
(Verva Pharmaceutical's protocol ID)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>VVP808
dose: 40 mg twice a day
duration: 24 weeks
mode of administration: oral (capsule)</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (microcrystalline cellulose)
Dose: 40 mg twice a day
duration: 24 weeks
mode of administration: oral (capsule)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The safety and tolerability of 40 mg VVP808 administered twice a day, compared to placebo, in subjects with Type 2 diabetes as determined by the incidence of acidosis based on Venous Blood Gas (VBG) parameters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks from randomisation.
Th safety and tolerability primary outcome will be assessed continuously throughout the study (evey study visit).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The efficacy of VVP808 compared to placebo, in subjects with Type 2 diabetes in improving glucose control as quantified by glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c).</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks following randomisation. The efficacy primary outcome will be assessed at weeks 12, 18 and 24.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The safety and tolerability of 40 mg of VVP808 administered twice a day compared to placebo in subjects with Type 2 diabetes as assessed by biochemistry parameters and adverse event reporting. Potential adverse events include: 
loss of appetite, 
taste alteration 
gastrointestinal disturbances such as gas, flatulence, indigestion, abdominal discomfort, nausea, vomiting, and diarrhoea.
a tingling feeling in the hands and feet; hearing problems or buzzing in the ears; tiredness; excessive passage of urine; acidosis (accumulation of acid in the blood),and transient nearsightedness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks following randomisation.
The safety and tolerability secondary endpoint will be assess continuously during the study (at every study visit).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The efficacy of 24-weeks treatment with VVP808, compared to placebo, in subjects with Type 2 diabetes in improving:
Fasting blood glucose;</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks frollowing randomisation.
The efficacy secondary endpoint will be assessed at weeks 12, 18 and 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The efficacy of 24-weeks treatment with VVP808, compared to placebo, in subjects with Type 2 diabetes in improving:
The proportion of subjects achieving recommended HbA1c and fasting blood glucose (FBG) targets;</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks frollowing randomisation.
The efficacy secondary endpoint will be assessed at weeks 12, 18 and 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The efficacy of 24-weeks treatment with VVP808, compared to placebo, in subjects with Type 2 diabetes in improving:
Subject measured capillary blood glucose profiles recorded on a memory-chip glucometer;</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks frollowing randomisation.
The efficacy secondary endpoint will be assessed daily during the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The efficacy of 24-weeks treatment with VVP808, compared to placebo, in subjects with Type 2 diabetes in improving:
Subject reported outcome as assessed by the SF-12 and DiabMedSat questionnaires; 
Subject risk factors (body weight, waist circumference, blood pressure, lipid profile and microalbuminuria).</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks frollowing randomisation.
The efficacy secondary endpoint will be assessed at the end of the study (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants with Type 2 diabetes mellitus; HbA1c between 6.5 and 8.5%, inclusive at screening; Body Mass Index (BMI) less than or equal to 40 kg/m2 and a total body weight greater than 50kg);</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current treatment with any hypoglycaemic drug other than metformin; Any systemic treatment with products, which in the Investigators opinion, could interfere with glucose metabolism (eg systemic glucocorticoids) within 3 months prior to randomisation; Subject has a clinically significant, active (during the past 12 months) disease of the gastrointestinal, hepatic (liver function tests, more than 200% upper limit of the reference range, except yGlutamuyl transferase), pulmonary, cardiovascular, neurological, genitourinary, endocrine, or haematological system that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may confound the results of the trial or pose additional risk in administering trial product; Current or past history of acidosis; Current hypokalaemia; hyponatraemia; glomerular filtration rate &lt; 60 mL/minute; or elevated plasma lactate; Adrenal insufficiency; Hypersensitivity to, or persons considered at increase risk of hypersensitivity to, methazolamide or acetazolamide, sulfonamides or sulfonamide derivatives, or any excipients in the formulation. (Cross sensitivity between acetazolamide, sulfonamides and other sulfonamide derivatives is possible); History of urolithiasis; History of narrow-angle glaucoma; 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) demonstrating QTc &gt; 450 msec at screening; Pregnant or nursing females; females of childbearing potential who are unwilling or unable to use an acceptable method of contraception from at least 14 days prior to the first dose of trial medication until completion of follow-up procedures;</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will be assigned a unique 3 digit identification number (Screening Number) as they are screened for the trial. 
On Day 0, Participants who are deemed eligible for randomisation will receive a randomisation number, consisting of a two-digit number. Randomisation numbers will be allocated sequentially starting at 01 as each participant is enrolled into the study. Participants will be identified by both the screening number and the randomisation number for the duration of the study. 

The Participants will be randomised to receive VVP808 or placebo in a 1:1 ratio.  Treatments will be administered according to the randomised sequence under the control of the unblinded pharmacist at the Geelong Hospital Pharmacy Department.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation code will be developed by a statistician - simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Verva Pharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4, 199 Moorabool St
Geelong VIC 3220</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Verva Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, 199 Moorabool St
Geelong VIC 3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Geelong Hospital
PO Box 281
Geelong VIC 3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/82</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/08/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Research &amp; Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>5 Arnold Street
BOX HILL VIC 3128
AUSTRALIA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>E41/1910</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Henry Buck Building
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3081</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>03801</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Geoff Nicholson</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical and Biomedical Sciences
The Geelong Hospital
PO Box 281
Geelong VIC 3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5226 7972</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5222 2420</fax>
      <email>geoffn@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Alana Sarah</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical and Biomedical Sciences
The Geelong Hospital
PO Box 281
Geelong VIC 3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5226 7621</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5260 3306</fax>
      <email>alanas@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kathy Skoff</name>
      <address>PO Box 490 Crows Nest NSW 1585</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)409 596 088</phone>
      <fax>NA</fax>
      <email>kskoff@vervapharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>