<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83452">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000087257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Determining which throat muscles are important in obstructive sleep apnoea</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Upper airway muscle function during wakefulness and sleep in individuals with and without obstructive sleep apnoea</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive sleep apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant will have two small catheters inserted into the upper airway (throat) and oesophagus via the nose.  Fine wire electrodes will be inserted into the genioglossus, geniohyoid, tensor palatini and levator palatini muscles.  The catheters and wires will be inserted in the late afternoon and remain in place until the following morning (approximately 15 hours total).  These wires and catheters will allow measurement of the activity of the upper airway muscles during wakefulness and sleep to determine which muscles are important in maintaining an open airway and how they may be failing to allow upper airway collapse in patients with sleep apnoea.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparisons of the activity of the upper airway muscles between individuals with and without obstructive sleep apnoea.  Upper airway muscle activity will be measured using intramuscular electromyography ( fine wires will be inserted into each muscle).  The amount of activity recorded will be compared between groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Overall, the study will run for 12 months.  Comparisons of upper airway activity will be made between groups as soon as data collection in all subjects is complete, which is likely to be at approximately 12 months, although may occur sooner.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparisons of catheter-based measurements of upper airway muscle activity with fine-wire measurements of upper airway muscle activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Overall, the study will run for 12 months. Comparisons of upper airway activity will be made between the fine wires and the catheter measurements of muscle activity as soon as data collection in all subjects is complete, which is likely to be at approximately 12 months, although may occur sooner.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age &gt;18yrs
Without uncontrolled hypertension, without type 1 diabetes or uncontrolled type II diabetes, without cardiovascular disease.
Healthy individual or diagnosis of obstructive sleep apnoea</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age &lt;18 years
Uncontrolled hypertension
type 1 diabetes 
uncontrolled type II diabetes
cardiovascular disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hospital Avenue Nedlands
Perth 6009 
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Project Grant No. 572647</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421, Canberra, ACT 2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstructive sleep apnoea is a common and treatable condition characterised by upper airway (throat) collapse which results in the repeated cessation of breathing during sleep.  It is associated with disrupted sleep and excessive daytime tiredness and lethargy, which have major consequences for social well-being and productivity in our community.  It is association with hypertension and is an independent risk factor for cardiovascular disease.

Upper airway muscle activity is important in the pathogenesis of obstructive sleep apnoea, both in the development of upper airway collapse and in the restoration of an open airway.  The gold standard method of measuring muscle activity by the use of intramuscular electrodes.  This technique while relatively painless is invasive as the skin must be punctured.  A catheter based technique may allow non-invasive measurement of muscle activity without puncturing the skin.  The purpose of this study is to (i) compare the effectiveness of intramuscular recordings of muscle activity with catheter-based recordings of muscle activity and (ii)to determine the role of the upper airway muscles (specifically the genioglossus, geniohyoid, tensor palatini and levator palatini) in maintaining an open airway with inspiratory loading (i.e. increased effort to breathe) during wakefulness and sleep in normal, healthy individuals and individuals with sleep apnoea.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee 
Level 1 E-Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital 
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands Perth 6009
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008-175</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/11/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Peter Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology
Level 5-G Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Perth WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 2888</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Eastwood@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Peter Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology
Level 5-G Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Perth WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 2888</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Eastwood@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Peter Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology
Level 5-G Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Perth WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 2888</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Eastwood@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>