<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="730">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000513617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>COMPARISON OF INTRANASAL CORTICOSTEROIDS WITH ALLERGEN AVOIDANCE FOR THE MANAGEMENT OF PERSISTENT RHINITIS</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>COMPARISON OF INTRANASAL CORTICOSTEROIDS WITH ALLERGEN AVOIDANCE FOR THE MANAGEMENT OF PERSISTENT RHINITIS</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Persistent Allergic Rhinitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is a parallel, stratified, randomised controlled trial. This protocol involves recruitment via a physician or the Woolcock Institute volunteer database, a 4-week run-in period where allergen exposure and symptoms are monitored to determine that the subject complies with the entry criteria. Subjects are then allocated, using a randomised block design, stratified for allergen exposure, to parallel interventions involving either multiple allergen avoidance methods (this includes bed encasings from Mite-GuardTM, Sunbeam HEPA air filter and frequent washing using the acaracide Acaril) or conventional pharmacotherapy (using Nasonex®, i.e. mometasone furoate) for 8 weeks. Twenty subjects are to be completed before early September.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. That mite allergen avoidance methods can provide marked reduction in total inhaled exposure to allergens if the allergen removal practices are frequent and aggressive and if they address both reservoirs of allergens and aeroallergens</outcome>
      <timepoint>Allergen levels measured every fortnight.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Such reductions in nocturnal exposure would improve symptoms of persistent rhinitis in subjects for whom mite allergens are their major allergen exposure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Symptom diaries measured daily.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. That pharmacotherapy can also provide effective management of rhinitis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Symptom diaries measured daily.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Both forms of management provide different time courses for the relief of symptoms (daily symptom diaries) and in the longer term, raise different issues of patient compliance and satisfaction with the treatment (compliance and satisfaction measured at the end of treatment using questionnaires).</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Physician-diagnosed, persistent allergic rhinitis. Mite allergic (SPT wheal &gt;2mm than +ve histamine control). Have &gt;75% of their total domestic mite allergen exposure while in bed. Have daily symptoms of rhinitis that will enable an improvement to be measured. No asthma, or have only mild to moderate asthma (as classified by Physician). Willing, able and otherwise suitable to participate and perform the required interventions. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Existing daily use of oral or topical intra-nasal corticosteroids. Severe asthma (as classified by Physician). Have an existing combination of allergies to other (non-mite) domestic allergens and associated exposure to these allergens that may compromise the effectiveness of the planned intervention directed at mite allergen exposure. For example, being cat allergic and being exposed to a cat at home would serve to exclude, as the intervention in beds cannot control cat allergen exposure in the house. However if there is cat allergy but no cat exposure, or cat exposure but no cat allergy, then this is not grounds for exclusion. Pregnancy. Current or recent history of a purulent nasal infection. Nasal Polyps. Exclusion criteria for the medication include tuberculosis, herpes simplex of the eye, recent nasal surgery or untreated nasal infections. Complete nasal obstruction.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patient names were placed into sealed envelopes and then randomly allocated into either arm of the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Coin toss; blocking</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/04/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>niversity of Sydney (Pharmacology Department)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney (Pharmacology Department)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Ana Acevska</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
University of Sydney
Level 4
Blackburn Building D06
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93512093</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93517451</fax>
      <email>aace3530@mail.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Wendy Taylor</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
PO Box M77
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95156578</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95505865</fax>
      <email>volunteers@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>