<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368599">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000578505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Combining Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS) with Cognitive Training for Cognitive Impairment following Traumatic Brain Injury: A Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating the neurobiological and neurocognitive effects of combining cognitive training with tDCS following traumatic brain injury.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will undergo repeated sessions (20 in total) of Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS). tDCS involves the application of a very gentle electrical current applied using two surface electrodes (anode and cathode) to the scalp . tDCS has been shown to increase brain activity in areas important for cognition.

Participants will be randomly allocated to one of the following two conditions;
1. Twenty sessions of 20 minute active tDCS to the left Dorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex (DLPFC) at a current density of 0.0057 ma/cm over four weeks, Monday-Friday combined with computerised cognitive training using 'Brain HQ' a commercially available cognitive training package from Posit Science.

2. Twenty sessions of 20 minute sham tDCS to the left DLPFC at a current density of 0.0057 ma/cm over four weeks, Monday-Friday combined with computerised cognitive training using 'Brain HQ' a commercially available cognitive training package from Posit Science.

The computerised cognitive training will be completed on a laptop computer for 5 x 30 minute sessions per week for 4 weeks. Cognitive training will be completed in the presence of a research assistant who will monitor engagement/adherence with the training. The computerised tasks are designed to target attention, processing speed and memory.</interventions>
    <comparator>Stimulation will be delivered using the StarStim system which allows for
programming of tDCS, itDCS and sham.
Sham tDCS is achieved by switching off stimulation after approx. 30s;
which occurs within the software of the Starstim system allowing for
administrator and patient blinding. There is no evidence that 30 seconds
of tDCS induces any changes in the brain. The provision of stimulation for
30 seconds allows participants to experience the initial physical
sensations of tDCS, which typically fade after 30seconds, thus providing
a robust sham. This is a standard method of blinding for tDCS.

The computerised cognitive training will be completed on a laptop computer for 5 x 30 minute sessions per week for 4 weeks. Cognitive training will be completed in the presence of a research assistant who will monitor engagement/adherence with the training. The computerised tasks are designed to target attention, processing speed and memory.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MATRICS Consensus battery
The MATRICS battery is a multi-domain cognitive battery specifically designed for repeated use. We will be
assessing the domains of speed of processing, attention, verbal learning, working memory, visual learning, reasoning, and problem solving.
Although all of these domains are measured separately by the MATRICS, it also allows for a Global Cognition score to be calculated.
This is a composite primary outcome.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Endpoint (i.e. pre and post 20 sessions of tDCS stimulation)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>TMS-EEG data.
TMS-EEG is performed by stimulating the scalp over the DLPFC while
simultaneously recording brain activity via surrounding EEG electrodes.
The TMS pulse produces a neurophysiological response in the underlying cortex, referred to as a TMS evoked potential (TEP), which is recorded onEEG and the TEP amplitude gives an index of cortical excitability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Endpoint (i.e. pre and post 20 sessions of tDCS)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be included if they: (1) are aged 18-65 and have capacity to consent; (2) have experienced a closed head injury of mild to moderate severity determined by patient reports and hospital records of a loss of consciousness (LOC) of less than 24 hours, and an initial GCS of more than 9 ; (3) are at least 6 weeks post injury to allow a degree a recovery from injuries sustained from the TBI prior to entering the trial; (4) have an IQ of greater than 70 as determined by performance on the Wechsler Test of Adult Reading (WTAR) (to ensure they understand the study requirements)  ; (5) exhibit cognitive impairment, defined as a performance greater than 1 SD below published norms on any domain within the MATRICS.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they (1) have a diagnosis of a Psychiatric illness, lifetime (i.e. either pre or post TBI). In particular, as rTMS is known to effectively treat depression and this may impact upon the outcome variables, the presence of a depressive disorder (DSM 5 criteria) will exclude participation; (2) have drug dependence or abuse; (3) have a personal or family history of a seizure disorder; (4) an unstable medical condition, neurological disorder, are currently pregnant or lactating; (5) have metal in the cranium, a pacemaker, cochlear implant, medication pump or other electronic device.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed; by the research assistant contacting the principal investigator who has a computer generated random sequence for treatment groups after the participant is deemed eligible and has consented for the study.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kate Hoy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>MAPrc,
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road,
Melbourne,
3004,
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council, RD Wright Biomedical Career Development Fellowship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash University
Victoria 3800
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash University
Victoria 3800
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI) can lead to fundamental changes in a persons ability to function day-to-day. The development of cognitive impairment is a particularly common and disabling consequence. As such, rehabilitation of cognition is an important part of post head injury treatment but current standard cognitive rehabilitation (consisting of either re-training / remediating impaired abilities) has generally resulted in only modest improvements in functioning.  
Our study will explore an innovative approach to repairing cognitive functioning following TBI that combines biological modulation of neural systems with behavioural remediation. We will combine transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS), a non-invasive brain stimulation technique, with cognitive training and examine the effectiveness of this combination using a Randomised Controlled Trial design. The ultimate aim of this research is the development of an effective targeted treatment for cognitive impairment following TBI to allow for a more complete recovery following injury.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004,</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>123/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>MAPrc, Level 4, 607 St Kilda Road, Melbourne, 3004 VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>MAPrc
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road,
Melbourne,
3004
VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>MAPrc
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road,
Melbourne,
3004
VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Hannah Coyle</name>
      <address>MAPrc
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road,
Melbourne,
3004
VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 8649</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hannah.coyle@monash.edu</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>