<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368827">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000826549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Eye Movement Desensitization and Reprocessing for postoperative pain management in adolescents</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To investigate the efficacy of Eye Movement Desensitization and Reprocessing (EMDR) for postoperative pain management in adolescents aged between 12 to 18. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-5644 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>postoperative pain </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An experimental, randomised controlled trial. 
The Wong-Baker FACES Pain Rating Scale (WBFS) was first administered to all patients approximately 2 hours post-surgery, when each patient was reported to be conscious and alert. Participants also had their blood pressure and heart rate taken at this point. Participants were then taken to a private room, where they either underwent the EMDR or control condition activities. Following the administration of the WBFS, EMDR was administered to participants in the treatment group for 60 minutes. 
EMDR therapy 
EMDR therapy typically involves eight distinct phases: 1) Client history, 2) Preparation, 3) Assessment, 4) Desensitization, 5) Installation, 6) Body Scan, 7) Closure, and 8) Re-evaluation (Shapiro &amp; Laliotis 2010). The first two stages are preparatory and primarily involve briefing the patient on the technique, as well as receiving relevant information regarding the patients history. The third stage (Assessment) centres around identifying negative and positive cognitions related to the trauma. It begins with identifying negative target memories for reprocessing, where participants are instructed to represent such memories as either a representative image or an associated negative cognition. In this experiment target cognitions comprised descriptions of negative beliefs associated with the surgery (e.g. I am in danger, or It will be painful) and/or negative images associated with the surgery (e.g. a visual representation of the surgical procedure). Participants were then instructed to form a positive cognition related to their target cognition/image. In this experiment participants were instructed to state how they would like to feel in words (e.g. I am in control or I am not in danger) or using imagery (lying in bed, free of pain). 
During the fourth and fifth stages (Desensitization and Installation), the negative cognition/image is recreated in the participants mind, and the patient is asked to track the therapists fingers, which are constantly displaced across the patients line of vision (Shapiro 1989). The speed of the eye movements is gradually increased until it is as fast as is comfortable for the client to maintain accurate tracking. During this process the patient is told to report any information that they become aware of, and once tracking is finished they are told to let it go or blank it out (Smith &amp; Yule 1999, p. 269). This process is repeated until no further improvements occur. The positive cognition is then installed by having patients think of the negative event and positive cognition in parallel, whilst completing a further set of eye movements. This is repeated until patients have internalized the positive cognition, as indicated by the Validity of Cognition (VOC) scale (see Shapiro et al. 2010).
 In the sixth stage (Body Scan), patients carry out a final set of eye movements, designed to target residual tension that occurs when participants are asked to again think of the original negative image/cognition. EMDR is only regarded as successful when participants can recall the initial image/cognition without experiencing body tension or pain. In the final two stages, Closure and Re-evaluation, participants are led through a range of relaxation exercises and debriefed. If participants require more than one session this is discussed in the final stage (Re-evaluation). In the current study patients all participated in only a single session. For a full overview of EMDR therapy, see Shapiro et al. (2010).

a psychologist who had training in EMDR administered the EMDR.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group were not administered EMDR, but were instead subjected to a range of carefully worded, emotionally neutral, open-ended interview questions over the 60-minute period. Questions specifically focused on patient history as well as some general questions about health beliefs. Participants in both conditions therefore had similar levels of interaction with health professionals following the surgery. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative pain intensity as assessed using the Wong-Baker FACES Pain Rating Scale (WBFS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours post-surgery

 The the Wong-Baker FACES Pain Rating Scale (WBFS) was administered to all patients approximately 2 hours post-surgery (pre test), and then  3 hours post-surgery (post test).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative anxiety as measured using the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI). </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours post surgery
The State-Trait Anxiety Inventory was administered 2 hours post-surgery (pre test),  and then  3 hours post-surgery (post test).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adolescents age between 12 to 18, candidates for abdominal surgery at Alzahra hospital, Isfahan, Iran. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>chronic medical problems, such as epilepsy, asthma, diabetic mellitus and haematological problems, and also children with psychiatric problems, including mental retardation, depressive and bipolar disorders and any kinds of psychotic disorders</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>9/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/08/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>56</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>56</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state>Isfahan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ms Shahla Zamani </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Azad University of Khorasgan,  Olum Tahghighat, Korasgan, Isfahan, Iran.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>the Azad University of Khorasgan, Olum Tahghighat, </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Azad University of Khorasgan,  Olum Tahghighat, Korasgan, Isfahan, Iran.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Zahra Izadikhah</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The School of Psychology and Counselling, the University of Southern Queensland, 487/521-535 West Street, Toowoomba, Queensland, Australia. Post Code: 4350.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>EMDR is an inexpensive, non-pharmacological intervention, initially used to treat Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD), but recent research has indicated the potential benefit of EMDR in a range of other physical and psychological conditions. In this experimental study, a total of 56 adolescent surgical patients aged between 12 and 18 years were allocated to gender-balanced EMDR (treatment) or non-EMDR (control) groups. Pain was measured using the Wong-Baker FACES "Registered Trademark" Pain Rating Scale (WBFS) before and after the intervention (or non-intervention for the control group). Data were analyzed using a range of non-parametric tests, and indicated that participants in the EMDR group experienced a significant reduction in pain intensity after treatment intervention in comparison with the control group.


 

 </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>NA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>the Azad University of Khorasgan, Olum e Tahghighat,  </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>the Azad University of Khorasgan, Olume Tahghighat, Khorasgan, Isfahan, Iran.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>48620701912004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zahra Izadikhah</name>
      <address>the School of Psychology and Counselling, The University of Southern Queensland, 487/521-535 West Street, Toowoomba, Queensland, Post Code: 4350.</address>
      <phone>+61 403 007 963</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zahra.izadikhah@usq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zahra Izadikhah</name>
      <address>the School of Psychology and Counselling, The University of Southern Queensland, 487/521-535 West Street, Toowoomba, Queensland, Post Code: 4350.</address>
      <phone>+61 403 007 963</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zahra.izadikhah@usq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zahra Izadikhah </name>
      <address>the School of Psychology and Counselling, The University of Southern Queensland,  487/521-535 West Street, Toowoomba, Queensland, Post Code: 4350.</address>
      <phone>+61 403 007 963</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zahra.izadikhah@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>