<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308380">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000737235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of an in-hospital exercise group for respiratory patients and physiotherapy care.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a twice weekly inpatient exercise group and standard physiotherapy care of respiratory patients on uptake of Pulmonary Rehabilitation, physical activity levels and Quality of Life</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Standard Physiotherapy care including mobilisation and airway clearance techniques and education as appropriate. Prescription based on individual needs.

Exercise Class including thoracic mobilisation exercises, Upper Limb strengthening exercises, education and cariovascular exercises. Prescription based on individual needs.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatment consists of Standard Physiotherapy care including mobilisation and airway clearance techniques and education as appropriate. Prescription based on individual needs.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attendance at Pulmonary Rehabilitation</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post discharge from acute hospital setting</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Related Quality of Life as measured on the Chronic Respiratory Disease Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post discharge from acute hospital setting</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Levels as based on the Six Minute Walk Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post discharge from acute hospital setting</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Admitted with an acute exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)
Be located on 44N / 44S
Be admitted under the respiratory 
Be medically stable
Blood Pressure appropriate for mobilisation (ie &gt; 100)
Heart Rate appropriate for mobilisation (ie &lt;120)
Oxygen Saturation (SpO2) &gt;or = 90% or within acceptable range documented by medical staff with or without oxygen
Oxygen &lt; or = 4L O2 / min via Nasal Prongs (NP)
Deemed appropriate by the treating unit to attend the group 
Be eligible to attend outpatient Pulmonary Rehabilitation classes following discharge
Be able to transfer with supervision or minimal assistance + / - gait aid</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Do not meet the medically stable criteria as listed above
Have been admitted from a Nursing Home, 
Do not have a basic understanding of both spoken and written English to be able to communicate effectively within the group session and understand the written information given (Respiratory Home Exercise Program Booklet).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The principal researcher will be responsible for identifying eligible participants based on hospital admission diagnosis, and other inclusion criteria as discussed previously.  At this time, the principal researcher will be unaware to which group the participant will be allocated to.

After providing informed consent, the independent recruitor will collect initial data Unit Record (UR) number, age, sex, relevant past medical history, and admission diagnosis.
Consenting participants will be randomly allocated to the exercise or control group. Allocation will be determined using computer generated allocation sequence and recorded and concealed until the participant has been admitted to the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated allocation sequence</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>78</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alison Fisher</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Health, Monash Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project will investigate the effect of a twice weekly inpatient exercise group and standard physiotherapy care of respiratory patients on uptake of Pulmonary Rehabilitation, physical activity levels, and Quality of Life.
Participants who are admitted with an acute exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease and located on 44 South or 44North, deemed able to exercise by the treating medical unit and able to participate in the group by the treating physiotherapist will be randomised into either the control or exercise group.  
The Grade One Physiotherapist who is not attached to either the Respiratory or General Medical Units will collect participant characteristics (age, COPD severity, Lung Function Test if available and admission dates), and questionnaire data once recruited to the project. Participants will then be randomized into control group (where they will receive standard physiotherapy treatment) or exercise group (where they will attend the Fit to Breathe Group as well as receiving standard physiotherapy treatment).
At discharge, discharge destination, questionnaire data (Chronic Respiratory Disease Questionnaire), physical activity levels (6MWT) and length of stay data will be collected.
On discharge, all participants will receive Pulmonary Rehabilitation Referrals and the Respiratory Home Exercise Booklet and completed Home Exercise Program.
All participants will return for follow up assessment 12 weeks following discharge.  At this assessment, 6MWT and the Chronic Respiratory Questionnaire will be repeated. The Pulmonary Rehabilitation coordinators will also be contacted to determine attendance at Pulmonary Rehabilitation. All patient information will be kept in the locked filing cabinet in the physiotherapy department.
All data will be collected by the Grade One physiotherapist and entered into a password-protected Microsoft excel table. Participant review dates will be recorded in the 2009 A4 diary which will also be kept in this filing cabinet. 

Differences in the proportion of participants who undertake outpatient Pulmonary Rehabilitation will be examined using chi squared test. Repeated measures analysis of variance will be used to examine differences in physical activity, 6-minute walk and quality of life data.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Ethics Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09181B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Alison Fisher</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9594 6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.fisher@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Alison Fisher</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9594 6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.fisher@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Alison Fisher</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9594 6666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.fisher@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>