<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366587">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000923662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Promoting Gross motor skills among toddlers in childcare settings. The Active Beginnings Pilot RCT.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Development of a fundamental movement skill program to enhance gross motor skill development and physical activity among children aged 1-3 years. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1158-3390</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gross Motor Skill Development in Toddlers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The purpose of this project is to develop a motor skill development resource for toddlers aged 1-3 years. The expected outcomes will be an evidence-based resource that meets the needs and wants of the community partner, Big Fat Smile. After development, educators will be trained in the area of toddler motor development for improved pedagogy and practice. Then, the toddlers will receive instruction in how to develop these motor skills, resulting in increased learning and motor skill development. 

Participants will comprise toddlers aged 1-3 years from four Big Fat Smile Community Pre-schools: Stewart Street, Kenny Street, Warrawong, and Barrack Heights. Two services will be randomised to the intervention group and two to the control group. The control group will receive the training and the resource at the end of the intervention. 
Toddlers will be asked to participate in a gross motor skills development intervention program. 

Pre-intervention and post-intervention assessments of gross motor skills will be conducted using the Gross motor sub-scale of the Bayley Scale of Infant and Toddler Development. Assessments will be conducted in Intervention and control groups. The intervention will last for 9 weeks in which toddlers will be better instructed by educators in how to develop these motor skills, resulting in increased learning and motor skill development. During the intervention, a process evaluation will be done to assess feasibility and accessibility. This will involve the research assistant observing the number of sessions that were implemented and gathering feedback from the educators through informal discussions and an interview their thoughts regarding the resource and its implementation.
The educators will develop confidence in this area through working together with UOW researchers, enabling them to repeat this process when refining resources in the future (sustainability).

Educators will receive training through a group session, coordinated by the centre director. This session will be attended by all Educators. There will be one session of two hours training. The training will be instructed by Chief Investigator Tony Okely. 

The toddler intervention duration and frequency will be a daily session of 10 minutes for the 9 week program. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive the training and the resource at the end of the intervention.
Assessments of gross motor skills will be conducted using the Gross motor sub-scale of the Bayley Scale of Infant and Toddler Development. Assessments will be conducted in Intervention and control groups, at baseline timepoint and 9 week follow up time point.

The Control group will receive their normal curriculum. 


</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The purpose of this project is to develop and assess a gross motor skill development resource for toddlers aged 1-3 years. To assess the effect of the program on the toddlers they will perform an assessment of Gross Motor Skills at Baseline and followup. 

Gross Motor Skills will be assessed using the Bayley Scale of Infant and Toddler Development. Areas to be assessed will be Jump, Kick and Balance. Two researchers and two assistants will assess the gross motor skills of the children included in this study. To reduce the chance in differences between ratings, and thereby influencing the inter-rater reliability, all assessors attended a two-hour training workshop and were provided opportunities to discuss and practice the measurements.
During baseline measurements all four assessors were blinded. At follow-up only the research assistants will be blinded, since the researchers will have been facilitating the Active Beginnings program in the two intervention centres. 
When assessing, the assessor will demonstrate each skill to the children and then the children will be asked to perform the skill to the best of their ability. While performing their balance, jump and kick skills, the assessor will then rate the different components of the skill according to the assessment tool.
This assessment will provide data on the impact of the resource on the children and effect the further development of the resource.

 The expected outcome will be an evidence-based resource that meets the needs and wants of the community partner, Big Fat Smile. 



No power calculations were performed since this is a pilot study and is not designed to detect statistically significant differences but rather to determine feasibility and acceptability of the resource. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline data collection at start. Follow-up data collection at 10 weeks. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasability data: Data on the amount of children in the centres, the amount of eligible children and the amount of recruited children was collected. The retention rate was calculated after the follow-up measurements were completed. Additionally, feasibility data were collected through overall questions on the program and the resource at the end of the intervention period.  

</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intervention and at 10 week post intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability data: During the intervention period the researcher collected data on acceptability by collecting data on the participation of the children and the educators in the experiences. Also data on the duration of the intentional learning experiences and the content were collected daily.

Educators from the intervention centres completed a standardized evaluation form after the facilitation of every gross motor skill. For some skills, this would be after two weeks, for others this would be after three weeks. Educators were asked to assess the different aspects of the resource including the appropriateness of the activities, the duration of the lessons and the equipment needed. Rating was done on a five scale, varying from highly inappropriate to highly appropriate. Additionally, they were asked to give suggestions for improvements and additional activities to add to the resource. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During intervention and at 10 week post intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be actively enrolled in the nominated Big Fat Smile Childcare Centre. Participants must be aged between 1 to 3 years old. 
Educators involved in assistting the implementation of the program must be actively employed by Big Fat Smile. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>3</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children participants must be within the eligible age range to participate. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Simple randomisation using procedure used - Names of centres were written on paper and randomly selected from a box. This box was out of the line of sight of the person selecting the names. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using numbered containers</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Approximately 50 children aged 1 and 3 years and six educators will be recruited across four Early Childhood services. Approximately 25 children will be from the intervention services and 25 from the control services

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>56</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>2528 - Barrack Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>2502 - Warrawong</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Wollongong, School of Education, Faculty of Social Sciences, Faculty Research Grant.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Education.
Northfields Ave.
University of Wollongong.
NSW, 2522, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Big Fat Smile. </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 98 Railway Street
Corrimal NSW 2518

PO Box 475 Corrimal NSW 2518</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this project is to develop a motor skill development resource for toddlers aged 1-3 years. The expected outcomes will be an evidence-based resource that meets the needs and wants of the community partner, Big Fat Smile. After development, educators will be trained in the area of toddler motor development for improved pedagogy and practice. Then, the toddlers will receive better instruction in how to develop these motor skills, resulting in increased learning and motor skill development. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Social Sciences Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Wollongong</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> 	The Social Sciences Human Research Ethics Committee,

Research Services Office
Building 20, Level 1
University of Wollongong,
Northfields Ave
Wollongong NSW 2522.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE14/068</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366587-Appendix A, Ver1 03-03-2014.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366587-Appendix B, Ver 1 03-03-14.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366587-Appendix C, Ver 1 03-03-14.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366587-Appendix D, Ver 1 03-03-14.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Tony Okely</name>
      <address>Tony Okely.
School of Education
Faculty of Social Sciences.
Northfields ave
University of Wollongong
NSW
2522</address>
      <phone>+61 02 42214641</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tokely@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Tony Okely</name>
      <address>Tony Okely.
School of Education
Faculty of Social Sciences.
Northfields ave
University of Wollongong
NSW
2522</address>
      <phone>+61 02 42214641</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tokely@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Tony Okley</name>
      <address>Tony Okely.
School of Education
Faculty of Social Sciences.
Northfields ave
University of Wollongong
NSW
2522</address>
      <phone>+61 02 42214641</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tokely@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Tamara Raso</name>
      <address>Building 22.106
School of Education
Faculty of Social Sciences.
Northfields ave
University of Wollongong
NSW
2522</address>
      <phone>+61 02 42215517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>traso@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>