<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372631">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000564358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Slip and trip training for falls prevention  in older adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Reactive step training to improve reactive responses to slips and trips in older adults: a randomized controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>The Slip-Trip study</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Reactive stepping performance to avoid falls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention (reactive step training) group will walk along a 10-m walkway consisting of 50cm x 50cm wooden decking tiles. They will be asked to step onto step-length black and white vinyl target tiles placed on the walkway with the accompaniment of music with a beat reflecting the desired cadence. Slips will be induced by a movable tile on two hidden low-friction rails with linear bearings that can slide upon foot contact (20cm, 30cm or 40cm). A friction plat will be applied to slow down the slip speed until a participant learns to respond well. Trips are induced using a tripping board (7cm or 14cm height) that flips up from the walkway at mid-swing using a wireless controller. The tripping board and the slipping tile are concealed and can be moved to various locations along the walkway so that proactive adaptation (e.g. changing gait with prediction) will be minimized and reactive stepping response can be specifically trained. Gait speed (40% to 90% of individual's normal gait), slip distance (20cm, 30cm or 40cm) and speed (with/without the friction plate) will be adjusted by a Health Fitness Programmer according to participant's anxiety level and perceived difficulty. Reactive step training will be conducted in three 40-minute sessions (120 minutes in total). Session 1 will train recovery from trips, session 2 will train recovery from slips and session 3 will train recovery from a mix of trips and slips. The 3 individual sessions will be held in 2 days (1st day: training sessions 1 and 2 with lunch break, 2nd day: training session 3) within a week. Attendance of and actual training contents (e.g. gait speed, slip distance and trip height) used for each participant will be recorded. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control (target step walking) group will walk on the same walkway. They will be asked to step on the target tiles, with the accompaniment of music with a beat reflecting the desired cadence but without slip and trip perturbations for 30 times (equivalent to the number of walks in a session for the intervention group) in one 40-minute session.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fall incidence after slip- and trip-perturbations in the laboratory. All participants will be asked to walk at 90% of their normal gait speed. The gait speed will be constrained using the black and white vinyl stepping tiles (adjusted to 95% of normal step length) and metronome (adjusted to 95% of normal cadence). Non-friction 70cm slip and 14cm trip at random locations will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Margin of stability after slip- and trip-perturbations. An 8-camera Vicon motion analysis system will be used to record kinematic data during slip and trip trials. The margin of stability in anterior-posterior direction will be calculated as the distance between an extrapolated centre of mass to a closest base of support limit. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kinematic characteristics of the balance response (step length/height, slipping distance/speed, extrapolated centre of mass displacement, foot contact angle, etc)  immidediately before and after slip- and trip-onsets. An 8-camera Vicon motion analysis system will be used to record kinematic data during slip and trip trials. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physiological profile assessment-short form</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Choice stepping reaction time (CSRT) with inhibitory stimulus. The CSRT system consists of an electronic step mat, integrated with a computer via Bluetooth. The computer unit and monitor will be placed on the ground 50 cm in front of the step mat. Participants will be asked to view the screen that displays the stepping arrows and step onto the corresponding step mat target panel as quickly as possible.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after the intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot reaction time. This will be assessed using a hand-held electronic timer and a light as the stimulus and depression of a switch by the foot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Older adults living independently in the community or retirement village.
Exercising  for  90  minutes  per  week  (e.g.  fitness  class,  walking  specifically  for  exercise,  strength training, Tai Chi, etc) for the past 3 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Osteoporosis, neurological impairment and a history of fractures in the last 3 years, or joint replacement in the past 12 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A research assistant, who is not a co-author, will perform the simple randomization using a random number created with Excel 2010 in a locked electronic file. A tester will contact this research assistant after baseline assessment to determine participants’ group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A simple randomization table will be created with Excel 2010.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Forty participants will be recruited. This sample size will be sufficient to detect a difference in the proportion of fallers in the intervention and control groups in the laboratory based on the following assumptions: (10% fallers in intervention group, 50% fallers in control group, alpha error: 0.05, power: 0,80 and allocation ratio: 1:1).

Chi-squared test will be used to examine the between-group difference in falls after the slip- and trip-perturbations. The analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be used to examine the time (pre/post) and group (intervention/control) interactions in the continuous outcomes. Paired t-test will be used to examine the within-group (pre-post) changes in the continuous outcomes. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>21/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>20</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>7/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA) - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neuroscience Research Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street Randwick Sydney NSW 2031 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, Fawkner Centre, 499 St Kilda Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Japan Society for the Promotion of Science</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5-3-1 Kojimachi, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 102-0083</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Japan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Falls among older adults cause serious challenges for the individual and health care systems, including bone fractures. Our recent systematic review and meta-analysis has shown that reactive step training (repeated exposure to balance perturbations) can reduce falls by approximately 50%  (Okubo et al., 2016).  However, the methods to generate perturbations (e.g. slips) in previous studies have been considerably heterogeneous and have limitations to training reactive balance control. We have developed a novel overground perturbation system which can generate both slips and trips in random locations. Since this system can provide unpredictable slips and trips, it is theoretically possible to train specifically reactive balance control (as opposed to proactive balance control or prediction). This randomized controlled trial will examine the effectiveness of the reactive step training using this perturbation system in older adults. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the University of New South Wales</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC16227</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen R Lord</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, Barker Street Randwick, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.lord@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yoshiro Okubo</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, Barker Street Randwick, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>y.okubo@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yoshiro Okubo</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, Barker Street Randwick, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>y.okubo@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yoshiro Okubo</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia, Barker Street Randwick, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1065</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>y.okubo@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>