<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82505">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/01/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000007336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The future of corneal refractive reshaping: can we control myopia or is the risk of corneal compromise too great?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, randomised, controlled, cross-over study to evaluate the effects of orthokeratology versus conventional rigid gas permeable contact lens wear on the progression of myopia in children and adolescents.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Progressing mild childhood myopia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects with progressing myopia will wear an orthokeratology lens (BE design; RD1800 material) in one eye on an overnight basis, and a conventional rigid gas-permeable (RGP) contact lens (J-Contour design, RD1800 material) in the other eye for either daily or extended wear, for a 6-month period.  After 6 months, the eye/lens combinations will be reversed and the lenses worn for a further 6 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>A matched control group of spectacle-wearing subjects will be enrolled and followed for 12 months.  The conventional RGP lens-wearing eye will also act as a contralateral control in the lens-wearing group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome variable will be axial length change as measured using the IOLMaster ocular biometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Axial length will be measured at baseline, and 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after commencement of lens wear.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The relative rate of corneal epithelial cell exfoliation during gentle eye wash with sterile saline, and the amount of bacterial binding to harvested epithelial cells will be determined using a previously published method (Ren et al, 1999).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cell exfoliation rate and bacterial binding will be determined at baseline, and 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after commencement of lens wear.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral refractive status will be determined at 10 degree intervals out to 30 degrees along the horizontal meridian using a Shin-Nippon NVision K5001 autorefractor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Peripheral refraction will be measured at baseline, and 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after commencement of lens wear.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be required to have myopic refractive error between -1.00 and -4.00D at the time of study enrolment, evidence of progression of myopia over the previous 12 months, &lt;0.75D refractive difference between the two eyes, &lt;1.50D with-the-rule corneal astigmatism, and no against-the-rule astigmatism.  Subjects must be of East Asian ethnicity, have good general and ocular health, and no history of rigid contact lens wear.  Normal corneal topography, normal binocular function, and vision correctable to 6/9 (20/30) or better are also required for study enrolment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential subjects will not be enrolled if they show any contraindications for rigid contact lens wear, abnormal binocular function, anisometropia &gt; 0.75D, ocular pathology or active ocular surface disease that would preclude contact lens wear.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomly generated allocations will be held in sealed envelopes by a third party not directly involved in the trial.  Allocation to lens-wearing versus spectacle-wearing (control) groups, and the lens/eye combination to be worn for the first 6 months for the lens-wearing group, will be determined by opening the next envelope in the appropriate sequence.</concealment>
    <sequence>The sequence will be generated by computer generated block randomisation methods, designed to stratify participants by severity of myopia and age, so that treatment and control groups are balanced.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The treatment group (contact lens-wearing group) will be assigned as a cross-over group.  The control (spectacle-wearing) group will be assigned as a parallel group.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/01/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/01/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/04/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Helen Swarbrick</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Optometry and Vision Science, University of New South Wales, Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council (ARC) Linkage Project Grant Scheme</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2702, Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Boston Products Group of Bausch &amp; Lomb</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Research Drive, Wilmington, Massachusetts 01887, USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BE Enterprises Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 7, 12th floor, 141 Queen St, Brisbane, Qld 4000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Capricornia Contact Lens Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/9 Cronulla Court, Slacks Creek, Brisbane, Qld 4127</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine whether the use of overnight orthokeratology contact lenses slows the progression of eye growth in myopic children and adolescents compared to conventional rigid contact lens wear and spectacle use.  At the same time the relative risk for corneal infection (microbial keratitis) with overnight orthokeratology will be evaluated indirectly, using a well-established technique that analyses corneal cell shedding rates and bacterial attachment to these harvested corneal cells.  The relationship between myopia progression and peripheral refractive status will also be investigated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>* Swarbrick H (2012).  Do myopia control studies really answer the important clinical questions?  Nederlands Contact Lens Congress
* Swarbrick H (2012).  Optimising optics and vision through orthokeratology: beyond myopia control.  The 3rd Asia Orthokeratology and Specialty Lens Conference
* Kang P, Swarbrick H (2012).  Orthokeratology, peripheral refraction and myopia control.  10th Congress of the Orthokeratology Society of Oceania
* Kang P (2012).  Future myopia research  where will it take us? 14th International Cornea and Contact Lens Congress
* Watt K, Evans B, Swarbrick H, Eakin P (2012). Phorias and OK. 10th Congress of the Orthokeratology Society of Oceania
* Kang P, Swarbrick H (2011). Peripheral refraction in myopic children wearing OK and GP lenses. Optom Vis Sci 88: 476-82
* Kang P, Swarbrick H (2011). Orthokeratology and peripheral refraction in myopic children. Optom Vis Sci 81:395-403
* Swarbrick H, Alharbi A, Watt K, Lum E (2011).  Controlling myopia progression with overnight orthokeratology.  Asia-ARVO meeting
* Swarbrick H, Alharbi A, Lum E, Watt K (2011). Overnight orthokeratology for myopia control: short-term effects on axial length and refractive error.  British Contact Lens Association
* Swarbrick H, Alharbi A, Lum E, Watt K (2011).  Changes in axial length and refractive error during overnight orthokeratology for myopia control. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 52: E-abstract 2829
* Swarbrick H, Alharbi A, Lum E, Watt K (2011). Effects of overnight orthokeratology on axial length and refractive error in progressive myopia. 16th meeting of the The International Society for Contact Lens Research
* Swarbrick H (2011). The science of overnight orthokeratology.Bausch &amp; Lomb Boston Seminar Series
* Kang P (2011). Myopia control with orthokeratology. Corneal and Contact Lens Society of Australia
* Swarbrick H (2010).  Research in orthokeratology: balancing risks versus benefits.  Global
Specialty Lens Symposium, Las Vegas, Nevada
* Swarbrick H (2010).  Latest OK research from the ROK Group. Nederlands Contactlens
Congres, Veldhoven, the Netherlands
* Swarbrick H (2010).  Balancing risks vs benefits: the safety of overnight OK. Nederlands
Contactlens Congres, Veldhoven, the Netherlands 
* Swarbrick H (2010).  Balancing risks and benefits: update on myopia control with OK lenses. 
Nederlands Contactlens Congres, Veldhoven, the Netherlands 
* Kang P, Swarbrick H (2010). Peripheral Refraction in Myopic Children Wearing OK and GP Contact Lenses. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 51: E-Abstract 3934
* Swarbrick H (2010).  ROK Group myopia study update.  Eighth Congress of the Orthokeratology Society of Oceania, Gold Coast, Queensland
* Swarbrick HA (2010).  Evaluating risks of MK: bacterial binding studies. Eighth Congress of the Orthokeratology Society of Oceania
* Lum E (2010). Are Asian kids OK for OK? Eighth Congress of the Orthokeratology Society of Oceania
* Kang P, Swarbrick H (2010).  Peripheral refraction and orthokeratology. Eighth Congress of the Orthokeratology Society of Oceania
*Swarbrick H (2010).  Orthokeratology and myopia control. 13th Biennial Scientific Meeting in Optometry
* Gifford, P, Kang P, Swarbrick H (2010). Peripheral refraction and orthokeratology.  13th Biennial Scientific Meeting in Optometry
* Kang P, Swarbrick H (2010). Orthokeratology and peripheral refraction in myopic children. 13th Biennial Scientific Meeting in Optometry
* Swarbrick H (2010).  Orthokeratology for myopia control: clinical results.  13th International Cornea and Contact Lens Congress
*Swarbrick H (2010). Managing myopia progression with overnight orthokeratology.  Orthokeratology Academy of America Vision By Design 2010 conference
*Swarbrick H (2010).  The role of overnight orthokeratology in managing childhood myopia progression.  2nd Asia Orthokeratology and Specialty Lens Conference
* Swarbrick H (2010). The role of overnight orthokeratology in managing childhood myopia progression.  TMVC seminar, Annual Meeting of Taiwanese Ophthalmology Society
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of New South Wales, Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/08/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 07032</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Helen Swarbrick</name>
      <address>School of Optometry and Vision Science, University of New South Wales, Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 4373</phone>
      <fax>+612 9313 6243</fax>
      <email>h.swarbrick@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Helen Swarbrick</name>
      <address>School of Optometry and Vision Science, University of New South Wales, Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 4613</phone>
      <fax>+612 9313 6243</fax>
      <email>rokinfo@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Helen Swarbrick</name>
      <address>School of Optometry and Vision Science, University of New South Wales, Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 4373</phone>
      <fax>+612 9313 6243</fax>
      <email>h.swarbrick@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Swarbrick</name>
      <address>School of Optometry and Vision Science, University of New South Wales, Sydney, 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 4373</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.swarbrick@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>