<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363257">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001214820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>To cross-validate the second generation EyeMapper (EyeMapper Gen 2) against the previously validated prototype instrument, EyeMapper Gen 1.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, open-labelled, cross-over, multiple group, randomised clinical trial measuring central and peripheral refractive errors and higher order aberrations using the EyeMapper Gen 1 and EyeMapper Gen 2 instruments in a minimum of 20 myopic and 20 non-myopic participants.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Refractive error of the eye.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be required to attend one visit. For the EyeMapper Gen 2 instrument, the participants head will be positioned on a chin rest and look at an internal fixation target. No contact will be made with the eye at any time. Following alignment, measurement is taken. Five consecutive measurements will be performed per instrument. Overall duration of measurements will be 10 minutes. The participants cross over measurements, not treatments so although this is a crossover trial there is no need for a wash out as the measurement is non invasive. The measurements will occur one after the other.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will be required to attend one visit. For the EyeMapper Gen 1 instrument, the participants head will be positioned on a chin rest and look at an internal fixation target. No contact will be made with the eye at any time. Following alignment, measurement is taken. Five consecutive measurements will be performed per instrument. Overall duration of measurements will be 10 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the central and peripheral refractive error and higher order aberrations between two peripheral aberrometers: the EyeMapper Gen 1 and the EyeMapper Gen 2.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Refractive error and high order aberration measures will be carried out with two non-invasive novel instruments (EyeMapper Gen 1 and EyeMapper Gen 2) before and after the dilation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>N/A</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
Be at least 18 years old, male or female.
Willing to comply with the clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjogrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus.  Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial.
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings / are known to affect a participants ocular health / physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial. 
NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial product is used.
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
Previous corneal refractive surgery.
Rigid gas Permeable or orthokeratology lens wear in the past month. 
Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products.
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.
Pregnancy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be screened for general clinical trial suitability by way of a routine eye examination which includes refraction, visual acuity and general eye health. Informed consent will be obtained prior to any clinical trial procedures.  Both experienced contact lens wearers and neophytes (participants with no prior lens wear experience) will be enrolled into the study; of which, 20 participants will be recruited with spherical equivalent refractive errors greater than -0.75D (non-myopes), and another 20 participants will be recruited with spherical equivalent refractive errors less than or equal to -0.75D (myopes). 

Enrolment will take place over approximately two months. A participant is enrolled when they have signed the Participant Information / Informed Consent Form.  A participant is considered “successfully enrolled” when the Investigator agrees that they conform to the inclusion / exclusion criteria. Central rendomisation will be performed by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised for the order of examination with the two new instruments. The randomisation plan will be generated from http://www.randomisation.com and be done by central randomisation by computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/12/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To cross-validate the second generation EyeMapper (EyeMapper Gen 2) against the previously validated prototype instrument, EyeMapper Gen 1.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road
Dulwich
south Australia 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-08-993</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ravi Bakaraju</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.bakaraju@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ravi Bakaraju</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.bakaraju@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elise Robertson</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.robertson@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ravi Bakaraju</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 7516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.bakaraju@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>