<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366714">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000794606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>To investigate the types of abnormal breathing patterns in patients with Motor neurone disease (MND) and to assess the usefulness of an 'intelligent' respiratory support device in patients who develop respiratory failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective study to systematically assess the nature and time course of sleep disordered breathing and respiratory failure in patients with motor neurone disease and to study the effects of auto-bilevel positive airway pressure [BiPAP] ( with variable expiratory positive airway pressure[EPAP]) vs. standard bilevel positive airway pressure [BiPAP]- spontaneous/timed (S/T) mode , in patients requiring non invasive ventilation(NIV) as per current guidelines</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1159-2858 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Motor Neurone Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ventilatory failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an prospective observational study with a phase II randomised controlled arm. We have previously demonstrated( retrospective observational study) that patients with motor neurone disease( MND) develop a spectrum of various types of sleep disordered breathing.
Aims:
1. A prospective study of 40 patients to delineate the nature and time course of sleep disordered breathing in MND patients referred to the Repatriation General Hospital MND clinic for assessment.
2. Detailed sleep studies of Auto BiPAP ( using BiPAP A 40 AVAPS AE mode AE mode with auto pressure support, auto EPAP and auto back-up rate) vs. currently recommended BiPAP-S/T using a cross-over randomized 2 overnight study design ( consecutive nights), to assess the acute effects of each treatment in patients with respiratory failure, followed by randomization to one of the two treatments and clinical follow-up for 6 months ( minimum). 
This part of the study will include all the patients who meet the criteria for NIV as per the current guidelines. There is no washout period between the two nights, for the cross-over trial.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control using the standard BiPAP S/T mode</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adequacy of nocturnal ventilation on NIV as measured by lowest oxygen saturation, time spent with oxygen saturation &lt;90%, oxygen desaturation index (ODI), minimum oxygen saturation and morning arterial blood gases</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of randomisation ,three and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quality as measured by apnea hypopnea index( AHI), Arousal index, sleep efficiency and  amount of REM sleep.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of randomisation and also 3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as measured by ALS functional rating scale, Calgari sleep apnea quality of life index (SAQLI) and Short form 36(SF 36</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of randomisation, 3 months and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a)	Age 18 or older
b)	Patients diagnosed to have MND as per El Escorial criteria
c)	  Ability to give informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a)	Patients already on NIV
b)	Cognitive impairment limiting the ability to participate in the trial
c)	Decompensated heart failure as defined by sudden or gradual onset of symptoms or signs of heart failure requiring unplanned clinic visits, hospitalization of emergency department visits within past 3 months or Left ventricular ejection fraction less than 40%
d)	Recent stroke (within 6 months)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Vinod Aiyappan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Repat Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Respiratory failure is the major cause of mortality and morbidity in patients with MND. Non-invasive ventilation provides respiratory support via a mask and machine and has become part of standard care for MND patients who develop sleep symptoms or respiratory failure. The current recommendations for NIV are mainly based on one study which reported that NIV prolonged survival and increased quality of life in a sub-group of patients with MND. However this study had only 22 patients in the NIV treatment group and NIV settings were changed based on patient tolerance and daytime blood gas changes, rather than in response to the type of abnormal breathing. In clinical practice, NIV is initially delivered during sleep, but is sometimes extended to the daytime as the disease progresses. The usual mode of NIV requires that the patient generates sufficient inspiratory effort to trigger pressure delivery by the machine. Inspiratory (and expiratory) pressure levels are usually chosen empirically without a sleep study. In a recent preliminary study including more systematic sleep studies, we found that NIV as currently provided to MND patients is suboptimal and in some instances may be dangerous. MND patients showed a variety of breathing abnormalities including obstructive apnea (a clinically silent variant not associated with snoring), central sleep apnea and varying levels of hypoventilation. Consequently, the traditional one size fits all approach to NIV treatment using empirically determined pressure settings is clearly sub-optimal. This project aims, for the first time, to characterize the patterns of abnormal breathing in MND patients and to investigate changes in breathing abnormalities as the disease progresses. We will also test the usefulness of a new smart ventilator in MND patients. This will help clarify the nature of gradually progressive deteriorations in breathing and how best to tailor treatments to improve breathing, sleep, quality of life and survival in patients with MND.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee (SAC HREC) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Office
The Flats, G5 - Rooms 3 and 4
Flinders Drive 
Flinders Medical Centre 
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>vinod aiyappan</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751187</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8277 6890</fax>
      <email>vinod.aiyappan@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>vinod aiyappan</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751187</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8277 6890</fax>
      <email>vinod.aiyappan@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>vinod aiyappan</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751187</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8277 6890</fax>
      <email>vinod.aiyappan@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>