<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343120">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000694910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of an exercise training intervention on clinical and functional outcomes for obese individuals following gastric banding surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of an exercise training intervention on clinical and functional outcomes for morbidly obese females who have undergone laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding (LAGB)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-4477</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will follow standard care in addition to exercise training. The exercise intervention will consist of a 12 month  exercise program of small group and individual physical activity sessions (all supervised) and also home-based physical activity. The supervised exercise training will consist of the following, starting 2 weeks after surgery:
3 x 1 hour supervised exercise sessions per week (weeks 1-6)
2 x 1 hour supervised exercise session per week (weeks 7-12)
1 x 1 hour supervised exercise session per week (weeks 13-26)
2 x 1 hour supervised exercise sessions per month (weeks 27-52)

The exercise training will consist of both moderate intensity aerobic and strength training using a variety of machines and free weights. Home-based physical activity will be developed around each participants access to equipment and facilities. It will predominantly include aerobic based exercise early in the program. Later in the program during the period of infrequent supervised sessions the home based program will be aerobic and resistance exercise as most suited to each participant. It is expected that the particiants continue to progress the volume of the home based program during the 12 month intervention. Progression will lead to a minimum target of 200 minutes per week (including supervised sessions). Daily exercise will be encouraged.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will follow current usual care provided after Laparoscopic Adjustable Gastric Banding (LAGB) which includes nutritional assistance, counselling as required and encouragement to engage in physical activity. Regular post surgical reviews will occur during the first 12 months after surgery with adjustments made to the band as required.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak aerobic power (VO2 peak) as measured using a graded exercise test on a motorised treadmill.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in physical function identified through: Muscular strength measured using 3 repetition max protocol. 30 sec sit to stands.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DEXA derived body composition</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7 day Accelorometer acquired physical activity and exercise volume using Acti-heart device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using MOT SF-36 quality of life questionnnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Musculoskeletal pain using 9 site visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24 hour ambulatory blood pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and anxiety measured by:
Mini international neuropsychiatric interview,
Beck Depression Inventory II &amp; Beck Depression Inventory Fast Screen,
Spielberger's State and Trait Anxiety Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial function measured using endopat device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle sympathetic nerve activity through microneurography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oral glucose tolerance test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bone formation and resorption measured through changes in osteocalcin, undercarboxylated osteocalcin, Procollagen I C-terminal propeptide, and C-telopeptide of type I collagen.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes to proinflammatory markers such as Interleukin-6, tumour necrosis factor-alpha, adiponectin, leptin through serum assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood lipid profile through fasting blood sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: Baseline, and 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Committed to having Laparoscopic adjustable gastric banding.
Females aged 18-50 years.
Premenopausal</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Type 1 diabetes,
unstable cardiac condition,
Significant musculoskeletal complaint that prevents participation in any exercise,
Pregnant or planning pregnancy in the 12 months following surgery.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be enrolled through LapSurgery Australia. The will be provided with a 1 page information flyer included as part of the pre surgical assessment. Participants, if interested will be screened at the surgery with the clinical nurse to ensure inclusion and exclusion criteria are met. The potential participant will then be contacted by the research team to discuss the project and provided with a detailed participant information and consent form. Once consented baseline testing is completed prior to surgery. Randomisation is conducted after successful surgery is confirmed. Allocation will be made by a person external to the study using sealed opaque envelopes for concealment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified balanced randomisation using PETO method (Peto, R., et al., Design and analysis of randomized clinical trials requiring prolonged observation of each patient. Introduction and design. Br J Cancer, 1976. 34(6): p. 585-612)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Deakin University
Melbourne Campus at Burwood
221 Burwood Highway
BURWOOD   VIC  3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Deakin University
Melbourne Campus at Burwood
221 Burwood Highway
BURWOOD   VIC  3125</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute (BIHDI)
PO Box 6492,
St Kilda Road Central, VIC, 8008</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>LapSurgery Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Langwith Consulting Suites
2 Langwith Avenue
BORONIA VIC 3155</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim
To determine if the inclusion of an exercise program following adjustable gastric banding (obesity surgery where a small band is placed around the top portion of the stomach) has superior health benefits compared to standard post surgical care.

Design and Methods
60 pre menopausal  females, aged 18 and 50 years referred for adjustable gastric banding surgery will be recruited for this study from Lapsurgery Australia Participants will be randomly allocated into either a 12 month exercise intervention (exercise + standard care) group or control (standard care) group. Testing will occur prior to surgery. People will be excluded from the study if they have: (i) muscle or joint problems that limit physical activity, (ii) have type 1 diabetes, (iii) are pregnant or planning to become pregnant in the next 12 months, or are breast feeding, (iv) those that are not suitable for surgery or require an alternative surgical procedure (v) Unstable cardiac condition.

The exercise group will train with an accredited exercise physiologist (AEP) and/or Masters of clinical exercise physiology student three days per week for 6 weeks and slowly reduce in face to face contact over the 12-month period. During the 12-month period participants will increase home based exercise developed in conjunction with the AEP and/or Masters student. The AEP will remain in regular contact with the participants through the use of telecommunication, email and social networking in addition to the supervised training that progressively reduces to fortnightly consultations in the second 6 month period. The intention of this model is to help the participant move from high reliance and contact with the AEP to self-management of their own exercise program, while still receiving ongoing support of the AEP. Training will consist of a variety of aerobic and resistance exercise with a 5 minute warm up followed by 50 minutes of exercise and 5 minutes of cool down at either: Deakin University Burwood campus, BakerIDI, or community based facility

Before surgery  (within 4 weeks of surgery) and 3, 6 and 12 months, after surgery participants will undergo the following assessments at either Deakin University Burwood or Baker IDI:
Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) body scan to measure body fat, muscle and bone; fasting blood collection to measure cholesterol, glucose, insulin, markers of bone formation and breakdown; muscle strength tests, aerobic capacity (fitness) test; sit to stand out of a chair, blood pressure over 24 hours, physical activity recordings using an accelerometor, recordings of nerve activity of the leg and testing of the elasticity of the blood vessels using non-invasive methods; and questionnaires to assess quality of life, exercise self efficacy, and rating of musculoskeletal pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00213)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Deakin University
Melbourne Campus at Burwood
221 Burwood Highway
BURWOOD   VIC  3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/07/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee (EC00315)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital 
6A Commercial Rd, 
Prahran, VIC, 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/08/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Steve Selig</name>
      <address>School of Exercise &amp; Nutrition Sciences
Deakin University
Melbourne Campus at Burwood
221 Burwood Highway
BURWOOD   VIC  3125</address>
      <phone>(int + 61 3) 9251 7165</phone>
      <fax>(int + 61 3) 9244 5551</fax>
      <email>steve.selig@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Steve Selig</name>
      <address>School of Exercise &amp; Nutrition Sciences
Deakin University
Melbourne Campus at Burwood
221 Burwood Highway
BURWOOD   VIC  3125</address>
      <phone>(int + 61 3) 9251 7165</phone>
      <fax>(int + 61 3) 9244 5551</fax>
      <email>steve.selig@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Steve Selig</name>
      <address>School of Exercise &amp; Nutrition Sciences
Deakin University
Melbourne Campus at Burwood
221 Burwood Highway
BURWOOD   VIC  3125</address>
      <phone>(int + 61 3) 9251 7165</phone>
      <fax>(int + 61 3) 9244 5551</fax>
      <email>steve.selig@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>