<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343245">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000797976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can patients reproduce partial weight bearing orders?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Partial weight bearing in orthopaedic in-patients: ability to reproduce partial weight bearing orders, factors influencing this and effect on clinical outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Orthopaedic inpatients who are prescribed partial weight bearing as part of their management</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will receive standard medical, nursing and allied health care during and after their hospital admission. This care, including instruction in partial weight bearing during mobilisation by physiotherapists, will not change as a result of participation in the current study. Our physiotherapists currently use the hand-under-foot or bathroom scale method to instruct patients in partial weight bearing, with the method chosen at the discretion of the treating physiotherapist. Instruction is repeated until the patient and physiotherapist are confident that the patient can reproduce the partial weight bearing orders. Further instruction on subsequent episodes of mobilisation is undertaken as deemed necessary. Additionally, when mobilising patients, physiotherapy staff observe the patients style of mobilisation and estimate whether partial weight bearing to the prescribed level is occurring. Repeated instruction is provided for patients when over-loading is suspected.
Instruction in partial weight bearing status will occur only during the period of hospitalisation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum difference between the target load and actual load will be recorded (in kg) using the SmartStep monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily weekday basis during the period of hospitalisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean (standard deviation) weight during the period of mobilisation will also be recorded using the SmartStep monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily weekday basis during the period of hospitalisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In order to investigate factors that could potentially impact on patients' ability to reproduce partial weight bearing orders, descriptive data will be collected. These data will include age, sex, body mass index, primary diagnosis, medical conditions that could affect patients' ability to perform partial weight bearing (eg, musculoskeletal or neurological conditions), conditions that could affect patients' ability to understand partial weight bearing instructions (eg, English as a second language, cognitive impairment) and pain at the time of mobilisation (measured on a verbal analogue scale where 0 = no pain and 10 = worst pain imaginable). These data will collected by one of the investigators (SK, TM or CJ) from medical records or by questioning the patient.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily weekday basis during the period of hospitalisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Broad clinical outcomes will be retrieved from data routinely recorded on a form which is completed by orthopaedic surgeons/registrars when patients attend Orthopaedic Outpatient clinics. This form includes information about patients' ability to walk, pain, range of motion, complications and xray findings. Importantly, the latter two points (ie, complications and xray findings) will indicate whether there has been a clinically important loss of fracture reduction and/or implant loosening, which would be the most important adverse effects that might result from excessive weight bearing during the period of fracture healing and/or recovery from orthopaedic surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months post-injury.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patients admitted to the Royal Adelaide Hospital with an orthopaedic problem/condition where the management includes the prescription of partial weight bearing.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unwilling to participate</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/02/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/03/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>47</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide
 South Australia 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Allied Health Research Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of this study is to determine objectively whether orthopaedic in-patients are able to reproduce partial weight bearing orders by assessing dynamic weight bearing using a highly accurate insole monitor. The study also seeks to investigate factors that influence patients ability to accurately reproduce partial weight bearing orders. Finally, the study will investigate, in a preliminary manner, whether the ability to accurately reproduce partial weight bearing orders affects clinical outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Publication:
Yu S, McDonald T, Jesudason C, Stiller K, Sullivan T (2014) Orthopedic in-patients ability to accurately reproduce partial weight bearing orders. Orthopedics 37:e10-e18.

Presentation:
October 2013; Yu S, McDonald T, Jesudason C, Stiller K, Sullivan T (2013)
Orthopaedic in-patients ability to reproduce partial weight bearing orders: factors influencing this and effect on clinical outcomes. An observational study. Australian Physiotherapy Association Physiotherapy Conference, Melbourne, Australia.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Committee
Level 3, Hanson Institute
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>110711</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/07/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathy Stiller</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>61 8 82225334</phone>
      <fax>61 8 82224279</fax>
      <email>kathy.stiller@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathy Stiller</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>61 8 82225334</phone>
      <fax>61 8 82224279</fax>
      <email>kathy.stiller@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kathy Stiller</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>61 8 82225334</phone>
      <fax>61 8 82224279</fax>
      <email>kathy.stiller@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathy Stiller</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace Adelaide South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>61 8 82225334</phone>
      <fax>61 8 82224279</fax>
      <email>kathy.stiller@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>