<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369496">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000708459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Outcome of Anterior Cruciate Ligament Plus Lateral Extra-articular Tenodesis Compared to Isolated Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction: A Feasibility Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical Outcome of Anterior Cruciate Ligament Plus Lateral Extra-articular Stabilisation Compared to Isolated Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction in 18 to 40 year old patients to compare the return to function and re-rupture rates between the two treatment modalities</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anterior cruciate ligament rupture</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly allocated to one of two treatment arms by opening a sealed envelope. They will then undergo either i) ACL reconstruction using a 4-strand hamstring ACL graft and iliotibial band (ITB) lateral extra-articular tenodesis, or ii) isolated intra-articular ACL reconstruction with a 4-strand hamstring graft. The duration of each procedure is approximately 45-60 minutes and will be performed by the consultant orthopaedic surgeon and his team. Post-operatively, participants will undertake a standard rehabilitation protocol for ACL reconstruction. Following surgery, clinical reviews will be conducted at 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 2 years post-operatively. Participants will no longer receive the yearly questionnaire, as stated previously.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control  - isolated ACL reconstruction</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional outcome following ACL reconstruction plus lateral extra-articular tenodesis will be measured using functional knee outcome tests including International Knee Documentation Committee (IKDC) score, Lysholm score, Tegner activity scale, Knee injury, Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS) and hop test. Knee laxity will be assessed using KT1000. The results of these tests will be included as a composite primary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical reviews will be conducted at 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 2 years post-operatively. Participants will no longer receive a questionnaire, as stated previously.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction will be assessed using Global Rating of Change Score and ACL Recovery Score designed specifically for this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical reviews will be conducted at 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 2 years post-operatively. Participants will no longer receive a questionnaire, as stated previously.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower re-rupture rate following ACL reconstruction plus lateral extra-articular tenodesis. The integrity of the graft will be assessed through clinical examination of the participant's knee during each of the post-operative follow-up appointments. If there are any concerns, further radiological investigations will be organised, including an X-ray and/or an MRI scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical reviews will be conducted at 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 2 years post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For inclusion in the study patients must be aged between 18 and 40 years, have Grade 2 or 3 knee instability on pivot shift test and have a confirmed ACL tear on MRI scan. They must also be medically able to undergo a general or regional anaesthetic.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with multi-ligament knee injury or any other ligaments requiring surgery will be excluded, along with people from non-English speaking backgrounds, those residing interstate or overseas and those who are unable to provide their own consent for any reason.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation by sealed envelope</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using sealed envelopes</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/03/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2022</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Toby Leys</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o Coastal Orthopaedics
Bethesda Hospital
25 Queenslea Drive
Claremont
WA 6010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
WA 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) is an important stabilizing ligament of the knee. It is also the most common knee ligament injury requiring surgery, with an annual incidence of approximately 1 in 3500 in the general population. Numerous technological advances have been made in recent times in the surgical techniques for ACL reconstruction but, in spite of this, the failure rate remains approximately 7-15% and many people do not return to full function in their knee after ACL reconstruction.

The anterolateral ligament (ALL), a structure located in the anterolateral part of the knee, has recently been identified as an important contributor to rotational stability of the knee in addition to the ACL. Loss of ALL integrity may be responsible for some cases of failure post-operatively. Although intra-articular ACL reconstruction remains the current gold standard for operative management, it does not address the extra-articular ALL deficiency and therefore does not restore normal knee kinematics.

The aim of this study is to compare the return to function and re-rupture rates following combined ACL reconstruction with lateral extra-articular tenodesis versus an isolated intra-articular ACL reconstruction.

Participants will be randomly allocated to one of two treatment arms by opening a sealed envelope. They will then undergo either i) ACL reconstruction using a 4-strand hamstring ACL graft and iliotibial band (ITB) lateral extra-articular tenodesis, or ii) isolated intra-articular ACL reconstruction with a 4-strand hamstring graft.

Following surgery, clinical reviews will be conducted at 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 2 years post-operatively during which the physiotherapist will make an assessment using a variety of objective knee scoring systems and a patient satisfaction survey. Any post-operative complications will also be recorded. Comparison will then be made to determine which technique has better functional outcome and lower re-rupture rate. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC No: 2015-144</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Toby Leys</name>
      <address>c/o Coastal Orthopaedics
Bethesda Hospital
25 Queenslea Drive
Claremont
WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 411 411 359</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9230 6332</fax>
      <email>tobyleys@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Toby Leys</name>
      <address>c/o Coastal Orthopaedics
Bethesda Hospital
25 Queenslea Drive
Claremont
WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 411 411 359</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9230 6332</fax>
      <email>tobyleys@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Toby Leys</name>
      <address>c/o Coastal Orthopaedics
Bethesda Hospital
25 Queenslea Drive
Claremont
WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9230 6333</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9230 6332</fax>
      <email>tobyleys@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Toby Leys</name>
      <address>c/o Coastal Orthopaedics
Bethesda Hospital
25 Queenslea Drive
Claremont
WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9230 6333</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9230 6332</fax>
      <email>tobyleys@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>