<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364588">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000797774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mindfulness-based Stress Reduction for Restless Legs Syndrome: A Single Arm Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effect of Mindfulness-based Stress Reduction on Severity of Symptoms in People with Restless Legs Syndrome: A Single Arm Pilot Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Restless Legs Syndrome
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction (MBSR).
MBSR, developed by Jon Kabat-Zinn (1990) incorporates meditation practice together with mindfulness principles (i.e., the attitudinal foundations of mindfulness practice described by Kabat-Zinn (1990), non-striving, acceptance, non-judging, beginner's mind, trust, patience, letting go). It will be taught over a 6 week period, with 2 hour weekly sessions in a group setting of 8-10 participants. These sessions will be facilitated by a provisional psychologist who has specific training in MBSR and is supervised by a registered clinical psychologist and sleep physicians (the medical directors) from the Melbourne Sleep Disorders Centre. 

Adherence to MBSR intervention will be monitored by recording participant attendance to the weekly sessions, and also by asking participants to record their mindfulness practice, in terms of frequency, duration and type of mindfulness (formal or informal) practice in a daily log.</interventions>
    <comparator>The design of this research is a repeated measures design, using standard treatment for control, as it is currently prescribed by their treating physician.   </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 10-item International Restless Legs Severity Scale (IRLS; The International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group [IRLSSG], 2003) will be used in this study to assess RLS-specific symptom severity and psychosocial impairment due to RLS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 25-item Restless Legs Cognitions Questionnaire (RLSCQ; Sim, Greenwood, Cunnington, &amp; Swieca, 2012) is a newly developed measure assessing the cognitive content related to symptoms of RLS across five subscales: 1) Psychosocial impairment on social life (e.g., I think that having RLS has limited my social activities); 2) Perseverance (e.g., I think that I am able to put up with the symptoms); 3) Medication persistence (e.g., I think that I will be unable to cope with RLS without the medication); 4) Helplessness (e.g., I think about the things that I did today to cause this episode); and, 5) Unbearable cognitions (e.g., I think that the symptoms will never end). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The self-report, 18-item, Restless Legs Syndrome Quality of Life scale (RLS-QoL; Abetz, Vallow, et al., 2005) will be used to assess the impact of RLS on daily living, morning and evening activity, concentration, sexual activity, and work over the past four weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Medical Outcomes Study, 36-item, Short Form Health Survey (SF-36) will be used to assess general health status across eight components: 1) physical functioning; 2) role-physical functioning (i.e., physical health limitations in usual role activities); 3) bodily pain; 4) general health perceptions; 5) vitality (energy and fatigue); 6) social functioning (i.e., health limitations or interference with normal social activities); 7) role-emotional (i.e., problems with daily activities as a result of emotional issues); and, 8) mental health and psychological wellbeing (Ware, 2000; Ware &amp; Sherbourne, 1992).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Symptom Checklist-90-Revised (SCL-90-R; Derogatis, 1994) will be used to evaluate a broad range of symptoms of psychopathology, and to measure progress and change due to the intervention.  The SCL-90-R is a 90-item questionnaire that is designed to measure overall psychological distress, the number of self-reported symptoms and the intensity of symptoms of psychopathology.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS; Zigmond &amp; Snaith, 1983) was developed as a valid and reliable self-assessment measure in identifying anxiety and depression psychopathology in nonpsychiatric hospital and medical settings. The HADS consists of 14 items evenly divided into depression (HADS-D), and anxiety (HADS-A) subscales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 19-item, self-rated, Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI; Buysse, Reynolds III, Monk, Berman, &amp; Kupfer, 1988) will be used to measure sleep quality across seven components of subjective sleep quality, sleep latency, sleep duration, habitual sleep efficiency, sleep disturbances, use of sleeping medication, and daytime dysfunction. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 8-item,self-rated, Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) will be used to assess daytime sleepiness, as a large negative impact on quality of life for RLS sufferers is daytime tiredness and sleepiness. Each itemis rated on 4-point scale ranging from 0 (would never doze) to 3 (high chance of dozing). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Five-Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ; Baer, Smith, Hopkins, Krietemeyer, &amp; Toney, 2006) will be used in this study as it is based on a factor analytic study of five independent and well established mindfulness questionnaires which yielded five factors representing mindfulness. These are observing, describing, acting with awareness, non-judging and non-reacting. The FFMQ consists of 39 items which are self-rated on a 5-point scale from 1 (never or very rarely true)to 5 (very often, or always true). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), Pre-intervention (week 4), post-intervention (week 10), 3 months follow up (3 months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For inclusion in this study, men and women must be aged above 18 years and must present with restless legs syndrome (RLS), and significant psychosocial impairment or distress due to RLS according to the International Restless Legs Syndrome Study Group's (IRLSSG) diagnostic criteria, and determined via a diagnostic screening interview. Both unmedicated and medicated patients will be included in this study if treatment response has been stable for the past four weeks and there is no foreseeable medication change. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria are patients with neuropathic disorders; iron deficiency anaemia; uraemia (or renal failure); serious psychiatric disorders (i.e., severe major depressive disorder with suicidality, severe post-traumatic stress disorder or substance dependency); and, patients with severe cognitive deficits that would impair their ability to comply with research requirements or their ability to give consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures>repeated measures design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>RMIT University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Plenty Road, Bundoora, VIC, 3083</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Melbourne Sleep Disorders Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 508, level 5, 100 Victoria Parade, East Melbourne, VIC, 3002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>RMIT University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Plenty Road, Bundoora, VIC, 3083</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Melbourne Sleep Disorders Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>100 Victoria Parade, East Melbourne, VIC, 3002</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to investigate whether Mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) can be used as an effective treatment option for people with restless legs syndrome (RLS). Specifically, the aim is to evaluate the effectiveness of the six-week MBSR group program in enhancing measures of RLS-specific quality of life, general health, sleep, RLS-specific symptom severity, depression and anxiety symptoms, and mindfulness skills. 
It is hypothesised that there will be a significant improvement in subjective measures of RLS symptom severity, RLS-related quality of life, general health, symptoms of psychopathology, including anxiety and depression, and subjective and objective measures of sleep, directly following the MBSR program and at three months post-intervention. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RMIT Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, Building 91
110 Swanston St, Carlton
VIC, 3053
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>project number 45/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Vicky Bablas</name>
      <address>Division of Psychology 
School of Health Sciences
RMIT University
Plenty Road, Bundoora
VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 4976 7311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vicky.bablas@student.rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Vicky Bablas</name>
      <address>Division of Psychology 
School of Health Sciences
RMIT University
Plenty Road, Bundoora
VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 4976 7311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vicky.bablas@student.rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Vicky Bablas</name>
      <address>Division of Psychology 
School of Health Sciences
RMIT University
Plenty Road, Bundoora
VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 4976 7311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vicky.bablas@student.rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Vicky Bablas</name>
      <address>Division of Psychology 
School of Health Sciences
RMIT University
Plenty Road, Bundoora
VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 4976 7311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vicky.bablas@student.rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>