<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363313">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001259831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of a promotional DVD on bowel screening uptake for 
Maori and Pacific within the Bowel Screening Pilot</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Maori and Pacific bowel screening invitees receiving a promotional DVD compared to usual care reminder processes; impact on screening uptake.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Participation in a bowel screening pilot</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A six minute promotional DVD is currently being introduced in the Waitemata DHB bowel screening pilot. The DVD is being offered in addition to usual care. ). Usual care is a standard reminder letter, and for priority groups (Maori, Pacific and Asian), also a phone call follow-up from a culturally appropriate outreach co-ordinator located in the bowel screening pilot. The Data Manager estimates that approximately 50% of priority group participants are able to be reached with 3x phone follow up attempts. There will be no change to usual care for any participant group.

The DVD shows a well known local Maori couple (kaumatua Pio and whaea Chrissy Jacobs) telling the story of whaea Chrissys recent experience of bowel screening, and being screened positive (having a positive test followed by a colonoscopy). The DVD is narrated by ex-All Black Frano Botica, and includes a small amount of educational commentary on how to participate in bowel screening, and how to return the test kit (for example labelling and postage details). The DVD is intended to be watched in participant's own home, in their own time, when it is convenient for them, on their own DVD playing equipment. 

The DVD was designed by the Community Awareness Raising team in the bowel screening pilot to be a culturally appropriate for Maori. The DVD was developed with the intention to promote bowel screening and to motivate invitees to participate by returning their test kits.

The study will run for approximately a year (calculated on the number of Maori and Pacific people to be invited in the remainder of the current screening round), in order to reach the numbers suggested by the power calculation (4600 - 2600 Maori and 2000 Pacific).</interventions>
    <comparator>Those screening invitees who do not respond to the initial invitation are offered usual care. Usual care is to be sent a reminder letter at four weeks, and for priority groups (including Maori and Pacific), a telephone follow-up is also attempted in usual care (approximately 50% of these groups are also reached by phone as noted previously).

The study will run for approximately a year.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in uptake between those who receive the DVD and those who do not.

The bowel screening pilot involves self-testing faecal matter in the participants own home with the supplied test kit, sealing the kit as instructed, labelling it (including barcode), signing the consent form and returning the kit in the supplied sealed bag in the post direct to the laboratory.

Uptake as an outcome in this study refers to participation in the bowel screening pilot by return of the test kit. The purpose of the reminder letter (and the DVD as an intervention at this point) is to encourage people to participate in bowel screening. 

Uptake (or participation) is routinely measured in the bowel screening pilot, when a kit is received by the laboratory. It is measured at 4 weeks post invitation in order to generate a list of those who have not responded to be followed-up (as part of usual care) with a reminder letter and phone calls (for priority groups). Uptake is then measured continuously after that; no further reminders are sent by participants are able to send their test kit in to be analysed at any time after their reminder letter. 

For the purposes of this study the Data Manager has been asked to provide the researchers the proportion of test kits returned (the uptake) at 6 weeks post reminder.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 weeks post initial invitation a reminder letter is sent out by the bowel screening pilot. The DVD will be included with this mail-out.

Uptake of screening will be assessed at 6 weeks post reminder letter/DVD mail-out. 

The trial will recruit for approximately one year.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the rate of spoiled kits returned between those who receive the DVD and those who do not. Spoiled kits are those with labelling or collection issues affecting the ability for the laboratory to process the sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Bowel screening pilot invitees (male or female Waitemata DHB residents aged 50-69 year old, who are eligible for publically funded healthcare). 
2. Non responders to the initial invitation at four weeks
3. Maori or Pacific</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All other ethnic groups.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>For the remainder of the first screening round of the bowel screening pilot (approximately a year) all Maori and Pacific invitees who are sent a reminder letter will be randomised into receiving the DVD or not receiving the DVD.

Allocation is not concealed from the bowel screening pilot (who need to manually separate reminder letters by ethnicity in order to add the DVD to the mail-out). Allocation is concealed from the researchers who will not have any identifiable data on the participants, and so will not know who is allocated to the groups).</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be by week of reminder letter generation, ie DVDs will be included for all those Maori and Pacific people receiving reminder letters in one week, and no DVDs included the following week.

This form of randomisation (quasi-randomisation) appears to be the only practical way to allocate groups (and for the bowel screening pilot to match the group with the uptake) within the pilot. Discussions were held within the research team and with the Data Manager about the possibility of using randomisation software at the point where reminder letters are separated manually by ethnicity however this will add a whole series of manual steps for the bowel screening pilot for which we would have to justify extra resources (this study is funded within baseline funding allocation for the pilot).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The impact on Maori and Pacific will be examined in parallel.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>4600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>5277</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/07/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Debbie Holdsworth</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Chief Planning Officer and Chair of the Bowel Screening Pilot Steering Committee
Waitemata DHB, Planning and Funding
Level 2, 15 Shea Terrace
Private Bag 93-503
Takapuna 0740
Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bowel screening pilot - Waitemata DHB</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Debbie Holdsworth
Chief Planning Officer and Chair of the bowel screening pilot steering group
Level 2, 15 Shea Terrace
Private Bag 93-503
Takapuna 0740
Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It has been suggested that the DVD may be useful as an intervention to improve screening uptake for Maori, and that it may have potential transferable benefits for other groups, for example Pacific (ie it is aimed at reducing ethnic inequalities). This study is a community intervention with all 
Maori and Pacific invitees receiving a reminder letter for the remainder of the first round of screening (one year) either receiving usual care, or usual care and a promotional DVD. The study aims to determine whether the DVD has an impact on:  
(a) Screening participation (return of the test kit)
(b) The spoiled test kit rate (kits with labelling or collection issues affecting the ability for the laboratory to process the sample).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>In progress</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Peter Sandiford</name>
      <address>Planning and Funding
Waitemata DHB
Level 1, 15 Shea Terrace
Private Bay 93-503
Takapuna 0740
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 486 8920 x2923</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Sandiford@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Peter Sandiford</name>
      <address>Planning and Funding
Waitemata DHB
Level 1, 15 Shea Terrace
Private Bay 93-503
Takapuna 0740
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 486 8920 x2923</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Sandiford@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Karen Bartholomew</name>
      <address>Planning and Funding
Waitemata DHB
Level 1, 15 Shea Terrace
Private Bay 93-503
Takapuna 0740
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 486 8920 x5434</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Karen.Bartholomew@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Sandiford</name>
      <address>Private Bag 93-503 Takapuna Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 4868920</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Sandiford@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>