<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362082">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000188831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of green tea and high intensity intermittent exercise on blood fat levels after consuming a high fat meal</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of green tea and high intensity intermittent exercise on postprandial lipemia after consuming a high fat meal in young males</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postprandial lipemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each subject will be involved with four arms of the trial which will consist of: a placebo, a green tea capsule, an exercise bout, and a green tea capsule and exercise bout condition. The green tea and placebo capsules will be ingested with lunch and dinner on the day before the  high fat meal and in the morning, 1.5 hour before the high fat meal. The high fat meal will be consumed after overnight fasting early in the morning.  exercise will be performed 12 hours before consumption of the high fat meal. The green tea will consist of a standardized green tea (total of 340 mg polyphenols and 136 mg EGCG), maltodextrin, microcrystalline cellulose, sodium croscarmellose, stearic acid, silicon dioxide, magnesium stearate (vegetable origin), hydroxypropylmethyl cellulose coating, and glycerine (vegetable origin). The amount of green tea contained in each capsule will be equivalent to three cups of green tea.  Exercise will consist of cycling on a stationary bike for 20 minutes.  The high fat meal will be in milkshake form and will consist of 270 ml of whipping cream and 65 g of specialty ice cream. The meal will provide 4.1 MJ (980 kcal; 0.05 MJ/kg body weight), 100 g fat (1.1 g/kg); 66.5 g saturated, 29.5 monounsaturated, 4.0 g polyunsaturated, 17 g carbohydrate (0.2 g/kg), and 3 g protein (0.03 g/kg). Percent fat is about 92%. This meal has been successfully used in previous studies to induce postprandial lipemia. Twelve hours before the high fat meal subjects will perform 20 minutes of high intensity intermittent exercise when in the exerclse alone or exercise/green tea condition. Exercise will consist of cycling flat out for 8 s then resting (turn the pedals over slowly) for 12 s continuously for a 20-min period. Thus, in a 20-min period subjects will cycle vigorously for 8 min and cycle slowly for 12 min (60 sprints). Load will be determined from subjects maximal oxygen uptake values. Heart rates are typically between 150 and 160 bpm during this protocol. Period between conditions will be one week. One order out of a possible six different order of the above conditions will be randomly assigned to subjects'</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects will ingest a placebo capsule that will contain 500 mg of cellulose.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We hypothesize that high intensity intermittent exercise and green tea will result in a:

*	significant decrease in blood levels of triglyceride after consumption of the high fat meal</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a high fat meal consumed along with green tea capsules and a bout of prior exercise blood fats will peak about 3-4 hours later but it is expected that their levels will be significantly lower after green tea and exercise. Two blood samples will be collected at baseline, and three during the resting phase (one per hour). Thus, 5 samples per subject will be analyzed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We hypothesize that high intensity intermittent exercise and green tea will result in a:

*	significant decrease in fat oxidation levels after consumption of the high fat meal</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fat oxidation will be assessed through a metabolic cart and canopy.  Gases will collected throughout the 3-hour period after the high fat meal.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes will be the assessment of glycerol and growth hormone from the blood samples which are expected to be larger in the green tea and exercise conditions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two blood samples will be collected at baseline, and three during the resting phase (one per hour).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male, aged between 18 and 30 years.  No history of exercise or consumption of green tea. exercise history will be assessed by a lifestyle questionnaire and use of the seven day physical activity recall questionnaire.  Exclusion will be based on an exercise regimen that involves moderately hard exercise for more than two times per week.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion
-	Smokers
-	On any regular medication
-	Regular green tea consumption
-	Suffering from diabetes or any cardiovascular diseases
-	Any other clinical conditions which may prevent them from participating in this clinical trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All subjects will complete four conditions:
1. Placebo
2. Exercise
3. Green tea ingestion
4. Exercise and green tea ingestion

Allocation will be by sealed opaque envelopes. Allocation will be concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Order of conditions will be balanced across subjects.  One order out of a possible six different order of the above conditions will be randomly assigned to subjects. Order of conditions to each subject will be decided by drawing each subject order from 24 possible permutations from a hat.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University New South wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>High Street
Randwick
Sydney 2052
New South Wales</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Post-prandial lipemia is an elevation in triglyceride (TG) and chylomicron remnants that occurs after digesting a fat-containing meal.  Post-prandial lipemia has been established as a risk factor for atherosclerosis and cardiovascular disease.  However, dietary intake of green tea and aerobic exercise results in lowered post-prandial lipemia.  The study will examine the effect of a different form of exercise called high intensity intermittent exercise (HIIE) and green tea on postprandial lipemia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephen H Boutcher</name>
      <address>4 Arthur St 
School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
University New South Wales
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 (2) 9385 2877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.boutcher@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephen H Boutcher</name>
      <address>4 Arthur St 
School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
University New South Wales
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 (2) 9385 2877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.boutcher@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stephen H Boutcher</name>
      <address>4 Arthur St 
School of Medical Sciences
Faculty of Medicine
University New South Wales
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 (2) 9385 2877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.boutcher@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>