<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82158">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/07/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/08/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000395437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Presentation of preventive health information: a comparison of paper versus computer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Population-based cancer screening: Distinguishing the influence of tailoring content and presentation via the web, compared to paper-based material, on knowledge of and attitudes to colorectal cancer screening</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal cancer screening</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Baseline survey  (measuring attitudes to screening and readiness to engage in screening) followed by endpoint survey approximately 2 weeks later for all intervention groups and control group. Separate interventions will occur immediately before administration of the endpoint survey: non-personalised paper-based colorectal cancer (CRC) screening information; personalised paper-based CRC screening information; non-personalised web-based CRC screening information; personalised web-based CRC screening information; baseline and endpoint survey only (control). Those individuals who, in the endpoint survey, indicate they are ready to screen will be provided with a FOBT (faecal occult blood test) kit. Those that indicate that they are not ready to screen will be provided with a "request for kit" card to return within one year of the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in screening decision stage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the endpoint survey.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For the intervention groups, intention to screen and tracking of decision making processes will be measured immediately following the intervention (ie as part of the intervention). Actual uptake of screening will be measured for intervention and control groups at 35 days from provision of the FOBT kit. Tracking of decision processes will not be an outcome for the control group.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Some familiarity with using a computer to search the Internet.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>76</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current regular CRC screening; diagnosis of colorectal cancer or polyps.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be a random sample within certain electoral areas, provided by the Australian Electoral Commission. Names will again be randomised and then divided into 5 groups by a researcher not working on the study</concealment>
    <sequence>Each of the 5 groups will be randomly assigned to one of four intervention groups or to control groups using computer-generated random number sequence. This will be performed by a researcher not involved with the study</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>125</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CSIRO Preventative Health Flagship</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO) Preventative Health Flagship (internal funding)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Adelaide Colorectal Cancer Collaborative</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of the study is to investigate whether it is perceived personal relevance (through tailoring of messages to an individual's specific health beliefs concerning colorectal cancer screening), or ease of navigation (through web-based delivery) to access personally relevant material, or both factors, that has the greater effect on the decision to screen for colorectal cancer using a Faecal Occult Blood kit (FOBT). Our hypothesis is that individuals receiving tailored, web-based information are more likely to decide to screen. The study fits in with the broader aim of attempting to understand the factors that motivate people to participate in colorectal cancer screening, and can serve as a basis for providing consumer information and decision tools designed to increase participation in colorectal cancer screening technologies.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Human Nutrition</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kintore Avenue
Adelaide SA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/20</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Carlene Wilson</name>
      <address>CSIRO Human Nutrition
PO Box 10041
Kintore Avenue
Adelaide BC SA 5000</address>
      <phone>(08) 8303 8906</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carlene.wilson@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Ingrid Flight</name>
      <address>CSIRO Human Nutrition
PO Box 10041
Kintore Avenue
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>(08) 8303 8881</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ingrid.flight@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>