<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365006">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001063707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of a whole body vibration training program for preventing falls in institutionalised elderly with fear of falling.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Among older people living in a nursing home does the use of whole body vibration lead to improvements in balance, strength, fear of falling, quality of life and a reduction in falls risk compared to a placebo group. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Falls risk</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Strength</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Balance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fear of falling</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of life</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Exercise group will receive a three months whole body vibration treatment. Placebo group will receive a similar treatment without vibration. During the study, all participants will receive usual inpatient  care of the nursing home. Whole body vibration will be applied during one hour per week distributed between different days and consist of six static exercises with rest between exercises targeting lower limb muscles. Participants will stand on the whole body vibration or placebo platform in a semi-squat position and hold on to the railings secured onto the platform. The frequency (load) of the vibrating platform will be at 12.5 to 18.5 Hz and the amplitude will be 4 mm. The intervention will begin with two 30 seconds sets of three exercices with 30 seconds rest between exercises. The exercise volume and intensity will be progressively increased according to the overload-principle. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive usual care of the nursing home and a placebo trainning. Placebo group will make the same exercises than vibration group in the placebo platform. This platform has the appearance of a conventional vibrating platform. It has a speaker hidden in the base and is connected to a computer, but it does not emit any kind of vibration. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Fear of falling (Fes-I)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Balance (Biodex Balance System)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Sense to vibration (Vibratron II, The Vibratron II provides a non-invasive means of measuring the sensitivity to vibration of a patient's feet)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Weight (using a Seca 780 bascule)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Body mass Index (bioimpedance with Tanita BC-418 MA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Physical Activity (IPAQ, CHAMPS)  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Daily functioning (Barthel index)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Perceived exertion (Borg Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>In each training session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Depression (GDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Vision (FVSQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Attitude to a fall prevention intervention (AFRIS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fitness tests (Time Up &amp; Go, Chair &amp; Stand test, 6 minutes walking test, 10 meter test, Functional Reach, Sit &amp; Reach, Four Square Step test, hand strength) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Leg strength (isokinetic dynamometer)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Health related quality of life (EQ-5D-5L, 15-D and SF-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and three months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals are potentially eligible if they meet all of the following criteria: (i) Aged 65 years or over; (ii) living in a nursing home; (iii) have fear of falling (FES-I score &gt;23) ; (iv) can provide written informed consent to participate in the study; (v) can do all the physical fitness tests; (vi) have capacity to understand instructions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>120</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Clinicians may consider a patient unsuitable to enrol if they have any of the following: (i) History of severe trauma; (ii) Artificial prosthesis; (iii) Peripheral nerve entrapment; (iv) Inflammatory rheumatic diseases; (v) Severe cognitive impairment or otherwise judged unable to understand or comply with treatment protocol; (vi) Other diseases that do not allow them to make the training protocol; (vii) Having some other pathology that contraindicates exercise program or requiring special care (coronary artery disease, thrombosis, bone diseases, lung or kidney moderate or severe); (viii) Having some pathology that required daily intake of psychotropic drugs or affecting the vestibular system (Parkinson, etc..) to avoid the influence on measures of balance; (ix) Participation in regular physical exercise programs more than once a week for 30 minutes or more, during two weeks, in the last five years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited from a nursing home. Eligible patients will be screened for inclusion in the study. They will be informed about the study intervention and protocol. If they agree in participate then they will be visited by a research assistant and informed consent will be obtained. Following this, they will be randomised in an intervention or placebo group. Randomisation will be ascertained by a randomisation schedule held at a distant site. This schedule will be compiled by someone with no involvement in the study to maintain the blindage. In this sense, people who apply the training to patients are different from those who will perform the initial and final measurements. Researchers conducting measurements will not know to which group each participant pertain.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be generated using a through numeric list randomly generated within Microsoft Excel </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>CACERES</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Extremadura</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Sport Sciences
Avenida de la Universidad, sin numero.
10071, Caceres</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Goverment of Extremadura
Ayudas para la formacion predoctoral de investigadores</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CONSEJERIA DE EMPLEO, EMPRESA E INNOVACION
D.G. de Modernizacion e Innovacion Tecnologica 
Paseo Roma, sin numero
06800 Merida, Badajoz

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the present study we intend to apply a three months whole body vibration exercise protocol with oscillating platform in isntitutionalised older people with fear of falling. 

The main aim is to test the applicability and observe improvements of this training protocol in fear of falling, balance, strength, sense to vibration and quality of life in this population. The second aim is to analyse the improvements obtained in psychological parameters (as depression, dayly living functioning), fitness, weight, body mass index, physical activity, etc. In addition we intend to evaluate if this programm is cost-efective. 

This protocol could improve all variables described and could be a good, cost-efective and feasible strategy for falls prevention in institutionalized older people with fear of falling.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Balance training reduces fear of falling and improves dynamic balance and isometric strength in institutionalised older people: a randomised trial.

Gusi N, Carmelo Adsuar J, Corzo H, Del Pozo-Cruz B, Olivares PR, Parraca JA.

Journal of Physiotherapy, 2012;58(2):97-104. doi: 10.1016/S1836-9553(12)70089-9.


http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22613239</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Biosecurity and Bioethics Committee  of the University of Extremadura</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Vicerrectorado de Investigacion, Transferencia e Innovacion.
Campus Universitario
Avenida de Elvas, sin numero.
06071 Badajoz

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Narcis Gusi Fuertes</name>
      <address>Exercise, Quality of Life &amp; Health Economics
Faculty of Sport Sciences
Universidad de Extremadura
10071 Caceres (Spain)

</address>
      <phone>+34 927 257460</phone>
      <fax>+34 927 257461</fax>
      <email>ngusi@unex.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Narcis Gusi Fuertes</name>
      <address>Exercise, Quality of Life &amp; Health Economics
Faculty of Sport Sciences
Universidad de Extremadura
10071 Caceres (Spain)</address>
      <phone>+34 927 257460</phone>
      <fax>+34 927 257461</fax>
      <email>ngusi@unex.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Narcis Gusi Fuertes</name>
      <address>Exercise, Quality of Life &amp; Health Economics
Faculty of Sport Sciences
Universidad de Extremadura
10071 Caceres (Spain)</address>
      <phone>+34 927 257460</phone>
      <fax>+34 927 257461</fax>
      <email>ngusi@unex.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Narcis Gusi Fuertes</name>
      <address>Exercise, Quality of Life &amp; Health Economics
Faculty of Sport Sciences
Universidad de Extremadura
10071 Caceres (Spain)</address>
      <phone>+34 927 257460</phone>
      <fax>+34 927 257461</fax>
      <email>ngusi@unex.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>