<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371005">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000928415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Fish Oil Cell Uptake Study of Inflammation  a trial of fish oil supplementation in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Fish Oil Cell Uptake Study of Inflammation  a trial of fish oil supplementation in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FOCUS IN</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vascular and adipose inflammation in atherosclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Healthy human volunteers will be randomised to one of four groups: 
Group 1: Fish oil capsules high in EPA. 
Group 2: Fish oil capsules high in DHA. 
Group 3: Standard fish oil capsules, with 3:2 ratio of EPA to DHA. 
Group 4: Placebo capsules. 
Participants will be randomised in a 1:1:1:1 ratio. Participants will have blood taken before supplementation, and again after 30 days of supplementation.

Group 1: 8 capsules per day for 30 days. Each capsules contains 500mg of EPA and negligible DHA. Adherence monitored by counting of returned capsules.

Group 2: 6 capsules per day for 30 days. Each capsules contains 30mg of EPA and 707.5mg of DHA. Adherence monitored by counting of returned capsules.

Group 3: 7 capsules per day for 30 days. Each capsules contains 400mg of EPA and 200mg of DHA. Adherence monitored by counting of returned capsules.

Group 4: 7 capsules per day for 30 days. Each capsules contains 10mg of EPA and 6mg DHA. Adherence monitored by counting of returned capsules.</interventions>
    <comparator>Healthy human volunteers will take placebo capsules

Placebo capsule ingredients are: palm oil, gelatin (bovine), glycerol, sunflower oil, rapeseed oil, fish oil, mixed tocopherols.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: The impact of fish oil on the expression of inflammatory mediators produced by stimulated human umbilical vein endothelial cells (i.e. VCAM-1, ICAM-1, MCP-1) and mouse 3T3L1 adipocytes (i.e. IL-1beta, IL6, IL18, TNF-alpha, adiponectin, leptin and resistin).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at Day 1 and Day 30 by adding human serum to cells in culture</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy adult male and female human volunteers with no significant past medical history.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current cardiovascular medications. 
Regular use of anti-inflammatory medications or blood-thinning medications. Current regular fish oil consumption or regular consumption within the last 6 months. 
Regular consumption of 2 or more fish meals per week over the last 6 months. Pregnant and breastfeeding women are excluded. 
Language barrier. 
Seafood allergy and intolerance to fish oil capsules. 
Anticipated medical indication for interruption of fish oil consumption during study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be done via numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>the random order for the allocation of subjects into different groups will be done by simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The total sample size is 40 participants. This is based on the paper published in NEJM titled The effect of dietary supplementation with n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids on the synthesis of interleukin-1 and tumor necrosis factor by mononuclear cells. In this study, volunteers had fish oil added to their usual Western diet for 6 weeks. Blood was taken before and after supplementation, and the production of interleukin 1-beta and tumor necrosis factor (proinflammatory cytokines) by mononuclear cells was measured. Mononuclear cells from whole blood were isolated using the Ficoll technique. These inflammatory cytokines significantly reduced after fish oil, with 9 participants in the study. In the current study, we propose a sample size of 10 per group to demonstrate a significant change in inflammatory markers, allowing for participant non-compliance or dropout.
Comparison of multiple vascular and adipose inflammatory markers between treatment groups will be made using a Kruskal-Wallis test and Dunns test for multiple comparisons.

The sample size was based on the paper mentioned above, and no additional power calculation was performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/10/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>12/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute (SAHMRI) - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Anthony Pisaniello</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6, South
Heart Health Theme
SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Anthony Pisaniello</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6, South
Heart Health Theme
SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The FOCUS IN study is a clinical trial evaluating the impact of omega-3 fatty acids, found in fish oil, on inflammatory factors that contribute to heart disease. Coronary heart disease is due to a process called atherosclerosis, which the build-up of fatty tissue and plaque in arteries. Inflammation has been shown to be an important causal factor in atherosclerosis, and omega-3 fatty acids have been shown to have anti-inflammatory properties in previous studies. Study participants will be randomised to supplementation with various types of fish oil or a placebo for 30 days, and serum will be taken before and after supplementation. Serum will be added to cells in culture, derived from blood vessels and fat cells, and the impact of the serum on inflammatory factors that contribute to heart disease will be measured. This method of adding omega-3s to cells is a more biologically plausible method of studying the impact of omega-3 consumption on cellular function than adding pure omega-3s directly. The results of this study will guide further human studies of omega-3 supplementation on the development of heart disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.focusinstudy.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Adelaide Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>THE UNIVERSITY OF ADELAIDE Research Branch	
Level 4 Rundle Mall Plaza
50 Rundle Mall 
SA 5005</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2015-123</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anthony Pisaniello</name>
      <address>Level 6, South
Heart Health Theme
SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61881284529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Anthony.Pisaniello@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anthony Pisaniello</name>
      <address>Level 6, South
Heart Health Theme
SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61881284529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Anthony.Pisaniello@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anthony Pisaniello</name>
      <address>Level 6, South
Heart Health Theme
SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61881284529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Anthony.Pisaniello@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Peta King</name>
      <address>Level 6, South
Heart Health Theme
SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61881284495</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peta.king@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>