<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363137">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001098820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of daily cleaning of contact lenses on adverse event rates in new and experienced lens wearers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, controlled, open label, bilateral, clinical trial to investigate daily, morning cleaning of silicone hydrogel contact lenses worn during  extended wear as a strategy for reducing adverse events associated with contact lens wear in neophyte and experienced lens wearers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>NIL</utrn>
    <trialacronym>R&amp;R Efficacy study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The study purpose is to investigate the efficacy of daily morning cleaning of lenses with a multipurpose disinfection solution as a means of reducing contact lens related ocular adverse events.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prospective, controlled, open label, bilateral, clinical trial to investigate daily, morning cleaning of silicone hydrogel contact lenses worn during  three months extended wear as a strategy for reducing adverse events associated with contact lens wear in neophyte and experienced lens wearers. Lenses will be worn for one month extended wear (i.e. during the day and night). For the test group, each morning following waking, the lenses will be removed, several drops of Biotrue multipurpose solution applied to the lens. The lenses are then cleaned by rubbing and then rinsing with the same solution and then reinserted on eye.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will wear the same lens type for the same duration but will not remove the lenses daily for cleaning (i.e. standard extended wear)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if daily cleaning of contact lenses during continuous wear of silicone hydrogel contact lenses reduces the incidence of contact lens related ocular adverse events, including infiltrative keratitis, contact lens induced peripheral ulcer and acute red eye. Assessment will be conducted using a slit lamp biomicroscope.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week, 1 month, 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if daily cleaning of contact lenses during continuous wear of silicone hydrogel contact lenses reduces the contamination rate of contact lenses. Worn lenses will be removed aseptically by the clinician at monthly scheduled visits, placed in phosphate buffered saline and sent for microbiological analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month, 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
-Be at least 18 years old, male or female.
-Be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.
-Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses.
-Have vision that is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses/spectacles.
-Be experienced or inexperienced at wearing contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including keratoconus and herpes keratitis) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
-Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosis. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
-An active corneal infection or any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
-Use of or a need for any therapeutic ocular medication up to 4 weeks prior to and during the trial;
-Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse manner or risk providing a false positive.
-Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
-Previous corneal refractive surgery.
-Contraindications to contact lens wear.
-Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products.
-Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly allocated into either the test group (lenses to be cleaned each morning) or control group (standard continuous wear, i.e. no daily cleaning required). Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation plan will be generated generated from http://www.randomization.com/.  A randomisation list will be generated by the biostatistician and based on an independent group design.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Hyderabad</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building, Barker St, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building, Barker St, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The hypothesis for this study is that regular lens cleaning with a contact lens disinfection solution during extended wear exposes the eye to a clean lens surface thereby reducing bacterial build-up on the lens surface, compared to standard extended wear, resulting in less bacterially driven ocular adverse events.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NA</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hyderabad Eye Research Foundation Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>L V Prasad Eye Institute, L V Prasad Marg, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad, 500-034</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LEC 11-192</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>India</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building, Barker St, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>61293857516</phone>
      <fax>Nil</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building, Barker St, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>61293857516</phone>
      <fax>Nil</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building, Barker St, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>61293857516</phone>
      <fax>Nil</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Varsha Rathi</name>
      <address>L V Prasad Eye Institute, Banjara Hills, Hyderabad, 500-034</address>
      <phone>+91 40 3061 2345</phone>
      <fax>+91 40 2345 8271</fax>
      <email>communications@lvpei.org</email>
      <country>India</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>