<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365294">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001255774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>RESOLVE Clinical Trial: Vagal Block for Obesity Triggered Diabetes and Hypertension 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The RESOLVE study: A Single-arm Clinical Study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of vagal block using the EnteroMedics Maestro System in the management of patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypertension 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes  </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Maestro Registered Trademark Rechargeable System. System consists of a neuromodulation device that delivers intermittent, controllable electrical blocking algorithms, defined as VBLOC Therapy, to the intra-abdominal vagus nerve for the treatment of metabolic disease, including obesity and the obesity-related comorbid conditions of type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypertension. 

The Maestro System neuromodulation system consists of the following implantable and external components:
Implantable components: two flexible leads (including one electrode each for the anterior and posterior intra-abdominal vagal nerve trunks) that are connected to an implantable neuroregulator placed subcutaneously on the rib cage on the mid-axillary line and above the costal margin (a minimum of two or three finger widths above), or a location determined by the surgeon and consistent with device operation.  The leads are implanted laparoscopically into the intra-abdominal cavity and the neuroregulator is implanted in a subcutaneous pocket, similar to that used to implant a cardiac pacemaker.
 
External components: One mobile charger for the implanted neuroregulator, which is connected via a small, flexible cable to a cutaneous transmit coil that is positioned over the implanted neuroregulator when charging the device or determining the status of the device; a software program on a laptop computer that transmits information to the neuroregulator and uploads data from the neuroregulator, which is available to the clinician, allowing both change in treatment regimens and assessment of treatment.

The Maestro System works by delivering electronic neuronal blocking algorithms to the anterior and posterior trunks of the intra-abdominal vagus nerve.  Blocking of nerve signals carried by these vagal trunks has potential for significant therapeutic benefit, because down-regulates these effects.
Duration of the implantation surgery less than 60 Minutes 
Device remains in-situ permanently.
Patient may be involved in activating and recharging device but always under the instruction and supervision of the clinician. </interventions>
    <comparator>No Control Group </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The main objectives of this study are to evaluate the efficacy of the EnteroMedics Maestro System in in the management of patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypertension. Assessed with tests to see changes in HbA1 from baseline, Changes in systolic and diastolic blodd pressures from baseline and tests to see changes in fasting plasma glucose from basline </outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Change in HbA1c from baseline at: hospital discharge (post-index procedure), 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years post-implant. 
2.	Change in systolic and diastolic blood pressures from baseline at: hospital discharge (post-index procedure), 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years post-implant.
3.	Change in fasting plasma glucose from baseline at: hospital discharge (post-index procedure), 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years-post-implant. 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate safety of the EnteroMedics Maestro System in the management of patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypertension. Assessed with tests to see changes in HbA1 from baseline, Changes in systolic and diastolic blodd pressures from baseline and tests to see changes in fasting plasma glucose from basline </outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Change in HbA1c from baseline at: hospital discharge (post-index procedure), 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years post-implant. 
2.	Change in systolic and diastolic blood pressures from baseline at: hospital discharge (post-index procedure), 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years post-implant.
3.	Change in fasting plasma glucose from baseline at: hospital discharge (post-index procedure), 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years-post-implant. 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Additionally, the study intends to further explore potential physiologic mechanisms of the Maestro Systems impact on these two disease processes. Assessed through Device-related adverse events at hospital discharge, 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years post-implant. Change in weight from baseline at hospital discharge. 

Low Probability risks 

Intra-operative

Death, Respiratory complications
Cardiac (anesthesia related),Bleeding,Esophageal perforation,DVT/pulmonary embolus,Electrode misplacement
Electrode malfunction,vagal nerve injury (mechanical)

Post-operative 
Esophageal erosion
Organ entrapment or strangulation
Small bowel obstruction
DVT/pulmonary embolism
Vagal nerve injury (mechanical)
Wound dehiscence 
Infection, other
Infection, lead location
Infection, neuroregulator location
Electrode dislodgement or malfunction
Neuroregulator malfunction
Neuroregulator migration or erosion
Electric shock
Skin reaction to coil

Medium Probability Risks
Post-operative 
Infection, superficial
Inflammation
All risks are assessed using good clinical judgement and reduced by having Implant training; experienced surgical team, Experienced anesthesiology team previous Implant training, surgical technique. Training; stimulation and impedance testing, Replacing any malfunctiong electrodes using Sterile surgical technique; post- op wound care, Design controls; Clinical follow-up and Alternate attachment methods for rection to coil on skin or malfuncting devices.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Device-related adverse events at hospital discharge, 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years post-implant.
2.	Change in weight from baseline at: hospital discharge (post-index procedure), 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and quarterly through three (3) years post-implant. This will be reported as absolute, TBL and EWL.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Body mass index (BMI) 27-40 kg/m2 inclusive
Type 2 diabetes mellitus
HbA1c levels greater than or equal to 7.0%
Systolic blood pressure &gt;130 mmHg
18-70 years of age inclusive
Patient is adhering to a stable anti-hypertensive drug regimen (with no changes for a minimum of 2 weeks prior to enrollment) that is expected to be maintained for at least 6 months  
Females of child-bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test (blood or urine) at study entrance, and must consent to using an Investigator- approved contraception method for the first 6 months after device implant
Patient or patients legal representative has been informed of the nature of the trial and agrees to its provisions and has provided written informed consent as approved by Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) of the respective investigational site. 
Patient agrees to comply with all specified follow-up evaluations
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Concurrent chronic pancreatic disease
2.	History of Crohns disease and/or ulcerative colitis
3.	History of gastric resection or major upper-abdominal surgery (Acceptable surgeries include cholecystectomy, hysterectomy.)
4.	History of pulmonary embolism or blood coagulation disorders 
5.	Clinically significant hiatal hernias 
6.	Intra-operative exclusion: hiatal hernia requiring surgical repair or extensive dissection at esophagogastric junction at time of surgery
7.	Smoking cessation within the prior three months
8.	Known genetic cause of obesity (e.g., Prader-Willi Syndrome)
9.	DM with associated autonomic neuropathy, e.g., diabetes-associated gastroparesis
10.	Current or recent history (within 12 months) of ongoing binge eating disorder, bulimia, or night eating disorder
11.	Current alterations in treatment for thyroid disorders (stable treatment regimen for prior three months acceptable)
12.	Current alterations in treatment for epilepsy (stable treatment regimen for prior six months acceptable)
13.	Current treatment for peptic ulcer disease (previous history acceptable)
14.	Chronic treatment with narcotic analgesic drug regimens 
15.	Current alterations in treatment regimens of anti-cholinergic drugs, including tricyclic antidepressants (stable treatment regimen for prior six months acceptable)
16.	Current medical condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would make subject unfit for surgery under general anesthesia or that would be exacerbated by intentional weight loss.  Some examples include diagnosis of cancer, recent heart attack, recent stroke or recent serious trauma
17.	Presence of permanently implanted electrical powered medical device or implanted gastrointestinal device or prosthesis 
18.	Significant psychiatric disorders that, in the opinion of the investigator, may interfere with subjects ability to follow study procedures and/or instructions
19.	Pre-operative diet with intent to lose weight prior to surgery
20.	Life expectancy &lt; 12 months 
21.	Currently participating in an investigational drug or another device trial that has not completed the primary endpoint or that clinically interferes with the current trial endpoints
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a prospective, single arm clinical study. Patient data will be collected at baseline, index procedure, 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and at quarterly intervals through three years post-implant.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>EnteroMedics 'Registered Trademark' Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2800 Patton Road
St. Paul, MN 55113  United States
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>EnteroMedics 'Registered Trademark' Inc.
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2800 Patton Road
St. Paul, MN 55113  United States
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Pacific Clinical Research Group (PCRG)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Suite G03, 1 Cassins Ave,
North Sydney
NSW
2060</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The RESOLVE study: A Single-arm Clinical Study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the EnteroMedics Maestro System in the management of patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypertension. 
EnteroMedics Maestro Registered Trademark Rechargeable System (Maestro System)
This is a prospective, single arm clinical study.
The main objectives of this study are to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the EnteroMedics Maestro System in the management of patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus and hypertension. Additionally, the study intends to further explore potential physiologic mechanisms of the Maestro Systems impact on these two disease processes.
Up to 25 patients.
Patient data will be collected at baseline, index procedure, 1, 7, 14, 30 days, 6 months, and at quarterly intervals through three years post-implant 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Henry Krum</name>
      <address>3rd Floor, Burnet Building, 
The Alfred
Commercial Road
Prahran, Vic. 3181
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0042</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>henry.krum@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ross Prpic</name>
      <address>Pacific Clinical Research Group (PCRG)
Suite G03, 1 Cassins Ave
North Sydney
NSW
2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9925 4200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ross.prpic@pcrg.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ross Prpic</name>
      <address>Pacific Clinical Research Group (PCRG)
Suite G03, 1 Cassins Ave
North Sydney
NSW
2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9925 4200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ross.prpic@pcrg.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Susan Doolan</name>
      <address>Pacific Clinical Research Group (PCRG)
Suite G03, 1 Cassins Ave
North Sydney
NSW
2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9925 4214</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susan.doolan@pcrg.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>