<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371131">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000990426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Vascular, cognitive and cerebrovascular function responses to acute consumption of chocolate in postmenopausal women  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Vascular, cognitive and cerebrovascular function responses to acute consumption of chocolate in postmenopausal women  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vascular function </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cerebrovascular function </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive function </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In a counterbalanced within-subjects cross-over design, post-menopausal women will complete three experimental trials (plus an introductory session) at the School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health, The University of Western Australia. A washout period of one week will occur between each of the four sessions. Participants will be supervised for the duration of all sessions. They will be instructed to complete a food diary and abstain from caffeine, alcohol, chocolate and vigorous physical activity in the 24 h prior to the introductory session and to replicate this in the 24 h prior to each experimental session. At each session, participants will have 15min to consume one of the following energy-matched chocolate treatments (2099 kJ each); (a) 84 g of a high concentration cocoa (80%) dark chocolate, (b) 87 g of a lower concentration cocoa (35%) milk chocolate and (c) 85 g of a cocoa butter white chocolate (0% cocoa solids). Measures of cerebral blood flow velocity responses, recorded before and during completion of a computerised cognitive assessment battery (CogState), brachial artery flow-mediated dilation (FMD) and hemodynamic responses (heart rate, blood pressure) will be obtained in response to chocolate consumption. Each session will be approximately 2 hours in duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>The three chocolate conditions will be isocaloric, but contain varied polyphenol content to assess a dose response (80% cocoa 'dark' chocolate (395 mg polyphenols), a 35% cocoa 'milk' chocolate (200 mg polyphenols) and a cocoa butter 'white' chocolate (35 mg polyphenols).</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurovascular reactivity: Assessment of cerebral blood flow responses to chocolate ingestion during simultaneous manipulation of cerebral metabolism (change in cognitive demand). 

Cerebral blood flow response: Continuous cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFv) of bilateral middle cerebral arteries will be assessed via transcranial Doppler. Participants will be instrumented with a headframe (Marc 600, Spencer Technologies) capable of bilaterally transfixing two 2-MHz ultrasound probes over the temporal window. Measurements will obtained and exported in real time to a data acquisition system (PowerLab, LabChart 7; ADInstruments, Sydney, Australia) for post hoc analysis. 

Cognitive demand: Participants will complete a computer-based cognitive battery (CogState Research TM), a widely used and accepted academic research tool. For the measurement of neurovascular reactivity, This CogState task is used as a tool to stimulate changes in cerebral metabolism which in turn can influence CBFv. this corresponding change in CBFv is what is being assessed. Further details of the CogState test are detailed below in secondary outcomes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During the familiarisation session and 60mins post-chocolate consumption of white, milk and dark chocolate on experimental trial days.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular endothelial function: Assessed via flow-mediated dilation which is a non-invasive high-resolution ultrasound (Terason, t3200, Burlington, MA 01803, USA) imaging technique of the brachial artery which will be performed on the non-dominant arm. Images will be optimised and recordings taken during a 1 minute resting baseline which will be follwoed by the inflation of an occlussion cuff for 5 min to 220 mmHg around the forearm. Scanning will be continued following deflation of the cuff for 3 min. Continuous (30 Hz) brachial lumen cross-sectional area and Doppler velocity will be used to calculate brachial blood flow and shear stress, along with changes in arterial diameter. FMD will be calculated in absolute (mm) and relative (%) terms as the increase from the 1 min resting baseline diameter. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Vascular endothelial function will be assessed at baseline (pre-chocolate) and 80 min following chocolate consumption.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting cerebrovascular perfusion: Resting cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFv) of bilateral middle cerebral arteries will be assessed via transcranial Doppler. Participants will be instrumented with a headframe (Marc 600, Spencer Technologies) capable of bilaterally transfixing two 2-MHz ultrasound probes over the temporal window.  Measurements will obtained and exported in real time to a data acquisition system (PowerLab, LabChart 7; ADInstruments, Sydney, Australia) for post hoc analysis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Resting CBFv will be obtained for 5 min in a rested state in a standardised room devoid of stimulation. Participants will be seated in front of a blank whiteboard and told to focus on the screen. Measurements will obtained in this way during the familiarisation session, and prior to, and 60 min after chocolate consumption on each experimental session. .</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive function will be assessed using a computer-based cognitive battery (CogState Research TM), a widely used and accepted academic research tool. A laptop will be placed in front of the participants and they will be instructed to complete the battery of tests as accurately as possible. The battery requires approximately 20 min to complete and consists of 7 distinct tasks that will be presented in the same order.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the familiarisation session and 60mins post-chocolate consumption of white, milk and dark chocolate on experimental trial days.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hemodynamics: Beat-to-beat continuous heart rate, stroke volume and blood pressure (mean arterial pressure) will be  recorded using a Finometer PRO (Finapres Medical Systems, Amsterdam). Briefly, this involves a finger cuff placed around the middle finger of the participants non-dominant arm, which will be supported and remain stationary at the level of the right atrium on a platform. Vigilant supervision during recording will ensure this is the case. Measurements will obtained and exported in real time to a data acquisition system (PowerLab, LabChart 7; ADInstruments, Sydney, Australia) for post hoc analysis.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded continuously during the the assessments of resting cerebrovascular perfusion (during the familiarisation session, and prior to and 60min after chocolate consumption during each experimental session) and neurovascular reactivity (during the familiarisation session and 60min post-chocolate consumption during each experimental session). . </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy, postmenopausal women aged 50-65 yr. They must like eating all types of chocolate (white, milk, dark).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those who are taking any prescribed medication, have any known cardiovascular related diseases or smokers.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Within-subject, counterbalanced design </designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6009 - Crawley</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Western Australia, School of Sports Science, Exercise and Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia, School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, Australia, 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, Australia, 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cocoa contains polyphenols that are thought to be beneficial to vascular health, but no previous dose-response study has assessed the impact of chocolate containing distinct levels of cocoa on cerebrovascular function and cognition. This research aims to investigate the acute effect of chocolate consumption (80% cocoa [dark] versus 35% cocoa [milk] versus 0% cocoa [white]) on vascular endothelial function, cognition and cerebrovascular function in postmenopausal women. The results have the potential to provide insight into the effect of cocoa polyphenols on systemic blood flow responses and cognitive ability. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Western Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, Australia, 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/7321</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Channa Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, Australia, 6009</address>
      <phone>(+61 8) 6488 2361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>channa.marsh@research.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Channa Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, Australia, 6009</address>
      <phone>(+61 8) 6488 2361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>channa.marsh@research.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Channa Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, Australia, 6009</address>
      <phone>(+61 8) 6488 2361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>channa.marsh@research.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Channa Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, Australia, 6009</address>
      <phone>(+61 8) 6488 2361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>channa.marsh@research.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>