<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83396">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000060246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Two new tests, Multiple Breath Washout Technique and Acoustic Severe Asthma Monitor, to measure lung function (breathing) in young children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of Lung Function Using the Multiple Breath Washout Technique and Acoustic Severe Asthma Monitor in Pre-School Children with a History of Wheezing</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wheeze</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are two new tests that can be used to measure lung function in young children.  These are called the multiple breath washout (MBW) and Acoustic Severe Asthma Monitor (ASAM). The MBW equipment is registered in Australia for use in children from birth. This system uses a multiple-breath washin/washout technique using sulphur-hexafluoride (SF6) as a tracer gas and a commercially available, TGA approved, ultrasonic flowmeter which indirectly measures inert tracer gas concentrations by continuous mainstream recording of the molar mass of the gas.
The ASAM is a new breathing test and is not yet registered in Australia so its use is experimental. The ASAM is a combination of two technologies; incorporating both passive and active methods for continuous monitoring of the asthmatic patient.  The passive technology employs the detection of wheezes and coughing in the patient.  The active technology, which injects sound into the upper airways, monitors the degree of occlusion of intrapulmonary airways that occurs during asthma attacks.
All participants undergo both tests in one session, with devices assigned in random order. Particpants will not have follow up as part of the study but will follow usual care. 50 children who wheeze and 50 children who dont wheeze and have no other breathing problems shall be recruited and closeout shall occur within a year of commencement</interventions>
    <comparator>There are two new tests used to measure lung function in young children, the multiple breath washout (MBW) and Acoustic Severe Asthma Monitor (ASAM). The MBW equipment is registered in Australia for use and therefore most represents the control test in this study. All children within the study receive standard care and will have both tests in random order.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the feasibility of MBW for the detection of lung function abnormalities and reversibility to bronchodilators in preschool children with a history of wheeze.
To determine the feasibility of ASAM for the detection of reversibility to bronchodilators in preschool children with a history of wheeze. Comparisson of results of both test shall be cross examined and directly compared</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data analysis will be competed off site post test administration, conclusions are expected at the completion of the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The long term aim of this study is to develop techniques which provide objective markers of lung function and bronchodilator responsiveness in preschool children with wheezing with the two types of medical equipment tests and the direct comparison of results.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of the last test administered to participants</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>child is between 3 and 6 years of age and has been referred to the hospital because of wheeze</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>has another respiratory problem such as cystic fibrosis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Children Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/- The Royal Childrens Hosptial, Melbourne
Flemington Road, Parkville 
Victoria, 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PulmoSonix Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>336A GlenHuntly Rd
Elsternwick VIC 3185</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>PulmoSonix Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>336A GlenHuntly Rd
Elsternwick VIC 3185</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recent advances in diagnostic technologies and subsequent physiological research has lead to a number of techniques being widely available for use in the pre-school age group and resulted in the transition of these techniques into clinical practice. The use of these newer respiratory function techniques to assess airway function in pre-school children with recurrent wheeze may have major implications for our understanding of the pathophysiology of asthma.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital, Melbourne Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>28027A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jo Harrison</name>
      <address>Royal Childrens Hospital Melbourne
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455818</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jo.harrison@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jo Harrison</name>
      <address>Royal Childrens Hospital Melbourne
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455818</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jo.harrison@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Shaun Bowden</name>
      <address>PulmoSonix
336A GlenHuntly Rd
Elsternwick VIC 3185</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>sbowden@pulmosonix.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>