<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365368">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000019606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of blackcurrant consumption on physical fitness, bioenergetics and natural immunity during high intensity training; involvement of mitochondrial adaptation?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A crossover study examining blackcurrant consumption on physical fitness,  immunity and mitochondrial adaptation during high intensity training in healthy subjects.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1144-9954</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Fitness adaptation and natural immunity
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fitness adaptation, bioenergetics and mitochondria number/mass, function and fagility.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study design- The study is divided into 2 stages, the first stage will establish a high intensity training (HIT) protocol together with appropriate biological measurements (listed below). The second stage will apply the HIT protocol to assess the additional fitness &amp; health benefits of a consuming a blackcurrant extract prior to each HIT session. 
Stage 1. This first stage of the study will establish a HIT protocol that will identify adaptive changes in fitness and health (focus on mitochondrial bioenergenesis and natural immunity). These changes will be assessed by physical, subjective and blood biochemical parameters.    
Study participants - Participants will be assessed for their suitability by assessing their ability to do a short-cycle (5 km) with breathing apparatus on a stationary Wingate bike and a habitual Baecke questionnaire. During the trial, participants will be asked to complete on-line health and diet diaries each week (monitored by the trial co-ordinator) and asked to omit foods and dietary supplements that are high in antioxidants for the duration of the study (a list will given to all participants) . 
 Fitness assessments  (i) VO2 max. A stationary Wingate cycle ergometer will be used to assess participants VO2 max. This will require the participant to cycle at incrementally wattage until volitional fatigue. The rate of CO2 increase, heart rate and respiratory exchange ratio (ratio of CO2 exhaled vs. O2 inhaled) will also be measured. In addition, blood lactate will be measured immediately post exercise. (ii) 15K stationary cycle ergometer time-trial. Participants will initally be asked to donate blood (see listof tests below) and complete physiological (e.g. heart rate, O2/CO2 exchange, thigh /tenderness measurements) and subjective (VAS fatigue/pain) assessments. Subjects will then be asked to perform a 15K timed trial on a stationary Wingate bike as quickly as possible. The completion time plus heart rate, work output, O2/CO2 exchange will be assessed. Immediately post cycle, physiological and subjective evaluations will be repeated. The physiological parameters will then be continuously monitored over the first 10 mins of exercise recovery, followed by a final measurement taken 20 mins post exercise. Additional blood samples will be taken immediately post exercise and after 20 mins recovery. Blood collected during this fitness assessment will be analyzed for blood glucose &amp; lactate, insulin, inflammatory markers (C-reactive protein, IL-6, IL-10) levels, as well as oxidative and antioxidant parameters. In addition, blood leukocyte and platelet mitochondria function (e.g. respirometry, pro- &amp; anti-oxidant capacity, fragility) will be assessed. 
HIT protocol - This will be performed over a 2-week period using a stationary Wingate cycle ergometer. The HIT protocol consists of a total of 6 HIT sessions over a 2-week period; 3 sessions every week. Participants will complete a 5 min warm-up cycle at 50W immediately prior to each HIT. The HIT protocol will consist of a repeated bout of 30 sec all-out cycling on a Wingate ergometer set at a resistance corresponding to 4.0% of the subject's body mass. Each bout will be separated by 1 min active recovery (light cycle at 30W). Incremental training will be implemented by increasing the number of repetitions from 6 repeats during first 2 sessions, to eight repeats during sessions 3 and 4 and then ten repeats during sessions 5 and 6. Within each HIT session, we aim to assess (i) leg swelling (thigh diameter &amp; tenderness and (ii) VAS (fatigue, pain/soreness) and RPE evaluation. 
Stage 2:  The fitness assessment, HIT and biological parameters established in stage 1 will be applied. The trial is designed as a double-blind cross-over involving two 2-week HIT blocks  sandwiched between the two fitness assessments (VO2max and a 15K cycle ergometer time-trial) at the beginning and end of each 2-week HIT block. The dietary intervention will be taken prior to each of the HIT session (see above for details)
Dietary Intervention - Participants will consume 3.2mg/Kg (anthocyanin equivalent) of a commercially-available anthocyanin-rich 30% blackcurrant extract (Just-The-Berries, NZ) OR a placebo (equivalent sugar and vitamin C present in the blackcurrant extract). Following a 2-week wash-out period, trial subjects will then cross-over the dietary interventions. The blackcurrant extract contains only blackcurrant and consists of 89% anthocyanin and 11% non-anthocyanin polyphenols). The blackcurrant extract will given to participants within opague gelatin capsules. Furthermore, neither the trial subjects nor the trial co-ordinator will know the order or the treatment being given in each arm of the study. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Opague gelatin capsules containing equivalent sugar and vitamin C present within the blackcurrant extract.
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in fitness, biogenerensis and immunity before and after HIT training. 
(1) Exercise (physical and subject) parameters: VO2max L/min, O2/CO2 exchange, Heart rate, Work output, Lactate threshold, rating of perceived exertion (RPE), Fatigue, pain/soreness VAS &amp; thigh swelling. 
(2) Innate immunity. Circulating inflammatory markers (IL-6, IL-10, C-reactive protein), leukocyte immune responsiveness to bacterial (TLR4 /TL2 ligands) and viral (TLR7 ligands) antigens (ex vivo studies) 
(3) Mitochondrial number, function (respirometry)and fagility status in circulating leukocytes and platelets.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The above assessment will be taken as part of the 15K cycle time-trial fitness assessment. Measruements will be be made before and immediately after the completion of the 15Km time trial and then after 20 mins recovery.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood biochemistry (as indicators of change in general health and well-being). Antioxidant (FRAP, SOD, catalase, GPx), oxidative stress parameters (carbonyls, MDA) and insulin and free fatty acid profiles.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The above assessment will be taken as part of the 15K cycle time-trial fitness assessment. Measruements will be be made before and immediately after the completion of the time trial and then after 20 mins recovery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy persons of either gender</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants in this study will be excluded if they have any of the following conditions: (i) blood borne diseases, e.g. hepatitis; (ii) clinically diagnosed high/low blood pressure; (iii) pregnant, or planning to get pregnant; (iv) recent bacterial or viral illness or vaccinations; (v) chronic illness that affects their immune system (e.g. lupus) or (vi) any medication that affects the properties of blood, e.g. clotting. 
In addition subjects recruited for this study will be excluded if they have (i) any health conditions that affect their ability to perform the exercise regime required in this study (i.e. heart and/or breathing problems, hernia or injury) or (ii) intolerance, hypersensitivity or allergy to foods, especially fruit.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed. Allocation is assigned by a single fellow scientist who is not associated with the work.  No participants or trial scientists undertaking the work are aware of the allocation.  Allocation is held concealed until completion of the trial and analysis of the data is finalized.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization using a spreadsheet random function</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis of data.
All trial data will be captured on study specific visit worksheets (except for online surveys) and transcribed to an access database, held at Plant and Food Research. Data will be expressed as mean +/- standard error of the mean. 
(a) Exercise trial data analysis. Previous studies have shown that a sample size of 10 has a desired statistical power level of 0.8 with a probability level of 0.05.  This is calculated on an anticipated effect size (Cohenss d) of 1.159 based on paired SD for a difference in VO2 Max L/min. In this study, data will be analyzed using Statistical Analysis Software (SAS) 9.1 for Windows (version 5.1.2600). Using a repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA), comparison between conditions over time for each measure (independent variable) will also be determined, providing levels of significance for trial effect, treatment effect, and interaction effect between treatment and trial. A post-hoc tests will also be performed to identify significant differences at each time point. Values will be presented as means +/- standard deviation (or standard error) at a 95% significance level (P equal to 0.05). Pearsons Product Moment Correlation Coefficients may also be assessed using SPSS 15.0 for Windows to investigate if there are any relationships between certain variables by giving an R-value between 0.0 and 1.00 (or -0.0 and -1.00).

(b) Ex vivo cell experiment data analysis. Statistical significance for the comparison between two groups will be assessed using a paired Student's t-test. Multiple comparisons were assessed by a two-way ANOVA. Where appropriate, the original data will be transformed to achieve normality and constant variance in the residuals. Statistical significance for all indices was set at P less than or equal to 0.05 with a confidence level of 95%.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton, Waikato, New Zealand</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The New Zealand Institute of Plant and Food Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92169 Auckland 1142
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The New Zealand Institute of Plant and Food Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 92169 Auckland 1142
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Eating fruit as part of a daily diet is essential in the maintenance of health and well-being. Recent studies show that in addition to containing antioxidants, certain fruit contain other compounds that boost our body's defenses. Similarly, regular exercise has been shown to improve fitness and wellbeing. In this study we identify fruits that if eaten prior to exercise will facilitate the health benefits of regular exercise. The study is divided into 2 stages. Stage 1, will establish a high intensity exercise that if performed 3 days a week for 2-weeks will show an improvement in fitness and the body's defenses. In stage 2, this training strategy will be applied to determine whether eating blackcurrants before each exercise bout will improve the health effects observed from exercising alone. In stages 2 and 3, the participant will be asked to complete 2 fitness assessments on a cycle ergometer; VO2 max and a time trial over 15 Km; during these assessments the subjects breathing (O2/CO2 exchange) and heart rate will be monitor. Blood will also be taken to assess mitochondrial  bioenergetics and natural immunity. The participation time required for stage 1 will be 24 days, whereas for stage 2, it will be 60 days due to the cross-over design of the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 The Terrace C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House 10 Brandon Street PO Box 5013 Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> 13/CEN/169</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name> Suzanne Hurst</name>
      <address>NZ Institute for Plant and Food Research
Food Industry Science Centre
Batchelar Road
Palmerston North 4472
New Zealand


</address>
      <phone>+64 6 355 6231</phone>
      <fax>+64 6 351 7050</fax>
      <email>suzanne.hurst@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kirsty Lyall</name>
      <address>NZ Institute for Plant and Food Research
Ruakura Research Centre
Bisley Rd
Hamilton 3214
New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>6479594468</phone>
      <fax>64 79594431</fax>
      <email>kirsty.lyall@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Hurst</name>
      <address>NZ Institute for Plant and Food Research
Food Industry Science Centre
Batchelar Road
Palmerston North 4472
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 6 355 6231</phone>
      <fax>+64 6 351 7050</fax>
      <email>suzanne.hurst@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>