<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372957">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000818336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and tolerability of experimental hookworm infection in humans with metabolic disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Safety and tolerability of experimental hookworm infection in humans with metabolic disease: Proof of Concept (Phase 1b) clinical trial </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1196-6430 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>WAM </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Randomised controlled double-blind, placebo controlled Phase 1b safety and tolerability trial in otherwise healthy women aged 18-44 with central obesity (waist circumference (WC) &gt;90cm) and features of MetS (either abnormal TG/HDL cholesterol, BP&gt;=135/85, raised fasting BSL) experimentally infected with 20 or 40 larvae of the human hookworm Necator americanus (20 L3, 40 L3) over 24 months. There will be 3 arms (n=15 receiving 20 L3 dose, n=15 receiving 40 L3 dose and n=15 controls receiving Tabasco sauce placebo).
Innoculation takes twice at weeks 0 and weeks 8. Innoculation involves direct skin administration of 200ul of solution containing either treatment or placebo. Confirmation of infection occurs at week 8 via faecal sample</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be 3 arms (n=15 receiving 20 L3 dose, n=15 receiving 40 L3 dose and n=15 controls receiving Tabasco sauce placebo).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary, composite outcome will be the safety of experimental inoculation of participants with 20 L3, defined by (a) Number of reported adverse events (AEs), relative to placebo cohort, (b) Assessment of general health and (c) Successful completion of 24 month trial. 
Adverse reaction coudl include but are not limited to abdominal pain, rash, fever, weight loss, fatigue, nausea. these will be assessed by the trial Doctor as being mild, moderate or severe following clinical examination. either by interview in person with trial participant or via phone/internet communication. These adverse evemts will be documented at each participant contact on the data collection database being maintained with all study data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of the 24 month trial. Paticipants will have direct contact with researchers at week 0, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months and 24 months. These contact points will be face to face and the participants will undergo medical examination and questionaire completion
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Insulin Sensitivity from Blood Pathology taken at each particpant contact point during the 24 month trial</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months, 12 months, 18 montjs and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in BMI Measured by any alteration Weight (kg) and Height (cm) as measured by weigh scales and height measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 6 month, 12 months, 18 months and 24 Months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Waist Circumference (cm) measured by tape measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>t6 months, 12 months, 18 months and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in baterial richness of microbiome measure by shotgun assay of faecal sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>Samples taken for analysis at 6 months, 12 months 18 months and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy adult females 18-44 years, with central obesity (WC&gt;90cm) and at least one other feature of MetS (dyslipidemia, raised blood pressure, abnormal liver function tests suggesting fatty liver disease, or raised fasting blood glucose or HbA1c). Have provided written informed consent and is willing to comply with all Protocol scheduled visits, if of childbearing potential, must be willing to use the acceptable methods of contraception</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>44</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, tobacco smoking, established chronic disease (CVD, diabetes, cancer, renal, gut disorder), history of substance abuse or current substance abuse, major allergies, known immunodeficiency disorder, asthma, taking prescribed medications or nutritional supplements likely to interfere with study outcomes, inability to provide informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Double Blinded, sealed envelopes and containers</concealment>
    <sequence>Block Randomization</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The safety of the hookworm infection, the primary outcome, will be assessed by using a chi-squared test of proportions to determine whether there are differences in the proportions satisfying the safety criteria between the placebo, 20 L3 and 40 L3 hookworm groups. Cox regression models will assess safe progression through the study in each cohort. We will perform standard descriptive statistics on all outcome measures at baseline, all interim points of assessment and at 24 months after inoculation (categorical variables: absolute and relative frequencies; numerical variables: mean and SD or median and IQR). Of particular interest will be changes in weight, visceral fat mass (DXA), insulin sensitivity (HOMA-IR) and adiponectin.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Cairns Base Hospital - Cairns</hospital>
    <postcode>4870 - Cairns</postcode>
    <postcode>4878 - Smithfield</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>James Cook University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 6811
Building D3
Smithfield University Campus
Cairns
Queensland
4878</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>James Cook University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6811
Building D3
Smithfield University Campus
Smithfield
Cairns
Queensland
4878</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Safety and tolerability of experimental hookworm infection in humans with metabolic disease: Proof of Concept (Phase 1b) clinical trial Aims:
1.	To establish the acceptability, safety and tolerability of experimental infection with the hookworm Necator americanus (Na) in young obese women with features of the metabolic syndrome (MetS).
2.	Conduct exploratory studies into the impact of hookworms on stabilizing or improving immune/inflammatory, metabolic and microbiological parameters associated with metabolic disease
Background: Central obesity and subsequent type 2 diabetes (T2DM) are causing a global epidemic of disability and premature death which threatens to bankrupt health systems even in wealthy countries. The vast majority (80%) of all diabetes cases and 88% of deaths occur in low to middle income countries, many of which still have a significant infectious disease burden. T2DM and several associated chronic conditions are increasingly recognized as having common pro-inflammatory pathways and it is these effects which account for much end-organ damage, especially in the liver, muscle, kidneys, vascular endothelium and brain (Calle et al, 2012). Animal studies and more recently, human observational reports from those transitional populations with high prevalence of helminth exposure and metabolic illness, suggest that helminth infection protects against T2DM and MetS (Hayes, 2015; Tracey, 2016). A plausible biological pathway for this effect has been demonstrated in animal models, where helminth infection stimulates a T helper Type 2 (Th2)-type immune response that, in concert with worm-induced regulatory T cell responses may improve insulin sensitivity, either directly or via suppression of pro-inflammatory Th1/Th17 immune responses. There is evidence that this effect is mediated, at least in part, by changes induced by the worm to the host gut microbiota.
Members of the team (AL, PG) have established that experimental inoculation with the human hookworm Necator americanus is safe and efficacious in the treatment of humans with celiac disease (CeD), and which is currently in use in a NHMRC-funded multi-centre clinical trial (ref protocol, Croese 2016). Previous studies have demonstrated that these controlled hookworm infections are associated with a biased Type 2 cytokine response (Gaze at al 2012), with concomitant regulatory T cell responses (Croese et al 2015) that fit the profile of an agent that may be effective at treating the dysregulated inflammation associated with MetS or T2DM.
Thus, we propose to use this experimental human infection model in a proof-of-concept phase 1 trial of safety in healthy young women with central obesity and features of the Metabolic Syndrome (MetS). 
Hypotheses: That experimental hookworm infection
1.	will be tolerated and safe in otherwise healthy obese young women;
2.	will induce a biased Type 2 and regulatory immune response and suppression of systemic pro-inflammatory Type 1 immune responses
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>James Cook University Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 6811
Building D3
James Cook University
Smithfield Campus
Cairns
4878
Queensland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>APP1143102</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn McDermott</name>
      <address>PO Box 6811
Building D3
Smithfield University Campus
James Cook University
Cairns
Queensland
Smithfield 4878</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (7) 4232 1575</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.mcdermott@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn McDermott</name>
      <address>PO Box 6811
Building D3
Smithfield University Campus
James Cook University
Cairns
Smithfield 4878
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (7) 4232 1575</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.mcdermott@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn McDermott</name>
      <address>PO Box 6811
Building D3
Smithfield University Campus
James Cook University
Cairns
Smithfield 4878
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (7) 4232 1575</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.mcdermott@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>