<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370981">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000860460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of the Triple P Parenting Intervention for Migrant and Former-Refugee Parents: Randomized Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Examining the efficacy of a brief, evidence-based parenting intervention aimed at improving family adjustment during settlement in Australia: Randomized controlled trial comparing the Triple P Disobedience Discussion Group program against wait-list control with migrant and former-refugee parents from culturally and linguistically diverse (CALD) backgrounds. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>psychological wellbeing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>parenting practices and behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>sociocultural adaptation and acculturative stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>child emotional and behavioural problems</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>parenting confidence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions> Intervention involves parental attendance at a brief, group-based parenting program: Triple P Disobedience Discussion Group. A group-based program is cost-effective and can offer a favourable environment in which participants can build connections through interacting with others with shared experiences. The intervention itself will involve parental attendance at a single three-hour discussion group focused on preventing and managing child misbehaviour, and encouraging positive behaviours. Parents may attend individually or with their partner, however data will be collected from a single caregiver only. The program draws on social learning theory and through utilizing the key principals of the Triple P System, encourages an interactive environment that facilitates open discussion between participants. Up to five groups (with identical content) will be held with approximately 10 participants in each. Two weeks following the intervention, a group-based two-hour consultation session will be offered to participants to assist with strategy implementation and discuss concerns and/or questions that may arise following the program.  

Parents will receive a workbook (that is theirs to keep), and a resource pack (including behaviour monitoring records and positive behaviour charts etc). During the intervention, parents will view powerpoint slides including short video segments. To ensure program fidelity it maintained, accredited program facilitators will follow a detailed presentation guide and will have the content of their sessions monitored using a program checklist.  Participants in the intervention group will be known as the "Start Now" group.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be a wait-list control, known as the "Start Later" group. Parents in the Start Later group will be assessed at the same time points as the intervention group participants (i.e. baseline, 4 weeks following the final intervention group program, and 6 months later).  Start Later group participants will be offered access to a suitable Triple P parenting program following collection of the final data point (i.e. 6 months following the final intervention group attends the program).   Parents will continue to have access to all usual community-based family support services throughout the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting Confidence - total score as measured by the CAPES Parent Efficacy Scale (Morawska et al., 2014).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, 4-weeks post-intervention, 6-months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental Psychological Well-being as measured by the DASS-21 (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995): Total Depression, Anxiety, and Stress symptom scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, 4-weeks post-intervention, 6-months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental Acculturative Stress total score as measured by the Riverside Acculturative Stress Inventory (Miller, Kim, &amp; Benet-Martinez, 2011). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, 4-weeks post-intervention, 6-months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting behaviour and practices as measured by the The Parenting Scale (Arnold, OLeary, Wolff, &amp; Acker, 1993) and The Corporal Punishment Questionnaire (adapted from UNICEF Division of Policy and Planning, Multiple Indicator Cluster Survey Manual, 2006).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, 4-weeks post-intervention, 6-months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child adjustment indicated by the frequency of parent reported emotional and behavioural problems as measured by CAPES- Child Adjustment Scale (Morawska et al., 2104).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, 4-weeks post-intervention, 6-months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental sociocultural adjustment as measured by the Sociocultural Adaptation Scale (Ward &amp; Kennedy, 1999).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, 4-weeks post-intervention, 6-months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Program satisfaction: assessed using the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire (adapted) (Morawska &amp; Sanders, 2010).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4-weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participant inclusion criteria will specify that participants: (i) are a parent of a 2-12 year old child, (ii) have lived in Australia no more than five years (iii) can read and understand basic English, and (iv) are over the age of 18 (the age of consent).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> Participants will be excluded from participating if they (i) are known to be in the process of receiving treatment for a severe psychological illness, (ii) are unable to read or understand basic English (in order to understand program content), (iii) or do not possess a valid humanitarian or migrant visa. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment> Opaque enveloped labelled with participant ID number and containing a randomization notification letter will be used to conceal group allocation. Allocation to groups will not be revealed until all participants have been recruited for the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation will occur using a computer based random number generator. 

</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Target sample size was determined using analysis software and a review of previous research, based on a desire to have power (.95) to detect a medium effect (d=.50), with an assumed alpha level of .05. An additional 20% was added to the resulting sample size to account for attrition, based on the percentage of participants lost at follow-up in the preceding pilot study.  Mixed between-within ANOVAs and MANOVAs will be conducted to evaluate intervention effects following program completion, and at 6-months follow up. Pairwise comparisons will be used to examine significant differences in the dependent variables between conditions (i.e. intervention vs. waitlist control) and times (i.e. pre-intervention, post-intervention, 6-month follow up).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>82</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kathryn Monty</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
Rm s327, Social Sciences Building (Blg 24),
The University of Queensland
ST LUCIA
QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland, Parenting and Family Support Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
Rm s327, Social Sciences Building (Blg 24),
The University of Queensland
ST LUCIA
QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Divna Haslam</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
Social Sciences Building (Blg 24)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will answer the research question of whether receiving contextually and culturally appropriate parenting support early in the settlement period can improve adjustment in migrant and former-refuge families, and by extension, facilitate positive sociocultural adaptation. The aims of the project are to: (a) Determine whether parental participation in a Triple P intervention within the first five years of settlement is effective at improving migrant and former-refugee family outcomes, and (b) Evaluate the efficacy of the program for improving sociocultural adjustment and reducing acculturative stress in migrant parents. The rigorous methodology being utilised in the current study will provide a strong indication as to the generalizability of the results to migrant and former-refugee families in other geographic regions. Should the intervention prove to be effective, it has the potential to fill an important research and service gap, providing an innovative, cost-effective, and evidence-based means to strengthen family relationships and promote positive adjustment in migrant children and their parents. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UQ Behavioural &amp; Social Sciences Ethical Review Committee (BSSERC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UQ Research &amp; Innovation
Cumbrae-Stewart Building (72)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016000274</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn Monty</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre School of Psychology Rm s327, Social Sciences Building (Blg 24), The University of Queensland
ST LUCIA QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 8870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.monty@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn Monty</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre School of Psychology Rm s327, Social Sciences Building (Blg 24), The University of Queensland
ST LUCIA QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 8870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.monty@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn Monty</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre School of Psychology Rm s327, Social Sciences Building (Blg 24), The University of Queensland
ST LUCIA QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 8870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.monty@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn Monty</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre School of Psychology Rm s327, Social Sciences Building (Blg 24), The University of Queensland
ST LUCIA QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 8870</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.monty@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>