<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335273">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000292077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of SYR-472 on Cardiac Function in Healthy Adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo- and Positive-controlled, Parallel Study to Evaluate the Effect of SYR-472 on the QT/QTc Interval in Healthy Adult Male and Female Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1114-4448</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Effects on Cardiac QT/QTc Interval</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention 1: SYR-472 200 mg, tablets, orally, one day only.

Intervention 2: SYR-472 800 mg, tablets, orally, one day only.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intervention 3: Moxifloxacin 400 mg  (positive control), tablets, orally, one day only.


Intervention 4: Placebo-matching tablets (microcrystalline cellulose 202 mg), orally, one day only</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The largest difference in time-matched baseline-adjusted least squares means in QT interval corrected for heart rate using the Fridericia method (QTcF) between SYR-472 and placebo at post-treatment electrocardiogram collection times.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Final Collection Date (Up to 23.5 hours post dosing).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference in time-matched baseline-adjusted least squares means in QTcF and QT interval corrected for heart rate using the study-specific method (QTcss) between SYR-472 and placebo at post-treatment electrocardiogram collection times.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Final Collection Date (Up to 23.5 hours post dosing).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Categorical evaluation of the number and percentage of subjects with time-matched increases in QTcF and QTcss intervals of &gt;30 ms and &gt;60 ms from baseline, and the number and percentage of subjects with QTcF and QTcss intervals of &gt;450 ms, &gt;480 ms and &gt;500 ms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Final Collection Date (Up to 23.5 hours post dosing).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety assessments including adverse events (potential adverse events are not yet known), safety electrocardiograms, vital signs, weight and clinical laboratory values (hematology and serum chemistry).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Final Visit (Up to 8 days post final dosing).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Subjects must be healthy volunteers
*Subjects must weigh at least 50 kg and have a body mass index greater than or equal to 18.5 kg/m2 and less than 30 kg/m2
*Subjects must be in good health in the judgment of the investigator.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Subjects will not be enrolled if the screening electrocardiogram has abnormalities including second- or third-degree atrioventricular block, or one or more of the following: QTcF &gt;450 milliseconds (ms), QRS &gt;120 ms, PR interval of &gt;240 ms or any other rhythm than sinus rhythm, which is interpreted by the investigator to be clinically significant.
* History of additional risk factors for Torsade de pointes (e.g., long QT syndrome)
* Has a heart rate at rest of &lt;50 bpm or &gt;100 bpm
*Uses prescription medications within 4 weeks (28 days) prior to the start of the investigational drug administration
*Use of over-the-counter medications within 1 week (7 days) prior to the start of the investigational drug administration.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Approximately 260 healthy subjects will be randomized in this study to receive one of the following 4 treatments (65 subjects per treatment group): SYR-472 200 mg, SYR-472 800 mg, placebo or moxifloxacin. This study is double-blind except for  the moxifloxacin positive control group included to establish assay sensitivity in the subjects enrolled in this study. 

Study drug will be prescribed in numerical order by using a randomization-table (schedule) generated by computer and prepared by sex, and will be provided to the investigator in advance. All randomization information will be stored in a secured area accessible only to authorized personnel. Allocation concealed.

If the subject has satisfied all the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria for randomization, the subject will be randomized. If the investigator judges that there are some problems with the eligibility of a subject at check-in, the subject may be replaced by a reserve subject. In such cases, the reserve subject will receive the investigational drug that was allocated to the original subject.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be assigned in the order in which they are enrolled into the study and receive the next available randomization sequence number allocated to the study site and gender. Subjects will be stratified by gender.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>260</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Takeda Pharmaceutical Company Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1-1 Doshomachi 4-chome, Chuo-ku, Osaka 540-8645</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Japan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Takeda Pharmaceutical Company Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1-1 Doshomachi 4-chome, Chuo-ku, Osaka 540-8645</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Japan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 2 diabetes mellitus is a complex metabolic disorder characterized by abnormal insulin secretion and an abnormal glucose balance. The primary risk factor for developing type 2 diabetes mellitus is obesity, which can result in insulin resistance in the body. Insulin resistance is characterized by an impaired response to the physiologic effects of insulin, and leads to decreased cellular glucose uptake, increased hepatic gluconeogenesis and a compensatory increase in insulin secretion that contributes to beta-cell exhaustion.

SYR-472 is being developed by Takeda Pharmaceutical Company Ltd. as an adjunct to diet and exercise to treat patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus.

Medicinal products that prolong cardiac repolarization have been associated with a specific, potentially fatal polymorphic ventricular tachycardia called torsade de pointes. 

Although no evidence of cardiovascular effects have been noted in non-clinical studies of SYR-472 nor treatment-related trends revealed in phase 1 studies of SYR-472, this study is being conducted to investigate the effect of SYR-472 on electrocardiography in healthy adults, in compliance with the International Conference of Harmonization Tripartite Guideline: The clinical evaluation of QT/QTc (QT interval corrected for heart rate ) interval prolongation and proarrhythmic potential for non-antiarrhythmic drugs (ICH E14).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.nucleusnetwork.com.au/page.aspx?54</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>34/10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Primary Investigator</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Limited  
5th Floor Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct, 89 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61-3-9076-8960</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-9076-8940</fax>
      <email>medicalinformation@tpna.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Project Manager</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Limited  
5th Floor Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct, 89 Commercial Road Melbourne, Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61-3-9076-9017</phone>
      <fax>+61-3-9076-8911</fax>
      <email>medicalinformation@tpna.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Trial Registration &amp; Results Disclosure Department</name>
      <address>675 N Field Drive
Lake Forest, IL 60045</address>
      <phone>+1-800-778-2860</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clinicaltrialregistry@tpna.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>