<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371994">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000121369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of physiotherapy on selected indicators in elderly women.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The influence of physiotherapy on the haematological and rheological properties of blood and functional stability in elderly women.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>instability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>anemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>cardiovascular disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>blood rheology</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>blood fluidity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of platelets and erythrocytes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Rehabilitation protocols
One group will participate in the general rehabilitation exercises (GRE), and the other in dance movement therapy (DMT). Both GRE and DMT rehabilitation programs will last for 5 months (three sessions per week). In line with the motor rehabilitation guidelines for geriatric patients, each single session will last no longer than 45-50 minutes and the intensity of exercising will be corresponded to no more than 40-60% of heart rate reserve. Both GRE and DMT rehabilitation programs will be supervised by a physical therapist. Exercise sessions will group-based at the study site, at University of Physical Education in Cracow. Attendance of the sessions will be register.
The GRE program will be consisted of 5-10-minute warm-up, 30-minute endurance and balance training and 5-10-minute cool-down. Strengthening exercise training will include low-level progressive resistance exercise with light free weights, exercise ladders and exercise benches. The participants will perform 10-15 repetitions of each exercise, with a resistance corresponding to 40-60% of one-repetition maximum. 
Each DMT session will be followed the same protocol. It will start with a low-intensity warm-up lasting 5-10 minutes and preparing the participants to a more strenuous exercise. The main phase of each training session will be included selected steps and figures of folk dance, ballroom dance and integration dance, as well as practicing predefined and modified choreographies, dancing-gymnastic exercises and dancing improvisation. The final phase of each training session will be lasted 5-10 minutes and included cooling-down with breathing and relaxation exercises, as well as stretching exercises aimed at optimization of the training effects.


</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison outcomes between two groups (GRE group and DMT group).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The influence of the physiotherapy on the selected hematological indicators: red blood cell count, hematocrit, hemoglobin concentration, mean corpuscular hemoglobin, mean corpuscular volume, mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration, leukocyte count and platelet count. Hematological measurements will performer using a blood analyzer (ABX Micros Hematology Analyzer,Horiba ABX Diagnostics, France).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately following the final physiotherapy session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The influence of the physiotherapy on the selected rheological indicators: elongation index, aggregation index, the amplitude and total extent of aggregation, the half time and plasma viscosity. The elongation and aggregation of red blood cells will be determined using a Laser-assisted Optical Rotational Cell Analyzer (LORRCA, RR Mechatronics, Holland). The viscosity of plasma will determine in a viscosimeter (type D-52159 Roetgen, Myrenne, Germany).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately following the final physiotherapy session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The influence of the physiotherapy on the selected biochemical indicators: fibrinogen, reticulocytes count, glutathione, acethylcholinesterase, glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase and nitric oxide.  Concentration of fibrinogen will determine with an aid of Chrom-7 coagulometer. Reticulocytes will be counted in 1000 encountered erythrocytes. Level of reduced GSH, AChe and G-6-PD will be determined according to spectrophotometric method Beuther. The level of NO will be determined spectrophotometrically with a commercially available kit (Nitrate/Nitrite Calorimetric Assay Kit, catalogue no. 780001, Cayman, USA), in line with the manufacturers instructions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately following the final physiotherapy session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The influence of the physiotherapy on functional stability (body balance), measured using a BioSway balance platform (Biodex).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately following the final physiotherapy session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Elderly women
2. Between 60 and 90 years of age.
3. Only healthy participation without e.g. paralysis and paresis interacting with independent mobility, severe vertigo, dementia, diabetes mellitus, and cardiovascular disorders. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Men
2. Women below 60 and above 90 years of age
3. Participants with paralysis and paresis interacting with independent mobility, severe vertigo, dementia, diabetes mellitus, and cardiovascular disorders. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Malopolska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Katarzyna Filar-Mierzwa</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Physical Education
al. Jana Pawla II 78 
31-571 Krakow, Poland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Physical Education</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>al. Jana Pawla II 79
31-571 Krakow
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study will be to analyze the influence of the physiotherapy on the selected hematological and rheological indicators and body balance in older women. The research will be performed among elderly women. Research material will include about 60 participants, only women between 60 and 90 years of age. Women will be subjected to a five-month physiotherapy program (three 45-minute sessions per week). One group (30 participants) will participate in the general rehabilitation exercises (GRE), and the other (30 participants) in dance movement therapy (DMT). Before and after physiotherapy program, blood samples from all the women will be examined for:
- hematological parameters (red blood cell count, hematocrit, hemoglobin concentration, mean corpuscular hemoglobin, mean corpuscular volume, mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration, leukocyte count and platelet count), 
- rheological parameters (elongation index, aggregation index, the amplitude and total extent of aggregation, the half time, plasma viscosity), 
- biochemical parameters (fibrinogen, reticulocytes count, glutathione, acethylcholinesterase, glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase, nitric oxide).
Subjects will be tested on the BioSway balance platform (Biodex) prior to the study and five months thereafter.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Boiethics Commision at the Regional Medical Chamber in Krakow</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ul. Krupnicza 11a
31-123 Krakow</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Nr 24 /KBL/OIL/2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371994-Komisja bioetyczna 1.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371994-komisja bioetyczna 2.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katarzyna Filar-Mierzwa</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education
Department of Occupational Therapy
al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48126831102</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katarzyna.filar@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katarzyna Filar-Mierzwa</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education
Department of Occupational Therapy
al. Jana Pawla II 78 
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48126831102</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katarzyna.filar@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katarzyna Filar-Mierzwa</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education
Department of Occupational Therapy
al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48126831102</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katarzyna.filar@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katarzyna Filar-Mierzwa</name>
      <address>al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48126831102</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>