<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363254">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001225808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of calcium to improve fertilisation in patients with previous poor fertilisation or failed fertilisation and in patients with poor sperm quality.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of oocyte activation using a calcium ionophore on fertilisation and clinical pregnancy rate following intra-cytoplasmic sperm injection (ICSI) in patients with previous poor fertilisation or failed fertilisation and for patients with severe male factor infertility.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-8947</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infertile patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>GM508 Cult-Active- oocytes are placed into the 1.0% calcium ionophore (GM508 Cult-Active) for 15 mins following ICSI. The oocytes are then removed, washed in our normal culture media and returned to the culture drops as per PIVET protocol. Patients may opt to have this treatment as many times as they want</interventions>
    <comparator>The patients previous IVF/ICSI cycle in which the calcium ionophore had not been used. i.e the patient who is been treated with the calcium ionophore's previous cycle where fertilisation was reduced.

This cycle will more than likely be within 6 months of the calcium ionophore treatment cycle</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% Clinical pregnancy rate. We have an internal data base that will calculate: the rate of number of clinical pregnancies (presence of a heartbeat at 7 week ultrasound scan)/ number of embryo transfers</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% Fertilisation rate. We have an internal data base that will calculate: the number of two pronuclear oocytes/the number of oocytes injected with sperm</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% Blastocyst rate:We have an internal data base that will calculate: Number of blastocysts formed on Day 5 and/or Day 6/the number of two pronuclear oocytes</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% Live Birth: Number of live babies born/number of embryo transfers</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants will be patients of PIVET Medical Centre and under the clinical management of one or more of the Fertility Specialists who work at PIVET. No outside patients will be involved in this study. Eligible patients must have had previous complete failed fertilisation, reduced fertilisation (&lt;50%)  or have severe male factor infertility (Sperm concentration &lt; 2 x 106 million/ml, Sperm motility &lt; 5%
Strict criteria normal morphology &lt; 4%). Patients with surgically collected sperm (epididymal collected sperm or testicular collected sperm) will also be included</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any patients that has had fertilisation rate of greater than 50% in a previous cycle will be excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients must have had previous complete failed fertilisation, reduced fertilisation (&lt;50%)  or have severe male factor infertility. Patients with surgically collected sperm (epididymal collected sperm or testicular collected sperm) will also be included. Patients will be consulted by their Clinician on the benefits and risks of calcium ionophore usage. They will be given an information sheet and consent. They will need to read this information sheet. Patients will have the opportunity to discuss and ask any questions or raise any concerns about the ionophore for a second time at their routine embryologist consult before the egg collection. When or if they decide to use the ionophore, they can sign the consent. No calcium ionophore treatment will be given without a signed, witnessed consent in the patient file.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>PIVET Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>166-168 Cambridge St Leederville WA 6007</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PIVET Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>166-168 Cambridge St Leederville WA 6007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Oocyte activation is characterised by a dramatic increase in intracellular calcium concentration followed by short high frequency calcium oscillations. This is triggered when the spermatozoa penetrates the egg. Without this calcium influx the oocyte will fail to fertilise.

Many studies have shown that the fertilsation rate can be improved as well as embryo development and consequent implantation rates, by mimicking the physiological cell-signalling mechanism using an activation agent such as a calcium ionophore. 

We wish to use a commercially avaliable calcium ionophore, GM508 Cult-Active, supplied by Gynemed Germany to study this effect on our patients who have undergone a complete failed fertilization cycle or a reduced fertilzation cycle (&lt; 50% of oocytes injected) or where severe male factor infertility is evident.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jason Conceicao</name>
      <address>166-168 Cambridge St Leederville WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+61 (08)9422 5400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jconceicao@pivet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jason Conceicao</name>
      <address>166-168 Cambridge St Leederville WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+61 (08)9422 5400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jconceicao@pivet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jason Conceicao</name>
      <address>166-168 Cambridge St Leederville WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+61 (08)9422 5400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jconceicao@pivet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>