<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368234">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000014459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating the neurobiological and neurocognitive effects of repeated sessions of transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) in schizophrenia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating the neurobiological and neurocognitive effects of repeated sessions of tDCS and itDCS in schizophrenia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1168-6162</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will undergo repeated sessions (5 in total) of Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS). tDCS involves the application of a very gentle electrical current applied using two surface electrodes (anode and cathode) to the scalp . tDCS has been shown to increase brain activity in areas important for cognition.
Participants will be randomly allocated to one of the following three conditions;
1.	 Five sessions of 20 minute active tDCS to the left Dorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex (DLPFC) at a current density of 0.0057 ma/cm within a single week on consecutive days.

2.	Five sessions of 20 minute active itDCS to the left DLPFC at a current density of 0.0057 ma/cm within a single week on consecutive days.

3.	Five sessions of 20 minute sham tDCS to the left DLPFC at a current density of 0.0057 ma/cm within a single week on consecutive days.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Stimulation will be delivered using the StarStim system which allows for programming of tDCS, itDCS and sham.

Sham tDCS is achieved by switching off stimulation after approx. 30s; which occurs within the software of the Starstim system allowing for administrator and patient blinding. There is no evidence that 30 seconds of tDCS induces any changes in the brain. The provision of stimulation for 30 seconds allows participants to experience the initial physical sensations of tDCS, which typically fade after 30seconds, thus providing a robust sham.  This is a standard method of blinding for tDCS.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MATRICS Consensus battery
 The MATRICS battery was developed by a panel of experts to measure the most commonly impaired skills in patients with SCZ, it is a multi-domain cognitive battery specifically designed for repeated use. We will be assessing the domains of speed of processing, attention, verbal learning, working memory, visual learning, reasoning, and problem solving. Although all of these domains are measured separately by the MATRICS, it also allows for a Global Cognition score to be calculated. 

This is a composite primary outcome. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Endpoint (i.e. pre and post 5 sessions of tDCS stimulation) and One Month Follow Up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>TMS-EEG data.
TMS-EEG is performed by stimulating the scalp over the DLPFC while simultaneously recording brain activity via surrounding EEG electrodes. The TMS pulse produces a neurophysiological response in the underlying cortex, referred to as a TMS evoked potential (TEP), which is recorded on EEG and the TEP amplitude gives an index of cortical excitability. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Endpoint (i.e. pre and post 5 sessions of tDCS)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	competent to consent based on their ability to provide a spontaneous narrative description of the key elements of the study, as assessed by a clinical staff member independent of the research project
-	have a diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder as confirmed by the MINI
-	are between the ages of 18 and 60
- have been on a stable dose of medication for at least 4 weeks</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	have a DSM-IV history of substance abuse or dependence in the last 6 months
-	have a concomitant major and unstable medical or neurological illness
-	are pregnant
-	are currently taking any medication shown to interfere with the effects of tDCS; namely benzodiazepines or tegretol. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed; by the research assistant contacting the principal investigator who has a computer generated random sequence for treatment groups after the participant is deemed eligible and has consented for the study. 






</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data Analysis: Neurocognitive data will be analysed using linear mixed-effects modeling (participant as random effect) of the group x time interaction. If a significant interaction between stimulation type and time is observed, post-hoc between-group comparisons of the change will occur. The dependent variables will be the MATRICS (H1: Global Cognition Score, H2: Domain Scores). Neurobiological data will again be conducted using linear mixed-effects modeling as described above. Dependent variables will be TEPs, coherence at rest and during the cognitive task. Finally, to assist our understanding of how changes in functional connectivity are associated with the observed changes in cognitive performance, changes in EEG coherence will be correlated with changes in MATRICS scores. In all cases, p-values &lt;0.05 will be considered significant.

Power Analysis:  The study is powered to detect a significant difference in the cognitive outcome measure, i.e. MATRICS Global Cognition Score. Our pilot data showed that single session tDCS had a moderate effect size on cognition (Cohens d = 0.50-0.56). Therefore, in the  proposed study we are  predicting that repeated sessions of  tDCS will result in a moderate to large effect size (d = 0.70); using this effect size a sample of 60 will provide greater than 80% power with an alpha of 0.05 in a Repeated Measures ANOVA. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kate Hoy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>MAPrc,
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road,
Melbourne,
3004,
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council, RD Wright Biomedical Career Development Fellowship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash University
Victoria 3800
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash University
Victoria 3800
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with schizophrenia can experience difficulties with attention, concentration and memory; these are referred to as cognitive symptoms.  There are currently no effective treatments for these symptoms. We are investigating whether non-invasive brain stimulation, specifically transcranial Direct Current Stimulation (tDCS), is able to improve cognition in individuals with schizophrenia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004,</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>528/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>MAPrc,
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne,
3004
VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>MAPrc,
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne,
3004
VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>MAPrc,
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne,
3004
VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kirsten Gainsford</name>
      <address>MAPrc,
Level 4,
607 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne,
3004
VIC</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 6592</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kirsten.gainsford@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>