<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343310">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000836932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of a colour coded HbA1c-recording graph in improving diabetes control in people with type 2 diabetes: A randomized control trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of colour coded HbA1c recording graph in improving diabetes control as compare to HbA1c recording table in patient with type 2 diabetes: A randomized control trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>diabetes mellitus control</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>education about the diabetes control</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A graph measured 12 x 13cm with 7 points on the y- axis and 6 points on the x- axis was printed on a ivory white card measured 21cmx24cm. The graph was divided horizontally into green, yellow, red and black area, represented good, can be improved, high and too high HbA1c level respectively. The card was covered with a blue colour paper printed with title HbA1c Card  and the researcher name plus the phone number.

The HbA1c result was plotted on the graph at the corresponding follow up duration (x-axis) and trend were exhibited by drawing a line between the results.

The patient in the HbA1c recording graph group will received the card at the recruitment day. They will keep the card and bring it during the follow up day. The researcher will update the HbA1c reading on the card on each visit . A standardized explanation on the HbA1c result was given to each participant(e.g. the HbA1c result is normal or high and the HbA1c result had improved or worsen)

The patient will be seen at 3- month and  6-month. So the total duration of follow up was 6 months.

At the end of the study, the patient will keep the card.</interventions>
    <comparator>A table measured 11cm x 11cm with 3 columns and 7 rows was printed on a ivory white card measured 21cmx24cm.The card was covered with a blue colour paper printed with title HbA1c Card  and the researcher name plus the phone number.

The tool used in the control arm were adapted from the diabetes passport used by the Malaysian Ministry of Health . The dates and HbA1c results were recorded in numerical form in the corresponding row.


The patient in the HbA1c recording table group will received the card at the recruitment day. They will keep the card and bring it during the follow up day. The researcher will update the HbA1c reading on the card on each visit .

 A standardized explanation on the HbA1c result was given to each participant(e.g. the HbA1c result is normal or high and the HbA1c result had improved or worsen)

The patient will be seen at 3- month and  6-month. So the total duration of follow up was 6 months.

At the end of the study, the patient will keep the card.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>evaluate the effectiveness of colour coded HbA1c recording- graph in improving diabetes control as compared to HbA1c-recording table.

the effectiveness was assessed by using the mean improvement in the HbA1c result at 6-month comparing the HbA1c recording graph group and the HbA1c recording table group.

The result was analyzed using the student-t test</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 month</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pairwise difference in the mean changes in HbA1c result within the group over time (Compared mean HbA1c result at baseline, 3 month and 6 month follow up visit).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The magnitude of improvement in the mean HbA1c knowledge score between the groups at 3- month follow up visit.

THe Hba1c knowledge was assessed using the questionnaire. It comprised of three questions:
1)Do you know about HbA1c?
2)From your understading,HbA1c level represents the control over how long?
3)In your opinion, the normal HbA1c level is less than__________________

After the assessment, patients were grouped into: do not understand HbA1c, partial understanding and good understanding on HbA1c.

Patients were classified as 
1)Do not understand. HbA1c if they answered" no" for question no 1 above.
2)Partial understanding. implies correct answer was given for duration of control or for the target level of HbA1c. 
3)Good understanding. implies correct answers were given for both the duration of control and the target level of HbA1c.

"Three months duration" was accepted as the correct answer for duration of control.
 
Hba1c level of either 6.5% or 7% were accepted as the correct answer for level of HbA1c. The reason for having two correct answers for target HbA1c was:
HbA1c target level of 6.5% was the target level stated in the recent Malaysian practice guideline. The target HbA1c was recently changed 7.0% to 6.5%. After reviewing the evidence available, I had put the target level at 7.0%. As such HbA1c value of 7.0% or 6.5% was taken as the correct answer for target HbA1c level.

Those who answered the two questions correctly will score "two" marks.The score was is "one" if they only answered one question correctly or zero if all the answers was wrong.

The same set of questionnaires was administrated twice to score the participant knowledge, first time during the recruitment and second time during the 3- month follow up.

the mean of improvement in the score was 
 obtained and the result was analysed using the paired t-test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>patients diagnosed with type 2 diabetes for at least 1 year; recent HbA1c result &gt; 7.0%; and can read and comprehend numbers.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with disabilities and  debilitating illness( e.g. cancer, severe heart failure, end stage renal failure, blindness, colour blind, major psychiatric illness, dementia, stroke which affects the cognitive function, tetraplegia.) or on any medications that might interfere with the sugar control, such as corticosteroid, were excluded from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment
Written invitation were given to the diabetes patients who had HbA1c level &gt;7%. Patient who were willing to participate would be screened. A written consent was taken from those who fulfill the research criteria.

Randomization
Patients who consented to participate were then randomized using the thick envelope method in blocks .The sequence was generated by a research assistant who was not involved in the recruitment and implementation process. Thick envelopes were then numbered in ascending order according to the sequence generated. Allocation was carried out according to the number in ascending order. Both the researcher and patient were blinded until the intervention was assigned.</concealment>
    <sequence>thick envelope method</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>kuala lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Malaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Lembah Pantai,
59100 Kuala Lumpur,
Malaysia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Malaya</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lembah Pantai,
59100 Kuala Lumpur,
Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This was a randomized control trial carried out in the primary care clinic in University Malaya Medical Centre, Malaysia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>The study was presented during the thesis defense for master candidate</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lembah Pantai,
59100 Kuala Lumpur,
Malaysia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/02/0691</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stalia Wong Siew Lee</name>
      <address>Primary Care Department,
University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai,
59100 Kuala Lumpur.</address>
      <phone>600123271517</phone>
      <fax>Malaysia</fax>
      <email>staliawong@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>STALIA WONG SIEW LEE</name>
      <address>Primary Care Department,
University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai,
59100 Kuala Lumpur.</address>
      <phone>600123271517</phone>
      <fax>Malaysia</fax>
      <email>staliawong@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stalia Wong Siew Lee</name>
      <address>Primary Care Department,
University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai,
59100 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>600123271517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>staliawong@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>