<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372844">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000655347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dynamic and static functional imaging and morphological imaging in Neuroendocrine Tumour (NET) with known liver metastases.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot project to assess liver metastases by comparing novel, dynamic and static functional imaging, and also morphological imaging with standard of care in WHO Grade I and Grade II Neuroendocrine Tumour (NET).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neuroendocrine Tumour (NET)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Liver metastases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neuroendocrine tumour (NET)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant will receive a Ga-68-DOTATATE PET/MR and PET/CT Scan at Herston Imaging Research Facility (HIRF) on the same day.  

Initial PET-MRI Scan
After emptying your bladder, a qualified Nuclear Medicine Technologist will ask you to lie on the scanner bed. They will insert a tube into your vein and inject a radioactive substance called Ga-68-DOTATATE as well as a special dye called contrast.  
The scan involves lying flat with knees supported and arms resting by your side. You will be scanned from the top of your head to the middle of your thighs.  The scan time for the PET-MRI will be approximately 45 minutes. During this time the MR part of the scanner will make buzzing or knocking noises as it generates different kinds of images.

PET-CT Scan
You will be asked empty your bladder again and walk to the PET-CT scanner in the room next door. The PET-CT scan involves lying flat and takes approximately 30 minutes to scan you from the top of your head to the middle of your thighs. 

Final PET-MRI Scan
After the PET-CT Scan, you will be asked to walk back to the PET-MRI scanner where a final PET-MRI will be performed. This scan will not require any further injections. This scan will go from the top of your head to the middle of your thighs and should take approximately 30 minutes. This scan is performed to directly compare the PET-CT images to the PET-MRI images. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison of attenuation correction between the MR and CT mu maps will be performed qualitatively via Nuclear Medicine physician and quantitatively via image analysis. 

CT attenuation will be considered the gold standard with MR attenuation map compared with it. The comparison will documented as following grading
Grade 1  no difference
Grade 2  MR reconstruction suboptimal
Grade 3- MR reconstruction cant delineate the lesion 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Accuracy of DOTATATE PET/MR imaging compared to the current gold standard of DOTATATE PET/CT in the detection of liver metastases in patients with NETs, graded as follows:
Grade 1  no difference
Grade 2  MR reconstruction suboptimal
Grade 3- MR reconstruction cant delineate the lesion</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of CT attenuation map to those created by MRI.
Graded by radiologists as follows:
Grade 1  no difference
Grade 2  MR reconstruction suboptimal
Grade 3- MR reconstruction cant delineate the lesion</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dosimetry over kidneys and liver lesions will be calculated. If a decision is made to proceed to Lutetium-177-DOTATATE radionuclide therapy, current dosimetry will be compared with dosimetry calculated during Lutetium-177-DOTATATE therapy to see if MRI can more accurately assess the renal dose for targeted radionuclide therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Histologically proven WHO Grade I (defined as slowly proliferating tumors, measured on histology by a marker Ki-67 with value of &lt;3%) to WHO Grade II (Ki-67 3-20%) NET with known liver metastases
2. Clinically requires Ga-68-DOTATATE PET-CT scan
3. Liver metastases on diagnostic CT
4. Written informed consent
5. All women of childbearing age must have a pregnancy test before enrolment
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnant or breastfeeding
2. Life expectancy less than 6 months
3. Previously known non-Ga-DOTATATE avid disease. 
4. Contraindication to MRI
5. Severe claustrophobia
6. Known renal impairment
7. Hypersensitivity to Primovist
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Metro North Hospital and Health Service
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston Queensland 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Birsbane and Women's Hospital, Herston Imaging Research Facility Seed Funding</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Metro North Hospital and Health Service
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston Queensland 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to compare the accuracy of novel, dynamic and static functional imaging, and also morphological imaging, with standard of care imaging for the detection of liver metastases in patients with neuroendocrine tumour (NET).

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with histologically proven WHO Grade I or Grade II NET with known liver metastases.

Study details
All participants in this study will receive three scans on a single day: an initial PET-MRI Scan, followed by a PET-CT Scan, and then a final PET-MRI Scan. For the initial PET-MRI scan a qualified Nuclear Medicine Technologist will ask you to lie on the scanner bed. They will insert a tube into your vein and inject a radioactive substance called Ga-68-DOTATATE as well as a special dye called contrast. The scan involves lying flat with knees supported and arms resting by your side. You will be scanned from the top of your head to the middle of your thighs. The scan time for the PET-MRI will be approximately 45 minutes. The PET-CT scan involves lying flat and takes approximately 30 minutes to scan you from the top of your head to the middle of your thighs. The final PET-MRI scan will not require any further injections. This scan will go from the top of your head to the middle of your thighs and should take approximately 30 minutes. This scan is performed to directly compare the PET-CT images to the PET-MRI images.

The images generated will be independently reviewed by trained Nuclear Medicine physicians partaking in the study to count the number of liver metastases.
It is hoped that additional dynamic PET may further increase the sensitivity of detecting liver metastases. This may potentially influence treatment options in individual patients, including possibly avoiding futile surgery in patients with more extensive disease burden than detected on current standard imaging
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital 
Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 7 Block 7
Herston Road Herston Queensland 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/QRBW/52</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Manoj Bhatt</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Department of Nuclear Medicine
Level 3 Ned Hanlon Building
Herston Road Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>manoj.bhatt@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Manoj Bhatt</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Department of Nuclear Medicine
Level 3 Ned Hanlon Building
Herston Road Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>manoj.bhatt@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Manoj Bhatt</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Department of Nuclear Medicine
Level 3 Ned Hanlon Building
Herston Road Herston Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>manoj.bhatt@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>