<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370434">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000426482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>SMARTphone-based, early cardiac REHABilitation in patients with acute coronary syndromes: A Randomized Controlled Trial Protocol [SMART-REHAB Trial]</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>SMARTphone-based, early cardiac REHABilitation in patients with acute coronary syndromes: A Randomized Controlled Trial Protocol [SMART-REHAB Trial]</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-4032</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SMART-REHAB Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Heart Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Myocardial Infarction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The smartphone-based secondary prevention program will be delivered over 8 weeks starting at time of discharge from hospital through a smartphone application (app). This is a multi-faceted intervention with particular emphasis on early mobilization. The app provides a platform to deliver a comprehensive secondary prevention program. The different components of the program are: 

1. Exercise Prescription - Patients will have access to real-time feedback of their activity levels through the apps activity tracker which links to the smartphones accelerometer feature. Patients will be able to monitor the number of steps taken and the distance walked.  Patients will undertake a graded walking program increasing in time and intensity over the 8 weeks.  Patients will increase their daily steps by 1,000steps a week until they reach 10,000 steps. 
2. Dynamic tracking of cardiovascular risk factors - Patients will have an interactive personal dashboard highlighting the status of their cardiovascular risk factors. Blood pressure, cholesterol levels, glucose levels, weight, smoking status will be graded depending whether they are at recommended target levels.
3. Dietary Habits - Dietary habits will be tracked through the app via access to the phones inbuilt camera. Patients will be encouraged to photograph the food they consume.
4. Cardiac Education - Two educational messages per week will be delivered to the participants as they progress through the 8-week SSPP. 
5. Cardiac Medication List - Patients will input their discharge medications into the app prior to leaving hospital. The medication list will be reviewed to ensure that appropriate evidence-based pharmacotherapy (dual antiplatelet therapy, statin, angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor/angiotensin receptor blocker, beta-blocker) has been prescribed.
6. Interactive and Personalized Feedback -Patients will receive five personalized messages per week via the app messaging service. Two of the messages will be educational and the remaining three messages provide goal setting feedback on physical activity levels and diet. 
7. Support - The messaging service also allows the patient to initiate contact if they have any questions regarding their cardiac condition or rehabilitation process. 

Adherence will be measure by number of times a patient logs into app. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control group is assigned to usual post-discharge acute coronary syndrome care which includes traditional cardiac rehabilitation</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in exercise capacity as measure by change in six-minute walk test distance from baseline to 8-week assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in BP measured by digital sphygmomanometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in total cholesterol measured by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in weight measure on scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Change in waist circumference measured by tape measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking status assessed by self-report.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to secondary prevention pharmacotherapy by pill-count on drug packet.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major adverse cardiovascular events (combination of death, mortality, stroke and unplanned revascularisation) verified by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression assessed by the cardiac depression scale and depression scale-short form</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety assessed by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in quality of life assessed by SF-36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of adjusted life years as calculated by EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital readmissions verified by medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in LDL-cholesterol measured by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in HDL-cholesterol measured by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in triglycerides as measured by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8-weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Acute coronary syndromes with documented coronary artery disease
Smartphone ownership 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Untreated ventricular tachycardia
* Severe heart failure
* Significant residual coronary artery disease requiring revascularisation
* treatment with coronary artery bypass surgery
* life-threatening coexisting disease with life-expectancy less than 1 year
* significant exercise limitations for reasons other than CHD.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients will be randomized in a 1:1 fashion to smartphone based secondary prevention program or usual care through a computerized randomization program. Randomization will be stratified by study site and be overseen by the Centre of Cardiovascular Research and Education in Therapeutics; an independent research body within the School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine at Monash University (Melbourne, Australia). Assessors of the primary outcomes are blind to treatment allocation; however participants are not blinded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation stratified by study site.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We calculate a sample size of 152 participants (76 per group) will be required to detect a minimal clinically important difference of 25 metres for the six-minute walk test in patients with ACS with 80% power at 5% level of significance. This is based on a mean (SD) six-minute walk test distance of 480 (104). Accounting for 20% loss to follow-up rate we will aim to recruit 100 patients in each arm.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong Hospital campus - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Heart Foundation of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 12/500 Collins Street 
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Cardiac Clinical Network</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 20, 50 Lonsdale Street
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim

The aim of this trial is to assess the impact of a smartphone-based secondary prevention program, initiated on discharge in patients with acute coronary syndromes, on exercise capacity, cardiovascular risk factors, quality of life and mood. 

Hypothesis
The primary hypothesis is that a smartphone-based secondary prevention program would improve exercise capacity, as measure by a 6-minute walk test, compared to standard care. Secondary hypotheses are: A smartphone-based secondary prevention program will result in earlier return to work and improvement in cardiac depression and quality of life scores.  It is also hypothesized that there will an improvements in cardiovascular risk factors (lipid profile, blood pressure, HbA1C, anthropometry) and secondary prevention pharmacotherapy use between the groups.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Road
PO BOX 5555 
Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/Austin/128</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matias Yudi</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Cardiology Department
145 Studley Road
PO BOX 5555
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matias.yudi@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matias Yudi</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Cardiology Department
145 Studley Road
PO BOX 5555
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matias.yudi@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matias Yudi</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Cardiology Department
145 Studley Road
PO BOX 5555
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matias.yudi@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matias Yudi</name>
      <address>145 Studley Road
PO BOX 5555
Heidelberg, VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matias.yudi@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>