<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83923">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000389202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Depression in Epilespy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the effectiveness of Cognitive Behavioural Therapy to improve quality of life and mood in people with epilepsy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Milena Gandy</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epilepsy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of Life</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>If participants agree to take part in this study they will be randomly allocated to one of two conditions, an immediate treatment condition or a waitlist control. The immediate treatment condition involves a detailed assessment of psychological functioning and 8 weeks of individual psychological treatment based on cognitive behavioural therapy principles. This program is specific to improving quality of life and mood in the context of epilepsy. Each weekly treatment session lasts 50 mins. Therapy will include the following elements; completion of weekly seizures &amp; trigger diaries; education about epilepsy and its affects on quality of life, goal-setting; the role and management of lifestyle factors, sleep, alcohol, exercise, diet; implementation of lifestyle management plan, management of ictal / post-ictal mood symptoms; behavioural aspects of mood impairment: role of pleasant events and avoidance; implementation of behavioural management of mood strategies; cognitive aspects of mood impairment: identifying unhelpful thoughts. Behavioural aspects of mood impairment: graded exposure; monitoring unhelpful thoughts with mood diary; cognitive aspects of mood impairment: challenging unhelpful thoughts; challenging unhelpful thoughts with mood diary. Implementation of graded exposure; social aspects of living with epilepsy: talking with others and assertiveness; talking to key others about change to management of epilepsy; relapse prevention strategies; development and practice of relapse prevention strategies; and review and re-setting of goals for future.</interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control. They will be offered treatment 4 months following the immediate control condition</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive sympotmolgy. This will be measure using the Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale (HADS; Zigmond &amp; Snaith, 1983) 14 item self-report measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (assessment session) at post treatment (final therapy session) then 3 and 6 months post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Neurological Depressive Disorders Inventory NDDI-E (Gilliam et al., 2006). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (assessment session) at post treatment (final therapy session) then 3 months post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life. This will be measured using the Quality of Life Inventory in Epilepsy 31 item (Cramer et al., 1998).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment (assessment session) at post treatment (final therapy session) then 3 and 6 months post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People with Epilepsy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>About to undergo major surgery or significant change to medication 
Significantly impaired cognitive functioning 
psychosis
inability to speak English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible participants were provided with an information and consent form.  Those who consented completed the battery of baseline measures.  Following completion of baseline measures, participants were randomly allocated to treatment condition.  A list of random numbers using the Bernoulli function was generated by an independent researcher who was not involved in the treatment or assessment of the participants.  The set of random numbers was consecutively assigned to each new participant.  Random allocation was concealed until after participants had completed the baseline data. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/01/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>21/12/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>8 East Neurology,
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown 
NSW
2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Psychology Clinic The Univerisy</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Psychology Clinic 
Transient Building F12
Camperdown
2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The effectiveness of psychological treatments for depression in People with epilepsy (PWE) is currently unknown, although there are some encouraging results to suggest that Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) might have a useful role (Ramarantnam, Baker, &amp; Goldstein, 2008).  This study aims to assess the effectiveness of a CBT intervention to improve Quality of Life (QoL) and mood in people with epilepsy.  This study will be the first to help us to assess the effectiveness of CBT interventions in an Australian sample to improve quality of life and mood in PWE. In addition, it will help us to develop an understanding of two important additional questions: do particular sub-groups benefit more than others from CBT and what are the mechanisms of treatment change? The costs of depression in epilepsy are high both for the individuals concerned, in terms of quality of life and seizure activity, but also for society due to greater economic and health care costs in those with untreated depression and epilepsy (Cramer, Blum, Fanning, &amp; Reed, 2004).  Neurologists report that they tend not to screen for depression due to lack of available resources for its treatment (Gilliam et al., 2004), and so the development of an effective and available local service may increase the overall rates of detection and treatment in this group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>28/05/2013. Title Presentation:  Depression In Epilepsy: Clinical Applications presented at the annual Psychologist Network Training Day for the Sydney and South Western Sydney Local Health Districts Area.
04/07/2013. Title Presentation: The Identification, Prediction and Management of Depression in People with Epilepsy at the Royal Prince Alfred Hospital.
21/11/2012. Presentation Title: A randomized controlled trial of Cognitive Behavioural Therapy to improve depression in adults with epilepsy at The Fifth Annual Sydney Postgraduate Psychology Conference.
01/09/2012. Presented the results of my PhD randomized controlled trial of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy to Improve Depression in Adults with Epilepsy at Psychotherapy &amp; Neuroscience: Evidence &amp; Challenges for CBT: 42nd European Association of Behavioral and Cognitive Therapy Switzerland. 
11/2011. Presented Preliminary findings of my PhD The Identification, Prediction and Management of Depression in People with Epilepsy at Fourth Annual Sydney Postgraduate Psychology Conference
24/11/2010. Presentation Presented the rationale and methodological plans for my PhD research The Third Annual Sydney Postgraduate Psychology Conference

Publications:
Gandy, M., Sharpe, L., Nicholson Perry, K., (2013). Cognitive behavior therapy for depression in people with epilepsy: a systematic review. Epilepsia, 54(10) 1725-34.
Gandy, M., Sharpe, L., Nicholson Perry, K., Miller, L., Thayer, Z., Boserio, J., et al. (2013). The psychosocial predictors of depression and suicidality in people with epilepsy. Journal of Psychosomatic Research, 74(3) 227-232.
Gandy, M., Sharpe, L., Nicholson Perry, K, Miller, L., Thayer, Z., Boserio, J., et al. (2013). Rates of DSM-IV mood, anxiety disorders and suicidality in Australian adult epilepsy outpatients: A comparison of well-controlled versus refractory epilepsy. Epilepsy &amp; Behaviour, 26(1), 29-53.
Gandy, M., Sharpe, L., Nicholson Perry, K., Miller, L, Thayer, Z, Boserio, J.et al. (2012). Assessing the efficacy of 2 screening measures for depression in people with epilepsy. Neurology, 79(4), 371-375.
Gandy, M., Sharpe, L., &amp; Nicholson Perry, K. (2012). Psychosocial predictors of depression and anxiety in patients with epilepsy: A systematic review. Journal of Affective Disorders, 140(3), 222-232.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)  X09-0155 &amp; HREC/09/RPAH/247  Ratified by Sydney University Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/RPAH/247</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Milena Gandy</name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health
eCentreClinic,
Department of Psychology, 
Macquarie University NSW 2109.</address>
      <phone>+61  298504152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>milena.gandy@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Milena Gandy</name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health
eCentreClinic,
Department of Psychology, 
Macquarie University NSW 2109.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98504152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>milena.gandy@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Milena Gandy</name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health
eCentreClinic,
Department of Psychology, 
Macquarie University NSW 2109.</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 98504152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>milena.gandy@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>