<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373034">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001050347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of  nerve blocks applied for preventing muscle contractions in bladder tumor surgeries</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of classic and inguinal obturator nerve blocks applied for preventing adductor muscle contractions in bladder tumor surgeries: A prospective randomized trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>bladder tumor</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>adductor muscle contractions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bladder</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Before surgery, 500 mL intravenous 0.9% NaCl is administered to the patients. Heart rate, SpO2, blood pressure, and electrocardiography are monitored in the operating room. Spinal anesthesia is performed using 12.5 mg hyperbaric bupivacaine after insertion of a 25-gauge Quincke spinal needle from L3-4 or L4-5  in the sitting position. Patients are laid in the supine position. Development of sensory block is examined at the T10 level. 

Required anatomic markings were made on the wall where the tumor was located  by the approach to be applied:
In the classic method, the puncture point is marked 1.5 cm lateral of tuberculum pubis and 1.5 cm caudal.
In the inguinal method, the tuberculum pubis, spina iliaca anterior superior, inguinal ligament, and femoral artery are marked. The puncture entry point is determined as the middle of the tuberculum pubis and femoral artery, and 5-8 cm below the inguinal ligament.
Obturator nerve block (ONB) has been performed in surgeries of transurethral resection of bladder tumors (TUR-BT) for the prevention of the development of obturator muscle contraction. Currently, classic and inguinal approaches are frequently being used. 

Patients are randomized for classic (n=33) and inguinal (n=33) ONBs.  Simple randomization is done before study commencement by the Excel (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA) random number generation function. Adductor muscle contractions that occurred during the resection are recorded by a urologist who is blinded to the ONB technique. 

The peripheral nerve stimulator (Pajunk, Melsungen, Germany) is adjusted to 1.5 mA 1 Hz. Insertion is applied from the determined points using an isolated 22-gauge, 100-mm nerve stimulator needle (Pajunk, Melsungen, Germany). The needle is directed cephalad in the inguinal approach. In the classic method, the needle is perpendicularly inserted and slightly withdrawn after reaching the bone; the needle is manipulated 2-4 cm towards the medial. First, suction is performed, and then ten mL 0.25% bupivacaine are administered when an adductor muscle contraction area is detected with the peripheral nerve stimulator between the range of 0.4-0.7 mA.
All ONB and TUR-BT procedures are performed by the same anesthesiologists and urologists.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison of classic and inguinal obturator nerve blocks  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The success rate of classic and inguinal Obturator nerve block approaches will be compared by review of surgical records. (ONB is recorded as ineffective if adductor muscle contractions occurred during the resection.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant is assessed in at the end of the ONB procedure.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The performance speed (The duration of the determination of the obturator nerve) of classic and inguinal Obturator nerve block approaches will be compared by stopwatch timing of procedure by the research assistant. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant is assessed in at the end of the ONB procedure.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> The complication risks, such as hematoma or sensory/motor neuronal deficit, of classic and inguinal Obturator nerve block approaches are compared by review of surgical records.
(Vein injuries, hematoma, and complications such as neurologic problems are evaluated during the procedure and 24 hours after the surgery)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant is assessed during 24 hours when the ONB procedure is completed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who have lateral wall bladder tumor and will be performed the Transurethral resection of bladder tumors (TUR-BT) under spinal anesthesia.
Patients who are American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) risk grade I-III and aged between 18-80 years are included in the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who had undergone previous surgery in the study region and had anatomic disorders, neurologic problems, muscle disease, and coagulation disorders are excluded.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Simple randomization is done before study commencement by the Excel (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA) random number generation function. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by
computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) 23.0 (IBM SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) is used in data analysis. The Chi-square test is used in the comparison of qualitative data in addition to descriptive statistical methods (frequency, percentage, mean, standard deviation). The Kolmogorov-Smirnov and Shapiro-Wilk tests are used in the evaluation of normally distributed data. The independent samples t-test was used to evaluate normally distributed quantitative data, and the Mann-Whitney U test is used in the evaluation of data with no normal distribution. Correlations of variables are evaluated using Pearsons correlation tests. Probability values less than (P) a=0.05 are regarded as significant and indicating a difference between the groups. Power analysis was performed the G*Power 3.1.9.2 Statistical Package Program; and power (1-ß) is found as 0.90 considering n1=33, n2=33, a=0.05, and effect size as d=0.8.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Kirsehir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Recai Dagli</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ahi Evran University Faculty of Medicine,  Bagbasi Mahallesi, Sht. Sahir Kurutluoglu Cd., 40100 Kirsehir, Turkey.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ahi Evran University Training and Research Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ahi Evran University Training and Research Hospital, 40100, Kirsehir</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim: Obturator nerve block (ONB) has been performed in surgeries of transurethral resection of bladder tumors (TUR-BT) for the prevention of the development of obturator muscle contraction. Currently, classic and inguinal approaches are frequently being used. In the present study, we aimed to compare the success rate, performance speed, and complication risks of both approaches. 
Method: Sixty-six patients who underwent TUR-BT under spinal anesthesia are randomly selected, and ONB is performed on the tumor location side using classic (n=33) or inguinal (n=33) approaches. Ten milliliters of 0.25% bupivacaine are administered using a peripheral nerve stimulator in both approaches. The duration of the determination of the obturator nerve, number of interventions, development of contractions, and complications are recorded.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>the Clinical Research Ethics Committee of Turgut Ozal University Faculty of Medicine</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>99950669/104</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Recai Dagli</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation, Ahi Evran University Faculty of Medicine, Bagbasi Campus, 40100, Kirsehir, Turkey, </address>
      <phone>+905426536975</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drresel@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Sahin Bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Ahi Evran University Faculty of Medicine, Bagbasi Campus, 40100, Kirsehir, Turkey, </address>
      <phone>+905054450075</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahiin1980@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Levent Emir</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Ahi Evran University Faculty of Medicine, Bagbasi Campus, 40100, Kirsehir, Turkey, </address>
      <phone>+905054579050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lemir2005@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>