<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365652">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000208606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Integrated community case management (iCCM) of pneumonia, malaria and diarrhea among children under 5years in Homabay County, Kenya</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of integrated community case management of pneumonia, malaria and diarrhea in sick children under 5 years in Homabay County, Kenya</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1152-2805</utrn>
    <trialacronym>HBICCM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pneumonia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>malaria</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>diarrhoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention that will be carried out in this research is integrated community case management (iCCM) of pneumonia, malaria and diarrhoea. However, because zinc and Oral Rehydration Solution (ORS), Rapid Diagnostic Test (RDTs) and anti-malarials have been ratified for use in the community by the Kenya Ministry of health, our focus shall be on pneumonia home case management primarily and on diarrhoea secondarily.  Community Health Workers (CHWs) will be trained to diagnose and treat these three ailments as described below
1. Giving antibiotic to a child with fast breathing and or chest indrawing 
2. Giving an antimalarial to a child with a positive RDT 
3. Giving Oral Rehydration Solution (ORS) and Zinc to a child with diarrhea 

Training of community health workers 
The CHWs will be trained to classify and treat children with diarrhoea, pneumonia or malaria and also manage stock of appropriate drugs and supplies. The CHWs will also be trained to perform RDTs for malaria diagnosis. They will also require skills to be able to accurately complete the relevant registers and data collection forms as well as counseling of caregivers and general health education. The training will last for 6 days. The training manual that will be used has already been developed by the Kenya iCCM taskforce. This manual was adapted from the WHOs Community Health Workers Handbook. The training will be conducted by a training team experienced in Integrated Management of Childhood illnesses skills with support from the County and district iCCM CHW trainers of trainers. The training will be conducted in groups of 30 at link health facilities.

The training will use a variety of methodologies including lectures, presentations, discussions, case studies, demonstrations, practice, role-plays, and video shows. The CHWs will take quality time to go through and practice the use of a diagnostic tool that will be developed to assist them to classify cases. The trainer/supervisors will follow up the CHWs one month after the initial training to ensure that they acquired the necessary skills. There will be refresher courses at approximately week 6 and week 10 after the first training and subsequently every six months. This will be hands on 1-2 day trainings. 

Children aged 259 months with cough, fever, and difficult breathing during regular home visitation schedule, or whose mothers seek care from the CHW will be assessed and classified children according to the WHO classification for pneumonia as below. 

1.	No pneumonia: cough or cold
a.	No signs of pneumonia or severe pneumonia

2.	Pneumonia
Fast breathing:
a.	Greater than or equal to 50 breaths/min in a child aged 211 months 
b.	Greater than or equal to 40 breaths/min in a child aged 15 years

3.	Severe pneumonia (Pneumonia with danger signs) 
Cough or difficulty in breathing with 
a.	Severe respiratory distress (e.g. grunting, very severe chest indrawing)
b.	Signs of pneumonia with a general danger sign (inability to breastfeed or drink, lethargy or reduced level of consciousness, convulsions)

CHWs will provide oral amoxicillin 8090 mg/kg per day twice a day to infants aged 211 months and twice a day for those aged 1259 months) for 5 days to children with pneumonia (includes both chest in drawing pneumonia and fast breathing pneumonia) and give the mother specific guidance about its use. This dosage has been found to be safe and efficacious for treatment of even severe pneumonia in community settings. Children will be seen by the CHW either in the patient's home or at the CHWs house on day 4. This day 4 visit is recommended by the WHO.  At this visit, adherence to the oral antibiotic will be assessed, as well as the child's clinical status and the presence of any danger sign and adverse events. The child will be regarded as lost to follow-up if contact cannot be made on day 4. 
CHWs will also be trained as follows:-
If child has fever (less than 7 days)
1.	If RDT is positive, give oral antimalarial i.e. Artemether-Lumefantrine (AL). One tablet of AL contains 20mg Artemether and 120mg Lumefantrine).
It is to be given twice daily for 3 days as follows
	 Age 2 months up to 5 months -1/2 tablet (total 3 tabs)
         Age 5 months up to 3 years1 tablet (total 6 tabs)
	 Age 3 years up to 5 years2 tablets (total 12 tabs)
2.	Help caregiver give first dose. Advise to give 2nd dose after 8 hours, and to give dose twice daily for 2 more days.

If child has diarrhoea less than 14 days

 Give ORS. Help caregiver give child ORS solution in front of you until child is no longer thirsty. The ORS being utilized is low osmolar ORS (245mmol/l) and contains approximately 2.6g/l of sodium chloride, 13.5g/l of anhydrous glucose, 1.5g/l of potassium chloride and 2.9g/l of trisodium citrate, dehydrate. The ORS come in Sachets of powder for dilution in 500 ml and 1 liter.

Instructions:
 Give caregiver 4 ORS packets to take home. Advise to give as much as child wants, but at least 
50-100 ml (or a quarter to half a large cup of fluid) for children under 2 years and 100-200 ml (one half to one large cup of fluid) for children ages 2-5 years after each loose stool until diarrhea stops.

In addition to the ORS, CHWs will be trained to give Zinc supplementation. The zinc formulation to be used in this study is the dispersible formulation. Each dispersible tablet contains 10 mg or 20 mg of elemental zinc only. It does not contain any other vitamins or chemicals. The Zinc is packaged in blister packs of 10 tablets. The 20mg tablets of elemental zinc are scored.  The CHW will be trained as follows

 Give zinc supplement (20mg tablet). Give 1 dose daily for 10 days:
	Age 2 months up to 6 months1/2 tablet (total 5 tabs)
        Age 6 months up to 5 years1 tablet (total 10 tabs)
Help caregiver to give first dose

Children will be referred if they have pneumonia with danger signs or very severe disease, have diarrhoea with severe dehydration, are severely malnourished, their caregiver refuses home case or are already on antibiotics for more than 48hrs with no improvement. 

CHWs will also be trained to administer Vitamin A supplementation described as vitamin A capsules for the right child age as defined in the Kenya government vitamin A guidelines i.e. giving a vitamin A capsule of 100,000 IU to children aged 6 to 11 months and 200,000 IU capsules to children aged 12 to 59 months. Vitamin A will be given to all children who have not received supplementation in the last 6 months regardless of what health condition except if the child has bilateral pitting edema as per the training manual. 

ESTIMATED TIMELINE
This study will be completed in a period of 24 months.  Start up activities will take place during the first 3 months during which ethical approval will be sought, all stakeholders sensitized. During the 4th to 6th month, the community health units will be mapped and the baseline surveys at the household level and with the community health workers conducted. From the 7th to the 9th month, iCCM will be set up, CHWs trained and the interventions piloted. The ensuing 12 months (month 10-21) will involve the actual implementation of the interventions as well as a midline survey during month 16. The final three months (22-24) of the study period will be used for data management, data cleaning, analyses, and write-up of study results.   </interventions>
    <comparator>Compared to baseline where CHWs only diagnose and refer to the health centers</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of children under 5 years with pneumonia who receive appropriate antibiotic treatment

a household survey with interviews of mothers/caretakers of children who have experienced cough in the previous four weeks. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (month 0)

End line (month 12)
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of CHWs who are able to rationally use antibiotics for treatment of pneumonia 

source of data: 
CHW sick child recording forms
CHW treatment register
Research nurse  treatment report

Each time a CHW sees a suspected pneumonia case, s/he sends a please call me text to a hotline number. The information on his sick child recording form is then entered into a web based application which is able to determine if the right diagnosis has been made and correct treatment given and generate a report. In addition, a trained nurse will go and independently verify each pneumonia case within 24 hrs and enter the information into a mobile phone based sick child recording form. This will generate a report comparing the CHW to the computer system and the nurse. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Endline (month 12)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of CHWs who appropriately account for supplied commodities

Source of data: 
CHW inventory control card, CHEW stock control card, CHEW requisition, issue and order voucher, CHEW supply register

These tools are logistics and supply tools which allow the CHW and CHEW to keep track of the medicinal and diagnostic products they are using on sick children on a monthly basis 

Furthermore we will conduct interviews with CHW at end line asking them  whether in the last three months they experienced stock outs. We will identify the point in time and the duration of the stock out period </outcome>
      <timepoint>Endline (month 12)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of CHWs who are able to rationally use antimalarials 

source of data: sick child recording forms
CHW treatment and tracking register 

We will evaluate if children whose caregivers mentioned fever less than 7 days, were tested for Malaria using an RDT. Correct management entails giving an antimalarial for a child with a positive RDT and not giving if the RDT is negative

From this tools, we will be able to determine the CHWs performance in classification and treatment. For classification, we will calculate the percentage of misclassification (number misclassified based on the complaints out of the total number classified multiply by 100). For treatment, we will calculate the percentage of inappropriate treatment (number inappropriately treated based on classification out of the total number classified multiply by 100).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Endline  (month 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of CHWs who are able to rationally use ORS and zinc 

source of data: sick child recording forms
CHW treatment and tracking register 

We will evaluate if children whose caregivers mentioned diarrhea
 less than 14 days. Correct management entails giving an Zinc and ORS for a child with diarrhea and not giving for a child who has no diarrhea

From this tools, we will be able to determine the CHWs performance in classification and treatment. For classification, we will calculate the percentage of misclassification (number misclassified based on the complaints out of the total number classified multiply by 100). For treatment, we will calculate the percentage of inappropriate treatment (number inappropriately treated based on classification out of the total number classified multiply by 100).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Endline (month 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of mothers of children under 5 years who have symptoms of pneumonia or malaria who seek care from an appropriate provider

A household survey with  mothers/caretakers of children who have experienced fever in the previous four weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (month 0)

Endline (month 12)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of children treated for pneumonia who do not respond to treatment (experience treatment failure or relapse)

The children with pneumonia seen by the CHWs will be followed up at home by trained nurses on day 4  to assess the outcome of the treatment given or recommended. For children with severe pneumonia, a follow up visit will be done on day 4 and day 6. Treatment failure is defined in this study as appearance of any of the following:-
a)	Appearance of any signs of pneumonia with any danger signs such as inability to breastfeed or drink, or vomiting everything, convulsions, lethargy or unconsciousness, severe respiratory distress e.g. head nodding
b)	Change of antibiotic treatment or use of additional antibiotics beyond those prescribed and dispensed by the CHW
c)	Persistence of fever greater than 38 degrees Celsius with lower chest indrawing and or fast breathing on day 4 (after 3 days of initiation of treatment)
d)	Either fever greater than 38 degrees Celsius or lower chest indrawing or fast breathing alone at day 6
e)	Death</outcome>
      <timepoint>Endline (month 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of CHWs who are able to correctly administer VAS, defined as giving vitamin A supplementation to children aged 6 to 59 months on a semi-annual basis in the County

source of data
CHW Treatment and tracking register
Household surveys with children under 5 who have received vitamin A supplementation in the last 6 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>Endline (month 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of children aged 6 to 59 months who received VAS on a semi-annual basis.

Source of data: Household survey (immunization module)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Endline (month 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children between two months and five years from within Homabay County who present to a CHW with diarrhoea, fever and/or cough/difficult breathing

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children less than 2 months or greater than 59 months
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>888</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Kenya</country>
      <state>Homabay County</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>United Nations Complex, Gigiri, Block D
UNICEF Kenya Country Office
P.O. Pox 44145-00100
Nairobi, Kenya</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Kenya</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>United Nations Complex, Gigiri, Block D
UNICEF Kenya Country Office
P.O. Pox 44145-00100
Nairobi, Kenya </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Kenya</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization(WHO)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>WHO/GSC/GPL
BLOCK 3510
JALAN TEKNOKRAT 6
CYBERJAYA 63000
MALAYSIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>World Health Organization (WHO)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>WHO/GSC/GPL
BLOCK 3510
JALAN TEKNOKRAT 6
CYBERJAYA 63000
MALAYSIA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Malaysia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this project is to demonstrate the effectiveness and feasibility of training CHWs and supplying them with ORS, Zinc, RDTs, Artemether-Lumefantrine and amoxicillin to treat diarrhoea, pneumonia and malaria at the community level, with the overarching goal of enhancing the capacity of CHWs to provide early, effective and appropriate treatment to children under five in areas of particularly poor access to facility based health care. We hypothesize that iCCM will increase: 
1.	The proportion of children with fast breathing and or chest indrawing who receive early and appropriate treatment for pneumonia will be increased by at least 20% over baseline among CHWs trained to treat pneumonia. 
2.	The proportion of children with fever who receive early and appropriate treatment for malaria will be increased by at least 20% over baseline among CHWs trained to treat malaria. 
3.	The proportion of children with watery diarrhoea who receive early and appropriate treatment for diarrhoea will be increased by at least 20% over baseline among CHWs trained to treat diarrhoea.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Kenya Ethical Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kenya Medical Research Institute
PO BOX 54840-00200
Nairobi</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>FWA00002066</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Kenya</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>World Health Organization</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Avenue Appia-CH-1211
Geneva, Switzerland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maricianah Onono</name>
      <address>Kenya Medical Research Institute
Center for Microbiology Research
PO BOX 614-40100
Kisumu, Kenya</address>
      <phone>+254732390992</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>monono@kemri.org</email>
      <country>Kenya</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Bukusi</name>
      <address>Kenya Medical Research Institute
Center for Microbiology Research
Box 19464, post code 00202, Nairobi</address>
      <phone>+254733617503 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ebukusi@kemri.org</email>
      <country>Kenya</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maricianah Onono</name>
      <address>Kenya Medical Research Institute
Center for Microbiology Research
PO BOX 614-40100
Kisumu, Kenya</address>
      <phone>+254732390992</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>monono@kemri-ucsf.org</email>
      <country>Kenya</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maricianah Onono</name>
      <address>Kenya Medical Research Institute
Center for Microbiology Research
PO BOX 614-40100
Kisumu, Kenya</address>
      <phone>+254732390992</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>monono@kemri-ucsf.org</email>
      <country>Kenya</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>