<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362737">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000732886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Rosuvastatin versus Protease Inhibitor Switching for Hypercholesterolaemia in HIV-infected Adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To compare the effects of rosuvastatin (10 mg daily) and ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitor switching on the fasting total cholesterol of treatment-experienced HIV-infected adults over 12 weeks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SoS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypercholesterolaemia associated with ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitor therapy in of HIV-infected adults</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS / HIV)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Rosuvastatin tablets, dose 10 mg daily (5 mg daily in Asian participants), taken once daily for 12 weeks. Participants assigned to this intervention will continue ritonavir-boosted anti-retroviral therapy.</interventions>
    <comparator>Switching of ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitor to an alternative anti-retroviral agent as part of combination anti-retroviral therapy for HIV-1 infection.

Valid switch options are based on the U.S Department of Health and Human Services anti-retroviral guidelines in adolescents and adults, and include nevirapine tablets (400 mg daily), rilpivirine tablets (25 mg daily), raltegravir tablets (400 mg twice daily) and unboosted atazanavir tablets (400 mg daily). Final decisions regarding switch medication will be made by the treating physician, but will be for a duration of 12 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effects of rosuvastatin to switching of ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitor to an alternate anti-retroviral agent on the fasting total cholesterol over 12 weeks in treatment-experienced HIV-infected adults.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening visit blood testing to assess for study eligibility
Baseline visit blood testing (Week 0)
Week 4 visit blood testing to assess change from baseline
Week 12 visit blood testing to assess change from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety parameters (includes HIV-1 RNA level,  clinical adverse events, serious adverse events, laboratory adverse events, modifications to anti-retroviral therapy)

Clinical adverse events (for example, skin rashes) or laboratory events (for example, elevated liver enzymes) occurring during the study will be clinically assessed. Any adverse events ongoing at Week 12 deemed related to study drug by an investigator will be followed up for at least 30 days, or until resolution. Additional unscheduled visits and pathology tests may be required as part of this follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0)
Week 4 visit
Week 12 visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (assessed via the SF-12 survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0)
Week 4 visit
Week 12 visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting HDL/LDL cholesterol, LDL particle size, triglycerides and total:HDL cholesterol, D-dimer, C-reactive protein, fasting glucose and insulin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Week 0)
Week 4 visit
Week 12 visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Calculated cardiovascular risk scores (Framingham and D:A:D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening visit
Week 12 visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	HIV-positive status 
2.	Adults (&gt;=18 years of age)
3.	Stable and well-tolerated combination ART including a ritonavir-boosted PI for the previous 6 months
4.	HIV RNA &lt;50 copies/mL for at least the preceding 3 months
5.	Fasting total cholesterol &gt;5.5 mmol/L (&gt;213 mg/dL)
6.	Framingham risk score &gt;=8% at 10 years OR diabetes mellitus OR a family history of premature coronary artery disease in a first-degree relative 
7.	Provision of written, informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>8.	Any statin in the previous 12 weeks
9.	Previous statin-induced myopathy or hepatitis 
10.	History of coronary artery disease, stroke or any other indication for the use of statin therapy (hyperlipidaemia: genetic, secondary or idiopathic)
11.	Concurrent use of:
a). oral corticosteroids use other than for replacement therapy (ie. prednisolone 5-7.5 mg, hydrocortisone 20-30 mg, cortisone acetate 25-37.5 mg daily)
b). other immunosuppressive or immunomodulating drugs
12.	Contra-indication to rosuvastatin therapy:
a). liver transaminases &gt;5 times the upper normal limit
b). creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min
c). known myopathy
d). current fibrate therapy
e). known resistance to one or more backbone ART drugs
13.	No potent switch ART drug available to replace the current ritonavir-boosted PI
14.	Known intolerance to rosuvastatin or the proposed switch ART drug
15.	Women attempting or likely to become pregnant, or who are pregnant or breast-feeding 
16.	A patient with a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality, or other circumstance that might confound the results of the study, or interfere with the patients participation for the full duration of the study
17.	Unable to complete study procedures.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a randomized, open-label, 12-week prospective trial. Sixty (60) eligible subjects will be randomly allocated 1:1 to either:
(A) switch their existing ritonavir-boosted PI to another potent ART drug with lesser effects on serum cholesterol selected by the investigator; OR 
(B) continue ritonavir-boosted PI-based ART and commence rosuvastatin 10 mg daily (5 mg daily in Asian participants).</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified by baseline protease inhibitor type and by baseline total cholesterol (&gt;7.0 mmol/L or &lt;=7.0 mmol/L [275 mg/dL]). Randomisation within each stratum will be performed by St. Vincent's Centre for Applied Medical Research staff otherwise not involved in the study. A computerized random number generator will be used to produce a random order of interventions.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2010</postcode>
    <postcode>3004</postcode>
    <postcode>3068</postcode>
    <postcode>3181</postcode>
    <postcode>3182</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St. Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria Street, Darlinghurst, New South Wales, 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To compare the effects of adding rosuvastatin to switching of ritonavir-boosted protease inhibitor on total cholesterol levels in HIV-infected adults with increased cardiovascular risk profiles over a 12-week period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St. Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/SVH/194</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Andrew Carr</name>
      <address>St. Vincent's Centre for Applied Medical Research
Clinical Research Program
St. Vincent's Hospital
Level 4, Xavier Building
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst, New South Wales, 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83823359</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83822090</fax>
      <email>acarr@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nicola Mackenzie</name>
      <address>St. Vincent's Centre for Applied Medical Research
Clinical Research Program
St. Vincent's Hospital
Level 4, Xavier Building
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst, New South Wales, 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83822919</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83823869</fax>
      <email>nmackenzie@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Frederick Lee</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>flee3@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>