<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364452">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000687796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Predictability of Increasing Tooth Velocity using Invisalign Aligners in a Group of Teenage Subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial evaluating the predictability of increasing tooth velocity using Invisalign aligners in a group of teenagers requiring orthodontic treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Accuracy of tooth movement after increasing the velocity of tooth movement from 0.25mm - 0.5mm per fortnight</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Clear orthodontic aligners (Invisalign) moving teeth at a rate of either 0.25mm or 0.5mm per fortnight

Test subjects - Aligners will be programmed using Invisalign Clincheck software with activations to move premolars and the anterior dentition at 0.5mm per fortnight per set of aligners. Aligners will be delivered to the patient and expected to be worn 22 hours a day. Appointments will be made every six weeks to deliver the next three sets of aligners. Each set of aligners will be changed sequentially every 2 weeks.  
At every six week appointment an intra oral iTero optical scan will be taken of each arch

Participants will be asked to keep a diary of the amount of time spent without aligners in their mouth to monitor adherence to the protocol.

Total duration of study/intervention depends on the individual severity of the case/malocclusion.  Typically an orthodontic case takes 18-24 months to treat.  This will be the total duration of the study.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control subjects - Aligners will be programmed using Invisalign Clincheck software with activations to move premolars and the anterior dentition at the current default of 0.25mm per fortnight per set of aligners.  Aligners will be delivered to the patient and expected to be worn 22 hours a day.  Appointments will be made every six weeks to deliver the next three sets of aligners.  At every six week appointment an intra oral iTero optical scan will be taken of each arch</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical accuracy of the Invisalign(TM) orthodontic aligner system (Align Technology, California, USA) when teeth are moved at a rate 0.5mm per fortnight, per set of aligners

The study will assess the amount of tooth movement achieved by superimposing the computer-proposed tooth movements with actual clinical tooth movement

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra oral 3D photo every 6 weeks until orthodontic treatment is finished</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical accuracy of the Invisalign(TM) orthodontic aligner system (Align Technology, California, USA) when teeth are moved at a rate 0.25mm per fortnight, per set of aligners

The study will assess the amount of tooth movement achieved by superimposing the computer-proposed tooth movements with actual clinical tooth movement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra oral 3D photo every 6 weeks until treatment finished</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Teenage subjects (aged 13-19 years) requiring orthodontic treatment and deemed suitable for Invisalign (i.e. good oral hygiene, compliant and willing to wear aligners for 22 hours a day) will be eligible to participate.  To be included, subjects must be in good general health, non-smokers and have a healthy dentition with all permanent teeth present (except third molars).  Parents and potential subjects will be advised of the project and given the option to participate in the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>19</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children who are regular users of NSAIDS, steroid medication, or medication that may influence bone metabolism or bone physiology will be excluded.  Pregnant patients will also be excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed

A sample of 40 consecutive subjects from one specialist orthodontic practice who meet the inclusion/exclusion requirements and consent to the study will be selected</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated sequence will be used to randomly allocate the teenagers into the control or treatment group and will ensure there is the same number of subjects in each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A sample of 40 (20 treatment and 20 controls) will be assessed

The minimum sample size for this study was determined using SPSS Sample Power.  Calculations were based on the main variable to be tested - a comparison of predicted and actual tooth movement measured from cusp tips of the specific tooth.   With a sample of 16 subjects per group the study will have a power of 80% and level of confidence set at 0.05.  This means there is an 80% likelihood that the study will yield a statistically significant effect; and hence will determine if the mean dental movement achieved clinically differs from that estimated by ClinCheck.  This figure is based on the assumption that the Invisalign system will achieve 80% of predicted dental movement with a standard deviation of 30%.  40 participants will be recruited for the study allowing for four to drop out (a 13% dropout rate).  

Multiple measurements will be taken per patient (ten data points per arch, twenty data points per patient), increasing the data available to measure to a sample of 400 points. This will allow for an increase in confidence interval or power levels. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne, School of Dentistry </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>720 Swanston Street
Carlton, 
VIC 3053
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Align Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Align Technology, Inc. 2560 Orchard Parkway, San Jose, California 95131</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Vicki Vlaskalic</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>V Orthodontics, 870 Toorak Rd, Hawthorn East, VIC 3123</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will investigate the clinical accuracy of the Invisalign(TM) orthodontic aligner system (Align Technology, California, USA) by comparing computer-proposed tooth movements with actual clinical tooth movement, following an increase in the rate of tooth movement per set of aligners from the default 0.25mm per fortnight to 0.5mm per fortnight.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne - School of Dentistry</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>720 Swanston Street
Carlton
VIC 3053
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>1238666</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Schneider</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne
School of Dentistry, Orthodontic department
720 Swanston Street
Carlton
VIC 3053
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 1500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pmschn@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Margaret Wang</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne
School of Dentistry, Orthodontic department
720 Swanston Street
Carlton
VIC 3053
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 1073</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wanm@unimelb.student.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Margaret Wang</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne
School of Dentistry, Orthodontic department
720 Swanston Street
Carlton
VIC 3053
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 1073</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wanm@student.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>