<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83393">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000031268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of benzyl-nicotinate on wound infection in surgical patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of topical benzyl-nicotinate application on surgical site infection in patients undergoing general surgical operations with a skin incision.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Surgical site infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A topical cream containing benzyl nicotinate will be applied on the site of planned surgical incision. This molecule has a distinct vasodilative effect peaking at the 10th minute of application which lasts about 45 minutes. The cream which contains benzyl nicotinate also contains etofenamate; an antiinflammatory agent. The cream is placed in a syringe with the needle removed. The cream is applied to the incision with a dose of 1 mg benzyl nicotinate applied to each cm of the wound (1 ml cream/10 cm). The cream is applied on the operating table on the planned incision. The necessary amount will be distibuted homogenously on the planned incision with a width of 1 cm. Then the skin is prepared and draped. The surgery goes on as usual. The observation period is 30 postoperative days.</interventions>
    <comparator>A gel containing only etofenamate as the active agent will be used as the control. In order to apply the same dose of etofenamate as applied in the study group (10 mg to each cm) 2 ml of the control gel will be applied to each 10 cm of the planned wound. The operation goes on as usual as described in the intervention group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surgical site infection. This will be assessed by monitorization of the health care professionals. If the wound is opened microbiological culture assessment will be done additionally.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days of the operation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause mortality. This will be assessed by health care professionals if the patient is still hospitalized. If the patient is discharged within the time frame of the study the patient will be invited for clinical examination. If this is not possible the patient will be contacted by telephone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days of the operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All general surgical patients needing a skin incision.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The patients who refuse to participate, operations involving perianal region, burn patients, patients undergoing a secondary operation within 30 days unless the reason is the surgical site infection.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1260</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baskent University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1. Cadde 16. Sokak No:11 06490 Bahcelievler / ANKARA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Baskent University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1. Cadde 16. Sokak No:11 06490 Bahcelievler / ANKARA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Wound infection following general surgical operations is a serious problem. As the number of the surgical procedures performed is large, any intervention having the potential to decrease this morbidity even by a small fraction will be beneficial. The most important barrier to infection is a healthy, well vascularized wound. A cream containing benzyl-nicotinate dilates the capillaries and small vessels and increases the blood flow in the skin and subcutaneous tissues when applied to the skin. In this study, the effect of this vessel dilating cream will be assessed on wound infection in patients undergoing general surgical operations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tarik Zafer Nursal</name>
      <address>Gürselpasa Mah. Mavi Bulvar No:133/2 Senbayrak Sitesi B-Blok Seyhan / Adana</address>
      <phone>+905327763645</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tznursal@baskent-adn.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tarik Zafer Nursal</name>
      <address>Gürselpasa Mah. Mavi Bulvar No:133/2 Senbayrak Sitesi B-Blok Seyhan / Adana</address>
      <phone>+905327763645</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tznursal@baskent-adn.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>