<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364999">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000493640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Integrative medicine for plaque psoriasis combining Chinese herbal medicine with conventional therapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A feasibility study of Integrative medicine for plaque psoriasis combining Chinese herbal medicine with conventional therapy on Psoriasis Area Severity Index (PASI) score and quality of life in people with mild to moderate plaque psoriasis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1148-1686</utrn>
    <trialacronym>IMPPS (Integrative Medicine for Psoriasis Pilot Study)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Plaque psoriasis (psoriasis vulgaris)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>ARM 1: Chinese herbal botanical granulated extract PSORI-CM01 (YXBCM01)
packaged as 5.5g per sachet and mixed with water administered orally twice daily for 12 weeks 

- Calcipotriol 0.005% (50 microgram/g) cream, (30 g tubes)
administered daily to affected body surface areas for 12 weeks according to American Academy of Dermatology (AAD) guidelines (1% surface area coverage = 0.5 fingertip units) 

Both interventions to commence together.
Adherence monitored via daily patient diary and weekly assessor consultation.</interventions>
    <comparator>- Oral granulated placebo identical in color and closest possible to taste to the Chinese herb, made from herbal starch containing no active ingredients.
packaged as 5.5g per sachet and mixed with water administered orally twice daily for 12 weeks  

- Calcipotriol 0.005% (50 microgram/g) cream, (30 g tubes)
administered daily to affected body surface areas for 12 weeks according to American Academy of Dermatology (AAD) guidelines (1% surface area coverage = 0.5 fingertip units) 

As per intervention for adherence and commencement.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in Psoriasis Area Severity Index (PASI) score (%)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life improvement change in Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) score (%)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life improvement change in SKINDEX 29 score</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>adverse effects.
nausea, diarrhoea, abdominal pain assessed by patient report at assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>relapse rate (defined as return of the rash to 50% of the area it involved before treatment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of treatment (measured on an ordinal scale from 0-10 where 0 equals very dissatisfied with the treatment and 10 equals very satisfied with the treatment)  and willingness to repeat (measured at each assessment period on a Likert scale with a choice of response; Definitely No, Probably No, Probably yes, Definitely yes and Unsure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Surface Area (BSA) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood test (Kidney and liver function as well as analysis of key psoriasis specific cytokine changes)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health resource utilisation data (participant reported GP visits, hospital visits and use of medication)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1 People aged between 18 years and 70 years;
2 People with at least 12 months history of psoriasis vulgaris symptoms diagnosed by physician and where calcipotriol would be appropriate treatment
3 Patient informed consent

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1 Pregnant or breast feeding females;
2 Type of psoriasis other than vulgaris;
3 PASI score &gt;12 or &lt;7
4 Patients taking systemic drugs or phototherapy for psoriasis within 4 weeks prior to screening;
5 Taking topical drug treatment for psoriasis within 2 weeks prior to screening
6 Other severe disorders;
7 Known disorders of calcium metabolism (high blood calcium levels);
7 Known kidney function disorders.
8 Taking calcium, vitamin D supplements or vitamin D-like medicines.
9 Known sensitivity to Chinese herbs.
10 Known sensitivity to calcipotriol
11 Unwilling/unable to cease other topical and systemic psoriasis related medication use for the duration of the trial.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly allocated to intervention group (CHM plus WM) or control group (CHM placebo plus WM) in equal ratio (1:1). The randomization codes will be kept in sealed opaque envelopes and the envelopes will be opened sequentially for each participant only after participant details are written on the outside of the envelope. A number code inside the envelope will correspond with a package number that will contain 12 weeks of either real CHM granule or an identically packaged placebo granule. Neither participant nor trialists will know what package the participant has been randomised to.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation numbers will be generated by computer program with sequenced blocks (blinded block number).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline demographic characteristics such as gender and age will be analysed by chi square test or t test to determine equivalence between the two groups. Variables showing baseline imbalance will be taken into consideration when conducting data analysis (using the variables as covariates or performing sensitivity analysis to reveal the relationship between the variables and the outcome measures). Intention-to-treat analysis will be applied to outcome data to minimise bias due to withdrawals, all missing data will be replaced using the last observation carried forward (LOCF) method. Sensitivity analysis will be applied to measure changes to data output as a result of using the LOCF. Continuous data will be presented as means and standard deviation (SD), or 95% confidence interval (CI). Dichotomies data such as the percentage of participants achieving PASI 75 will be presented at Risk Ratio (RR) and 95% CI. P value =0.05 will be considered as statistically significant when comparing two groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3083 - Bundoora</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Guangdong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>RMIT University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Plenty Road, Bundoora, Victoria 3083</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>RMIT University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Plenty Road, Bundoora, Victoria 3083</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Guangdong Provincial Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>106 Zhongshan 2nd Rd, Yuexiu, Guangzhou 510120</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Guangdong Provincial Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>106 Zhongshan 2nd Rd, Yuexiu, Guangzhou 510120</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>China</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Psoriasis currently has no cure. Whilst new therapies manage severe psoriasis well mild-moderate conditions have evidence of poor management. Chinese medicine regularly treats psoriasis successfully in a clinical scenario. This study will test a previously researched herbal formula and evaluate its efficacy when integrated with standard conventional therapy (calcipotriol). The study will randomize participants to either a herbal medicine plus calcipotriol group or a placebo plus calcipotriol group and compare changes in symptom severity, quality of life and blood markers for changes after 12 weeks of the intervention. It will also assess the safety of integrating the two therapies and acceptability of the treatment as well as assess any significant difference between health resource utilization of the two groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Parker S, Zhang AL, Zhang CS, Goodman G, Wen Z, Lu C, Xue CC.
Oral granulated Chinese herbal medicine (YXBCM01) plus topical calcipotriol for psoriasis vulgaris: study protocol for a double-blind, randomized placebo controlled trial.
Trials. 2014 Dec 19;15:495. doi: 10.1186/1745-6215-15-495.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RMIT University Research ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Plenty Road Bundoora, Victoria, 3083</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>54/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Charlie Xue</name>
      <address>RMIT University
PO Box 71
Bundoora VIC, 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9925 7178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>charlie.xue@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tony Zhang</name>
      <address>RMIT University
PO Box 71
Bundoora, VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9925 7788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony.zhang@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tony Zhang</name>
      <address>RMIT University
PO Box 71
Bundoora VIC, 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9925 7788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony.zhang@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Shefton Parker</name>
      <address>RMIT University
PO Box 71
Bundoora, VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9925 7635</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shefton.parker@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>