<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362189">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000536864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect  of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs on hormones and metabolism in overweight men with low testosterone and obstructive sleep apnea (optional partner participation)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Endocrine and metabolic effects of non steroidal anti-inflammatory therapy in overweight, hypogonadal men with obstructive sleep apnea: A pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>u1111-1128-9098</utrn>
    <trialacronym>INFLATE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypogonadism- low testosterone</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>overweight/obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>200 mg Celecoxib (oral capsule) once daily for 3 months

Partner: no intervention however completion of questionnaires to gather information related to sleep and breathing as well as general health, sexual health, quality of life, relationships, mood and energy at baseline and at 3 months. This will take 20-30 minutes to complete.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo control once daily for 3 months (microcellulose capsule)

Partner: observational only- no intervention</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serial repetitive testosterone, estradiol, luteinizing and follicle stimulating hormone concentrations sampled over 12 and 24 hours. Free and total hormone concentrations will be calculated using mass equations and the outcome will be assessed using serum assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (10 minute sampling over 12 hours)
3 months (10 minute sampling over 24 hours)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MINMOD (Modified Minimal Model) and HOMA (homeostasis model of assessment) for the measurement of insulin sensitivity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24-hour blood pressure monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other hormones and binding globulins (eg ACTH, cortisol, testosterone, estradiol, LH, FSH, SHBG)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 month, 3 month (single blood draws)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic markers (insulin, fasting blood glucose, adiponectin, leptin, ghrelin) assessed through serum or plasma assays</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 month, 3 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammatory markers (micro-CRP, ESR, WBC, IL-1, IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, IL-1RA and TNF-alpha) assessed through serum or plasma assays</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 month, 3 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular health (lipid profiles, anthropometry, body composition (BIA scale), blood pressure, cardiovascular risk as assessed by diagnosis of Metabolic Syndrome and Framingham risk score).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 month, 3 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Polysomnography (PSG)</outcome>
      <timepoint>overnight at baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General quality of life (QOL) measurements (SF36, ESS, FOSQ, DASS, IWqOL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 months and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sex specific quality of life  [International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF), Brief Male Sexual Function Inventory (BMSFI)], European Male Ageing Study Sexual Function Questionnaire (EMAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 months, 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 month, 3 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motivation (compliance, completion) through medication diaries (to ensure participants are taking their medication) and their completion of the trial (attrition rates)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 1 month, 2 month, 3 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quality and activity counts via actigraphy</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Partner:	Quality of life measurements (SF36, ESS, FOSQ, DASS, MAPQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Partner: Relationship quality measurements (SERS, Dyadic Adjustment Scale, Female Sexual Functioning Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Males aged 18-65 with obstructive sleep apnea with respiratory disturbance Index (RDI) greater than or equal to 5/hr 
2.	Overweight or obese (BMI &gt; 27 kg.m-2)
3.	Hypogonadism (T &lt; 10 nmol/L) measured on two occasions 
4.	Waitlisted for CPAP-therapy or treatment refusers 
5.	Medical history, physical examination and laboratory screening indicating no clinical or laboratory evidence for significant and uncontrolled cardiovascular (ischemic, hypertension), renal, liver disease (serum electrolytes, urea and creatinine, liver function tests and full blood count).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Females
2.	Anemia
3.	Patients currently receiving CPAP-therapy
4.	Severe OSA requiring immediate treatment due to severity or increased associated risk (eg Transport worker)
5.	Significant and uncontrolled cardiovascular (ischemic heart disease, Congestive heart failure (NYHA II-IV), , hypertension, stroke), renal, liver disease as determined by medical history, physical examination and laboratory screening indicating clinical or laboratory evidence.
6.	Doctor diagnosed diabetes. 
7.  Known hypersensitivity to celecoxib or any of the excipients contained in the celeboxib capsules (lactose, sodium lauryl sulfate, povidine, croscarmellose sodium, magnesium stearate, gelatin, titanium dioxide, iron yellow oxide, indigo carmine).
8.	Demonstrated allergic-type reactions to sulfonamides. 
9.	Patients who have experienced asthma, urticaria, or allergic-type reactions after taking aspirin or other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, including other COX-2 specific inhibitors. 
10.	Patients using other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs because of the absence of any evidence demonstrating synergistic benefits and the potential for additive adverse reactions (excluding low dose &lt; 150 mg daily  aspirin).
11.	Active peptic ulceration or gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding. 
12.	Patients with estimated creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min. 
13.	Severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh score 10- classifies the severity of liver disease)
14.	Perioperative CABG surgery, unstable (thrombus aetiology), significant IHD, peripheral artery, cerebrovascular disease
15.	Drug and alcohol abuse/dependence
16.	 Shift workers or patients with an irregular sleep / wake routine. 
17.	 Current smokers
18.	 Current infection
19.	 Any chronic medical conditions likely, in the judgment of the investigator, that makes the patient unable to complete the study safely, or otherwise unsuitable for the study or that may interfere with or influence study treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The current estimated waitlist for initiation of CPAP treatment is about 2-3 months in the public hospital setting.  In this study, patients will be randomised to receive Celecoxib or placebo during this usual waiting period.
Prior to starting this study, a patient will be assessed for eligibility, will have signed an informed consent form and be allocated a unique patient screening number in sequential, ascending chronological order. This number will be a two-digit number prefixed by “S” (e.g. S01, S02 etc) and will be used to identify patients during the screening phase prior to randomisation.
Randomisation will take place on the day of allocation of treatment and involves assigning a unique patient number in sequential, ascending chronological orderaccording to a computer generated randomisation list.  To ensure the participant’s anonymity, documents will use the participant’s unique participant identification number (randomisation number). 
The investigator and study staff will be blinded to the treatment of any participant. Unblinding of a participant will be possible when required for urgent medical reasons requiring knowledge of treatment for medical care according to the judgment of the principal investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation list prepared by an individual not directly involved in subject assessments. This number will be a two digit number prefixed by “R” (e.g. R01, R02 etc) and will be used to identify the randomised treatment order the patient received.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Option for partner to be enrolled in study to complete questionnaires related to quality of life, relationship and sleep quality. This will provide observational information regarding the effect of changes in testosterone/sleep apnea on the bed partner.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2000</postcode>
    <postcode>2037</postcode>
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Woolcock</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe, NSW. 2037. Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC Centre for Integrated Research &amp; Understanding of Sleep</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
University of Sydney NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sydney Local Health District- Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box M30
Missendon Road, NSW
2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Pfizer Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>38-42 Wharf Road 
West Ryde NSW 2114</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a parrallel randomised controlled pilot study designed to investigate the effect of non-steroidal therapy on inflammation in obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) with regard to sleep apnea severity, reproductive function, androgen profile, cardio-metabolic health and quality of life. This study will use the drug celecoxib (Celebrex) which is a marketed drug in Australia that is commonly prescribed for arthritic conditions to relieve joint pain. 
Participants will be asked to attend the clinic for a 3 month period involving 5 short visits and 2 overnight stays with PSG and blood sampling.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District- Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box M30
Missendon Road
NSW
2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/12/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X11-0331</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box M30
Missenden Road
NSW, 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/12/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X11-0331</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Camilla Hoyos</name>
      <address>The Woolcock Institute
431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe
NSW
2037</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9114 0409</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9550 5865</fax>
      <email>camillah@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Liz Machan</name>
      <address>The Woolcock Institute
431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe
NSW
2037</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9114 0456</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9550 5865</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.machan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Liz Machan</name>
      <address>The Woolcock Institute
431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe
NSW
2037</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9114 0456</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9550 5865</fax>
      <email>elizabeth.machan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Liu</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research 
431 Glebe Point Road Glebe NSW 2037
Postal Address: PO Box M77 Missenden Road NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>camilla.hoyos@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>