<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370256">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000456459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Management of tooth decay in refugee children: a conservative approach</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of topical silver diamine fluoride application on arresting dental caries in refugee children</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-2684</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dental Caries</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Children under 12 years of age presenting to the Refugee Health Service (RHS) will undergo dental assessment as per current protocols. The option of fluoride treatment will be offered to the parents of children presenting with at least one carious lesion. Eligible children will then undergo simple sequential randomisation and single dose controlled application of 0.05ml Silver Diamine Fluoride (SDF) (intervention group) or 0.4ml  5% Sodium Fluoride varnish (NaF) (control group) will be applied to the carious lesions using a micro brush and adequate isolation. 

Dental review and SDF or NaF applications will be conducted such that:
- SDF or NaF will be applied to carious lesions on initial screening if the eligibility criteria is satisfied
- SDF or NaF application will then be performed again at 6 months, 12 months and a final review of each carious lesion will be completed at 18 months post-initial application. As such if a carious lesion is detected on initial screening it will receive a total of three SDF or three NaF applications at the aforementioned intervals. The carious lesions will be documented and reviewed at each of these intervals with a final review and dental charting conducted at 18 post initial visit.</interventions>
    <comparator>Following sequential randomisation, fluoride varnish (5% Sodium Fluoride) will be applied to children in the control group at initial visit, 6 months and 12 months with a final review at 18 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The arrest of dental caries:
Progression of dental caries will be assessed using clinical examination, ICDAS classification, clinical photographs and shade comparisons. Dmft scores will also be recorded at baseline and redone throughout the duration of the study at each review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Progression of dental caries will be assessed at each review/SDF application i.e 6 months, 12 months and finally 18 months post-initial SDF application</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Oral Health-Related Quality of Life will be assessed using Early Childhood Oral Health Impact Scale (ECOHIS) and the Child Oral Health-Related Quality of Life scale (COHRQoL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quality of life will be assessed using questionnaires at each review appointment  i.e 6 months, 12 months and finally 18 months post-initial SDF application</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevented fraction as assessed by changes in the dmft index</outcome>
      <timepoint>The dmft index of each child will be recorded at baseline and then re-evaluated and recorded at the final 18 month review. Prevented fractions will be calculated by comparing the dmft indices. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for emergency dental treatment: The need or uptake of emergency dental treatment due to teeth that develop pain, abscess and undergo emergency treatment such as  extraction will be recorded. Information such as which teeth required emergency treatment, the nature of emergency treatment e.g. extraction under general anaesthesia, service accessed e.g. private clinic or public hospital will be collected. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This information will be obtained through clinical examination and information collected from patient history during each review appointment (6 months, 12 months and 18 months) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Refugee children under 12 years of age deemed eligible for treatment through the Refugee Health Service i.e. satisfying visa conditions etc set out by the Humanitarian Entrant Health Service
- Children found to have atleast one carious lesion i.e. children who are caries free will not be included, however they may be included if at 6 month review are found to have developed a carious lesion

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Non-vital teeth (determined by pulpal exposure, presence of an abscess or a sinus, obvious discoloration, and premature hypermobility) will be excluded from treatment as extraction is better indicated in these situations. These cases will be referred for appropriate management through the current referral pathways.
- Children found to be caries free will be excluded from this study. However, they will be reviewed in 6 months and may be included if a carious lesion has developed. 
- Parents who do not wish their child to participate or children who refuse treatment will not be included.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple sequential randomisation using computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An estimated sample size of 100 children per group is required based on an absolute difference of 10% in the rate of caries arrest, with the power of the study set at 90% and with a=0.05 as the statistical significance level. Accounting for an anticipated drop-out rate of 20%, 120 children per group, a total of 240 children will need to be recruited.

Descriptive analysis: PPHs among refugee children, estimated treatment costs, length of stay
Quantitative Analysis: Prevented fraction, caries progression, need for emergency management
Qualitative Analysis: Changes in QoL, analysis of dental treatment burden</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/09/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>50</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Dentistry, University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>17 Monash Ave, Nedlands WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>17 Monash Ave, Nedlands WA 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dental caries (tooth decay) in the early childhood, known as Early Childhood Caries (ECC) can be debilitating, significantly impacting on a childs growth, nutrition, sleep, learning, appearance and quality of life. Children from refugee backgrounds face significant barriers in accessing timely care and therefore continue to experience significant disparities in oral health. The persisting barriers to seek and provide dental care inevitably leads to emergency hospitalisations and dental extractions.

Topical fluoride varnish application, specifically 5% sodium fluoride varnish (NaF), has been recommended in the prevention and control of dental caries in children. This forms part of current best practice in caries prevention along with provision of oral hygiene and dietary advice. Silver diamine fluoride (SDF) is another topical fluoride modality that has shown to have greater efficacy than NaF and is non-invasive, easy to apply, and effective treatment modality to arrest dental caries in high-risk children. 
The aims of this project are to evaluate the:
(i)   effectiveness of SDF in arresting carious lesions in refugee children
(ii)  quality of life (QoL) changes in refugee children before and after SDF application 

Refugee children under the age of 12 years will undergo a dental examination through the RHS, as per current protocols. The option of fluoride treatment will be offered to the parents of children presenting with at least one carious lesion. Eligible children will then undergo simple sequential randomisation and SDF or NaF will be applied to the carious lesions at initial visit, 6 months and 12 months at RHS and final review will be conducted at OHCWA at 18 months. Follow-up QoL surveys, dental charting and intra-oral photographs will be taken to assess changes in the carious lesions.  

The expected outcome of this study is to develop the use of SDF as an adjunctive treatment modality for refugee children, thereby improving their quality of life and reducing the need for emergency dental treatment.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Roberts Rd, Subiaco WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016117EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jilen Patel</name>
      <address>School of Dentistry M512
The University of Western Australia
17 Monash Ave, Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 7868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jilen.patel@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Robert Anthonappa</name>
      <address>School of Dentistry M512
The University of Western Australia
17 Monash Ave, Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 7868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robert.anthonappa@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Robert Anthonappa</name>
      <address>School of Dentistry M512
The University of Western Australia
17 Monash Ave, Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 7868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robert.anthonappa@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jilen Patel</name>
      <address>School of Dentistry M512
The University of Western Australia
17 Monash Ave, Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 7868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jilen.patel@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>