<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365421">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000002583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Patellofemoral joint osteoarthritis: the effect of foot orthoses on pain, function and bone marrow lesions. A pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Patellofemoral joint osteoarthritis: the effect of custom foot orthoses compared to specialised footwear on pain, function and bone marrow lesions. A pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1151-0192</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patellofemoral Joint Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: customised EVA (Shore 50) foot orthoses (Orthema Australasia) prescribed according to a predefined protocol, and/or motion control footwear (New Balance 857, Boston, Massachusetts).

Group 1 participants will be asked to wear the custom foot orthoses and prescribed footwear for a period of 4 months.

Group 2 participants will be asked to wear the prescribed footwear only, for a 4 month period. 

The interventions are to be worn as often as is practical/possible during the 4 month period of the trial, aiming for at least 8 hours per day.

Adherence will be documented and encouraged by regular SMS reminders and emails to participants. Participants will be asked to keep a diary of the hours of use of foot orthoses and/or footwear per day, activity levels, and type of footwear worn when not wearing the prescribed footwear. Participants will have review appointments at 1, 2 and 4 months where diary completion will be reviewed, and any issues pertaining to the interventions can be discussed, and if necessary, rectified.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator treatment: prescribed motion control footwear. 
Group 2 will wear the prescribed footwear for a 4-month period to determine the effects of footwear alone. 

Adherence to the footwear condition will be documented at 2 and 4 months, and encouraged by regular SMS reminders to participants. Participants will be asked to keep a diary of the hours of use of the footwear use per day, activity levels, and type of footwear worn when not wearing the prescribed footwear.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome for this study will be the feasibility of a Phase 3 trial. Feasibility will be assessed by evaluating recruitment rate, the number of eligible participants, the willingness of participants to commit to the study protocol, optimal time frames for manufacture and provision of the interventions, adherence to the interventions over the 4 months of the study, the number of adverse events, diary completion, and drop-out rate. </outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anterior Knee Pain Scale: This questionnaire consists of 13 specific questions related to patellofemoral pain, symptoms and functional difficulties. Participants select the best response to each question. Each question is scored and collectively added together to give a score from 0 (maximal disability) to 100 (no disability). A change of 10 or more points indicates a clinically meaningful change in symptoms and function.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ): Participants will be required to document the amount of time (minutes to hours per day, or alternatively days per week) they spend sitting, walking, and doing moderate or vigorous exercise.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patellofemoral Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (PFOOS): This questionnaire consists of 5 separate subscales that cover pain, symptoms, function in activities of daily living, function in sports and recreational activities, and knee-related quality of life. Participants select the most appropriate response to each question, and a normalised score for each subscale is calculated (0 = extreme knee problems, 100 = no knee problems).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction of treatment will comprise 2 questions:
1. Overall satisfaction of treatment 
2. Satisfaction to live with current symptoms

Participants will be asked to respond to each question using a 5-point scale (very satisfied, somewhat satisfied, neither satisfied nor dissatisfied, somewhat dissatisfied, very dissatisfied).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Success of Treatment: Participants will be asked 2 questions related to their perception of treatment success.
1. Participant's agreement that the treatment has been successful (Yes/No)
2. Would the participant recommend the same treatment to a friend (Yes/No)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self Reported Rate of Recovery: Participants will score how well they feel they have recovered from their knee pain, ranging from 0 (not at all) to 100 (totally recovered).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Acceptable Symptoms State (PASS): Participants are asked in a statement if their current condition is satisfactory based on their general function and current pain (Yes/No). </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in bone marrow lesion volume on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the study knee. Bone marrow lesion volume will be measured according to an established protocol prior to the prescribed intervention, and at the end of the 4-month intervention period. Differences in bone marrow lesion volume pre- and post-intervention, within and between groups, will be evaluated. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate their average knee pain on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible) over the past week.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PainDETECT: The painDETECT questionnaire will be used to identify the presence of neuropathic pain. This questionnaire consists of nine items; seven evaluating pain quality, one evaluating pain pattern, and one evaluating pain radiation; which contribute to an aggregate score ranging from 1 to 38. A higher score indicates more neuropathiclike symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical Outcomes Study 36-Item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36): This questionnaire is a generic measure of health-related quality of life. Thirty-six items are used to calculate eight scores across the following domains: physical functioning, role limitations due to physical health problems, bodily pain, general health, vitality (energy/fatigue), social functioning, role limitations due to emotional problems, and mental health. Transformed scores range from 0 (worst health state) to 100 (best health state).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EQ-5D: Quality of life will be measured using the EQ-5D (EuroQoL) questionnaire. The EQ-5D is a generic measure of health-related quality of life and has 5 dimensions: (i) mobility; (ii) self-care; (iii) usual activities; (iv) pain/discomfort; and (v) anxiety/depression. Each question has three possible responses: no problems, some problems, or extreme problems. The EQ-5D also has a health state scale which asks participants to rate their state of health on a 100-point scale, with 0 indicating worst imaginable health state and 100 indicating best imaginable health state.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia: Kinesiophobia will be assessed with the Tampa Scale for Kinesiophobia. It consists of 17 statements on subjective experience of injury and physical activity, which are each scored on a 4-point Likert scale ranging from strongly disagree to strongly agree. A total score from 17 to 68 is then calculated by summing the individual item scores, where 17 represents no fear of movement or re-injury, and 68 indicates a greater fear. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arthritis Self-Efficacy Scale : The Arthritis Self Efficacy scale is a 20-item scale with 3 subscales: self-efficacy for managing pain (5 items); self-efficacy for physical function (9 items); and self-efficacy for controlling other symptoms (6 items). Items are rated on a 10-point scale regarding their certainty of their ability to perform a task, manage their pain or control their symptoms, with 0 being very uncertain and 10 being very certain. Each subscale is scored individually as the mean of all items, with higher scores indicating higher self-efficacy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety and Depression (HAD) Scale: The HAD scale is a 14-item scale that will be used to investigate whether there is an association between PFJ OA and emotional state. Seven questions relate to anxiety and seven to depression. Participants select the best of 4 responses to each item. Items are scored from 0 to 3 with scores for anxiety and depression summed separately to give total scores for each component. Scores of 07 represent no anxiety or depression, 810 is borderline, and 1121 indicates the presence of an anxious or depressive state. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rating on a 10cm visual analogue scale (VAS) the following: 1. Usual pain on movement in the previous week. Scale ranges from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain imaginable).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rating on a 10cm visual analogue scale (VAS), the following: 1. Usual pain during nominated aggravating activity in the previous week. Scale ranges from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worse pain imaginable).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global rating of change (GROC): participants will be asked to rate their overall change on a 6-point Likert scale (completely recovered, much improved, improved, no change, worse, much worse)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate their worst knee pain on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible) over the past week.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate their average amount of knee pain felt at rest over the past week on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate their average amount of knee pain on movement over the last week on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate the average amount of restriction caused by their knee to daily activities on a scale from 0 (no restriction) to 10 (maximum restriction possible) over the past week .  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to name the activity that caused the most knee pain in the last week and to rate the average amount of pain caused by this activity on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate their maximum knee pain over the past week when walking on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible) .  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate their maximum knee pain in the past week when sitting for one hour on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked to rate their maximum knee pain in the past week when rising from sitting on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be ask to rate their maximum pain in the past week when going up and down stairs on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be ask to rate their maximum pain in the past week when squatting on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be ask to rate their maximum pain in the past week when running on a scale from 0 (no pain) to 10 (worst pain possible).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will be asked:
"Overall, how would you rate your knee pain now?" 

Participants will be asked to circle the most appropriate response from the following: 
no problem, mild, moderate, somewhat severe, severe</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i) aged &gt;= 40 years;
ii) anterior knee pain aggravated by at least two activities that load the patellofemoral joint (e.g. squatting, stair ambulation);
iii) pain during these activities present on most days in the past month;
iv) pain severity &gt;30mm on a 100mm visual analogue scale during aggravating activities;
v) radiographic evidence of patellofemoral joint osteoarthritis (&gt;= OARSI atlas grade 1), or MRI evidence (a definite osteophyte &amp; partial or full thickness cartilage loss. Hunter et al, 2011). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) concomitant pain from other knee structures (including TFJ), hip or lumbar spine;
(ii) recent treatment for patellofemoral pain (knee injections within the previous 3 months; foot orthoses or physiotherapy within the previous 12 months);
(iii) any foot condition precluding the use of foot orthoses;
(iv) knee or hip arthroplasty or osteotomy;
(v) planned lower limb surgery in the following 2 months; 
(vi) moderate to severe concomitant tibiofemoral osteoarthritis (Kellgren and Lawrence grade &gt;= 3 on radiograph);
(vii) neurological or systemic arthritis conditions;
(viii) physical inability to undertake testing procedures;
(ix) contraindications to x-ray (e.g. pregnant, breastfeeding);
(x) inability to understand written and spoken English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will respond to advertisements calling for subjects to participate in the trial. 
Telephone screenings will then be conducted to determine if a volunteer meets the inclusion criteria. All potentially eligible volunteers will then be required to undergo an x-ray to ensure radiographic evidence of patellofemoral osteoarthritis, and exclude moderate tibiofemoral joint osteoarthritis. Eligible and consenting participants will then be randomly allocated via concealed allocation to either the custom orthoses + footwear group, or the footwear only group after baseline testing. Allocation will be determined by a central administration site where the allocation schedule will be held.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation schedule</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Single blinded randomised controlled trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As this is an exploratory pilot study, sample size has been chosen based on feasibility with respect to time and funding. As such, 22 participants per group (allowing for a drop out rate of 10%) will be selected, giving an overall total of 44 participants.

Analysis will be conducted blinded to group allocation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>45</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/03/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4072 - University Of Queensland</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Kay Crossley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Allied Health, 
College of Science, 
Health and Engineering , 
La Trobe University, 
Bundoora , 
Victoria  3086 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Australian Podiatry Education and Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>89 Nicholson Street,
Brunswick East,
Victoria, 3057</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Australian Academy of Podiatric Sports Medicine</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 78,
Mitchell, 
ACT 2911</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Bill Vicenzino</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences 
Therapies Building 84A
Therapies Road,
University of Queensland
St Lucia 4072
Queensland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Natalie Collins</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences 
Therapies Building 84A
Therapies Road,
University of Queensland
St Lucia 4072
Queensland
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patellofemoral osteoarthritis is a common condition that results in pain and functional limitations. Custom foot orthoses are effective at improving pain and function in younger people with patellofemoral pain, and thus may also be of benefit in older people with patellofemoral osteoarthritis. This Phase 2 study aims to investigate the feasibility of a Phase 3 randomised controlled trial evaluating the effect of custom foot orthoses and footwear on pain, lower limb function and bone marrow lesions in patellofemoral osteoarthritis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
St Lucia, Queensland 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014000068</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health, 
College of Science, 
Health and Engineering , 
La Trobe University, 
Bundoora , 
Victoria  3086 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 3902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health, 
College of Science, 
Health and Engineering , 
La Trobe University, 
Bundoora , 
Victoria  3086 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 3902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Crossley</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health, 
College of Science, 
Health and Engineering , 
La Trobe University, 
Bundoora , 
Victoria  3086 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9479 3902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.crossley@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Narelle Wyndow</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland
The School of Health and Rehabilitation Science/ Division of Physiotherapy
St Lucia, Queensland, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61413 161 779</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.wyndow@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>