<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367297">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000283572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validation of Electronic Visual Analogue Scales (VAS) for Subjective Measures in older adults in rehabilitation for musculoskeletal and neurological conditions; Pain, Fatigue, Exertion, Enjoyment and Perceived benefits</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of the use of visual analogue scales using paper based and iPad based VAS for Pain, Fatigue, Exertion, Enjoyment and Perceived benefits in older adults in rehabilitation </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Older adults in rehabilitation for musculoskeletal conditions</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Older adults in rehabilitation for neurological conditions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Data will be collected once using a touch screen on an iPad device.  Participants wil complete 4 screens using their finger on a touch screen and complete a VAS Pain, VAS fatigue, borg rating of exertion, plus a rating scale for enjoyment, perceived benefit and ease of use.  It is anticipated that it would take 5 minutes to explain and complete</interventions>
    <comparator>Data will be collected once using a pen and paper resting on a clipboard. Participants wil complete 4 sheets of paper  complete a VAS Pain, VAS fatigue, borg rating of extertion, plus a rating scale for enjoyment, perceived benefit and ease of use.  It is anticipated that it would take 5 minutes to explain and complete.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean difference (in mm) and limits of agreement VAS pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean difference (in mm) and limits of agreement VAS fatigue</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean difference and limits of agreement borg rating scale of perceived exertion</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Co-efficient of variation of the score on the VAS for pain and fatigue</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Older adults attending for exercise class or rehabilitation for musculoskeletal or neurological conditions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Neurological conditions that impact on communication and prohibit informed consent to be made including
aphasia
dementia
cognitive impairment
vision</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants who attend exercise classes will be invited by the researchers to participate in the study.  As this is a cross over trial, all participants will receive both interventions and randomisation will occur just prior to data collection.  Participants and researchers will not blinded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will draw a coloured chip from a hat (eyes closed) and select either a blue or red chip.  Participants who draw a red chip will complete the paper scales first; participants who draw a blue chip will complete the electronic scales first.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Bland altman plots will be generated from the mean data to determine limits of agreement for the two methods of data collection (paper and iPad).  As well, co-efficient of variation will be generated for the novel data collection tool - the iPad.  Sample size is based on previous research examining validity of VAS for pain in acute care where scores on a VAS ranged from 0 to 100 and the standard deviation was 24.29 and correlation between electronic and visual scales 0.90. A sample size of 24 reported a power of 90% to detect a difference of 2.22 or greater.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>7/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>22</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Launceston General Hospital - Launceston</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The School of Health Sciences
Locked Bag 1322
Launceston, 7250
Tasmania</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Tasmania</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The School of Health Sciences
Locked Bag 1322
Launceston, 7250
Tasmania</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is determine if data collected on a mobile device has the same accuracy and reliability as the traditional paper based method of data collection. Data collection using mobile technology (including iPads) has the capacity to improve the efficiency of data collection and reduce transcription errors in large data sets.
Measurement of subjective measures such as Pain, Fatigue, Exertion, Enjoyment and Perceived benefits of an intervention allow researchers to determine valuable information, from the perspective of the participants, in any intervention that they are carrying out.  These factors have been identified as important barriers or facilitators to participation in in physical activity or exercise programs.  Tools to measure these parameters have been validated in paper form.  In larger studies the ability to collect this data electronically has huge potential to improve research efficiency, but to date no validation studies have been done using the iPad and these tools in an older population. Advantages:
*Reduced time for data collection
*Improved storage of data (no paper copies required)
*Reduced research time (no data transcription required)
*Easy ability to securely gain and store de-identified/re-identifiable data
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Health and Medical Research Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
Hobart TAS 7001
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0014062</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marie-Louise Bird</name>
      <address>The Faculty of Health
University of Tasmania
Locked Bag 1322
Launceston 7250 
Tasmania</address>
      <phone>+61 3 63425497</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>birdm@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marie-Louise Bird</name>
      <address>The Faculty of Health
University of Tasmania
Locked Bag 1322
Launceston 7250 
Tasmania</address>
      <phone>+61 3 63425497</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>birdm@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marie-Louise Bird</name>
      <address>The Faculty of Health
University of Tasmania
Locked Bag 1322
Launceston 7250 
Tasmania</address>
      <phone>+61 3 63425497</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>birdm@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marie-Louise Bird</name>
      <address>The Faculty of Health
University of Tasmania
Locked Bag 1322
Launceston 7250 
Tasmania</address>
      <phone>+61 3 63425497</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>birdm@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>