<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83934">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000702213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to compare the effects of taking 2.5mg of the antihstamine, Loratidine, four times a day with taking 10mg of Loratidine once a day in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Maxiclear PD Study: A Double Blind, Randomised, Cross-over Trial to Compare the Pharmacodynamic Effects of Loratadine 2. 5 mg Four Times a Day with Loratadine 10 mg Once Daily in healthy volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Maxiclear PD Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NTX/09/06/052
Health and Disability Ethics Committees, Northern X Regional Ethics Committee, New Zealand</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Allergic rhinitis and relief of other allergic symptoms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Loratadine 2.5 mg tablet four times a day orally for 72 hours. Participants who are on the this dose regimen in the first study phase will swap to the other dose regimen (loratadine 10 mg once daily) in the second cross-over study phase. Washout is at least 10 days between these two study phases.</interventions>
    <comparator>Loratadine 10 mg once a day orally for 72 hours. Washout is at least 10 days between two study phases. Placebo tablets containing lactose will be used to match the different dosing frequency that is for the four doses per day, one dose is on loratadine 10 mg tablet and all the other three doses are on placebo tablets.  Placebo tablets will alos be taken orally for 72 hours.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The area under the curve (AUC) of the wheal induced by a skin prick test of a standard dose of histamine 72 hours after the first dose</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours after the first dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events will be assessed and determined up to 7 days after the last dose.These adverse sevents reporting will include self-report on participant follow up notebook and clinician assessment during each study visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 7 days after the last dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy volunteers, males and females aged 18-50 years.
Females must be sterile or using adequate contraception.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants who have any concomitant medications currently, or in the 7 days prior to the start of the each study phase. The only exception are oral contraceptives, ibuprofen and paracetamol. 
Suffering from any other diseases or condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, means that it would not be in the participant's best interests to participate in this study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who are eligible, will be randomised to receieve loratadine tablets as two different dose regimens (loratadine 10 mg once daily, loratadine 2.5 mg four times daily) in two sequences. The randomisation code will specify which dose regimen the participant will receive during the first study phase and which during the second cross-over study phase. This randomization code will be sealed in a opaque envelope and allow investigators to have the access of information that the participant is on which treatment in case of any emergency. Another set of this randomization code list is hold by the biostatistician who generates this list.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomization sequence will be generated by a computer and the randomisation code will specify which dose regimen the participant will receive during the first study phase and which during the second cross-over study phase.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Double Dummy-Placebos will be used for the dose regimen of loratadine 10 mg once daily to match the different dosing frequency with loratadine 2.5 mg four times daily.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/09/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>22/10/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>31</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/11/2009</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street,
PO Box 33 203 
Takapuna, Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street,
PO Box 33 203 
Takapuna, Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Loratadine is usually given as a 10 mg dose once daily for the treatment of allergic condictions. However, based on pharmacokinetic principles it is likely that divided daily dosing such as 2.5 mg four times a day will also produce a similar effect on histamine effect compared with loratadine 10 mg once daily. This would enable smaller doses of loratadine to be combined with shorter acting agents such as phenylephrine.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>This study was not published yet </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee, Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hartley Atkinson</name>
      <address>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street,
PO Box 33 203 
Takapuna, Auckland</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax>+ 64 9 488 0234</fax>
      <email>hartley@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jennifer Zhang</name>
      <address>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street,
PO Box 33 203 
Takapuna, Auckland</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax>+ 64 9 488 0234</fax>
      <email>jennifer@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennifer Zhang</name>
      <address>Level 2, 9 Anzac Street,
PO Box 33 203 
Takapuna, Auckland</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax>+ 64 9 488 0234</fax>
      <email>jennifer@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christian Schwabe </name>
      <address>Auckland Clinical Studies, Ground Floor, ECOM House, 3 Ferncroft St, Grafton, Auckland 1150, New Zealand </address>
      <phone>+ 09-373 3474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christian@clinicalstudies.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>