<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336621">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000505909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effectiveness of hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) for healing venous leg ulcers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) for healing chronic venous leg ulcers: A randomised, double blind, placebo-controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>WMI CRC 3-02</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Venous leg ulcers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group 1: Participants will be treated with a multilayered high compression system (gold standard evidence based practice) once per week throughout the duration of the study. Those randomised to Group 1 will receive hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) treatments. Each HBOT treatment will consist of oxygen at 2.4 atmospheres absolute (ATA) for 110 minutes. Oxygen is pressurised in a cyclical routine through a number of compression/decompression phases during the treatment. Patients will receive these HBOT treatment 5 days/week for 6 weeks or until healed, an upper limit of 30 treatments.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2: Participants will be treated with a multilayered high compression system (gold standard evidence based practice) once per week throughout the study. Those randomised to Group 2 will receive a sham HBOT treatment. Each sham HBOT treatment will consist of an exact time replica of the treatment protocol using air pressurised to 1.2 ATA then decreased to 1.0 ATA. This is repeated in a cyclical routine through the compression/decompression phases of the treatment protocol. The patient is maintained at 1.0 ATA through the 85 minute treatment phase. Participants will receive the sham treatment 5 days/week for 6 weeks or until healed, an upper limit of 30 treatments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of healed ulcers/group. Ulcer area will be calculated using wound tracings, digital photography and digital planimetry to determine area reduction, percent reduction and total healing rates. A healed ulcer is defined as full epithelialisation maintained for at least two weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed every week up to 12 weeks from randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to ulcer healing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed every week up to 12 weeks from randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ulcer area percentage reduction in each group</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed every week up to 12 weeks from randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PUSH scores of each group
(Stotts et al. 2001. J Gerontol Biol Sci 56:M795)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed every week up to 12 weeks from randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life of each group, measured with:
1.  SF-12 
2. Medical Outcomes Study Pain Measures 
3. Geriatric Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon enrolment in the study and at 12 weeks from randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness of each group will be evaluated by a health economist, utilising measures of the number and costs of health services provided, investigations, dressings and bandages used while unhealed, occasions of care provision and staff time, loss of functional ability and QALYs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of the study, 12 weeks after the initiation of the HBOT treatments.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>incidence of treatment emergent adverse effects for each group (e.g., ear barotrauma, oxygen toxicity effects such as seizures, myopic visual effects). These side effects are all temporary changes. A nurse is present with patients through all hyperbaric treatments and will check with the patient re whether they have any ear pain or other symptoms and treat and record any adverse effects. Patients will also be asked if they have had any of these symptoms at each study visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at every HBOT or sham HBOT treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Persons presenting with a venous leg ulcer that have an Ankle branchial pressure index  between 0.8 and 1.2, a TCOM reading that indicates a hypoxic wound responsive to an oxygen challenge, who are not at risk for hyperbaric-related complications and whose ulcer has not responded to standard treatment (i.e., &lt;50% reduction in ulcer area following 4 weeks of treatment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Persons with cognitive impairment.
2. Persons with an Ankle Branchial Pressure Index &lt;0.8 or &gt;1.2. 
3. Persons with leg ulcers of non-venous aetiology.
4. Persons considered to be at specific risk for hyperbaric-related complications, as specified below:
-pregnancy
-concurrent administration of disulfuram, or antineoplastic agents doxorubicin and cisplatinum.
-reactive airway disease (COPD with CO2 retention), radiographic evidence of pulmonary blebs/bullae
-untreated pneumothorax or history of spontaneous pneumothorax 
-previous documented ejection fraction less than 35% or cardiovascular instability
-history of seizures - except childhood febrile seizures
-unable to follow simple commands, not orientated to person, place, time.
-prior chest surgery, middle ear surgery, optic neuritis, fever, congenital , spherocytosis, claustrophobia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients presenting with a venous leg ulcer
and fitting the inclusion and exclusion criteria
will be invited to participate in the study. Once
a patient has been identified by the clinician in
charge as fitting the inclusion criteria, the
Research Assistant will approach the patient to
invite them to participate and give them an
information and consent package. If the patient
consents to participate in the study, the
Research Assistant will collect baseline data
from the patient’s records and give the patient
a questionnaire to fill in. Where more than one ulcer is present, a target ulcer will be identified for the purpose of the study (i.e., the largest ulcer).The Research
Assistant will open a randomisation envelope
and the patient will be allocated to either
Treatment group 1 or Treatment group 2. A
staff member not working on this project will
have previously filled sealed opaque envelopes
with the allocation sequence.</concealment>
    <sequence>Prior to commencement of the study a
randomisation allocation sequence will be
generated with a computerised randomisation
program.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/08/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/11/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>84</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>74</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Collaborate Sponsorship: Wesley Centre for Hyperbaric Medicine, Queensland University of Technology, and the Wound Management Innovation CRC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wound Management Innovation CRC, Level 2, 8 Carraway Street, Kelvin Grove QLD 4059

Wesley Centre for Hyperbaric Medicine, 30 Chasely St 
Auchenflower, QLD 4066

School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery, QUT, Victoria Park Rd, Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wound Management Innovation Cooperative Research Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 8 Carraway Street
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to conduct a blinded, randomised, placebo-controlled trial to determine the effectiveness of hyperbaric oxygen therapy for patients with non-healing venous leg ulcers on progress in wound healing, pain, quality of life and cost effectiveness of care.

Study Therapy:  
Active - Oxygen at 2.4 atmospheres absolute for 110 minutes in the Hyperbaric Chamber.
Placebo - Exact time replica of the treatment protocol using air pressurised to 1.2 ATA then decreased to 1.0 ATA. This is repeated in a cyclical routine through the compression/decompression phases of the treatment protocol. The patient is maintained at 1.0 ATA through the 85 minute treatment phase. 
	
Study Population:	Male and female adults with non-healing venous leg ulcers and who fit with the study inclusion/exclusion criteria will be recruited into the study. 
To complete 58 study participants in the HBOT blinded study, at least 84 volunteers will need to be enrolled into the four week pre-HBOT treatment assessment period. 
	
No. Centres: 1. Wesley Centre for Hyperbaric Medicine
	
Study Design: The study has a randomised, double-blind, placebo controlled design.
	
Study Duration: Total of 16 weeks including the four weeks prior to and six weeks following the HBOT intervention of six weeks duration.
	
Objectives of the Study: To determine the effectiveness of hyperbaric oxygen therapy for study participants with non-healing venous leg ulcers on progress in wound healing, pain, quality of life and cost effectiveness of care.
	
Study Endpoints:  (Primary and Secondary)	
Primary wound healing outcome measure will be the incidence of complete wound closure  at the completion of the study (12 weeks after initiation of the HBOT study).  
Secondary outcomes will include time to healing, ulcer area percentage reduction and differences in PUSH scores.
The primary safety endpoints will be incidence of treatment emergent adverse events.  Study participants are assessed prior to commencing HBOT and then at every treatment for adverse effects e.g. ear barotrauma, oxygen toxicity effects (seizures, myopic visual effects).  These side effects are all temporary changes. 
Quality of Life data will be measured at the beginning and end of the 16-week study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Nil as yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>QUT Human Research Ethics Unit
Office of Research
Level 4, 88 Musk Avenue
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1000001172</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uniting Care Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5 
193 North Quay, BRISBANE 
QLD
4000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1102</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Ken Thistlethwaite</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston, Qld, 4059</address>
      <phone>61 7 3371 6033</phone>
      <fax>61 7 3371 1566</fax>
      <email>kenneth.thistlethwaite@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Ken Thistlethwaite</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston, Qld, 4059</address>
      <phone>61 7 3371 6033</phone>
      <fax>61 7 3371 1566</fax>
      <email>kenneth.thistlethwaite@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathleen Finlayson</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation, QUT
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, Qld, 4059</address>
      <phone>61 7 31386105</phone>
      <fax>61 7 31386030</fax>
      <email>k.finlayson@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ken Thistlethwaite</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston, Qld, 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 428683112</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kenneth.Thistlethwaite@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>