<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373281">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001193369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of cardiovascular disease and dynamic endurance exercise training on cardiovascular function in middle-aged and older women.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of cardiovascular disease and dynamic endurance exercise training on cardiovascular function in middle-aged and older women.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary heart disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Women aged 50-80 years with and without cardiovascular disease will perform a 16-week supervised, group-based dynamic endurance exercise programme. The exercise prescription will be individualised and we aim to keep the training flexible and alter mode, duration or intensity if necessary (e.g. to suit fitness level or any limitations to particular modes of exercise).

The programme includes a combination of cycling, rowing and walking/jogging exercise. During the first 4 weeks, exercise prescription will include 3 moderate-intensity (50-75% of VO2peak) continuous exercise sessions with a duration of 45 minutes. Once tolerated (generally within the first 4 weeks), exercise duration will be increased to 60 minutes for the remainder of the intervention. At week 4 and 8, a moderate intensity continuous training session will be substituted for an interval type session. Following a 10 minute moderate intensity warm-up, the participant will perform two minutes of vigorous-intensity (80-95% VO2peak) exercise followed by three minutes of active recovery (40-60%VO2 peak). This work-recovery protocol will be repeated five times.

Exercise sessions will be supervised by exercise physiologists.

A strategy to promote adherence to the exercise programme will be implemented. Researchers will stay in contact with participants throughout the exercise programme and exercise sessions will be monitored when changes are made to the programme, or as requested by the participant. Participants will be encouraged to contact the researchers if they have any queries or concerns about their exercise programme, and we aim to keep the programme flexible and individualised. 

Heart rate will be monitored during all exercise sessions using a provided Polar heart rate monitor and watch. This data will be used to quantify exercise training volume and adherence to the exercise programme.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>Women aged 50-80 years without cardiovascular disease with no chronic medical problems and not currently taking any cardiovascular or renal medications. All control participants will have an exercise history of less than 150 minutes per week of moderate-intensity dynamic endurance-type exercise over the prior 6 months. All healthy women will perform the 16-week exercise intervention. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum exercise capacity (peak oxygen uptake, VO2 peak) via the analysis of expired gas fractions and volumes with a metabolic cart during an incremental upright cycle test to volitional exhaustion. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke volume during sub-maximal upright cycle exercise via the non-invasive CO2 rebreathing techique </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke volume during maximal upright cycle exercise via the non-invasive CO2 rebreathing techique </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left ventricular mass via MRI </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral (calf) vascular conductance during supine rest via venous occlusion plethysmography using indium-gallium strain gauge </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral metaboreflex control of blood pressure via manual auscultation of the brachial artery during ischemic rhythmic handgrip exercise</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5-day physical activity levels via an accelerometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life via a Short-form 36 Quality of life questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal peripheral (calf) vascular conductance via venous occlusion plethysmography using an indium-gallium strain gauge, assessed after ischemic calf extensions</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral metaboreflex control of heart rate via 3-lead ECG during ischemic rhythmic handgrip exercise</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left ventricular end-diastolic and end-systolic volume via MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral metaboreflex control of blood flow via venous occlusion plethysmography using indium-gallium strain gauge during ischemic rhythmic handgrip exercise</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior and after 16-weeks of exercise training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Cardiovascular disease cohort
Women aged 50-80 years
Have had a documented prior event or surgical intervention associated with coronary heart disease including but not limited to myocardial infarction, percutaneous coronary intervention and/or coronary artery bypass graft. 
Performing less than 150 minutes per week of moderate-intensity dynamic exercise over the prior 6 months. 

Healthy control (without cardiovascular disease) cohort.
Women aged 50-80 years
Performing less than 150 minutes per week of moderate-intensity dynamic exercise over the prior 6 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Heart failure
Significant cardiac arrhythmia or severe valvular disease
Cerebrovascular disease (as evidenced by previous stroke or transient ischemic attack)
Severe obesity (BMI&gt;40kg/m2)
High levels of frailty (assessed by clinical frailty scale)
Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
Renal disease
Recent (&lt;4 wk) hospital admission with a cardiac event</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The effect of cardiovascular disease on peak exercise capacity and participant characteristics will be assessed by Student's t-test. To determine the interaction effects of group and exercise condition on exercise variables, a repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be performed. Secondary analysis (post-hoc testing) will be performed if an interaction effect that includes time achieves a p value &lt;0.05.

Training-related changes in peak exercise capacity and participant characteristics will be assessed with paired t-tests. To determine interaction effects of group and time point on exercise variables, a repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be performed. Secondary analysis (post-hoc testing) will be performed if an interaction effect that includes time achieves a p value &lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/04/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research office
Building 620
Level 10
49-51 Symonds St
Auckland, 1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is a significant health and life-threatening chronic disease in New Zealand women.

CVD is associated with a diminished exercise capacity, which is particularly profound in women. A low exercise capacity has severe clinical consequences as it is strongly associated with the development of chronic disease (heart failure, stroke, obesity, some forms of cancer), and cardiovascular-related and all-cause mortality. Although women with CVD have a high risk of poor clinical outcomes, there has been scarce research examining cardiovascular function in this patient population. 

Regular exercise increases exercise capacity and cardiovascular function in healthy young adults. Young and older healthy females demonstrate a blunted cardiovascular adaptation to dynamic (endurance) exercise training compared to their male peers. Despite evidence that suggests that women have a unique response to dynamic exercise training, there is very limited data comprehensively describing the cardiovascular adaptations to exercise training in late middle-aged and older women with and without CVD. Understanding how women with CVD respond to exercise training has important implications for prescribing  exercise programmes to women in cardiac rehabilitation to achieve optimal health outcomes. 

Thus, the global objective of this study is to examine the effects of CVD and dynamic (endurance) exercise training on cardiovascular structure, function and circulatory control in late middle-aged and older (50-80 yr) women. Secondary outcomes include physical activity levels and physical and health-related quality of life. 

A comprehensive array of physiological measurements will be collected to examine the effects of CVD and a 16-week exercise-based intervention on cardiac and blood vessel structure and function. This testing will include sub-maximal and maximal exercise testing, resting and exercise vascular function measurements, and non-invasive imaging (MRI) of resting cardiac structure.

There are two main hypotheses attached to this project;
Hypothesis 1: It is hypothesized that women with CVD will have a markedly impaired exercise capacity, cardiovascular function during exercise, quality of life and physical activity levels compared to aged-similar healthy controls. 

Hypothesis 2: It is hypothesized that four-months of dynamic exercise training will improve exercise capacity, cardiovascular function during exercise, quality of life and physical activity levels in women with CVD.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
Wellington, 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Graeme Carrick-Ranson</name>
      <address>Department of Exercise Sciences
University of Auckland 
Building 731, 
261 Morrin Rd, 
St Johns, 
Auckland, 1072</address>
      <phone>+64 09 373 6849</phone>
      <fax>+64 09 373 7043</fax>
      <email>g.ranson@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Graeme Carrick-Ranson</name>
      <address>Department of Exercise Sciences
University of Auckland 
Building 731, 
261 Morrin Rd, 
St Johns, 
Auckland, 1072</address>
      <phone>+64 09 373 6849</phone>
      <fax>+64 09 373 7043</fax>
      <email>g.ranson@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Graeme Carrick-Ranson</name>
      <address>Department of Exercise Sciences
University of Auckland 
Building 731, 
261 Morrin Rd, 
St Johns, 
Auckland, 1072</address>
      <phone>+64 09 373 6849</phone>
      <fax>+64 09 373 7043</fax>
      <email>g.ranson@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Graeme Carrick-Ranson</name>
      <address>Department of Exercise Sciences
University of Auckland 
Building 731, 
261 Morrin Rd, 
St Johns, 
Auckland, 1072</address>
      <phone>+64 09 373 6849</phone>
      <fax>+64 09 373 7043</fax>
      <email>g.ranson@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>