<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364439">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000713796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>PENOH - Percutaneous Endoscopic Gastrostomy versus Nasogastric Tube Feeding in Older Hospitalized Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An evaluation of complication rates in percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy versus nasogastric tube feeding in dysphagic older hospitalized patients
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1144-8493</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PENOH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysphagia on Older Patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Percutaneous Endoscopic Gastrostomy - A feeding tube is inserted through the skin on the abdominal wall into the stomach with the aid of an endoscope which is inserted into the stomach for direct visualization of the procedure. The patient usually needs light sedation and local anaesthetic. The intervention will continue for as long as required by the patient. Patients will choose to have a PEG inserted for feeding purposes or whether to stay in NG feeding. Patients will be recruited if they are judged to require enteral feeding for a minimum of 6 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nasogastric tube feeding - A finebore nasogastric feeding tube is inserted via the nostril through the nasopharynx, oropharynx and oesophagus into the stomach. The patient is asked to swallow during this procedure to aid the introduction of the feeding tube. NG feeding will continue for as long as clinically required. Patients will choose to have a PEG inserted for feeding purposes or whether to stay in NG feeding. Patients will be recruited if they are judged to require enteral feeding for a minimum of 6 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Complication Rate- including procedural complications, pneumonia, missed feeds, hospitalizations, tube dislodgement</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedural complications
-discomfort, dislodged tube, replacement, infection, perforation and any unexpected outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospitalization</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pneumonia</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional Status- assessed with the MNA</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality- Verified through hospital records and national registry</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life of Patient and Carer- determined by EUROQoL and SF-12 respectively</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Patients have to be 65 years old and above with a diagnosis of dysphagia.

- Recommended for long term nutritional support via the enteral route.

- Likely to require artificial feeding for at least 6 weeks.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Patients had contraindications to either NG feeding or PEG feeding.

- Terminal phase of illness, acute gastrointestinal haemorrhage, acute coronary syndrome and end-stage dementia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>100 patients and their carers will be approached to participate in the study once identified by their physician as suitable. They will be provided with information about the study and a contact number and a further appointment made for 24 hours later for the consent process. Consent will be sought from the patients or the next-of-kin.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation is not done.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline characteristics were analyzed by using the Independent t-test, after the Shapiro-Wilk normality testing indicated a good fit (p-value &gt;0.05). Non-normally distributed data were compared using the Mann-Whitney U test and categorical data with the Chi-squared test. Complication rates were compared at three weeks, two months and four months using the Chi-squared test and adjusted for potential confounders using logistic regression. Missing values were replaced by using the last observation carried forward (LOCF) method. Intention-to-treat analysis was performed for the composite outcome of mortality and any complication. 
Nutritional outcomes were assessed only in those patients with a minimum period of follow-up of four months. An independent t-test was used to compare findings between differing groups, with p-value &lt;0.05 considered statistically significant. For within group analysis, baseline and 4 month post tube insertion data were compared using a paired t-test. Missing data were only replaced for those lost to follow-up using multiple imputation and linear interpolation19.
 A Kaplan-Meier survival analysis and the Log-Rank test were used to compare survival between the NG group and PEG group. The Cox-regression model was then used to determine the effect of tube feeding on survival controlling for differences in the co-variables at baseline. To determine differences in time to first hospitalization and death, sets of similar survival analyses were performed using the Cox-regression method.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>102</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/10/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Malaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine,
University of Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Malaya
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50603 Kuala Lumpur
Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Halyard Healthcare</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Tower 2, Wisma AmFirst, Jalan SS7/15 (Jalan Stadium), Kelana Jaya, Petaling Jaya, Selangor 47301</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will explore the potential use of PEG feeding in dysphagic older people requiring artificial feeding for a variety of medical conditions in an Asian population.  A study exploring long term nutritional support in the elderly population such as this will have important implications for the care of older people in developing countries as it contributes significantly to the socioeconomic burdens of these countries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lembah Pantai,
59100 Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>974.5</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tan Maw Pin</name>
      <address>A/Prof Tan Maw Pin,
Department of Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine,
University of Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60162066558</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mptan@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mohamad Hasif Bin Jaafar</name>
      <address>Mohamad Hasif Bin Jaafar,
Department of Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine,
University of Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60189630117</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hasifjaafar@siswa.um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tan Maw Pin</name>
      <address>A/Prof Tan Maw Pin,
Department of Medicine,
Faculty of Medicine,
University of Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60162066558</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mptan@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hasif Jaafar</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine 
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60189630117</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hasifjaafar@siswa.um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>