<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83795">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000222246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Observational study monitoring the effects of oral cabergoline on avoidance of symptoms of Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome (OHSS) in patients at risk of ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome when undergoing an In-Vitro Fertilisation (IVF) cycle</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An observational study monitoring the effects of oral cabergoline on avoidance of symptoms of Ovarian Hyperstimulation Syndrome (OHSS) in patients at risk of ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome when undergoing an In-Vitro Fertilisation (IVF) cycle.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CABERGOLINE FOR OHSS</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (OHSS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In an IVF cycle oral cabergoline tablets 0.5mg per day will be taken from the day of initiation of follicular maturation by the sub-cutaneous injection of human chorionic gonadotrophin (HCG) prior to egg collection for a total of seven days. Despite egg collection and their fertilisation by their partner's sperm, embryos will be frozen and no fresh embryo transfer will be performed as these patients are at risk of OHSS. This is a 3 year observational study of all patients at risk of OHSS. Patients will only take the cabergoline as described if they are considered at risk of OHSS during their IVF cycle.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison will be our historical data (2006-2009) of hospital admission for OHSS.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OHSS. This is an internationally defined medical condition based on patient's symptoms and clinical tests; ultrasound examination and blood tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every patient in every IVF cycle is observed closely for the symptoms of OHSS after their egg collection and prior to the onset of menstruation (usually approximately 14 days). They will be in daily contact with the IVF unit in case of any emergency and they will be asked about any symptoms on a regular basis during the study, at the discontinuation of cabergoline and at the end of onset of menstruation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Side-effects or adverse outcomes. None are anticipated from the previous reported Randomised Controlled Trails (RTCs) and cabergoline is regularly used in gynaecological practice. The side-effects will be determined by verbally asking the patients and if required appropriate clinical tests will be performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>OHSS is a rare consequence of IVF occurring in approximately 1-3% of IVF cycles. Our unit undertakes roughly 400 cycles per year and it is therefore envisaged that approximately 4-12 patients per year will be recruited. They will be given cabergoline for seven days from the time of HCG injection. This observational study will run for 3 years and will include all patients at risk of OHSS administered with cabergoline. They will all be asked about any side-effects from the treatment during the course of this seven day time period on a regular basis and at the end of the 7 day period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients whose oestradiol level is &gt;15,000 pmol/l, or more than 20 follicles on ultrasound examination prior to the day of HCG trigger</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with a significant concurrent medical illness or a contraindication to the administration of cabergoline.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fertility Specialists of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bethesda Hospital, 25 Queenslea Drive, Claremont WA 6010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>School of Women's and Infants Health, University of Western Australia (UWA)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>King Edward Memorial Hospital, 374 Bagot Road, Subiaco WA 6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>2 randomised controlled trials have demonstrated the safety and efficacy of cabergoline to limit the development of ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (OHSS) in women at risk of this condition undergoing IVF treatment. This prospective observational study aims to look at the incidence of the development of the condition and any side-effects caused by the administration of cabergoline by women at risk of OHSS.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR 147/2008</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Roger Hart</name>
      <address>Fertility Specialists of Western Australia
Bethesda Hospital, 25 Queenslea Drive, Claremont WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93406419</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rogerhart@fertilitywa.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Roger Hart</name>
      <address>Fertility Specialists of Western Australia
Bethesda Hospital, 25 Queenslea Drive, Claremont WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93406419</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@fertilitywa.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Roger Hart</name>
      <address>Fertility Specialists of Western Australia
Bethesda Hospital, 25 Queenslea Drive, Claremont WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93406419</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rogerhart@fertilitywa.com.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>