<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362715">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000719831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Acupuncture on Cognitive Function in Healthy Adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects in healthy adults undergoing acupuncture in comparison to a wait-list control group in cognitive function outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will undergo 3 x 30 minute acupuncture session per week for 2 weeks (6 session in total).
Manual acupuncture will be administered by a same qualified acupuncturist throughout the study on four chosen acupoints (ST36 (Zusanli), HT7 (Shenmen), GV20 (Baihui) and CV12 (Zhongwang)). 
All participants will be treated with disposable sterile stainless steel needles (size 40mm×0.30mm for ST36 (Zusanli) and 25mm×0.30mm for all other points).
Each treatment will run for approximately 30 minutes. The needles will be inserted perpendicular to the skin surface and inserted to a depth of up to 2cm depending on the acupoint. 
These needles will be rotated backwards and forwards with an even motion at a rate of 60hz with an amplitude of 180 degree. Manipulation on each acupoint will be done immediately after needle insertion, at 15 minutes and immediately prior to removal of the needles. Stimulation on each point will last for 30 seconds.
The different deqi or acupuncture sensations experienced by the subject during needle manipulation including aching, soreness, numbness, and distension will be scored by the participant on a scale of 05 after every procedure. 
It was the acupuncturists aim to generate deqi or acupuncture sensations without provoking undue discomfort or sharp pain [Hui et al., 2000, 2005].</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator in this study will be a no-treatment wait list control group. This group will undergo the same testing procedures as the active intervention group however will not recieve any acupuncture treatment. 
Once they have completed the study within the wait list group they will be given the option to recieve acupuncture treatment.
This serves the purpose of providing an untreated comparison for the active group to examine the potential effects of acupuncture on cognitive function, while at the same time allowing the wait-listed participants an opportunity to obtain the intervention at a later date.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome in this study is the effect of acupuncture on cognitive performance. 
This will be measured by the Computerised Mental Performance Assessment System (COMPASS) which will be employ a range of computerised tasks to assess attention, short-term and working memory, executive and visospatial function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary endpoints will be the results from the COMPASS measured before any treatment and after all 6 acupuncture treatment only.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measure in this study will be evoked potentials assessed with non-invasively electroencephalogram (EEG). 
Visual and auditory P300 waveforms will be assessed for changes in amplitude and latency. 
Frequency power will also be assessed using the EEG.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary endpoints will be the results from the EEG measured before any treatment and after all 6 acupuncture treatment only.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy adults aged between 25 and 75 years of age
Non-smoker
Mini Mental State Exam (MMSE) score &gt; 21</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Use of acupuncture within a month.
- Current use of cognitive therapies such as gingko biloba or other supplements
- History of severe diseases such as diabetes with complications, asthma, serious pulmonary disorders; history of insomnia, anxiety, epilepsy, psychiatric disorders.
- Any mental illness as reported by the potential participant
- History of drug or alcohol abuse 
- Pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be briefed and informed consent obtained prior to the screening session. The screening session will be used to determine a participant's eligibility. 
Once they have been deemed eligible, they will be formally enrolled and provided with a study identification number. 
They will then be allocated to either a wait list control or active treatment group. Participants and study researchers will not be blinded however allocation will be concealed and randomised by the CompleMED Research Program Coordinator who is external to the research team. Allocations will be individually sealed according to participant enrollment and only opened once a participant is fully enrolled</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised via a computer randomisation package conducted externally to the research team by a CompleMED Research Program Coordinator. The researchers will be concealed to the randomisation process.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study is a parallel group, randomized wait list-controlled pilot study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2560</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research (CompleMED)
University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus, Building 5
Locked Bag 1797, Penrith
NSW 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research (CompleMED)
University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus, Building 5
Locked Bag 1797, Penrith
NSW 2751</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is aim to determine whether acute acupuncture intervention can improve cognitive functionality in a cohort of relatively healthy participants.

We hypothesize that there will be a statistically significant increase in both behavioural and physiological measures of cognitive performance in comparison to untreated control after six acupuncture treatments.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
Kingswood Campus, Building K
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H8196</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yu-Ting Sun</name>
      <address>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research (CompleMED)
University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus, Building 5
Locked Bag 1797, Penrith
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+612 4620 3278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>16595082@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yu-Ting Sun</name>
      <address>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research (CompleMED)
University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus, Building 5
Locked Bag 1797, Penrith
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+612 4620 3278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>16595082@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yu-Ting Sun</name>
      <address>Centre for Complementary Medicine Research (CompleMED)
University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus, Building 5
Locked Bag 1797, Penrith
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+612 4620 3278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>16595082@student.uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>