<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372543">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000389303p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Teleconsulting versus normal consulting in the care of inflammatory bowel disease in rural Southern District Health Board patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Establishing the role of Teleconsulting in the care of chronic conditions in rural areas of the Southern District Health Board (SDHB): A randomised controlled trial (RCT) in patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1194-1395</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Crohn's disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>ulcerative colitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>inflammatory bowel disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1:
The intervention will last 12 months for each participant. Teleconsulting + IBDsmart. Those allocated to the teleconsulting + IBDsmart group will be treated in teleconsulting suites in Dunstan and Queenstown for the duration of the study. Their gastroenterologist will be situated at a teleconsulting unit in Dunedin Hospital. IBDsmart is a previously developed smartphone app that contains validated disease activity indices for IBD patients that can be completed by the patient on their smartphone and sent directly to their gastroenterologist and/or IBD Nurse remotely. A profile containing the patients details is generated by the IBD Nurse and IBDsmart is downloaded to the patients smartphone. Before each teleconsulting clinic, the patient will send a symptom score from the IBDsmart app on their phone to the gastroenterology unit in Dunedin and the generated report including past scores will be uploaded to Health Connect South. Crohns disease (CD) patients will send a Harvey-Bradshaw Index (HBI) and ulcerative colitis (UC) patients will send a Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index (SCCAI). 
The teleconsultations will occur as often as they normally would for the patient (e.g., if the patient is normally seen by their gastroenterologist every six months, each teleconsultation will happen six monthly). Each teleconsultation will be of the normal length of an outpatient appointment (i.e. 15-30 minutes). The teleconsultations will replace normal person-to-person appointments and the content of them will be the same apart from the fact the doctor will not be sitting in the same room as the patient.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2:
Those allocated to the standard medical care group will be seen by their gastroenterologist in person for the duration of the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease control. Measured by clinical disease activity indices measured at each clinic visit, frequency of clinic visits, number of flare-ups, and frequency of emergency consultations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease specific quality of life. Measured using the Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire (IBDQ). The IBDQ contains 32 items divided into 4 health subdimensions: bowel symptoms (e.g., loose stools, abdominal pain; 10 items), systemic symptoms (e.g., fatigue, sleeping problems; 5 items), social functioning (e.g., limited social activity, school, or work attendance; 5 items), and emotional functioning (e.g., irritability, anger, depression; 12 items). The IBDQ has a minimum clinically significant change score of 20 points.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectivness. A cost-effectiveness analysis comparing teleconsulting + IBDsmart to standard medical care for IBD patients in Central Otago will be conducted from a predominantly societal perspective. Direct costs will comprise service delivery costs including clinician time and travel, clinic, technology costs and additional medical costs such as hospital in-patient care. Indirect costs will include out-of-pocket costs to patients such as GP visits, travel costs and time off work.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability. Measured using custom made questionnaires prepared for the Dr and patients in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) diagnosed with IBD, 2) aged 18 or older, 3) living rurally, and 4) able to speak English. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>do not have IBD, aged less than 18, not living rurally, and unable to speak English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be performed by the biostatistician (statistician, who will not be involved in recruitment or screening). A small random component will be incorporated to conceal allocation.   Statistician will allocate patients in batches and return these with a non-informative group code (A or B).  Statistician will remain blinded to the actual groups until all primary analyses are completed. </concealment>
    <sequence>Fifty percent of patients will be randomly allocated to the teleconsulting + IBDsmart group and 50% to standard medical care (face-to-face clinics). Allocation will be performed by the biostatistician using minimisation  by disease category (CD versus UC, and IBD-unspecified), severity (low-need versus high-need ), and centre.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The electronic data will be managed in a password protected database and all physical records will be kept under lock and storage.
The two groups will be compared using regression models examining follow-up outcomes while adjusting for baseline values.  Standard regression diagnostics will be performed.  Should missing data rates exceed 5%, multiple imputation will be used to generate data sets for data missing (completely) at random (M[C]AR) and plausible scenarios will be examined for missing not at random (MNAR). Analyses will be performed using Stata 14.2 and/or R 3.3.2.
The RCT is designed to demonstrate non-inferiority with 80% power where this is defined by IBDQ scores being less than or equal to 20 pts lower (SD 38), SCCAI scores less than or equal to 3 points lower (SD 3.5) in UC, and HBI scores less than or equal to 3 points lower (SD 4.7) in CD,  when using one-sided 95% CI.  Without making any assumptions about correlations between baseline and follow-up scores, this will require n=90 participants with IBD at follow-up (for IBDQ), and n=62 with CD and n=34 with UC (for the disease-specific scales).  Our previous research suggests that approximately 50% of cases will be CD, 40% UC, and 10% indeterminate colitis and so of the approximately 100 IBD patients living in Central Otago, assuming 80% enrolment and that loss to follow-up over the year is less than or equal to 5%, we would expect approximately 75 IBD patients (40 CD, 35 UC) with full data.  As the study cannot be performed as a fully-powered RCT within the region (limited number of patients), we will perform an interim analysis after one year to determine whether to expand the study to other centres to achieve the required sample size.  This analysis will only proceed once a full statistical analysis plan has been produced and the results from the interim analysis will not be published if recruitment continues.  As a conservative approach, we will consider the study futile and not attempt further recruitment should the 95% confidence intervals for each outcome be strictly below the non-inferiority limits and otherwise perform the non-inferiority analyses on the final data set without further adjustment.  
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Dunedin
362 Leith St
North Dunedin
Dunedin 9016
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern District Health Board Health Service Delivery Research Grant </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Health Research South
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Crohns disease and ulcerative colitis, collectively called inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), are chronic conditions that fluctuate in severity over time; IBD is characterized by episodes of remission but also flare-ups when patients need urgent specialist attention. Research has shown that rural care for IBD patients can be suboptimal. We have developed a patient smartphone application called IBDsmart that allows direct interaction with a specialist at any time for disease monitoring but real time face-to-face contact is often still warranted. Teleconsulting allows remote but real time face-to-face patient-specialist contact. 
This study aims to perform a randomized controlled trial evaluating the role of teleconsulting in IBD management for rural patients residing in Central Otago, New Zealand. Patients residing in Central Otago will be randomly allocated to teleconsulting + IBDsmart versus standard medical care and comparisons will be made in terms of disease control, quality of life and economic sustainability. The primary hypothesis is that disease control and disease specific QoL will be non-inferior in the teleconsulting + IBDsmart group relative to the standard medical care group. Secondarily, it is hypothesized that teleconsulting + IBDsmart will be cost effective, and feasible and acceptable  to doctors and patients . If successful, this can be extended into other locations and diseases.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>New Zealand Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Christine Ho</name>
      <address>Clinical IBD Nurse Specialist
Department of Gastroenterology
Dunedin Hospital
201 Great King St,
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64275554438</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Christine.Ho@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Schultz</name>
      <address>Gastroenterologist, 
Department of Medicine, 
University of Otago, Dunedin
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64276102395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Michael.Schultz@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Schultz</name>
      <address>Gastroenterologist, 
Department of Medicine, 
University of Otago, Dunedin
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64276102395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Michael.Schultz@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew McCombie</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64272626111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mccombieandrew@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>