<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367664">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000098538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Determination of the Blood Pharmacodynamic Effects following a Single Dose of Oral Anatabine Citrate in Normal Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single site, open label study to evaluate the pharmacodynamic effects of a single dose of oral anatabine citrate in healthy adult volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1163-5079</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pharmacodynamic effects study conducted in healthy volunteers with no health condition or problem studied.

This study is being conducted in healthy volunteers who are not being treated for the conditions that anatabine citrate are indicated for.  Anatabine citrate is a naturally occurring alkaloid found in the Solanaceae plant family.  It is also the ingredient of a number of dietary supplements.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single dose study where each participant receives one dose of anatabine citrate on one occasion.  The dosage will be either 3 or 4 mg oral tablet based on body weight taken with 240 ml water.  If the subject weighs less than or equal to 81.4 kg the dose given will be 3 mg.  If the subject weighs 81.5 kg or above they will receive 4 mg.  The intervention for this trial is the test formulation of anatabine citrate.

All subjects will receive their dosage and blood samples will be collected immediately prior to dosing and then one hour after dosing via venipuncture.

Subjects who meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be included in this study.  Pre and post study laboratory tests will be performed along with an ECG and medical evaluation.  A follow up visit will also be completed to assess for safety.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacodynamic effects of a single oral dose of anatabine citrate on the ex vivo expression/activity of pro-inflammatory mediators from activated peripheral blood mononuclear cells in healthy adult volunteers.

At Visit 2, blood samples will be drawn prior to study product administration and one hour (+/- 10 minutes) post-dosing for evaluation of PD measures.  Blood samples may also be evaluated for anatabine levels, although formal pharmacokinetic evaluations will not be performed.   PD assessments will include evaluation of the production of pro-inflammatory mediators from PBMCs stimulated ex vivo with LPS.  Relationships between PD outcomes and anatabine will be explored. Serum concentrations of anatabine will be determined by validated LC/MS/MS analytical methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time zero and one hour after dosing.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Not applicable for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Not applicable for this study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males or females
In good general health
Aged between 18-65 years of age inclusive
Weighing between 45 and 100 kg
Laboratory tests within normal ranges or assessed not significant by the Clinical Investigator
Normal ECG</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current users of tobacco (cigarettes or smokeless)
Current user of anatabine citrate dietary supplements
Allergy to any of the product ingredients
Significant medical condition that could in the Investigator's opinion interfere with the study, or put the subject at significant risk
Participation in any drug or medical device study within 30 days of entering this study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is an open label, nonrandomised, uncontrolled study with one treatment.  

Each participant will be identified by a 3 digit screening number and a 2 digit subject number.  The screening number will be issued once the participant has given written consent to participate in the study and the two digit subject number will be issued after acceptance into the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be accepted onto the study based on the order of enrollment.  No randomisation programme will be used.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/01/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zenith Technology Corp Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Rock Creek Pharmaceuticals, Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2040 Whitfield Ave, Suite 300
Sarasota, FL 34243</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To evaluate the pharmacodynamic effects of a single dose of oral anatabine citrate in healthy volunteers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>No presentations or citations available. Final CSR provided to Sponsor Company for Registration Purposes</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTA/193</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Noelyn Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>noelyn.hung@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Linda Folland</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>linda.folland@zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cheung-Tak Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation Limited
156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>tak.hung@zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>