<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362738">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000743864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can a participatory workplace intervention improve sedentary behaviour and physical activity in office workers?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In office workers, is a participatory workplace intervention focussed on work tasks more effective than participatory workplace interventions focussed on discretionary time or workstation ergonomics in reducing sustained sedentary time and increasing physical activity?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be involved in one of three workplace based interventions of 12 weeks duration. Prior to the intervention participants will attend 2 structured workplace meetings each of 45-60 minutes duration with the members of their intervention group. At the first meeting, the participants will be presented with information on the important health implications of office work and discuss potential changes they could make around the focus of their intervention. At the second meeting, approximately 2 weeks after the first meeting, participants will discuss ideas for change, develop the strategies and rate their ease of implementation and likely effect, again with the assistance of a facilitator. Work groups will then be given 4-6 weeks to organise the implementation of their chosen strategies including getting organisational approval. At this point the 12 week intervention period will be deemed to have begun. There will be 2 intervention groups and an 'active' control group which will develop interventions in line with their focus as listed below:

(1) Work task modification focus to reduce sedentary behaviour and increase physical activity. For example, provision of an active workstation which is an electronic height adjustable desk that is connected to a treadmill or exercise bike enabling participants to walk and work. Other interventions may include changing default printers to a more distant location or walking to communicate with colleagues rather than emailing - to encourage incidental activity during work tasks in the workplace.

(2) Discretionary time focus to reduce sedentary behaviour and increase physical activity. For example walking during work breaks (lunch/coffee) and before and after work. Participants in this group may be provided with a pedometer for use in a steps challenge. Other interventions may include promotion of active transport, groups exercise classes or lunchtime walking groups.

(3) 'Active' control focussed on office workstation ergonomics review and modification. For example, revision of workstation set up and the introduction to active sitting, a sitting technique that encourages trunk muscle activity while sitting. Participants may be provided with an air cushion that facilitates active sitting.</interventions>
    <comparator>'Active' control focussed on office workstation ergonomics review and modification. For example, revision of workstation set up and the introduction to active sitting, a sitting technique that encourages trunk muscle activity while sitting. Participants may be provided with an air cushion that facilitates active sitting.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total sedentary time assessed with Actigraph triaxial accelerometer worn at waist level for 7 days. Accelerometry data assesses the duration and intensity of physical activity on work days and weekend days and during work time and outside of work time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sustained sedentary time (periods of uninterupted sedentary time of greater than 30 minutes) assessed with Actigraph triaxial accelerometer worn at waist level for 7 days. Accelerometry data assesses the duration and intensity of physical activityon work days and weekend days and during work time and outside of work time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total light activity time assessed with Actigraph triaxial accelerometer worn at waist level for 7 days. Accelerometry data assesses the duration and intensity of physical activity on work days and weekend days and during work time and outside of work time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of breaks in sedentary time assessed with Actigraph triaxial accelerometer worn at waist level for 7 days. Accelerometry data assesses the duration and intensity of physical activity on work days and weekend days and during work time and outside of work time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported sitting time assessed by International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) (Craig et al, 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported physical activity time assessed by International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) (Craig et al, 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported musculoskeletal pain assessed by modified Nordic musculoskeletal pain questionnaire (Kuorinka et al, 1987)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported job satisfaction modified Job Satisfaction Survey (Warr, 1990)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Readiness for physical activity self assessed by readiness for physical activity questionnaire which categorises subjects into stages of change categories (Precontemplation,  Contemplation, Action and Maintenance)(Marcus et al, 1992)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported health and productivity modified World Health Organisation Health and Work Performance Questionnaire (HPQ) (Kessler et al, 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, during last week of 12 week intervention period and 3 months post intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative feedback about the success and barriers to the intervention  - tailored feedback form</outcome>
      <timepoint>Last week of intervention period and 3 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Office based workers working 4 or more days per week, for 6 or more hours each work day</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Physical or psychological impairments that would interfere with their ability to participate in the trial, for example being wheelchair bound</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants in each organisation will be divided into 3 groups based on the physical location of the teams that they work in. Each group within the workplace will be randomly allocated (sealed envelope) into one of the intervention groups or the control group</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be to one of the 3 interventions (2 focussed on physical activity, 1 'active' control focussed on workstation ergonomics). Simple randomisation sequence will therefore be used as only only 3 options are required. Sealed envelopes will be drawn from a box at each organisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Clustered randomised and controlled trial - where three physically separated groups of workers in each participating organisation will be randomised to the intervention and control groups.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/04/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/08/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>62</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Queensland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>St Lucia
Brisbane
Qld 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Physical inactivity is one of the major causes of many chronic preventable diseases such as obesity, diabetes and cardiovascular disease. There is a growing understanding that low energy activity or sedentary behaviour and breaks in sedentary time are also independently linked to cardiometabolic risk factors. Furthermore, in the technological age, occupational physical activity has reduced. Currently, it is estimated that office workers spend approximately 75% of their working hours sedentary (sitting) and are therefore at risk of many of the adverse health consequences associated with prolonged sedentary behaviour.  Workplace activity intervention programmes have focussed on increasing moderate/vigorous physical activity typically by encouraging walking before and after work or during breaks. To date, there is no research that has examined the effect of modifying office work to incorporate short bouts of light intensity physical activity and encouraging breaks in sedentary behaviour.
Aims
1) To assess if a participatory work-based programme to encourage incidental and light intensity physical activity can reduce sedentary time of office workers
2) To assess if a participatory work task focussed intervention to promote reduced sustained sedentary time and increased incidental activity is more effective at reducing sedentary time than interventions focussed on physical activity in discretionary time or an office workstation ergonomics intervention
3) To assess if changes that result from a participatory work-based intervention programme are sustained 3 months following the intervention
4) To determine if there is a relationship between participatory workplace health programmes and musculoskeletal pain and job satisfaction</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Parry, S., Straker, L., Gilson, N., &amp; Smith, A. (2013). Participatory workplace programmes can reduce sedentary time for office workers - a randomised controlled trial. PlosOne, 8, e78957.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Wa 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/06/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR20/2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U 1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3699</fax>
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U 1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3699</fax>
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U 1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3699</fax>
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>