<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373321">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001089325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treating Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in Lockyer Valley youth following the 2011 Queensland floods </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An evaluation of a cognitive-behavioural protocol with a trauma focus in the treatment of PTSD among children and adolescents living in the Lockyer Valley following the 2011 Queensland flood disaster.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>PTSD</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention evaluated was a cognitive-behavioural manualized intervention with a trauma focus ("My story of the floods", Cobham &amp; McDermott, 2011). It consisted of 2 parent/caregiver sessions (1.5 hours duration each), followed by up to 8 individually administered child/adolescent sessions (1.5 hours duration each). Within the 8 child/adolescent sessions, there was an optional session (focusing on grief) which the majority of children did not require. A brief (~30 minutes) booster session was offered between 2 and 4 weeks after the completion of the intervention. All children were provided with a therapy workbook. The intervention was delivered by therapists who were either Clinical Psychology trainees completing a partial externship on this project under the supervision of Dr. Cobham, or experienced mental health clinicians (clinical psychologists and one psychiatrist - all with more than 5 years experience). All therapists completed training in the manualized protocol, delivered by Dr. Cobham. Treatment was conducted at children's schools in a face to face format. Sessions were weekly over a 12-14 week period (including the booster session). Only the trauma narrative component of each session was routinely recorded, however, each child's workbook was photocopied, so some measure of treatment adherence will be able to be extrapolated from this.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group - this evaluation was conducted in the context of a state government public health initiative.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic outcomes as measured using the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for Children - specifically, the % of children free of PTSD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (completed after the booster session), ~ 4 weeks after the final active treatment session. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic outcomes - specifically % of children free of other comorbid conditions met at pre-treatment. This was assessed using the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for Children (ADIS-C-IV).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnostic interview completed at post-treatment (primary time point). Also completed at 6 and 12 months following completion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Youth self-report questionnaires - specifically, the Posttraumatic Stress Reaction Index (PTSD-RI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires were administered post-treatment, 6-months after the completion of treatment and 12 months after the completion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Youth self-report questionnaires - specifically, the Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (SCAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment and 6 and 12 months following completion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Youth self-report questionnaires - specifically,  the Children's Depression Inventory - Short Version (CDI-S).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post treatment, and 6- and 12-months following completion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children who received the evaluated intervention were part of the 2011 Queensland Child and Youth Disaster Response, the overarching public health initiative funded by the Federal government, under which this intervention was delivered and evaluated.
Eligible youth were those living in disaster affected areas in the Lockyer Valley of Queensland, Australia during the floods of January 2011. Eligible youth had parental consent to participate in a 2-stage screening process which was conducted in their schools. Eligible youth had to have proceeded to the second stage of screening (the diagnostic interview) and to have met criteria for flood-related PTSD on the diagnostic interview in order to be included in the intervention.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Youth were excluded if their parents/caregivers did not consent for them to participate in treatment; if they did not meet criteria on the diagnostic interview for flood-related PTSD; or if they had a pre-existing trauma history that indicated that more intensive treatment might be required.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This trial was an open, uncontrolled evaluation of a cognitive-behavioural, trauma-focused manualized intervention. Treatment was offered in the context of a larger public health service initiative following the 2011 Queensland floods. It was not intended as a piece of research. No power calculations were conducted. Children and adolescents who required treatment were all offered the manualized intervention, and their outcomes were evaluated.
Outcome data have been examined in a preliminary fashion only at this point.
Primary outcomes (diagnostic status) will be examined using chi square analyses. Secondary outcomes (questionnaire data) will be examined using repeated measures ANOVAs.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Psychosocial</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection />
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/04/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/07/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>33</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>19/12/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4347 - Grantham</postcode>
    <postcode>4347 - Ma Ma Creek</postcode>
    <postcode>4347 - Mount Whitestone</postcode>
    <postcode>4352 - Murphys Creek</postcode>
    <postcode>4341 - Laidley</postcode>
    <postcode>4352 - Withcott</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Vanessa Cobham</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
University of Queensland
St. Lucia, 4067, Queensland,
Australia.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mental Health, Alcohol and Other Drugs Branch,
Butterfield Street,
Herston, 4029, Queensland,
Australia.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Brett McDermott</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Medicine and Dentistry,
James Cook University,
1 James Cook Drive, Townsville, QLD 4811
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The TraumaFocused Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (TF-CBT) manualized protocol is a component of the QLD Health child and adolescent mental health stepped care response to the 2011 flood and cyclone disasters. This intervention is only being offered to children identified through a two stage screening process as experiencing a posttraumatic mental health problem following the 2011 QLD disasters. The protocol consists of 2 parent sessions
and 8 sessions of individual therapy with children. Sessions are conducted in childrens schools during school hours in order to minimize the inconvenience experienced by families. 
The followup assessments (to be conducted posttreatment, 6 and 12 months following completion of treatment) consist of the same tools used to identify children in the first instance through screening. These consist of the Spence Children's Anxiety Scale, the UCLA PTSDReaction Index, the Children's Depression Inventory, and the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for Children (parent and child versions).
The broad aims of the intervention are to improve parents confidence and competence in managing their childrens posttraumatic mental health problems; and to reduce childrens symptomatology. TF-CBT has the strongest evidence base of any psychological therapy with children experiencing posttraumatic mental health problems.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Cobham, V.E., &amp; McDermott, B. (2013). My Story of the Flood: Piloting a trauma-focused CBT protocol with youth experiencing PTSD following a natural disaster. Paper presented at the World Congress of Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Lima, Peru.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The children referred to in this application received an intervention because they were part of the Statewide Child and Youth Disaster Response following the 2011 QLD floods. We are seeking to retrospectively register this evaluation in order to be able to publish the outcomes and contribute to the very small body of research examining children's mental health post-disaster. It is important to stress that the intervention (and evaluation of same) were delivered as part of the wider disaster response. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital HREC, Brisbane, Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>At the time of application, this HREC was based at the Royal Children's Hospital (RCH), then located in Herston, Brisbane. 
Herston Road, Herston, QLD, 4006.
The RCH was merged with the Mater Children's Hospital (MCH) in 2014, resulting in a new hospital and health service - Children's Health Queensland (CHQ) with a new HREC (CHQ).</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/QRCH/153</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vanessa Cobham</name>
      <address>School of Psychology,
University of Queensland,
St. Lucia, Queensland, 4067</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33469911</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vanessa@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vanessa Cobham</name>
      <address>School of Psychology,
University of Queensland,
St. Lucia, Queensland, 4067</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33469911</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vanessa@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vanessa Cobham</name>
      <address>School of Psychology,
University of Queensland,
St. Lucia, Queensland, 4067</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33469911</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vanessa@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vanessa Cobham</name>
      <address>School of Psychology,
University of Queensland,
St. Lucia, Queensland, 4067</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33469911</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vanessa@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>