<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336213">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001087044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of exercise and medical therapies to improve cardiac function among patients with exertional shortness of breath due to lung congestion</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Exertional dyspnoea with increased filling pressure - Mechanisms and treatment strategies</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diastolic dysfunction, heart failure with preserved ejection fraction (HFpEF)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be randomly allocated to; daily oral doses of ivabradine 5mg, isosorbide mononitrate 120mg, or placebo for 7 days. Assessment of cardiovascular function will be performed at rest and exercise at baseline and after the intervention.

After a 2 week wash-out, patients will be re-randomised to an exercise training intervention, daily oral spironolactone 25mg or placebo (matching) tablet for 6 months. The exercise intervention will be supervised by an exercise physiologist, and will comprise aerobic and resistance training, for 3 x 60 minute sessions per week at 65-70% maximum heart rate. Assessment of cardiovascular function will be repeated after the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (oral tablet comprising inactive filler)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of exercise filling pressure, as estimated by echo-Doppler assessment of E/e'</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days
After phase 1 randomisation to ivabradine, nitrate or placebo</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in exercise capacity, as estimated by treadmill VO2</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months
After phase 2 re-randomisation to exercise, spironolactone or placebo</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-exercise LV filling pressure, as estimated by echo-Doppler assessment of E/e'</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevention of the hypertensive response to exercise, as measured by sphygmomanometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After phase 1 randomisation to ivabradine, nitrate or placebo (7 days)

After phase 2 re-randomisation to exercise, spironolactone or placebo (6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of aortic stiffness and central blood pressure, as estimated by arterial tonometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>After phase 1 randomisation to ivabradine, nitrate or placebo (7 days)

After phase 2 re-randomisation to exercise, spironolactone or placebo (6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in myocardial deformation properties, as estimated by Doppler and 2D speckle assessment of LV strain</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We intend to recruit patients who are found to demonstrate increased E/e at exercise echo with reduced exercise capacity.  Exercise intolerance will be defined by either a previous exercise test with exercise capacity reduced &gt;20% from published normal ranges or reduction of predicted exercise capacity based on the Duke Activity Status questionnaire</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) atrial fibrillation (variations in cycle length may be problematic for calculating E/E), (2) ischemia evidenced by angina or a positive diagnostic test (where improvement of exercise capacity may be due to reduction of ischemia), (3) patients already on nitrate, ivabradine or spironolactone and (4) patients with renal impairment (creatinine &gt; 0.18) or hyperkalaemia (&gt; 5.5 mmol/L).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be identified from an large outpatient exercise echocardiography department. Patients meeting the inclusion criteria will be approached and informed of the study. After recruitment, patients will undergo a comprehensive screening assessment of myocardial (echocardiography) and arterial function (central blood pressure and arterial stiffness) at rest and exercise. If patients meet the inclusion criteria (reduced exercise capacity and raised E/e'), the hospital pharmacy will randomly allocate patients to either ivabradine, nitrate or placebo for 7 days (phase 1) and after a 2-week wash-out period, will re-randomise to exercise training, spironolactone or placebo for 6 months (phase 2).</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization will be performed from computerized sequence generation to distribute patients into the randomisation groups. Both the patients and investigators will be blinded (i.e. double blind) to treatment option. The pharmacy will control the randomisation code and is responsible for the randomisation process.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Slip Road
St Lucia QLD 4072 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Previous studies of diastolic heart failure have been limited by confusion about the definition of this entity, and evidence for specific treatments are undefined. The characterization of IFPE will permit us to identify a homogeneous group. However, the most appropriate therapeutic response to increased filling pressure causing exertional dyspnea is undefined.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Holland D, Prasad S, Marwick TH.  Contribution of exercise echocardiography to the diagnosis of heart failure with preserved ejection fraction. Heart 2010 Apr 20. [Epub ahead of print]
Holland D, Prasad S, Marwick TH.  Prognostic implications of estimated left ventricular filling pressure with exercise. Circulation CV Imaging 2010;3:149-56.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital,
Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba, Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/03/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/165</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Lucia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007000580</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/03/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr B Haluska</name>
      <address>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba 4102 Qld</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5324</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 5344</fax>
      <email>b.haluska@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>UQ School of Medicine</name>
      <address>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba, Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5324</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 5344</fax>
      <email>tom_marwick@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr B Haluska</name>
      <address>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba 4102 Qld</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5324</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 5344</fax>
      <email>b.haluska@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>