<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364302">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000591752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An evaluation of individually delivered Secret Agent Society: A multi-component social skills intervention for children with Asperger syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In children aged 8-12 years with Asperger Syndrome, is the Secret Agent Society social skills intervention program effective in improving social skills, emotion regulation, emotion management strategies, social perception and self-report popularity.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Social skills deficits</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Asperger's syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Secret Agent Society (SAS) program (Beaumont, 2010a) is a multi-component social skills intervention program for children aged 8 to 12 years old with Asperger Syndrome (AS). It was specifically designed as a group intervention to improve childrens emotional understanding and social skills through weekly group sessions, parent training, teacher tip sheets and a multi-level computer game (Beaumont, 2010a). Current study will be evaluating the SAS program delivered individually. The manualised program comprises of an initial parent information session and 9 weekly 75-minute sessions. Both parents can attend all sessions, including the parent information session, with the child. The graduate psychology student administering the program will spend the first 60 minutes of each session engaging the child in various therapeutic games and activities. This will be followed by a 15-minute review of the program content to the parent. Tips on how parents can support their child in honing their social skills will be discussed. Weekly tip sheets will also be provided through the parents to teachers so that their social skills in school will also be reinforced. Parents and teachers will be required to complete weekly home-school diaries to monitor their child's social skills and to reward their efforts at applying learnt skills.</interventions>
    <comparator>The current study employs a single-case design that typically involves the use of a small sample number of participants to study behaviour modification and therapy across a diverse population (Fitzgerald, Matson, &amp; Barker, 2011). Single-case designs are common in Autism research. Each participant in single-case research designs is the unit of analysis and serves as his/her own control by participating in all conditions (e.g., the baseline, intervention and follow-up conditions as proposed in the current study). </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total score on The Social Skills Questionnaires (SSQ) - Parent (SSQ-P) and teacher (SSQ-T) (Spence, 1995a)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-baseline (a week prior to baseline observations), pre-intervention (a week prior to intervention), mid-intervention (5 weeks), post-intervention(10 weeks), and at 6 weeks after intervention completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total Score on The Emotional Regulation and Social Skills Questionnaire (ERSSQ) - Parent (ERSSQ-P) and Teacher (ERSSQ-T) (Beaumont &amp; Sofronoff, 2008; Butterworth et al., submitted)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-baseline (a week prior to baseline observations), pre-intervention (a week prior to intervention), mid-intervention (5 weeks), post-intervention(10 weeks), and at 6 weeks after intervention completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total score on The Child and Adolescent Social Perception measure (Magill-Evans, Koning, Cameron-Sadava, &amp; Manyk, 1995) </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-baseline (a week prior to baseline observations), pre-intervention (a week prior to intervention), mid-intervention (5 weeks), post-intervention(10 weeks), and at 6 weeks after intervention completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of strategies on James and the Maths Test (Attwood, 2004a)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-baseline (a week prior to baseline observations), pre-intervention (a week prior to intervention), mid-intervention (5 weeks), post-intervention(10 weeks), and at 6 weeks after intervention completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of strategies onDylan is Being Teased (Attwood, 2004b)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-baseline (a week prior to baseline observations), pre-intervention (a week prior to intervention), mid-intervention (5 weeks), post-intervention(10 weeks), and at 6 weeks after intervention completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total score on Piers-Harris Self-Concept Scale (PHS; Piers, 1984) </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-baseline (a week prior to baseline observations), pre-intervention (a week prior to intervention), mid-intervention (5 weeks), post-intervention(10 weeks), and at 6 weeks after intervention completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Observational Measure

An observational coding tool was developed based on 2 existing rating scales (Beaumont, 2010: Barry et al., 2003) for assessing social skills of children with AS. The observational coding tool consists of 10 and 12 relevant items respectively selected from Barry and colleagues (2003) and Beaumonts (2010) rating scales, and covers 3 broad domains: non-verbal communication, cooperation and conversation, and conflict resolution. 

The child and his/her sibling will be observed on a weekly basis.  Children will choose a game from those prepared by the psychology graduate student and they will play the chosen game for 10 minutes. These observation sessions will be videotaped for later scoring using the observational coding tool.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout baseline, intervention and 6-week follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria are: (a) an AS diagnosis confirmed by a paediatrician, (b) a WASI-II pro rated IQ score of 85 or above, (c) aged between 8 and 12 years, (d) the ability to read English, (e) have a typically developing sibling aged 8 to 12 years, (f) not participating in any psychotherapy or other interventions over the course of the study, and (g) parents with DASS-21 scores within normal or mild range and Parenting Scale total score of less than 3.2. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>N/A</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study is a multiple baseline across subjects design.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size: According to Matson (2012), one participant is not sufficient to demonstrate treatment efficacy in a single-case research design, rather a replication of results across two or three cases would enhance reliability of the study. Each participant will act as his/her own control by participating in the baseline, intervention and follow-up conditions. Meta analysis (McConnell, 2002) examining the effects of interventions among children with Autism Spectrum Disorder has primarily reviewed studies with 3 or more participants; hence the current study is proposing a sample size of 3.

Data Analysis: Outcome measures will be analysed by computing a reliable change (RC) score for each participant. Computation of the RC score requires estimates of the outcomes reliability and variability for a population of children with Asperger syndrome. These estimates can be obtained from previous studies (Beaumont &amp; Sofronoff, 2008; Butterworth et al., submitted; Koning et al., in press). An RC score of 1.96 or greater is considered to reflect a reliable change (Jacobson &amp; Traux, 1991).  Observational data will be tested using the split-middle line method in conjunction with the binomial test (Portney &amp; Watkin, 2000).


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>19/07/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>3</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6102 - Bentley</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Trevor Mazzucchelli</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Social Skills Training Institute, a division of Triple P International Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1300 Milton QLD 4064, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Lynette Tan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study will trial the effectiveness of the Secret Agent Society (SAS) program delivered individually to children with Asperger syndrome. Originally designed as a group-based intervention, SAS has been found to result in a variety of benefits for children including improvements in their social skills, ability to regulate their emotions and knowledge in dealing with bullying and teasing. As such, it is anticipated that the individually delivered SAS protocol adopted in this study will result in similar improvements. Results from the study is expected to increase practitioners and parents confidence in delivering SAS individually to children and potentially increase the interventions reach.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
PO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR60/2013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trevor Mazzucchelli</name>
      <address>Curtin University
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+618 92667182</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trevor.mazzucchelli@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lynette Tan</name>
      <address>Curtin University
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61413897271</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>16072545@student.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trevor Mazzucchelli</name>
      <address>Curtin University
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+618 92667182</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trevor.mazzucchelli@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>