<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="361979">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000190808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Impact of Social Cognition Training and Oxytocin on Social Functioning in Early Psychosis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Clinical Trial Investigating the Impact of Social Cognition Training and Oxytocin on Social Functioning in Early Psychosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-4918</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Early Psychosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Social Cognition Training (SCT): 
SCT is an evidence based psychosocial intervention administered by Clinical Psychologists with expertise in social information processing deficits. Targeted treatment addresses four key areas of social cognitive impairement; emotion recognition, theory of mind, social knowledge and attribution bias. Intervention is comprised of various online training programs and group based activities. The 6 week treatment program is delivered weekly (2 x 1 hour sessions) in a small group format of 6-8 participants for a total of 12 sessions. Participants will also undergo treatment as usual (TAU), that is, continuing their standard routine clinical care (e.g., psychiatrist appointment).  
 
Oxytocin (OT) Nasal Spray:
Research focused on the neurobiology of social cognition and behaviour highlights the central role of Oxytocin (OT). This neuropeptide is implicated in modulating peer recognition and social approach/avoidance in mammals. It also plays a critical role in the development of partner preference and social bonds. 

Approved by the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA), OT is supplied by a registered compounding chemist and is matched with an identical placebo containing all ingredients except the active OT. Participants are assigned one pre-packed treatment containing identical active OT or placebo nasal spray according to the randomisation schedule developed by the chemist. OT or placebo is administered twice daily for the 6 weeks of social cognition training. We use a standard adult dose of OT that has been used in previous human studies, 24 International Units (IU; 1 puff per nostril with each puff containing 12 IU) twice daily. Moreover, participants undergoing SCT will be asked to administer an additional 24 IU dose of OT (or placebo) 10 minutes prior to the commencement of group.</interventions>
    <comparator>SCT + Placebo Nasal Spray (saline solution)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Social Cognition 
1. The Reading the Mind in the Eyes Test (RMET; Baron-Cohen et al. 2001)

The RMET consists of 36 images displaying the eye-region of human faces and depict various emotional expressions. RMET tests the inference of the internal state from subtle affective facial expression. The participant is asked to pick which of the four words best describes what the person in the photo is thinking or feeling. RMET yields a total score of correct answers. The RMET has been used widely in the research literature to demonstrate social cognitive deficits in patients with schizophrenia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Social Function 
1. The Social Functioning Scale (SFS; Birchwood et al. 1990) 

The Social Functioning Scale (SFS) assesses the most relevant areas of social functioning for the support of patients with schizophrenia within the community. The purpose of the scale is to provide a detailed evaluation of both the strengths and weaknesses of each patient?s social functioning and to identify specific objectives of intervention. The SFS covers seven areas of social functioning: (1) Withdrawal; (2) Interpersonal behavior; (3) Prosocial activities; (4) Recreation; (5) Independence-Performance; (6) Independence-Competence; and (7) Employment/Occupation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Positive and Negative Symptom Severity 
1. The Scale for the Assessment of Positive Symptoms (SAPS; Andreasen, 1984a)  

The SAPS and SANS are hallmark assessment measures of positive and negative symptoms that characterize Schizophrenia. The SAPS is a 34-item scale used to rate the severity of four positive symptoms of schizophrenia: Hallucinations, Delusions, Bizarre Behavior, and Formal Thought Disorder. Each symptom cluster is evaluated on the basis of a global rating. Symptoms are rated on a 6-point scale ranging from zero, for "none," to 5 for "severe." The SANS includes items reflecting the severity of 19 specific negative symptoms regrouped into five symptom subscales: Affective Flattening, Alogia, Avolition-Apathy, Anhedonia-Asociality, and Attention deficit. Each subscale includes a global rating resulting in a total of 24 items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Emotion Recognition Ability
1. The Facial Expressions of Emotions: Stimuli and Tests (FEEST;  Young et al. 2002)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Theory of Mind Ability
1. The Faux Pas Recognition Test (Stone et al. 1998) 
2. False Belief Picture Sequencing Task (FBPST; Langdon et al. 2007)
3. The Movie Stills Task (Adolphs &amp; Tranel, 2003)
4. The Cambridge Empathy Quotient (EQ; Lawrence et al. 2004)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Attribution Style
1. The Ambiguous Intentions Hostility Questionnaire-Ambiguous items (AIHQ; Combs et al. 2007)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Social Interaction Ability
1. The Interpersonal Competence Questionnaire (ICQ; Buhrmester et al. 1988)
2. The Social Skills Performance Assessment Task (SSPA; Patterson et al. 2001)
3. Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS; Sheehan, 1983)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Social-Cognitive Mechanisms 
1. The Eye-Gaze Task  (see Guastella et al. 2008)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Biological Measures
1. Peripheral  measures of blood to assess OT plasma levels and /or OT to AVP (vasopressin) ratio
2. Heart Rate Variability measured by non-invasive recording discs placed on the wrist and neck.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Symptom Severity
1. Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K-10; Kessler et al. 2010)
2. Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS 21; Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)
3. Social Interaction Anxiety Scale (SIAS; Mattick &amp; Clarke, 1989)
4. Clinical Global Impression (CGI; Roberts et al. 2009)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conducted at three assessment time points; pre assessment (following referral and diagnostic interview), post assessment (within two weeks following completion of group) and 3-month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Meets DSM-IV-TR criteria for current or past diagnosis of Schizophrenia Spectrum Psychosis based on the SCID. (Schizophrenia, Schizophreniform Disorder, or Schizoaffective Disorder)
- Within the first three years of treatment for psychosis 
- Stabilised on psychotropic medication for atleast 6 weeks prior to participation.
- Intelligence quotient of 70 or above</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Florid psychotic sympotms and/or mania likely to require acute clinical intervention
- Current substance dependence</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This study employs a randomised controlled between-subject, double blind design. According to the randomisation schedule developed by the compounding chemist, participants are assigned to one of two treatment conditions (a) SCT combined with adjunctive OT and TAU or, (b) SCT combined with   an adjunctive placebo and TAU. Drug will be stratified by gender, years of education, duration of illness, and concurrent medication type.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/01/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
    <postcode>2046</postcode>
    <postcode>2131</postcode>
    <postcode>2041</postcode>
    <postcode>2137</postcode>
    <postcode>2132</postcode>
    <postcode>2042</postcode>
    <postcode>2040</postcode>
    <postcode>2045</postcode>
    <postcode>2204</postcode>
    <postcode>2130</postcode>
    <postcode>2007</postcode>
    <postcode>2560</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>College St  University of Sydney NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ARC Linkage Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 11 Lancaster Place
Majura Park ACT 2609
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Evidence demonstrates that social cognition training improves social cognition and social functioning in individuals with a psychotic disorder. The aim of this study is to determine the critical cognitive and biological markers underlying the effects of social cognition training and the degree to which they predict changes in social functioning for young people with a psychotic illness. 
As suggested in the literature, face perception, emotion recognition, theory of mind and attribution bias are key cognitive markers of social functioning in humans. We speculate that OT may further underlie these cognitive changes via feedforward mechanisms stimulated by engaging with social cognition training. This will be investigated by examining the impact of social cognition training on plasma levels. We also directly administer OT in-order to amplify biological and cognitive markers that facilitate improvements in social-functioning. 

Hypotheses
Following SCT treatment, individuals with early psychosis in the SCT + OT + TAU condition compared to SCT + Placebo + TAU condition will demonstrate:

Outcome Hypothesis
1. Significant improvement on measures of social cognition and social function. 

Mechanism Hypothesis
1. OT administration will enhance social-cognitive and biological markers compared to the placebo condition.
2. OT administration will enhance social functioning outcomes following SCT training compared to the placebo group.
3. Changes in biological and social-cognitive markers in both the OT and Placebo SCT groups will predict improvements in social functioning. This association will be stronger in the OT condition given the influence of OT on critical markers will be amplified.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) - The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6 
Jane Foss Russell Building G02
University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13166</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/09/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Adam Guastella</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney
100 Mallett St, Camperdown 
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0799</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 0731</fax>
      <email>adam.guastella@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Cristina Cacciotti Saija</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney
100 Mallett St, Camperdown 
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0799</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 0731</fax>
      <email>cristina.cacciottisaija@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cristina Cacciotti Saija</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney
100 Mallett St, Camperdown 
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0799</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 0731</fax>
      <email>cristina.cacciottisaija@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Adam Guastella</name>
      <address>100 Mallett St
Camperdown, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93510539</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>adam.guastella@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>