<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363812">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000301763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dietary modification for asthma control in pregnancy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of dietary modification to improve asthma control in pregnant women with asthma.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>At ~12 weeks gestation, asthmatic women will be recruited to participate in the 12 week intervention study, with an initial 4 week run-in period. At this initial visit, women will have the study procedures explained and have their asthma assessed (by a respiratory nurse). At 14 weeks gestation, the run-in period will commence in which all women will be provided asthma management, education and advice (by a respiratory nurse). It is important that the women in the study receive this, as previous data obtained from Lyell McEwin Hospital indicate that 16% of pregnant women have asthma and it is often poorly controlled, leading to high exacerbation rates. These procedures will also occur at week 16 and at week 18, in which the women will then be randomized into a control or intervention group.

The intervention group will be advised to consume increased consumption of foods containing antioxidants (i.e. at least 5 servings of vegetables/day, at least 2 servings of fruit/day) as well as antioxidant-rich nuts and wholegrains. The intervention group will receive a booklet on the current Australian Guide to Healthy Eating for pregnancy in which the desirable number of servings of food groups are outlined. Participants will be counselled and provided with a list of foods containing antioxidant-rich foods, and will be asked to identify which types of fruits and vegetables they are most likely to purchase and consume over the 12 weeks. They will also be given meal/snack suggestions to assist compliance.

Every 2 weeks during the intervention (i.e. weeks 20, 22, 26 and 28), women will be phoned by the registered nutritionist who will provide additional dietary counselling and support regarding the consumption of antioxidant-rich foods and will be questioned on their fruit and vegetable intake. Telephone calls will last approximately 15 minutes. Mid-way through the intervertion (i.e. ~24 weeks gestation), women will come to Lyell McEwin Hospital to also have this dietary counseling, along with further assessments.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive standard care which includes a booklet on healthy eating during pregnancy and lactation. No other dietary education will be provided to this group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Asthma control score, using the validated ACQ6 questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed every 2 weeks during the 12 week study (i.e. at ~18, 20, 22, 24, 26 and 30 weeks gestation).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma circulating concentrations of antioxidants </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning and at the end of the 12 week study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Markers of oxidative stress (plasma 8-F2 isoprostanes)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning and at the end of the 12 week study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exhaled nitric oxide (FENO: direct measure of airway inflammation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning and at the end of the 12 week study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to, and number of, exacerbations: Asthma exacerbations during pregnancy (moderate and severe exacerbations) defined as events for which the participant sought medical attention (i.e. an unscheduled visit to a doctor, presentation to the emergency department room or admission to hospital, or when oral corticosteroids were used for treatment of asthma).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the beginning and at the end of the 12 week study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant women with mild or moderate/severe asthma and currently using inhaled corticosteroids, &gt;18 years of age, and poor diet quality (less than 1 serving/day fruit and less than 2 servings/day vegetable, determined from Food Frequency Questionnaire).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Recent (past month) respiratory tract infection, intermittent asthma, current smoker, use of antioxidant supplements, or previous pregnancy complications including growth restriction, still birth or preterm delivery.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>At ~12 weeks gestation, asthmatic women will be recruited to participate in the 12 week intervention study, with an initial 4 week run-in period. At this initial visit, women will have the study procedures explained and have their asthma assessed. At 14 weeks gestation, the run-in period will commence in which women will be provided asthma management, education and advice. At week 18 of gestation (after the run-in) the women will be randomized into a control or intervention group.</concealment>
    <sequence>A telephone randomization service with balanced variable blocks, prepared by an independent investigator, will be used. Stratification will be by parity and pre-pregnancy asthma severity. During the randomization call, eligibility will be checked and information collected to enable stratification and assist in follow-up.</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>All statistics will be performed using SPSS version 20.0 (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Frequencies and descriptives of the study population will be reported as mean (SD) or between groups as mean (+/-SEM). Prior to hypothesis testing, the distribution of the data will be examined for normality. Any skewed data will be natural log transformed. Outcome comparisons will be made according to the treatment allocation at randomization on an intention to treat basis. Both adjusted and unadjusted analyses will be carried out. Continuous variables with repeated measurements (i.e. ACQ6 score, blood results) will be analysed using a generalized linear mixed model with a random intercept for individuals to account for repeated measurements. Planned sub-analyses will be undertaken to assess the effects of asthma severity, asthma control, FEV1, FENO, on the primary and secondary outcomes. All tests will be conducted two-sided, and a P-value P&lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>104</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth Vale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Robinson Institute
Level 2, Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Road
Elizabeth Vale, SA, 5112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Asthma is the most common serious medical problem to complicate pregnancies worldwide, with a prevalence between 8-13%, and affecting around 12% of pregnant women in Australia or 36,000 pregnancies each year. The health expenditure on asthma is significant and the economic burden of asthma is high. A recent meta-analysis demonstrated clear associations between asthma in pregnancies and adverse perinatal outcomes, with a 22-54% increased risk for low birth weight, small-for-gestational age, preterm delivery and pre-eclampsia. Previous work the laboratory also indicates asthma exacerbation contributes to poor outcomes including preterm delivery, growth restriction and stillbirth, and occurs in up to 55% of pregnancies. Oxidative stress is a potential mechanism driving the increased incidence of asthma exacerbation in pregnancy. Oxidative stress and inflammation manifest during pregnancy; however asthma in pregnancies further intensifies oxidative stress. We have previously identified that there are altered pathways regarding oxidant and antioxidant status in pregnant women with asthma, and consumption of antioxidant rich foods are beneficial for asthma control in non-pregnant adults with asthma. It has not been investigated whether antioxidant-rich foods can improve the elevated oxidative stress that occurs with asthma in pregnancies, thereby improving asthma control.
We will reverse this oxidative burden through intervening with antioxidant-rich foods. We propose that 12 weeks of increased consumption of fruits, vegetables and wholegrains will modify the maternal biochemical profile of pregnancies complicated by asthma such that markers of oxidative stress will decrease and levels of antioxidants will increase. This novel approach will counteract the added oxidative stress caused by asthma during pregnancy and subsequently improve asthma control. No dietary guidelines exist for asthma management during pregnancy. Outcomes from our study will provide an avenue for which the development of new asthma management strategies can be devised.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (TQEH/LMH/MH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Basil Hetzel Institute
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South, SA, 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jessica Grieger</name>
      <address>School of Paediatrics and Reproductive Health
The University of Adelaide
The Robinsons Institute
Level 2
Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Rd, Elizabeth Vale, SA, 5112</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8133 2132</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.grieger@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Vicki Clifton</name>
      <address>School of Paediatrics and Reproductive Health
The University of Adelaide
The Robinsons Institute
Level 2
Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Rd, Elizabeth Vale, SA, 5112</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8133 2133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vicki.clifton@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Vicki Clifton</name>
      <address>School of Paediatrics and Reproductive Health
The University of Adelaide
The Robinsons Institute
Level 2
Lyell McEwin Hospital
Haydown Rd, Elizabeth Vale, SA, 5112</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8133 2133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vicki.clifton@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>