<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="171">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/08/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000366651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A double-blind, dose-ranging study to determine the optimal dose of oral morphine or oxycodone needed to treat breakthrough pain for people on regular opioid in the palliative care setting.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blind, dose-ranging study to determine the optimal dose of oral morphine or oxycodone needed to treat breakthrough pain for people on regular opioid in the palliative care setting</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breakthrough Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral morphine or oxycodone.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not Applicable </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the optimal dose of either oral immediate release morphine or oxycodone solution for breakthrough pain based on the % reduction in pain scores at 30 minutes between the three doses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 30 minutes between the three doses.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. To determine lowest effective dose of either oral immediate release morphine or oxycodone solution for breakthrough pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30,60 and 120 minutes after study dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. To determine difference in the side effect profile between doses of study doses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30,60 and 120 minutes after study dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A subset of 15 patients  using Morphine as their regular breakthrough medication will be asked to provide blood samples for the purposes of an exploratory pharmacokinetic study .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Not Applicable </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>English speaking, AKPS performance status of 100 to 30, Calculated  creatinine clearance of &gt; 20 ml/minVenous blood sample for creatinine level, Stable background  oral opioid for the previous 4 days, Successfully using breakthrough doses, Physically able to complete study measures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Confusion, Uncontrolled nausea or vomiting, Suspected gastro-intestinal obstruction, Known or suspected hypersensitivity to morphine or oxycodone, Past history of substance misuse, Declines to participate.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Doses are prepared in central pharmacy and dispensed in separate numbered containers. The allocation is externally prepared and concealed from the investigators by placing each allocation in sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Computer generated; blocking used.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>26/12/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>138</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>81</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>5001 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Repatriation General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Daws Road
Daw Park 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sometimes patients who have strong pain and take regular morphine or oxycodone (opioid drugs) to treat their pain, experience times when pain breaks through the normal control provided by regular doses of pain medication.  This is called breakthrough pain. 
 Usually, extra doses of morphine or oxycodone, called breakthrough doses, are prescribed to treat this pain.  The dose of breakthrough medication that will have the best chance of relieving your pain, together with the least chance of causing unwanted side effects, is not known with certainty.
Presently doctors determines the dose, by calculating each dose as a percent of the daily dose of  regular pain medication. The calculated percent varies between doctors, we do not know if any calculated percent is better or worse than another percent. 
The purpose of this research study is to determine if there is a breakthrough dose calculation better for breakthrough pain and with fewer side effects.

Who can participate in this study?

Anyone over 18 years of age taking regular opioid medication for pain and who has taken at least one breakthrough dose in the last 7 days. 

You will then be provided with six doses of oral morphine or oxycodone solution (depending on your usual medication) to use when you have breakthrough pain over the 28 day study period.You will take a total of 3 different strengths of medication over the 6 doses. You can be assured that you will take a dose of medication that would normally be expected to give relief each time.
  Each dose will be individually packed and is a complete dose in itself. Each time you need a breakthrough dose for pain, for the first occurrence of pain for the day you will be asked to take one of the doses supplied by the study.
 After each study dose taken, you will need to answer some questions about your pain and other symptoms four times in the records packed with the doses. 
You will be in the study until all 6 study doses have been taken, for up to 28 days. During that time you will be contacted by telephone by the study nurse each week. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Drive 
Bedford Park
SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>66/067</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2005</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Currow</name>
      <address>Palliative and Supportive Services Flinders University Bedford Park SA 5042  </address>
      <phone>+61 08 82751057 </phone>
      <fax>+61 08 8275 1201</fax>
      <email>daivd.currow@health.sa.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Currow</name>
      <address>Palliative and Supportive Services
Flinders University
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 08 82751057 </phone>
      <fax>+61 08 8275 1201</fax>
      <email>david.currow@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Aine Greene</name>
      <address>Southern Adelaide Palliative Services Repatriation General Hospital 700 Goodwood Rd Daw Park SA 5041  </address>
      <phone>+61 08 82751057 </phone>
      <fax>+61 08 8275 1201</fax>
      <email>aine.greene@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Currow</name>
      <address>Palliative and Supportive Services Flinders University Bedford Park SA 5042  </address>
      <phone>+61 08 82751057</phone>
      <fax>+61 08 8275 1201</fax>
      <email>david.currow@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>