<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369819">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000013460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of forced air warming for patients undergoing interventional cardiology procedures with sedation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Maintaining normoTHERMIa during SEDation in the cardiac catheterisation laboratory: A randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>sedation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>hypothermia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomised to the intervention group will receive forced air warming for the duration of the procedure. The WarmTouchTM WT 6000 Warming Unit (Covidien, USA) will be used. The upper body blanket attachment will be used for percutaneous coronary interventions and ablation of cardiac arrhythmias. The lower body blanket attachment will be used for cardiac rhythm management device implantation procedures. Device temperature will be initially set at 43 degrees C. Participants will be monitored for sweating, flushing and thermal discomfort so that the device temperature can be titrated accordingly. The step-down protocol will be followed if a participant complains of feeling uncomfortable (Appendix A). Temperature will also be monitored at 30 minute intervals using an infrared aural canal thermometer for warming device titration purposes. If temperature rises above 37.5 degrees C, active warming will be ceased. Active warming will be ceased at the end of procedures. </interventions>
    <comparator>All randomised participants will receive usual care, which involves passive warming with heated cotton blankets throughout the peri-procedural period that will be applied at the discretion of the nurses.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypothermia defined as temperature less than 36 degrees C (measured non-invasively with an oral digital thermometer placed in the left or right sublingual pocket)</outcome>
      <timepoint>As soon as possible post-procedure (within 5 minutes)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean change in temperature (measured non-invasively with an oral digital thermometer placed in the left or right sublingual pocket)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre to post procedure (on entry to department for pre-procedural measurement and as soon as possible post procedure, within 5 minutes)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thermal comfort (Research assistant will ask participants, using a standardised script, to score how comfortable they are with their body temperature on a five point scale with the indicators 'Too cold', 'cool', 'just right', 'warm', 'too warm')</outcome>
      <timepoint>As soon as possible post-procedure (within 5 minutes)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major complications (from a medical chart review), defined as:
a.	Local infection that required re-intervention (not just antibiotics); or 
b.	Systemic infection/endocarditis.

c.	Bleeding (TIMI major [symptomatic intracranial haemorrhage, clinically overt signs of bleeding associated with a drop in haemoglobin of more than 4g/dL or fatal bleeding] or required blood transfusion or procedural/surgical re-intervention)

d.	Cardiovascular complications 
i.	Cardiac arrest (defined as ventricular fibrillation, asystole, electromechanical dissociation or ventricular tachycardia without cardiac output that required cardiopulmonary resuscitation and cardioversion) 
ii.	Myocardial infarction (defined as confirmed myocardial infarction distinct from index event)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness (The net monetary benefit (NB) for the alternate treatment options will be calculated by multiplying the effect by the willingness-to-pay threshold minus the cost. The cost-effective intervention will be the one that yields the highest expected NB.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability-free survival (measured with the World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0) </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of conducting a larger clinical trial (Descriptive statistics will be used to calculate rate of recruitment, the number of eligible patients who agreed to participate, the number of patients who received the correct protocol and the number of patients who completed the trial. Acceptability of the intervention will be evaluated by using descriptive statistics to determine the number of intervention group participants who did not tolerate the active warming device for the whole procedure.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing an interventional procedure for cardiovascular disease in the Cardiac Catheter Theatres at The Wesley Hospital and the Cardiac Catheter Laboratory at St Vincents Private Hospital, Sydney that is expected to require sedation and be of more than 30 minutes duration will be included. Interventional procedures include percutaneous coronary interventions, implantation of cardiac rhythm management devices (e.g. permanent pacemaker, implantable cardioverter-defibrillator) and ablation of cardiac arrhythmias.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded from the study if they:

-are less than 18 years of age;
-are cognitively impaired (due to inability to provide informed consent); 
-are unable to understand and speak English (due to inability to provide written informed consent); 
-are undergoing an emergency procedure (e.g. percutaneous coronary intervention for ST elevation myocardial infarction);
-are undergoing a diagnostic procedure (e.g. coronary angiogram, electrophysiology study without ablation);
-have a current temperature above 37.5 degrees C;
-are scheduled for general anaesthesia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes organized in sequential order will be used to conceal the allocation to intervention and control groups. The RA will hand the envelope to the Scout nurse only once eligibility and consent has been confirmed.</concealment>
    <sequence>All consented eligible patients will be allocated randomly to intervention and control groups. A statistician from the Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation’s Research Methods Group with no clinical involvement in the trial will generate a stratified (by site and into groups where an anaesthetist is going to be present during the procedure or not) block randomised sequence. Participants will be grouped into these strata because it will be important for the use of propofol to be balanced between the intervention and control groups. In our previous study we identified that the administration of propofol, which is only used when an anaesthetist is present, was an independent predictor of hypothermia.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>140</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>27/04/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Wesley Hospital - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Private Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute of Health &amp; Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Clinic Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>St Vincents Clinic Foundation
	Level 4
	St Vincents Clinic
	438 Victoria Street
	Darlinghurst  NSW  2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council

GPO Box 1421

Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Covidien LP, a Medtronic company, located at 6135 Gunbarrel Avenue, Boulder, Colorado 80301 USA (Covidien)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hypothermia is a known adverse effect of general and regional anaesthesia. It is associated with increased risk of complications including surgical site infections and bleeding. For this reason, it is recommended that strategies are implemented to prevent hypothermia. The most effective strategy is forced-air warming. Of note, with advances in medical technology continuing to expand the indications for minimally invasive surgical techniques, sedation is likely to be increasingly used for many procedures that once could only be performed with general anaesthesia. Interventions to prevent hypothermia from occurring, such as forced air warming, are not currently used for sedated patients. Yet, we recently observed in one of our previous studies that about one quarter of patients undergoing procedures with sedation were hypothermic after their procedure. Sedated patients who become hypothermic may be at similar risk of developing complications, like infections and bleeding, to those patients who undergo a general or regional anaesthetic. As such, investigation of the clinical benefits of preventing hypothermia in sedated patients is required. This research aims to determine whether forced air warming reduces hypothermia in sedated patients. The results could potentially benefit the large number of patients undergoing interventional procedures with sedation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uniting Care Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor Moorlands House
The Wesley Hospital
451 Coronation Drive, Auchenflower QLD 4066</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1505</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/263</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aaron Conway</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61731386124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaron.conway@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aaron Conway</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61731386124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaron.conway@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aaron Conway</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61731386124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaron.conway@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aaron Conway</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61731386124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaron.conway@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>