<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336791">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000400965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can use of active virtual reality games improve motor competence in children with developmental coordination disorder?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Among children with developmental coordination disorder, does use of active virtual reality games lead to improved motor competence, physical activity and mental health?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-6697</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Developmental coordination disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Active electronic games will involve the provision of a Sony PlayStation 3 with Move and Eye input devices and Microsoft Xbox360 with Kinect input device and a range of non-violent games for 16 weeks. PlayStation 3 games include: Sports Champions, Start the Party, TV Superstars and EyePet. Xbox360 games include: Kinect Sports, Motion Sports, Kinect Adventures, Sonic - Free Riders, Dance Central and Dr Kawashima's Body and Brain Exercises.
Children are requested to play these games for at least 20 minutes each day for at least 5 days a week. Actual dose is monitored by children keeping a diary and regular phone calls to the children to record the diary data at study headquarters.
Half of the children start with this condition then crossover to the control condition and half will follow the opposite order. There will be no real wash-out period between conditions as outcomes measures from the end of the 16 week conditions will be used.</interventions>
    <comparator>No active electronic games will involve all active input electronic games being removed from the family home with a contract that active electronic games will be avoided where possible at other locations for 16 weeks. Other than avoidance of active electronic games, participants will play games as they would without involvment in the study - ie their usual activities. This will include the ability to play any gamesbe able to play traditional electronic games using a game pad input during this period provided the family usually had this equipment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor coordination assessed by Movement Assessement Battery for Children-2.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor coordination during single leg stance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor coordination during finger to nose to finger task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor coordination during run, jump, ball strike, ball kick, ball throw and catch</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor coordination during PlayStation 3 Move Table Tennis and Archery and Xbox 360 Kinect Table Tennis and Soccer Kick tasks</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent report of child coordination difficulties interfering with daily life  will be assessed with the revised Developmental Coordination Questionnaire '07 (Wilson and Crawford 2010)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity. Time spent in sedentary, light and moderate to vigorous intensity physical activity, as well as total movement, will be assessed over 7 days using Actical accelerometers worn on the  hip. Total weekly physical activity as well as weekend physical activity and after school weekday physical activity will be assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attitudes to physical activity will be assessed using the revised Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self perceptions will be assessed using Harter's Self-Perception Profile for Children (Harter 1985) across domains of Scholastic Competence, Social Acceptance, Athletic Competence, Physical Appearance and Behavioural Conduct, and a subscale designed to evaluate global self-worth that assesses self-esteem independent from the competence domains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety will be assessed using Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (Spence 1997) across six subscales, namely panic attack and agoraphobia, separation anxiety disorder, social phobia, physical injury fears, obsessive compulsive disorder, and generalized anxiety disorder.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive symptoms will be assessed using the Moods and Feelings Questionnaire - short Form (Angold et al. 1995) that covers areas such as affective, vegetative and cognitive symptoms of depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention period and post control period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Scoring in the bottom 15 percent on the Movement Assessment Battery for Children - version 2.
Otherwise healthy.
Able to play electronic games on most days.
Metropolitan Perth.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosed disorder likely to impact on coordination, study participation or electronic game use.
Live in a shared arrangement where child spends a significant amount of time in different houses and is unable to maintain game access.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants recruited in response to newspaper, radio and school notices. Allocated to randomised and balanced ordering of intervention and control period based on sequential recruitment. Allocation was not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple alternating order.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Elligible volunteers participate in both conditions. Order is balance across participants.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/04/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>21</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Queensland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>St Lucia
Queensland 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background
A healthy start to life requires adequate motor development and physical activity participation. Currently 5-15% of children have impaired motor development without any obvious disorder. These children are at greater risk of obesity, musculoskeletal disorders, low social confidence and poor mental health. Traditional electronic game use may impact on motor development and physical activity creating a vicious cycle. However new virtual reality (VR) game interfaces may provide motor experiences that enhance motor development and lead to an increase in motor coordination and better physical activity and mental health outcomes. VR games are beginning to be used for rehabilitation, however there is no reported trial of the impact of these games on motor coordination in children with developmental coordination disorder. 
Methods
This cross-over randomised and controlled trial will examine whether motor coordination is enhanced by access to active electronic games and whether daily activity, attitudes to physical activity and mental health are also enhanced. Thirty children aged 10-12 years with poor motor coordination (below 15th percentile) will be recruited and randomised to a balanced ordering of no active electronic games and active electronic games. Each child will participate in both conditions for 16 weeks, and be assessed prior to participation and at the end of each condition. The primary outcome is motor coordination, assessed by kinematic and kinetic motion analysis laboratory measures. Physical activity and sedentariness will be assessed by accelerometry, coordination in daily life by parent report questionnaire and attitudes to physical activity, self-confidence, anxiety and depressed mood will be assessed by self report questionnaire. 
Discussion
This is the first trial to examine the impact of new virtual reality games on motor coordination in children with developmental coordination disorder. The findings will provide critical information to understand whether these electronic games can be used to have a positive impact on the physical and mental health of these children. Given the importance of adequate motor coordination, physical activity and mental health in childhood, this project can inform interventions which could have a profound impact on the long term health of this group of children.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Straker, L., Howie, E., Smith, A., Jensen, L., Piek, J., &amp; Campbell, A. (2015). A crossover randomised and controlled trial of the impact of active video games on motor coordination and perceptions of physical ability in children with developmental coordination disorder. Human Movement Science, 42, 146-160.

Larke, D., Campbell, A., Jensen, L., &amp; Straker, L. (2015). The responsiveness of clinical and laboratory measures for detecting intervention effects in children with DCD. Paediatric Physical Therapy, 27(1), 44-51.

Gonsalves, L., Campbell, A., Jensen, L., &amp; Straker, L. (2015). Children with Developmental Coordination Disorder play active virtual reality games differently to typically developing children. Physical Therapy, 95(3), 360-368.

Bufton, A., A. Campbell, E. Howie and L. Straker (2014). A comparison of the upper limb movement kinematics utilized by children playing virtual and real table tennis. Human Movement Science 38: 84-93. 

Maddison, R., Straker, L., Palmeira, A., Simons, M., Hansen, L., &amp; Thin, A. (2013). Active video games - an opportunity for enhanced learning and positive health effects? Cognitive Technology Journal, 18(1), 6-13.

Straker, L., Fenner, A., Howie, E., Feltz, D., Gray, C., Lu, A.,Mueller,F. &amp; Barnett, L. (2015). Efficient and effective change principles in Active Video Games. Games for Health, 4(1), 43-52.

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR11/2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92663634</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>