<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373249">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001065381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Volatile Anaesthesia and Perioperative Outcomes Related to Cancer (VAPOR-C): A Feasibility Study </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Volatile Anaesthesia and Perioperative Outcomes Related to Cancer (VAPOR-C): A Feasibility Study </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-8426</utrn>
    <trialacronym>VAPOR-C Feasibiity</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Adult  patients  scheduled  for  elective  major  cancer  surgery  (breast,  lung,  prostate,  melanoma, colorectal, other), expecting to last 2 or more hours and anticipated to require a minimum of one day in-hospital stay after surgery will be screened for eligibility. Recruited patients will be block randomised by cancer type to receive either volatile anaesthesia or propofol anaesthesia. . Clinicians  will  deliver propofol via weight-based technique (mg/kg/hour) or via target controlled infusion models (TCI; µg/ml  effect  or  plasma  concentration)  or  titrate  volatile  anaesthesia  at  a  minimum  alveolar concentration (MAC) to attain BIS values in the range of 40-60. FiO2 will be maintained at 40% following induction and the admixture with air titrated to maintain SpO2 &gt;95%.

The volatile anaesthetics to be used in this study are Sevoflurane, Isoflurane and Desflurane. They are all volatile anaesthetics approved for clinical use in Australia and used routinely for induction and maintenance of anaesthesia. Volatile anaesthetic dose is titrated by the treating anaesthetist in response to level of sedation, heart rate, respiratory rate, blood pressure and Bispectoral index monitoring, using a vaporiser connected to an anaesthetic circuit. 

Anaesthetists are trained to use both intravenous and inhaled anaesthetic techniques. The decision to use one technique over another is based on multitude of patient, anaesthetic and surgical factors. These include, but are not limited to: patient preference, allergy or contraindication to an agent, history of severe postoperative nausea and vomiting, medical status of patient at time of surgery, availability of equipment to perform TIVA, preference of treating anaesthetist, type, duration and location of surgery. The treating anaesthetist makes an educated decision on which anaesthetic to use for every patient guided by his or her experience and specialist anaesthetic training.</interventions>
    <comparator>Propofol is an intravenously administered anaesthetic drug approved for clinical use in Australia and used routinely for induction and maintenance of anaesthesia. Initial bolus of 2-4mg/kg is used for induction followed by maintenance infusion. 

Most often, a target controlled infusion pump (TCI) is used to deliver the maintenance infusion using a pre-programmed pharmacokinetic algorithm. If a TCI pump is not available, the infusion is titrated to clinical effect by the treating anaesthetist, and is usually administered in the range of 8-12mg/kg/hr.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the ability to recruit eligible patients into the study. Criteria: The study protocol will be assessed as feasible if a recruitment rate of at least 75% is achieved.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary endpoint will be measured at 6 months, or once all patients have been recruited, which ever occurs first.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To  measure  the  ability  to  successfully  deliver  each  of  the two  anaesthetic  techniques (volatile-based  general  anaesthesia  and  TIVA-based  anaesthesia)  according  to  the  research protocol. 
Criteria: The study protocol will be assessed as feasible if a successful delivery rate of at least 90% is achieved. 
'Successful delivery' is defined as delivery of the anaesthetic as per treatment arm for the entire operation, without limitation by correct equipment, or perioperative event indicating change from one anaesthetic technique to the other'.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary endpoint will be measured at 6 months, or once all patients have been recruited, which ever occurs first.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To  measure  the  ability  to  capture  the  emerging  key  performance  indicator  Return  to Intended Oncologic Therapy (RIOT; i.e. planned date for postoperative adjuvant therapy).
Criteria: All patient records will be screened for details of planned postoperative oncological therapy and planned date of commencement. the following outcomes will be measured:
	Percentage RIOT achieved on time

To be calculated by 'number of patients who achieved RIOT by the date determined pre-operatively by treating oncology team' / ' total number of patients who achieved RIOT'.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Variable. Expected to be 6-8 weeks post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Percentage RIOT delayed
To be calculated by 'number of patients who achieved RIOT but WITH delay' / ' total number of patients who achieved RIOT'.
Delay is defined as an actual start date for postoperative chemo-radiotherapy DIFFERENT to planned start date as determined and recorded by treating oncology team. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Variable - expected time point 6-8 weeks post date of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Percentage RIOT failed.
Defined by 'number of patients that were planned for adjuvant chemotherapy but who DID NOT achieve RIOT / 'number of patients that were intended to have postoperative adjuvant therapy as determined by the treating oncology team</outcome>
      <timepoint>variable - average of 6-8 weeks post-date of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Reasons for delayed or failed RIOT
Descriptive data on reasons for failure to achieve RIOT (eg, death, sepsis, neutropaenia, organ impairment/failure, progression of disease, surgical complication)
-This outcome will be assessed by review of patient medical records
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Variable. 6-8 post-date of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To  test  the  feasibility  of  using  routine  administrative  cost  data  to  determine  differences  in health  system  costs  and  government  funding  for  the  two  study  groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary endpoint will be measured at 6 months, or once all patients have been recruited, which ever occurs first.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days alive and out of hospital (DAOH) at 30 days post-surgery, which incorporates mortality and all hospitalizations into a single measure.
-outcome to be assessed by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male or female 
2. Age 18-80 years. 
3. Elective surgery 
4. Major cancer surgery expecting to last two or more hours, for: 
Breast (mastectomy or segmentectomy PLUS sentinel node dissection), 
Colorectal, 
Lung, 
Prostate, 
Melanoma  (excision  of  melanoma  PLUS  lymph  node  dissection  AND/OR  skin  flap construction, or 
Other major cancer surgeries (e.g. oesophagectomy, head and neck cancer, etc.) </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Palliative surgery for end-stage disease with no curative intent
2. Emergency surgery
3. Extensive co-morbid disease, i.e. ASA &gt;4
4. Refusal or inability to provide valid informed consent
5. Risk of severe postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV risk score &gt;3)
6. Previous allergy or contraindication to either anaesthetic medication
 7. Indication for gas induction of anaesthesia</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomised by someone otherwise  not  involved in the study, to limit  selection  bias. Participants will be  randomized via  a  central  computer-generated  randomization  program with direct notification to the treating anaesthetist.</concealment>
    <sequence>1. Block randomisation by cancer type.
2. Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The feasibility study requires a total of 200 participants that meet inclusion and exclusion criteria to be recruited  from the  participating  hospitals.  If 75% of eligible patients are  found to provide conformed  consent  (150/200), then  the  95%  CI  of  the  true  underlying informed  consent  rate  is [68%, 81%]. Assuming 75 patients are recruited to each arm, then if a successful delivery rate of 91%  is  observed  (68/75),  then  the  95%  CI  of  the  true  underlying successful  delivery  rate  is [82%,  96%],  using  and  exact  (Clopper-Pearson)  method  to  measure  the  95%  confidence intervals.  In  this  feasibility  study,  statistical  analysis  will  be  primarily  descriptive  and  testing  (if  any) will be  reported  with  caution.  Descriptive  statistics  will  consist of  number  and  percentage  for categorical variables. Mean and standard deviation (SD) or median and interquartile range (IQR) will be  reported  for  continuous  variables.  The  asymptotic  [Wald] method  based on  the  normal approximation for the two-sided 95% confidence interval for a single proportion will be used toobtain  the  confidence  interval  for  the  proportion of  eligible  patients  who  provided  informed consent  (primary  aim  1)  and  the  proportion of  randomized  patients  for  whom  the  anaesthetic procedure   was   completed   successfully,   for each   procedure   separately   (primary   aim   2). Successful  delivery of  anaesthetic  technique  will be  defined as  a  patient  undergoing  surgery under  assigned  anaesthetic  group,  without  crossover to  other  anaesthetic  technique  during  the operation. Reasons  for  failure to successfully  deliver anaesthetic technique  may  include  lack ofaccess to TCI pump to deliver propofol anaesthetic, or crossover to other anaesthetic technique for medical reasons, as determined by treating anaesthetist. Initial estimates of cost-effectiveness will  also be  available to  inform  design of  the  VAPOR-C  trial  and  provide an  indication of  the likely cost benefits. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>27/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Office of Cancer Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>630 St Kilda Rd., Melbourne VIC 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Melbourne Clinical and Translational Science Platform</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 202 Berkeley Street, Parkville, Victoria, 3010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative and Pain Medicine, Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to assess feasibility of conducting a randomised efficacy trial to compare two different methods of anaesthesia in patients undergoing major cancer surgery.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years and over and are scheduled to undergo major cancer surgery expecting to last two or more hours. 

Study details
Study participants will be allocated by chance to one of the two groups. Group 1 - Inhaled anaesthesia, Group 2 - Anaesthesia administered via a cannula into a vein in the arm.

This study will inform conduct of a large efficacy trial which will aim to provide insight into the mechanisms by which anaesthetics potentially drive cancer progression with the ultimate goal of developing novel biomarkers and strategies to limit the impact of anaesthetics on cancer progression.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Dubowitz, J. "Volatile Anaesthesia and Perioperative Outcomes Related to Cancer - VAPOR-C: A Feasibility Study." ANZCA Clinical Trials Network Annual Meeting, August 13, 2016, Sydney.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/PMCC/171</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bernhard Riedel</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative and Pain Medicine
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8559 7681</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernhard.riedel@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sam McKeown</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative and Pain Medicine
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8559 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.mckeownl@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bernhard Riedel</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative and Pain Medicine
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8559 7681</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernhard.riedel@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julia Dubowitz</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Perioperative and Pain Medicine
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3000</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>juliadubowitz@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>