<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367584">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000011583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of Trauma release exercises (TRE) on symptoms of restless legs syndrome (RLS): A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of Trauma Release Exercises (TRE) on International Restless Legs Syndrome Rating Scale (IRLS) scores in Adults with Restless Legs Syndrome (RLS)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Restless Legs Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Tension and Trauma Release Exercises (TRE). TRE are a series of exercises that stretch and fatigue specific muscles in the body, invoking self-induced therapeutic tremors (SITT). 
Participants in the intervention group will receive 6 TRE sessions under direct physiotherapist supervision (1 each week) and will complete home based exercises. The first physiotherapy session will be 3 hours, followed by five 1 hour sessions. At least 1.5 hours of home exercises will be required each week during this time or as required for symptom relief. 
After the 6 week intervention, participants will then complete home based exercises alone for 6 weeks (minimum 1 hour per week). 
Participants will be asked to keep a diary of when they complete home exercises. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>6 weekly sessions (1 each week) where participants will take part in focus groups discussing the lived experience of RLS. 
They will then complete 6 weeks of TRE (the same as the first 6 weeks for the intervention group). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>International Restless Legs Syndrome Rating Scale (IRLS). Measures severity of RLS on a 10 item questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at the end of each week (12 weeks total)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual analogue scale (0-10) for global RLS severity, where 0 indicates no RLS symptoms and 10 indicates very severe RLS symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at the end of each week (12 weeks total)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual analogue scale (0-10) for overall stress levels, where 0 indicates no stress and 10 indicates very severe stress</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at the end of each week (12 weeks total)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Major Depression Inventory (MDI), used to measure depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at the end of each week (12 weeks total)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified 20 item version of the Pittsburgh Insomnia Rating Scale (PIRS), a 65 item scale used to assess the severity of insomnia </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at the end of each week (12 weeks total)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must have all four of the RLS diagnostic criteria below
1.	An urge to move the legs, usually accompanied or caused by uncomfortable and unpleasant sensations in the legs
2.	The urge to move or unpleasant sensations begin or worsen during periods of rest or inactivity such as lying or sitting
3.	The urge to move or unpleasant sensations are partially or totally relieved by movement, such as walking or stretching, at least as long as the activity continues
4.	The urge to move or unpleasant sensations are worse in the evening or night than during the day or only occur in the evening or night

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Acute mental health issue, physically unable to complete the TRE exercises. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Advertisements will include an email address and phone number where participants can leave expressions of interest in participating in the study. Participants will be screened for eligibility over the phone, and those who meet the inclusion criteria will be advised that they will be randomised to either immediate or delayed intervention. They will be advised regarding the nature of the intervention and control conditions, the attendance requirements and the location of the program. Those who remain interested will be invited to enter the study and enrolled.
After enrollment, participants will be stratified for age and severity of RLS and randomly allocated to intervention or control groups using a computer generated sequence. A research assistant without any role in enrollment will complete the randomisation procedures using participant ID numbers only, and will then provide the research team with group allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intervention and control groups will be compared for primary and secondary outcomes at baseline, and at each of the subsequent 12 weeks.
Sample size was determined using a power analysis for IRLS scores (scale 0-40) based on results of similar studies where physical interventions for RLS were compared to control groups. With a sample of six in each group the study would be powered (.8) to detect a difference between means of 9 IRLS points when alpha was set at .05 using a two-tailed t test.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>11/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>18</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3931 - Mornington</postcode>
    <postcode>3930 - Mount Eliza</postcode>
    <postcode>3910 - Langwarrin</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eloise Harrison</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash University Peninsula Campus
Building C, Level 2, McMahons Road, Frankston VIC 3199</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Building C, Level 2, McMahons Road, Frankston VIC 3199</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Jenny Keating</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash University Peninsula Campus
Building C, Level 2, McMahons Road, Frankston VIC 3199</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to determine the effect of Tension and Trauma Release exercises (TRE) on the severity of symptoms of Restless Legs Syndrome (RLS). This treatment is currently offered to sufferers but no data supports its effectiveness. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.restlesslegsresearch.com.au </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee (MUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Research Office
Building 3d
Monash University
Victoria 3800
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF14/1931 - 2014000986</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jenny Keating</name>
      <address>Monash University Peninsula Campus
Building C, Level 2, McMahons Road, Frankston VIC 3199</address>
      <phone>+613 9904 4817</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.keating@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Eloise Harrison</name>
      <address>Monash University Peninsula Campus
Building C, Level 2, McMahons Road, Frankston VIC 3199</address>
      <phone>+613 9904 4817</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eghar3@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jenny Keating</name>
      <address>Monash University Peninsula Campus
Building C, Level 2, McMahons Road, Frankston VIC 3199</address>
      <phone>+613 9904 4817</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.keating@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>