<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363590">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000179730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise for falls prevention in residential aged care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Resistance and balance exercise in residential aged care for falls prevention
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL KNOWN</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Falls</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mobility and balance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fear of falling and cognition</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Progressive resistance training (PRT) and balance exercise for residents of Aged Care Facilities. Dosage is two one hour classes per week for 6 months using pneumatic resistance equipment and closely supervised high level balance exercise. PRT will target: hip and knee flexors and extensors, abdominals, back extensors, hip abductors, hip adductors, elbow and shoulder flexors and extensors. Exercise will be individually prescribed and upgraded an exercise professional (physiotherapist or exercise physiologist) to enable participants to achieve 2-3 sets of 10-15 repetitions for each exercise. Balance exercises will include a combination of heel raises, stepping in different directions, reaching outside the base of support, single leg standing, step ups and balance platform work. 

A maintenance program including balance, weight-bearing and functional exercises will continue for the next 6 months.  Sessions will be supervised by a diversional therapist or physiotherapy assistant and run twice per week for 20 minutes. </interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care - participants continue with their usual (pre-inclusion) activities for the 12 month study period but are requested not to commence a resistance or balance program during this time. Examples of such activities may include participation in games or other interests as part of the diversional therapy program within the aged care facility.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls - defined as the number of fallers and the number of falls for each participant.
This will be measured monthly for 12 months by auditing both daily progress notes and incident forms kept at the aged care facility. 
Participants will also be asked at the time of the 6 and 12 month assessments if they have fallen since they were last assessed. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured monthly for 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - Measured by the SF-36 &amp; EQ-5D-5L</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility - 1) The short physical performance battery (SPPB) will be used to evaluate, balance, gait, strength, and endurance;  2)  The Step Test will be used to assess dynamic  balance and agility; and 3) The University of Alabama  Life Space Assessment (UAB-LSA) will be used to assess the extent of mobility and frequency of movement along with any assistance needed</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of falling - Falls Efficacy Scale  international (FES-I)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognition - The Addenbrookes Cognitive Examination-R (ACE-R) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness - The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio will also be calculated relative to the control group (cost per quality of life year - QALY).  To perform this analysis the health benefits associated with the program will be estimated using the SF-36  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 12 months and extended to estimated lifetime of participant lifespan.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Permanent residents of aged care facilities.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Terminal or unstable illness; significant advanced cognitive decline (that precludes safely following direction for exercise and equipment use); specific neuromuscular disease (Parkinsons Disease, Hemiplegia post cerebro-vascular accident, syncope); permanently wheel chair or bed bound; or have performed a similar balance and/or resistance training program in the past 12 months; insufficient English to complete outcome measures questionnaires.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealed allocation via centralised computer generated cluster randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>Cluster randomisation by aged care facility using a randomisation table created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analyses will be conducted at the participant level but appropriately adjusted for clustering of participants within aged care faciities using mixed models. 
A logistic mixed model will be used to analyse the number of residents that fall during the study period (binary outcome). The number of falls (a count outcome) will be analysed using a Poisson mixed model. 

The cost-effectiveness ($AUD) component will be presented as net costs and benefits for intervention and usual care aged care facilities.  The cost of the intervention will be measured along with any cost-savings due to avoided health care utilisation. The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio will also be calculated relative to the control group (cost per quality of life year - QALY).  To perform this analysis the health benefits associated with the program will be estimated using the SF-36  a preference-based single utility measure, using Australian preference weights, will be derived from these data.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Prof Kathryn Refshauge, Prof Lindy Clemson, Jennifer Hewitt
c/o Arthritis and Musculo-skeletal Research Laboratory
A203 
Faculty of Health Sciences
75 East Street
LIDCOMBE NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Health Sciences 
75 East Street
LIDCOMBE NSW 2141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Technology, Sydney.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dr Stephen Goodall
University of Technology, Sydney.
Centre for Health Economic Research and Evaluation
PO Box 123
BROADWAY NSW 2007
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dr Tim Henwood
University of Queensland/Blue Care Research &amp; Practice Development Centre
School of Nursing and Midwifery
56 Sylvan Rd		
Toowong QLD 4066
	
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Falls are common in the population aged 65 years and over and present a major challenge to older people, health care providers and the health system.  Over one third of community dwelling people in this age group fall each year and the rate of falling is even higher in residents of aged care facilities.  There is now extensive evidence to demonstrate fall rates can be reduced using exercise.  Programs that target balance and lower limb muscle strength appear to be most successful however the vast majority of research has focused on community dwelling adults.  The results of trials into exercise on falls prevention in residential care are inconsistent.  This randomized controlled trial will test the efficacy of an exercise intervention that combines key components of programs from successful community based research on residents of long term aged care.  The primary outcome will be falls (fall rates and number of fallers). Quality of life, mobility, and fear of falling will also be measured and a cost benefit analysis will be performed.  Outcomes from this study have the potential to impact on a substantial individual and international healthcare problem. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building - G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 AUSTRALIA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14995</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kathryn Refshauge</name>
      <address>The University of Sydney
Office of the Dean 
Faculty of Health Sciences
75 East Street
LIDCOMBE NSW 2141 
AUSTRALIA
	

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9222 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9688             </fax>
      <email>kathryn.refshauge@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Hewitt</name>
      <address>Room A203
Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney 
75 East Street
LIDCOMBE NSW 2141 
AUSTRALIA

       </address>
      <phone>+61 427 226 045 OR +61 2 9036 7305</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9688 </fax>
      <email>jhew4562@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Hewitt</name>
      <address>Room A203
Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney 
75 East Street
LIDCOMBE NSW 2141 
AUSTRALIA
</address>
      <phone>+61 427 226 045 OR +61 2 9351 9000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9688 </fax>
      <email>jhew4562@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jennifer Hewitt</name>
      <address>Room A203
Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney 
75 East Street
LIDCOMBE NSW 2141 
AUSTRALIA
</address>
      <phone>+61 427 226 045 OR +61 29351 9000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 9688 </fax>
      <email>jhew4562@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>