<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372281">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000500358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>NEST4E: A pilot study into the clinical effectiveness of Non-invasive Preimplantation Genetic Screening (PGS) method for Embryo ploidy status among patients undergoing IVF treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>NEST4E: A pilot study into the clinical effectiveness of Non-invasive Preimplantation Genetic Screening (PGS) method for determining Embryo ploidy status among patients undergoing IVF treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-4733 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>NEST4E</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infertility</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Embryo genetics</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The purpose of this pilot trial is to test a non-invasive Preimplantation Genetic Screening (PGS) method for human embryos. The investigators have developed a method for amplifying cell-free DNA from human embryo culture medium and using Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) to determine embryo aneuploid vs euploid status of the embryo, This technology eliminates the need for an invasive embryo biopsy to perform preimplantation genetic screening. This trial will be conducted at Repromed on 15 patients undergoing IVF treatment that would benefit from preimplantation genetic screening. Spent media will be collected by the scientists from the embryo culture dish and used to determine if the embryo is aneuploid or euploid. Each embryo undergoes this method once only on a single occasion, with the exception that if the non-invasive screen does not provide a conclusive result, a trophectoderm biopsy will be reformed on the embryo that fails the non-invasive screen to detect aneuploidy/euploidy.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The measured primary outcomes of this NEST4E pilot study are:
The number of embryos screened as euploid that are not required to be biopsied. This will be assessed by amplifying the cell-free DNA from the embryos spent culture media, The DNA will be sequenced using next generation sequencing and the data analysed using the Illumina platform to determine the ploidy status of the embryo. If the sequence data shows that the embryo is euploid the embryo will be transferred. The embryo will be confirmed as euploid at the primary time point (ie. following preimplantation and 1st trimester screening) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Following preimplantation and 1st trimester screening.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For euploid embryos, the percentage of concordance of media sample results to non-invasive NIPT based first trimester screening which can be befriend as early as 10 weeks pregnant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following non-invasive NIPT based first trimester screening which can be performed as early as 10 weeks </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For anueploid embryos, the percentage of embryos that show concordance with confirmatory biopsy next generation sequencing screening results.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Next generation sequencing results of biopsied cells can be obtained with 2 weeks post trophectoderm biopsy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measured secondary outcomes are: 
Clinical pregnancy rates of embryos screened as euploid using the non-invasive NEST4E technology. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Determination of a positive pregnancy test occurs 12-14 days post embryo transfer via detection of HCG levels from a maternal blood test. Confirmation of a viable pregnancy is performed at 6-8 weeks of pregnancy via ulstrasound to detect fetal heart beat  Live birth outcomes will be collected 2-4 weeks post the due date as per standard clinical protocol.,</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Live birth rates of embryos screened as euploid using the non-invasive NEST4E test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Live birth outcomes will be collected as per standard Repromed patient care. This information is generally collected in writing from the treating obstetrician/doctor, or alternatively directly from the patient with a follow up phone call from the clinic nurses several weeks post due date. It is a regulatory requirement that gestation length, birthweight, sex, method of delivery and details of any maternal or neonatal complications are reported to ANZARD (Australian &amp; New Zealand Assisted Reproduction Database).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of euploid vs aneuploidy embryos as determined by NEST4E non-invasive screening. Any embryos screened as Aneuploid will undergo trophectoderm biopsy and PGS screening to confirm the aneuploidy. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collection and analysis will be coordinated by the Principal Investigator and Co Investigators, all who have had extensive previous experience with data analysis and interpretation of pilot studies and clinical trials. These results will be reported directly to the Clinical Genetics Team and the patients clinician. A Data Monitoring Committee chaired by Repromeds Clinical Director will perform an interim analysis after 5 participants embryos (approx 16-20 embryos) have been screened using NEST4E to ensure that the results are concordant with the biopsy screening. Final analysis will take place immediately after collection of the final birth outcome. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This study is a pilot study on fifteen couples (approximately 60 transferrable embryos) to assess the ability of this technology to screen embryos for aneuploidy. Participants will be consenting patients undergoing IVF treatment with PGS at Repromed, 180 Fullarton Rd., Dulwich, South Australia. Participation in the study will be offered to those patients whom PGS in general is discussed as a treatment option.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>53</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Patients involved in the Donor program (oocyte and sperm)
2.	Patients with a known infectious disease (HIV, HEP B, HEP C)
3.	Patients using Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis (PGD) for single genes or translocations.  
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>non-randomised trial </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>none</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This study is a pilot study on fifteen couples (approximately 60 transferrable embryos) to assess the ability of this technology to screen embryos for aneuploidy. Data collection and analysis will be coordinated by the Principal Investigator and Co Investigators. These results will be reported directly to the Clinical Genetics Team and the patients clinician. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Repromed Day Surgery - Dulwich</hospital>
    <postcode>5065 - Dulwich</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Repromed</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>180 Fullarton Road Dulwich SA 5065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Repromed</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>180 Fullarton Road Dulwich SA 5065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this pilot study is to evaluate the clinical effectiveness of our NEST4E non-invasive method for screening embryo ploidy by determining the number of embryos that can that be successfully screened for aneuploidy using the NEST4E rather than invasive biopsy.
Aim 1: For euploid embryos the percentage concordance of media sample screening will be confirmed using non-invasive NIPT based first trimester screening as early as 10 week pregnancy. For aneuploid embryos, we will determine the percentage of embryos with concordance by confirmatory trophectoderm biopsy and PGS screening.
Aim 2: To determine clinical pregnancy rates and live birth outcomes of embryos that are transferred once screened as euploid. 
Fifteen patients will be recruited by informed consent to participate in this pilot study to assess the clinical efficacy of our NEST4E non-invasive PGS test to screen their embryos for aneuploidy. Participants will be made aware that their participation in the study is entirely voluntary and that they can withdraw at any point in time. As per standard protocol, patient confidentially will be strictly maintained and their identity will not be revealed in any reviews and reports of this study which may be published. 
Patients treatment will not be altered in any way and will proceed as per standard IVF cycle, including medications, oocyte retrieval, insemination and fertilization and embryo culture. Patient embryos will be cultured as per standard protocols; G1/G2 Plus media (Vitrolife) overlayed with oil (Ovoil, Vitrolife) in 6% CO2, 5% O2, 37 degrees.  A 4 micro litre drop of the spent culture medium will be sampled using PCR grade filtered tips, under laminar flow, and placed into PCR grade 0.6 ml tubes and assessed for aneuploidy as described below.
DNA from the culture media sample will be amplified. If this amplification should fail, the embryo will be removed from the trial and will revert to standard care which involves a biopsy followed by vitrification and sample screening. If the amplification is successful, the embryo will be vitrified and the DNA amplified from the media sample used for screening by NEST4E. If conclusive sequence data is obtained, euploid embryos will be made available for transfer. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood South Australia 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-12-891</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michelle Lane</name>
      <address>Repromed - 180 Fullarton Road Dulwich SA 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83338111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mlane@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hamish Hamilton</name>
      <address>Repromed - 180 Fullarton Road Dulwich SA 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83338111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hhamilton@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hamish Hamilton</name>
      <address>Repromed- 180 Fullarton Road Dulwich SA 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83338111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hhamilton@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Francesca Bell</name>
      <address>Repromed - 180 Fullarton Road Dulwich SA 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 83338111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fbell@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>