<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373902">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001528347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The use of antibiotics in elective non-hysterectomy gynaecological laparoscopy for benign procedures</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Antibiotic Prophylaxis in Benign Gynaecological Laparoscopic Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1204-4989</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Benign Gynaecological Laparoscopic Surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>2g intravenous Cephazolin made into a 10ml solution, given within 30min prior to the beginning of Laparoscopic Surgery</interventions>
    <comparator>10ml injection of normal saline, given within 30min prior to the beginning of laparoscopic surgery</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The post-operative infections rates.  Patients will be encouraged to seek assistance if any concerns about an infection. Surgical site infection will be diagnosed clinically by the treating team or a primary care doctor (e.g. general practitioner or emergency physician) although wound swabs are encouraged to confirm diagnosis and type of bacteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post-operative</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study feasibility. This will be assessed by recruitment rates of potential research participants, the rates of unblinding of treatment allocation to the patient or treating team, and rates of follow-up at 6 weeks post-partum. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 6 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antibiotic related reactions. These will be identified clinically at the time of surgery as anaphylaxis or skin reactions such as urticaria, rash, exanthem and pruritis 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30min post antibiotic administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Re-admission to hospital.  Patients will be provided with a letter of participation which will include the participant number and contact details for the research team.  The letter will ask that treating doctors contact the surgical team directly if any infection occurs requiring admission to hospital.  For suspected infections not requiring admission to hospital, treating doctors will be requested to provide a discharge or summary letter from the consultation to bring to their 6 week appointment.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 6 weeks post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Till time of discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Patients requiring an elective laparoscopic procedure (that does not include hysterectomy) for a benign gynaecological condition as determined jointly by the surgeon and the patient.
2.	English speaking.
3.	Over 18 years of age at time of surgery.
4.	Patients who understand the conditions of the study and are willing to participate for the length of the prescribed term of follow-up. 
5.	Patients who are capable of, and have given, informed consent to their participation in the study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Pregnant women.
2.	Immunocompromised patients.
3.	Patients with a documented history of cephalosporin allergy
4.	Patients with a documented history of major penicillin allergy
5.	Current involvement in any other research project.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generator</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All data from the Case-Report Forms will be entered into an electronic database.  Data will be analysed using SPSS (v X2 SPSS Inc, Chicago Ill).  Feasibility will be determined by rates of cases completed without accidental unblinding and analysis of adverse events in each group. Analysis of all primary and secondary outcome measures will be on an intention-to-treat basis although it is not expected to reach significance in this pilot trial.  Demographic data will be compared using appropriate parametric and non-parametric statistical tests following the assessment of the distribution of the data by the Kolgarov-Smirnov method.  Categorical data such as the presence or absence of infection will be compared using a Chi-square test with Fischers exact test where appropriate.  
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/02/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/10/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>21/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Hospital for Women</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Barker St, 
Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australasian Gynaecological Endoscopy and Surgery Society</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 717
Indooroopilly
QLD 4068
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Surgical site infections are recognised as a common surgical complication, and the use of antibiotic prophylaxis has become an important method of reducing the risk of infection.  However, given increasing concerns regarding antibiotic resistance, it is important that the use of antibiotic prophylaxis be evidence based.  Local and international guidelines attempt to aid clinicians by outlining the evidence available for prophylaxis for various gynaecological procedures.  The current Australian Therapeutic Guidelines recommend antibiotic prophylaxis for hysterectomy, termination of pregnancy and caesarean delivery, with no specific reference to non-hysterectomy complex laparoscopic procedures.  
Although anaphylactic reactions to cephalosporins are reported to be rare (0.001 to 0.1%), skin reactions such as urticaria, rash, exanthem and pruritis occur in 1-3% of patients. Other reported reactions include serum-sickness-like reaction, fever and immunohematologic reactions.  Additionally, the potential costs of antibiotic resistance mean all clinicians have a heightened responsibility to ensure administration of antibiotics is for appropriate indications.
Medicare data shows that at least 25000 non-hysterectomy, operative laparoscopic gynaecological procedures were performed in Australia last year.  In view of the frequency with which such surgery is performed, there is a clear need for an appropriately powered study to examine whether there is a role for antibiotic prophylaxis for non-hysterectomy laparoscopic surgery in gynaecology.  To ensure this a study of this magnitude can be carried out correctly, it is essential to perform this pilot study to assess the feasibility of future studies.  Given the potential costs to both patients and the health-care system of post-operative infectious morbidity, as well as the costs of using antibiotics, including the actual cost of drug administration, adverse reactions in individual patients, and potential increases in antibiotic resistance, the results of this study have the potential to significantly impact both local and international policy in this area.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>No Website</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office
G71, East Wing
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/10/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jason Abbott</name>
      <address>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61293826111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.abbott@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jason Abbott</name>
      <address>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61293826111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.abbott@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jason Abbott</name>
      <address>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61293826111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.abbott@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aaron Budden</name>
      <address>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61293826111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aaron.budden@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>