<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366572">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000847617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Wheeze and Steroids in Preschoolers: Main study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In children aged between 24 and 59 months, presenting to emergency departments with acute preschool wheeze associated with a respiratory tract infection, is oral prednisolone 2mg/kg for 3 days equivalent to placebo in terms of respiratory distress measured at 24 hours by the Preschool Respiratory Assessment Measure (PRAM score).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-1526</utrn>
    <trialacronym>WASP: Main study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preschool wheeze</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>2mg/kg oral prednisilone, once daily for 3 days. First dose will be directly observed, adherence to doses 2 and 3 will be via parental report without additional monitoring.</interventions>
    <comparator>2mg/kg oral placebo, once daily for 3 days. First dose will be directly observed, adherence to doses 2 and 3 will be via parental report without additional monitoring.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in PRAM (Preschool Respiratory Assessment Measure) score from baseline to 24 hours after the first dose of study medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRAM score at 4 hours/12 hours and discharge from ED.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge/4 hours/12 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay in ED - measured by data linkage/chart review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Variable.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Admission Rate - measured by data linkage/chart review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Variable.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of inpatient stay - measured by data linkage/chart review.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Variable.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events (infection/behaviour) - measured by chart review and parental report.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to seven days post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount of salbutamol given in 48 hours - measured by chart review/parental report.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 hours post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount of salbutamol given in first 7 days - measured by chart review/parental report.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to return to normal activity - measured by parental report via survey.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Variable.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Representation to hospital or general practitioner within 7 days with respiratory distress/illness - measured by parental report via survey/chart review/linkage.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Care Costs - measured from data linkage/survey of medication use.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post first dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 24 to 59 months
Wheeze heard with or without a stethoscope
Presenting with an acute respiratory illness</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>24</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>PRAM score &lt; 3
Unable to be followed up in 18-38 hours
Corticosteroid in last 7 days
Chronic respiratory, neurological or cardiac disease
Contraindication to corticosteroid or allergy to prednisilone
History consistent with foreign body inhalation
Currently severe disease (i.e using life threatening asthma protocol or in resuscitation room)
History of life threatening asthma
Previously randomised in WASP study
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients who present to the ED with a respiratory illness are potential participants for inclusion in the study. Patients who present with other problems (e.g. a fracture or injury) and have wheeze are not eligible. Inclusion and exclusion criteria are listed in the previous section. In practice, the study form CRF1, “patient eligibility,” will be used to assess if a patient is suitable for the WASP study. 

CRF1 will be completed on all patients between 24 and 59 months of age (2 and 4 years of age) who present with a respiratory illness and have wheeze. 

If a patient is eligible the family will be approached for consent. 

Once consented the treating team will open an opaque sealed envelope (to be opened in sequential order). This envelope will contain a randomisation (study number) which will correspond to a bottle of study intervention medication (prednisolone or placebo). These bottles are exactly the same in presentation and taste. 

The bottles are prepared by the study pharmacists using a randomisation key developed by the study statistician utilising the random number generator in Excel (Microsoft corporation). 

Families, treating team members and outcome assessers are blinded to study group allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>Study participants will be stratified by site, by the study statistician. The randomisation key developed by the study statistician will utilise Excels random number generator (Microsoft corporation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistics 

Power and number of participants
	The study is powered as an equivalence trial, using the standard deviation found in the pilot for change in PRAM at 24 hours of 2.3, this is consistent with the standard deviation of 2.3 found in previous studies, and allowing for 15% lost to follow-up. 400 children will be required to have 95% power to confirm equivalence of prednisolone to placebo (equivalence limit set at 1, minimum detectable difference in PRAM scores)(alpha=0.05). An equivalence design with high power has been chosen as clinicians widely use prednisolone in children with preschool wheeze, thus if prednisolone is found to be equivalent to placebo, in order to influence practice clinicians will require a high level of certainty.
	
Data analysis
Data from trial clinical research forms (CRFs) will be entered into a trial database, with appropriate data quality checks. Data will then be extracted into SAS for analysis. Analysis will be intention-to-treat. Continuous data (primary outcome) will be assessed for normality, and transformed if appropriate. Continuous data will be reported as means and 95% confidence intervals (CIs), or medians and inter-quartile range (IQR). Differences between groups will be reported as differences between means (95% CI). Dichotomised data will be reported as incidence rates, with differences between groups reported as odds ratios (95% CI) and corresponding number needed to treat/harm (NNT/NNH). 

Sensitivity analysis will assess for any differences at baseline between groups and for the impact of missing data. 

A priori sub-group analysis will determine the effect of the study interventions in participants determined to be salbutamol responsive. Salbutamol response will be determined as a reduction in PRAM score of =3 following 3x600 mcg salbutamol administered via a spacer, or in the first 1 hour of treatment. This sub-group was determined as being clinically relevant as a previous survey of ED physicians (unpublished data) has suggested that they are more likely to prescribe prednisolone to this sub-group group of preschool wheezers on the basis that response to salbutamol may determine likelihood of the wheeze being closer to asthma in phenotype. Based on pilot data the study will have 80% power (alpha=0.05) to determine the effect in this sub-group. A further a priori sub-group analysis will determine the effect of the study interventions in participants determined to be at higher risk of latter asthma, as measured by the Asthma Predictive Index.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of NZ</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>110 Stanley Street
Grafton
Auckland 1010
New-Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>ADHB Charitable Trust (A+ Trust) </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>C/O Auckland District Health Board
Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In school age children and adults we know prednisolone helps to reduce the length of wheezing. In children less than two years of age we know that prednisolone does not help children who wheeze. The few scientific studies that have been carried out in preschool children to assess the effect of prednisolone have had conflicting results. 
No one knows for sure if prednisolone helps preschool children with wheeze or not.
Currently preschool children with wheeze are sometimes given prednisolone and sometimes they are not. We dont know if giving prednisolone or not is the best treatment.
The aim of this study is to determine if prednisolone helps to reduce the symptoms in preschool children with wheeze.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011
New-Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTA/83</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stuart Dalziel</name>
      <address>Children's Emergency Department
Starship Children's Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1142
New-Zealand</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 3074902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sdalziel@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Megan Bonisch</name>
      <address>Children's Emergency Department
Starship Children's Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1142
New-Zealand</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 3074902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mbonisch@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stuart Dalziel</name>
      <address>Children's Emergency Department
Starship Children's Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1142
New-Zealand</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 3074902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sdalziel@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Megan Bonisch</name>
      <address>Children's Emergency Department
Starship Children's Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1142
New-Zealand</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 3074902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mbonisch@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>