<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363815">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000282785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of a physiotherapy program for individuals following arthroscopic surgery for symptomatic femoroacetabular impingement: a randomised controlled trial </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To evaluate the effects of a physiotherapist-supervised rehabilitation program compared to no formal rehabilitation program on self-reported outcomes in people following hip arthroscopy for symptomatic femoroacetabular impingement.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1140-2259 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>FAIR (FemoroAcetabular Impingement Rehabilitation) Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Symptomatic Femoroacetabular impingement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Physiotherapist-supervised rehabilitation group. Participants in the physiotherapy group will receive standard post-surgical care in addition to attending a project physiotherapist for seven treatment sessions. This will include one pre-operative visit approximately 30 minutes long and within two weeks prior to surgery. There will be six post-operative visits over 12 weeks, commencing approximately two weeks post-operatively. Each session will be an individual appointment of approximately 30 minutes. Participants in the physiotherapy group will receive a home exercise program, education and advice regarding activity, manual therapy and an unsupervised gym program. </interventions>
    <comparator>No physiotherapist-supervised rehabilitation group: The control group will receive standard post-surgical care. Participants in the control group will not receive the formal rehabilitation program. Participants will gradually increase their physical activity levels and return to exercise and sport based on information provided by their surgeon. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The international Hip Outcome Tool (iHOT-33), which is a self administered tool that measures health-related quality of life in young people with hip disorders </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 14 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Sport subscale of the Hip Outcome Scale (HOS), which is a self-administered questionnaire designed to assess function in sport activities in patients undergoing hip arthroscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 14 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The international Hip Outcome Tool (iHOT-33), which is a self administered tool that measures health-related quality of life in young people with hip disorders </outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Sport subscale of the Hip Outcome Scale (HOS), which is a self-administered questionnaire designed to assess function in sport activities in patients undergoing hip arthroscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 week after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Activities of Daily Living subscale of the Hip Outcome Scale (HOS), which is a self-administered questionnaire designed to assess function in activities of daily living in patients undergoing hip arthroscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks and 24 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Copenhagen Hip and Groin Outcome Score (HAGOS), which is a patient-reported questionnaire specifically developed for young to middle-aged, physically active individuals with hip and groin pain. It consists of 37 items in six separate subscales relating to the past week assessing Pain, Symptoms, Physical function in daily living , Physical function in Sport and Recreation, Participation in Physical Activities and hip and/or groin-related Quality of Life. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks and 24 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant-rated global rating of change - participants will rate their perceived overall change compared to baseline on a seven-point ordinal scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>14 and 24 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence  this will be assessed in the physiotherapist-supervised rehabilitation group by the number of physiotherapy sessions attended and by adherence to the rehabilitation program as recorded in a log book by the participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly throughout the physiotherapy program </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants level of physical activity and sports participation will be measured by a modified Tegner Activity Scale and the Heidelberg Sports Activity Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 14 and 24 weeks post-surgery </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip pathology and surgical procedure details</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be eligible if they are aged 16-35 years, have had hip/groin symptoms for at least 3 months, have been diagnosed with FAI by an orthopaedic surgeon based on symptoms, clinical signs and imaging findings and are scheduled for hip arthroscopy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria will include: (i) radiographic evidence of hip osteoarthritis that is more than mild in severity defined as Tonnis &gt;grade 1; (ii) professional athlete; (iii) planning to have bilateral surgery within 24 weeks; (iv) other concurrent injury/condition that would affect performance on the rehabilitation program and/or assessment procedures; (v) unable to attend a study physiotherapist or participate in the rehabilitation program if randomised to the physiotherapy group; (vi) planning to undertake formal supervised rehabilitation following hip arthroscopy; and (vii) inability to understand English. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutively numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes containing group allocation will be prepared by a researcher with no other involvement in the study. The envelopes will be stored in a locked location and will be opened in sequence to reveal group allocation by a researcher not involved in recruitment or assessment of outcomes</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be prepared by the study biostatistician using computer generated random permuted blocks of varying size, and stratified according to orthopaedic surgeon so that each surgeon contributes approximately equal numbers in each group to control for surgical variation. Participants randomised to the physiotherapy group will choose their preferred project physiotherapist according to geographical convenience. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A biostatistician will oversee the blinded analyses of the data. Main comparative analyses between groups will be performed using an intention-to-treat analysis. For continuous outcome measures, differences in mean change (baseline minus follow-up) will be compared between groups using linear regression random effects modelling adjusted for baseline values of the outcome</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>25/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Kim Bennell</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
Department of Physiotherapy
University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Program Grant
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council 
GPO Box 1421 
Canberra ACT 2601
 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent’s Private Hospital
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Fitzroy Campus
59-61 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Australian Hip Arthroscopy Education and Research Foundation

</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>21 Erin Street
Richmond Victoria 3121
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>YMCA Victoria

</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>582 Heidelberg Road
Fairfield VIC 3078</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Australian Hip Arthroscopy Education and Research Foundation


</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>21 Erin Street
Richmond Victoria 3121</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Femoroacetabular impingement (FAI) is a common condition that can cause hip and/or groin pain in young active adults, as well as give rise to stiffness, muscle weakness, reduced physical function and lower quality of life. It has also been proposed as a possible risk factor for early onset of hip osteoarthritis. In symptomatic FAI, treatment often involves arthroscopic surgery. Currently, post-operative management is quite variable and dependent on surgeon preferences. Post-operative physiotherapy is not routine practice, largely because it has not been established if rehabilitation following surgery is needed to improve patient outcomes. Thus, this project primarily aims to investigate the effectiveness of physiotherapist-supervised rehabilitation following hip arthroscopy surgery for FAI in young adults. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research Ethics &amp; Integrity
Level 1, 780 Elizabeth St
The University of Melbourne
VIC 3010
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1238190</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Director
Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine, 
Department of Physiotherapy, School of Health Sciences, University of Melbourne  Victoria 3010
 

</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Libby Spiers</name>
      <address>Research Assistant
Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine, 
Department of Physiotherapy, School of Health Sciences, University of Melbourne  Victoria 3010
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90353886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>libby.spiers@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Director
Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine, 
Department of Physiotherapy, School of Health Sciences, University of Melbourne  Victoria 3010
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Director
Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine, 
Department of Physiotherapy, School of Health Sciences, University of Melbourne  Victoria 3010
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>