<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369708">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001355561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Single Oral Dose Study of DUR-928 in Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) Patients and Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Dose Ranging, Single Dose Safety and Pharmacokinetic Study of DUR-928 in Subjects with Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) and Control Healthy Subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>DUR-928 powder for constitution.
Each dose of DUR-928 is given in 60 mL of ORA-Blend (registered trademark) SF taste masking suspending vehicle. The dose will be taken orally.
Each subject will receive a single dose of DUR-928 according to the Cohort they are participating in. 
The study will look at the effect of DUR-928 when given as a single dose at 2 different dose levels. All doses will be administered and supervised by study staff. The doses of the intervention are described below per cohort:
Cohort 1:  50 mg DUR-928 
Cohort 2:  200 mg DUR-928 
Participants will be confined to the study unit for a total of 2 nights and 3 days, inclusive of 24 hours post dose monitoring. Study participants may take part in more than one cohort, as long as a 4 week washout period is observed. All study participants will be confined to the study unit for the treatment period. Study staff will administer all doses.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Healthy volunteers are allocated to the same dose cohorts as the NASH patients, and serve as the control group at each dose level. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety of DUR-928 in subjects with NASH following single ascending dose at three dose level compared to healthy subjects control. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Routine vital sign measurements (temperature [T], blood pressure [BP], pulse and respiratory rate [RR]) will be measured at screening, check-in (Day -1), pre-dose, and 1, 2, 4, 6, 12, 24 and 48 hours post-dose and at trial completion. Physical examination will be performed at screening, check-in (Day -1), and at trial completion. The physical exam done on Day -1 will be abbreviated (including general appearance and evaluation of head, eyes, ears, nose, throat and neurological system). Safety Laboratory tests (Chemistry, Hematology, and Urinalysis) will be drawn at screening, check-in (Day -1), 24 and 48 hours post-dose, and on Day 7 (trial completion). Twelve-lead ECGs will be obtained from subjects at screening, check-in (Day -1), and at approximately 2, 4, 12 and 48 hours post-dose. Additional ECGs may be obtained if clinically indicated. Timepoint: AE collection starts from the time the subject checks in (Day -1) and continues through trial completion/early termination (Day 7). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacokinetics of DUR-928 in subjects with NASH following single ascending dose at three dose level compared to healthy subjects control. The pharmacokinetics of DUR-928 are evalutated using blood and urine samples. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pharmacokinetic samples are collected at the following timepoints: pre-dose, and at 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 24 and 48 hours post-dose.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effects of DUR-928 selected biomarkers following a single dose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The following biomarkers will be assessed using blood samples:
*High-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP) 
*HOMA- IR (insulin sensitivity) 
*CK-18 fragments (cCK18, fCK18) 
*Subset of cytokines (IL-1beta, IL6, IL12, IL-18 and TNFa) 
*Lipid Panel (TG, HDL, LDL), Hepatic Enzyme Levels (AST, ALT), Total Bilirubin 
Biomarker blood samples are collected at the following timepoints: Day -1, pre-dose , and at 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24 and 48 hours post-dose. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants:
* Be in good health as determined by medical history, physical examination, 12 lead ECG and clinical laboratory evaluations at screening;
* Male subjects must agree to use a medically acceptable method of contraception/birth control throughout the study duration and for 90 days after the study is completed; 
* Female subjects must be of non-childbearing potential; 
* Willing and be able to be admitted to the clinical study unit for 2 nights and 3 days;
* Able to abstain from alcohol and tobacco use during the trial.

NASH Subjects (in addition to All Participants)
* A diagnosis of NASH on the basis of liver biopsy performed within the last 6 months or radiological evidence of steatosis and a clinical diagnosis of NASH based on fulfilling the remaining inclusion/exclusion criteria. 
* For subjects with cirrhosis there must be a prior histological evidence of cirrhosis or clinical and/or radiological evidence of cirrhosis in conjunction with a FibroScan greater than or equal to 12.5 kPa and Child Pugh A 5-6. 
* For non cirrhosis subjects there must be prior histological evidence for the absence of cirrhosis within the past 12 months or the absence of clinical and/or radiological evidence for cirrhosis in conjunction with a FibroScan less than 9.5 kPa. 
For cirrhotic/non-cirrhotic indeterminate subjects will include subjects who have: 
(a) Fibroscan greater than or equal to 12.5 but no radiological evidence of cirrhosis 
(b) Fibroscan less than 12.5 but greater than or equal 9.5 
(c) Clinical / radiological features of cirrhosis but Fibroscan less than 9.5


Healthy Volunteers (in addition to All Participants)
* Subjects must have normal hepatic function. 
* Demographically comparable to NASH subjects as follows:
^ Mean BMI (kg/m2) within +/- 25% 
^ Mean age within +/- 10 years 
^ Similar gender ratio 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All participants:
* Disease or surgery of the gastrointestinal tract that may interfere with drug absorption or may otherwise influence the pharmacokinetics of the investigational medicinal product 
* Participation in an investigational drug study within 30 days prior to dosing.
* History of drug or alcohol abuse.  
* Disease or surgery of the gastrointestinal tract that may interfere with drug absorption or may otherwise influence the pharmacokinetics of the investigational medicinal product (e.g., inflammatory bowel disease, restrictions of the small or large intestine, etc.) 
* History of febrile illness within 5 days prior to dosing. 
* Positive tests for HIV, hepatitis B, drugs of abuse or alcohol breath-test. 
* Clinically significant abnormalities 
* Women of child-bearing potential, pregnant or nursing (lactating) women 

NASH Subjects (in addition to All Participants)
* Subject has evidence of other forms of chronic liver disease 
* Hepatic Cirrhosis with a Child-Pugh classification of B or C (score &gt; 6) 
* Alcohol use greater than or equal to 30 g/day 
* Type I diabetes 
* History of bariatric surgery 
* Concurrent Anti-NASH therapy(s) with washout less than or equal to 30 days 
* Viral hepatitis (i.e., serologies for Hepatitis B and C should be negative) However, subjects who are Hepatitis C Virus (HCV)-antibody positive but hepatitis C virus-ribonucleic acid (HCV-RNA) negative who have been successfully treated with antiviral agents and have a sustained virological response (SVR) following HCV therapy or documentation of HCV-RNA negative for a minimum of 6 months prior to inclusion and who meet all other eligibility criteria may be considered for enrollment. 
Healthy Volunteers (in addition to All Participants)
* Evidence of clinically significant uncontrolled hematological, endocrine, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, renal, psychiatric, neurologic, or allergic disease (including drug allergies, but excluding untreated, asymptomatic, seasonal allergies at the time of dosing) 
* Presence of impaired renal function as indicated by abnormal creatinine (creatinine clearance &lt; 80 ml/min) values and/or serum creatinine greater than or equal to 1.8 mg/dL 
* History of regular alcohol consumption exceeding 28 drinks/week within 6 months of screening 
* Positive tests for hepatitis C.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The proposed multiple cohort study will be conducted in 2 successive cohorts evaluating 2 single-dose levels of oral DUR-928. 
For each cohort 10 subjects with Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) will be enrolled. Of those 10 NASH subjects to be enrolled there will be an approximately equal distribution of cirrhotic and non-cirrhotic subjects. 
Following enrollment of the NASH subjects in a cohort, six additional healthy subjects with normal liver function will be enrolled and receive a single dose of DUR-928. The healthy subjects will be matched to the NASH group for a given cohort by average age (+/- 10 years), average BMI (+/- 25%) and gender ratio. 
Allocation is not concealed
</concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>2 cohorts (10 NASH Subjects and 6 Healthy Volunteers per cohort) will be given a single oral dose of DUR-928. Cohort 2 continues only after the safety assessment of Cohort 1. 32 subjects in total will be enrolled (20 NASH Subjects and 12 Healthy Volunteers).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Safety  Safety will be evaluated by assessment of clinical laboratory tests, physical examinations including vital signs, and ECGs, and by the documentation of all spontaneously reported adverse events. Treatment-emergent AEs will be listed and summarized by dose level and cirrhotic status. Treatment-emergent changes from baseline in clinical laboratory tests, ECG, and vital signs will be derived by dose level. 
Pharmacokinetics  Plasma concentration data of DUR-928 and its metabolite at each dose level will be used to calculate relevant pharmacokinetic parameters.  Pharmacokinetic parameters will summarized by dose level, using descriptive statistics. At each dose level, the pharmacokinetics of DUR-928 will be compared between the NASH subjects and the healthy subjects control to support the safety review for escalation to the next dose level. 
Biomarkers - The biomarker data at baseline and at each post-dose time point will be plotted and listed for each subject for evaluation of any change from baseline or over time. Baseline for each biomarker will be derived from the average.
This is an exploratory study. No power or sample size calculations have been performed.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>32</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>INC Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>159 Port Rd, 
Hindmarsh,
South Australia, 5007 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>DURECT Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10260 Bubb Road
Cupertino, CA  95014, USA
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research project is being conducted to look at how safe and well tolerated a new drug called DUR-928 is when given as an oral dose to subjects with Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH), when compared to healthy volunteers. The study will look at the study drugs effect when given as a single dose at 2 different dose levels. The pharmacokinetics of DUR-928 will also be studied; this is done by measuring the amount of DUR-928 in the blood at different times throughout the dosing periods, allowing us to evaluate how DUR-928 is handled by the body (for example how quickly it gets into the blood stream). The pharmacodynamics will also be studied; this is done by measuring the amount of selected biomarkers in the blood at different times throughout the dosing periods, allowing us to evaluate the effect of DUR-928 on the body. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC, 3004
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>547/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>William Kemp</name>
      <address>Alfred Health
Gastroenterology Dept
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria, Australia 3004
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 3375 </phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9076 2194 </fax>
      <email>W.Kemp@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Biljana Georgievska </name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Limited 
Level 5, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct, 
89 Commercial Road, Melbourne 
Victoria 3004 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 9017</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8911 </fax>
      <email>b.georgievska@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research
159 Port Road, 
Hindmarsh, SA 5007</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1510</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599 </fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@incresearch.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research
159 Port Road, 
Hindmarsh, SA 5007</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1510</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599 </fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@incresearch.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>