<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1477">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/07/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000325505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Outcomes of Increased Flexion Total Knee Replacement.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate  knee range of motion (ROM), pain and functional outcomes of patients after primary total knee arthroplasty (TKA) for knee osteoarthritis with the Increased Flexion Profix Total Knee  System (Smith &amp; Nephew, Inc.).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Dr Simon Journeaux</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of the knee</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Total knee arthroplasty with  the Profix Total Knee System (Smith &amp; Nephew, Inc). This system enables the surgeon to implant the femoral prosthesis in a 4 degree flexed position (increased flexion technique) or in a neutral position (standard technique)</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of motion of the knee: flexion
Knee flexion will be assessed using computer analysis of a digital photograph of the knee in maximum passive knee flexion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively, intra-operatively and post-operatively at 6 weeks, 6 months, one year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function, strength, quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively and post-operatively at 6 weeks, 6 months, one and two years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults listed for total knee replacement at the Mater Adult Hospital, with a diagnosis of non-inflammatory degenerative joint disease, who will be available for follow-up evaluations for 2 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Active local or systemic infection, patients undergoing revision knee or complex primary arthroplasty, patients who are to have bilateral knee arthroplasty or those who have had knee arthroplasty in the previous 12 months. Pre-existing severe osteoporosis, or any other systemic or metabolic disorders causing progressive deterioration of bone.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation concealed in opaque envelopes and provided to surgeon. Details of surgical technique (increased flexion or standard instrumentation) sealed in opaque envelope within medical chart.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will follow a computer generated blocked randomisation sequence. The size of the blocks is not variable and was determined independently to maintain blinding of assessors. Allocation was stratified according to pre-operative range of knee motion.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/06/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mater Health Services</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane, Queensland, 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Smith &amp; Nephew</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>85 Waterloo Road

North Ryde NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland, School of Health &amp; Rehabilitation Sciences.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Lucia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Total knee arthroplasty (TKA) is a common, successful and safe operation for people who have end-stage knee arthritis. Pain-free knee flexion or bend of 135 degrees or more with stability is the goal of TKA. There are substantial improvements in pain and function. However, a major problem that persists is that patients do not consistently achieve knee flexion or bend greater than 110 degrees. 
The need to improve surgical technique and prosthetic designs to provide better flexibility and function is therefore essential. Many designs are available and currently in use. This study involves the use of one of these designs; the Profix Total Knee System (Smith &amp; Nephew, Inc.). This system gives the surgeon the option to implant the prosthesis onto the leg using either increased flexion or standard instruments. The instruments are used by the surgeon to ensure accurate placement of the prosthesis. 
The objective of this study is to compare knee flexion range of motion (ROM), pain and functional outcomes of patients after primary TKA with the Profix Total Knee System.

The primary hypothesis is that patients who have Profix TKAs implanted by the surgeon with increased flexion instruments will achieve significantly greater knee flexion than those implanted with standard instruments. 
The secondary hypothesis is that this increased knee flexion will allow improved functional ability with less pain and as a result better quality of life.
The trial is a double blind study with patients, assessors and data analysts blinded to group allocation</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Health Services,</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/11/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> 910A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Qld</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/03/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006000159</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Murphy</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics
Mater Health Services
South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38408787</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38408877</fax>
      <email>michael.murphy@mater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Murphy</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics
Mater Health Services
South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38408787</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38408877</fax>
      <email>michael.murphy@mater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>