<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365777">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000204640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> A randomised, open-label study using continuous glucose monitoring to compare the effects of once a day versus twice a day prednisolone dosing schedule on glycaemic control in people with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> A randomised, open-label study using continuous glucose monitoring to compare the effects of once a day versus twice a day prednisolone dosing schedule on glycaemic control in people with type 2 diabetes mellitus.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1152-1267 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral prednisolone twice a day given as 10 mg doses at 08:00 and 18:00 (time is 24 hour clock time), for 3 days. Adherence will be monitored by drug tablet return and participant diary. There is a wash-out period between treatments of 3 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Once a day morning oral dosing with 20 mg prednisolone given at 08:00), for 3 days. Adherence will be monitored by drug tablet return and participant diary. There is a wash-out period between treatments of 3 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> The amount of time per day (% and area under the curve (AUC) of glucose-time curve with interstitial glucose level greater than  or equal to 10.0 mmol/L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing, data from continuous glucose monitoring system.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	The amount of time per day (% and AUC of glucose-time curve) with interstitial glucose level &gt; 15.0 mmol/L, assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	Average post-prandial interstitial glucose level excursion on steroid, assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3.	Average incremental AUCglucose post-breakfast, post-lunch and post-dinner, assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4.	Average fasting interstitial glucose level and average interstitial glucose level (24 hour average), assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5.	Timing of maximum and nadir interstitial glucose level (time of day and in relation to the time of steroid dose), assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6.	Mean interstitial glucose level during the following time blocks: 2400-1200; 1200-2400; 0800-1400; 1400-2000; 2000-0200; 0200-0800, assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7.	Glycaemic variability assessed using MAGE (mean amplitude of glycaemic excursion) index, standard deviation of glucose concentration, CONGA- 1, 2, 3, 4 (continuous overall net glycaemic action at 1, 2 , 3 or 4 hours), J-index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>8.	The average difference between fasting interstitial glucose level and each of pre-lunch and pre-dinner interstitial glucose levels, assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>9.	The average difference between peak post-breakfast interstitial glucose level and each of peak post-lunch and post-dinner interstitial glucose levels, assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>10.	The amount of time per day (%) with interstitial glucose level &lt; 4.0 mmol/L, assessed using continuous glucose monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Averaged from the 3 days of prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>11.	Sleep quality score assessed by modified Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3 of the prednisolone dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Informed consent obtained before any trial-related activities 
2.	Male or female
3.	Age greater than or equal to 18 years 
4.	Type 2 diabetes, diagnosis established from medical history
5.	Duration of diabetes greater than or equal to 6 months
6.	Stable daily dose of anti-diabetic medications for at least 60 days preceding the screening visit 
7.	HbA1c 6.5% to 9.9% (48 to 85 mmol/mol, both inclusive) at screening visit
8.	Current treatment for diabetes: diet and exercise, metformin, a sulphonylurea, pioglitazone, a dipeptidyl peptidase 4 inhibitor, acarbose
9.	Body mass index greater than or equal to  18 kg/m2 and less than or equal to 40 kg/m2 
10.	Able and willing to perform self-monitoring of glucose levels according to the protocol, to
keep a log sheet for glucose levels and food diary, and use the continuous glucose monitoring system.
11.	Participant, if female, agrees to avoid pregnancy while participating in the study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Type 1 diabetes, gestational diabetes or secondary diabetes (e.g. Cushings syndrome)
2.	On treatment with insulin within 60 days of the screening visit
3.	On treatment with GLP-1 receptor agonists within 60 days of the screening visit
4.	Pregnant, lactating or intends to become pregnant during the course of the study
5.	Body mass index &lt; 18 kg/m2 or  &gt; 40 kg/m2 
6.	Clinically significant, active (during the past 12 months) disease of the gastrointestinal, pulmonary, neurological, genitourinary, renal, hepatic or haematological system (except for conditions associated with type 2 diabetes), that in the opinion of the Investigator, may confound the results of the trial
7.	Severe uncontrolled treated or untreated hypertension (systolic blood pressure &gt;160  mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure &gt;95 mm Hg)
8.	Current or anticipated requirement for medications (e.g. oral  or injected steroids required for arthritis or asthma or chronic pulmonary disease) or operations that will adversely affect glucose metabolism during the trial
9.	Inability to perform self monitoring of glucose with a blood glucose meter.
10.	Participation in another clinical trial. The participant must have completed any previous study at least 30 days before the screening visit.
11.	Mental incapacity, unwillingness, language barrier or other factor that in the investigators opinion precludes adequate understanding of the trial procedure or cooperation with trial site personnel.
12.	Abuse of alcohol or narcotics
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the designated holder of the allocation schedule, who is an administration staff person from another department in the institute. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size determination
No previous published studies have evaluated the effect of dosing regimen on interstitial glucose levels in people with T2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). In a published study by Burt et al, the people with T2DM treated with glucocorticoid spent 21.5 +/- 8.1% of the total duration of CGMS with BGL greater than or equal to 10 mmol/L. Our sample size calculations are based on detection of a difference of 6.45% (30% of 21.5%) with 80% power and 5% level of significance. This requires a minimum of 25 participants; our study will have 30 participants (to allow for possible drop out).

ANALYSIS
Repeated measures ANOVA will be used to assess between treatment comparisons. A p value&lt;0.05 will be considered significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>16</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/01/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>75 Commercial Road, Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetes Australia Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO BOX 3156 
CANBERRA  ACT   2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Steroids are commonly used medications used to treat for inflammatory conditions. They raise glucose levels. In this study, we will test in people with type 2 diabetes whether changing the timing of doses of oral steroids to twice a day administration, compared to the usual morning dosing, produces a more even pattern of glucose levels and less glucose fluctuation. The study will use continuous glucose monitoring to assess glucose patterns before, during and after three days of steroids.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>OFFICE OF ETHICS &amp; RESEARCH GOVERNANCE, The Alfred,  PO Box 315, Prahran VIC 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>41/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>A Reutens</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, PO Box 6492 St Kilda Rd Central, Melbourne VIC 8008</address>
      <phone>61 3 8532 1800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.reutens@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>A Reutens</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, PO Box 6492 St Kilda Rd Central, Melbourne VIC 8008</address>
      <phone>61 3 8532 1800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.reutens@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>A Reutens</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, PO Box 6492 St Kilda Rd Central, Melbourne VIC 8008</address>
      <phone>61 3 8532 1800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.reutens@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>