<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308284">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000647235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Multicentre, Randomised, Double-Blind, Parallel Group Comparison Of The Efficacy And Safety Of Transdermal Buprenorphine (Norspan'registered trade mark' Buprenorphine transdermal system [BTDS]) And Placebo In Patients With Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathic Pain.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multicentre, Randomised, Double-Blind, Parallel Group Comparison Of The Efficacy And Safety Of Transdermal Buprenorphine (Norspan'registered trade mark' Buprenorphine transdermal system [BTDS]) And Placebo In Patients With  Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathic Pain.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ASSET DPNP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>BUP3029</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathic Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Buprenorphine Transdermal Delivery System (patch applied to the skin), 5, 10, 20, 30, 40 micrograms per hour, titration at the physician's discretion evaluated at patient visits.
Patch is worn continuously for 7 days.
Duration of treatment: maximum of 16 weeks</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo Transdermal Delivery System (placebo patch). The inactive components are the same as the inactive components of the Active treatment. 
Patch is worn continuously for 7 days.
Duration of treatment: maximum of 16 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects obtaining reductions in pain intensity from baseline to the end of the assessment phase of at least 30% based on the daily numerical rating scale (NRS) score for average pain intensity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit Screening then daily up to the final assessment visit (i.e. final assessment visit is 12 weeks after randomisation).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in mean NRS score for average pain intensity to the end of the assessment phase</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit Screening, Visit Wk12 (final assessment visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in mean NRS score for least pain intensity to each week of the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>All visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in mean NRS score for worst pain intensity to each week of the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>All visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in mean NRS score for night pain intensity to each week of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean categorical scale score for pain relief to each week of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in Neuropathic Pain Symptom Inventory (NPSI) scores for pain intensity, including total intensity score and subscores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects obtaining reductions in pain intensity from baseline to the end of the assessment phase of at least 50% based on the NRS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit Screening then daily up to the final assessment visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Median average daily dose of paracetamol rescue medication used during the trial, as reported in the patient daily diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit Screening then daily up to the final assessment visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>differences in total medication usage between active an placebo treatment groups at Wk6 and final assessment visit (Wk12), as reported in the patient diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Mean Daily Sleep Interference Scale (DSIS) to each week of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Short-Form McGill Pain Questionnaire (SF-MPQ) including total sore as well as sensory an affective pain dimension sub-scores, the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) Score rating pain over last 7 days and present pain intensity score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in interference by pain in daily activities as measured by the Breif Pain Inventory (BPI), as baseline, Wk6 and final assessment (Wk12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in affective state as measured by the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II) at baseline, Wk6 and final assessment (Wk12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in affective state as measured by the Profile of Mood States (POMS), at baseline, Wk6 and final assessment visit (Wk12), which includes total score from the scale and an overall Mood disturbance scores for the key dimensions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Health Related Quality of Life (QOL) as measured by the SF-36 at baseline, Wk6, Wk12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Global Impression of Change at Wk6 and Final Assessment (Wk12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinican global impression of change at Wk6 and final assessment visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit Wk6, Visit Wk12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must have documented diagnosis of Type 1 or Type 2 diabetes mellitus for the last 6 months with stable glycaemic control for three months as assessed by the Investigator and a glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c) of &lt;= 8.5% and without any major swings in blood glucose levels associated with frequent hypoglycaemia may enter the study. 

Patients must have a history of diabetic peripheral neuropathic pain (DPNP) attributable to diabetic sensorimotor polyneuropathy on clinical grounds.

Patients must have a pain intensity of at least moderate intensity (NRS &gt;= 4/10) at the screening visit (WkS).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient has other cause of neuropathy or lower extremity pain which may confound assessment of DPNP.

Patient has clinical evidence of active infection at the site of DPNP.

Patient has undergone prior neurolytic treatment (nerve destructive procedures by application of chemicals, heat or cold), intrathecal pump insertion, or spinal cord stimulation for DPNP or other lower limb symptomatology, or has had somatic or sympathetic nerve blocks within the last six months for DPNP or other lower limb symptomatology.

Patient has symptomatic Peripheral Vascular Disease (PVD).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Centralised Randomisation system using an Interactive Web Response System</concealment>
    <sequence>Random allocation schedule generated by a computer program</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>186</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mundipharma Pty Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>50 Bridge Street
Sydney NSW 2000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mundipharma Pty Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Bridge Street
Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to evaluate the clinical efficacy and safety of Norspan (registered trademark)(Buprenorphine Transdermal Delivery System, BTDS) in reducing neuropathic pain in patients with Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathic Pain (DPNP) compared with those on a placebo patch.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>N/A</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bellberry Limited
229 Greenhill Road
Dulwich  SA  5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/07/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christine Smith</name>
      <address>50 Bridge Street
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+612 9231 7200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.smith@mundipharma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christine Smith</name>
      <address>50 Bridge Street
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+612 9231 7200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.smith@mundipharma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christine Smith</name>
      <address>50 Bridge Street
Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>christine.smith@mundipharma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dennis Yue</name>
      <address>The Diabetes Centre
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Level 6, West Wing
Missenden Rd
Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+612 9515 5888</phone>
      <fax>N/A</fax>
      <email>dennis@email.cs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>