<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365673">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000129684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>We Think You Can Dance! A pilot randomised controlled trial for aged care residents with dementia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In aged care residents with dementia, does a dance program, compared to a music  and socialisation program, improve or maintain cognition?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The treatment intervention will be delivered for 3 x 45 minute sessions a week for 16 weeks by a professional dancer/dance teacher. 

Each small group session (n=8) of the We Think You Can Dance! program will have the following structure: 1) seated warm-up involving arms and hands, and foot and leg movements, 2) standing group dance combinations, 3) learning a sequence of choreographed movements partnering with the group leader or staff volunteer 4) cool down, 5) social dance. The program builds in complexity and range of movements over time, and has been designed to be achievable, fun and encourage social interactions. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control intervention will be delivered for 3 x 45 minute sessions a week for 16 weeks by a professional dancer/dance teacher. 

Each small group session (n=8) of the classical music and socialisation control program will be themed around a classical composer or instrument and comprise: 1) the facilitator greeting and welcoming each participant; 2) reading a short biography of the composer and information about each piece played; 3) playing music, 4) discussion of the piece of music by the group. The control group will provide additional attention for participants in a social setting, as well as the experience of listening to music. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scores on the Severe Impairment Battery (Saxton, McGonigle-Gibson, Swihart &amp; Boller, 1990). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 and 24 weeks after commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ADCS-Clinical Global Impression of Change ratings (Schneider et al. 1997)  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 and 24 weeks after commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on the Short Physical Performance Assessment Battery (Guralnik et al. 1994)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 and 24 weeks after commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on the Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory (Cohen-Mansfield, Marx &amp; Rosenthal, 1989) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 and 24 weeks after commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scores on the ADCS-Activities of Daily Living (Windblad, Kilander, Erikson et al, 2006)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 and 24 weeks after commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>50 years or older; dementia diagnosis (any type); able to walk three-meters unassisted (use of stick for security is allowable); not fully blind or deaf; English-speaking; not anticipated to leave the specified dementia unit in the residential facility in the next 6 months; Mini Mental State Examination score of 20 or less</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>limited life expectancy; floridly psychotic; general practitioner advice against exercise; very high falls risk defined as not being able to stand unaided, plus a recent history of any significant or multiple falls (i.e. a fall that lead to hospital presentation, and/or two or more falls in the last month); exhibiting behaviour presenting a risk to study personnel; under public guardianship with no person responsible to consent on their behalf. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Residential aged care facility staff shall invite residents, families and staff to attend an on-site information session about the trial. A presentation about the study will be given, and information sheets and consent forms will be distributed along with reply paid envelopes. It will be emphasised that participation is completely voluntary and that declining to participate will not influence care or employment conditions. Staff will also distribute information sheets and consent forms to residents and family members who cannot attend the information session. Residents and family members can contact the researchers directly for more information or return the consent forms.
After written consent or proxy written consent is obtained, 8 residents will be randomly assigned to the Dance program (intervention group) and 8 randomly assigned to the music and socialisation program (control group).
All care staff (estimate n = 6) who assist with the dance program shall be invited to participate in the process evaluation. Care staff (estimate n = 4) who know participating residents well will also be invited to answer some questions on the resident.
The person to determine eligibility for inclusion in the trial, e.g. collect consents and perform baseline assessments, will not be the same person to generate group allocation.   Allocation will involve contacting a researcher at the University of NSW, rather than a researcher at the residential aged care facility.  </concealment>
    <sequence>All residents will have an ID code and the statistician will use MINIM (a program for randomising participants to treatment groups in clinical trials by the method of minimisation - Evans, Day &amp; Royston), to ensure equal allocation to groups by age,  gender and MMSE score. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Linear mixed models will be conducted using SPSS to compare differences in changes over time on the outcome measures between the dance and music groups. Covariates will be: age; sex; past/present interest in dance/music; and baseline MMSE.   </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2167 - Glenfield</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Lee-Fay Low</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 303, Level 3 AGSM Building
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Healthy Brain Ageing, University of New South Wales. </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CHeBA Euroa Centre, 
Prince of Wales Hospital
Barker Street, 
Randwick, NSW, 2031</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Jess Baker</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 304, Level 3 AGSM Building
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is a single-blind randomized controlled pilot of a cognitively-enriched dance intervention called We Think You can Dance! for aged care facility residents with dementia. Residents will be randomly assigned to the dance program (n=8) or passive listening to a classical music and socialisation control group (n=8), for three 45-minute sessions a week for 16 weeks. Assessments will be conducted before, immediately and 2 months after the 16 week intervention period. We hypothesise that residents who participate in the dance group will improve in cognition, clinical assessment of change, agitation, physical function and activities of daily living relative to the control group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC
UNSW,
Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HC13374</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lee-Fay Low</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 303, Level 3 AGSM Building
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (0)2 9385-2599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lf.low@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jess Baker</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 304, Level 3 AGSM Building
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 2605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.baker@unsw.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jess Baker</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 304, Level 3 AGSM Building
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 2605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.baker@unsw.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jess Baker</name>
      <address>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre
Room 304, Level 3 AGSM Building
University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052
</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 2605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.baker@unsw.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>