<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372950">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000812392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Kidskin II Study
15 year follow-up of Western Australian Kidskin Study to determine impact on myopia in early adulthood. 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does Modification of Time Spent Outdoors During Childhood Affect Myopia in Early Adulthood.A Follow up of the Western Australian Kidskin Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myopia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>skin health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We aim to assess myopia or short-sightedness rates in approx. 900 to 1776 original young adult participants, who were part of the Western Australian Kidskin Study while they were in primary school in the 1990s.  The Kidskin study intervention resulted in a reduction in time spent outdoors and an increase in the use of sun protection while outdoors.  We wish to now investigate the possible impact that this intervention has had on the development of myopia in these participants who are now young adults.

To gather the data we would like to repeat during one follow-up visit, some of the questions and measures that we performed in the original Kidskin Study, approximately 15 years ago.  This includes completing a questionnaire, undertaking a comprehensive eye examination, have naevi counts, and we will also ask to provide a blood sample.
Schools in the intervention groups received a multicomponent intervention.  Both the moderate and high intervention groups were taught a specially designed sun protection curriculum. </interventions>
    <comparator>An initial cohort of 1776 children from 33 schools in Perth was recruited in 1995 and followed up after 4 years and again after 6 years.  Children were assigned to 1 of 3 groups: A control group, a moderate intervention group or a high-intervention group.  Schools in the control group received the standard health curriculum. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual acuity:  Reading letters on a eye chart.  LogMAR chart (EDTRS chart)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short or longsighted:  A composite outcome using a autorefractor (Nidek ARK-510A) will determine this and whether you require glasses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eye movements:  focusing on a near target and then cover each eye alternatively.  The test is then repeated up close.  This will determine if the eyes are straight or if an eye turn is present.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stereopsis:  Using a 3D card to assess depth perception or seeing things in three dimensions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular dominance:  To see if one eye is used more that the other eye.
A person's dominant eye is determined subjectively by alignment of two objects presented at a stereo disparity far beyond Panum's area.  There are a number of tests available, but the method of choice in this study is the Miles test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ultra violet photography:  Photos will be taken of the eye to assess UV damage to the front of the eye.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eye colour photos:  Taking photos of the eye colour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Axial length:  an ultrasound machine will measure the length of the eye from back to front.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central corneal thickness:  A pachymeter is a medical device used to measure the thickness of the eye's cornea.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intra Ocular Pressure:   To measure the pressure of the fluid in the eye a Icare TAO1i Tonometer will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Photographs of the back of the eye to examine the anatomy of the retina and optic disk to determine if myopia is associated with other markers of outdoor activity eg. pterygium, melanocytic naevi counts and melanocytic naevus trajectory:  A Canon CF-60DSI Digital Fundus Camera will be used for this assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure measurements: A blood pressure monitor will be used to get an accurate reading.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 times with 2 minutes resting periods.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring height and weight:  Stadiometer for height and Digital Scales for weight.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood or if patient prefers a saliva sample to look specifically at epigenetics which looks at how external factors might influence the packaging of DNA, an exploratory outcome:
Two 10ml EDTA blood collection tubes for DNA sampling. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Once.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Kidskin II Questionnaire which was designed for this study:  A measure for the time spent indoors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eyelid position photos:  To determine the symmetry between the eyes and also the parts around eyes including the eye lid.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To detect sun damage areas eg. pterygium:  Using a camera the Conjunctival autofluorescence photography will be used for this assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Melanocytic naevi count:  A research assistant will count the number of naevi on your right arm and back.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dorsal hand skin wrinkling/skin impression:  Using dental paste an impression of the back of the hand will be taken. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood or if patient prefers a saliva sample to assess the Vitamin D levels (serum 25 (OH)D3):  One serum 3.5ml SST gel tube for Vitamin D analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participation in the initial Kidskin Study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unconsenting participants.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Aim 1 analysis:  (a) Myopia rates will be compared between the control and intervention groups (on an intent-to =treat basis) using mixed effects logistic regression, adjusting for age, gender, ethnicity, parental myopia and child and parental education status and nesting by school (level 2) and family (level1) identifiers.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Random sample</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>900</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lions Eye Institute Day Surgery Centre - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lions Eye Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2 Verdun St
NEDLANDS  WA  6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lions Eye Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2 Verdun St
NEDLANDS  WA  6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telethon Kids Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Roberts Rd
SUBIACO  WA  6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of the Kidskin Follow up Study is to;
- Determine if there is a difference in the prevalence of myopia between children in the Kidskin intervention and control schools and whether an individual's of sun protection during childhood is associated with myopia.
- Determine if myopia is associated with other markers of outdoor activity, conjunctival UV auto-fluorescence (CUVAF), pterygium, melanocytic naevi counts and trajectory dorsal hand skin wrinkling and vitamin D levels.
- Determine which aspects of myopia-related ocular biometry are associated with the protective effect of outdoor activity.
- Investigate gene-environment interactions of myopia-risk gene-markers with sun-exposure measures.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Australia - Human  Ethics Office</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>35 Stirling Hwy
CRAWLEY  WA  6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/6807</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372950-Kidskin_Initial_Application_Approval_23102014.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372950-Kidskin_InformationSheet.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Mackey</name>
      <address>Lions Eye Institute
2 Verdun St
Nedlands  WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9381 0777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidmackey@lei.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Mackey</name>
      <address>Lions Eye Institute
2 Verdun St
Nedlands  WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9381 0777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidmackey@lei.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Mackey</name>
      <address>Lions Eye Institute
2 Verdun St
Nedlands  WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9381 0777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidmackey@lei.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Amelia Jason</name>
      <address>Lions Eye Institute
2 Verdun St
Nedlands  WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9381 0777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ameliajason@lei.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>