<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308031">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000482268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised controlled trial of Zonnic and nicotine patch (ZAP) in smoking cessation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised placebo-controlled trial of Zonnic and nicotine patch in heavy smokers for smoking cessation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tobacco Addiction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Smoking Cessation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Zonnic (peppermit flavoured nicotine mouthspray) plus nicotine patch compared to placebo-Zonnic plus active nicotine patch. Zonnic for 6 months, nicotine patch for 5 months. Zonnic contains 1mg nicotine per spray, use at the discretion of the participant for first 5 months, wean during 6th month. Use patches daily with dose titrated to amount smoked using standard schedule recommended by manufacturer. In 5th month wean from patches in step-wise manner as laid out by manufacturer. Zonnic and patches both start at the second clinic visit. Quit date is the first quit day at the end of the 3 weeks of smoking reduction.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo Zonnnic plus active nicotine patch. Placebo Zonnic is identical to active Zonnic except that it does not contain nicotine, and instead contains a small amount of capsacian.  Placebo Zonnic is used according to the same frequency and weaning protocol as Active Group.  The patch used in the control group is the same active patch and same dose and frequency as that in the Active Group. Both patch and placebo-Zonnic start at the 2nd clinic visit. Quit date is the first day of smoking abstinence at the end of the smoking reduction period.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-cessation smoking abstinence assessed by self-report and hair nicotine. Hair nicotine testing involves the collection of a sample of hair from the head, which is analysed in the laboratory to measure its nicotine content.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post smoking cessation date.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continuous smoking abstinence between quit date and end of study by self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the 12 month period after smoking cessation. During this period continuous smoking abstinence is measured by self-report on daily diary cards from Week 2 to Week 5, and for a fortnight every month thereafter. It is biochemically verified by exhaled carbon monoxide tests at each clinic visit (1, 3, 6, and 12 months post smoking cessation) and by the nicotine content of a sample of hair taken from the head at 12 months post-smoking cessation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abstinence rates at 3 months verified by exhaled carbon monoxide</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post smoking cessation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abstinence rates at 6 months assessed by exhaled carbon monoxide.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post smoking cessation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Continued use of Zonnic after the planned stop date, assessed by self-report.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between stop date (after 6 months use of Zonnic) and end of the study. This will be assessed by self-report at clinic visits at 3, 6 and 12 months post smoking-cessation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between 12 month quit rate, and the magnitude of reduction in brief-Questionnaire of Smoking Urges score pre and post first use of Zonnic at Visit 2.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visit 2 is the start of using Zonnic, and 12 month quit rate is determined 12 months post smoking cessation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abstinence rates at 1 month post quit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The 1 month quit rate will be assessed one month after the subject's quit date, which is 3 weeks after they start taking the nicotine replacement therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Smokers of 15 or more cigarettes per day, with Fagerstrom Test of Nicotine Dependence score of 3 or greater.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any serious medical condition, history of peptic ulcer, cardiovascular disease, pregnancy, breastfeeding, inadequate contraception.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Random numbers generated by computer when new subject meets inclusion criteria, study drugs are made up into sealed boxes labeled with random number. Boxes are made up by independent staff.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generated at moment of enrolment by computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/03/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/06/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 5541
Wellesley Street 
Auckland 1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 5541
Wellesley Street
Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We aim to test the effect on 12 month quit rates of adding Zonnic (a nicotine mouthspray) to nicotine patch therapy compared to nicotine patch therapy plus placebo Zonnic.  Subjects will receive 5 months of nicotine patch, and 6 months of Zonnic.  Subjects will reduce their smoking in the first month, then quit smoking and continue to use Zonnic and patches.  Abstinence will be measured at 12 months post-cessationo and verified by plasma or hair nicotine.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>We have written a manuscript of the main results of this study, and submitted it to a journal, and it is currently under peer-review</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brent Caldwell</name>
      <address>PO Box 7343
WELLINGTON 6242</address>
      <phone>+6449186041</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brent.caldwell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brent Caldwell</name>
      <address>PO Box 7343
WELLINGTON 6242</address>
      <phone>+6449186041</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brent.caldwell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brent Caldwell</name>
      <address>PO Box 7343
WELLINGTON 6242</address>
      <phone>+6449186041</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brent.caldwell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Julian Crane</name>
      <address>University of Otago, Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)4 918 5258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julian.crane@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>