<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83353">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000020280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing the use of a "wound protector" with traditional retraction techniques, in terms of the incidence of surgical site infection in adults undergoing elective open colorectal resection surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised control trial of adults undergoing elective open colorectal resection, comparing the use of a "wound protector" with traditional retraction techniques in terms of the incidence of surgical site infection.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Surgical site infection in colorectal resection.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Method of retraction of sides of surgical incision to expose operation field in open elective colorectal resection, "wound protector". This intervention is used once on each participant in this arm of the study. The intervention involves the use of a "wound protector" for the retraction of the sides of the incision to expose the operation field. The intervention is a temporary measure, it is used only for the duration of the surgical procedure, it is removed  immediately before closure of the surgical incision. The follow up period for the detection of surgical site infection (the primary outcome measure) is 30 days post surgery. The use of a "wound protector" differs from the comparator technique "traditional retraction techniques" in terms of the technique used to retract the sides of the surgical incision to expose the operation field. The use of a "wound protector" involves the insertion of one end of a plastic cylindrical device into the surgical incision, the device is then wound taut to retract the sides of the incision and expose the operation field. The "wound protector" is removed at the end of the operation, immediately prior to closure of the surgical incision. "Traditional retraction techniques" involves the use of traditional metal surgical retractors to retract the sides of the surgical incision and expose the operation field. These retractors are removed immediately prior the closure of the surgical incision.</interventions>
    <comparator>Method of retraction of sides of surgical incision to expose operation field in open elective colorectal resection, "traditional retraction techniques". This intervention is used once on each participant in this arm of the study. The intervention involves the use of a "traditional retraction techniques" for the retraction of the the sides of the incision to expose the operation field. The intervention is a temporary measure, it is used only for the duration of the surgical procedure, all retraction devices are removed immediately before closure of the surgical incision. The follow up period for the detection of surgical site infection (the primary outcome measure) is 30 days post surgery. The use of a "traditional retraction techniques" differs from the comparator technique "wound protector" in terms of the technique used to retract the sides of the surgical incision to expose the operation field. "Traditional retraction techniques" involve the use of traditional metal surgical retractors to retract the sides of the surgical incision and expose the operation field. These retractors are removed immediately prior the the closure of the surgical incision. The use of a "wound protector" involves the insertion of a one end of plastic cylindrical device into the surgical incision, the device is then wound taught to retract the sides of the incision and expose the operation field. The "wound protector" is removed at the end of the operation, immediately prior to closure of the surgical incision.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surgical site infection as defined by the Centres for Disease Control (CDC). This outcome will be assessed by a blinded, independent, surgeon trained observer. This observer will assess the wound at regular intervals in the 30 days following surgery. Clinical criteria will be used to determine the presence of a surgical site infection (SSI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Infection occurring with in 30 days of completion of surgery. Participants will be assessed for the presence of surgical site infection on post operative days 3 and 5, and on the day they are discharged from hospital and at the time of their follow up appointment with their treating surgeon. All assessments will be made by an independent surgeon trained observer.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Not applicable to this study, there is only one outcome measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Not applicable</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults undergoing elective open colorectal resection.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those under 18, those unable to make informed consent to take part in the trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects enrolled at the time of scheduling of elective open colorectal resection surgery. Allocation of treatment group was achieved by the use of sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>All randomisation envelopes required for the trial were filled and sealed prior to the commencement of the trial. These envelopes were then randomly assigned to participants, and opened by the surgeon at the time of surgery. Simple randomisation was achieved by creation of equal numbers of active and control envelopes, which were then sealed, shuffled and sequentially assigned to study participants by a blinded assistant.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>320</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brian Draganic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>G7, Ground Floor Medical Suites Newcastle Private Hospital, Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights, NSW, 2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brian Draganic</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>G7, Ground Floor Medical Suites Newcastle Private Hospital, Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights, NSW, 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Stephen Smith</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>G7, Ground Floor Medical Suites Newcastle Private Hospital, Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights, NSW, 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Stephen Smith</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>G7, Ground Floor Medical Suites Newcastle Private Hospital, Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights, NSW, 2305</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study compares two methods of retracting the sides of the surgical incision to expose the operation field in open elective colorectal resection surgery, using a "wound protector" versus "traditional retraction techniques". The study seeks to determine the incidence of surgical site infection following surgery when each of these techniques is used. There is a high incidence of surgical site infection following colorectal surgery, and so determining if the use of different retraction techniques can reduce this incidence is important.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Comitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hunter New England Health, Locked Bag 1, New Lambton, NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/11/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/11/22/5.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Brian Draganic</name>
      <address>G7, Ground Floor Medical Suites Newcastle Private Hospital, Lookout Rd, New Lampton Heights, NSW, 2305</address>
      <phone>+612 49563244</phone>
      <fax>+612 49563246</fax>
      <email>helen@bdss.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Brian Draganic</name>
      <address>G7, Ground Floor Medical Suites Newcastle Private Hospital, Lookout Rd, New Lampton Heights, NSW, 2305</address>
      <phone>+612 49563244</phone>
      <fax>+612 49563246</fax>
      <email>helen@bdss.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kate Reid</name>
      <address>G7, Ground Floor Medical Suites Newcastle Private Hospital, Lookout Rd, New Lampton Heights, NSW, 2305</address>
      <phone>+612 49563243</phone>
      <fax>+612 49563246</fax>
      <email>kate.c.reid@bigpond.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>