<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320548">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000674033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Need for dialysis access procedures among patients receiving peritoneal dialysis and hemodialysis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Among patients who choose between peritoneal dialysis and hemodialysis, does the initial access type influence access related adverse events?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>end stage renal disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Incident patients with end stage renal disease (ESRD) who are eligible for both are offerred peritoneal dialysis (PD) or hemodialysis (HD). The PD group has access to up to two nursing visits a day to assisted with PD (primarily cycler PD).

Peritoneal dialysis is treatment by continuous ambulatory PD or automated PD. 
 
Hemodialysis is intermittent treatments usually three times per week but patients could receive more treatments per week if clinically indicated.
 
Observation was from the start of dialysis to the end of dialysis (transplant, death) or lost to follow-up or end of the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients who receive any form of chronic hemodialysis as their treatment modality including incenter, satellite, or home dialysis.

Observation was from the start of dialysis to the end of dialysis (transplant, death) or lost to follow-up or end of the study. The minimum follow-up was six months. The mean follow-up is likely to be about 1.5 years.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of invasive procedures to maintain access for dialysis. Primary nurse review the medical record every 3 months and record any invasive access procedures that occurred into a web-based database that is double reviewed by the investigators. All procedures must be referenced to medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Observation was from the start of dialysis to the end of dialysis (transplant, death) or lost to follow-up or end of the study. It varied only depending on the above events and is not likely to vary much per group. 

Study follow-up is variable - minimum follow-up is six months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of invasive access procedures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minimum follow-up is 6 months. Median follow-up should be approximately 1.5 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Access-related hospitalizations. Nurses entered invasive interventions, hospitalizations (duration and reason for admission) and death every three months based on reviewing the medical record.  All data was reviewed by investigators every three months using a web-based system to ensure outcomes were recorded using a standardized classification system. The primary sources of data were surgical and radiological procedure notes and discharge summaries but the entire medical record could be reviewed as necessary. If the cause was not clear during the review process every three months it will be arbritrated by the two investigators at the end of the study. It was not blinded because the knowledge of first access attempted (fistula, PD catheter, or HD catheter) was often known at the time of the event.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minimum follow-up is 6 months. Median follow-up should be approximately 1.5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Access-related death</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minimum follow-up is 6 months. Median follow-up should be approximately 1.5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Written or verbal diagnosis of stage 5 chronic kidney disease or end stage renal disease by nephrologist initiated dialysis therapy

3) Eligible for both peritoneal dialysis and hemodialysis. 

3) Lives in region and residence where home care assistance for peritoneal dialysis is available.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>120</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Determined to be a prevalent (not incident) dialysis patient defined as having received dialysis for greater than three months any time prior to assessment or having received a previous kidney transplant 

2) Died, withdrew from dialysis, or moved out of region prior to completing multidisciplinary assessment

3) Recovered renal function and discontinued dialysis

4) Refused to participate in a complete multidisciplinary assessment for modality eligibility</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>412</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Canadian Institutes of Health Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>160 Elgin Street, 9th Floor
Address Locator 4809A
Ottawa, ON, K1A 0W9</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Canada</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canadian Institutes of Health Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>160 Elgin Street, 9th Floor
Address Locator 4809A
Ottawa, ON, K1A 0W9</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Canada</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Minstry of Health and Long Term Care of Ontario</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>M-1B114, Macdonald Block
900 Bay Street
Toronto ON  M7A 1N3
Canada</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Canada</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this study is to compare the risk of access-related procedures between peritoneal dialysis and hemodialysis  Procedures to maintain access to the peritoneum or the bloodstream are important measures of safety because they are caused by complications that require intervention in order to prevent permanent impairment or damage.  This usually meets the definition of a serious adverse event because loss of access is a life-threatening event for a chronic dialysis patient.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>M. J. Oliver, R. R. Quinn, E. P. Richardson, A. J. Kiss, D. L. Lamping, and B. J. Manns. Home care assistance and the utilization of peritoneal dialysis. Kidney Int. 71 (7):673-678, 2007.

M. J. Oliver, A. X. Garg, P. G. Blake, J. F. Johnson, M. Verrelli, J. M. Zacharias, S. Pandeya, and R. R. Quinn. Impact of contraindications, barriers to self-care and support on incident peritoneal dialysis utilization. Nephrol.Dial.Transplant., 2010.

V. R. Williams, R. Quinn, S. Callery, A. Kiss, and M. J. Oliver. The impact of treatment modality on infection-related hospitalization rates in peritoneal dialysis and hemodialysis Perit.Dial.Int., 2010.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matthew J. Oliver</name>
      <address>Room A239 
2075 Bayview Avenue Toronto ON 
M4N 3M5</address>
      <phone>+1 416-480-4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.oliver@sunnybrook.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matthew J. Oliver</name>
      <address>Room A239 2075 Bayview Avenue Toronto ON M4N 3M5</address>
      <phone>+1 416-480-4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.oliver@sunnybrook.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matthew J. Oliver</name>
      <address>Room A239 
2075 Bayview Avenue Toronto ON 
M4N 3M5</address>
      <phone>+1 416-480-4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.oliver@sunnybrook.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>