<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81722">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/11/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000121460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial of Bolus Versus Fifteen Minute Infusion of Metoclopramide to Determine the Incidence and Severity of Drug Induced Akathisia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial of Bolus Versus Fifteen Minute Infusion of Metoclopramide to Determine the Incidence and Severity of Drug Induced Akathisia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute drug induced akathisia (DIA) in adult Emergency Department (ED).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2 />
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A. Normal saline 10ml bolus over two minutes is placebo and then Metoclopramide Intravenous Infusion (MII): Metoclopramide 20mg in 100ml of Normal Saline as intravenous infusion over 15 minutes, is intervention. 
  
B. Metoclopramide Intravenous Bolus (MIB): Metoclopramide 20mg as 10ml bolus over 2 minutes intravenously, is the control treatment, and an infusion of Normal Saline over 15 minutes, is placebo.</interventions>
    <comparator>A. Normal saline 10ml bolus over two minutes is placebo 
  
B. Infusion of Normal Saline over 15 minutes, is placebo.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of drug induced akathisia (DIA) as measured by a patient derived global outcome measure and the Prince Henry Hospital Akathisia Rating Scale (PHARS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 15 minutes after infusion, then every 15 minutes for an hour. If akathisia occurs in this time it is a negative outcome.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The severity of DIA as measured by a patient derived global outcome measure and PHARS. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes measured at fifteen minutes after infusion, then every 15 minutes for one hour.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The degree of distress resulting from DIA as measured by a patient derived global score. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes measured at fifteen minutes after infusion, then every 15 minutes for one hour.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients receiving metoclopramide in the ED for any indication.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Evidence of pre-existing akathisia or previous DIA,  patients who are unstable or too unwell to participate, Parkinson disease, restless leg syndrome, taking of dopamine antagonist drugs such as tricyclic anti-depressants (TCA), antiemetic or antipsychotic in the preceding 24 hours and those in whom akathisia rescue medication would be contra indicated, such as glaucoma or urinary retention. Patients with cognitive impairment or English as a second language.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Pharmacy will receive the randomisation list from the researcher and keep it in a secure place. The clinician enrols a subject and gets their consent. Pharmacy will confirm completed enrolment and consent forms and the subjects are allocated to intervention A or B using the randomisation list. This will ensure that the sequence was concealed until allocation has occurred. Pharmacy will then prepare identical appearing infusion and bolus drugs and placebo labelled A or B in sealed unmarked container and give it to the clinician to administer. The after-hours nurse coordinator will perform this role using pre-prepared pharmacy packs in non-pharmacy hours.</concealment>
    <sequence>A permute block method will be used to ensure equal number in both intervention groups. This will be done using the Moses-Oakford method for treatment assignment that has been previously described. Group codes of A-MII and B-MIB arbitrary block allocation would be performed to allocate to two intervention groups. A list of random numbers would be obtained from a random number chart. After recording the random numbers a final block order and thus randomisation list would be produced.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Subjects, therapist, and  assessor will be blinded</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/02/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr.Diana Egerton-Warburton</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Health, Monash Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr.Kirsty Povey</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Metoclopramide is a frequently used drug in emergency departments. It can cause unpleasant side effects called akathisia. We are trying to find out if giving the metoclopramide slowly makes getting akathisia less likely.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Medical Centre, Southern Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kirsty Povey</name>
      <address>Monash Medical Centre
Locked Bag 29
Clayton South VIC 6169</address>
      <phone>0395942707</phone>
      <fax>0395946564</fax>
      <email>kirstypovey@netspace.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Diana Egerton-Warburton</name>
      <address>Monash Medical Centre
Locked Bag 29
Clayton South VIC 6169</address>
      <phone>0395942707</phone>
      <fax>0395946564</fax>
      <email>diana.egertonwarburton@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>