<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366437">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000632695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimized carbon dioxide pressure in retroperitoneoscopic adrenalectomy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of physiological response between different insufflated carbon dioxide pressures in patients undergoing retroperitoneoscopic adrenalectomy for adrenal tumors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-4467</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adrenal tumors</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study Procedures:
All patients will undergo retro-peritoneoscopic adrenalectomy. A opening into the retroperitoneal space will be created below the tip of the 12 th rib. A 12 mm balloon port will be placed into the retroperitoneal space after which carbon dioxide will be administered into the retroperitoneal space. The carbon dioxide will be administered throughout the procedure. The current study proposes to administer a pressure of 25 mmHg in group A and 20 mmHg in Group B.
 If the surgeon believes there is impaired visibility or bleeding in group B, the CO2 pressure is increased to 25 mmHg. If the patient experiences CO2 retention, the operation will be halted, and then restarted at the pressured used, in line with current clinical routine.

Routine clinical blood samples (arterial line blood gases) will be taken every thirty minutes according to the clinical routine. The results of these blood samples are recorded for data analysis. Also, clinical data such as blood pressure, central venous pressure, respiratory minute volume, Tidal volume, and End tidal carbon dioxide level  will be collected every thirty minutes. Other clinical data such as patient age, gender, tumor size, pathology of tumor, and operative time are also recorded. </interventions>
    <comparator>20 mmHg (low pressure) versus 25 mmHg (standard pressure) of insufflated carbon dioxide pressure</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure of carbon dioxide (CO2) by arterial blood gas analysis


</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes after insufflation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pH in an arterial bloodgas analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>End tidal CO2 (measurement of CO2 by Capnography.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure of carbon dioxide (CO2) by arterial blood gas analysis
</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 minutes </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective increase of bleeding defined as surgeon decision to increase pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pH in an arterial bloodgas analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>End tidal CO2 (measurement of CO2 by Capnography.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Operative time</outcome>
      <timepoint>From start of surgery to end of surgery.
Start defined as time of skin incision
End defined as time of all wounds sutured.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All adult patients undergoing retroperitoneoscopic adrenalectomy at north shore private by Dr Mark Sywak. 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy. Mental impairment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment was performed as randomization by sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Blocked randomization will be used and randomization will be done in the operating theatre after induction of anaesthetics. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A student T-test, assuming a common standard deviation of 1.5 mmHg and 43mmHg pCO2 in one group and 45 mmHg pCO2 in the other group, using a power of 90% and an alpha level of 0.05, a sample size of 12 patients in each group would be needed.

Data analysis will include statistical testing between groups of blood gas pCO2, pH and endtidal pCO2 after 30 and 60 minutes as well as difference in operative time. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>North Shore Private Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Mark Sywak</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dr Mark Sywak
Sydney Endocrine Surgical Unit
suite 202, 69 Christie Street 
St Leonards 2065
NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Unfunded</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unfunded</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Surgical removal of the adrenal glands is in our unit performed by a posterior approach were the adrenal is accessed from the back with keyhole surgery. The retroperitoneum (space around the adrenal) is inflated with pressurized carbon dioxide (CO2) to create an operative space. Normally, we use a starting pressure of 25mmHg, which may be increased to 28 mmHg, at the surgeons discretion. Occasionally, CO2 retention with increasing levels of CO2 in blood can occur and the retroperitoneum needs to be deflated for the patients CO2 levels to recover. On the other hand, with too low pressure, bleeding may increase and visibility may become be impaired. 
In the early experiences of retroscopicadrenalectomy, centers reported that they used pressures of 12mmHg to 15mmHg with success. However, many  authors claim to have less bleeding and better visibility using pressures over 20-24mmHg.  Also, in the largest cohort of retroperitoneoscopic adrenalectomy published, a pressure between 20mmHg and 28mmHg was routinely used without any excess of adverse events.
The implications of using different pressures have been reported in a few studies. The first one compared pressures at 15 mmHg and at 20mmHg in retroperitoneoscopic adrenalectomy and showed a statistical, but not clinical, significant difference in arterial pCO2 levels. Another study did not show any difference in arterial carbon dioxide pressure between patients undergoing open and retroperitoneoscopic adrenalectomy at 12 to 16mmHg. There are no studies examining the different physiological effects of pressures between 25-20mmHg in retroperitoneoscopic adrenalectomy, but nonetheless high pressures are routinely used in general practise with very few adverse events.

The current study proposes to start with a pressure of 25 mmHg in group A and 20 mmHg in Group B as insufflation pressures during retroperitonescopic (keyhole) adrenalectomy. 

Routine clinical blood samples (arterial line blood gases) will be drawn every 30 minutes, and these samples are, together with selected clinical data, recorded for data analysis.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North shore Private hospital ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Shore Private Hospital, Westbourne Street, ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NSPHEC 2013-008</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Sywak</name>
      <address>A/prof Mark Sywak
Sydney Endocrine Surgical Unit
Suite 202, 69 Christie Street 
St Leonards 2065
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9437 1731</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marksywak@nebsc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Sywak</name>
      <address>A/prof Mark Sywak
Sydney Endocrine Surgical Unit
Suite 202, 69 Christie Street 
St Leonards 2065
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9437 1731</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marksywak@nebsc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Sywak</name>
      <address>A/prof Mark Sywak
Sydney Endocrine Surgical Unit
Suite 202, 69 Christie Street 
St Leonards 2065
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9437 1731</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marksywak@nebsc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Sywak</name>
      <address>A/prof Mark Sywak
Sydney Endocrine Surgical Unit
Suite 202, 69 Christie Street 
St Leonards 2065
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9437 1731</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marksywak@nebsc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>