<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82671">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000681954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Chiropractic manipulation for osteoarthritis of the hip.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Chiropractic manipulation for osteoarthritic hip pain for changes in pain, range of motion, quality of life, cost, and risk for falls in subjects with hip osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hip osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group A: will receive 9 manipulative therapy treatments (adjustments) to one area: the hip with pre-manipulative static and post active-assisted stretch of tight hip muscles. After the last (or 9th) treatment these patients will receive general advice and recommendations on managing hip osteoarthritis and how to gently and safely increase general exercise. Chiropractic treatment will be provided as one on one therapy, of 20 minutes duration, at a frequency of two time per week for the first four weeks. 

Group B: will receive 9 treatments with manipulative therapy treatments (adjustments) to the entire kinetic chain (five areas): the lumbosacral, sacroiliac, hip, knee, ankle and foot joints with pre-manipulative static and post active-assisted stretch of tight hip muscles. Chiropractic treatment will be provided as one on one therapy, of 20 minutes duration, at a frequency of two time per week for the first four weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group A</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (functional quality of life)</outcome>
      <timepoint>9th Treatment, 3 month, 6 month, 9 month</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Treatment Effect (OTE) (general improvement and patient satisfaction)</outcome>
      <timepoint>9th Treatment, 3 month, 6 month, 9 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Harris Hip Score (osteoarthritis functional changes)</outcome>
      <timepoint>9th Treatment, 3 month, 6 month, 9 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Berg Balance Scale (risk for falls)</outcome>
      <timepoint>9th Treatment, 3 month, 6 month, 9 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual Analog Scale (pain) and long arm goniometry (range of motion)</outcome>
      <timepoint>9th Treatment, 3 month, 6 month, 9 month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis is made based upon the American College of Rheumatology guidelines, daily hip pain and/or stiffness for &gt; 60 mins, radiographic diagnosis of hip osteoarthritis made using the ACR guidelines, &lt;15 internal rotation and &lt; 115 flexion.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous hip surgery, visual/ vestibular/ neurological/ peripheral or sensory disorders, rheumatoid arthritis, severe osteoporosis, lumbar herniated disc.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will contact a research assistant in response to print advertisement. Particiapnst will then be telephone screened, upon passing they will be invited for a physical and radiographic screening. Upon the diagnosis of osteoarthritis participant will then be randomised into Group A or Group B by concealed allocation via central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random Number generator by using a randomisation table created by a computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2122</postcode>
    <postcode>2113</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Henry Pollard</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>84 The Kingsway
Cronulla NSW 2230</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Henry Pollard</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>84 The Kingsway
Cronulla NSW 2230</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cleveland College of Chiropractic</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cleveland Chiropractic College 
590 North Vermont Avenue 
Los Angeles, California 90004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study was to investigate if chiropractic treatment for the entire lower limb kinetic chain (lumbar spine, hip, knee, ankle and foot joints) has better outcomes than treatment of the symptomatic hip alone. Our hypothesis is that full lower limb kinetic chain treatment is better for changes in pain, range of motion, quality of life and risk for falls in subjects with hip osteoarthritis. The intervention tested was chiropractic manipulation performed at one area (symptomatic osteoarthritic hip) versus chiropractic manipulation at various areas (ipsilateral lower limb kinetic chain).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Brantingham JW, Globe G, Cassa T, Globe D, de Luca K, Pollard H. Full kinetic chain manual and manipulative therapy plus exercise compared with targeted manual and manipulative therapy plus exercise for symptomatic osteoarthritis of the hip - a randomised clinical trial. In Press  Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation. 

de Luca K, Pollard H, Brantingham J, Cassa T, Globe G. A randomised controlled trial of chiropractic management for the lower limb kinetic chain in sufferers of hip osteoarthritis: a protocol. In Press  Journal of Chiropractic Medicine.


Brantingham JW, Globe G, Cassa T, Globe D, de Luca K, Pollard H, Lee F, Bates C, Jensen M, Mayer S, Korporaal C. A single-group pre-test post-test design using full kinetic chain manipulative therapy with rehabilitation in the treatment of 27 patients with hip osteoarthritis. Journal of the American Chiropractic Association 2010; 47(6):8-26.

de Luca K, Pollard H, Brantingham J, Cassa T, Globe G. Chiropractic management of the kinetic chain for the treatment of hip osteoarthritis: an Australian case series. Journal of Manipulative and Physiological Therapeutics 2010; 33(6):474-9.

Brantingham J, Globe G, Cassa T, Globe D, de Luca K, Pollard H, et al. A single-group pre-test post-test design using full kinetic chain manipulative therapy with rehabilitation in the treatment of 18 patients with hip osteoarthritis. Journal of Manipulative and Physiological Therapeutics 2010; 33(6):445-57.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 3, Research HUB, Building C5C
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE22FEB2008-R05639</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Henry Pollard</name>
      <address>84 The Kingsway 
Cronulla NSW 2230</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9523 4600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hpollard@optushome.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Henry Pollard</name>
      <address>84 The Kingsway 
Cronulla NSW 2230</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9523 4600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hpollard@optushome.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katie de Luca</name>
      <address>84 The Kingsway
Cronulla NSW 2230</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>chirokatie@live.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>