<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="850">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/10/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/11/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000698673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mifepristone ovarian function study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study to determine the effect of one day administration of mifepristone and the same regimen followed by four days of daily administration of ethinyl oestradiol on ovulatory function  and cervical mucus in women using Implanon</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The effect of administering a progestogen receptor modulator with or without oestrogen on the ovarian function and quality of cervical mucus in women using the progestogen-only sub-dermal contraceptive, Implanon.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cervical (Cervix)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible women will be randomised to either twice daily mifepristone 25mg on day 1 followed by 4 days of ethinyl oestradiol 20mcgs daily or placebo daily for 4 days Vaginal ultrasound, cervical mucus assessment and serum oestradiol and progestogen will be carried out at intervals for 4 weeks. Each woman will be in the study for four weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progestogen level &gt;9nmol/L in any of the serum samples taken</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serum samples taken 2 days prior to treatment, 2 and 6 days after treatment has been started and then twice weekly for 3 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean maximum size of ovarian follicles</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cervical mucus score assessed for the individual woman at each visit and the mean score at the end of the 4 week study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Implanon users, who have been using Implanon for three months.Women who are willing to participate in a research investigation of new approaches to the therapy of breakthrough bleeding.Women who are prepared to have regular venepuncture, vaginal ultrasound and cervical mucus collection over a period of four weeks.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy. Women who have currently or previously had Heart attack or strokeBlood clot in a veinHigh blood pressureSevere liver or kidney diseaseBlood pressure &gt;160mm systolic or &gt;95mm diastolicFocal migraineBreast cancer or any genital cancerWomen with known sensitivity to ethinyl oestradiol, or lactoseWomen taking phenytoin, carbamazepine or phenobarbitol or Women who are lactating.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Treatments will be packaged in identical bottles and placed according to randomisation code   in sequentially numbered opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer derived randomisation scheme in blocks with equal numbers in both groups</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Ultrasounds, cervical mucus assessment and serum oestradiol and progestogen levels will be carried out blind by a single operator. The randomisation code will not be broken until after the results are analysed</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/08/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>FPA Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>FPA Health Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim is to determine whether the administration of mifepristone alone or in combination with ethinyl oestradiol will effect the contraceptive efficacy of Implanon whose main mode of action is ovulation suppression and a secondary effect on cervical mucus making it impenatrable to sper. Both the treaments we will use have been shown to have a beneficial effect on bleeding patterns in women using progestogen-only contraceptive methods. Bleeding problems are the major reason for women discontinuing these highly effective contraceptives.Eligible women will be randomised to either mifepristone followed by 4 days of placebo or mifepristone followed by four days of ethinyl oestradiol. Women will undergo vaginal ultrasound to assess follicular size, assessment of cervical mucus quality and have blood taken for serum levels of oestradiol and progesterone 2 days before commencing treatment, on the third treatment day, 6 days after starting treament and then twice weekly for 3 weeks. Women will be required to use condoms for the duration of the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Centre for Reproductive Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Division of FPA Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Ian Fraser</name>
      <address>Queen Elizabeth Research Institute
University of Sydney 
Camperdown NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93512478</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93514560</fax>
      <email>helena@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Edith Weisberg</name>
      <address>Sydney Centre for Reproductive Health Research
Research Division
FPA Health
328-336 Liverpool Road
Ashfield NSW 2131</address>
      <phone>+61 2 87524342</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 97165073</fax>
      <email>edithw@fpahealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>