<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83712">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000271202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>International Study to Predict Optimised Treatment in Children and Adolescents with Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>International Study to Predict Optimised Treatment response to short-acting methylphenidate in children and adolescents diagnosed with Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) as compared to matched healthy controls.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>iSPOT-A</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) in children and adolescents</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Once Baseline testing is completed, ADHD subjects will be dosed with short-acting methylphenidate as per local/country standard of care. Therefore, the length of treatment will differ and is based on the subjects response.

Baseline testing consists of a clinical interview and medical history, a pregnancy test (for females of childbearing potential), web-based questionnaire, psychophysiology data collection, touchscreen cognitive testing, saliva collection for Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) analysis. A urine sample may be requested to rule out current illicit drug use. Structural and Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) will be performed at selected sites and in 10% of subjects. This part of the baseline assessment is optional. 
Baseline testing is expected to take up to 7 hours and may be completed over 2 days. 

Recommended Dosage: 5 mg twice daily given as oral tablets with gradual increments of 5 to 10 mg weekly. Daily dosage above 60 mg is not recommended.</interventions>
    <comparator>Matched healthy subjects not taking medication. Control subjects must not have any psychiatric diagnosis, medical condition, disease or disorder that could interfere with the study assessments, history of brain injury or substance dependence.
Groups will be matched for age, gender and years of education.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite markers from 165 different assessments/variables will be assessed to identify genetic, brain structure/function and cognitive markers (or combination of markers) which predict acute drug treatment response in ADHD. This will be assessed using: The MINI International Neuropsychatric Interview for Children and Adolescents, ADHD Rating Scale IV, Conners Rating Scales - Revised (Long versions - parent and teacher). Web based questionnaire (web-Q), including: Brain Resource Inventory of Social Cognition (BRISC), Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS21), Neuroticism, Extraversion, and Openness Five Factor Inventory (NEO-FFI), Paediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PEDS-QL). Psychophysiological assessment (including, respiratory rate, sweat rate, Electroencephalography (EEG) and Event Related Potential) and a Cognitive test battery. Genetic analysis. Structural and functional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks after baseline visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether markers of acute treatment prediction are also predictive of functional outcome over 6-12 months. Using Conners Rating Scales - Revised (Long versions - parent and teacher) and Paediatric Quality of Life Inventory (PEDS-QL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM) IV criteria for primary diagnosis of ADHD, have an Attention Deficit / Hyperactivity Disorder Rating Scale (ADHD-RS IV) score &gt; 6 for inattention and/or hyperactivity-impulsivity, subject is a candidate for methylphenidate, and is stimulant naive or stimulant free. Fluent and literate in English or Dutch.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior or recent use of methylphenidate of other stimulant medication. History of brain injury/blow resulting in loss of consciousness. Severe impediment to vision, hearing and/or hand movement which may interfere with their ability to complete the protocol required tests.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1344</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2145</postcode>
    <postcode>5042</postcode>
    <postcode>3122</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Bryanston</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state>Nijmegen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brain Resource Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 12, 235 Jones St
Ultimo, NSW, 2007</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brain Resource Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 12, 235 Jones St
Ultimo, NSW, 2007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purposes of the iSPOT-A study are 1) to identify objective markers of ADHD, using cognitive, brain and genetic markers, and 2) to identify objective markers that predict treatment response to short-acting methylphenidate using cognitive, brain and genetic markers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Copernicus Group Institutional Review Board (IRB)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>One Triangle Drive, Suite 100
P.O. Box 110605
Research Triangle Park, NC 27709</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/02/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>BRA1-09-021</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lea Williams, PhD</name>
      <address>Level 12, 235 Jones Street
Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 8195</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lea_williams@wmi.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mimma Mason</name>
      <address>Level 12, 235 Jones Street
Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9211 7120</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mimma.mason@brainresource.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katherine Rock</name>
      <address>Level 12, 235 Jones Street
Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9213 6600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>katherine.rock@brainresource.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>