<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372791">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000821392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nitric Oxide during Cardio Pulmonary Bypass during surgery for congenital heart defects: A Randomised Controlled Trial. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In infants and children &lt; 2 years of age with congenital heart defects, what is the effect of Nitric Oxide during open heart surgery with Cardio Pulmonary Bypass on postoperative length of mechanical ventilation? -  A Randomised Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>NA yet</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NA yet</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIl known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>congenital heart disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients allocated to the study gas arm will receive nitric oxide (NO), which will be blended into the fresh gas flow for the CPB oxygenator and maintained at 20 ppm via an Ikaria INOmax DSIR  (Ikaria, NJ, USA), with continuous sampling of NO and NO2  concentration from an access port just prior to the oxygenator. NO will be started when the patient is on CPB and ceased once coming off CPB. 
Perfusionists will maintain an protected electronic  documentation start time, stop time of the study drug and achieved maximal and minimal NO concentration (in ppm). This documentation will be blinded for other study investigators.The lead perfusionists at each site are responsible to audit biweekly the documentation.</interventions>
    <comparator>For patients allocated to the Placebo arm will receive standard respiratory gases (oxygen-air mix) during bypass.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of mechanical ventilation as defined as the duration of respiratory support for all episodes with an endotracheal tube in situ for the first 28 days post randomisation. The outcome will be reported using ventilator free days (VFD). A systematically zero value will be assigned for patients who die to allow important weight to death as the most pejorative outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of Incidence of Low cardiac output syndrome, need for Extracorporeal Life Support, and Mortality:

The components of the composite outcome are defined as below:
LCOS is defined as the inability of the myocardium to provide adequate oxygen delivery (DO2) to the tissue. DO2 measurements are not feasible in daily practice, hence accepted surrogate measures are commonly used. For the purpose of this study, LCOS will be defined as: 
- blood lactate level greater than 4 mmol/l with a mixed venous saturation level less than 60% in a fully corrected heart (or the SaO2-SvO2 gradient &gt;35% in uncorrected lesion) within the first 48 hours postoperatively
and/or
- high inotrope requirement: Inotrope requirement will be calculated by means of the Vasoactive-Inotrope Score (VIS) (2): VIS = dopamine dose (mcg/kg/min) + dobutamine dose (mcg/kg/min) + 100 x adrenaline dose (mcg/kg/min) + 100 x noradrenaline dose (mcg/kg/min) + 10 x milrinone dose (mcg/kg/min) + 10,000 x vasopressin dose (U/kg/min). A score &gt;15 indicating low cardiac output syndrome

ECLS will be assessed if initiated in theatre or postoperatively in intensive care using prospective data capture in PICU and the ward

Death will be assessed post-operatively using prospective data capture in PICU and the ward


</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The length of stay in PICU:
Length of stay in PICU will be defined by the time span from PICU admission following the cardiac surgery to the first discharge from PICU following the cardiac surgery. This definition is required as some children are admitted to PICU pre surgery, depending on institutional practices, severity, and other diseases leading to PICU admission pre-surgery.
PICU admission dates and time in hours:minutes are captured as a default mandatory data field in all contributing units, and are part of the mandatory ANZPICR dataset.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of hospitalization in PICU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite of levels of systemic inflammatory markers and levels of markers of myocardial injury, including TNF, IL6, BNP and Troponin I. An expanded panel of markers may be used depending on availability/costs.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood markers for myocardial injury and inflammatory response will be collected on induction of anaesthetics (baseline  pre bypass), at admission to PICU (0 hours  post bypass) and at 12, and 18-24 hours for the following purposes: i) to test the impact of the intervention on markers of inflammation; ii) to stratify patients in to high- versus low inflammatory groups; iii) to biochemically define responders to the intervention (to identify patient subgroups that are more likely to respond to a specific treatment), iv) to develop improved markers of outcome post cardiac surgery. Marker measurement will occur in batch.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay:
Length of stay in hospital will be defined by the time span from PICU admission following the cardiac surgery to the first discharge from hospital following the cardiac surgery. This definition is required as some children are admitted to hospital pre surgery, depending on institutional practices, severity, and other diseases leading to hospital admission pre-surgery.
PICU and Hospital admission dates and time in hours:minutes are captured as a default mandatory data field in all contributing units, and are part of the mandatory ANZPICR dataset.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of hospitalization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health care costs:
A with-in trial economic evaluation will be undertaken from the health system perspective to compare the cost of providing NO to that of usual care.  Resources to be measured and costed will include the numeric length of stay (in PICU and/or non-intensive stay), and the length of ECLS treatment.  Costs will be assigned by the hospital cost centre or standard national sources (e.g. Independent Hospital Pricing Authority). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Direct health care costs related to the duration of hospital admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All infants and children &lt; 2 years of age undergoing elective open heart surgery on CPB, and consent of parents/guardian.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>2</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Signs of persistently elevated pulmonary vascular resistance preoperatively requiring iNO or preoperative use of drugs involved in the NO pathway such as GTN, sildenafil within 48 hours prior to CPB.
2. Patient is on ECLS prior to surgery 
3. Concurrent known confirmed bacterial acute infection, including pulmonary condition such as pneumonia diagnosed within &lt;5 days prior to surgery and being actively treated with antibiotics at time of surgery
4. Preoperative acute respiratory distress syndrome requiring HFOV ventilation
5. Patient requires high doses of vasoactive drugs prior to surgery with a score &gt;15 met within 24 hours prior to surgery: Inotrope requirement will be calculated by means of the Vasoactive-Inotrope Score (VIS) (2): VIS = dopamine dose (mcg/kg/min) + dobutamine dose (mcg/kg/min) + 100 x adrenaline dose (mcg/kg/min) + 100 x noradrenaline dose (mcg/kg/min) + 10 x milrinone dose (mcg/kg/min) + 10,000 x vasopressin dose (U/kg/min). 
6. Cardiac arrest within one week (7d)  prior to surgery
7. Emergency cardiac surgery (defined as acutely required life-saving procedure in a patient unlikely to survive the next 48hours without the surgery)
8. pre-existing methaemoglobinemia
9. Patients that were previously enrolled and randomized into the study with surgical procedure performed that required use of cardio-pulmonary bypass will not get re-randomized. Previously enrolled and randomized patients will undergo the same treatment allocation for subsequent surgeries, unless parents opt out.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concelement: central randomisation by computer using web-based randomization.

Blinding arrangements: Of the investigating team, only the study perfusionist will be aware of the randomisation and NO delivery. Blinding arrangement in the operating theatre will be achieved by covering the NO delivery system with drapes.  The dedicated study NO delivery system will be in connected to the patient at all times, independent of randomization. The surgeons, anaesthetists and ICU staff will be not aware which treatment arm a patient been allocated to. The perfusionists will be advised that all aspects of CPB except for provision of NO (or not) should be performed in a standard fashion for study participants. The perfusionist is not attending the surgical handover in PICU. The data safety monitoring board will be unblinded in the event of an adverse event. </concealment>
    <sequence>Study patients will be randomly allocated to NO or control and stratified by age group (&lt;42 days, 42 days -24 months) and uni-versus biventricular cardiac lesion for each site. Randomisation will done by using webpage allocation. For incomplete data or withdrawal of consent the intention to treat principle will be applied.
Stratification
-	age group (0-42 days and 42 days to 2 years) 
-	uni-versus biventricular (cyanotic vs acyanotic) 
-	study site
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on the primary outcome measure of length of mechanical ventilation in the pilot, 1470 patients would be required. Sample size estimation assumed primary analysis of two-sample comparison of survivor functions using Log-rank test. The survivor functions are based on time to event where the event is removal from mechanical ventilation. Deaths would be censored at the time of removal from the ventilator. Assuming 90% power, two sided alpha level of significance of 5%, 10% withdrawals, 3% censoring in the control group and a hazard ratio of 0.833 (estimated by the ratio of medians of duration of ventilation in the pilot study overall, i.e. 20/24) then sample size is 1470. 
Descriptive statistics will be utilised to report on the baseline characteristics of the total study cohort and each subgroup, as well as by site.  The primary outcome measure investigating length of mechanical ventilation will be analysed using a Mann-Whitney test (assuming the data is non-normally distributed).  Analysis of secondary outcomes includes both comparisons of measurements and proportions, using confidence intervals of differences as the major method of presentation where possible, otherwise standard techniques such as Mann-Whitney U tests, t-tests and chi-squared tests will be utilised.  All analyses will be by intention-to-treat. Statistical significance will be set at the 0.05 level for the primary outcomes.  Post-hoc power analyses may be undertaken to determine if results found in sub-group analyses are reliable.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1470</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Luregn Schlapbach</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Paediatric Intensive Care Unit - 
Level 4, Lady Cilento Children's Hospital
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane, QLD 4101
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children`s Health Foundation Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Childrens Hospital Foundation Queensland
PO Box 8009
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Kids Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>HeartKids Australia Inc
Street Address:
Suite 301, Level 2 / 39 Hume Street
Crows Nest NSW 2065
Postal Address:
PO Box 149
Crows Nest NSW 1585</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Andreas Schibler</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Paediatric Intensive Care Unit - 
Level 4, Lady Cilento Children's Hospital
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane, QLD 4101
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Each year, over 2000 children are born with congenital heart disease in Australia, of which the majority requires surgical intervention. Congenital heart disease ranks still within the top causes of infant mortality in industrialized countries. Despite considerable advances over the past decade, the exposure to cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB), which is needed for most surgeries, remains responsible for major side effects: The exposure of patient blood to large artificial surfaces in the CPB circuit triggers a very strong systemic inflammatory syndrome, which leads in a third of patients to low cardiac output syndrome (LCOS). LCOS is defined as a condition with a reduced oxygen delivery to end organs due the postoperative heart not being able to meet the circulatory demand. LCOS manifests with severe organ dysfunction such as respiratory and renal failure, and can lead to brain hypoperfusion, cardiac arrest, and death. Survivors are at increased risk for long term neurological impairment. Patients with LCOS require increased length of respiratory support, prolonged length of stay in intensive care and hospital, resulting in significantly increased health care costs, and translating into lifelong costs due to neurological impairment. Previous attempts to reduce the detrimental inflammatory effects of CPB using immunomodulating drugs such as corticosteroids have failed to show a demonstrable benefit. Nitric oxide is a endogenous anti-inflammatory mediator, with direct actions on endothelial bed and immunologically active cells. Previous studies suggest that the delivery of gaseous nitric oxide (NO) to bypass circuits results in myocardial protection and in a reduction in bypass-induced inflammation. We have therefore performed a randomised controlled single centre pilot trial and showed that the delivery of gaseous nitric oxide (NO) to the oxygenator of the CPB circuit for children undergoing cardiac surgery for congenital heart defect resulted in a twofold reduced incidence of LCOS, and improved patient-centred outcomes including less need for extracorporeal life support post surgery, and shorter duration of mechanical ventilation, with a trend to improved mortality. 
In order to confirm these single centre pilot data we aim to investigate in a multicentre randomised controlled trial if NO reduces length of mechanical ventilation as a primary outcome, and reduced LCOS/ECLS/death as secondary outcomes. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Trial pilot publication:
https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27686343
James C, Millar J, Horton S, Brizard C, Molesworth C, Butt W. Nitric oxide administration during paediatric cardiopulmonary bypass: a randomised controlled trial.
Intensive Care Med. 2016 Nov;42(11):1744-1752. Epub 2016 Sep 30.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children`s Health Queensland HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC/17/QRCH/43</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CHILDREN’S HEALTH QUEENSLAND HOSPITAL AND HEALTH SERVICE HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane QLD 4101
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/QRCH/43</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andreas Schibler</name>
      <address>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group, 
Paediatric Intensive Care Unit
Lady Cilento Children`s Hospital
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane
QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)730681111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.schibler@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Luregn Schlapbach</name>
      <address>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group, 
Paediatric Intensive Care Unit
Lady Cilento Children`s Hospital
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane
QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)730681111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.schlapbach@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Luregn Schlapbach</name>
      <address>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group, 
Paediatric Intensive Care Unit
Lady Cilento Children`s Hospital
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane
QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)730681111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.schlapbach@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Luregn Schlapbach</name>
      <address>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group, 
Paediatric Intensive Care Unit
Lady Cilento Children`s Hospital
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane
QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)730681111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.schlapbach@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>