<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367356">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001198617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Insulin pump therapy for adolescents with type 1 diabetes and poor glycaemic control</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Insulin pump therapy (Medtronic Veo) for adolescents aged 14 to 18 years with type 1 diabetes and poor glycaemic control (HbA1c greater than 10% for the previous 6 months) , a 12 month pilot study investigating the effect on HbA1c.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1163-6494 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this pilot interventional study, we will study patients with type 1 diabetes. They will recieve a 6 week education package on diabetes control and how to use an insulin pump. The education package will consisit of 4 x 2hour one on one sessions, three of which are with a diabetes nurse educator, and one with a dietician. The four sessions will be spread over 6 weeks and will occur at times that are convenient to the participant and health practitioner. They will be then started on an insulin pump and followed up for a period of 12 months. 
  We will use the Medtronic Veo insulin pump. This device delivers insulin in two ways: background basal insulin as a slow sub cutaneous infusion, and as bolus ammounts for carbohydrate that is eaten or to correct high blood glucose. The background basal rates and insulin bolus amounts are unique for each patient and are calculated by the team at pump start.
Participant compliance and progress will be monitored in their usual diabetes outpatient clinic by the paediatric endocrinologist.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treamtent will be compared by identifying matched controls within our diabetes database. Standard treatment is continuing on regular injected insulin. At each clinic appointment (every 3 months, or sooner if the clinician deems this necessary) they have access to the diabetes consultant, dietician, social worker and diabetes nurse educator.
They will be matched by HbA1c, gender, age, and length of time with diabetes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c. HbA1c is measured at every clinic appointment (every 3 months, or sooner if the clinically indicated), by a point of care DCA 1000 analyzer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after starting insulin pump therapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Episodes of diabetic ketoacidosis requiring hospital admission. Diabetic ketoacidosis is defined as having a blood glucose of greater than 11mmol/L, a venous pH less than 7.3, and the presence of blood or urine ketones.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of events over the 12 month study duration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sever hypoglycaemia, defined by an episode resulting in seizure or coma requiring help by a third party</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of events over the 12 month study duration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction using insulin pump therapy, assessed using the validated "pump satisfaction questionnaire"</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of hypoglycaemia assessed by the University of Virginia hypoglycaemia fear survey for adolescents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypoglycaemia awareness assessed by the modified Clarke hypoglycaemia awareness questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Problem Areas in Diabetes (psychosocial) assessment), assessed by the Problem Areas in Diabetes Questionnaire (DAWN)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life, assessed using the validated PedsQL diabetes module Version 3.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age 14 - 18 years with type 1 diabetes
2. Duration of diabetes at least 12 months
3. Insulin pump therapy naive
4. HbA1C&gt;10% for the preceding 6 months
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnancy
2. Any additional condition(s) that in the investigators opinion would warrant exclusion from the study or prevent the subject from completing the study
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients currently being seen by the Princess Margaret Hospital diabetes and Endocrinology team who are aged 14 - 18 years and have an HbA1c of greater than 10% for the previous 6 months will be identified through our patient database. 
Eligible patients will be offerred entry into the trial, and will be accepted in a first come first serve basis.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a pilot study. Should we show improvement in glycaemia in the 12 month period we envisage designing an in clinic program that can be assessed prospectively in the future.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Study participants will be matched 2:1 with active patients in our database (matched for HbA1c, age, and length of diabetes). We will use a students t test (2 tailed).

10 patients will be enrolled. This is assuming a mean baseline HbA1c of 11%, and a mean reduction of 1.5%, with an SD of 1.3%(see ref). This is based on a power calculation of 80%


REF: Johnson SR, Cooper MN, Jones TW, Davis EA. Long-term outcome of insulin pump therapy in children with type 1 diabetes assessed in a large population-based casecontrol study. Diabetologia. 2013;56(11):2392-400. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Martin de Bock</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital
Roberts Road
Subiaco
Perth 6008
Western Australia </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Margaret Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO box D184, Perth WA 6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Elizabeth Davis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital
Roberts Road
Subiaco
Perth 6008
Western Australia </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will let us explore the role of insulin pump therapy for adolescent with type 1 diabetes and poor control. These patients are often excluded from accessing this therapeutic tools due to concerns regarding safety, or because a lack of financial support. We will look at many outcomes including glycaemic control, episodes of diabetic ketoacidosis and severe hypoglycaemia, as well general quality of life and psychosocial functioning.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO box D184
Perth
WA 6840</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin de Bock</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital Roberts Road
Subiaco
Perth WA 6008 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 93407915 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.debock@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin de Bock</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital Roberts Road
Subiaco
Perth WA 6008 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 93407915 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.debock@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin de Bock</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital Roberts Road
Subiaco
Perth WA 6008 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 93407915 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.debock@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin de Bock</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital Roberts Road
Subiaco
Perth WA 6008 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 93407915 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.debock@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>