<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372225">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000167369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mini sling or retropubic sling in women with Stress Urinary Incontinence - a Randomised Controlled Trial (Mini Retro)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of mini sling versus retropubic sling in women with Stress Urinary Incontinence - a RCT study (Mini Retro)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Mini Retro</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stress urinary incontinence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To assess the subjective cure rate (positive answer to leaks when you cough or sneeze or leaks when physically active/exercising on ICIQ-UI) of the Altis minisling at 6 months post-surgical treatment of female urodynamic stress incontinence
This sling procedure for treatment of stress urinary incontinence is usually done as a day procedure and will take approximately half an hour. The sling is inserted at the midurethra to provide support during periods of increased intraabdominal pressure to prevent stress urinary incontinence. The Altis minisling is a single incision sling system with small integrated self-fixating tips that anchor into the obturator internus muscle. This potentially avoids complications associated with trocar passage through retropubic or transobturator route.This surgery will be done by a urogynaecologist</interventions>
    <comparator>To assess the subjective cure rate (positive answer to leaks when you cough or sneeze or leaks when physically active/exercising on ICIQ-UI) of the tension free vaginal tape (TVT)  retropubic sling at 6 months post-surgical treatment of female urodynamic stress incontinence
This sling procedure for treatment of stress urinary incontinence is usually done as a day procedure and will take approximately half an hour. The TVT differs from the altis minisling in the length of the sling and the way it is inserted. . The retropubic approach of the TVT involves tunneling the sling from the suburethral region, in close contact to the bladder in the retropubic space (behind the pubic bone), to the lower abdominal wall. Hence, clinically significant complications such as bladder injuries and haematoma have been reported. This surgery will be done by a urogynaecologist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the subjective cure rate (positive answer to leaks when you cough or sneeze or leaks when physically active/exercising on ICIQ-UI) of the minisling against the retropubic sling</outcome>
      <timepoint>6  months post-surgical treatment </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess objective cure rate (negative cough stress test) </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgical intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess immediate and short term post-operative complications of the minisling against the retropubic sling for example urinary tract infections based on self-report of participant, haematoma based on participant symptoms, clinical examination and ultrasound findings,, </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with improvement in quality of life using quality of life questionnaires - PGI-I.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months and 24 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the subjective outcomes of overactive bladder using validated symptoms questionnaires ICIQ UI SF and  ICIQ OAB,</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months and 24 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the impact on quality of life using the Incontinence impact questionnaire-  IIQ7.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months and 24 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess length of  hospital stay based on review of medical records, </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess post-operative pain based on VAS scoring, </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess post-operative voiding dysfunction based on review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants between the ages of 18-80 years with USI who have failed conservative management and have been placed on the surgical waitlist are eligible and would be offered to participate in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Stress urinary Incontinence associated with intrinsic sphincter deficiency
Untreated Detrusor overactivity
Significant voiding dysfunction 
Lower urinary tract anomaly (congenital)
Neurogenic bladder disorders
Previous radiation therapy to pelvis
Past history of any form of fistula involving the vagina
Allergy to polypropylene or local anaesthetic
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Prior to surgery, the surgeon will call the central number for allocation of the type of sling. A urogynaecology nurse consultant holds the randomization codes and will notify surgeon of allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>randomized with equal probability to Altis minisling or TVTTM retropubic sling using a central computer-generated random allocation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Interim analysis after the first 44 patients in each arm have completed 6 months of follow up: cessation of ongoing recruitment if minisling has greater than 25% difference in subjective cure rate compared with retropubic sling at 6months
Intention to treat analysis
Outcomes were compared with Pearson chi2 test for categorical data and Student t test or Wilcoxon rank-sum for continuous data as appropriate. 2 sided 95% confidence intervals will be used
Pre-operative  &amp; post-operative changes in ICIQ UI SF, ICIQ OAB ,PGI-I, IIQ7, PISQ-12, EQ5D were analysed using repeated measures analysis of variance ANOVA or Friedman test as appropriate
Incidence of subjective stress urinary incontinence symptoms (beyond 6 months) analysed using Kaplan Meier survival curves
Changes in EQ5D are used to derive changes in QALY for cost utility analysis
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>176</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Moorabbin campus - East Bentleigh</hospital>
    <postcode>3165 - East Bentleigh</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Health,  Pelvic Floor Clinic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>865 Centre Road, Bentleigh East, Vic 3165</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Coloplast Corp</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1601 West River Road North, Minneapolis, MN 55411</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stress incontinence (SUI) is defined as urinary leakage with activities that increase intra-abdominal pressure (e.g. cough, sneeze, laugh and exercise). SUI is a prevalent condition with high burden of suffering. Midurethral slings (MUS) have become the operation of choice for treatment of female stress urinary incontinence. MUS are synthetic tapes that are implanted transvaginally to support the urethra. The urethra is a tube that connects the bladder to the outside of the body and removes urine from the body.


Midurethral slings can be deployed in a retropubic or transobturator fashion. A retropubic approach involves tunneling the sling from the suburethral region, in close contact to the bladder in the retropubic space (behind the pubic bone), to the lower abdominal wall. In contrast, the transobturator approach involves the passage of a sling through the obturator membrane which is further away from the bladder. This approach has been shown to have a reduced rate of intra-operative bladder perforation.

Recent systematic reviews of retropubic or transobturator midurethral tapes suggest equivalent efficacy, at least in the medium term. Long term success rates of the retropubic approach are up to 91%. Both midurethral systems continue to have clinically significant complications such as bladder injuries, vagina mesh exposures, voiding difficulty, denovo (new onset) urgency and groin/thigh pain reported. Retropubic slings have more hematoma, bladder perforations, whereas transobturator slings have less over active bladder symptoms and less voiding difficulties. 

The minisling is a single incision sling system with small integrated self-fixating tips that anchor into the obturator internus muscle. This potentially avoids complications associated with trocar passage through retropubic or transobturator route.

Randomised trials of minislings against transobturator slings have shown similar results, with the added advantage of less overactive bladder symptoms and voiding difficulties. The self-fixating tips of the minislings allow them to be placed under more tension, whilst retaining the advantages of the transobturator sling. 

There have been no studies comparing the efficacy of the  retropubic sling with the minisling. Minislings may provide equivalent results as the retropubic sling with lower complication rates. We seek to examine if the minisling is as efficacious as the retropubic sling for women with urodynamic stress incontinence (USI) and compare their clinical outcomes. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Committee Ethics                                                                                                                                  Southern Health,                                                                                                                       
 246 Clayton Road, Clayton Vic 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lin Li Ow</name>
      <address>Monash Health Moorabin
865 Centre Road,
Bentleigh East
Vic 3165</address>
      <phone>+613 9928 8588</phone>
      <fax>+613 9928 8338</fax>
      <email>owlinli@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alison Leitch</name>
      <address>Monash Health Moorabin
865 Centre Road,
Bentleigh East
Vic 3165</address>
      <phone>+613 9928 8588</phone>
      <fax>+613 9928 8338</fax>
      <email>alison.leitch@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lin Li Ow</name>
      <address>Monash Health Moorabin
865 Centre Road,
Bentleigh East
Vic 3165</address>
      <phone>+613 9928 8588</phone>
      <fax>+613 9928 8338</fax>
      <email>owlinli@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lin Li Ow</name>
      <address>Monash Health Moorabin
865 Centre Road,
Bentleigh East
Vic 3165</address>
      <phone>+613 9928 8588</phone>
      <fax>+613 9928 8338</fax>
      <email>owlinli@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>