<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343036">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000597998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A phase II study of lenalidomide and prednisolone as post-autologous stem cell transplant (ASCT) maintenance therapy for patients with Multiple Myeloma incorporating residual disease monitoring.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase II study of lenalidomide and prednisolone as post-ASCT maintenance therapy for patients with Multiple Myeloma incorporating residual disease monitoring.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LEOPARD study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Residual Multiple Myeloma in patients post autologous stem cell transplant.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Myeloma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Lenalidomide will be commenced orally at a dose of 10mg daily for 6 weeks following stem cell transplant. If this dose is well tolerated it may be increased at the discretion of the attending haematologist 2 months following commencement. Converseley, in patients with suspected lenalidomide toxicity, dose reductions in 5mg steps will be allowed for management of myelo-suppression. Dose re-escalation of lenalidomide at the discretion of the attending haematologist will be allowed subsequently where toxicity abates.
Alternate-day prednisolone will start at a dose of 50mg. No escalation of prednisolone will be allowed to manage toxicities. Patients intolerantof prednisolone can continue on single agent lenalidomide.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document changes in the depth of disease response in MM patients who receive lenalidomide and alternate-day prednisolone maintenace therapy post stem cell transplant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease judged by blood analysis, physical examinations, bone marrow analysis and adverse events experienced by the patient.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To subsequently quantify minimal residual disease in patients who have achieved complete remission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease, by free lite chains, heavy lite and plasma cells in the bone marrow and peripheral blood throughout the study and at investigators discretion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate kinetics of responses and loss of response and correlate with clinical outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease. By blood and bone marrow analysis throughout the study and at investigators discretion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document progression free survival.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease, judged by clinical review, blood analysis, physical examinations, bone marrow analysis and adverse events experienced by the patient.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the utility of ASO-PCR to detect minmal residual disease in patients who have achieved complete remission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare response rates to those in comparable historical cohorts of patients receiving no post stem cell transplant therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease, judged throughout the study by clinical review, blood analysis, physical examinations, bone marrow analysis and adverse events experienced by the patient.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively evaluate lymphocyte subsets, cytokines and T-cell immune reconstitution, T-cell clonality and T-Reg populations following stem cell transplant in patients receiving lenalidomide and prednisolone maintenance therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease judged by blood and bone marrow analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To sequentially evaluate lenalidomide and prednisolone related modulation of haemostatic correlates of venous thrombo embolism risk.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease judged by blood analysis throughout the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To correlate pre stem cell transplant myeloma tumour cell protein expression profiles with attainment of post stem cell transplant complete remission</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until acceptable toxicity or relapse/progressive disease by blood and bone marrow analysis throughout the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>At registration pre-ASCT
-Age over 17 years
-Diagnosis of multiple myeloma as per IMWG    
  criteria
-No more than 12 months  total prior standard-
  dose chemotherapy.
-No previous high-dose chemotherapy or
  autologous transplantation procedure.
-ECOG performance status 0, 1, or 2.
-Normal liver and kidney function (within 2 x the 
  institutional upper limit of normal).
-No contraindication to the use of any of the study 
  drugs
-Greater than or equal to 2.0 x 106/kg CD34+ stem cells available for 
  infusion.
-Written informed consent.

To commence RAP post-ASCT
-Have reached Day 42 post-ASCT with evidence of  
  haemopoietic reconstitution (neutrophils &gt; 1.5 x 109/litre  
  and platelets unsupported &gt;50 x 109/litre).
-No evidence of progressive myeloma.
-All women of childbearing potential must agree to 
  have a negative pregnancy test in the 24hrs before 
  commencing lenalidomide, 
  take adequate precautions to prevent pregnancy,
  not plan on conceiving children during or within 6 months  
  following lenalidomide.
-All male participants must use barrier contraception during  
  and for 4 weeks after completion of lenalidomide.
-No contraindication to prednisolone or lenalidomide
-Have an ECOG performance status of 0  2.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Patients with monoclonal gammopathy of uncertain   
  significance.
-Patients with progressive MM pre or post stem cell   
  transplant.
-Patients whose general condition makes them unsuitable 
  for intensive treatment e.g. significant cardiac or 
  pulmonary disease.
-Active infections or other illnesses that would preclude 
  conditioning chemotherapy or maintenance therapy 
  administration or patient compliance.
-Pregnant or lactating women.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/12/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Malignant haematology and stem cell transplant Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Prof. Andrew Spencer
Malignant haematology and stem cell transplant service
The Alfred Hospital
Ground Floor, William Buckland Building
Commercial Rd
Prahran, Victoria, 3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Celgene Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>James Bowles
Celgene Pty Ltd
Level 9, Avaya House 
123 Epping Road
North Ryde, NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Malignant haematology and stem cell transplant Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Prof. Andrew Spencer
Malignant haematology and stem cell transplant service
The Alfred Hospital
Ground Floor, William Buckland Building
Commercial Rd
Prahran, Victoria, 3181</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Malignant haematology and stem cell transplant Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Prof. Andrew Spencer
Malignant haematology and stem cell transplant service
The Alfred Hospital
Ground Floor, William Buckland Building
Commercial Rd
Prahran, Victoria, 3181</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A post stem cell transplant maintenance study with lenalidomide in combination with alternate day prednisolone.
All patients will be registered prior to stem cell transplant, be planned for single high dose Melphalan-conditioned stem cell transplant and have no evidence of disease progression at re-staging 6 weeks post transplant.
Oral lenalidomde will commence at a dose of 10mg daily. After 2 months following commencement, escalation or reduction of lenalidomide can be made at the discretion of the treating doctor, depending on tolerance or intolerance of the treatment. Alternate day prednisolone will commence at a dose of 50mg on alternate days with lenalidomide. No dose escalation of prednisolone is planned. Dose reductions are permitted to manage any side effects according to the study protocol. This treatment will continue until unacceptable side effects or disease relapse/progressive disease. 
Pre transplant, all patients will undergo disease restaging with blood tests and bone marrow aspirate. Bloods for serum storage for DNA analysis will be obtained. 6 weeks post transplant patients with adequate recovery will undergo rstaging of their disease with blood testing and bone marrow, to confirm continuing disease response. Patients with disease progression evident on re-staging will not be eligible for treatment on this study. On study, all patients will continue to be evaluated every 4 weeks with repeat blood testsfor response and monitoring until disease progression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital
Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion
Commercial Rd
Prahran, Victoria, 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nola Kennedy</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital
1st Floor, William Buckland Building
Commercial Rd,
Prahran, Victoria, 3181</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 7712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Kennedy@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nola Kennedy</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital
1st Floor, William Buckland Building
Commercial Rd,
Prahran,  Victoria, 3181</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 7712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Kennedy@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>