<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370881">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000797471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Probiotics and the EARly Life effects on intestinal bacteria and inflammation in children with Cystic Fibrosis (PEARL-CF)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Probiotics and the EARly Life effects on intestinal bacteria and inflammation in children with Cystic Fibrosis (PEARL-CF)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PEARL-CF </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All subjects with CF will be randomised to either receive probiotic once daily (1 gram once daily) for 12 months or no probiotics. A convenient 1 gram dosage spoon will be included with bottle of probiotics.. The probiotic powder can be added to water, juice, milk (any volume of liquid as long as full volume taken), or food or taken directly from a spoon. Instructions mentioned above will be provided on the bottle.

1g of the probiotic oral powder contains:
1. LACTOBACILLUS RHAMNOSUS			7.0 BILLION colony forming units (CFU)
2. BIFIDOBACTERIUM LACTIS				7.0 BILLION CFU
3. LACTOBACILLUS PARACASEI				2.0 BILLION CFU
4. LACTOBACILLUS PLANTARUM				2.0 BILLION CFU
5. LACTOBACILLUS SALIVARIUS, SUBSP SALIVARIUS	800 MILLION CFU
6. LACTOBACILLUS BREVIS				800 MILLION CFU
7. LACTOBACILLUS GASSERI				400 MILLION CFU
8. BIFIDOBACTERIUM BREVE				400 MILLION CFU
9. BIFIDOBACTERIUM LONGUM			360 MILLION CFU
10. LACTOBACILLUS REUTERI 				240 MILLION CFU

The following strategies will be employed to improve and monitor adherence by the study investigator/coordinator:
1. Once daily dosing.
2. Initial and ongoing regular education and reminder for parents regarding the importance of following study guidelines at the initial product dispensing visit and during visit thereafter.
3. Instructions about taking intervention including dose timing, storage, and what to do in the event of a missed dose.
4. The probiotic will come in a 60g bottle, and is expected to last 60 days. Participants will be provided a new bottle at 50-60 days with return and inspection of the old bottle at the same time. Unused powder due to missed dosing will be weighed and recorded on the appropriate case report form.

For the control arm, at each stool collection time-point,  the study investigator will enquire if participants are self-administering probiotics. </interventions>
    <comparator>CF children randomised not to receive probiotics will serve as controls. 

Healthy children without CF will also be recruited as controls. Healthy controls do not receive probiotics.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcomes: Intestinal microbial profiles from stool samples will be measured by: 
(i)	Microbial richness expressed by the total number of operational taxonomic units at a species level</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 monthly for the first 12 months, and then 3 monthly for the next 12 months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcomes: Intestinal microbial profiles from stool samples will be measured by: 
(ii)	Microbial diversity using Shannons diversity index
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 monthly for the first 12 months, and then 3 monthly for the next 12 months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcomes: Intestinal microbial profiles from stool samples will be measured by: 
(iii)	Bray-Curtis dissimilarity
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 monthly for the first 12 months, and then 3 monthly for the next 12 months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intestinal inflammation as measured by stool calprotectin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 monthly for the first 12 months, and then 3 monthly for the next 12 months. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) All subjects with CF must fulfil the diagnostic criteria for CF (sweat chloride greater or equal to 60 mmol/L and/or 2 CF-causing mutations).

(2) Healthy controls include healthy full term infants (38-40 weeks gestation; &gt;3.0kg birth weight), and who do not have any major non-CF disease (e.g. spina bifida) or gut disease (e.g. inflammatory bowel disease).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Patients with CF who have had previous intestinal surgery (e.g. meconium ileus) and/or have intestinal resection resulting in short gut syndrome.
(2) Any CF subject already on probiotics but who are not willing to stop supplementation for 3 weeks prior to randomization.
(3) Healthy controls on probiotics who are not willing to stop.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomization with a 1:1 allocation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All outcome measures will be analysed cross-sectionally and temporally. Descriptive statistics will be calculated for all of the outcome parameters for each cohort, according to normality of distribution. A linear random-effects mixed-model will be conducted to evaluate cross-sectional and temporal analyses of outcome measures. Analysis will be conducted according to intention-to-treat. Correlations between microbiota profile, stool inflammatory marker and clinical parameters will also be measured cross-sectionally and temporally by mixed-model analyses. SAS v9.4 will be used; PRIMER-E and Progenesis statistical packages will also be used for microbial analyses. Correlations between bacterial profile and other parameters will also be analysed using the network analysis tool incorporated in Cytoscape. A two-sided P-value of &lt;0.05 is considered statistically significant. 

SAMPLE SIZE

In our published gut microbiota study [Nielsen et al. Sci Reports 2016], the average number of species (microbial richness) was 186.5 (SD 62.9) in patients with CF, and 407.6 (SD 156.6) in healthy controls. The Shannons index (microbial diversity) was 2.80 (SD 0.56) in patients with CF, and 3.77 (SD 0.67) in healthy controls. If we assume that patients with CF who take probiotics will achieve an improvement in the number of species and Shannon Index, such that their values are increased by 75% of the difference between CF patients and healthy controls, the following sample sizes would be required:
(i)	Number of Species - If the true difference in the experimental and control means is 165.8 (standard deviation 156.5), we will need to study 15 experimental subjects and 15 control subjects to be able to reject the null hypothesis that the population means of the experimental and control groups are equal with probability (power) 0.8. The Type I error probability associated with this test of this null hypothesis is 0.05, and the ratio of experimental to control patients is 1:1.
(ii)	Shannons index - If the true difference in the experimental and control means is 0.726 (standard deviation 0.666), we will need to study 14 experimental subjects and 14 control subjects to be able to reject the null hypothesis that the population means of the experimental and control groups are equal with probability (power) 0.8.   The Type I error probability associated with this test of this null hypothesis is 0.05, and the ratio of experimental to control patients is 1:1.

Thus, this study requires 15 subjects for each cohort. Assuming a total refusal and drop-out rate of 33%, we will recruit 22 subjects for each cohort i.e. 22 subjects with CF on probiotics (0-3 year olds: n=11; &gt;3-6 year olds: n=11), 22 CF subjects not on probiotics (0-3 year olds: n=11; &gt;3-6 year olds: n=11), and 22 healthy controls (0-3 year olds: n=11; &gt;3-6 year olds: n=11).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sydney Children's Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Children's Hospitals Network</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>High Street, Randwick 2031, New South Wales</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Thrasher Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>68 S Main St, Suite 400, 
Salt Lake City, UT 84101  </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The PEARL-CF study is a randomised, controlled trial of probiotic supplementation given once daily for one year in children with CF (aged 0-6 years). Randomization will occur among CF subjects and performed as block randomization with a 1:1 allocation. Stool will be collected and analysed over a two year period.

The hypothesis is probiotics restores the abnormal gut microbiota in children with CF, which in turn reduces the risk of developing intestinal inflammation. We also hypothesise that when probiotics are given in early life, the effects of probiotics, even when ceased, are sustained compared to when probiotics are given after the gut microbiota has become established (~3 years old).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Children's Hospital Network HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/SCHN/167</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>(Keith) Chee Y. Ooi</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital Randwick
High Street, Randwick 2031, New South Wales</address>
      <phone>+61293821752</phone>
      <fax>+61293821401</fax>
      <email>keith.ooi@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Coffey</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital Randwick
High Street, Randwick 2031, New South Wales</address>
      <phone>+61404949508</phone>
      <fax>+61293821401</fax>
      <email>michael.coffey@unswalumni.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>(Keith) Chee Y. Ooi</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital Randwick
High Street, Randwick 2031, New South Wales</address>
      <phone>+61293821752</phone>
      <fax>+61293821401</fax>
      <email>keith.ooi@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>(Keith) Chee Y. Ooi</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital Randwick
High Street, Randwick 2031, New South Wales</address>
      <phone>+61293821752</phone>
      <fax>+61293821401</fax>
      <email>keith.ooi@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>