<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365949">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000280606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The dressing and securement of tunnelled, cuffed Central Venous Access Devices (CVADs), in acute care paediatrics: a pilot, randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of tissue adhesive, combined securement and dressing product or external stabilisation devices versus standard care (bordered polyurethane) dressings to prevent central venous access device failure in paediatric acute care patients with tunnelled, cuffed central venous access devices: the CASCADE Junior trial 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-3706</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The CASCADE Junior Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Central venous access device failure prior to completion of therapy </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients in this study have central venous access devices (CVADs) used in medical, surgical, anaesthetic and intensive care departments, and only paediatric patients. Consenting parents or legal guardians, and patients (if appropriate) will have their tunnelled, cuffed CVADs secured with one of the following randomly assigned dressings and securements: 

Arm 1: Tissue Adhesive (TA) is a medical grade 'superglue' 
(cyanoacrylate) used mainly to close skin acerations/wounds as an alternative to sutures and staples. A bordered polyurethane dressing will also be applied.

Arm 2: Sutureless Stabilisation Device (SSD) have a large adhesive padded footplate with locking clasp made of hard plastic or velcro. SSD are used in addition to bordered polyurethane. 

Arm 3: Combined securement and dressing product: extra-reinforced borders, with an absorbent layer around the polyurethane claimed to wick moisture away from the wound

Arm 4 (Control): Bordered polyurethane (BPU) dressings involve a clear polyurethane with an added external adhesive border of foam or cloth fabric. They will also have their CVAD secured with prolene sutures.

The randomly allocated dressing will be applied until completion of therapy, hospital discharge or at 4 weeks. The dressing will be applied at CVAD insertion and then changed every 7 days, or on disruption of the dressing integrity. </interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 4 (Control): Bordered polyurethane (BPU) dressings involve a clear polyurethane with an added external adhesive border of foam or cloth fabric. They will also have their CVAD secured with prolene sutures.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CVAD failure and complication: Composite measure of any reason for unplanned CVAD removal, prior to the completion of therapy. This includes (i) Central Line-Associated Bloodstream Infection (CLABSI); (ii) local infection of skin or sutures: (iii) dislodgement: (iv) occlusion (v) CVAD breakage and (vi) venous thrombosis. The primary outcome of device failure is an objective measure, assigned by clinical staff (not research staff or investigators). This is routine clinical practice. Research staff will collect the primary endpoint from the medical records with additional information obtained from the clinical staff/patients if required</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, 4 weeks, or hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of a full efficacy trial as established by:
*Eligibility: Percentage of patients screened that are eligible; 
*Recruitment: Percentage of eligible patients who agree to enrol;
*Retention and attrition: Percentage of participants who are lost to follow-up or withdraw from study;
*Protocol adherence: Percentage of participants who receive their allocated treatment throughout their study participation;
*Missing data: Percentage of data missed during study data collection;
*Parent and healthcare staff satisfaction and acceptability: Using a semi-structured survey; and
*Sample size estimates: a reduction in all-case CVAD failure (defined in the secondary outcomes) by at least 5% in the experimental arms, in comparison to standard care.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At conclusion of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central line-associated bloodstream infection (CLABSI):
A laboratory-confirmed bloodstream infection (LCBI) in a patient who had a central line within the 48 hour period before the development of the BSI, and that is not related to an infection at another site. The CLABSI must meet one of the following criteria of LCBI: Criterion 1: Patient has a recognised pathogen cultured from one or more blood cultures and Organism cultured from blood is not related to an infection at another site. OR Criterion 2: Patient has at least one of the following signs or symptoms: fever (greater than 38 degrees C), chills, or hypotension, and signs and symptoms and positive laboratory results are not related to an infection at another site, and common skin contaminant* is cultured from two or more blood cultures drawn on separate occasions. Examples of common skin contaminants: diphtheroids [Corynebacterium spp.], Bacillus [not B. anthracis] spp., Propionibacterium spp., coagulasenegative staphylococci [including S. epidermidis], viridans group streptococci, Aerococcus spp., Micrococcus spp.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, 4 weeks, or hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Local infection of the skin:
Purulent discharge, or redness extending 1cm beyond the site that prompts clinician to order removal and commence antimicrobial therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, 4 weeks, or hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dislodgement:
Partial: any post-insertion change in the length of the CVAD body from the hub to the CVAD tip, as measured by the catheter marking in closest approximation to hub.
Total: CVAD body completely leaves the vein, or must be removed
because CVAD tip is no longer in the superior vena cava (diagnosed by XRay/leakage from site on injection/clinician diagnosis)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, 4 weeks, or hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occlusion:
&gt;/=1 lumen unable to be flushed/aspirated, diagnosed by treating
clinician</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, 4 weeks, or hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CVAD breakage:
Visible split in CVAD material diagnosed by treating clinician</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, 4 weeks, or hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dressing/securement failure:
Early replacement before seven days for loose, soiled or missing
dressings</outcome>
      <timepoint>At seven days after dressing application.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CVAD dwell time, and dressing dwell time:
Time in hours from insertion/application until removal</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of CVAD removal.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parentand staff satisfaction and acceptability ranked on a 10-point scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, 4 weeks, or hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Venous thrombosis: Development of thrombosed vessel (partial or complete) at the CVAD site diagnosed radiologically as requested by the treating clinician in a symptomatic patient; </outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of CVAD removal, hospital discharge or 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness: Estimates of direct product costs, healthcare resource utilisation (including additional equipment, staff time) and failure-associated resource usage using previously established cost estimates; </outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety: Skin complications including skin rash, skin tears, blisters, pruritis, local or systemic allergic reaction during study as assessed by clinical staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>CVAD removal, hospital discharge or 4 weeks after insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: 
*Patient requires the insertion of a tunnelled, cuffed CVAD for &gt;24 hours;
*Will remain in admitted to the RCH or Lady Cilento Childrens Hospital for &gt;24 hours; and
*Parent or legal guardian, and child if developmentally appropriate, gives informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:
*Non-tunnelled, peripherally inserted, dialysis, or implanted CVADs or pulmonary artery catheters;
*Current bloodstream infection;
*CVAD to be inserted through diseased, burned or scarred skin;
*Allergy to study product; and
*Previous study enrolment in this admission to hospital.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The research nurse (RN) will screen patients daily (screening log kept), gain informed consent, and perform randomisation. The RN will have the study products in pre-packs and liaise closely with the ordering and 
inserting surgeon. All elligible patients (or 
their representative) will be approached for written informed consent by the RN or inserter. If this is given, the staff member use a centralised web-based randomisation service. Allocation is fully concealed until the patient is randomised. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated.  Randomisation will be in a 1:1:1:1 ratio between the four study groups.  Permuted blocks in randomly varied sizes will be used</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All randomised patients will be analysed by intention to treat, regardless of treatment received. The patient is the unit of measurement with one CVAD per patient. 
Feasibility outcomes will be described using descriptive statistics including mean, median, range, IQR, counts and percentages. Comparability of groups at baseline will be assessed using clinical parameters. Relative incidence rates of CVAD and dressing failure per 100 devices and per 1,000 device days with 95% confidence intervals (CIs) will summarise the impact of each dressing, and to test 
difference between groups. Kaplan-Meier survival curves (with log rank Mantel-Cox test) will compare CVAD failure over time. Secondary endpoints including CVAD dwell-time, costs, dislodgement, occlusion, CVAD breakage, patient/staff satisfaction scores and adverse events will be compared between groups using parametric/nonparametric techniques as appropriate.  Data will be 
exported into PASW 18.0 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL). Prior to analysis, data cleaning of outlying figures, missing, and implausible data will be 
undertaken, and a random 5% sample of source data rechecked. All attempts will be made to collect the primary endpoint. Missing data will be modelled for best- and worst-case outcomes to assess for effect on overall results. A per-protocol analysis will assess the effect of protocol 
violations. P values of &lt;0.05 will be considered significant. 
 
Sample size and study power: This is a pilot study to gain information to prepare for an efficacy trial. Twenty participants per study arm will be recruited - totaling 80 participants.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>48</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>13/05/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>13/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Nathan Campus, 
170 Kessels Road, 
Nathan, QLD 4111 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Griffith University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nathan Campus, 
170 Kessels Road, 
Nathan, QLD 4111 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centurion Medical Products</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Centurion Way
Williamstown, MI 48895
United States</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Children admitted to an acute care facility frequently require the insertion of a CVAD for the administration of medication and fluids. When treatment is required for an extended duration, clinicians often elect to insert a tunnelled, cuffed CVAD. These CVADs are associated with a high rate of failure, including CVAD-related bloodstream infection (BSI).   In order to prevent failure, dressings, such as bordered polyurethane (BPU), are used to protect the CVAD insertion site from contamination. Additional securement devices, such as sutures, are used to reduce movement of the catheter. 

New products, including tissue adhesive (TA), sutureless securement devices (SSD), and combined securement and dressing products (CSD), are available to clinicians to provide securement and dressings for CVAD. It is not known whether these new products are effective at reducing CVAD failure, in comparison to standard care (BPU and suture).  
The primary aim of this research is to evaluate the feasibility of launching a full-scale efficacy trial, using pre-defined feasibility criteria for recruitment, retention and protocol fidelity. The secondary aim is to compare the effectiveness of dressings and securement products on CVAD failure due to infection, occlusion, dislodgement, thrombosis, or breakage, for children with tunnelled, cuffed CVAD in acute care.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Services, Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston, QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QRCH/181</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Nathan Campus, 
170 Kessels Road, 
Nathan, QLD 4111 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NRS/10/14/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Ullman</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing, Griffith University 
170 Kessels Rd, Nathan, QLD 4111 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 7854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.ullman@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Ullman</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing, Griffith University 
170 Kessels Rd, Nathan, QLD 4111 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 7854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.ullman@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Ullman</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing, Griffith University 
170 Kessels Rd, Nathan, QLD 4111 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 7854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.ullman@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Ullman</name>
      <address>NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence in Nursing, Griffith University 
170 Kessels Rd, Nathan, QLD 4111 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 7854</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.ullman@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>