<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373799">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001486314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can consuming caffeine after a nap improve productivity, alertness and safety?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Combining nap and caffeine countermeasures to improve productivity, alertness and safety in healthy adults undergoing a simulated nightshift</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Shiftwork</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sleep inertia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sleep deprivation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will undergo two 37h in laboratory sleep deprivation protocols. Participants will enter the laboratory at 11am on day 1; stay awake all night; and then sleep between 12pm and 6pm on day 2. Participants will remain in the lab until 12am.

Participants will undergo 2 conditions, with the order of conditions randomised: 1) 30min nap with 200mg caffeine gum on waking; and 2) a 30min nap with placebo gum. The 30min nap will be allowed between 2 to 2:30am.

They will visit the laboratory twice, a week apart, in a within groups, repeated measures design. Each person will be their own control. 

A 30 minute cognitive performance test battery, consisting of a 10 minute Psychomotor Vigilance Task, Karolinska Sleepiness Scale, Positive and Negative Affect Schedule, and mood Visual Analogue Scales will be administered at 8:30pm and 11pm on day 1 and at 1am, 5am, 9am, and 8:30pm on day 2. A 20 minute learning reversal decision task will be performed at 9pm on day 1 and 7:30am and 8:30pm on day 2. This computerised task is based on a go/no go paradigm. Initially four two-digit numbers are assigned to the go (response) set and four two-digit numbers are assigned to the no go (no response) set. Participants have a 750ms window to either respond or withhold a response to the number displayed on the screen. A hypothetical money reward/punishment is displayed to allow participants to determine which numbers are in the go set and which are in the no go set. After a number of trials (56, 60, or 64) the response sets are reversed for another 40 trials. A 40 minute driving simulation task (Yorke Driving Simulator) will be conducted at 7:30pm on day 1 and 6:30am, 10am, and 7:30pm on day 2. A sleep inertia test battery will be conducted post nap starting at 2:30am. 

Sleep inertia testing will consist of a 3 minute Psychomotor Vigilance Task, Karolinska Sleepiness Scale, and mood Visual Analogue Scales, and performed every 10 minutes (4 sleep inertia tests to map performance in the hour post nap).  

Venous blood sampling will be at 12:30pm on day 1 and 3:15am, 4:10am, 5:40am, and 11am on day 2 to quantify plasma caffeine concentrations for pharmacokinetic assessment, the impact of the caffeine gum on cortisol as a marker of stress and the impact of the caffeine gum on melatonin sectretion. Hourly saliva sampling will used to measure melatonin levels during wake periods.

Data will be analysed using mixed models and pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamics modelling will be used to investigate the relationship between blood (plasma) caffeine concentrations and various indices of sleep inertia.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shift in melatonin onset as measured in saliva using radioimmunoassay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Saliva will be collected hourly from 1800 to 0000 prior to caffeine administration and collected hourly from 1800 to 0000 post caffeine administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3 minute Psychomotor Vigilance Task</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutes, 15 minutes, 25 minutes, and 35 minutes post caffeine administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in melatonin secretion profile measured in plasma using radioimmunoassay</outcome>
      <timepoint>0,75 hours, 1.75 hours, and 3.25 hours  post caffeine administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurobehavioural Test Battery (10 minute Psychomotor Vigilance Task, Karolinska Sleepiness Scale, Positive and Negative Affect Scale, Visual Analogue Scales of mood)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2.5 hours, 6.5 hours, and 18 hours post caffeine administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A 20 minute learning reversal decision task (Go/No Go)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 hours and 18 hours post caffeine administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>40 Minute driving simulator task using the Yorke Driving Simulator</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 hours, 7.5 hours, and 17 hours post caffeine administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>BMI between 18.5-29 kg/m2
Habitual bedtime between 2100h and 2400h
Habitual wake time between 0600h and 0900h
Less than 2 hours of structured high impact activity per week
Currently taking a contraceptive pill or experiencing regular menstrual cycles (females)
Valid drivers licence or sufficient driving experience
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of smoking, drug, or alcohol abuse in the past year
History of psychiatric illness or sleep disorders such as insomnia and sleep apnoea
Food allergies
Trans-meridian travel in the 30 days prior to the study commencing
Clinically significant abnormalities in blood and urine
Shiftwork
Habitual napping
Caffeine intake exceeding 400mg per day on average
Score &lt;22 or &gt;44 on the Composite Morningness Questionnaire
Score &gt;14 on the Beck Depression Index
Score &gt;5 on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index
History of cardiovascular disease
History of a neurological disorder
Pulmonary disease requiring daily inhaler use
Kidney disease
Liver disease
History of psychiatric disorder requiring hospitalisation or psychiatric product for any length of time
Positive urine pregnancy result
Resting blood pressure above 140/90
Resting pulse &gt;110
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using procedures like coin-tossing and dice-rolling 
 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a pilot study. The results will be used to determine the number of participants needed to achieve the objectives of future studies.

Mixed Model Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) will be employed, including a random factor for subjects and fixed repeated-measures effects for caffeine group and test session. A fixed between-subjects (grouping) factor also will be included. Other analytical procedures (e.g. regression and/or discontinuous growth modelling) may be used to further evaluate interactive effects of caffeine vs placebo, naps and sleep loss.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>29/09/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>21/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>3</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assoc Prof Siobhan Banks</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of South Australia
Magill Campus
Sleep and Chronobiology Laboratory
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA 5072 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
101 Currie Street
Adelaide SA 5000
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Assoc Prof Jill Dorrian</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of South Australia
Magill Campus
Sleep and Chronobiology Laboratory
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA, 5072
Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Assoc Prof Alison Coates</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of South Australia
City East Campus
School of Health Sciences
Frome Road
Adelaide, SA 5000
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Stephanie Reuter Lange</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of South Australia
City East Campus
School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences
Frome Road
Adelaide, SA 5000
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Allan Evans</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of South Australia
City West Campus
Provost and Chief Academic Officer Chancellery and Council Services
North Tce
Adelaide, SA 5000
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Kurt Lushington</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Head of School
University of South Australia
Magill Campus
Psychology, Social Work and Social Policy
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA, 5072
Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Antonietta Colella</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Industry Engagement Adviser
Safework SA
4/33 Richmond Rd
Keswick SA 5035</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mercedes Iasiello</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Principal WHS Strategy and Policy Consultant, Strategy Policy and Performance
SA Health
Citi Centre Building
11 Hindmarsh Square
Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Fatigue causes a deterioration in cognitive performance that leads to workplace errors, injury and reduced safety. Shift work is a major source of fatigue because it disrupts the timing and duration of sleep opportunities; and therefore night workers are often chronically sleep deprived. Our work shows that 30min naps can be a powerful tool for maintaining performance during conditions of sleep deprivation. Naps can be particularly beneficial for night workers, who are on duty at times when their body rhythms naturally prime them to be asleep. However, napping can also be hazardous. Our studies show that it can have deleterious effects, in particular, `sleep inertia, the groggy feeling and performance impairment experienced after waking where workers are extremely vulnerable to errors. This is problematic for oncall workers or health care professionals who take naps during extended hours or night shifts, but on waking need to process complex information, or engage in safety critical activities. Our recent systematic review found very few studies have investigated countermeasures that that can be implemented immediately on waking to reduce sleep inertia. Our work with caffeine gum, funded by USA and Australian Army has found it is fast acting (i.e. within 5min). It could therefore be the ideal countermeasure for the sleep inertia associated with night time naps.

This study aims to answer two questions:
1.	Will 200mg of caffeine (given in gum form) administered upon waking from a 30 min nap at 2:30am prevent sleep inertia when compared to placebo?
2.	Will 200mg of caffeine (given in gum form) administered upon waking from a 30 min nap at 2:30am impact daytime recovery sleep between 12 and 6pm? 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia’s Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of South Australia
Magill Campus
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA, 5072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000036014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Siobhan Banks</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
Magill Campus
Sleep and Chronobiology Laboratory
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA, 5072
</address>
      <phone>+618 8302 1712</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Siobhan.banks@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jackie Stepien-Hulleman</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
Magill Campus
Sleep and Chronobiology Laboratory
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA, 5072
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+618 8302 1970</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jacqueline.stepien-hulleman@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jackie Stepien-Hulleman</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
Magill Campus
Sleep and Chronobiology Laboratory
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA, 5072
Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8302 1970</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jacqueline.stepien-hulleman@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jackie Stepien-Hulleman</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
Magill Campus
Sleep and Chronobiology Laboratory
St Bernards Rd
Magill, SA, 5072
Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 8302 1970</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jacqueline.stepien-hulleman@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>