<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372337">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000274370p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does naltrexone reduce pain or disability after a whiplash?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does low dose naltrexone help to reduce pain or disability after a whiplash following a car crash? A pilot study of effects of low dose naltrexone on glial activation and neuroinflammatory process. The NALWHIP Study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-4123</utrn>
    <trialacronym>the NALWHIP study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>whiplash injury
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>whiplash associated disorder
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>a randomised, placebo-controlled pilot trial of low dose naltrexone given  after a whiplash injury. 20 participants are needed in each group (total=40). The participants will enter the observation period (2 weeks) prior to commencing the treatment period. Low dose naltrexone (LDN) is equivalent to 4.5 mg daily, compounded in a specialist pharmacy and administered as an oral tablet at bed time for a total of 8 weeks (treatment period). </interventions>
    <comparator>the control group will include 20 participants, who sustained a whiplash injury following a car crash in the preceding 4 weeks. They will undergo an observation period for 2 weeks prior to enter the control group. The participants will be given sham tablets which have the same colour and taste as the LDN tablet. Sham tablets are composed of a coated sweetener. Total period of control (placebo) treatment is 8 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion of participants in each group with a reduction in the numerical pain score (NPS) of &gt;=30 points (measured on a scale from 0-100). NPS reduction will be calculated from NPS at end of treatment period (each group) subtracted from the NPS in the observation period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>NPS reduction will be measured as the change in NPS at completion of the 8 weeks treatment period (each group) compared to the baseline NPS value at end of the 2 weeks observation period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion of participants in each group with a reduction in the neck disability index (NDI) score of &gt;=10 points(measured on a scale of 50 points, multiplied by 2 to give a maximum score of a 100 points), at end of treatment compared to NDI scores at end of the observation period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>the NDI scores  reduction is calculated from the difference between the NDI at completion of the 8 weeks treatment period and the baseline NDI at end of the 2 weeks observation period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants in each group with a  &gt;=30% reduction in cold allodynia measured using quantitative sensory testing (QST) to cold at preselected anatomical sites at completion of the treatment period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cold allodynia at completion of the 8 weeks treatment period compared to that at end of the 2 weeks observation period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion of participants in each group with a reduction in the numerical pain score (NPS) of &gt;=30 points (measured on a scale from 0-100) at follow up visits compared to baseline NPS at end of the observation period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months post randomisation (follow up visits), compared to baseline NPS at end of the 2 weeks observation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion of participants in each group with a reduction in the NDI score of &gt;=10 points at follow up visits compared to baseline NDI scores at end of observation period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At  6 months post randomisation (follow up visits), compared to baseline NDI at end of the 2 weeks observation period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion  of participants in each group with a  &gt;=30 reduction in cold pain allodynia  measured at preselected anatomical sites.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months from randomisation (follow up visit) compared to baseline value at end of  the 2 weeks observation period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion of participants in each group with a reduction in DASS21 score (depression, anxiety, stress questionnaire) of &gt;=6 points (maximum possible score of 63= worst symptoms imaginable) at completion of treatment period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>DASS21 at completion of the 8 weeks treatment period compared to baseline DASS21 at end of the 2 weeks observation period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1- an adult who had a whiplash injury following a car crash in the past 4 weeks.
2- moderately severe initial injury (WAD class II and III).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1- very severe whiplash injury (WAD IV)
2- pregnant patients.
3- patients with immune disorders or inflammatory arthritis e.g. multiple sclerosis, fibromyalgia, rheumatoid arthritis , systemic lupus erythematosus and Diabetes mellitus.
4- patients on opioid analgesics.
5- participants who have difficulty understanding English
6- participants who may have problems accessing online surveys/diaries to complete data entries.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation to a group will be provide via sealed opaque envelops.</concealment>
    <sequence>simple randomisation using a toss of a coin.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>the number of participants was calculated on the basis of the IMMPACT latest statement for proof of concept studies, power=80%, type-I error (false positive rate)=0.2. and a reduction of average pain by 30% compared to baseline average pain scores.
An experienced statistician will be recruited to analyse the data and help its interpretation.  The p- value is chosen to be 0.2 per the IMMPACT latest statements on proof of concept studies, 2015 (higher type I error i.e. false positive rate is planned to increase the chance of detecting any efficacy of LDN).
All analyses were conducted using SPSS statistical package V. The primary clinical end-point was self-reported daily pain. Because this study used an intensive longitudinal design, assumptions of independent and identically distributed residuals could not be made, and therefore, the proper modelling of data interdependency across time was a significant concern. To test all models, the linear mixed model (LMM) approach was used. The LMM allows for correlated observations in the dependent variable. Denominator degrees of freedom were estimated via SPSS conventions when using LMMs with repeated-measures data.
To test the primary clinical outcome, the percentage of change in the level of pain from baseline was entered as the dependent variable, and the study day was entered as the repeated index. The optimal working correlation matrix for repeated measures was determined by contrasting the available options with the Bayesian information criterion, with autoregressive as the default structure. Baseline pain was calculated by averaging pain across the entire 14-day baseline period. To contrast the placebo and low-dose naltrexone conditions, the percentage of pain reduction from baseline was assessed during the final 3 days of each treatment condition. Condition (placebo versus low-dose naltrexone) was entered as a fixed factor. Two control variables were also tested in the model. First, baseline pain severity was entered. The baseline pain control variable was designed to determine if individuals with greater baseline severity were more likely to respond to placebo or low-dose naltrexone. Second, a linear time function was entered. The time variable was included to determine if change in pain could be attributed simply to natural improvement over time. The time variable was created by entering the observation day (days 170) for each outcome data point. The time variable was tested in a separate model to properly include the entire longitudinal data set, and to avoid artificial overlap with the condition X group interaction. The modelling approach was repeated for all secondary outcomes. 
Differences in response rate between the placebo and LDN conditions and differences in proportions of other secondary outcomes and QSTs results are statistically assessed with a chi-square test.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Joondalup Health Campus - Joondalup</hospital>
    <postcode>6027 - Joondalup</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Notre Dame University Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Notre Dame University
32 Mouat Street, Fremantle WA 6160
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Joondalup Health Campus</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Shenton Avenue,
Joondalup WA 6027
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Design: this is a randomised, double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial in patients with whiplash injury. it aims at testing whether a medicine we are trialling may reduce long term pain after a whiplash injury.
Each group will include 20 participants, who will be recruited after presenting to the emergency department at JHC. Detailed information sheet will be supplied to all participants prior to asking them to consent for the trail. Participants will voluntarily enter the trial, have their rights of declining participation and terminating their participation explained to them in the first interview and provided to them in writing. All their data will be secured on a computer, not shared with anyone outside this research group. All their personal details will be destroyed once data analysis and journal submission is complete.
You will be entering one of the groups by the order of chance using opaque sealed envelops. The investigators will have no prior knowledge which group you will fall into and no knowledge of which group you belong to during the phases of this study. If you are randomly selected into the treatment group, you will receive the active medicine, called low dose naltrexone. it is given as one tablet at bed time.
If you are randomly selected into the 'placebo' group, you will be give a' sham' tablet to take daily at bed time. 

The study will run an observation period of 2 weeks, followed by a treatment period of 8 weeks, and a follow up visit at 6 months from the time you were randomised into a group.
Observation phase: all participants will have daily numerical pain scale reported (0-100), zero equals no pain at all and a 100 means the worst imaginable pain, highest neck disability index (NDI) will be measured based on a validated questionnaire, Sensory testing (called QST) of your sensitivity to graded  cold on specific sites of the body will be tested,.  An assessment of your stress, anxiety and depression will be conducted using a specific questionnaire (DASS21), This will be done at same time points as the measures of neck disability and skin testing. 
 A baseline blood test for inflammatory markers will obtained once from each participant.
Treatment phase: placebo group will receive sham tablets at bed time for 8 weeks, treatment group will receive LDN at bed time for 8 weeks. All participants will record their NPS at the same time of taking the tablet. NDI, QST and DASS21 will be conducted at end of treatment period, and CRP will be tested once at end of the 8 weeks treatment period.

Follow-up: at 6 months from entering a study group; we are planning to measure NPS, NDI, conduct QSTs, DASS21 and  repeat the CRP test once per visit.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>none</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Notre Dame Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>32 Mouat Street, Fremantle WA 6160</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasir Al-Tamimi</name>
      <address>Department of anaesthesia and pain management 
Joondalup Health Campus
Shenton avenue, Joondalup WA 6027
</address>
      <phone>+618 94009400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>altamimiy@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasir Al-Tamimi</name>
      <address>Department of anaesthesia and pain management 
Joondalup Health Campus
Shenton avenue, Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 94009400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>altamimiy@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Eric Visser</name>
      <address>Department of anaesthesia and pain management 
Joondalup Health Campus
Shenton avenue, Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61894009400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vissere@ramsayhealth.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>