<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336421">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000147987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison study of two different techniques for knee replacement</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with osteoarthritis of the knee, are patient specific cutting guides used for total knee joint replacement as good as computer-assisted surgery for patient outcomes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-0601</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ShapeMatchNZRCT-10</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of the knee</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>For patients requiring a total knee replacement a new method has been developed which may improve patient satisfaction levels in terms of function and pain after surgery.  Instead of using conventional measuring and cutting equipment and computer-assisted navigation (Control Group), patient-specific cutting guides will be manufactured based on pre-operative Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scans of the patient's leg (Intervention Group).  The patient will have a total knee replacement performed using these cutting guides which will ultimately align the patients prosthesis according to their natural leg alignment (as opposed to the convention way where the patients leg is aligned according to a mechanical axis of 0 degrees).  The procedure will take approximately 45 minutes.
Both groups will receive the same type of implant.   Patients will be followed up at 6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months and also have a Computed Tomography (CT) scan at 3 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the Control Group will receive a total knee replacement using conventional methods and equipment where their implant will be positioned so that their leg is a straight line from their hip to their ankle (i.e. mechanical axis of 0 degrees).  The procedure will take approximately 45 minutes.

Patients will be randomized to either the Control Group or Intervention Group  and will not be told which group they have been assigned to.  As a result, patients assigned to the Control Group will also need to have a pre-operative MRI scan.   
Patients in the Control Group will also be followed up at 6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months, and also have a Computed Tomography (CT) scan at 3 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To demonstrate, through calculation of Oxford Knee Score at 12 months postoperative, that total knee replacement (TKR) performed using the ShapeMatch Cutting Guide provides improvement from preoperative levels of patient pain and function comparable to the improvement obtained with TKR performed using computer-assisted Navigation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively and 6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The efficacy objective is to compare radiographic, pain, function and health-related quality of life (QOL) between the ShapeMatch Cutting Guide group and the computer-assisted Navigation control group. This objective will be achieved by utilizing the following instruments pre-operatively and at the 6-week, 6-month and 12 month visits:
-	Perth CT protocol
-	AP and ML X-rays
-	The International Knee Society Score (IKSS)
-	The Forgotten Joint Score (FJS-12)
-	WOMAC
-	EQ-5D
-	VAS Pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively and 6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the cost-effectiveness and cost-utility of the procedure between the ShapeMatch Cutting Guide group and the computer-assisted Navigation control group. This objective will be assessed by recording and calculating the following parameters:
-	Wound length
-	Total duration of operating procedure (anaesthetic time and skin-to-skin incision time)
-	Cost of consumable items used during operating procedure
-	Length of stay in hospital
-	Quality-adjusted life-years (QALYs) from EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra-operatively, at hospital discharge and at 6 weeks, 6 months and 12 post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	The patient is a male or non-pregnant female between the ages of 50-80.
-	The patient requires a primary total knee replacement and is indicated for computer-assisted surgery.
-	The patient has a primary diagnosis of osteoarthritis (OA).
-	The patient has intact collateral ligaments.
-	The patient is able to undergo MRI scanning of the affected limb.
-	The patient has signed the study specific, HREC-approved, Informed Consent document.
-	The patient is willing and able to comply with the specified pre-operative and post-operative clinical and radiographic evaluations.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	The patient has a history of total, unicompartmental reconstruction or fusion of the affected joint.
-	Patient has had a high tibial osteotomy or femoral osteotomy.
-	The patient is morbidly obese (BMI is greater than or equal to 40).
-	The patient has a deformity which will require the use of stems, wedges or augments in conjunction with the Triathlon Total Knee System. 
-	The patient has varus or valgus malalignment greater than or equal to 15 degrees (relative to mechanical axis).
-	The patient has a fixed flexion deformity greater than or equal to 15 degrees.
-	The patient has a neuromuscular or neurosensory deficiency, which would limit the ability to assess the performance of the device.
-	The patient has a systemic or metabolic disorder leading to progressive bone deterioration.
-	The patient is immunologically suppressed or receiving steroids in excess of normal physiological requirements.
-	Patient has a cognitive impairment, an intellectual disability or a mental illness.
-	The patient is pregnant.
-	The patient has metal hardware present in the region of the hip, knee or ankle (as this is known to create geometrical distortion in the region of the implant).
-	The patient has any known contraindications for undergoing assessment by MRI (e.g. ferrous implants, metallic clips, magnetically activated implanted devices such as cardiac pacemakers, etc).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be enrolled in the study after signing the informed consent form and meeting the inclusion and exclusion criteria.  If participants met these criteria they will be randomised to either the Control Group or the Intervention Group.
This will be achieved via a block randomisation process. A central randomisation list will be computer generated by a consultant statistician. Once a patient has met criteria for enrolment, the Principal Investigator or designee will phone/email the Sponsor with the Initials, Date of Birth and Patient Number (assigned in ascending order at time of recruitment). A randomisation number, corresponding to a randomisation envelope held at the study site, will be provided. Once this number is received the envelope will be located and opened. The Principal Investigator will note the group allocation in the Case Report Form.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer will generate a randomisation sequence which will allocate each study number to either the control group or the intervention group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Stryker Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>8 Herbert Street
St Leonards, Sydney
NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Stryker Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>8 Herbert Street
St Leonards, Sydney
NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Traditionally the goal of the knee replacement has been to position the components such that the alignment goal is a straight limb, or a mechanical axis of 0 degrees.  This has been considered desirable from an engineering point of view to maximise implant longevity, however patient satisfaction of total knee replacement has not always been ideal.

The opportunity exists to provide an alternative approach to total knee replacement surgery which may improve patient outcomes.  One such approach is to determine the optimal placement of components based on the individual anatomy of patients, rather than a generic limb alignment philosophy.  A three-dimensional description of the anatomy can be obtained by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans obtained pre-operatively.  It is then possible to develop a model of the arthritic bone and cartilage, adapt that model to take into account degenerative processes, and generate a model of the pre-arthritic anatomy.  The pre-arthritic state then becomes the surgical goal in terms of limb alignment.  Custom cutting guides are generated for each individual patient to enable the surgeon to perform the bone resections in such a way that the resultant construct with the total knee replacement components reproduces the pre-disease limb alignment.

The aim of the study is to observe whether there is any difference in outcome following a total knee replacement in terms of pain and function at early follow-up (6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months) between the ShapeMatch Cutting Guide group and the control group.  Radiographic, pain, function and health-related quality of life will be compared between both groups using various questionnaires which patients will complete prior to the operation and at 6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months following their total knee replacement.

The study will also aim to compare the cost-effectiveness and cost-utility of the procedure between the ShapeMatch group and the Navigation group by recording and calculating various parameters including total duration of operating procedure and length of stay in hospital following the operation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3rd Floor, Unisys Building
650 Great South Road, Penrose, Auckland, NZ</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/11/03/017</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Timothy Barker</name>
      <address>Director of Clinical Research
Stryker Australia
8 Herbert Street
ST LEONARDS
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3840 5200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tim.barker@stryker.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Timothy Barker</name>
      <address>Director of Clinical Research
Stryker Australia
8 Herbert Street
ST LEONARDS
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3840 5200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tim.barker@stryker.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Timothy Barker</name>
      <address>Director of Clinical Research 
Stryker Australia
8 Herbert Street
ST LEONARDS
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3840 5200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tim.barker@stryker.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>