<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343359">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000992909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of Galvus on post-meal artery function and triglyceride levels in Type 2 diabetic individuals with high triglyceride levels who are on a statin medication.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of Galvus (vildagliptin) on post-prandial endothelial function and post-prandial hypertriglyceridaemia in individuals with Type 2 diabetes and fasting hypertriglyceridaemia, treated with statins.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-8144</utrn>
    <trialacronym>VIPER Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertriglyceridaemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>vildagliptin 50mg oral tablet twice daily for 6 weeks. 

The wash out period between the two treatment arms is 6 weeks.

During the study period participants will continue with their usual metformin and statin treatments.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo replica oral tablet without the active ingredient, twice daily for 6 weeks.


The wash out period between the two treatment arms is 6 weeks.


During the study period participants will continue with their usual metformin and statin treatments.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUC and incremental AUC for serum triglycerides following standardised fat meal which contains 129 grams of fat.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the Week 6 and Week 18 Visits AUC and incremental AUC for serum triglycerides following a standardised fat meal will be assessed at timepoints 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 120, 150, 180, 210, 240, 300, 360, 420 and 480 minutes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak post-ischaemic forearm blood flow and post-ischaemic flow debt repayment, measured by forearm plethysmography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the Week 6 and Week 18 Visits Peak post-ischaemic forearm blood flow and post-ischaemic flow debt repayment, measured by forearm plethysmography will be measured at timepoints 0 and 4 hours post a standardised fat meal.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUC and incremental AUC for serum apoB48, apoB100, glucose, insulin, cholesterol and free fatty acids following standardized fat meal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the Week 6 and Week 18 Visits AUC and incremental AUC for serum apoB48, apoB100, glucose, insulin, cholesterol and free fatty acids following standardized fat meal will be assessed at timepoints 0, 120, 240, 360 and 480 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Outpatients with Type 2 diabetes on metformin treatment only (at doses 500mg to 1000mg twice daily).
HbA1c &lt; 8%.
Already treated with a statin for at least 6 weeks with LDL cholesterol&lt;2.5 mmol/L.
Hypertriglyceridaemia (Triglycerides &gt; 1.7 mmol/L) on a random blood sample.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Treatment with other oral diabetes medications other than metformin.
Treatment with insulin or exenatide.
HbA1c &gt; 8%.
Treatment with fibrates.
Premenopausal females. Menopause is defined as 12 consecutive months without menstruation. If menopausal status is in question, a follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) level of &gt; 30 mIU/ml must be documented.
Primary dyslipidaemia, including the E2/E2 genotype.
Type III dyslipedaemia.
Uncontrollable hypertension: resting BP &gt; 150/90.
Consumption of  &gt; 30g alcohol per week. 
Tobacco smoking.
Significantly abnormal liver function (ALT or AST &gt; 3 times ULN).
Creatine kinase &gt; 3 x ULN.
Creatinaemia (&gt; 150 micromols).
Macroproteinuria.
Significantly abnormal thyroid function.
Atrial fibrillation or significant dysrythmia.
Cardiovascular event in the last 6 months.
Anaemia.
Gastric disorders.
Any other serious medical / systemic illness  (e.g cancer).
Use of steroids or other medications that may affect lipid metabolism.
Psychiatric illness.
Allergies to eggs, cream, milk.
Likelihood of poor compliance to the study.
Likelihood of not completing the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Type 2 diabetes who fulfill the selection criteria will be randomly allocated to one of two sequence groups (Group A and B). 


Allocation will be concealed from study staff.

Allocation involves contacting the person holding the allocation schedule who is not involved in the study.


Group A will be treated with vildagliptin in addition to Metformin and Statin medications for a 6 week treatment period, followed by 6 weeks washout period, then followed by treatment with placebo in addition to Metformin and Statin medication for a 6 week treatment period.


Group B will be treated with placebo in addition to Metformin and Statin medications for a 6 week treatment period, followed by 6 weeks washout period, then followed by treatment with valdagliptin in addition to Metformin and Statin medication for a 6 week treatment period.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomised sequence generated by computer</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>6000-6250</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Seng Khee Gan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Western Australia
School of Medicine and Pharmacology, Royal Perth Hospital
Level 4, MRF Building
50 (rear) Murray Street,
Perth. 6000
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>35 Stirling Highway
Crawley  6009
Perth. Western Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis Pharmaceuticals Australia Pty Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>54 Waterloo Road
North Ryde 2113
New South Wales</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Perth Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Wellington Street
Perth. 6000
Western Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cardiovascular disease is a common major complication in patients with Type 2 diabetes. People with Type 2 diabetes have abnormal blood fat levels which contribute to this risk of heart disease, particularly high triglycerides, low HDL (good) cholesterol and high small dense LDL (bad) cholesterol. Cholesterol lowering medications called statins are widely used to treat this abnormal blood fat metabolism found in Type 2 diabetes. Cholesterol guidelines advise that the LDL-cholesterol be treated to a level of less than 2.5mmol/L. However, more than 30% of patients with Type 2 diabetes continue to have high triglycerides at levels greater than 1.7mmol/L even when their LDL-cholesterol is treated to less than 2.5mmol/L. These patients with high triglyceride levels remain at higher risk of cardiovascular disease despite the statin therapy.   

Vildagliptin is used to lower blood sugar in patients with Type 2 diabetes.  It belongs to a class of medicines known as DPP-4 inhibitors (dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitors) and is effective in lowering post-meal blood sugar levels. Current evidence suggests that vildagliptin lowers post-meal blood triglyceride levels in patients with Type 2 diabetes not taking statin therapy.  It is not known whether vildagliptin improves artery function (a marker of risk of cardiovascular disease) in people with Type 2 diabetes.  It is proposed that, for the group of patients with Type 2 diabetes and high blood triglyceride levels despite statin treatment, an improvement of artery function could occur concurrently with improvement of post-meal blood triglyceride levels with vildagliptin treatment.  Thus, vildagliptin may help reduce the high risk of future cardiovascular disease in this group of patients.

The aim of this study is to examine the effect of vildagliptin on post-meal blood fat levels and post-meal artery function in patients with type 2 diabetes and high blood triglyceride levels despite taking statins.  Participating patients will already be receiving metformin to control blood sugar.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5, Colonial House
Royal Perth Hospital
Murray Street,
Perth. 6000 
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof. Seng Khee Gan</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Medicine and Pharmacology
Royal Perth Hospital
Level 4, MRF Building
50 (rear) Murray Street,
Perth. 6000
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61, 8 92240256</phone>
      <fax>+61, 8, 92240246</fax>
      <email>seng.gan@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Laurie Kear</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Medicine and Pharmacology
Royal Perth Hospital
Level 3, MRF Building
50 (rear) Murray Street,
Perth.  6000
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61, 8, 92240390</phone>
      <fax>+61, 8, 92240243</fax>
      <email>laurie.kear@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof. Seng Khee Gan</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Medicine and Pharmacology
Royal Perth Hospital
Level 4, MRF Building
50 (rear) Murray Street,
Perth. 6000
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61, 8 92240256</phone>
      <fax>+61, 8, 92240246</fax>
      <email>seng.gan@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>