<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373377">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001179325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sonographic Monitoring of Diaphragm after Cardiac Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ultrasonographic Evaluation of the Diaphragm in patients undergoing cardiac surgery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diaphragm dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The enrolled patients will undergo to a sonographic measurement of diaphragmatic motion (right and left hemidiaphragmatic excursion) and diaphragmatic thickness (on the right side) the day before surgery, during the weaning trial, the day after the weaning trials and at the patient  discharge. 
All patients will be evaluated in a semi-recumbent position, with the head of the bed elevated at an angle between 30° and 45°. Ultrasound will be performed using a SonoSite ultrasound system equipped with a 5 MHz convex probe for the subcostal approach and a 13 MHz linear probe for the approach in the zone of apposition.
To evaluate diaphragmatic displacement, the probe is places immediately below the right or left costal margin, between the mid-clavicular and anterior axillary lines, using liver or spleen as acoustic windows. The probe is directed medially, cephalad and dorsally, so that the ultrasound beam reaches perpendicularly the posterior third of the corresponding hemi-diaphragm. 
Diaphragm is identified as a hyperechoic line, produced by the pleura tighten adherent to the muscle.The two dimensional (2D) mode is initially used to obtain the best approach and select the exploration line. The M-mode is then used to display the motion of the anatomical structures along the selected line.
To evaluate diaphragmatic thickness,, the probe is placed in the zone of apposition of the diaphragm to the rib cage, between the 8th and the 10th intercostals space in the mid-axillary line, 0,5-2 cm below the costophrenic sinus. 
In this area, the diaphragm is observed as a structure made of three distinct layers: the nearest line is the parietal pleura, the deeper one is the peritoneum; the diaphragm is the less echogenic structure between these two lines. The Thickening Fraction (TF) can be calculated as widely described in the literature.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate if cardiac surgery can reduce the respiratory effort as assessed through the diaphragm ultrasonogaphy</outcome>
      <timepoint>The enrolled patients will undergo to a sonographic measurement of diaphragmatic motion to assess the diaphragm thickening fractio (TF) the day before surgery, during the weaning trial daily before extubation, and the day after the weaning trials and at the patient  discharge. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate if cardiac surgery can reduce the respiratory drive as assessed through the diaphragm ultrasonogaphy</outcome>
      <timepoint>The enrolled patients will undergo to a sonographic measurement of diaphragmatic motion to assess the diaphragm craniocaudal displacement the day before surgery, during the weaning trial daily before extubation, and the day after the weaning trials and at the patient  discharge. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the diaphragmatic dysfunction evolution until the patient discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ultrasound diaphragm assessment (i.e. diaphragm displacement and thickening fraction) will be done the day before surgery, during the weaning trial, the day after the weaning trial daily before extubation and at the patient  discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the rate of severe diaphragmatic dysfunction, measured like a diaphragmatic excursion trough diaphragmatic ultrasound less than 10mm during normal spontaneous breathing</outcome>
      <timepoint>After extubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patients that are undergoing an elective heart surgery</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria are: 1) age &lt;18 years; 2) urgent surgery; 3) death of the patient; 4) elevated hemidiaphragm on a preoperative chest radiographs; 5) presence or history of thoracostomy, pneumothorax, pneumomediastinum, phrenic nerve injury, neuromuscular disease, brain injury</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>We therefore have computed our sample size basing on data by Matamis et al (4). A minimum of 63 patients will be required to show a 10% reduction in diaphragm displacement after 24 hours from the surgery, respect to baseline (alpha error = 0.05, desired power 0.80).To evaluate the variation among intra and inter observers measurements, we will compute the interclass coefficient. The normal distribution will be assessed through the Kolmogorov- Smirnov test.  Data will be presented as mean and standard deviation or median and interquartile range, Data will be compared with an analisys of variance for repeated measures and a Bonferroni post-hoc test for pairwise comparisons. 
Some variables will be also analyzed in relation to the percentage of reduction of the diaphragm displacement. In particular the following variables will be insert in a multiple linear stepwise regression model: patients-related risk factors (age, obesity, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease , diabetes mellitus type 2, hypo or hyper tyrodism) or surgery related factors (cold cardioplegia, left internal mammary artery isolation, aortic clamp time).
Tested variables will be insert in the model for p values &lt;0.05 and removed if p&gt;0.10.
p values &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>63</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Federico Longhini</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Chirurgiche, Università Magna Graecia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Viale Europa - Loc. Germaneto 88100 Catanzaro
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Antonio Gemelli</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, ospedale Mater Domini, Viale Europa - Loc. Germaneto 88100, Catanzaro
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Italy</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Paolo Navalesi</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Chirurgiche, Università Magna Graecia, Viale Europa - Loc. Germaneto 88100 
Catanzaro
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Italy</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A recent analysis by Deg et al. of data collected on 2084 consecutive patients, who underwent cardiac surgery, found 53 phrenic nerve injuries (2,5%). 
This prospective study aims to evaluate if cardiac surgery can change diaphragmatic function. The secondary outcomes are:
1)	evaluating the diaphragmatic dysfunction until the patient discharge,
2)	identifying risk factors patient-correlate (age, body mass index, CPOD, diabetes, hypothyroidism, hyperthyroidism) or surgery correlate (cold cardioplegia, harvesting of the IMA, time of the aortic cross-clump).
3)	Recognize severe diaphragmatic dysfunction, measured like a diaphragmatic excursion less than 10mm during normal spontaneous breathing
The enrolled patients will undergo to a sonographic measurement of diaphragmatic motion (right and left hemidiaphragmatic excursion) and diaphragmatic thickness (on the right side) the day before surgery, during the weaning trial, the day after the weaning trials and at the patient  discharge. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comitato Etico sezione Centro - Regione Calabria</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>A.O.U. Mater Domini in Via Tommaso Campanella, 115 Catanzaro</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>124/2017</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Italy</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paolo Navalesi</name>
      <address>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Chirurgiche, Università Magna Graecia, Viale Europa - Loc. Germaneto 88100, Catanzaro,
</address>
      <phone>+393355321910</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pnavalesi@unicz.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Federico Longhini</name>
      <address>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli </address>
      <phone>+393475395967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>longhini.federico@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Federico Longhini</name>
      <address>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli </address>
      <phone>+393475395967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>longhini.federico@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Federico Longhini</name>
      <address>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli </address>
      <phone>+393475395967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>longhini.federico@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>