<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367503">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001317684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of a tailored Cardiac-Diabetes Trans-Care program compared to usual care on hospital readmission rates and health-related quality of life in patients with dual diagnoses of acute coronary syndrome and type 2 diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a tailored Cardiac-Diabetes Trans-Care program compared to usual care on hospital readmission rates and health-related quality of life in patients with dual diagnoses of acute coronary syndrome and type 2 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1164-5013</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Cardiac/Diabetes TRANS-CARE: Cardiac/Diabetes transitional care program</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None. This study has not been registered with any other registry.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute coronary syndrome </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The "Cardiac/Diabetes TRANS-CARE program", which consists of two face-to-face sessions, a home visit and telephone follow-up. Purpose of the intervention: to increase self-efficacy to enhance self-management behaviours and thus improve health outcomes and reduce hospital readmissions. 

Contents/Duration (Reference: Wu &amp; Chang 2014 http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/inr.12104/pdf ):
- 2 sessions (2 x 30 minute sessions, separated by 1 day)  while in hospital: these sessions will be provided by a trained research nurse, and focusing on 1) assessing patients knowledge of their conditions and skills and confidence in self-management; 2) providing patient examples or models of someone in a similar situation. 
- 1 in-home visit with duration of approx 1 hour: The home visit will be provided by a trained research nurse within the first week post discharge. This visit is to ensure that patients will be sufficient support, information, self-management activities including their treatment regimens are carried out in home environment, reinforcement and further explanation of self-management program
- weekly telephone calls for 4 weeks after home visit, and monthly up to 6 months. These calls will be undertaken by the trained research nurse. The telephone follow up calls are to ensure that patients have sufficient support, to encourage and reinforce the participant to continue practising the knowledge and skills to self-manage their conditions. Each phone call will take 20-30 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator in this study is standard care  Cardiac patients with diabetes admitted to acute hospital receive standard cardiac education and are referred to a cardiac rehabilitation nurse or diabetes educator when necessary.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Six month readmission rate: data linkage to patient medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life: will be measured by Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3 and 6 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomedical markers: will be measured by patient medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, 1, 3, 6 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-management behaviour: will be measured by Self-efficacy for managing chronic disease 6-item scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3 months and 6 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>patients who are admitted to hospital with acute coronary syndrome (ACS) and diagnosed with type 2 diabetes </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are critically ill, or unconscious, being referred for cardiac surgery, on respiratory ventilation, have a current significant cognitive impairment. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Baseline data collection is blinded and will be undertaken before randomisation. Allocation will be concealed by using sealed, numbered, opaque envelopes; list generation will be provided by researcher off site, after randomisation. Patients are not blinded to ‘intervention’ and surveys do not have group ID, thus data entry is blinded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table (computerised sequence generation) will be used.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An initial target of 432 eligible subjects will be recruited to the study. It is anticipated that there will be approximately 20% attrition over the 6 month follow-up period, to enable &gt;90% power to detect a difference between groups in 6-month readmission rate. To inform the effect size for this sample size calculation we performed a subgroup analyses from our previous randomised trial that investigated an intervention with a home visit and 6-month telephone follow-up. That sub-group analysis (n=49) indicated a between group difference in 6-month readmission rate of 31.5% (Medium effect size), with statistical significance level of .05.
1) Baseline data for both the intervention and control groups will be examined to check for similarity of the groups.
2) Comparisons between groups will be undertaken. e.g. Chi square tests will be used for proportions of patients re-admitted.
3) Repeated measures regression model will be used to investigate differences over the 4 data collection points and determine the effect of the intervention over time.
4) The economic evaluation will comprise a cost-effectiveness (cost-utility) modelling conducted alongside the RCT 

Because the sample size estimate for this investigation was not calculated from pilot data obtained from this specific target population, an interim analysis of hospital re-presentation event rate in the sample will be undertaken. This analysis will examine the 3-month representation rate (both groups combined) to see whether it is higher or lower than rates used in the sample size calculation. This will be conducted using the first (approximately) 10% of the target sample to reached the 3-month re-assessment point by a statistician not involved in the day-to-day operations of the trial. The statistician will be provided with a dataset from each trial site that does not include a variable for group allocation and no attempt to compare event rates between groups during the interim analysis will occur. Rather the sole purpose of the event rate interim analysis is to verify or refute whether the effect size used in the initial sample size estimate is plausible based on the rate at which patients in the target sample are re-presenting to the participating hospitals. If the event rate is substantially discordant with the sample size estimate the investigator team will decide (in conjunction with the local ethics committees) whether an amendment to the trial protocol (to increase the sample size or cease the trial early) is warranted. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>432</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Catholic University (ACU)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Nursing, Midwifery and Paramedicine, Faculty of Health Sciences, Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo Queensland 4014 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Nursing, Midwifery and Paramedicine, Faculty of Health Sciences, Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo Queensland 4014 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital (RBWH)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Butterfield St, Herston QLD 4006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St Vincent’s Hospital Melbourne (SVHM)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Victoria Parade, Fitzroy, VIC 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Participants with dual diagnoses of acute coronary syndrome and type 2 diabetes in both intervention and control groups will be evaluated on primary and secondary outcomes to determine whether aims of the study have achieved.
Aims: 1)To evaluate the effect of the Cardiac/Diabetes TRANS-CARE on: 6-month re-admission rates, time to first readmission, unplanned emergency department presentations, general practitioner visits after discharge, self-reported health status, psychosocial well-being at 1, 3 and 6 months. 2) To evaluate the cost-effectiveness of this intervention from the perspective of the health system
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women’s Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Butterfield Street, Herston, QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QRBW/301</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Human Research Ethics Committee-A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>41 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-A 127/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Australian Catholic University, PO Box 456, Virginia, QLD 4014</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014 309Q</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Courtney</name>
      <address>National Head, School of Nursing, Midwifery and Paramedicine, Faculty of Health Sciences, Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo Queensland 4014 Australia


</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7719</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mary.Courtney@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Wu</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo Queensland 4014 Australia

</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7889</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jo.Wu@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Wu</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo Queensland 4014 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7889</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jo.Wu@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Wu</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo Queensland 4014 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7889</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jo.Wu@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>