<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373644">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001343392p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Managing fluency and disruptive behaviours in children who stutter: An integrated behavioural and stuttering treatment program
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Managing fluency and disruptive behaviours in children who stutter: An integrated behavioural and stuttering treatment program
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>developmental stuttering disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will comprise three groups of children who stutter. 
Group 1: Children who stutter with disruptive behaviours who receive stuttering therapy only. 
Group 2: Children who stutter without disruptive behaviour who receive stuttering therapy only. 
Group 3: Children who stutter with disruptive behaviours who receive stuttering therapy, in addition the Group Triple P Program.

Stuttering therapy will be overseen by speech pathologists who have 10 years of specialised experience in the assessment and management of stuttering disorders. Stuttering therapy sessions will be delivered face-to-face, in individual sessions. The duration of stuttering therapy will be 12 weeks for all children, involving 1x hourly session per week delivered weekly. Sessions will take place at the Curtin University Treatment Clinic or in private metropolitan community clinics in Western Australia. The parent is encouraged to observe therapy sessions (between clinician and child) where the clinician implements stuttering therapy. The child is required to play and engage with the clinician during therapy using age appropriate fun activities such as: Play Doh, Go Fish, Shopping Game. Stuttering therapy principles will be implemented during these activities, mapping on to the Demands and Capacities Model as well as using Response Contingent Stimulation principles. 

The Triple P Program will be delivered by a registered Triple P Provider over an 8 week period. Parents will attend this training without their children. This will comprise of 3x 2-hour face-to-face group sessions weekly, then 3x individual 20-30 minute telephone calls delivered weekly, followed by a final 2-hour face-to-face session in the final week of the program. The Triple P training will be provided to parents at the Curtin University Stuttering Treatment clinics. It is a standardised and well recognised family behavioural intervention. Parents will learn strategies to encourage positive parenting, improve parent-child relationships and learn how to better manage their child's behaviour. Parents receiving the training will be provided with a work book to complete as part of their training, entitled "Every Parent's Group Workbook". 

To ensure treatment fidelity of fluency therapy, each therapist will complete standard checklists after each session (including session structure and stuttering treatment principles implemented). Sessions will be video recorded and 10% randomly analysed by an independent observer. Rater reliability will be assessed. A similar process will be followed for the Triple P Program. All group sessions will be video-recorded, the Triple P provider will complete a standardised Triple P fidelity checklist at the end of each group session, and 10% of sessions will be rated by an external reviewer. </interventions>
    <comparator>Two active unenhanced control groups (Group 1 and Group 2).

Group 1: Children who stutter (aged 2-6 years) with disruptive behaviours who receive stuttering therapy only. 
Group 2: Children who stutter (aged 2-6 years) without disruptive behaviour who receive stuttering therapy only. 

Both groups do not receive the Triple P component as part of their management, thus making up the active unenhanced control groups. Both groups are not withheld from stuttering therapy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stuttering Severity. This is assessed by calculating percentage of syllables stuttered by a speech pathologist. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post treatment and at 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting Practices - assessed by the Parenting and Family Adjustment Scales (PAFAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post treatment and at 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Disruptive Behaviours - assessed by (1) the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire and (2) Effortful Control Subscale of the Child Behavior Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post treatment and at 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative understanding of the effect of the Triple P Program on stuttering, parenting and child behavioural outcomes. This is  a composite secondary outcome. 

Qualitative interviews will be conducted and thematically analysed using QSR Nvivo 8 qualitative analysis software. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children:
- Hearing within normal limits (assessed by parent report following compulsory Western Australian hearing screen at birth)
- Presence of developmental stuttering disorder as diagnosed by a speech pathologist
- Speech and language within normal limits

Parents:
- No regular contact with another professional service for child behavioural problems 
- No regular contact with another professional service for parenting support

Children will be classified into groups using the ADHD Rating Scale. 
The following cut-off criteria will be applied for grouping, based on Donaher and Richels (2012): children will be classified as presenting with disruptive behaviours if they score a rating of 2 (often) or greater on any 2 items related to inattention (inattentive type), or any 2 items related to hyperactivity/ impulsivity (hyperactive/impulsive type). In addition, the participants overall score on the scale has to be greater than the 80th percentile for their gender (DuPaul et al., 1998; McGoey et al., 2007).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Regular contact with another professional service for child behavioural problems.
- Regular contact with another professional service for parenting support. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/08/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Townsing Drive, Bentley, Perth WA, 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Townsing Drive, Bentley, PERTH WA, 6102

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to explore the relationship between childhood behaviours and stuttering. 

This study will identify how many children who stutter have challenging behaviours, as well as determine if challenging behaviours affect stuttering therapy. In addition, one aspect of the study will implement an integrated stuttering intervention program that addresses child behaviour in addition to stuttering. The effect of addressing child behaviour in children who stutter, as a component of stuttering therapy, on stuttering outcomes, parenting and child behaviour will be examined. 

We anticipate that the project will provide invaluable information for future stuttering therapy, with the possibility of addressing child behaviour as a component of future therapy. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Janet Beilby</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7463</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Beilby@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Janet Beilby</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7463</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Beilby@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Janet Beilby</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7463</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Beilby@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Kerianne Bloch</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>