<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335701">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000568011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of timing of buffet-meal presentation on energy intake following a nutrient preload in humans: relationships with gastrointestinal functions.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of timing of buffet-meal presentation on energy intake following a nutrient preload in lean and obese humans: relationships with gastric emptying, antral area and gastrointestinal hormone release.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Three 500ml nutrient preloads (Ensure; 2240kJ (2.24MJ)), taken at t = 180 (Study Condition EI180), t = 90 (Study Condition EI90), t = 30 (Study Condition EI30), and one 500ml water preload (control condition). The same nutrient preload will be taken in all study conditions, excluding the water control condition.

Appetite sensation questionnaires in the form of a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), blood samples, 2D Ultrasound scan to assess antral area.

A buffet meal will be presented 30, 90 or 180 minutes after the nutrient preload ingestion, and 180 minutes after the water preload ingestion, and the participant has 30 minutes to eat until comfortably full. The buffet meal consists of 300ml orange juice, 600ml water, 375ml iced coffee, 4 slices white bread, 4 slices brown bread, 100g deli leg ham, 100g virginian chicken, 4 slices cheese, 100g tomato, 100g cucumber, 100g lettuce, 2 portions mayonnaise, 2 portions margarine, 1 medium apple, 1 medium banana, 200g chocolate custard, 150g fruit salad, and 200g strawberry yoghurt.

Each volunteer will recieve one nutrient preload on each of 3 study days, and the water preload on the remaining study day. Each study visit will be separated by approximately one week, and will last approximately 2-4 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: A 500ml 0kJ water preload.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antral area, assessed using 2D Ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On each study visit, a 2D Ultrasound scan will be performed to assess antral area at baseline (t = -10). In all conditions, antral area will be assessed every 5 min after preload ingestion, until t = 180 min.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Macronutrient and total energy intake at the buffet meal will be analysed using the FoodWorks software program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Buffet meal will be presented at t = 180 min, and the subject will be allowed to freely consume food until comfortably full for 30 min (until t = 210</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite perceptions using a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) (satiety, hunger, fullness, thirst, desire to eat, prospective consumption).</outcome>
      <timepoint>On all study days, at t = -10 a baseline blood sample and VAS will be obtained.

Study condition EI180 and Control: Blood sample and VAS obtained at 10 min intervals from t = 0-30, at 15 min intervals from t = 30-90, and then at 30 min intervals until presentation of buffet meal at t = 180.
Study condition EI90: Blood sample and VAS obatined at t = 0, at 10 min intervals from t = 90-120, and at then 15 min intervals until presentation of buffet meal at t = 180.
Study condition EI30: Blood sample and VAS obtained at t = 0, then at 10 min intervals from t = 150 until presentation of buffet meal at t = 180.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Non-obese with a Body Mass Index (BMI) of 19-25kg/m2) and obese with a BMI &gt;30kg/m2 and waist circumference &gt; 102cm for males and &gt;97cm for females.

Female subjects will be included on the basis that they are using an appropriate contraceptive method (i.e. oral contraceptive pill, diaphragm, Depo-Provera hormonal contraceptive injection, intrauterine device (IUD), Norplant method).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant gastrointestinal symptoms, disease or surgery. Current use of prescribed or non-prescribed medications (including vitamins and herbal supplements) which may affect energy metabolism, gastrointestinal (GI) function, body weight or appetite (e.g. domperidone and cisapride, anticholinergic drugs (e.g. atropine), metclopramide, erythromycin, hyoscine, orlistat, green tea extracts, Astragalus, St John's Wort etc). Significant illness as assessed by the investigator.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will undergo a screening visit at which they will complete questionnaires to assess their suitability for the study, and also provide informed, written, consent.  At this screening visit, we will collect a fasting blood sample to assess haemoglobin (Hb) and iron levels. Study dates are established. Eligible volunteers are randomised into a treatment for each study visit, using a randomisation table created in an excel spreadsheet. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation table was generated using Microsoft Office Excel.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>5043</postcode>
    <postcode>5061</postcode>
    <postcode>5038</postcode>
    <postcode>5037</postcode>
    <postcode>5045</postcode>
    <postcode>5008</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christine Feinle-Bisset</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd
Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus St
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Tanya Little</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd
Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study has been designed to investigate how energy intake at a buffet meal will be affected when the meal is presented at different times following a nutrient preload, and and how it is related to antral area, gut hormones and appetite sensations.

Volunteers are required to visit the department on 4 occasions approximately 1 week apart. They will be required to ingest either a water or liquid nutrient preload, and 2D Ultrasound scans, blood samples and VAS will be taken at various timepoints depending on the treatment. A buffet meal will be presented 30, 90 or 180 min after the preload, and will be consumed over 30 min until the volunteer is comfortable full.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute
North Tce
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>100606</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tanya Little</name>
      <address>Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Bulding
Frome Rd
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 0724</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.little@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Tanya Little</name>
      <address>Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Bulding
Frome Rd
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 0724</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.little@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Briohny Bartlett</name>
      <address>Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Bulding
Frome Rd
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4130</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>briohny.bartlett@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>