<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83233">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000013268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of de-alcoholised wine on Deoxyribonucleic Acid (DNA) damage.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of de-alcoholised red and white wine on spontaneous and oxidative damage to Deoxyribonucleic Acid (DNA) in healthy women.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of spontaneous and oxidative damage to DNA in healthy women</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to 1 of 3 treatments. 1 acute day (once per week for 3 weeks) of 600ml of red or white de-alcoholised wine given as a drink (to be entirely consumed within 10 minutes of the baseline blood sample being collected) compared with 600ml water as the control (to be completely consumed within 10 minutes of the baseline blood sample being collected).
Each participant will be involved for 3 weeks.  On day one of the first week, each participant will be randomised to one of the study drinks or the control drink. At visit 2 (one week later) the participant will be randomised to either one of the remaining study drinks or control drink.  At the third visit (one week after visit 2), participants will consume either the remaining study drink or control drink.  Participants will refrain from foods and beverages containing polyphenolic compounds for 24 hours prior to each of their 3 weekly visits, and will fast (water allowed) for 10 hours prior to each visit. Week 1: Following the last blood sample being collected on the morning of each visit, the participants will resume their usual diet until 24 hours prior to each of their second and 3rd clinic visits.
There will be two groups of 4 participants on this trial over a six week period.  Each group of 4 participants will complete 3 consecutive weeks on the study.  The 7 days between each visit is the washout period.</interventions>
    <comparator>600ml water to be consumed within 10 minutes of the baseline blood sample collection</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome measures will be oxidative dna damage which will be measured by determining micronucleus frequency using the cytokinesis-block micronucleus assay scored by visual microscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint -10mins - fasting baseline blood sample; Time point 0 - consume 600ml study drink or control within 10 minutes;
Timepoint 1.0hr post drink blood sample; 
Timepoint 2.0hr post drink blood sample.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the secondary outcome measures will be nucleoplasmic bridges, nuclear buds, cell death and nuclear division index, which will be measured using the cytokinesis-block micronucleus assay scored by visual microscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint -10mins - fasting baseline blood sample; Time point 0 - consume 600ml study drink or control within 10 minutes;
Timepoint 1.0hr post drink blood sample; 
Timepoint 2.0hr post drink blood sample.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy females; aged 25 - 50 years; willing to refrain from consuming polyphenolic-rich food/beverages for 24 hours prior to each study day(e.g. red and/or white wine); females who drink red and white wine.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Cigarette smoker currently or within the past six months; receiving medical treatment including anti-folate drugs currently or within the past six months e.g. aminopterin (AMT) and methotrexate (MTX); planning a pregnancy or currently pregnant; females allergic to compounds present in red and white wines.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants are screened for inclusion and exclusion criteria and once deemed eligible are randomly allocated into one of the 3 treatments. Allocation was concealed by central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random allocation using the computer software "Clinstat".</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Vintage Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 170 Greenhill Road
Parkside SA 5063</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Vintage Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 170 Greenhill Road
Parkside SA 5063</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO) Human Nutrition</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
ADELAIDE  SA  5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim: A study investigating the bio-efficiency of de-alcoholised red and white wine as an antioxidant in humans using both red and white wine formulas.  The study will be split into two 3 week blocks.  Each participant will be involved for only 3 consecutive weeks.
Recruitment: 8 healthy females are required.
Study design: Participants will fast for 10 hours overnight (water allowed) prior to each study day.  During the 24 hours prior to each visit, participants will be asked to refrain from consuming foods/drinks that are rich in polyphenolic compounds (a list will be provided to them). In the first week, participants will be randomised to one of 3 treatments.  In the second week, participants will be randomised to one of the remaining 2 treatments and in the third week, participants will cross over to the last treatment.  Drinks will be blinded to minimise any impact on the outcomes of the research.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Human Nutrition Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/08/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Fenech</name>
      <address>CSIRO Human Nutrition
Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
ADELAIDE SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038880</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83038899</fax>
      <email>michael.fenech@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vanessa Courage</name>
      <address>CSIRO Human Nutrition
Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
ADELAIDE SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038988</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83038899</fax>
      <email>vanessa.courage@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vanessa Courage</name>
      <address>CSIRO Human Nutrition
Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
ADELAIDE SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038988</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83038899</fax>
      <email>vanessa.courage@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>