<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369106">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001303538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Specific Physiotherapy Management for Subacromial Impingement</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective randomised double blinded control trial to compare the effect of three evidence based physiotherapy treatments (mobilisation of thoracic spine versus posterior shoulder treatment versus ultrasound) on shoulder and thoracic range of motion, pain and function in adults with subacromial impingement.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1176-8981 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Subacromial Shoulder Impingement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Physiotherapy treatment provided for six consecutive weeks. Twice a week for three weeks followed by once a week for three weeks.
Intervention One is mobilisation of thoracic spine in prone position which consists of transverse mobilisations from the direction of painful side to non-painful side and costovertebral mobilisation on the painful side at thoracic levels 1 to 6.  Time taken = 20 minutes..A home exercise of lying on rolled towel positioned longitudinally along thoracic spine for 5 mins, twice a day - to be continued on a daily basis for the full twelve weeks of the study. 
Intervention two is release of posterior shoulder tightness using massage to the posterior soft tissues and AP mobilisation of painful glenohumeral joint.  Time taken = 20 minutes. A home programme of passive cross adduction stretch in standing, performed twice for the count of 20, two times during the day - to be continued on a daily basis for the full twelve weeks of the study 
The home programme is monitored via exercise diary provided to the subjects.</interventions>
    <comparator>Ultrasound is being used as the control. Previous studies using ultrasound have shown there is no benefit in the treatment of shoulder impingement but ultrasound is considered a standard physiotherapy treatment.
Ultrasound is applied at 1MHz 50% Pulsed 0,5wcm(squared) for 5 mins to the subacromial area. This treatment is administered for six consecutive weeks being twice a weeks for three weeks followed by once a week for three weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in range of thoracic motion. Sagittal plane digital photographs are taken and software used to measure the change in thoracic angles from these photographs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements taken initially and repeated at three weeks, six weeks (physiotherapy intervention ceases here), nine weeks and twelve weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numeric Rating Scale for level of shoulder pain. 0 = no pain and 10 being the worst pain imaginable.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements taken initially and repeated at three weeks, six weeks (physiotherapy intervention ceases here), nine weeks and twelve weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SPADI outcome measure (Shoulder Pain and Disability Index).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements taken initially and repeated at three weeks, six weeks (physiotherapy intervention ceases here), nine weeks and twelve weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Painful shoulder range of motion using standard plastic goniometer by the one principal investigator.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements taken initially and repeated at three weeks, six weeks (physiotherapy intervention ceases here), nine weeks and twelve weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Minimum of three positive orthopaedic special tests. Hawkins- Kennedy and/or Neer must be positive along with two of the following: Painful Arc, Speed, Cross Body Adduction, External Rotation Resistance Test and pain on tendon palpation.
Catching or aching pain without appreciable joint stiffness.
Pain localized to the anterior or antero-lateral-superior shoulder.
Insidious onset of symptoms with a possible history of gradual progression over time but without history of trauma.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previously undergone shoulder surgery or suffered a fracture of the shoulder girdle
Presence of scoliosis or current cervical or thoracic signs or symptoms,
Glenohumeral instability by eliciting a grade 2 or 3 in an anterior, posterior or inferior load and shift test or have had a previous shoulder dislocation.
A diagnosed systemic or neurological disease.
The identification of osteophytes within the subacromial space; calcification of tendons or large rotator cuff tears on imaging
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation performed by administration officer at separate location to principal investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Three sample size calculations were estimated using 1.passive range of internal shoulder rotation (mean difference of 18 degrees and SD 14 degrees); 2. numeric rating scale (mean difference of 5 SD 2); 3. SPADI total score (mean score 30 SD 20). The maximum number of participants needed was calculated as 60 (20 in each group) to produce a power of 0.9 and alpha = 0.05 (level of significance. This sample size allows assumption of normal distribution and the use of independent t-tests and ANOVA for analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>16/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/11/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>9/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4810 - Townsville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Helen Land</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Helen Land
PhD Candidate
James Cook University
Discipline of Physiotherapy
JCU Physiotherapy Clinic
Building 500.  1 James Cook Drive
James Cook University
Douglas  4811  Queensland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>James Cook University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>James Cook University
1 James Cook Drive
Douglas  4811
Queensland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Susan Gordon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Professor Susan Gordon PhD Supervisor School Of Health Sciences, Flinders University 17 Rockville Avenue Daw Park 5041 South Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Shoulder impingement is a common diagnosis referred for physiotherapy treatment. Patients complain of pain when lifting their arm and difficulty with functions such as washing their hair or when reaching for objects. (Michener, McClure et al. 2003) suggest it is the most common disorder of the shoulder, accounting for 44-65% of all complaints of shoulder pain during a physicians office visit.  In addition, approximately one-fifth of all disability payments for musculoskeletal disorders are for shoulder disorders (Michener, Walsworth et al. 2004)
These statistics indicate that a large portion of the general community may be affected by a shoulder disorder and that it causes significant discomfort and limitation to their function.
Physiotherapists use past clinical experience in addition to a thorough examination to identify physical characteristics causing signs of impingement and which are able to be modified (Sorohan and Mc Creesh 2009). A study has been completed (JCU ethics approval number H3945) which took an homogeneous group, aged 40 to 60 years, presenting with positive shoulder impingement signs and symptoms of gradual onset and without trauma, and compared these physical characteristics to a matched asymptomatic group in age and physical activity level. Significant differences between groups were found in upper back (thoracic) posture, range of upper back (thoracic) movement and tightness in the back of the shoulder. No significant differences were found in shoulder muscle strength or shoulder blade positioning. 
This prospective, randomized double blinded,control trial will compare the clinical efficacy of two evidence based physiotherapy treatment approaches (one directed at the thoracic spine and one directed at the posterior shoulder) as compared to ultrasound treatment.
 The results of this project will result in the development of an evidence based program to manage shoulder impingement.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>James Cook University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>James Cook University
1 James Cook Drive
Douglas  4811
Queensland.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H6129</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369106-Approval Form H6129 Land.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369106-SIGNED REPORT.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Helen Land</name>
      <address>JCU Physiotherapy Clinic
Level 1, Building 500, Clinical Practice Building
James Cook University
1 James Cook Drive
Douglas  4811
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61747815840</phone>
      <fax>+61747792739</fax>
      <email>helen.land@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Helen Land</name>
      <address>JCU Physiotherapy Clinic
Level 1, Building 500, Clinical Practice Building
James Cook University
1 James Cook Drive
Douglas  4811
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61747815840</phone>
      <fax>+61747792739</fax>
      <email>helen.land@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Helen Land</name>
      <address>JCU Physiotherapy Clinic
Level 1, Building 500, Clinical Practice Building
James Cook University
1 James Cook Drive
Douglas  4811
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61747815840</phone>
      <fax>+61747792739</fax>
      <email>helen.land@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Helen Land</name>
      <address>JCU Physiotherapy Clinic
Level 1, Building 500, Clinical Practice Building
James Cook University
Townsville
Queensland  4811</address>
      <phone>+61747815840</phone>
      <fax>+61747792739</fax>
      <email>helen.land@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>