<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369931">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000108415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is the efficacy of nutritional vitamin D (cholecalciferol) comparable to active vitamin D (calcitriol) as maintenance therapy in dialysis dependent chronic kidney disease patients?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is the efficacy of nutritional vitamin D (cholecalciferol) comparable to active vitamin D (calcitriol) as maintenance therapy in dialysis dependent chronic kidney disease patients?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-5860</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CHOLCAL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic kidney disease-mineral and bone disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a cohort study conducted over 12 weeks at a Regional Renal Centre at Launceston General Hospital and its satellite Kings Meadows Dialysis Unit.
Dialysis dependent stage 5 chronic kidney disease (CKD) patients who have been stable on oral calcitriol therapy for 3 months will be switched  over to oral cholecalciferol therapy at the beginning of study period. Conversion of calcitriol to cholecalciferol will be based on the ratio of 0.25 mcg calcitriol to 25 mcg cholecalciferol. If participants are already on both pre-existing cholecalciferol and calcitriol, then calcitriol will be ceased followed by increased cholecalciferol dose based on the conversion ratio earlier. Monthly dispensing of cholecalciferol will be performed by Department of Pharmacy at Launceston General Hospital, to ensure compliance. 
Baseline participant characteristics including age, gender, ethnicity, body mass index (BMI), smoking status, primary kidney disease(s), time on dialysis, medical comorbidities, dialysate calcium concentration, phosphate binder prescriptions, pre-existing vitamin D therapy and previous  biochemical results will be collected. Medical records will be assessed if needed for the information. 
The effects of this new therapy will be studied over the course of 12 weeks, to determine the success or failure of that change in therapy (as defined by ability of cholecalciferol to maintain serum albumin-corrected calcium levels within target range of 2.10 mmol/L to 2.60 mmol/L). Blood specimens will be collected at baseline, 4-week, 8-week and 12-week after patients have been switched to cholecalciferol. Serum calcium, phosphate, intact parathyroid hormone, alkaline phosphatase, and vitamin D (25-hydroxyvitamin D3, 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3) will be measured to determine the effects. Cholecalciferol dosage will be reviewed at 4-week interval with the blood tests to determine the need for adjustment by the investigators (Nephrologist and Nephorology Advanced Trainee)</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants that can be successfully changed over to oral cholecalciferol from oral calcitriol therapy. The success will be determined by ability of cholecalciferol to maintain albumin-corrected serum calcium level between 2.10 and 2.60 mmol/L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post change over</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum phosphate level</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks post change over</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum intact parathyroid hormone level</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks post change over</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum alkaline phosphatase level</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks post change over</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 level</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks post change over</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3 level</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks post change over</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Patients with stage 5 chronic kidney disease who are on haemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis, and 
- with pre-existing maintenance calcitriol therapy for at least 3 months at time of recruitment, and 
- have normal serum calcium level at time of recruitment </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Patients younger than 18 years old 
- Pregnant women 
- Patients with hypocalcaemia or hypercalcaemia 
- Patients whose serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 level greater than or equal to 75 nmol/L 
- Patients with hypoparathyroidism or familial hypophosphataemic rickets </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The number of patients required to demonstrate a minimum of 25% of patients being able to be transferred to cholecalciferol (with 80% power; alpha 0.05) is a minimum of 26 patients. Hence, the study aims to recruit at least 30 participants. 
Primary outcome is proportion of participants that can be successfully changed over to cholecalciferol from calcitriol. The success will be determined by ability of cholecalciferol to maintain albumin-corrected serum calcium level between 2.10 and 2.60 mmol/L. The success rate will be estimated using repeated-measures Poisson regression, with adjustment for confounding covariates selected by stepwise regression from the recorded baseline patient characteristics.
Secondary outcome variables for analysis include serum phosphate, intact parathyroid hormone, alkaline phosphatase, and vitamin D (25-hydroxyvitamin D3, 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3). These parameters will not be manipulated as part of the protocol, and differences whilst taking the different medication will be assessed using repeated measures mixed effects linear regression, adjusted for confounding covariates as above.
Baseline participants characteristics including age, gender, ethnicity, body mass index (BMI), smoking status, primary kidney disease(s), time on dialysis, medical comorbidities, dialysate calcium concentration, phosphate binders, pre-existing vitamin D therapy, and previous serum biomarkers will be incorporated into the analysis of the outcome variables.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Launceston General Hospital - Launceston</hospital>
    <postcode>7250 - Launceston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Launceston General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Charles St, Launceston, TAS 7250.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5, W.D. Booth Centre, Launceston General Hospital, Charles St, Launceston, TAS 7250</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Tasmania</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Churchill Avenue, Hobart, TAS 7005</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>When chronic kidney disease patients on dialysis have low calcium due to low vitamin D activity, calcitriol is the standard therapy used. However, it is costly and more likely to cause side effects of high calcium and high phosphate. On the other hand, cholecalciferol is cheaper with possibly less side effects on calcium and phosphate. 
The purpose of this study is to compare cholecalciferol to calcitriol as vitamin D therapy in patients with chronic kidney disease who are on dialysis. We will change study participants who are on calcitriol to cholecalciferol, and examine cholecalciferols effectiveness through its effects on blood results over 12 weeks.
During recruitment, participants' age, gender, ethnicity, weight and height, smoking status, existing vitamin D therapy, kidney disease, time on dialysis, other medical conditions, dialysate calcium concentration, phosphate binders, and previous blood results will be obtained from them personally or through medical record. Baseline blood tests will be performed to analyze detailed components of the calcium and vitamin D metabolism systems. If they meet the inclusion criteria, their calcitriol therapy will be changed over to cholecalciferol. Further 3 sets of blood tests will be done at 4-week, 8-week, and 12-week period to monitor treatment effects and determine need for therapy adjustment. 
We would estimate the proportion of patients on maintenance calcitriol who can be changed successfully to cholecalciferol therapy. We hypothesize that the use of cholecalciferol for maintenance therapy in adult chronic kidney disease patients on dialysis is comparable to the use of calcitriol, as shown by successful change from calcitriol to cholecalciferol therapy in a worthwhile proportion of patients. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services, University of Tasmania Hobart Campus, 301 Sandy Bay Road, Sandy Bay, TAS 7005.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0015192</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chau Wang Ng</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine, Launceston General Hospital, Charles St, Launceston, TAS 7250.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6777 6777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Chau.Ng@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chau Wang Ng</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine, Launceston General Hospital, Charles St, Launceston, TAS 7250.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6777 6777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Chau.Ng@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mathew C Mathew</name>
      <address>Renal Unit, Department of Medicine, Launceston General Hospital, Charles St, Launceston, TAS 7250.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6777 6777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mathew.Mathew@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chau Wang Ng</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine, Launceston General Hospital, Charles St, Launceston, TAS 7250.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6777 6777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Chau.Ng@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>