<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371990">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000216314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase II dose escalation study of cyclophosphamide in haematopoietic stem cell transplantation in severe systemic sclerosis patients unfit for standard dose cyclophosphamide.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II dose escalation study of cyclophosphamide in haematopoietic stem cell transplantation in severe systemic sclerosis patients unfit for standard dose cyclophosphamide.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The ASSURE study </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>The ASSURE study (Autologous Stem transplant in Scleroderma Using Reduced Exposure to cyclophosphamide)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autoimmune disorder </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>systemic  sclerosis </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible Patients with severe systemic sclerosis not deemed suitable for standard dose cyclophosphamide  will be enrolled in the study . Dose finding study whereby 5 patients will be enrolled in cohort 1.  Next cohort will be enrolled after 12 months  re safety and efficacy. cohort 3 will start 12 moths after  cohort 2 reviewed re safety and efficacy  reviewed .

Cohort 1: Within 2-8 weeks of stem cell collection and cryopreservation the patients are to be admitted to St Vincents Hospital for the HSCT procedure. Patients will be placed in a single room and chemo-immunotherapy will be administered via a central venous line placed on hospital admission. Cyclophosphamide 12.5mg/kg is administered  intravenously  daily  for 2 doses on Day -3, and  Day-2 with hyperhydration (100-125 ml/hr isotonic fluid +/-  intravenous mesna  per 24 hours). Anti-thymocyte Globulin (ATG - Horse, ATGAM) 10mg/kg will be administered  intravenously daily for 4 doses  from  Day -6 to day -3. A test dose of ATG 0.001mg  given intradermal will be administered  several hours before  first dose on Day -6. Methylprednisolone 1mg/kg will be given  intravenously for serum sickness prophylaxis on the days of ATG. A minimum of 2 x 106/kg CD34+ cells without manipulation will be infused on Day 0. All patients will receive standard intravenous antibiotics upon neutropenic fever after blood cultures and chest X ray. In order to prevent hypertensive crisis, all Systemic Sclerosis patients will receive captopril to a maximally tolerated dose to maintain systolic blood pressure at 100 systolic. Following engraftment, all patients will receive Bactrim 1600mg/800mg, Fluconazole and Valaciclovir for prophylaxis of pneumocystitis jejuni, candida albicans and Herpes Zoster respectively for 6 months.

Cohort 2: Within 2-8 weeks of stem cell collection and cryopreservation the patients are to be admitted to St Vincents Hospital for the HSCT procedure. Patients will be placed in a single room and chemo-immunotherapy will be administered via a central venous line placed on hospital admission. Cyclophosphamide 25mg/kg is administered  intravenously  daily for 2 doses  on Day -3 and  Day -2 with hyperhydration (100-125 ml/hr isotonic fluid +/- intravenous mesna per 24 hours). Anti-thymocyte Globulin (ATG - Horse, ATGAM) 10mg/kg will be administered  intravenously once daily  for 4 doses from Day -6  to Day -3.  A test dose of ATG 0.001mg  will be given intradermal on Day -6 several hours before the first  dose.. Methylprednisolone 1mg/kg will be given  intravenously for serum sickness prophylaxis on the  same days as ATG. A minimum of 2 x 106/kg CD34+ cells without manipulation will be infused on Day 0. All patients will receive standard intravenous antibiotics upon neutropenic fever after blood cultures and chest X ray. In order to prevent hypertensive crisis, all Systemic Sclerosis patients will receive captopril to a maximally tolerated dose to maintain systolic blood pressure at 100 systolic. Following engraftment, all patients will receive Bactrim 1600mg/800mg, Fluconazole and Valaciclovir for prophylaxis of pneumocystitis jejuni, candida albicans and Herpes Zoster respectively for 6 months.

Cohort 3: Within 2-8 weeks of stem cell collection and cryopreservation the patients are to be admitted to St Vincents Hospital for the HSCT procedure. Patients will be placed in a single room and chemo-immunotherapy will be administered via a central venous line placed on Hospital admission. Cyclophosphamide 35mg/kg is administered intravenously daily for 2 doses on Day -3and  Day-2 with hyperhydration (100-125 ml/hr isotonic fluid +/- intravenous mesna  per 24 hours). Anti-thymocyte Globulin (ATG - Horse, ATGAM) 10mg/kg will be administered  intravenously  daily for 4 doses from  Day -6 to Day-3. A test dose  of ATG 0.001mg  will be given intradermal  several hours pro to  first dose.  Methylprednisolone 1mg/kg will be given intravenously for serum sickness prophylaxis on the days of ATG. A minimum of 2 x 106/kg CD34+ cells without manipulation will be infused on Day 0. All patients will receive standard intravenous antibiotics upon neutropenic fever after blood cultures and chest X ray. In order to prevent hypertensive crisis, all Systemic Sclerosis patients will receive captopril to a maximally tolerated dose to maintain systolic blood pressure at 100 systolic. Following engraftment, all patients will receive Bactrim 1600mg/800mg, Fluconazole and Valaciclovir for prophylaxis of pneumocystitis jejuni, candida albicans and Herpes Zoster respectively for 6 months.

Patient's regardless of the cohort have a blood test to  evaluate any below normal blood results and physical assessment /reviewed by their treating physician weekly for 1 month, then fortnightly then monthly. Assessment using Rodnan skin score. Patient will also complete questionnaires ( VAS, HAQ and SF-36) at the following timepoints; pre HSCT, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months then yearly </interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> transplant-related mortality </outcome>
      <timepoint>within first 100 days  post-HSCT</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>length of hospital stay by review of hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>number of days  from admission to   hospital discharge </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>number of days receiving blood products assessed by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>number of days  From HSCT to 100 days post-HSCT</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> IV antibiotic use assessed through review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>number of days  From HSCT to 100 days post-HSCT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of adequacy of stem cell collection using  low dose of cyclophosphamide by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint> number of stem cell collected at time of plasmapheresis by review of medical records. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy  of HSCT in lower dose Cyclophopshamide by reviewing physical assessment and  assessing skin dexterity using Modified Rodman Skin Score recorded in medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months post HSCT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of engraftment assessed through blood tests  taken daily until discharge and bone marrow biopsy (if applicable) and by review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>number of days  From HSCT to 100 days post-HSCT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> transfusion requirements assessed through review of medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>number of days  From HSCT to 100 days post-HSCT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy  of HSCT in lower dose Cyclophopshamide by  patient competing questionnaires to  measure  pain using VAS scale  and quality of life  using HAQ and SF-36 questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months post HSCT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to provide informed written consent
Severe SSc either de novo or unresponsive to previous therapies requiring HSCT (in the opinion of the referring physician) 
Age 16-65
ECOG 0,1,2,3.
Negative serology for HIV.
If hepatitis B positive willing to take entacavir for 1 year
If hepatitis C positive  must be cleared by anti-viral therapy prior to HSCT
Negative pregnancy test.
Absence of severe chronic infection.
Sperm collection or ova cryopreservation is to be offered prior to HSCT in those of child-bearing age.

Ineligible for HDCy using 200mg/kg due to pre-existing cardio-respiratory disease due to
Age greater than  60yrs
Cardiac LV Ejection Fraction less than 50%
Total Lung Capacity less than  50%
Resting mean pulmonary artery pressure (mPAP) greater than   25mmHg
mPAP greater than   30mm/hg after 500mls bolus
DLCO/VA less than  50%.
Abnormal Cardiac MRI 
Cardiac event (eg: arrhythmia, episode of chest pain or dysopnoea) whilst harvesting haemopoietic stem cells using the conventional protocol of HDCy 2g/m2 (these patient would be withdrawn from the standard protocol and consented to the low dose cohorts).
Known stable coronary artery disease ( equal to 30% stenosis of a major coronary artery or previous therapy for coronary disease).

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Karnofsky 40% or less
Cardiac Ejection fraction less than 40%
mPAP greater than  50mmHg
DLCO/VA less than 30%
Unstable coronary artery disease

Prior history of malignancy or other current medical condition which in the opinion of the investigators would restrict the ability of the patient to tolerate the procedure.

Unable to provide informed consent and/or the diagnosis of mental and cognitive deficits which can interfere with the capability of providing the informed consent.

Major bone marrow failure or condition which results in significant neutropenia (less than 1000/ul) or thrombocytopenia (less than 100,000/ul).

Severe renal (serum creatinine greater  than 200hmol/l) or liver disease (Bilirubin greater  than 50umol/l or known cirrhosis)

Uncontrolled infection.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>3 cohorts, enrol one cohort at a time </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Assuming a 10% adverse event (i.e death due to complications of HSCT) rate is unacceptable, an overall alpha of 0.05 and at least 80% power, a total sample of 15 with 5 participants in each of three cohorts is required. 

Stopping rules for the trial are: 1 event in the first cohort, 2 events in the second (of the total 10 participants up to that point) and 3 events in the 15 total participants in the third stage.

This calculation is based on Fleming's procedure.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>7/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>10/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney
390 Victoria st
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Health </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NSW Ministry of Health
73 Miller Street
North Sydney NSW 2060
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with severe systemic sclerosis   with cardiac complications requiring a stem cell transplant  after their disorder progressing after  standard treatment not deemed suitable for standard dose cyclophosphamide can be enrolled into an available cohort group to receive one of 3 different  LOW  doses of cyclophosphamide 

This study aims to reduce Treatment related side effects by reducing the intensity of conditioning, in particular cyclophosphamide dosage, in order to offer the potential benefits of stem cell  transplant to patients normally excluded from HSCT whilst potentially maintaining efficacy.

It is hypothesised that a lower dose cyclophosphamide stem cell transplant regimen of 12.5-35mg/kg/day in 3 cohorts will be tolerated with less toxicity than an historical cohort of 50mg/kg/day in patients with severe systemic sclerosis</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney
Research Translational centre
97 105 Boundary st
Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SVH 16 221</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9355 5602</fax>
      <email>pplenge@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>PAtricia Plenge </name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>pplenge@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Moore</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9355 5602</fax>
      <email>pplenge@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>