<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1210">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000147583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Individualised compared with conventional dosing of enoxaparin</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, randomised study to investigate if a patient-individualised dose regimen of enoxaparin reduces the incidence of bleeding and bruising as compared to conventional dosing in patients with ACS, AF, DVT and PE.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>i-ENOX</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute coronary syndromes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Deep vein thrombosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary embolism</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be identified and consented by an investigator before or immediately after the first dose of enoxaparin. Patients will be randomised (using a randomisation table).                                                                             The individualised arm (active) will recieve enoxaparin according to a new dosing strategy.                                                                                                                                                    The new dose strategy has been developed from two previous studies and uses lean body weight as the weight descriptor for dosing in obese (&gt;100kg) patients (as opposed to the normal total body weight dosing). Patients with renal impairment will be dose reduced according to their renal function. All doses will be subcutaneous.                                                                         The study started in May 2004 and will run for approximately 2 years, however an interim analysis was initiated in December 2005 and recruitment has not restarted (pending results).                                                                The study is suitably powered to 120 patients.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the control arm will recieve enoxaparin as per usual clinical practice and at the advice of the treating physician (subcutaneously).</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The total number of patients with a bleeding event. Each patient will be assessed by a nurse blinded to the treatment arm. This nurse will also review patient medical notes for any documentation of a bleeding event (for example overnight). Assessment will be daily until the last day of therapy (last dose of enoxaparin). The treating team will cease enoxaparin at a time suitable to them (usual practice will not be inhibited). The primary investigator will analyse all data.</outcome>
      <timepoint> Assessment will be daily until the last day of therapy (last dose of enoxaparin). The treating team will cease enoxaparin at a time suitable to them (usual practice will not be inhibited).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The total number of patients with a bleeding event (primary endpoint) or a major bruising event. A major bruisng event will be described as any bruise with a surface area greater thna 20cm2</outcome>
      <timepoint>A blinded nurse will review each patient daily (total body assessment) and measure the size and location of every bruise.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any patient (male or female) initiated or about to be initiated on treatment doses of enoxaparin.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, anticoagulation in the past 7 days, abnormal liver function test (more than twice the usual range).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An investigator, blinded to randomisation, will identify and consent the patients. Allocation to treatment arm involves contacting the holder of the randomisation table who is at a central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table from a statistic book</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The patient and the assessing nurse will be blinded to the treatment arm. The investigator and treating team will be aware of the randomisation after consent by the patient</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>QHDAC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland hospitals drug advisory committee</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Society of Hospital Pharmacists of Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to see if a new dosing regimen of enoxaparin (an anticoagulant used in the treatment of heart attacks, deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism) if safer than the current method of dosing (designed by the drug company). Patients will agree on being part of the study and then treated using one of the two methods (they will be unaware which group they will be in). The number of bleeding events and large bruises will be recorded for every patient.  The two methods of dosing can then be compared at the end of the study to see which one has caused the least bleeding/bruising events).  It is hope that the new dosing method will result in less events.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's hospital Human Ethics Research committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2003/083</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Barras</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Brisbane QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368355</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36361532</fax>
      <email>michael_barras@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Barras</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Brisbane QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368355</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36361532</fax>
      <email>michael_barras@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>