<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82939">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000348358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of continuous positive airway pressure treatment on markers of systemic inflammation, pulmonary function and respiratory-related quality of life, in patients with combined chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and obstructive sleep apnea, a parallel group randomized trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of continuous positive airway pressure treatment compared with usual therapy on markers of systemic inflammation, pulmonary function and respiratory-related quality of life in patients with combined chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and obstructive sleep apnea (OSA), a parallel group randomized trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive sleep apnoea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overlap syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Systemic inflammation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
Obstructive sleep apnoea
Overlap syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomised, parallel-group, controlled trial of the addition of 6 months continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy, in addition to usual medical care for COPD. 
Primary hypothesis: 
Treatment of moderate to severe OSA with CPAP in patients with Global strategy for the diagnosis, management, and prevention of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (GOLD) Stage III or IV COPD leads to reduced systemic inflammation. 

Secondary hypotheses: 	
This reduction in inflammation is associated with an improvement in respiratory outcomes (Quality of life, symptoms) in COPD. CPAP therapy is well-tolerated in COPD patients with significant OSA. CPAP therapy is used each night during sleep. It is a device which produces pressurised air, which is delivered through a nasal or face mask. It should be worn each night during sleep for the 6 month duration of the study. The pressure will vary between individuals. This pressure shall be determined by an overnight titration sleep study at the baseline study visit.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator treatment group will have usual medical care for COPD according to internationally recognised Global strategy for the diagnosis, management, and prevention of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (GOLD) guidelines, including inhalers and pulmonary rehabilitation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>High sensitivity C-reactive Protein (CRP) measured by blood sampling</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, 6, 12, 24 from baseline visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life variables from questionnaires Modified Medical Research Council (MMRC)
Transitional dyspnoea questionnaire/Baseline dyspnoea questionnaire (TDI/BDI)
36-item short-form health survey (SF36)
Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)
Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)
St George Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 6, 12, 24 from baseline visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function outcomes
Testing will consist of: 
- spirometry (prior to and after 400 mcg salbutamol), 
- lung volumes (by body plethysmography), 
- diffusing capacity for carbon monoxide,
- respiratory system resistance and reactance by forced oscillation technique,
- hypertonic saline challenge,
- sputum induction 
- exhaled nitric oxide assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 6, 12, 24 from baseline visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of exacerbations of COPD and medication use</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 6, 12, 24 from baseline visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other serum (blood sample analysis)inflammatory markers (eg. Adipokines, IL-6, IL-8 and TNF-alpha, insulin resistance (homeostatic model assessment))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0,  6, 12, 24 from baseline visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age &gt;= 18 years
2. GOLD Stage III or IV (severe COPD): post-bronchodilator forced expiratory volume in 1 second/forced vital (FEV1/FVC) &lt; 0.70, FEV1 &lt;50% predicted.
3. An established clinical history of COPD
4. Ex-smokers with a smoking history of at least 10 pack-years.  Ex-smokers are defined as those who have stopped smoking for at least 6 months prior to Visit 1.
5. Moderate to severe Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (Apnoea Hypopnea Index &gt;= 15)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A subject will not be eligible for inclusion in this study if any of
the following criteria apply:
-Subjects who have a moderate exacerbation (that required systemic corticosteroid therapy or antibiotics) of COPD in the previous month or a severe exacerbation (that required hospitalization) in the 3 months prior to baseline visit.
-Current respiratory disorders other than COPD and asthma (e.g., lung cancer, sarcoidosis, tuberculosis, lung fibrosis, bronchiectasis)
-Had lung-volume reduction surgery and/or a lung transplant
-Requirement for nocturnal non-invasive ventilation or long term oxygen therapy (defined as oxygen therapy prescribed for 12 hours or more per day) at start of study
-Receiving long-term oral corticosteroid therapy (defined as continuous use for greater than 6 weeks. Courses of oral corticosteroids separated by a period of less than 7 days will be considered as continuous use).
- Severe OSA (minimum oxygen saturation &lt; 65% or Respiratory Disturbance Index (RDI) &gt; 80) requiring immediate treatment due to severity or increased associated risk (eg Transport worker
-Current treatment with CPAP (defined as CPAP usage within 3 months of baseline visit).
-Unwilling to use CPAP therapy.
-Serious, uncontrolled non-respiratory disease (including serious psychological disorders) likely to interfere with the study and/or likely to cause death within the 6-month study duration.
-Have, in the opinion of the investigator, evidence of alcohol, drug or solvent abuse. 
-Participation in any other interventional research study in the last 4 weeks before baseline visit.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be achieved by the use of opaque, sealed envelopes.   The randomisation list and preparation of the sealed envelopes will be by an individual not involved with the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation list will be generated by computer program using random permuted blocks. There will be stratification by study centre (Sydney or Newcastle).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/08/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>6</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NHMRC Centre for Clinical Research Excellence in respiratory and sleep</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research 
PO Box M77, Missenden Road, 2050 NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC Centre for Clinical Research Excellence in respiratory and sleep</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research PO Box M77, Missenden Road, 2050 NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Respiratory Medicine</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road 
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Sleep and Respiratory Medicine</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this study, we aim to improve the evidence-based management of moderate to severe COPD patients with concurrent obstructive sleep apnea.
Our primary hypothesis: Treatment of moderate to severe OSA with CPAP in patients with GOLD Stage III COPD leads to reduced systemic inflammation.
Our secondary hypotheses: 	
1.	This reduction in inflammation is associated with an improvement in respiratory outcomes (Quality of life, symptoms) in COPD.
2.	CPAP therapy is well-tolerated in COPD patients with significant OSA.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South-West Sydney Area Health Service Ethics Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Level 8, Building 14
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
CAMPERDOWN  NSW  2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/06/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Ref. 08/RPAH/190</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Keith Wong</name>
      <address>Dept of Respiratory Medicine
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0445</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>keithw@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sarah Newton-John</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Operations Group
Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
PO Box 77, Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0436</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9114 0011</fax>
      <email>sarahnj@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Keith Wong</name>
      <address>Dept of Respiratory Medicine
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0445</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9515 8196</fax>
      <email>keithw@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Keith Wong</name>
      <address>Dept of Respiratory Medicine Royal Prince Alfred Hospital Missenden Road Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0445</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>keithw@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>