<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336102">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000865011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Systematic Termination of Pharmaceutical Agents Trial (STOPAT): a pilot randomised trial of stopping drug therapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Systematic Termination of Pharmaceutical Agents Trial: A pilot (feasibility) randomised controlled trial of deprescribing</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>STOPAT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Polypharmacy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Gradual withdrawal of one target medication selected from a defined list of Target Drugs (antihypertensive therapy, anti-anginal therapy, diuretics, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and COX-2 inhibitors). Dose reductions are made at two weekly intervals by general practitioner if participant remains clinically stable, until target drug has been ceased for two weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care continues in the control group (ie the protocol does not specify any change to management of these patients.  Medication therapy can be amended by treating general practitioner as clinically indicated).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of intervention participants in which successful medication withdrawal could be achieved (defined by patient self report)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At conclusion of study.  Each participant is assessed at two weekly intervals until i) target medication has been ceased for two weeks; or ii) further dose reductions are not possible (because participant is not clinically stable).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life: SF-36 and EQ5D visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant is assessed at baseline and at two weekly intervals until i) target medication has been ceased for two weeks; or ii) further dose reductions are not possible (because participant is not clinically stable).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication adherence: Morisky medication adherence scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant is assessed at baseline and at two weekly intervals until i) target medication has been ceased for two weeks; or ii) further dose reductions are not possible (because participant is not clinically stable).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>sleep quality:  Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index [PSQI]</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant is assessed at baseline and at two weekly intervals until i) target medication has been ceased for two weeks; or ii) further dose reductions are not possible (because participant is not clinically stable).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cognitive function: mini-mental state examination [MMSE]</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant is assessed at baseline and at two weekly intervals until i) target medication has been ceased for two weeks; or ii) further dose reductions are not possible (because participant is not clinically stable).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i)	participant taking at least one drug included in the Target Drug List (antihypertensive therapy, anti-anginal therapy, diuretics, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and COX-2 inhibitors);
ii)	 participant has stable chronic disease with respect to the medication targeted for withdrawal
iii)	patient reports at least one negative symptom ascribable to the drug therapy (effects specific to drug class, or possible adverse effects such as falls, confusion, malaise and nausea), or the patient is taking more than 5 drugs concurrently
iv)	 treating physicians concur with randomisation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i)	patient is taking warfarin</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants were openly assigned to intervention or control groups using a randomisation table</concealment>
    <sequence>Prospectively created using a computerised random number generator.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Perth Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington St, 
Perth WA 6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Perth Hospital Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box X2213
Perth WA 6847</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Western Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Stirling Hwy
Crawley WA 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Therapy with several drugs simultaneously entails several hazards related to drug interactions and side effects. Analysis of individual patients often reveals that some drugs are either unnecesary, or at least thought to be so, either because the indication for them no longer exists or because they were injudiciously prescribed in the first place. In support of this point of view, up to 25% of all acute medical admissions to hospital are due to a clinical problem related to drug treatment. It has been shown that withdrawal of some drugs can alleviate a tendency to fall in elderly patients, and there is evidence that antihypertensive medication may be "downtitrated" (i.e. the dose may be reduced) without loss of antihypertensive effect. We wish to undertake a formal trial of drug withdrawal as a therapeutic maneouvre. As a preliminary we wish to establish that such a trial is feasible and safe and therefore propose a pilot study in a limited number of patients. We have also adopted a restricted list of drugs for the purposes of the pilot study in order to enhance the safety aspects of the trial. Participants will be randomised to persist with current therapy or to have the target therapy withdrawn. They will be followed up frequently. The end point for the ultimate study will be efficacy and quality of life measures but in this study we are interested in safety and practicability only, though efficacy and QOL will be assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Beer C, Loh P, Peng YG, Potter K, Millar A. A pilot randomised controlled trial of deprescribing. Therapeutic Advances in Drug Safety 2011; 2(2):37-43.

Beer C, Potter K, Loh P-K, Peng YG, Millar A. A pilot randomized controlled trial of deprescribing: STOPAT (Systematic Termination of Pharmaceutical Agents Trial). Basic Clin Pharmacol Toxicol 2011;109 (Suppl 1): 156</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box X2213
PERTH WA 6847</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/09/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Beer</name>
      <address>GPO Box X2213
PERTH WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61892242750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.beer@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Beer</name>
      <address>GPO Box X2213
PERTH WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61892242750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.beer@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Beer</name>
      <address>GPO Box X2213
PERTH WA 6847</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>