<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367247">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001192673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>"The Change Program" - a pilot feasibility study of a weight management program in Australian general practice </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot feasibility study of a General Practitioner delivered weight management program for overweight and obese adults in primary care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A general practitioner delivered weight management program.The Change Program consists of a GP Handbook, Patient Workbook and a template that is to be integrated into the general practice software.  The Program content is based on current Australian guidelines for the management of overweight and obesity in primary care. The program is divided into three sections: Nutrition, Physical Activity and Behavioural Interventions.  The Program is flexible in its delivery to suit both the patient and GP, however the suggested appointments are: fortnightly for the first three months, then monthly if the patient is happy with their progress.  The full program runs over the course of two years.  This pilot study will follow each patient for a minimum of 6 months.

The Program provides both GP information and patient factsheets and worksheets in the three domains (nutrition, physical activity and behavioural supports).  The information in the factsheets is based on current Australian guidelines for nutrition and physical activity.  The behavioural supports are based on cognitive behavioural techniques including goal setting, self monitoring and stimulus control.

The worksheets do not all need to be done in session, but can be completed by the patient at home and aid discussion with their GP.  The Program also encourages the ongoing recording of the following data: BMI, waist circumference, blood pressure, relevant biochemical profile as well as a patient well-being score.

At the completion of the Program the patient can continue to be monitored by their GP as part of the usual GP/patient relationship and ongoing care.

Adherence will be monitored via the GP - we will collect information on appointment schedules, timing and interactions with other health professionals as appropriate.
</interventions>
    <comparator>As this is a pilot feasibility study there will not be a comparator, this is a trial testing the operationalisation of the program prior to undertaking a cluster randomised controlled trial.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of "The Change Program" when implemented in general practice 
This will be assessed using both quantatative and qualitative measures.  Patient and GP interviews; Online web based survey tool at initiation, half way and endpoint. Quantatative measures will include appointment attendance, time in consultation, time to recruitment, withdrawal rate.  Survey used is designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months
This will be assessed using both quantatative and qualitative measures.  Patient and GP interviews; Online web based survey tool at initiation, half way and endpoint. Quantatative measures will include appointment attendance, time in consultation, time to recruitment, withdrawal rate.  Survey used is designed specifically for this study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of "The Change Program" to general practitioners and patients </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months and 6 months
Patient and GP interviews; Online web based survey tool at initiation, half way and endpoint of pilot.  Survey used is designed specifically for this pilot.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>BMI over 25
English speaking and literate
Aged over 18 years
Has visited the GP at least 3 times in the last 2 years
Score of 6 or more on the AUSDRISK tool (Australian Type 2 Diabetes Risk Assessment Tool - validated tool for future risk of developing diabetes)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>BMI over 40
Uncontrolled medical or mental health condition
History of eating disorder
Pregnancy 
Breastfeeding
Age over 65 years
Taking weight loss medications
Past or scheduled bariatric surgery
Current history of diabetes, congestive heart failure, chronic renal failure, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
Significant immobility</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>As this is a pilot feasibility study to assess practicality and operationalisation of the program there will only be an intervention arm.
Patients will be assessed as suitability by their general practitioners and invited to participate. There will also be advertising material within the general practice to encourage patients to self-nominate.</concealment>
    <sequence>NA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>23</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian National University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Academic Unit of General Practice
ANU Medical School
PO Box 11
Woden ACT 2606</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian National University
Australian Primary Health Care Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Australian National University
Building 63
Corner Mills and Eggleston Roads
Acton, ACT, 0200</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Our research team has developed a GP-delivered weight management program for adults in primary care based on the current Australian guidelines.  "The Change Program" has already had qualitative review from both GPs and consumer representatives.  It will provide GPs with practical support in managing overweight and obese adults, making the current guidelines accessible and implementable in a clinical setting. 
The overarching aim of this research program is to develop an effective GP-delivered weight management program for adults that can be delivered in Australian general practice.  This is a pilot implementation study to determine the feasibility for a larger scale RCT of a weight management program for overweight and obese adults in general practice.  It will not have an effectiveness component at this stage.  The elements of feasibility that we aim to explore include: recruitment feasibility, dropout rates, refinement of the protocol and collection of cost data, determining time processes.
The outcome of this pilot will aim to feed into a large scale, longer term, RCT to determine the effectiveness of this GP-delivered intervention.
Currently there are no GP-delivered weight management interventions in Australia and this will be a practical tool that GPs can use in their practice on a daily basis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian National University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lower Ground Floor 
Chancelry 10B
East Road
The Australian National University
Acton ACT 0200</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Ann Sturgiss</name>
      <address>Academic Unit of General Practice
Australian National University Medical School
PO Box 11
Woden
ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61262444941</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.sturgiss@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Sturgiss</name>
      <address>Academic Unit of General Practice
Australian National University Medical School
PO Box 11
Woden
ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61262444953</phone>
      <fax>+61262444105</fax>
      <email>change.program@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Ann Sturgiss</name>
      <address>Academic Unit of General Practice
Australian National University Medical School
PO Box 11
Woden
ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61262442222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.sturgiss@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>