<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83298">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000256279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomized trial of homocysteine lowering treatment of depression in later life (B-VITAge)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized trial of citalopram plus vitamins B12, B6 and folate versus citalopram plus placebo for the treatment of depressive episodes amongst adults aged 50 years or over</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>B-VITage</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>B-VITAge50</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depressive disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Daily citalopram (20-40 mg) + 0.5 mg B12, 25 mg B6 and 2 mg folic acid (as a single tablet), both taken orally. Citalopram will be introduced at a dosage of 10mg per day and increased to 20mg per day after 2 weeks. After 4 weeks of treatment the dosage of citalopram will be increased to 30mg for those who still meet the Diagnostic &amp; Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for a depressive episode, and again to 40mg at week 8, if a major depressive episode is still present and no significant adverse events are reported. Treatment with citalopram and vitamins will continue for 12 weeks, after which the anti-depressive management of the patient will be maintained by the general practitioner (who will be free to increase/decrease the dosage of antidepressant or to change the medication). Blinded treatment with vitamins will continue for a further 40 weeks (52 weeks total).</interventions>
    <comparator>Daily citalopram (20-40 mg) + placebo. , taken orally. The dosage of citalopram will be determined as described (Description of intervention). The placebo tablets have the same shape, size, color, texture and taste as the active vitamin tablets. Treatment with citalopram and placebo tablets will continue for 12 weeks, after which the anti-depressive management of the patient will be transferred back to the general practitioner. Blinded treatment with placebo tablets will continue for a further 40 weeks (52 weeks total).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>50% reduction in the scores of the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 26 and 52 weeks after introduction of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Remission of symptoms (no longer meeting criteria for depressive episode)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 26 and 50 weeks after introduction of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of antidepressant medication (monitored by questionnaire and review of notes 26 and 52 weeks after the introduction of the intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 and 52 weeks after the introduction of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with treatment monitored by a medication diary (including antidepressant medication and vitamin or placebo tablets), pill counting by the Royal Perth Hospital Pharmacy, and monitoring of the serum concentrations of vitamin B12 and folate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 26 and 52 weeks after the introduction of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events monitored with a checklist of adverse experiences rated as 'not at all', 'a little', 'quite a bit', ''extremely': 
1.	Tremor of the hands
2.	Muscle stiffness
3.	Involuntary muscle contractions
4.	Muscle Cramps
5.	Pins and needles in the body
6.	Difficulty concentrating
7.	Agitation, feeling restless
8.	Feeling unhappy or depressed
9.	Irritability
10.	Feeling dizzy or faint
11.	Headache
12.	Other pain
13.	Arthritis or pain in the joints
14.	Nausea
15.	Diarrhoea
16.	Constipation
17.	Vomiting
18.	Anorexia (loss of appetite)
19.	Weight loss
20.	Weight gain
21.	Skin rash
22.	Nightmares
23.	Excessive somnolence
24.	Poor sleep
25.	Palpitations
26.	Dry mouth
27.	Other (any other events not listed above reported by participants in response to the question: 'Have you been bothered by any other physical or emotional symptom during the past 4 weeks?)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12, 26 and 52 weeks from baseline (after introduction of intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cognitive scores (Mini-Metal State Examination and cognitive subscale of the Consortium to Establish a Registry for Alzheimer's Disease - CERAD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 26 and 52 weeks from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- age 50 years or over, of either sex - meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (4th edition) criteria for the diagnosis of major depressive episode within the context of a depressive disorder - Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) score of 20 or more - fluent in written and spoken English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- evidence of concurrent alcohol or substance abuse or dependency (Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test  AUDIT = 7),
- clinical evidence of Parkinsons disease (including treatment),
- prior clinical history of strokes,
- evidence of clinically significant cognitive impairment (i.e., Mini-Mental State Examination  MMSE score &lt; 24),
- evidence of medical morbidity (such as cancer) that may compromise 12-month survival or availability for study assessments,
- currently receiving antidepressant treatment (antidepressant medication or electroconvulsive therapy), 
- use of B-vitamins daily for more than 3 months, or receive regular B12 injections
- prior allergic reaction to citalopram or escitalopram,
- use of a monoamine oxidase inhibitor during the preceding 2 weeks,
- no active general practitioner,
- suicide plans,
- no written informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>- Eligible participants will be recruited from all available sources (local general practitioners and metropolitan mental health services)
- vitamin and placebo capsules have the same shape, size, color, smell, weight and texture. Participants and research staff will be blind to group allocation until the collection of the final endpoint for all participants. 
- Randomization and distribution of the study medication will be done centrally by an independent off-site department of the Royal Perth Hospital (Pharmacy)</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomization</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/03/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>155</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>155</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/09/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1241
Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Perth Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>48 Murray St
Perth, WA 6000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Older people with depression have higher plasma concentration of a chemical called homocysteine than non-depressed older adults. The use of some vitamins of the B group are effective in reducing the plasma concentration of homocysteine. We designed this trial to determine if the use of adjunctive treatment with B-vitamins improves the efficacy of antidepressant treatment for people aged 60 years or over.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Ford, A.H., Flicker, L., McCaul, K., Van Bockxmeer, F., Hegarty, S., Hirani, V., Fenner, S. &amp; Almeida, O.P. (2010). The B-VITAGE trial: A randomized trial of homocysteine lowering treatment of depression in later life. Trials;11:8.

Almeida, O.P., Ford, A.H., Hirani, V., Singh, V., vanBockxmeer, F.M., McCaul, K. &amp; Flicker, L. (2014). B vitamins to enhance treatment response to antidepressants in middle-aged and older adults: results from the B-VITAGE randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. British Journal of Psychiatry, 205, 450-457.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box X2213
Perth, WA 6001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC 2008/197</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Osvaldo Almeida</name>
      <address>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92242855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osvaldo.almeida@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Osvaldo Almeida</name>
      <address>Western Australia Centre for Health &amp; Ageing (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92242855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osvaldo.almeida@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Osvaldo Almeida</name>
      <address>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92242855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osvaldo.almeida@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Osvaldo P. Almeida</name>
      <address>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing (M573)
University of Western Australia
35 Stirlingh Highway
Crawley, WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 2855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osvaldo.almeida@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>