<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="175">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000141640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CeMyLungs</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 3 year randomised, open label, multi-centre Investigator driven study comparing de Novo enteric coated Mycophenolate Sodium with delayed onset Everolimus, both arms in combination with Cyclosporin (using C2 monitoring) and Corticosteroids for the prevention of Bronchiolitis Obliterans Syndrome in Heart-Lung, Bilateral Lung and Single Lung Transplant recipients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Lung, Bilateral Lung and Single Lung Transplant recipients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following bronchoscopic confirmation of bronchial anastomotic healing, the patients will be randomised to either continue Mycophenolate  Sodium 1080mg BD, in combination with Cyclosporin and corticosteroids or switched to receive Everolimus (initial dose 1.5mg Bd), then dose adjusted on trough levels in combination with Cyclosporin and Corticosteroids. This treatment will continue for 3 years post transplantation.</interventions>
    <comparator>All patients are given Mycophenolate Sodium at time of transplant. At randomisation, they either continue with Mycophenolate Sodium or are switched onto Everolimus.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the incidence of patients with BOS, defined as a sustained fall (for &gt; 1 month) in maximum FEV1 of 20% or more (compared to baseline) over 3 years post transplant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over three years post transplant</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Assess the proportion of patients with each BOS grade</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 and 3 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Assess the proportion of patients with greater than or equal to  1 episode of acute allograft rejection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the first year of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. The number of acute rejection episodes per patient per year and per hundred patient days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Per year (at year one, two and three) post transplant and per hundred patient days post transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. The time to first rejection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over three years post transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5. A composite vascular rejection score (sum of A grades divided by the postoperative days).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three years post transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6. Sum of broncial rejection score (sum of B grades divided by the post operative days).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three years post transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>7. Patient and graft survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 and 3 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>8. Treatmetn Failure: a) drug discontinuation, b) graft loss, c) patient death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over three years post transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>9. SAE's &amp; AE's as defined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over three years post transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Recipients of a first heart-lung, bilateral lung or single lung allograft who are suitable to receive everolimus or mycophenolate sodium plus cyclosporin and corticosteroid triple therapy. 2. Patients capable of understanding the purposes and risks of the study and who have given informed written consent. 3. Male and female patients of childbearing age agree to maintain effective birth control practice during the study and fro 3 months after cessation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patietns who require immunosuppressive therapy other than study medication.2. Patients receiving a lobar lung transplant from a living donor.3. Patients who have received a prior ling or other organ transplant.4. Pregnant women and nursing mothers.5. Women unwilling to use adequate contraception during and for 3 months following the conclusion of treatment with study drug.6. Patients or their donors with serologic evidence of HIV, HbsAg or HCV antibodies.7. Patients with maligancies or history of malignancy with a recurrence free interval of &lt; 5 years except non metastatic basal or squameous cell carcinoma of the skin that has bee treated successfully.8. Patients with systemic infections requiring therapy at the time of entry into the study. A systemic infection is defined as a body temperature of 38 degrees C or above on 2 occasions, or 39 degrees C accompanied by a culture of body fluid regarded as significant by the local laboratory and requiring antibiotic therapy.9. Patients with panresistant infections with Burkholderia cepacia or mycobacteria in the last year.10. Patients with renal insufficiency (creatinine clearance &lt; 50ml/min)11. Patients with severe uncontrolled hypercholesterolaemia (greater than or equal too 350mg/dL, 9.1 mmol/L) or hypertriglyceridaemia (greater than or equal too 750mg/dL, 8.5 mmol/L).12. Patients with a white blood cell count of &lt;2,500/mm3 or platlet count &lt; 50,000/mm3.13. Presence of any severe allergy requiring acute or chronic treatment, or hypersensitivity to drugs similar to RAD (eg. erythromycin or other macrolide antibiotics) or to Myfortic.14. Patients on invasive ventilator devices or extracorporeal membrane oxygenators (ECMO).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>IVRS</concealment>
    <sequence>PATIENTS WILL BE STRATIFIED AS TO WHETHER THEY HAVE CYSTIC FIBROSIS OR NOT, AND THEN RANDOMISED VIA IVRS</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/08/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>320</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Allan R. Glanville</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Heart Lung Transplant Unit St. Vincent's Hospital Xavier 4 Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lichtstrasse 35, 4056 Basel</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To assess the efficacy and safety of delayed onset Certican (Everolimus) compared to Myfortic (enteric coated Mycophenolate Sodium: MPS), both arms in combination with Cyclosporin A (CsA)(monitored by C2 levels) and corticosteroids for the prevention of chronic rejection (Bronchiolitis Obliterans Syndrome: BOS) in the first 3 years post transplant when given as de novo maintenance therapy for the management of lung allograft recipients after bronchial anastomotic healing has been confirmed at bronchoscopy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St. Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sydney NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Prince Charles Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Brisbane QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Lee Mead</name>
      <address>Heart Lung Transplant Unit
St. Vincent's Hospital
Xavier 4
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 4257   </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9332 4267 </fax>
      <email>lmead2@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Allan R. Glanville </name>
      <address>Heart Lung Transplant Unit
St. Vincent's Hospital
Xavier 4
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2  8382 2175</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9332 4267</fax>
      <email>aglanville@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lee Mead</name>
      <address>Heart Lung Transplant Unit St. Vincent's Hospital Xavier 4 Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 4257</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9332 4267</fax>
      <email>lmead2@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Allan R. Glanville </name>
      <address>Heart Lung Transplant Unit St. Vincent's Hospital Xavier 4 Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 2175</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9332 4267</fax>
      <email>aglanville@stvincents.com.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>