<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371233">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001084471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Characterization of patients with established polymyalgia rheumatica </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Characterization of patients with established polymyalgia rheumatica treated
with long-term glucocorticoid therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-0234</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Polymyalgia rheumatica</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with an established diagnosis of PMR attending the Austin Hospital or referred by primary care providers and Rheumatologists in the Hospitals catchment area (north-eastern suburbs of Melbourne, Victoria) will be invited to partake.  After appropriate consent, demographic data, a range of questionnaires on symptoms and prednisolone-related treatment complications, and a general physical examination will be carried out as part of the initial visit (performed in the Rheumatology Department, Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital. time commitment 2 hours). Participants will then have a set of blood tests performed, along with the following imaging tests:  
- Bilateral hand x-rays (performed during initial visit); 
- Ultrasound of the wrists and shoulders (performed during initial visit);  
- Whole body Positron Emission Tomography (PET)/Computed Tomography (CT) scan (performed in Molecular Imaging and Therapy at Austin Hospital, time commitment 2 hours); 
- Whole body composition DEXA scan (performed in Bone and Mineral Research Unit, time commitment 1 hour). 

A subsequent visit will be arranged to the Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition at Deakin University (time commitment 2 hours), Burwood Campus where participants will undergo a range of muscle strength, power and function tests in a dedicated laboratory. A peripheral quantitative CT scan (a test capable of measuring muscle size and bone strength) will also be performed during this visit. 

In selected participants, targeted MRI may also be performed at a later date in order to permit correlation of whole body PET/CT findings (performed in the Radiology Department at Austin Hospital, time commitment 1 hour). 

At the conclusion of the study (no longer than one month from enrolment to completion of subsequent visit), the characteristics of participants with established PMR will be compared with those from a prior study at Austin Health of patients with newly diagnosed disease. It is hypothesized that this information will further delineate a distinct subset of patients refractory to the one size fits all cortisone approach, thereby permitting further study of alternate therapy in this group. In addition, the complications of long-term prednisolone use in PMR will be better appreciated.    
</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients with newly diagnosed PMR from a prior study at Austin Health (ACTRN12614000696695) will be the comparator group (data collected from June 2014 to June 2017).  </comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease activity, using PMR  Activity Score (PMR-AS):
- comprises patient visual analogue scale, physician visual analogue scale, C-reactive protein, duration of early morning stiffness and  elevation of upper limb score.     

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, using 36-Item Short Form Survey (SF36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, using Health Assessment Questionnaire  Disability Index (HAQ-DI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood, using Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep, using Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue, using Bristol Rheumatoid Arthritis Fatigue Multidimensional Questionnaire (BRAF-MDQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sarcopaenia, using SARC-F questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subsequent visit (within 1 month of initial visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity, using Habitual physical activity questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subsequent visit (within 1 month of initial visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cytokine profile, using multiplex assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abnormalities on ultrasound of bilateral wrists and shoulders</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distribution, incidence and intensity of joint and vascular FDG uptake on whole body PET/CT</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lean, fat and bone mass on whole body composition DEXA scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle cross-sectional area, subcutaneous fat cross-sectional area, muscle density, cortical bone thickness, cortical bone density and bone strength strain index on peripheral quantitative CT scan of radius, femur and tibia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subsequent visit (within 1 month of initial visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle power, using upper and lower limb maximal muscle power and strength, bilateral maximal isometric grip strength and bilateral maximal isometric dorsi-flexion strength, using Keiser pneumatic resistance training equipment fitted with A420 electronics, hand-held dynamometer and dorsiflexion dynamometer
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subsequent visit (within 1 month of initial visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity, using Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subsequent visit (within 1 month of initial visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance and coordination, using Choice Stepping Reaction Time (CSRT) and Four-Step Square Test (FSST)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subsequent visit (within 1 month of initial visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of PMR (as defined by the 2012 European League Against Rheumatism/American College of Rheumatology [EULAR/ACR] Classification Criteria) at least 18 months earlier;
AND
Long-term treatment with low-dose glucocorticoid therapy (stable prednisolone dose greater than or equal to 5mg and less than or equal to 15mg oral daily for at least 2 months duration).  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior diagnosis or current symptoms suggestive of Giant Cell Arteritis (GCA [headache, jaw claudication, scalp tenderness or sudden visual disturbance]);
Active malignancy; 
Active infection;  
Active neuromuscular disease; 
Other inflammatory conditions eg. Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA); 
Chronic pain syndromes;  
Treatment with concomitant Disease Modifying Anti-Rheumatic Drugs (DMARD).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>At completion of the study period, statistical analyses will be undertaken using Stata 13.0 to compare the characteristics of those patients with established PMR with those from a newly diagnosed population from a prior study. Parametric data will be compared using t-tests, while non-parametric data will be compared using the chi-square test or Kruskall-Wallis one-way analysis of variance. P-values of &lt;0.05 will be classified as statistically significant.  A more detailed multivariable and conditional logistic regression is also planned to control for the effects of variables such as gender, BMI and smoking status.

To the authors knowledge, no study has previously attempted to characterize the demographic, clinical, laboratory and radiologic features of patients with established PMR (as distinct from newly diagnosed PMR). In the absence of such pilot data, sample size calculation is difficult given the expected proportion of participants with a given outcome is unknown. With that said, the minimum sample size is anticipated to be similar to that enrolled in a prior study at Austin Health of newly diagnosed patients (~30 participants), in order to enable direct comparison of the two groups. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3081 - Heidelberg West</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rheumatology Department, 
Repatriation Campus, 
Level 1, North Wing,
300 Waterdale Road, 
Heidelberg West VIC 3081. 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Health </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rheumatology Department, 
Repatriation Campus, 
Level 1, North Wing,
300 Waterdale Road, 
Heidelberg West VIC 3081. </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arthritis Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2/255 Broadway,
Glebe NSW 2037. </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Arthritis Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 2/255 Broadway,
Glebe NSW 2037. </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deakin University </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition Research, 
Burwood Campus, 
Building J, 
221 Burwood Highway, 
Burwood VIC 3125.    </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite the fact that Polymyalgia Rheumatica (PMR) is the most common inflammatory rheumatic disease of the elderly, it is under-researched and poorly understood. With no diagnostic tests available, diagnosis is dependent upon a history of muscle pain and stiffness in the shoulder and hip regions, combined with raised inflammation levels in the blood. Treatment consists of prednisolone (commonly referred to as cortisone) prescribed in a one size fits all approach that lasts ~12 months in duration. However, the way in which PMR patients symptoms respond is very variable; some improve almost overnight, whilst other individuals require higher doses for much longer periods of time. Unfortunately, such long-term prednisolone use can result in many complications including osteoporosis, weight gain, high blood pressure and diabetes. This project therefore aims to identify the characteristics of PMR patients that have failed standard cortisone treatment and remain on long-term prednisolone. In addition, prednisolone-related treatment complications will be documented. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Road, 
Heidelberg VIC 3084. 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/Austin/77</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Russell Buchanan</name>
      <address>Austin Health 
Rheumatology Department, 
Repatriation Campus, 
Level 1, North Wing, 
300 Waterdale Road, 
Heidelberg West VIC 3081. 
</address>
      <phone>+613 9496 4013</phone>
      <fax>+613 9496 4012</fax>
      <email>russell.buchanan@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Owen </name>
      <address>Austin Health 
Rheumatology Department, 
Repatriation Campus, 
Level 1, North Wing, 
300 Waterdale Road, 
Heidelberg West VIC 3081. </address>
      <phone>+613 9496 4013</phone>
      <fax>+613 9496 4012</fax>
      <email>claire.owen@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Owen </name>
      <address>Austin Health 
Rheumatology Department, 
Repatriation Campus, 
Level 1, North Wing, 
300 Waterdale Road, 
Heidelberg West VIC 3081. </address>
      <phone>+613 9496 4013</phone>
      <fax>+613 9496 4012</fax>
      <email>claire.owen@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>