<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372408">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000556347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Influence of the exercise on reduction of sacroiliac dysfunction in pregnancy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Influence of the exercise on reduction of sacroiliac dysfunction in pregnancy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1193-3606</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sacroiliac dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study group will be trained on exercises to stabilize the sacroiliac joints by researchers. Training subjects will include four exercises to stabilise the sacroiliac joints which respondents performed at individual one-on-one session in hospital within a time period of 20 minutes (5 minutes each) two times a week until the end of pregnancy under the supervision of a physiotherapist.
Exercise 1. In four-legged position performed to exercise posterior pelvic tilt. The initial position would be four-legged relying on his hands and knees and pelvis in the neutral position. From neutral position of the pelvis performed to move posterior pelvic tilt and then return the pelvis to the neutral position.
Exercise 2. Stabilization of sacroiliac joints performed to the four-legged position. The initial position would be four-legged relying on his hands and knees, whereby the position of flexion of the knee and hip movement performed retroflexion thigh alternately with each upper leg.
Exercise 3. Stabilization of sacroiliac joints performed to and in a sitting position. The initial position would be sitting without back with feet on the ground. From the position of flexion of the knee and hip will be delivered movement anteflexion thigh but a shift in the thigh posterior direction towards sacroiliac joint. Exercise should be performed alternately by the right, and then the left foot.
Exercise 4. In the sitting position performed to exercise contraction of the gluteal muscles and posterior pelvic tilt. The starting position would have been sitting without back with  feet on the ground. Then is performed  the contraction of the gluteus and posterior pelvic tilt. Then would follow the return of the pelvis in the neutral position and relaxation gluteal muscles.
Every three weeks would be applied  clinically functional tests: Patrik-Faber's test, distraction test, 4P test, palpation of ramus os pubis and test palpation of the dorsal ligaments for detecting sacroiliac dysfunction in pregnancy, VAS scale for detecting the intensity of pain and Quebec scale for assessing the degree of disability.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group continued to adhere to their normal lifestyle without education exercises to stabilize the sacroiliac joints.
Every three weeks would be applied clinically functional tests: Patrik-Faber's test, distraction test, 4P test, palpation of ramus os pubis and test palpation of the dorsal ligaments for detecting sacroiliac dysfunction in pregnancy, VAS scale for detecting the intensity of pain and Quebec scale for assessing the degree of disability.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To detect the effectiveness of therapeutic exercise in pregnancy on reducing sacroiliac dysfunction by clinical funcional test (Patrik-Faber's test, distraction test, 4P test, palpation of ramus os pubis and test palpation of the dorsal ligaments), VAS scale (for detecting the intensity of pain) and Quebec scale (for assessing the degree of disability)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At physiotherapy assessment every 3 weeks until the end of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the incidence of sacroiliac dysfunction during pregnancy in primiparas / multiparas and singleton / multifetal  pregnancy by clinical funcional test (Patrik-Faber's test, distraction test, 4P test, palpation of ramus os pubis and test palpation of the dorsal ligaments)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At one physiotherapy assessment every 3 weeks until the end of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in symptoms of sacroiliac dysfunction from baseline to end of exercise intervention in primiparas / multiparas and singleton / multifetal  pregnancy by VAS scale (for detecting the intensity of pain) and Quebec scale (for assessing the degree of disability)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At physiotherapy assessment every 3 weeks until the end of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To detect a corelation between therapeutic exercise with functional capabilities of pregnant women with sacroiliac dysfunction Quebec scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>At physiotherapy assessment every 3 weeks until the end of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Primiparous / multiparous, singleton / multiple pregnancy, gestational age greater than 10 weeks and less than 34 weeks</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Surgical procedures in the area of the spine and pelvis, previous episodes of sacroiliac dysfunction before pregnancy, ankylosing spondylitis, and any other disease whose symptoms can cause symptoms of sacroiliac dysfunction</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After informed consent randomly selected espondents will be randomized into two groups. 
Allocation concealment was done by central randomisation by phone/fax/computer selected</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table from a statistic book.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the incidence of sacroiliac dysfunction in pregnancy it will be used calculate the frequency. To determine the significance of the connection in frequencies would be used chi squared test. The corelation between the development of sacroiliac dysfunction and exercise in pregnancy and parity determined to Pearson's correlation coefficient. For the determination of the significance of the contribution of exercise and length of exercise in pregnancy would be used method of multiple regression analysis. In interpreting the results statistically significant would be considered the value of P &lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>374</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <state>Zagreb</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh, Sveti Duh 64, 10 000 Zagreb</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Croatia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh, Sveti Duh 64, 10000 Zagreb</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Croatia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sacroiliac dysfunction during pregnancy leads to a reduction in quality and limit the activities of daily living pregnant women with incidence from 14% to 76.6%. The occurrence and development of sacroiliac dysfunction during pregnancy affect biomechanical and hormonal factors. Symptoms of sacroiliac dysfunction vary from minimal discomfort to harder disability during activities of daily living.
As during pregnancy due to hormonal changes disrupted ligaments function as a passive stabilizer of the pelvis is important to provide compensation by activation of muscles as active stabilizer. This is part of clinical management but without precise guidelines and standardised procedures. The tendency of this study is to investigate the role of exercise as a method of strengthening the muscles as active stabilizer sacroiliac joints during pregnancy in order to decrease the development of sacroiliac dysfunction.
Key words: pregnancy, exercise, sacroiliac dysfunction
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethic Committee of Clinical hospital Sveti Duh</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh, Sveti Duh 64, 10 000 Zagreb</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>N/A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Croatia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Manuela Filipec</name>
      <address>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh, Sveti Duh 64, 10 000 Zagreb</address>
      <phone>+385913712561</phone>
      <fax>+385913712206</fax>
      <email>manuela.filipec@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Manuela Filipec</name>
      <address>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh, Sveti Duh 64, 10 000 Zagreb</address>
      <phone>+385913712561</phone>
      <fax>+385913712206</fax>
      <email>manuela.filipec@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Manuela Filipec</name>
      <address>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh, Sveti Duh 64, 10 000 Zagreb</address>
      <phone>+385913712561</phone>
      <fax>+385913712206</fax>
      <email>manuela.filipec@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Manuela Filipec</name>
      <address>Clinical hospital Sveti Duh, Sveti Duh 64, 10 000 Zagreb</address>
      <phone>+385913712561</phone>
      <fax>+385913712206</fax>
      <email>manuela.filipec@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Croatia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>