<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369642">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001596493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of different intensity exercise training in patients with ventricular assist devices</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of different intensity exercise training on peak oxygen consumption in patients with left ventricular assist devices: a multicentre, randomized, control trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym> Exercise Training in Ventricular Assist Devices (ETVAD)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced Chronic Heart Failure with Left Ventricular Assist Device in situ.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>High-intensity Interval Training (HIT):
This is an intervention of 12-week exercise training program involving high-intensity interval training three times per week. The total duration of each session will be 60 minutes.
- The intervention will be delivered by an Exercise Physiologist with minimum 3 years' experience and will be supervised by a multidisciplinary team composed of Senior Exercise Physiologists, Senior Physiotherapists and a Registered Nurse in a hospital-based cardiac rehabilitation gymnasium.
- Sessions in both groups will commence/conclude with a warm-up/cool-down involving 5 minutes of low-intensity aerobic exercise, followed by 5 minutes of stretching. 
-Following warm up, 4 sets of 4-minute of aerobic exercise on a treadmill at 80-90% of VO2 reserve, interspersed with 3-minute intervals of active recovery at 50-60% of VO2 reserve.
-Resistance exercises, involving one set of 3 lower body (dual leg press, dual seated hamstring curl, dual leg extension) and 3 upper body exercises (incline press, lat pull down and biceps curl) at 50-75% of one-repetition maximum.. 
-The exercise training program will be reviewed every fortnight during the course of the intervention to adapt the exercise prescription for cardiopulmonary and strength changes.
- Adherence to exercise training program will be monitored at the cardiac rehabilitation gym on a daily basis, with exercise attendance log and mobile call for follow up in case of non-attendance. Compliance will be set as 90% adherence to the established exercise training program. </interventions>
    <comparator>Moderate-intensity Continuous Training (usual care):
-12-week exercise training program involving moderate-intensity continuous exercise training (MIT) three times per week. The total duration of each session will be 60 minutes.
-The intervention will be delivered by an Exercise Physiologist with minimum 3 years' experience and will be supervised by a multidisciplinary team composed of Senior Exercise Physiologists, Senior Physiotherapists and a Registered Nurse in a hospital-based cardiac rehabilitation gymnasium.
- Identical warm up and cool down as HIT group.
-Following warm up, 28 minutes of continuous treadmill exercise at 50-60% of VO2 reserve.
- Identical resistance training program as HIT group.
- The exercise training program will be also reviewed every fortnight in this group during the course of the intervention to adapt the exercise prescription for cardiopulmonary and strength changes.
- Adherence to exercise training program will be monitored at the cardiac rehabilitation gym on a daily basis, with exercise attendance log and mobile call for follow up in case of non-attendance. Compliance will be set as 90% adherence to established exercise training program. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak oxygen consumption (VO2 peak), measured by cardiopulmonary exercise test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac function and structure: An experienced echocardiographer will perform novel echocardiography assessment using post-hoc myocardial tissue imaging (speckle and strain) to assess changes in regional diastolic and systolic function.Left ventricular (LV) reserve will be determined using traditional LV dimensions (linear and volume). In addition, longitudinal strain will be assessed to evaluate the impact of exercise on residual contractility. Right heart function echo assessment will be measured in response to treadmill exercise to ascertain right heart response and how these relate to functional parameters.
-This is a composite outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial function: Brachial artery blood flow will be evaluated using non-invasive high resolution duplex ultrasound to assess flow-mediated dilatation (FMD). Recorded images will be analysed employing edge-detection software. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscular Strength: Maximal isotonic voluntary strength measures will be assessed using a one-repetition maximum protocol to guide the prescription of the resistance exercise component of the training regimen. Body strength will be assess during a preliminary exercise training session when the participant will be orientated to all exercise training equipment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional exercise capacity: This will be assessed using a six-minute walk test (6MWT) protocol.. Participants will perform two tests, at least 30 minutes apart with the best test recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall body composition: Total body lean tissue mass, fat mass, bone mineral density, and visceral adipose tissue will be measured by dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood samples will be collected to measure full blood count, creatinine, C-reactive protein, cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein, high-density lipoprotein (HDL), triglycerides, as well B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) and N-terminal-pro-BNP (NT-pro-BNP).

- This is a composite secondary assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (QoL): The Short Form 12 survey will be used to measure physical function, emotional state, social function, general health, mental health, and pain. 
 
- This is a single secondary outcome, measured by a 12-question survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart disease Self-efficacy Scale: This validated questionnaire assesses an individuals perceived ability to undertake different tasks of a physical nature.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 12 weeks following intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III-IV chronic heart failure with left ventricular systolic dysfunction.
- At least 6 weeks post implantation with a continuous-flow LVAD (Heartware, HeartMate II/III)
- Haemodynamic stability.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Any major co-morbidities that preclude exercise testing or training.
- Ventricular assist device complications including clotting, serious drive-line or systemic infections or mechanical problems.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Automated clinical trials allocation system operated by a third party.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>1:1 ratio of participants.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size will be based on the power to identify a difference in the change in the primary outcome (peak VO2) of 2.5ml/kg/min, a clinically meaningful but conservative difference based on a previous study comparing HIT vs. MIT in CHF. Assuming a SD of 2.1 mL/Kg/min,at  80% power, 5% significance level, the samples size will be 14 per group . We will aim to recruit a total of 40 participants across the three sites to allow a 25% drop out or loss to follow up.

Linear regression models comparing group, adjusting for baseline, will be used to estimate group differences and 95%CI for change in the primary and secondary outcomes, using post-LVAD measures as the outcome, and conditioning by baseline measures, with treatment condition as a fixed factor. The intention-to-treat principle will be used for data analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kent St, Bentley WA 6102
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Foundation -Vanguard Grant 2015</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>In WA:      
334 Rokeby Road Subiaco 
Perth WA 6008  

Mailing Address:
Heart Foundation WA Division
PO Box 1133, Subiaco WA 6904
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent Street, Bentley, Perth, WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many heart conditions impair the heart's ability to pump blood. This is known as heart failure. Exercise training is an important component in the management of heart failure, but in severe cases, symptoms such as breathlessness and fatigue limit patients' ability to undertake and benefit from exercise. Left ventricular assist devices (LVADs) are small pumps implanted into the heart of patients with severe heart failure to assist the heart in pumping blood around the body. LVADs reduce symptoms of heart failure, enabling patients to undertake exercise that wasn't previously possible. However, little is known about the most effective form of exercise training in patients with LVADs.

This research project will involve an international multicentre randomised controlled trial investigating the effects of a new approach of exercise training in patients with LVADs, involving alternating bouts of moderate and high-intensity exercise. Six weeks after being implanted with a LVAD, participants will be randomised to either 12 weeks of high-intensity interval exercise or 12 weeks of moderate intensity exercise. Before and after the exercise programs, participants will undergo tests to compare the effects of the two exercise programs on fitness, heart and blood vessel function and quality of life. We anticipate the findings of this project will help optimise exercise rehabilitation for people with LVADs and provide information that will help inform exercise prescription in people with cardiovascular disease more generally.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00270) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Southern Integrated Research Organisation (SIRO) 

Level 2, Southern Research Facility (Perkins South Building)
102  118 Murdoch Drive 
Murdoch WA 6150
Locked Bag 100 Palmyra DC WA 6961
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>REG 15-164</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>OFFICE OF ETHICS &amp; RESEARCH GOVERNANCE - Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, The Alfred 

The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/Alfred/119</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Fiona Stanely Hospital -Advanced Heart Failure and Transplant Service
Locked Bag 100
Palmyra DC
6961 WA
</address>
      <phone>+61 4 33567369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nacho Moreno Suarez</name>
      <address>Curtin University - Building 101,
Health Sciences Research Hub

Kent Street, Bentley, Perth
WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 4 03243221</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.morenosuarez@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>Fiona Stanely Hospital -Advanced Heart Failure and Transplant Service
Locked Bag 100
Palmyra DC
6961 WA
</address>
      <phone>+61 4 33567369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrew.Maiorana@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nacho Moreno Suarez</name>
      <address>Curtin University - Building 101, 
Health Sciences Research Hub

Kent Street, Bentley, Perth
WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 4 243221</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.morenosuarez@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>