<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370530">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000543482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Compassionate Mind: Evaluation of a Positive Psychology Psycho-educational workshop series for Middle School Students</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Compassionate Mind: Evaluation of a Positive Psychology Psycho-educational workshop series for Middle School Students</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CMP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wellbeing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Social worry</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low mood</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Perfectionism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Compassionate Mind program is a psycho-educational workshop series that has been developed for middle school students. This study is a controlled trial seeking to evaluate the effectiveness of this program, and to also better understand the relationships between perfectionism, self compassion, mindfulness and psychological wellbeing in this population. The Compassionate Mind program has been developed within an Acceptance and Commitment Therapy, Cognitive Behavioral Therapy and Positive Psychology framework. The program seeks to provide psychoeducation about thoughts, emotions and behavior as well as encourage the development of skills such as mindfulness, self-compassion and helping thinking styles. The primary outcomes to be measured are social worry (including fear of both positive and negative evaluation), perfectionism, low mood and general wellbeing. The program will be delivered by a registered psychologist face-to-face and involve both lectures and small group work. The intervention will be delivered over 8 weeks, for a total of 8 sessions for year 7 middle school students (approximately 150-200 students). The duration of each session will be 85 minutes and sessions will be conducted at the school the students are currently attending. Content will include psycho-education delivery, experiential exercises, mindfulness practice, in addition to individual pair and group-based activities to better illustrate relevant concepts. Informational material will include powerpoint slides, short video clips and role plays. A series of questionnaires will be administered to measure outcomes prior to the program starting, 8 weeks later at the end of the program and a follow-up set of questionnaires will be administered approximately 3-4months later post-program completion. </interventions>
    <comparator>Year 6 students enrolled at the same middle school who will not be receiving the intervention will serve as a control group. The same questionnaire administered to the Year 7 students will also be administered to the Year 6 students. At the same time as the Compassionate Mind Program received by year 7, year 6 will be receiving the equivalent of "treatment as usual", with an internal school pastoral care program. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of the project is to evaluate the efficacy of the Compassionate Mind program. A number of outcomes are measured as listed below. Firstly, Mindfulness Skill: The 15-itemed Mindful Attention Awareness Scale (MAAS; Brown &amp; Ryan, 2003). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome data will be collected at baseline, 8 weeks post workshop commencement, and 3 - 4 months post workshop completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social worry symptoms: 12-items drawn from the Fear of Negative Evaluation and Social Avoidance and Distress-general subscales of the Social Anxiety Scale for Adolescents (SASA) (Inderbitzen-Nolan &amp; Waters, 2000; La Greca &amp; Lopez, 1998), and the 10-itemed Fear of Positive Evaluation Scale (FPE, Weeks et al., 2012)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome data will be collected at baseline, 8 weeks post workshop commencement, and 3 - 4 months post workshop completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-Compassion: The 12-item self-compassion scale- short form (Raes, et al. 2011).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome data will be collected at baseline, 8 weeks post workshop commencement, and 3 - 4 months post workshop completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wellbeing: The brief 14-item version of the Mental Health Continuum  Short Form (MHCSF) (Keyes, 2005) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome data will be collected at baseline, 8 weeks post workshop commencement, and 3 - 4 months post workshop completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perfectionism: The 14-itemed Child and Adolescent Perfectionism Scale-Short Form (CAPS; O'Connor et al., 2009)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome data will be collected at baseline, 8 weeks post workshop commencement, and 3 - 4 months post workshop completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Demographics: age, postcode, country of birth for mother and father, language spoken at home, family characteristics, self-reported average school grades, and physical activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome data will be collected at baseline, 8 weeks post workshop commencement, and 3 - 4 months post workshop completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Year 6 and 7 students attending a specific Sydney-based middle school. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not providing consent or not being enrolled in the specific middle school .</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Correlation, Regression, t-test, ANOVA, Mediation, Moderation

Differences between groups will be examined using hierarchical mixed models containing random intercept and random slope terms as well as fixed effects for treatment received. We are also interested in further investigating self compassion and mindfulness as potential mediating variables in predicting outcomes such as low mood, social worry and overall well being. Anticipated sample size is 150-200 students in the intervention group and approximately 100 in the control group, which is comparable to other similar controlled trials. power analyses will also be conducted post-hoc when analysing the results. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>7/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>158</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>14/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2135 - Strathfield</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Catholic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>25A Barker Rd 
Strathfield 2135
NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>25A Barker Rd 
Strathfield 2135
NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background &amp; Project Aims
Mental health disorders form a substantial proportion of overall disease burden in young people in all societies (Patel, Flisher, Hetrick, &amp; McGorry, 2007). Internalising disorders, such as anxiety and depression, are consistently reported as the most common mental health problems amongst Australian children aged between 7 and 14 years and are often less likely to be detected compared to externalising disorders (Australian Institute of Health, 2012; Klein, Jacobs, &amp; Reinecke, 2007; Letcher, Sanson, Smart, &amp; Toumbourou, 2012; Seligman, Ernst, Gillham, Reivich, &amp; Linkins, 2009). Poor mental health often begins in early adolescence (12 years of age), and a shift toward early intervention has seen some promise in preventing the trajectory of later diagnosable conditions as well as enabling adolescents to fulfil their potential (Klein, et al., 2007; McGorry, Bates, &amp; Birchwood, 2013). Within this context of rising mental health disorder incident rates, early interventions which target underlying contributors to poor mental health are likely to prevent later trajectories of disorders.

Perfectionism has recently gained attention as is a transdiagnositic entity. This means it underlies many other series pathologies such as depression, social anxiety, generalized anxiety disorder, eating disorders and even personality disorders (Dimaggio et al., 2015; Holland, Bodell, &amp; Keel, 2013). Perfectionism refers to a tendency to strive for flawlessness and set exceedingly high standards for performance, accompanied by tendencies for overly critical evaluations (Stoeber, Eklund, &amp; Tenenbaum, 2014). Its transdiagnostic nature positions perfectionism to be an ideal target for early intervention in addition to low mood and social worry to prevent the longitudinal development of future mental health disorders.
 
Self-compassion is a construct gaining prominence over recent years and may directly target the key features of perfectionism, low mood and social worry (Neff, 2011; Neff &amp; Germer, 2013; Neff, 2010). Self-compassion refers to an adaptive way of relating to ones self when considering personal inadequacies or difficult life circumstances. Self-compassion has also been shown to be an effective intervention target for adolescents suffering from negative world views (Neff, 2010). 

When working with a non-clinical high school population, it is important to ensure content is relevant and engaging, and appropriate for this population. Thus the combined framework of ACT, CBT and positive psychology approaches have been adopted in developing a psycho-educational workshop series, COmpassionate Mind. In addition, high schools are an appropriate target for early intervention programs given their access to a large group and capacity for the provision of ongoing support. The current study seeks to evaluate the effectiveness of the Compassionate Mind program which targets self-compassion and mindfulness. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee at Australian Catholic University </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Manager, Ethics
c/o Office of the Deputy Vice Chancellor (Research)
Australian Catholic University
North Sydney Campus
PO Box 968
NORTH SYDNEY, NSW 2059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-44H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Madeleine Ferrari</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Level 1/C1.44, Edward Clancy Building, 25A Barker Road, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61297014726</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>madeleine.ferrari@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Madeleine Ferrari</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Level 1/C1.44, Edward Clancy Building, 25A Barker Road, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61297014726</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>madeleine.ferarri@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Madeleine Ferrari</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Level 1/C1.44, Edward Clancy Building, 25A Barker Road, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61297014726</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>madeleine.ferarri@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Madeleine Ferrari</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Level 1/C1.44, Edward Clancy Building, 25A Barker Road, Strathfield, NSW 2135</address>
      <phone>+61297014726</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>madeleine.ferrari@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>