<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364959">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001030763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of Smartphone Applications For Improving Physical Fitness - AIMFIT</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of smartphone applications for improving physical activity and physical fitness in youth aged 14-17 years: a three arm randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1147-9524 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>AIMFIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity and sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant will be randomised to one of three conditions: 1) immersive application, consisting of a training program combined with an immersing story delivered via headphones, 2) non-immersive application, consisting of the training program only delivered via headphones, or 3) usual care, where participants will be asked to continue with their usual physical activities. The applications will be installed on participants iPod touch (Registered Trademark) or smartphones and will consist of an 8 week training programme (approximately 25 workouts, 3 per week, with a 35 minutes duration each) designed to improve their fitness and run 5km. An app diary/log will be used by participants to self-report the dates and time they use the app.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the usual care arm will be asked to continue with their usual physical activities for the duration of the study. The applications will be added to their smartphones/ipods at the end of the trial. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Between-groups difference in change in the completion time (i.e. in minutes and seconds) of the 1mile/1.6 Km run/walk test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-invervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1 mile/1.6 km run/walk test, a cardiorespiratory fitness field test to measure physical fitness. A prediction equation developed by Cureton and colleagues will be used to estimate VO2Max expressed in ml/kg/min. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-invervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Questionnaire for Adolescents score (self-report physical activity levels)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average daily time spent in light to vigorous activities (minutes) as measured via accelerometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average time spent using the app (times/week) (self-report)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Self-Efficacy Scale (PASES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale (PACES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological Need Satisfaction in Exercise Scale (PNSE)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability and usability of the apps (survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Be aged 14 to 17 years
2. Live within the greater Auckland area
3. Own an iPod touch or a smartphone (iPhone - Registered Trademark or Android - Registered Trademark)
4. Be able to perform physical activities
5. Not meet the NZ physical activity recommendations
6. Be able to provide written informed consent to participate in the study
7. Speak and understand English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Medical condition which may limit ability to exercise safely
2. Downloaded/used the applications
3. Unable to understand and/or comply with the study protocol</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants’ eligibility will be ascertained through telephone screening. Eligible participants will read and sign a consent form and attend a baseline measurement session, followed by accelerometer delivery. Participants will be allocated to the respective group using opaque envelopes (for concealment), once they return their accelerometer at a second session.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified on sex. The within-group randomisation assignment will be previously generated by a statistician using a computer algorithm.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Normative data (The President's Challenge Program, 2013) with percentile scores based on age and test scores for the one mile/1.6 Km run/walk test indicate an average time of approximately 10 minutes for adolescents aged 14-17 in the 25th percentile to complete this test. An improvement in the completion time of this distance equivalent to a shift from the 25th to 50th percentile corresponds to an average of approximately less 78 seconds (standard deviation = 11 seconds) to complete the distance. Based on these data, a sample size of 14 adolescents per group (42 in total) will provide at least 80% power at 5% level of significance (two-sided) to detect a 16 seconds difference in change in running time from baseline between the two groups at the end of the running program, assuming a standard deviation of 15 seconds. Due to an expected 20% loss to follow-up a total sample size of 51 participants will be sought.  All statistical tests will be two-tailed and a 5% significance level maintained throughout the analyses. Baseline characteristics will be summarised using descriptive statistics. Continuous variables will be described as numbers of observed and missing values, mean, standard deviation, median, minimum and maximum. Categorical variables will be described as frequencies and percentages. Results will be presented for each of the treatment groups as well as overall. Outcome evaluation will be performed on the principle of intention to treat (ITT), using data collected from all randomised participants. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) regression model will be used to evaluate the main exposure effect on the primary outcome between groups, adjusting for its baseline measure, important demographics and other potential confounding factors (if they are statistically significant at 5% level). A similar approach will be used for secondary outcome measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>51</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>51</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Artur Direito</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019, Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Institute for Health Innovation, University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019, Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ralph Maddison</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019, Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Robyn Whittaker</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019, Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Public health researchers have begun to investigate innovative approaches such as interactive technologies (mobile phones) to enhance delivery of behaviour change interventions. Even though there are a rapidly growing number of these new technologies available, particularly smartphone applications for health-related behaviour change, their efficacy and actual value still needs to be proven. A prospective randomised study will compare the effectiveness of two smartphone applications in improving cardiorespiratory fitness. Both applications were designed for beginners training to run a 5km distance. Each participant will be randomised to one of three conditions: 1) immersive application, 2) non-immersive application, or 3) usual care. The applications, which will be installed in the participants iPod touch - Registered Trademark - or smartphone, consist of an 8-week training program (approximately 25 workouts, each with a 35 minutes duration) designed to improve their fitness and ability to run 5km. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Study protocol: 
Direito A, Jiang Y, Whittaker R, Maddison R. Smartphone apps to improve fitness and increase physical activity among young people: protocol of the Apps for IMproving FITness (AIMFIT) randomized controlled trial. BMC Pub Health 2015;15(1):635 [doi: 10.1186/s12889-015-1968-y] [PMID: 26159834]

Study results:
Direito A, Jiang Y, Whittaker R, Maddison R. Apps for IMproving FITness and Increasing Physical Activity Among Young People: The AIMFIT Pragmatic Randomized Controlled Trial. J Med Internet Res 2015;17(8):e210. [doi: 10.2196/jmir.4568] [PMID: 26316499]</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UAHPEC - University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics COmmittee
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Research Integrity Unit
Level 10, Building 620
49 Symonds Street
Auckland 1142</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ralph Maddison</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142 </address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 599 ext 84767 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.maddison@nihi.auckland.co.nz                  </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Artur Direito</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142 </address>
      <phone> +64 9 3737 599 ext 85285</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.direito@nihi.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ralph Maddison</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 599 ext 84767 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.maddison@nihi.auckland.co.nz  </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Artur Direito</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mailing Centre
Auckland, 1142 </address>
      <phone> +64 9 3737 599 ext 85285</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.direito@nihi.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>