<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364216">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000543785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Canteen Audit and Feedback Effectiveness study: A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Are school canteens that receive audit and feedback more likely than school canteens that receive no intervention to improve their school canteen menu to comply with the NSW  Fresh Tastes @ School - Healthy Canteen Policy?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The CAFE Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity Prevention</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Public Health- Health Promotion/ Education</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diet and Nutrition- Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will involve an audit and feedback process consisting of an initial introductory contact with canteen managers, followed by: a menu audit, a written feedback report and at least one telephone feedback/support call. This menu audit and feedback process will be conducted once per term (approximately 3 months apart) for 1 year after baseline (i.e. 4 school terms). 

The written feedback report will contain specific details about the compliance of schools menu with Fresh Tastes @ School policy. Feedback/support calls will involve discussion of the report and key areas required for improvement to comply with Fresh Tastes @ School policy.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Usual support - consisting of standard teacher development opportunities (up to one per year and attended dependant on opportunity) regarding healthy eating and physical activity programs in schools. These development opportunities may include staff training about specific government policy (e.g. Live Life Well @ School, Fresh Tastes @ School, Crunch and Sip) and/or the provision of miscellaneous resources relating to such policy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of schools with a canteen menu containing foods or beverages prohibited (red and banned items) under the Fresh Tastes @ School policy, assessed by a menu audit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of schools where healthy canteen items represent the majority (&gt;50%) of products listed on the menu as recommended by the Fresh Tastes @ School policy, assessed by a menu audit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to compliance - the number of days for a canteen to comply with Fresh Tastes @ School policy, assessed by a menu audit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The number of days from baseline until compliance, or 12 months post baseline, whichever comes first.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported measure of canteen profitability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of menu items in each category (red, amber, green) under Fresh Tastes @ School policy, assessed by a menu audit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Primary schools with a school canteen located in the New England Region of NSW or in rural or remote communities of  the Hunter Region of NSW, will be invited to participate. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Schools catering exclusively for children requiring specialist care, and schools without a canteen will also be ineligible. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible schools will be randomly allocated to either an intervention or control group in a 1:1 ratio by an investigator, not involved in data collection or intervention delivery, using a computer generated randomisation schedule.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will be generated a priori by an independent investigator using the random number function in EXCEL. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary outcomes will be assessed by comparing between group differences at follow-up using Chi-square tests under an intention to treat approach. A total of 36 schools in the intervention group and 36 in the control group will be sufficient to detect an absolute difference of 30% between groups with 80% power and an alpha of 0.05. This estimate is based on less than 25% (SD) of school menus in the control group compiling with Fresh Tastes @ School policy and accounts for up to 20% loss to follow up.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter New England Population Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The adoption of healthy school canteen policies has been recommended as a strategy to prevent excessive weight gain. A number of jurisdictions in Australia and internationally have policies requiring school adoption of healthy canteen strategies. Despite this, many schools have not adopted healthy canteen practices consistent with mandated policies.

One reason why many schools are yet to adopt healthy canteen policy is that current interventions aiming to improve practice cannot feasibility be extended to large numbers of schools, in particular to those in rural and remote communities. A promising solution to support population wide practice change of school canteens is audit and feedback. However, currently no evaluation of audit and feedback has been conducted in this setting. The aim of this research is to assess the effectiveness of an audit and feedback intervention to increase the adoption of canteen practices consistent with the mandatory NSW government healthy canteen policy (Fresh Tastes @ School).
 
Seventy-two primary schools that provide canteen services to students will be recruited to participate. Schools will be randomised to an intervention group receiving a 12 month audit and feedback intervention delivered via telephone and written report, or a no intervention comparison group. The effectiveness of the intervention will be determined by comparing post intervention differences between canteen menus audited by Dieticians in: i) the proportion of schools with a canteen menu containing foods or beverages restricted (red items) under the policy and; ii) the proportion of schools where healthy canteen items (green) represent the majority (&gt;50%) of products listed on the menu as recommended by the policy. 
The proposed research is the first evaluation of an audit and feedback intervention in primary schools. The study is of relevance to the efficient delivery of population wide services, particularly to those in rural and remote communities, aiming to reduce the burden of obesity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services 
Research Integrity Unit 
The Chancellery 
The University of Newcastle 
Callaghan NSW 2308 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2008-0343</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NSW Department of Education and Communities State Education Research Approvals Process </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3
1 Oxford St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012277</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Williams</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287</address>
      <phone>+61249246297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.m.williams@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Williams</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287</address>
      <phone>+61249246297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.m.williams@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Williams</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287</address>
      <phone>+61249246297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.m.williams@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Williams</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287</address>
      <phone>+61249246297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.m.williams@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>