<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365359">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001314718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is running re-education group more effective than high level balance group in reducing falls in the elderly living in the community?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is running re-education group more effective than high level balance group in reducing falls in the elderly living in the community?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Community dwelling individuals  who are over the age of 65 and have a history of one or more falls in the last 12 months</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The two interventions involved in this study are the High Level Balance group and the Running Re-education group.

Running re-education focuses on dynamic balance with an emphasis on quick movement and reaction in response to a perturbation. It is not the intention of the group for patients to return to running. It is called Running since all the components of its exercises involve a biomechanical element of running.

The High Level Balance Group is designed to provide an environment to facilitate measurable improvement in dynamic balance and offer strength training through functional activities. The program contains both aerobic and strengthening exercises performed at moderate intensity. Progression will be made accordingly to the participants capability

Patients in either group participate in a 60 min session, twice a week for 6 weeks.
Both groups involve a series of rehabilitation exercises all supervised by a physiotherapist and an allied health assistant.

A record sheet will be utilized in each session to document a patient's completion of an exercise component.

Both interventions will receive educational components encompassing, nursing, podiatry, occupational therapy, dietetics, physiotherapy and pharmacy. </interventions>
    <comparator>The standard treatment is the High Level Balance Group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The frequency of falls will be captured by the Falls Diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 26 weeks post intervention. Falls will be verified by a monthly phone call between within this period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at the completion of the 6 week program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic balance will be assessed by the 4 square step test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at the completion of the 6 week program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls Efficacy Scale is used to determine how confidently clients feel they are able to undertake an activity on a scale of 0 (not confident at all) to 10 (completely confident)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Captured at baseline, weeks 1, 6 and 26 post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be invited to participate provided they fulfill the following inclusion criteria:

Adult aged over 65 years referred to Community Rehabilitation Program at Peter James Centre with a history of one or more falls in the twelve months prior to being referred. A fall will be defined as an unexpected event in which the participant comes to rest on the ground, floor, or lower level (Lamb et al., 2005). This will be asked of the participants using the recommended wording: In the past twelve months, have you had any fall including a slip or a trip in which you lost your balance and landed on the floor or ground or lower level in the? (Lamb et al., 2005).

Able to understand Basic English.  This criterion will be passed if potential participants are able to read and understand the information and consent form. This understanding will be demonstrated to recruiters through patients verbally explaining their understanding of the risks and benefits of their participation in the study.

Participants must be cognitively able to give informed consent and/or follow instructions. This will be guided by clinical judgment.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they:
Live in supported accommodation (either low level or high level care).

Require assistance of another person for transferring or walking.

Are receiving individual physiotherapy while concurrently in a group program to enable any group differences to be assigned to the interventions with more confidence.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited on a consecutive basis from patients attending the Community Rehabilitation Program at Peter James Centre, Eastern Health. The treating physiotherapist will identify potential participants appropriate for the interventions with respect to the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The treating physiotherapist during a face-to-face session will provide verbal and written information about this study to the patient. Patients will be given the opportunity to discuss and clarify their concerns with both the principal researcher and associate researchers who will be available.

It must be noted that patients who participate in the study will be those who have just completed their one-on-one therapy with the physiotherapist. The treating physiotherapist will not have any influence on the patients' care or allocation. The clinicians who run the two groups will for obvious reasons be aware of the allocation. Therefore allocation is not concealed.

The secondary outcome measurements ("Time up and Go", "Four Square Step Test" and the "Falls Efficacy Scale") will be obtained by a third party who are not privy to the allocation.

Aim is to obtain 20 participants for each group (total 40)</concealment>
    <sequence>A coin-tossing approach will be used to randomize the subjects.

The therapist distributing the information will not be a member of the research team. Participants will be advised that participation in the project is completely voluntary, and that their decision, whether to participate or not, will not affect their normal therapy.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size of this pilot trial is designed to be sufficient to estimate effect sizes in the intervention that could lead to a design of a fully powered randomised controlled trial.  The sample size would be sufficient to detect very large differences between the two interventions if these existed at power of 0.80 and alpha level of 0.05.  For example, it would be sufficient to detect a reduction in falls rate from 0.6 (which is typical of this population) to 0.2, and sufficient to detect very large effect sizes (standardised mean differences) of 0.90 between the two interventions.
The primary analysis will determine an estimate of the effect size on the difference in falls rate between the two interventions, and the secondary analysis will estimate the effect size for the secondary continuous outcomes. The number of participants who fall and the number of participants who do not fall will be compared with relative risk ratios. Negative binomial regression models will then be applied to compare the number of falls and the falls rate per person in the two interventions groups in the 6 months.  For continuous secondary outcomes, analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will be used to compare the 2 groups at 6 weeks and 26 weeks, using the baseline measure as a covariate. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter James Centre - Forest Hill</hospital>
    <postcode>3151 - Burwood East</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eastern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cnr. Mahoneys Road &amp; Burwood Highway
Burwood East 
Vic 3151</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Peter James Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cnr. Mahoneys Road &amp; Burwood Highway
Burwood East 
Vic 3151</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Eastern Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cnr. Mahoneys Road &amp; Burwood Highway
Burwood East 
Vic 3151</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is evidence that suggest exercise can reduce the risk of falls and its associated injuries for the older population living in the community. Clients who are at risk or have a history of falls may be referred to the High Level Balance Group in the community rehabilitation program at Eastern Health, where the exercises are designed to strengthen and build standing endurance to improve an individuals balance. The other exercise class offered is the Running Re-education Group; patients participate in challenging tasks which demand balance and speed. This trial aims to find out whether running re-education group is more effective in reducing falls in the elderly living in the community.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, 5 Arnold St
Box Hill 
Vic 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>John Tran</name>
      <address>Peter James Centre

Cnr. Mahoneys Road &amp; Burwood Highway
Burwood East 
Vic 3151</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9881 1842</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ulnardeviation@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Cynthia Fong</name>
      <address>Peter James Centre

Cnr. Mahoneys Road &amp; Burwood Highway
Burwood East 
Vic 3151</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9881 1842</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cynthia.fong@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>John Tran</name>
      <address>Peter James Centre

Cnr. Mahoneys Road &amp; Burwood Highway
Burwood East 
Vic 3151</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9881 1842</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ulnardeviation@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>John Tran</name>
      <address>Peter James Centre

Cnr. Mahoneys Road &amp; Burwood Highway
Burwood East 
Vic 3151</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9881 1842</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ulnardeviation@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>