<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369241">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001323516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Schema Therapy for Eating Disorders</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Schema Therapy on Eating Disorder diagnosis in females with disordered eating</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>STED</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Eating Disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Schema is an integrative approach to treatment that combines the best aspects of cognitive behavioral, experiential, interpersonal and psychoanalytic therapies into one unified model. The schemas that are targeted in treatment are enduring and self-defeating patterns that typically begin early in life. These patterns consist of negative/ dysfunctional thoughts and feelings, have been repeated and elaborated upon, and pose obstacles for accomplishing one's goals and getting one's needs met. Although schemas are usually developed early in life (during childhood or adolescence), they can also form later, in adulthood. These schemas are perpetuated behaviorally through the coping styles of schema maintenance, schema avoidance, and schema compensation. The Schema-Focused model of treatment is designed to help the person to break these negative patterns of thinking, feeling and behaving, which are often very tenacious, and to develop healthier alternatives to replace them. Schema therapy is gaining widespread acceptability (e.g. it is offered by many private and public mental health hospitals in Australia), and it is becoming an increasingly popular psychological model for working with individuals who have a variety of mental and personality difficulties. This approach has been applied, in both individual and group forms, to a wide variety of clinical disorders, including, borderline personality disorder, chronic depression, and substance abuse (Masley, et al., 2012). A recent stringent systematic review found medium to large effect sizes for schema therapy in the treatment of most conditions (Masley, et al., 2012). The aim of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of group schema therapy for patients with eating disorders. An initial pilot in Scotland was found to be effective with this population in a previous study (Simpson, et al. 2010).

Patients will be asked to attend a one hour screening session with a provisionally or fully registered psychologist (supervised by Dr Smith) to ensure suitability for this type of therapy, before being invited to participate in the group. If they agree to participate in the group, they will then undergo a 2 hour assessment where they will complete a number of standard questionnaires and an assessment. They will then commence the therapy which consists of 25 weekly group sessions lasting for 1.5 hours. Eight to ten patients will be in each group. Each session will be facilitated by 1 to 2 therapists. At least one therapist will be a registered psychologist. Group attendance will be taken weekly to monitor adherence to the intervention. </interventions>
    <comparator>NA</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eating disorder symptom severity is the primary outcome. This will be measured using the Eating Disorder Examination - Questionnaire (EDE-Q) and will be numerical.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The second primary research outcome will be qualification for diagnosis of eating disorder. This will be measured using the Eating Disorder Examination. The outcome of qualification for diagnosis will be dichotomous (Yes/No)</outcome>
      <timepoint>.Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Schemas will be measured using the Young Schema Questionnaire (short form)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-Objectification will be measured using the Internalisation of Sociocultural Standards of Beauty (8 items)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General Quality of Life will be measured using the WHO-QOL Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Self Compassion will be measured using the Self Compassion Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personality Disorder features will be measured using The Borderline Symptoms Checklist-23 (BSL023) and The Millon Clinical Multiaxial Inventory (MCMI-III)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Schema Mode presentations will be neasured using the Schema Mode Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at pre- and post-intervention (at 25 weeks). Follow up timepoints will be 6 months and 1-year post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CORE-OM Outcome Measure Rating Scales of participants' own specific eating behaviours (problem areas)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly (during treatment group)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abbreviated EDE-Q measure of symptoms (drive for thinness, restriction etc)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly (during treatment group)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be 18 years of age or older and must have some form of disordered eating (e.g. anorexia nervosa, bulimia nervosa, binge-eating disorder, eating disorder not otherwise specified). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria include factors that would prevent participants from actively engaging in therapy and that would necessitate alternative treatment or admission to inpatient care (for instance, active suicidality). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Sydney University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bankstown Campus
Bullecourt Avenue
Milperra NSW 2214</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>UWS start-up funds</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bankstown Campus
Bullecourt Avenue
Milperra NSW 2214</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>UWS Women's Fellowship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bankstown Campus
Bullecourt Avenue
Milperra NSW 2214</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of South Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>101 Currie Street
Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Researchers at Western Sydney University are conducting a trial on group Schema Therapy for Eating Disorders. Participating in the study would involve attending a group therapy program conducted by two Clinical Psychologists, which will be held at the University of Western Sydney, Bankstown Campus. The program consists of one 90-minute group session per week, for 25 weeks. Participants must be 18 years or older and must have some form of disordered eating (e.g. anorexia nervosa, bulimia nervosa, binge-eating disorder, eating disorder not otherwise specified). Participants must not have current suicidal thinking. Participants will be asked to attend a screening session to assess their suitability for the group. If  suitable, they will be invited to attend a second appointment to be interviewed and to complete some questionnaires. They will be asked to take part in another interview and questionnaire session at the end of treatment, and again 6 and 12 months later.   

It is expected that those participating in the treatment group will lead to a significant reduction in eating disorder symptoms, reductions in general psychological symptoms and improvement of quality of life. This study is to identify whether or not schema therapy is effective in reducing symptoms. The study will explore patient perspectives about
what was helpful and not helpful about group schema therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Ethics: Western Sydney University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bankstown Campus
Bullecourt Avenue
Milperra 
NSW 2214</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H11151</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Evelyn Smith</name>
      <address>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9772 6707</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Evelyn.Smith@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Evelyn Smith</name>
      <address>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9772 6707</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Evelyn.Smith@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Evelyn Smith</name>
      <address>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9772 6707</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Evelyn.Smith@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Evelyn Smith</name>
      <address>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith
NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9772 6707</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Evelyn.Smith@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>