<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364435">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000678796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does the addition of imagery work improve outcome in standard psychological treatment for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD)?
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study evaluating Imagery Re-scripting and Exposure Response Prevention Therapy (IR-ERP) for Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD). </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1144-4762</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There will be two interventions used: (1) Exposure Response Prevention (ERP) and (2) Image Re-scripting (IR). 
ERP is a standard evidence-based behavioural treatment for OCD. It involves a graded approach to expose clients to feared objects/stimulus. IR is an imagery technique which has been found to help build client confidence and improve treatment adherence. This study seeks to integrate the two intervention to better the treatment outcome for clients with  OCD. 
There will be a total of 10 sessions. The sessions will be once/week for 90 minutes each, to a total of 10 weeks till completion. There is no follow-up plan. </interventions>
    <comparator>This study is a single case experimental design. There is no control group. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of OCD symptoms as assessed by Yale-Brown Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment or Baseline (1st session) and Post-treatment (on the 9th session out of 10)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Willingness to engage in ERP treatment as measured by Therapy Evaluation Form</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment or baseline (1st session) and post-treatment (9th session out of 10)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, anxiety and stress level as measured by the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment or Baseline (1st session) and Post-treatment (on the 9th session out of 10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy as measured by General Self-Efficacy Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment or baseline (1st session) and Post treatment (9th session out of 10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria are a primary diagnosis of OCD, age between 18 to 65 years old and no history of suicidal ideation 6 months prior to the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants with medication will be requested to provide their medication history and those with recent changes (within 3 months) to their medication will be excluded from the study. 

Screening for suicidal risk will be done in accordance to standard clinic procedure, which involves the use of suicide screening section of the MINI done during the duty screening over the telephone. Anybody identified as risk will be referred to appropriate support services and not invited to take part in this study.   
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The student therapist will coordinate with the Psychology Clinic manager at Curtin University to shortlist clients who have been referred for OCD treatment. The therapist will then contact these clients by telephone to do initial screening and clients who wish to proceed with treatment at the clinic will be offered an initial assessment session. 
During the initial assessment, clients will be interviewed and assessed using standardized measures such as the SCID-IV and Y-BOCS to determine the nature of the OCD symptoms. Clients who are found to meet the inclusion criteria will be informed of the study by the therapist conducting the assessment session. An information sheet regarding IR-ERP and consent forms will be provided to them, and treatment will only proceed after all consent forms are explained, signed and collected. Clients will clearly be informed that they have the choice not to take part in the study and this will not affect their participation in treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This study is planned to recruit 4 clients. This is an appropriate number as the hypotheses set up are a priori and they are based on existing theory. 
To ensure the study findings generalizability, this study will run the single-subject studies in parallel. By randomly selecting 4 participants from the targeted population, and monitor each participant over time, the observed changes across the 4 participants would be statistically sufficient to suggest that the intervention effect is generalizable to other members of the target population.  
In terms of analysis, this study plans to compare the changes (baseline vs post-treatment) and evaluate if these changes are of clinical significance. Clinical significance will be computed using the Jacobson-Truax method. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>4</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6845 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U1987 Perth,
Western Australia 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box U1987 Perth,
Western Australia 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project explores the viability to augment existing Exposure Response Prevention (ERP) treatment with Imagery Re-scripting (IR). Due to the aversive nature of ERP treatment, the authors postulate that the mastery of IR can help participants to foster confidence and improve adherence to in-vivo exposure exercises. Using a case-series methodology, four participants will take part in a 10-session, weekly therapy format. The IR-ERP treatment is hypothesized to bring about clinical improvements in terms of OCD symptoms, treatment adherence and general well-being such as depressive, anxiety, stress and self-efficacy. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>4466</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Clare Rees</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
GPO Box U1987 Perth,
Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3442</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>C.Rees@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Desmond Ang</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
GPO Box U1987 Perth,
Western Australia 6845

Personal address: 4/2 Canning Parade Como WA 6152</address>
      <phone>+61 424 168820</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toonsze.ang@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Clare Rees</name>
      <address>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987 Perth,
Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3442</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>C.Rees@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Desmond Ang</name>
      <address>Curtin University 
GPO Box U1987 Perth,
Western Australia 6845

Personal address: 4/2 Canning Parade Como WA 6152</address>
      <phone>+61 424 168820</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toonsze.ang@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>