<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367449">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001326684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Single Ascending Dose and Multiple Ascending Dose Phase I study of PXS-4728A Administered Orally in Healthy Adult Males.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Single Ascending Dose and Multiple Ascending Dose
Phase 1 Study to determine the safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic parameters of PXS-4728A Administered Orally in
Healthy Adult Males</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The interventional product, PXS-4728A, is a powder which will be dissolved in water for irrigation (stock solution). The final product will be formulated at 1-20 mg/100 mL in flavoured water at room temperature for oral administration.

The study is divided into 2 parts:

Part A - Single Ascending Dose (SAD) study in which PXS-4728A will be administered as a single dose (1/ 3/  6/ 10/ 15 or 20 mg).

Part B - Multiple Ascending Dose (MAD) study in which PXS-4728A will be administered once daily from Day 1 up to Day 14. However the dose for this part of the study will be decided based on the results of the SAD study.

The interventional product will be administered to the healthy volunteers while they are confined in the clinical facility under the direct supervision of the study team. This will ensure that strict adherence to the intervention are followed. 
 </interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator/ control for this trial is 100 mL of flavoured water at room temperature which will be administered as an oral solution. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. To evaluate the safety and tolerability of single ascending or repeated oral doses of PXS-4728A:
a) Recording of adverse events throughout the study.
b) Change from baseline in:
- Electrocardiogram (ECG) readings
- Clinical monitoring of blood pressure (BP)
- Heart rate (HR)
- Laboratory assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Part A (SAD): Measurements to be taken daily up to Day 5 following dosing on Day 1.

Part B (MAD): Measurements to be taken daily up to Day 21 following dosing on Day 1. Dosing will be once daily from Day until Day 14.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. To evaluate plasma pharmacokinetic parameters after single and repeat oral dosing of PXS-4728A:
a) AUC (0-t) and AUC (0-inf)
b) Cmax  maximum concentration
c) Tmax  time to maximum observed plasma drug concentration
d) t1/2  Terminal half-life
e) Accumulation ratio (For Part B only)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood and urine assessments were carried out for PK analysis. 

Part A: To be assessed 11 times on Day 1 and once on Day 2, 3, 4 and 5.

Part B: To be assessed 11 times on Day 1 and Day 14 and once on Day 2 and Day 15.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Assessment of plasma pharmacodynamic parameters after single and repeat dosing of PXS-4728A:
a) SSAO activity in plasma using enzymatic assay
b) SSAO concentration in plasma using ELISA method</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood assessments were carried out for PD parameters.

Part A (SAD): To be assessed 11 times on Day 1 and once on Day 2, 3, 4 and 5.

Part B (MAD): To be assessed 11 times on Day 1, once on Day 2 and Day 3 and 7 times on Day 14.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- healthy males.
- BMI - 18.5 to 30 kg/m2.
- no clinically relevant abnormality in an ECG; QTcF (QTc Fredericias correction) less than or equal to 450 ms, PR interval of 120-210 ms and a QRS duration less than or equal to 120 ms.
- adequate venous access.
- agree to use two approved methods of contraception from screening and until 30 days after administration of the study drug. 
- has given written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- clinically significant abnormal findings on the physical examination or medical history.
- clinically significant gastrointestinal, renal, hepatic, neurologic, hematologic, endocrine, oncologic, pulmonary, immunologic, psychiatric, skin or cardiovascular disease.
- history of significant drug allergies/ allergic reaction or currently suffers from clinically significant systemic allergic disease.
- abnormal wound healing as the result of surgery or trauma.
- received or is anticipated to receive any prescription systemic or topical medication within 14 days prior to the start of dosing or within 5 half lives of the drug, whichever is greater, or use any complimentary or alternative medicine 48 hours prior to the start of dosing or within 5 half
lives of the drug whichever is greater (excluding paracetamol).
- systolic blood pressure &lt;100 or &gt;140 mmHg, diastolic blood pressure &lt;50 or &gt;90 mmHg and heart rate (HR) &lt;55 or &gt;95 bpm.
- ALT, AST or bilirubin &gt;2x ULN.
- significant renal insufficiency, with an estimated
creatinine clearance less than 60 mL/min at screening.
- positive screening test for HbsAg or Hep C.
- history of drug abuse in the last 2 years.
- drink more than three (3) units of alcohol daily 
- used nicotine-containing products within 6 weeks before screening and unable to abstain until study completion.
- consumed caffeine and/or xanthine products for at least 48 hours prior to admission to the clinical facility, and whilst confined to the clinical facility.
- consumption of grapefruit, grapefruit juice, star fruit, oranges, orange juice, Seville oranges, red wine or other alcohol within 7 days prior to administration of study drug.
- positive urine screen for drugs of abuse and alcohol breath test at screening and study check-in. 
- receipt of blood or blood products, or loss or donation of 450 mL or more of blood within 90 days before the first dose administration.
- clinically significant abnormality detected on telemetry pre-dose.
- systemic infection other than coryza in the last week prior to dosing
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After informed consent has been obtained, all screening tests establishing subject eligibility will be performed within a period of 21 days before dosing. Subjects will be admitted to the clinical facility on Day -1.

In this study there are 6 cohorts for  Part A and 3 cohorts for Part B. Each Cohort will have 8 subjects. Subjects within a cohort will be randomly assigned to one of the 2 groups (PXS-4728A or placebo) in a 3:1 ratio respectively such that there are 6 subjects receiving PXS-4728A and 2 subjects receiving placebo within each cohort.

Sentinel dosing will be conducted for the first cohort of Part A. However sentinel dosing is not planned for the remaining cohorts but can be conducted if required based on the discretion of the Principal Investigator.

In Part A, single dose of PXS-4728A/ placebo will be administered to healthy males. In Part B, PXS-4728A/ placebo will be administered once daily from Day 1 to Day 14.

Allocation will be concealed by use of pre-labelled plastic bottles containing subject randomization numbers and use of sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>The investigational product (test or placebo) received by each volunteer will be determined according to the randomization schedule. 

Block randomisation using computerised software will be used for generating randomisation sequence. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Dose Escalating Study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Demographics and baseline characteristics will be tabulated and summarised by SAD/MAD dose level. Physical examination and medical/surgical history data will be listed by subject.
All clinical safety and tolerability data will be listed for each subject and summarised by dose. Vital signs and ECG parameters will be tabulated and summarised by SAD/MAD dose level. 
Laboratory values will be listed, along with comments as to clinical significance for values outside the laboratorys normal ranges.
Treatment-emergent adverse events, following the investigational product dosing, will be listed and summarised by dose level. All adverse events reported in this study will be coded using MedDRA.
Individual plasma concentrations and blood collection times will be listed by subject. Summaries of concentration data will include mean, standard deviation and coefficient of variation by SAD/MAD dose level at each scheduled collection time.
Summaries of PK parameters by SAD/MAD dose level will include mean, SD and CV.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/05/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>11/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>72</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pharmaxis Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>20 Rodborough Rd, Frenchs Forest, NSW 2086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pharmaxis Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Rodborough Rd, Frenchs Forest, NSW 2086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is the first in human study with PXS-4728A. The primary aim of the study is to establish the safety and tolerability while the secondary aim is to understand the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of PXS-4728A in healthy males.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-11-599</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sepehr Shakib</name>
      <address>CMAX, a division of Institute of Drug Technology (IDT) Australia Ltd, Level 5, East Wing, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2763</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2907</fax>
      <email>sepehr.shakib@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sepehr Shakib</name>
      <address>CMAX, a division of Institute of Drug Technology (IDT) Australia Ltd, Level 5, East Wing, Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2763</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2907</fax>
      <email>sepehr.shakib@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brett Charlton</name>
      <address>Pharmaxis Ltd.
20 Rodborough Rd, Frenchs Forest, NSW 2086</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9454 7210</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9451 3622</fax>
      <email>brett.charlton@pharmaxis.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gunjan Mody</name>
      <address>CPR Pharma Services, 28 Dalgleish Street, Thebarton SA 5031.</address>
      <phone>+61 08 8159 6255</phone>
      <fax>+61 08 8159 6348</fax>
      <email>gunjan.mody@cprservices.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>