<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371933">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001720404p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of chiropractic care on sensory integration in children with autism.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can chiropractic adjustments change multisensory integration and sensorimotor integration in children with autism? A pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism spectrum disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Asperger's Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single session of high-velocity, low amplitude, spinal manipulative therapy performed by a registered chiropractor in Auckland, New Zealand at the Centre for Chiropractic Research or at another suitable location. The intervention will involve assessing the full spine for any dysfunctional spinal segments and using spinal manipulation where necessary, this intervention will be pragmatic in style to best replicate chiropractic practice. The intervention session will take approximately 10-15 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Passive spinal range of motion will be used for the control group, performed by a chiropractor. This is aimed to mimic the full spine assessment and positional set up for chiropractic spinal manipulation, to control for any changes that may result simply from movement of the spine and tactile stimulation. This session will be less than 10 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measures will be data collected that relates to all study processes. Feasibility will be assessed by a composite of: recruitment rates, randomisation, percentage rate of completion of tasks for pre and post assessment measures and time taken to complete the protocol.  

As the intervention will only be a single session, there will not be a need to measure compliance rates with the intervention, as participants will not be required to do any follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and throughout all study processes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance on a sound-induced flash illusion task using a custom built Macroderma Sound-Induced Flash Illusion System. This task is used to measure multisensory integration by assessing how susceptible the individual is to experiencing the illusion. Where a greater susceptibility reflects poorer multisensory integration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention on the same day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The bilateral manual co-ordination subscale of the Sensory Integration and Praxis Tests will be used to assess vestibular and proprioceptive processing. This involves reproducing co-ordinated movements of the upper and lower limbs as demonstrated by a research assistant, this will be video and audio recorded and scored based on how well the child replicated the movements. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention on the same day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fine motor skills assessed by threading beads onto a string, This is a timed activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention on the same day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fine motor skills assessed by tracing an outline of a shape on a touch-screen tablet using a stylus, A computer program will measure deviation away from line and time taken to complete task.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention on the same day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Localisation of tactile stimuli is the second subscale of the Sensory Integration and Praxis tests that will be use to measure tactile proprioceptive awareness. While blind-folded the child will be asked to locate a point on the hand or arm with their finger where a research assistant has touched. The points will be marked and then the distance between the target and response points will be measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention on the same day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kinaesthesia is the third of the Sensory Integration and Praxis tests that will be used, this will assess tactile proprioceptive awareness.  While the child's blind-folded, the research assistant will place the child's finger on a specific location on the desk and orientate the child to this spot.  The research assistant will then move the child's finger to a second location, asking the child to be aware of how it feels to "move" to this new spot. After approximately 3 seconds, the research assistant will return the child's finger to the first location and then ask them to return the finger to the second location. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention on the same day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>High-functioning autism (HFA) or Aspergers Syndrome (AS) confirmed by parental report, and verbal.
Participants will also be screened with the following question, to determine if the child may have issues with sensory processing: Does your child struggle to cope in environments where there is a lot going on? E.g. environments that are loud/noisy, busy and/or bright? A yes to this question will result in inclusion and a no will result in exclusion from the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>non-verbal; hearing or vision impairments; specific reading disorder (such as dyslexia) or genetic disorder (e.g. tuberous sclerosis); or a history of seizures or traumatic brain injury</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be concealed as participants will be randomised using online computer software after baseline measures are taken.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Similar to other studies, a sample of 30 participants will allow us to assess the feasibility aspects of the study and to calculate potential effect sizes 
After data cleaning, assuming normality, paired t-tests will examine between group differences on each outcome measure. In any instances where normality is not maintained, a Wilcoxon Signed Rank Test will be used. Effect sizes (Eta squared) will inform sample size calculations for a full-scale clinical trial. Descriptive statistics will assess the feasibility of key study processes, including completion rates, time taken to complete the entire selection of tasks and recruitment.  Significance will be set at P = .05.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>55 Wellesley St E, Auckland, 1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>College of Chiropractic Neurodevelopmental Paediatrics</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1539 
Noosa Heads 
QLD 4567 
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Kids Summit</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2 Lincoln St 
Charlestown 
NSW 2290 
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Chiropractic Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6 Harrison Rd, 
Mount Wellington, 
Auckland, 1060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Centre for Chiropractic Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>6 Harrison Rd, 
Mount Wellington, 
Auckland 1060</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The principal study question being tested is, whether or not it would be worthwhile to perform a full scale study investigating if chiropractic adjustments can positively influence the way sensory information is processed by children with autism. To our knowledge there has been no study similar to this in the past, prior studies have used various outcome measures to determine that children with Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) have poor sensory integration. It appears that no studies have used these measures with a chiropractic intervention to determine if they are able to change the way children with ASD process and integrate sensory information in the brain. Furthermore, there is now a growing body of literature demonstrating that children with ASD have dysfunctional motor learning and motor control. For example: poor balance, poor handwriting skills, clumsiness, frequent delay in reaching motor milestones and difficulty with postural control, with studies of adults with ASD showing that some of these adults never reach the same level of postural control as typically developed adults (Freitag, Kleser, Schneider, &amp; von Gontard, 2007; Minshew, Sung, Jones, &amp; Furman, 2004; Wing, 1981). Moreover, a study by Freitag et al. (2007), found an association between the level of motor control impairment and the degree of social impairment. Those with the greatest degree of social impairment in general performed more poorly in terms of motor control. Some authors suggest that these motor control impairments seen in ASD may be a result of disrupted sensorimotor integration (SMI) (Siaperas et al., 2012; Weimer, Schatz, Lincoln, Ballantyne, &amp; Trauner, 2001). Current literature suggests that chiropractic adjustments help to improve SMI and multisensory integration (MSI) in adult, subclinical pain patients, as well as geriatric populations (Haavik Taylor, Holt, &amp; Murphy, 2010; Holt, 2014). Results demonstrated greater awareness of where the body was in space as well as improvements in processing visual and auditory information. Therefore, this study will assist in the planning of a future full-scale study, which will investigate if chiropractic adjusting can enhance SMI and MSI in children with ASD. As well as if these changes can result in improvements in motor control and social dysfunction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
133 Molesworth Street
Thorndon
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Jones</name>
      <address>National Institute for Stroke and Applied Neurosciences (mail code A-11)
AUT University
Private Bag 92006
Auckland 1142
New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>+64 212460587</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelly.jones@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Jones</name>
      <address>National Institute for Stroke and Applied Neurosciences (mail code A-11)
AUT University
Private Bag 92006
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kejones@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Jones</name>
      <address>National Institute for Stroke and Applied Neurosciences (mail code A-11)
AUT University
Private Bag 92006
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kejones@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Jones</name>
      <address>School of Public Health &amp; Psychosocial Studies
Auckland University of Technology
Private Bag 92006
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 7 838 4257</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kejones@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>