<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364303">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000894796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Intervention to Increase  Meaningful Occupation After Traumatic Brain Injury: The Participation, Engagement and Productive Alliance (PEPA) Program </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of the Participation, Engagement and Productive Alliance (PEPA) Program to increase meaningful occupation after traumatic brain injury using single case experimental design methodology</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PEPA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic brain injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Individual intervention will be provided to participants.  The intervention will target a minimum of three specific target behaviours related to the participants desired lifestyle changes, as selected by the participant during a goal-setting process.  The target behaviours will be tailored to each individual participant and will therefore differ among participants.  A participant-driven schedule of activity will be developed, initially drawing upon the Canadian Occupational Performance Measure and Goal Attainment Scaling.  The intervention will be administered by a psychologist or occupational therapist. Participants will attend 1x 1 hour individual session per week plus 1 x 20-30 minute telephone intervention per week for 15 weeks intervention. Adherence to intervention will be monitored in several ways. Participant attendance at intervention sessions will be monitored weekly. Additionally at each session the therapist will be checking whether the participant has followed-up activities planned at the previous session. Furthermore the therapists providing the intervention will have weekly supervision meetings with the lead researcher to monitor the intervention is adhering to the study protocol.</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be an initial baseline phase, during which there is no intervention, and in which the target behaviours will be measured for each participant. The baseline phase will serve as the control condition. The basleline will be 5 weeks duration.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The specified target behaviours, which will vary for each participant. Target behaviours will vary widely hence the measurement of target behaviours will vary. Some anticipated examples are measurement of number of steps participant  walks per day measured by a pedometer; or length of time spent in a specific activity per week measured by completion of an activity log; or number of social outings per week measured by completion of an activity log.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The frequency of measurement of target behaviours will vary depending on the target behaviour being addressed for the individual participant, but they will all be measured at most daily and at least weekly during baseline, intervention and a 1-week period post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of goal achievement using the Goal Attainment Scaling (GAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once during pre-intervention, once a week during intervention, and once 1 week post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participant's quality of life using the Quality of Life After Brain Injury (QOLIBRI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of change of leisure pursuits using the  Nottingham Leisure Questionnaire (NLQ)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants level of care and support needs using the Care and Needs Scale (CANS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants  community integration using the Community Integration Measure (CIM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants self-esteem using the Coopersmith Self-Esteem Inventory (CSEI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants levels of depression, anxiety and stress using the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participant's behavioural and executive function using the Frontal Systems Behavior Scale (FrSBe)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants life satisfaction using the Satisfaction With Life Scale (SWLS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants level of self-awareness of  their deficits using the Self-Awareness of Deficits Interview (SADI) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participant's social networks using the Lubben Social Network Scale (LSNS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure any change in participant's daily activity pattern using an activity log</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, during intervention, 1 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants level of social support using the Social Support Survey (SSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention, 2 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants psychosocial reintegration using the Sydney Psychosocial Reintegration Scale (SPRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants participation using the World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Scale (WHODAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure participant's readiness to change using the Readiness for Change Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure participant's level of commitment to working on goals using the Goal Commitment Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure change in participants goal setting and rating of goals using the Canadian Occupational Performance Measure (COPM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once pre-intervention, once during the week post-intervention, and once each at 2 and 6 month follow-up </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Sustained a severe TBI (duration of posttraumatic amnesia greater than one week)
2. Aged between 18 and 65 years
3. Between 1 and 15 years post trauma
4. Have received a comprehensive inpatient rehabilitation programme for the TBI
5. Living in the community in the Sydney metropolitan region
6. Independent in basic activities of daily living
7. Be able to travel independently by public transport
8. Have functional English to be able to participate in the therapy programme
9. Have sufficient neuropsychological skills (as documented in the neuropsychological and medical reports) to be able to participate in the therapy programme
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Current and major psychiatric disorder, including substance abuse as documented in medical records or determined by responses to the social and medical history form questionnaire
2. Participating in the competitive workforce
3. Pre-existing neurological disorder
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be referred to the study if the treating clinicians at the two hospital sites think that they are suitable for and would benefit from the study or if they are identified as being potentially eligible from a review of their medical record.  A letter of invitation will be sent to the potential participant and the research staff will telephone him/her after two weeks, unless the person indicates that they do not want to be contacted. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A single-case experimental design is used where the participant serves as his or her own control.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed using a variety of techniques:  
Target behaviours will be analysed using visual analysis of level, trend and variability, supported by quasi-statistical techniques (split-middle trend line and binomial test, percentage of non-overlapping data), along with modified time-series analysis where data permit.  Goal attainment scaling will also be used.
This study is using a single case experimental  design. The accepted current standard is that for direct intersubject replication at least 3 replications (original plus 3)  are required. In this study we will be researching 10 participants which surpasses the standard. Refer to Gast, D.L. (2010). "Single subject research methodology in behavioural sciences".  Routledge: New York.; Horner, R.H., Carr, E.C., Halle, J., McGee, G., Odom, S., &amp; Wolery, M. (2005).  "The use of single-subject research to identify evidence-based practice in special education".  Exceptional Children, 71(2), 165-179; and Barlow, D.H., Nock, M.K, &amp; Hersen, M. (2009). "Single case experimental designs: Strategies for studying behavior for change". 3rd ed. Boston: Pearson/Allyn and Bacon</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>16/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Rehabilitation Hospital - Coorabel/Moorong - Ryde</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Robyn Tate</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research
Kolling Institute
RNSH
Pacific Hwy 
St Leonards
NSW    2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lifetime Care and Support Authority (NSW)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 24, 580 George St,
Sydney
NSW    2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Participation in the workforce is often not possible for people who have sustained a severe traumatic brain injury (TBI). Furthermore, a large proportion of those who are unable to return to work also do not engage in any meaningful occupation in lieu of work. Such people generally have sustained major impairments of the cognitive functions essential to the development of meaningful occupational activities; specifically the ability to plan, initiate action, and to monitor and/or sustain activity. They often require structure and support if they are to develop a program of meaningful activities. This project specifically addresses the issue of diminished meaningful occupational activity for those who have sustained a TBI and are unable to return to work.  
Using single case experimental design methodology this study will provide individual intervention specifically aimed at increasing the persons engagement in meaningful activity.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1.	Tate RL, Wakim D, Genders M.  (2014).  A systematic review of the efficacy of community-based, leisure/social activity programs for people with traumatic brain injury.  Brain Impairment. 15(3), 157-176.
2.	Tate RL (December, 2015).  Increasing meaningful occupation after traumatic brain injury.  Final report to the Lifetime Care and Support Authority of New South Wales. 
3.	Tate RL, Wakim D, Sigmundsdottir L, Longley W. (September, 2016). An intervention to increase meaningful occupation after traumatic brain injury.  Paper presented at 39th annual meeting of the Australasian Society for the Study of Brain Impairment, Macau, China.
4.	Tate RL, Wakim D, Sigmundsdottir L, Longley W. (July, 2016). Developing an intervention to increase meaningful occupation after traumatic brain injury.  Paper presented at 13th annual meeting of the Special Interest Group in Neuropsychological Rehabilitation of the World Federation for NeuroRehabilitation. Glasgow, Scotland.
5.	Tate RL. (April, 2016).  Meaningful occupation after traumatic brain injury.  Paper presented at Brain Sciences Symposium, University of New South Wales, Sydney.
6.	Tate RL, Wakim D, Genders M. (July, 2015).  Which interventions are effective in improving meaningful occupation after traumatic brain injury?   A systematic review and recommendations for clinical practice.  Paper presented at the ASSBI/INS conference, Sydney, Australia.
7.	Tate RL. (July, 2015).  No work and no play makes Jacks life dull: what can we do?  Paper presented at the John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research Forum, Sydney, Australia.
8.	Tate RL. (November, 2015).  Using single-case experimental methodology in research and clinical practice.  Paper presented at the Clinical Advisory Board Meeting of the Moving Ahead NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence, Sydney, Australia.
9.	Tate RL. (November, 2014).  Using single-case experimental methodology to conduct research: Project to increase meaningful occupation after traumatic brain injury.  Paper presented at the Clinical Advisory Board Meeting of the Moving Ahead NHMRC Centre for Research Excellence, Sydney, Australia.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Coast Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00112)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Kolling Building, Level 13
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Hwy
St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00112</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Rehabilitation Centre Sydney Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 6
Ryde
NSW   1680</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SSA/12/06</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Western Sydney Local Health District Ethics and Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 7279
Liverpool BC
NSW   1871</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SSA/12/LPOOL/437</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn Tate</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research
Kolling Institute
RNSH
Pacific Hwy
St Leonards
NSW    2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926-4785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rtate@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn Tate</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research
Kolling Institute
RNSH
Pacific Hwy
St Leonards
NSW    2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926-4785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rtate@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn Tate</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research
Kolling Institute
RNSH
Pacific Hwy
St Leonards
NSW    2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926-4785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rtate@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Donna Wakim</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research
Kolling Institute
RNSH
Pacific Hwy
St Leonards
NSW    2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4785</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dwakim@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>