<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81646">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/11/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000486527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Measurement location for the indices of obstructive apnea / hypopnea frequency during Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) therapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of location of airflow measurement on the ability to assess Apnea Hypopnea Index (AHI) during Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) therapy in patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA) undergoing subtherapeutic CPAP and AutoCPAP therapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will receive an identical two-night titration protocol in random order up to 3 weeks apart. On one night, an auto-adjusting CPAP device will automatically titrate pressure throughout the night within the range of 4cmH2O  20cmH2O (cmH2O is a centimeter (centimetre) of water used to determine pressures during mechanical ventilation). On the other night, sub-therapeutic pressure will be delivered with the same device set in fixed pressure mode (2/3 of the subjects currently prescribed CPAP level (either home fixed CPAP level or the 95th percentile of pressure on current AutoCPAP device)). Subjects will undergo full polysomnography with additional flow measurements from four sites: mask, nares, CPAP machine airflow outlet and the analogue output of the CPAP device.There is no control group in this study. Auto-titrating CPAP therapy is increasingly used to treat sleep disordered breathing, however, the standard care remains fixed pressure CPAP therapy. This is an observational study as both conditions under which data is collected in this study represent actual clinical presentations of clinical patients receiving CPAP therapy.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of differences in Apnea Hypopnea Index (AHI) measured at four sites during overnight polysomnography (PSG) of subjects established on CPAP therapy. AHI will be measured during a two-night titration protocol (random order) using polysomnography in the sleep laboratory. Subjects will be connected to the CPAP device for the entirety of the PSG recording on both nights.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Polysomnography data will be recorded from Lights Out to Lights On (approximately 8 hour recording) during overnight PSG. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep architecture</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep efficiency</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total sleep time</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arousal index  cortical (EEG) and autonomic (Pulse Transit Time)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Flow limitation events (frequency of oxygen desaturation of &gt;3% per hour during sleep)Minimum oxygen saturation during sleep</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Autoset T data </outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Optimum CPAP Pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Near infra red spectroscopy data (cerebral blood volume/cerebral oxygen saturation).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcomes will be measured throughout the entire 8 hour PSG recording on both nights during a two-night protocol (random order) in the sleep laboratory.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects must satisfy the following inclusion criteria:Previously diagnosed with moderate-severe obstructive sleep apnea (RDI&gt;15)Compliant CPAP use for at least 3 months durationCompliance: CPAP use &gt; 4 hours per night for at least 5 nights per week No significant problems with CPAP therapy such as mask/mouth leak or severe nasal congestion. English speaking.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Other sleep disorders including:PLMD  Untreated RLS  &gt;10 Central apnoeas/hr on diagnostic sleep studyNeurological disordersPsychiatric disordersSignificant medical complaint including:Severe cardiovascular disease  Congestive heart failure  Significant lung disease (e.g., chronic obstructive pulmonary disease)  Daytime hypoxemia and respiratory failure from any cause  Prominent nocturnal desaturation other than from OSA (e.g., obesity hypoventilation syndrome).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/11/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/11/2005</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/04/2006</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>34</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>34</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>DiagnoseIT Pty Ltd, Sydney, NSW, Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 36 Tintenbar
NSW 2478
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>DiagnoseIT Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 36 Tintenbar
NSW 2478
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NIL</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Subjects who have been using chronic CPAP therapy will be invited to participate in the study.  The study will take place after the subjects have been instructed on the details of the trial and have provided informed consent.  Subjects are randomised to one of two nights in the sleep laboratory.  Under polysomnography and using an auto-titrating CPAP (AutoCPAP) systems, the subjects will be studied either under a sub-therapeutic pressure level for one night of recording (simulating a sub-standard therapy night  encountered by clinical patients), or on the AutoCPAP device in the therapeutic auto-titrating mode (which is also a commonly applied therapeutic device).  The study is observational in that the purpose and endpoints are collected as described below, under conditions in the laboratory simulating normal clinical occurrences.  Sleep and breathing parameters will be collected using standard laboratory methodologies, with the addition of flow measurement from four different sites: nares via a cannula; the CPAP machine flow outlet; the electronic output from the CPAP machine and the standard nasal mask via an oxygen port.  Integrity of the flow signal as well as the presence of break-through apnea / hypopnea phenomena are evaluated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Denotti, A. L., Wong, K. K., Dungan, G. C., 2nd, Gilholme, J. W., Marshall, N. S. and Grunstein, R. R. Residual sleep-disordered breathing during autotitrating continuous positive airway pressure therapy. Eur Respir J, 2012, 39: 1391-7.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X05-0176</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angela D'Rozario</name>
      <address>PO Box M77
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>0291140435</phone>
      <fax>0291140010</fax>
      <email>angela.drozario@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angela D'Rozario</name>
      <address>PO Box M77
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>0291140435</phone>
      <fax>0291140014</fax>
      <email>angela.drozario@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ronald R Grunstein</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute 
PO Box M77 Missenden Road
Sydney
2050</address>
      <phone>0291140438</phone>
      <fax>0291140014</fax>
      <email>ron.grunstein@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>