<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335377">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000488000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of cycloid vibration therapy for promoting exercise recovery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of cycloid vibration therapy for promoting exercise recovery in sedentary males</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>delayed onset muscle soreness</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Muscle damage will be induced by performing 100 maximal voluntary eccentric isokinetic contractions of the knee extensors of the right leg at 45°/sec through an 80° range of motion. The cycloidal vibration therapy treatment will involve the participant placing a therapy cushion under their right thigh while in a seated position with their legs hanging at approximately 90° which will vibrate their upper leg. Participants will undergo 15 min of treatment immediately after the post-exercise assessments are completed, and then twice daily for 20 min for seven days.</interventions>
    <comparator>The stretching/self massage treatment will involve participants massaging their upper leg for 14 minutes [4 minutes of effleurage; 2 minutes of tapotement (clapping); and 8 minutes of petrissage (kneading)] and 6 minutes of stretching their quadriceps by bringing their heel up to their buttocks while standing and pulling the knee back to lengthen the quadriceps. Three lots of stretches will be performed, each time the stretch will be held for 30 seconds with 30 seconds between for 2 minutes. This treatment will be applied immediately after the post-exercise assessments are completed, and then twice daily for 20 min for seven days. Participants will be trained in the massage and stretching techniques.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery of muscle force generating capacity. Maximal isometric knee extensor strength will then be assessed as the best of 3 maximal contractions with the knee flexed to an angle of 90 degrees on an isokinetic dynamometer (Biodex System 4, Chattanooga Group, USA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be 6 timepoints. Baseline assessments will be conducted before muscle soreness induction and then further assessments will be conducted immediately after the muscle soreness induction, and again at 24 hours, 48 hours, 72 hours and 7 days post muscle soreness induction.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alleviation of muscle pain. Muscle soreness will be evaluated using a visual analogue scale (VAS). The VAS will consist of a 100 mm horizontal line with anchor points consisting of 'no soreness' on the left to the 'worst soreness possible' on the right hand end.  Participants will be seated and requested to extend the knee of the right leg (so the leg is horizontal) while a 5 kg mass is suspended from the ankle.  The participants will place a mark at the point on the VAS corresponding to their perception of the soreness in the quadricep muscles of the leg.  The extent of the muscle soreness will be quantified using the measured distance (in mm) from the left hand end of the continuum to the mark made by the participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be 6 timepoints. Baseline assessments will be conducted before muscle soreness induction and then further assessments will be conducted immediately after the muscle soreness induction, and again at 24 hours, 48 hours, 72 hours and 7 days post muscle soreness induction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in muscle edema (measured by thigh circumference). Thigh circumference will be measured at the level of the mid-trochanterion-tibiale laterale site. The mean of three measures will be determined at each point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be 6 timepoints. Baseline assessments will be conducted before muscle soreness induction and then further assessments will be conducted immediately after the muscle soreness induction, and again at 24 hours, 48 hours, 72 hours and 7 days post muscle soreness induction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in markers of muscle damage and inflammation. Serum creatine kinase and myoglobin will be measured as markers of muscle damage using standard commercial assays. Serum C-reactive protein concentrations will be measured as a marker of inflammation using a commercial autoanalyser (Konelab 20 XTi, Thermo Electron Corporation).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples will be taken at 6 timepoints. Baseline sample will be taken before muscle soreness induction and then further samples will be taken immediately after the muscle soreness induction, and again at 24 hours, 48 hours, 72 hours and 7 days post muscle soreness induction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>sedentary (i.e. participate in regular physical activity no more than once per week for the purpose of improving or maintaining their physical fitness)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have undertaken resistance training of the quadriceps muscles during the three months prior to their anticipated participation in this study, have knee, quadricep or other musculo-skeletal or medical problem which might interfere with their ability to perform the required exercise to induce muscle soreness or have experienced significant delayed onset muscle soreness (DOMS) in their quadriceps muscles during the three months prior to their anticipated participation in this study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be recruited by newspaper advertisement and flyers. Volunteers will be screened via questionnaire to access their eligibility for the trial. Eligibility will be determined by the study coordinator. Treatment will be randomly allocated and will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is not directly involved in testing. The study will be single-blinded and treatment allocation will be concealed to research staff making the assements, but due to the nature of the treatments the participants will not be blinded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation by minimisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>68</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Jon Buckley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Advanced Lifestyle International</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 3, 15 Corporate Place
Hillcrest QLD 4118</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Rebecca Thomson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Peter Howe</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Intense exercise can lead to muscle damage, pain, swelling and loss of strength, which can take up to 7 days to recover. This recovery can impact negatively on athletic training and competition and predispose to injury. Cycloidal vibration therapy has been shown in recent studies to reduce limb swelling in patients who have undergone surgery and may be an effective treatment for reducing muscle swelling after exercise and promote recovery from intense exercise. 

The aim of the project is to evaluate the potential for the use of cycloidal vibration therapy to promote muscle recovery following exercise by examining effects on the return of muscle strength and the reduction in swelling, muscle damage and inflammation following intense exercise. This will provide evidence to support the use of cycloidal vibration therapy by athletes to promote recovery after exercise.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>General Purpose Building,
Mawson Lakes Campus
Mawson Lakes Boulevard
Mawson Lakes, SA 5095</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>P053/10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Jon Buckley</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1853</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.buckley@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.thomson@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>