<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369668">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001318572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Low cost body composition measurement for nutrition assessment from birth up to 2 years</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Validity of a low cost body composition measurement for nutrition assessment using Near Infrared (NIR) light reflection from birth up to 2 years</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>OPP1111820</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malnutrition</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a cross-sectional validation study recruiting infants and children from birth up to 2 years of age.

The intervention device is using: Near-Infrared (NIR) light reflection. 

The NIR hand held device will be measured through the skin's surface on 4 anatomical locations; triceps, subscapular, mid-thigh and flank for approximately 30 seconds performed by a research assistant or nurse. The infants / children will be seen at one single point in time at either birth (within 48 hours), 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months or 24 months of age following recruitment. </interventions>
    <comparator>The Near-Infrared (NIR) light reflection device will be compared against a range of criteria with reference to a gold standard which include:

Air displacement plethysmography (ADP) / Pea Pod involves measurement of the infant weight on a scale followed by the infant being placed inside a warmed compartment with fresh air to measure body volume, this test takes 2 minutes.

Dual-energy X-ray Absorptiometry (DXA)  involves the infant lying flat on a scanner bed to measure total Body % Fat and Bone Mineral Content (BMC), this test takes 3 minutes

Deuterium dilution to measure Total Body Water (TBW) involves firstly taking a basal saliva sample before the deuterium oxide dose is given,  1ml of deuterium oxide (D2O, 99.8 atom % 2H)  is administered using an oral syringe; saliva samples are collected up to 3 hours after the dose was consumed. 

Ultrasound involves moving a ultrasound transducer over the skin to measure the thickness of subcutaneous fat at two anatomical sites; thigh and abdomen, this test takes 10 minutes.

Anthropometry including; weight using electronic scales, length/height using a infantometer /stadiometer, head, abdomen, thigh and arm circumferences using a metal tape measure and skinfold measurements using hand-held callipers at 4 anatomical locations; triceps, subscapular, mid-thigh and flank .  Anthropometry testing will take approximately 30 minutes. 

The 3-Compartment Model will be used to measure body composition which requires determination of TBW, body mass, body volume and BMC and is classified as a reference technique.

The infants / children will be seen at one single point in time at either birth (within 48 hours), 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months or 24 months of age following recruitment. 

The newborns that are eligible (within 48 hours after birth) will have the following measurements: DXA, NIR light reflection, ADP / Pea Pod , ultrasound and anthropometry performed by a research assistant / nurse. 

Any infant / child who are 3 months or older will have the following procedures: DXA, NIR, Deuterium dilution, anthropometry, ultrasound performed by a research assistant / nurse.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the level of correlation between the 3-compartment model and the NIR body composition result</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at a single study visit following recruitment at either age; birth (within 48 hours) 3, 6, 12, 18 or 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the level of correlation between subcutaneous fat thickness assessed by ultrasound and the NIR body composition result.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at single study visit following recruitment at either birth (within first 48 hours), 3, 6, 12, 18 or 24 months
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the level of correlation between anthropometric variables and the NIR body composition result.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at single study visit following recruitment at either birth (within first 48 hours), 3, 6, 12, 18 or 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>INCLUSION CRITERIA
1. Written parental informed consent
2. Term gestational age (GA) (=&gt;37+0  41+6 weeks GA)
3. =&lt;2 years (24 months) of age
4. Black African or Indian ethnicity
5. Mother &gt;18 years old age
6. Singleton pregnancy
7. Mother lives within the study area
8. Can read and understand English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Hours</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>EXCLUSION CRITERIA
1. Any maternal condition or impairment with inability to give parental informed consent
2. Neonates: Prematurity (=&lt;36+6 weeks GA) and/ or the presence of any major congenital anomalies or morbidity that may contraindicate the neonatal body composition measurements
3. Infants and/or children: Birth defect (congenital anomalies, preterm birth (=&lt;36+6 weeks GA)
4. Physical or intellectual disability in infants and /or children, influencing physical activity or food habits
5. Chronic health problem in infants and / or children, influencing weight and length
6. If currently enrolled in any other research / clinical study
7. If any DXA scans completed in the past 12 months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>SAMPLE SIZE

The sample size is based on a true mean difference between BF% measured by a reference method (TBW and / or ADP and DXA) and BF% measured by NIR using a mean difference of 2.0 BF% with a standard deviation of 3.0 BF%, at a significance level of 0.05 with 80% power (1), a sample size of 28 infants and / or children at each age point are required to complete all aspects of the study. Thus with an expected non-compliance rate based on previous studies by Fields et al (1), we estimate the total number required would approximately ~ 720 in total to evaluate the accuracy, precision, bias, and reliability of the NIR device across 6 age groups (birth, 3, 6, 12,18,24 months).

STATISTICAL METHODS / ANALYSIS

For validation purposes, Pearsons correlation coefficients will be used to describe the associations between NIR against the 3 compartment model and /or ultrasound measurements. Coefficient of determination or R2 will be used to assess the best prediction equation and minimum wavelength for NIR body composition assessment.

Multiple and logistic regression will be used to analyse the relationship with anthropometric factors including circumferences and skinfolds.

For prediction of under and over nutrition positive and negative predictive values (PPV and NPV) and the sensitivity, specificity, and likelihood ratios with 95% confidence intervals. Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) curves will be used along with the ease of use, cost and portability of each method to determine the most appropriate tool for determining body composition.

REFERENCES

1. Fields DA, Allison DB. Air-Displacement Plethysmography Pediatric Option in 26 Years Old Using the Four-Compartment Model as a Criterion Method. Obesity. 2012;20(8):1732-7.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>720</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>650</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Johannesburg, Gauteng province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
New South Wales, 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>440 5th Ave N.
Seattle, WA 9810
Washington, United States</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Globally there are millions of under-five who are stunted (162M), underweight (99M), wasted (51M) or overweight (44M). The timing of child malnutrition reveals a 1,000 day period for meaningful intervention  before/during pregnancy, immediately following birth and up to 2 years of age - if the immediate effects on health and child mortality and the life-long impact of early onset adult disease are to be prevented.

Assessment of body composition is vital to deliver improved nutritional management of under and over nourished infants &amp; children. However, there is a lack of convenient, accurate and low cost devices for direct monitoring of nutritional status. This leads to difficulties for health workers to identify undernourished and overnourished infants and children and in monitoring changes in nutritional status following interventions. 

Our aim is to produce a suitable low-cost portable device using Near-Infrared (NIR) light reflection for direct monitoring of nutritional status from birth to two years of age. Using a cross-sectional design this study aims to validate Near-Infrared (NIR) light reflection against a range of criteria with reference to a gold standard from birth up to 2 years. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee
Research Integrity
Research Portfolio
Level 6, Jane Foss Russell
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/595</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369668-University of Sydney_Approval Letter 2015_595_10th November 2015.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369668-V1.4_Research Protocol_18032016_clean.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alistair McEwan</name>
      <address>Rm 850, School of Electrical and Information Engineering, J03 
The University of Sydney
 NSW, 2006
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7256</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 3847</fax>
      <email>alistair.mcewan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alistair McEwan</name>
      <address>Rm 850, School of Electrical and Information Engineering, J03 
The University of Sydney
 NSW, 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7256</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 3847</fax>
      <email>alistair.mcewan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alistair McEwan</name>
      <address>Rm 850, School of Electrical and Information Engineering, J03 
The University of Sydney
 NSW, 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7256</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 3847</fax>
      <email>alistair.mcewan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angela Carberry</name>
      <address>The Charles Perkins Centre, Research and Education Hub D17, Level 6 
The University of Sydney 
NSW, 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 0745  </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>angela.carberry@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>