<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1422">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/10/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/10/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000441516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A multi-site randomised controlled trial comparing regional and general anaesthesia for effects on neurodevelopmental outcome and apnoea in infants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-site randomised controlled trial comparing bupivacaine (regional) anaesthesia versus sevoflurane (general) anaesthesia for effects on neurodevelopmental outcome and apnoea in infants scheduled for unilateral or bilateral inguinal hernia repair</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>GAS Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NCT00756600</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infant scheduled for unilateral or bilateral inguinal hernia repair</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>General anaesthesia: sevoflurane (intervention drug) for induction and maintenance of general anaesthesia, dose up to 8% inspired for duration of procedure (approx 45 minutes)plus bupivacaine local anaesthetic blockade (up to 2.5 mg per kg) administered via caudal or ilioinguinal nerve block.                                                                                                                    Regional anaesthesia: up to 2.5 mg/kg bupivacaine administered by caudal or subarachnoid routes or both caudal and subarachnoid or subarachnoid and ilioinguinal nerve blockade.                                                        Single shot.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator treatment is regional anaesthesia (either: spinal block alone, 
spinal and caudal block, spinal and ilioinguinal block, caudal block alone) with bupivacaine to be administered by caudal and/or subarachnoid routes at the beginning of the surgical procedure.  Spinal dose: 0.2 ml/kg 0.5% bupivacaine. Caudal dose: 2.5 mg/kg bupivacaine.  The duration lasts for approximately 90 minutes.  Patients are observed for up to 12 hours (if they are in hospital) and parents are telephoned a week after the procedure to see how their child is recovering.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be the Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence - Third Edition (WPPSI-III) full Scale IQ score. This scale will be used to determine whether different types of anaesthesia (Regional vs General) given to infants undergoing inguinal hernia repair results in equivalent neurodevelopmental outcomes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 5 years corrected age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bayley neurodevelopmental scale. Investigators will also monitor and record heart rate, respiration and oxygen saturation post anaesthesia in order to measure the frequency and characteristics of apnoea in the post-operative period after both regional and general anaesthesia for inguinal hernia repair in infants for up to 12 hours post anaesthesia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years corrected age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Any infant scheduled for unilateral or bilateral inguinal hernia repair (with or without circumcision) * Any infant whose gestational age is 26 weeks or more (GA = 182 days)* Any infant whose post-menstrual age is up to 60 weeks  (PMA = 426 days)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>26</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Any child older than 60 weeks post menstrual age * Any child born at less than 26 weeks gestation * Any contraindication to general or spinal/caudal anaesthesia (for example: neuromuscular disorder or coagulopathy)* Pre-operative ventilation immediately prior to surgery* Congenital heart disease that has required surgery or will require surgery or which requires ongoing pharmacotherapy* Known chromosomal abnormality or any other known acquired or congenital abnormalities (apart from prematurity) which are likely to affect development* Children where follow-up would be difficult for geographic or social reasons* Families where English (or French for Paris and Montreal sites) is not the language spoken at home* Known neurological injury such as cystic periventricular leukomalacia (PVL), or grade 3 or 4 intra ventricular haemorrhage (IVH) (+/- post haemorrhage ventricular dilatation)* Previous exposure to volatile anaesthesia or benzodiazepines as a neonate or in the third trimester in utero.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Access to randomisation codes will be via a password protected 24 hour web-based randomisation service.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation sequence is generated by computerised sequence generation. Randomisation to either group will be by block and stratified by site and gestational age at birth. Gestational age at birth strata will be: 26 weeks to 29 weeks and 6 days, 30 weeks to 36 weeks and 6 days, 37 weeks and more.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The assessing psychologist will be blinded to treatment allocation. This study is a multisite trial and recruitment will take place in Melbourne, Adelaide, Brisbane, Perth, Auckland, Boston, Chicago, Washington, Montreal, Glasgow, Bristol, Birmingham, Belfast, Sheffield, Liverpool, and Paris</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/10/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/02/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>20/12/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/01/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>720</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>722</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3052</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Scotland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Andrew Davidson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Mary Ellen McCann</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Anesthesiology
Perioperative and Pain Medicine
Children's Hospital Boston
300 Longwood Avenue
Boston MA 02115-5737</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Neil Morton</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Royal Hospital for Sick Children
Yorkhill
Glasgow G3 8SJ</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the GAS study is to determine whether different types of anaesthesia (Spinal Vs General) given to 660 infants undergoing inguinal hernia repair results in equivalent neurodevelopmental outcomes. The study also aims to describe the incidence of apnoea in the post-operative period after both spinal and general anaesthesia for inguinal hernia repair in infants. This study is important as it will provide the greatest evidence for safety or toxicity of general anaesthesia for human infants.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Davidson AJ, Morton NS, Arnup SJ, de Graaff JC, Disma N, Withington DE, Frawley G, Hunt RW, Hardy P, Khotcholava M, von Ungern Sternberg BS, Wilton N, Tuo P, Salvo I, Ormond G, Stargatt R, Locatelli BG, McCann ME; General Anesthesia compared to Spinal anesthesia (GAS) Consortium. Apnea after Awake Regional and General Anesthesia in Infants: The General Anesthesia Compared to Spinal Anesthesia Study-Comparing Apnea and Neurodevelopmental Outcomes, A Randomized Controlled Trial. Anesthesiology. 2015 Jul;123(1):38-54.. 

Frawley G, Bell G, Disma N, Withington DE, de Graaff JC, Morton NS, McCann ME, Arnup SJ, Bagshaw O, Wolfler A, Bellinger D, Davidson AJ; General Anesthesia compared to Spinal anesthesia (GAS) Consortium. Predictors of Failure of Awake Regional Anesthesia for Neonatal Hernia Repair: Data from the General Anesthesia Compared to Spinal Anesthesia Study-Comparing Apnea and Neurodevelopmental Outcomes. Anesthesiology. 2015 Jul;123(1):55-65.

Davidson AJ, Disma N, de Graaff JC, Withington DE, Dorris L, Bell G, Stargatt R, Bellinger DC, Schuster T, Arnup SJ, Hardy P, Hunt RW, Takagi MJ, Giribaldi G, Hartmann PL, Salvo I, Morton NS, von Ungern Sternberg BS, Locatelli BG, Wilton N, Lynn A, Thomas JJ, Polaner D, Bagshaw O, Szmuk P, Absalom AR, Frawley G, Berde C, Ormond GD, Marmor J, McCann ME; GAS consortium. Neurodevelopmental outcome at 2 years of age after general anaesthesia and awake-regional anaesthesia in infancy (GAS): an international multicentre, randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2016 Jan 16;387(10015):239-50

Davidson AJ, Disma N, de Graaff JC, Withington DE, McCann ME. The GAS trial - Authors' reply. Lancet. 2016 Apr 16;387(10028):1615.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/11/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>26135</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Clinical Investigation Office, Children's Hospital Boston</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>333 Longwood Avenue
4th floor
Boston MA 02115-5737</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06-07-0320</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>West Glasgow Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>West Research Office
Administration Building
Ground Floor
Room 9
Western Infirmary
Glasgow G11 6NT</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07/S0709/20</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>United Kingdom</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Davidson </name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia 
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road 
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455233</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93456003</fax>
      <email>andrew.davidson@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Davidson</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia 
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road 
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455233</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93456003</fax>
      <email>andrew.davidson@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Suzette Sheppard</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia Royal Children's Hospital Flemington Road Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455233</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93456003</fax>
      <email>suzette.sheppard@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Davidson</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia Royal Children's Hospital Flemington Road Parkville VIC 3052 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455233 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93456003 </fax>
      <email>andrew.davidson@rch.org.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>