<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372980">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000873325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Evaluation of Holyoake's Methamphetamine Programs In Reducing Drug-Related Harms</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Evaluation of Holyoake's Methamphetamine Programs In Reducing Drug-Related Harms In Adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Methamphetamine dependnence</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Drug-related harms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Those in the intervention arm will receive counselling based on cognitive behaviour therapy (drawing on the approaches of Baker et al 2003 A Brief Cognitive Behavioural Intervention for Regular Amphetamine Users and Lee et al 2007 Turning Point clinical guidelines on Methamphetamine dependence and treatment). The intervention is delivered face-to-face and is a combination of individual counselling and / or group counselling sessions. The program will typically offer weekly contact, with 60 minute sessions as required, although initial sessions may be shorter if the cognitive deficits commonly found during methamphetamine withdrawal necessitate shorter sessions. The first 4 sessions are based on the Baker 2003 manual and cover commitment to change, coping with cravings, controlling thoughts and relapse prevention. Subsequent sessions have greater flexibly based on client needs. The total number of sessions will be based on the counsellors experience and clients requirements, with the expected minimum duration of treatment being 1 month to a maximum of 6 months.
Assertive follow-up occurs in standard care for those who opt to receive this: in the new intervention, assertive follow-up is a constituent part of the new intervention and will be used to contact those who relapse or drop out of treatment early. Staff will attempt to contact clients after any missed sessions both through their own telephone number and also numbers of family members provided by the client as contact points.
Those in the intervention arm, but not the control group, will also be offered and have access to additional services facilitated. These include an in-house clinician (GP) and clinical nurse with alcohol and other drug expertise to treat both general health and specific drug related problems. Holyoake will also undertake intensive case management to link people with other key services such as accommodation, legal and employment services as required. All of these additional services will be offered as required, based on the individual decision of the counsellor and client during treatment. Peer- and family-support workers will also be available outside counselling sessions to encourage engagement with the service and to model self-advocacy and empowerment. Family support workers provide these services to family and significant others of the client. 
Other than the number and type of sessions, plus use of additional services, fidelity of intervention content is not evaluated. However, clinical review of cases by the counselling team will occur after session 4 to consider the progress to date and future direction for each case plus any other services required.  Each client is subsequently reviewed every 4-6 weeks thereafter.
Counselling is delivered in a clinic setting. All counsellors (in both the active and control arms) have relevant tertiary qualifications (e.g. Psychology, Counselling, Social Work) and are experienced alcohol and other drug counsellors.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control - participants receive treatment as usual which is a combination of individual counselling and / or group counselling sessions. Counsellors draw on a range of established therapeutic approaches including motivational interviewing, CBT and social learning theory delivered typically over 6 to 12 sessions of about 60 minutes per session. Sessions are typically delivered once per week, with the exact number of sessions determined by clinical need assessed by the counsellor and client.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is the change in the  number of symptoms endorsed under stimulant related problems in the Composite International Diagnostic Interview. Reference period "last 30 days"</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Kessler-10 score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Family Assessment Device score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in scores on the Personal Wellbeing Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the Alcohol, Smoking and Substance Involvement Screening Test score (items on last 3 months use)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Descriptive data on major adverse events. These data will include details on hospital admissions, emergency department presentations and deaths.
NB  Assessing the WA Data Linkage System requires a second consent from study participants: these data will only be available for those who give this second consent.. 
NB Funding has yet to be obtained for this outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to 12 months (all events over this period)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-esteem (single item 5 point likert scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in social indicators: Housing  status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months
(study specific question
Has your housing situation
	Got better	1
	Stayed the same	2
	Got worse	3)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in social indicators: employment
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months
(study specific question
Has your employment situation
	Got better	1
	Stayed the same	2
	Got worse	3)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in social indicators: financial status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and six months 
(study specific question
Has your financial situation
	Got better	1
	Stayed the same	2
	Got worse	3)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for entry into the research project, participants must be aged 18 years or older or if aged 16-17 years can enter the study with just their consent if they have been deemed as mature minors by Juvenile Justice. In addition, they must report methamphetamine as their primary drug of concern or significant methamphetamine use disclosed during initial counselling sessions, have either a mobile phone, a landline phone or arrange telephone access at clinic. Clients must be new to the service or not have received service from Holyoake in the last one month. Due to the difficulty of retaining them in treatment and research, not currently experiencing acute mental health issues..</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not currently receiving key types of pharmacotherapy (e.g. naltrexone, bupropion/Zyban, modafinil, or mirtazapine which are currently under investigation for methamphetamine dependence), or receiving any other treatment for stimulant use (e.g. alcohol or other drug counselling from another service). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>There is no effective concealment. Participants are recruited at separate clinics.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable, based on study site.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Intervention participants are drawn from one clinical site: control participants from two clinical sites in the same geographical region.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The main analyses will use a multi-level mixed effects regression model with a random intercept term. This will control for clustering of variance within individuals over the repeated measures and clinic site. The main analysis will assess the group (new versus standard program) by time (baseline, 4 week and 6 months) change in i) CIDI score and ii) change in K-10 score.
The sample size was determined for 3 time points (baseline, 1 and 6 months) to test a between group (new versus standard program) interaction. Using G power, with a small to medium effect size (f=0.15), alpha 0.05, to achieve a power of 0.8 requires a total of 74 people. However, because of the clustered design, the effective sample size is reduced. If we recruited 120 people across the three clusters with an intra cluster correlation of 0.01, the effective sample size would be equivalent to a study with 75 people. In terms of K-10 scores this equates to a difference in means of 3 (SD=8).

However, some outcomes, such as change in employment status or housing status may be rare and will probably just be presented as descriptive data: if possible, we will model these outcomes using generalized estimating equations with multinomial logistic regression (e.g. improved: stable: declined). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>9</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Holyoake Northam - Northam</hospital>
    <hospital>Holyoake Merredin - Merredin</hospital>
    <hospital>Holyoake Narrogin - Narrogin</hospital>
    <postcode>6401 - Northam</postcode>
    <postcode>6415 - Merredin</postcode>
    <postcode>6312 - Narrogin</postcode>
    <postcode>6510 - Moora</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kent Street, Bentley, Perth, Western Australia 6102
Postal address
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Australian Primary Health Alliance</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 2-5 
7 Tanunda Drive, 
Rivervale WA 6103 
P.O Box 591, Belmont WA 6984 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to evaluate an evidence based approach to the design of a new treatment service for users of methamphetamine. Traditionally, services were designed for heroin or alcohol using clients who have different treatment needs and problems to methamphetamine users. Holyoake will implement an intensive case management model including medical, peer and family support for methamphetamine users at one site (Northam) but will offer its standard service at other regional sites (Narrogin and Merredin). We will compare outcomes for the new and standard programs (target to recruit 120 people in total) in terms of changes in substance use, mental health, wellbeing and social indicators (i.e. employment and housing status). Participants will be followed up by telephone at 4 weeks and 6 months and by record linkage at 12 months. We hypothesize that those receiving the intensive intervention will show greater improvement in key measures that the standard care group. We also plan telephone interviews with a close family member (e.g. partner, parent) to evaluate improved wellbeing for that person.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication>none</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Postcodes listed are indicative of the target area and not an exhaustive list - e.g. these are not part of the exclusion criteria.
We also plan to interviewing a significant other (e.g. family member or partner) of each participant to assess change in K-10, Personal wellbeing, Family assessment device and self-esteem scores at baseline, 4 weeks and 6 months.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kent Street, Bentley, Perth, Western Australia 6102
Postal address
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>approval recived</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert tait</name>
      <address>National Drug Research Institute
7 Parker Place, Building 609 level 2, Technology Park, Bentley, WA 6102
Post
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892661610</phone>
      <fax>+61892661611</fax>
      <email>robert.tait@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Tait</name>
      <address>National Drug Research Institute
7 Parker Place, Building 609 level 2, Technology Park, Bentley, WA 6102
Post
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892661610</phone>
      <fax>+61892661611</fax>
      <email>robert.tait@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Tait</name>
      <address>National Drug Research Institute
7 Parker Place, Building 609 level 2, Technology Park, Bentley, WA 6102
Post
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892661610</phone>
      <fax>+61892661611</fax>
      <email>robert.tait@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Tait</name>
      <address>National Drug Research Institute
7 Parker Place, Building 609 level 2, Technology Park, Bentley, WA 6102
Post
GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892661610</phone>
      <fax>+61892661611</fax>
      <email>robert.tait@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>