<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366130">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000408684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Gum Elastic Bougie vs The Frova Airway Intubating Catheter when using the Glidescope for difficult intubation

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of Portex tracheal tube and Frova intubating introducers used with the GlideScope videolaryngoscope in simulated difficult intubation on intubation time (s) and success rate (%) in patients with American Society of Anaesthesiologists (ASA) grade 1 or 2 physical status who required tracheal intubation for elective surgery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Difficult intubation
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: After standardised intravenous induction, cervical manual in-line stabilisation was performed to increase intubation difficulty. Intubation was performed under GlideScope videolaryngoscopy assisted by either the PTTI or the FII.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Two types of bougies are commonly used in our adult anaesthetic practice: the Frova intubating introducer (FII) (Cook Medical Inc., Bloomington, IN, USA) and Portex tracheal tube introducer (PTTI) (Smiths Medical International Ltd, Kent, UK). They facilitate placement of endotracheal tubes with an internal diameter greater than 6 mm. The FII is a single-use 14-French 70-cm-long semi-rigid hollow tube with an angulated tip. With the appropriate adapter, it is also used as a temporary ventilatory device during tracheal tube exchange. The PTTI is a 15-French 60-cm-long reusable solid catheter with an external diameter of 5 mm and an angulated tip . To date, no comparative studies of these devices have been performed in videolaryngoscopy-guided intubation. The aim of this study was to compare the PTTI and FII used with the GlideScope videolaryngoscope in simulated difficult intubation
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome criteria were intubation time .

Intubation time (s) was calculated from the time required to obtain a laryngeal view to the time when the upstroke of the capnographic trace was obtained. </outcome>
      <timepoint> If the pre-determined time limit of 3 min or oxygen saturation below 94% was reached. The patient was then ventilated by using the bag-mask technique and intubated without manual inline stabilaisation (MILS). This situation was considered to be failed intubation, but the intubation time was included in the subsequent analysis.

primary outcome was assessed on successful completion of intubation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>success rate of intubation (%). 

correct placement endotracheal intubation confirmed by capnography.
</outcome>
      <timepoint> Successful completion of intubation confirmed by Capnography trace obtained on the monitor</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Difficulty in intubation was assessed by the operator using both a visual analogue scale (VAS) ranging from 0 (easy) to 100 mm (very difficult) and an ordinal scale ranging from 1 (easy) to 4 (very difficult). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary outcome measures were VAS and ordinal scores. Assessed immediately after completion of intubation by the operator.

Difficulty in intubation was assessed by the operator using both a visual analogue scale (VAS) ranging from 0 (easy) to 100 mm (very difficult) and an ordinal scale ranging from 1 (easy) to 4 (very difficult).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The recruited patients required tracheal intubation for elective surgery and had American Society of Anaesthesiologists (ASA) grade 1 or 2 physical status</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those with known or suspected difficult intubation, cervical spine injury, raised intracranial pressure, risk of pulmonary aspiration, and risk of rapid oxygen desaturation were excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment> opening the opaque sealed envelope just before the intubation </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using opaque sealed envelope  contained  treatment allocation group. The envelope was opened just before intubation for allocation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The required sample size was calculated by power analysis of the expected intergroup difference in intubation time of 10 s. This duration was considered to represent a clinically meaningful difference that would justify use of one type of bougie over the other. No consensus has been reached on a clinically significant difference in intubation time; other authors chose cut-off points ranging from 5 to 30 s or a 33% reduction in intubation time. Non-parametric analysis was used to compare differences in intubation time and difficulty (MannWhitney U-test) with standard type I and type II error rates (alpha = 0.05, Beta = 0.20). Fisher's exact test was used to compare intubation success rates between the groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/08/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/07/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/07/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Palvannan Sivalingam,</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd
Woolloongabba , Qld 4102
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Anaesthetic department research fund, Princess Alexandra Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd
Woolloongabba , Qld 4102
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NIL</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: A bougie may be less traumatic than the GlideScope-specific intubating stylet during videolaryngoscopy-guided intubation, but no comparative studies of bougies have been performed.
Objective: To compare the Portex tracheal tube introducer (PTTI) and Frova intubating introducer (FII) used with the GlideScope videolaryngoscope in simulated difficult intubation.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NIL</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NIL</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>NIL</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>PAH HREC (presently called Metro South HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd
Woolloongabba , Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/057</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Palvannan Sivalingam</name>
      <address>Senior Consultant Anaesthetist
Department of Anaesthesia
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich road
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 418793209</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31765102</fax>
      <email>Palvannans@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Palvannan Sivalingam</name>
      <address>Senior Consultant Anaesthetist
Department of Anaesthesia
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich road
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 418793209</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31765102</fax>
      <email>Palvannans@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Palvannan Sivalingam</name>
      <address>Senior Consultant Anaesthetist
Department of Anaesthesia
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich road
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 418793209</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31765102</fax>
      <email>Palvannans@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Palvannan Sivalingam</name>
      <address>Senior Consultant Anaesthetist
Department of Anaesthesia
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich road
Woolloongabba, Brisbane
Qld 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 418793209</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31765102</fax>
      <email>Palvannans@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>