<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369208">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000991516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial of Hypnosis and Mindfulness for Acute Burn Pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Burns Patient use of Hypnosis and Mindfulness for Pain Experience</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Burn pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Hypnosis Recording: The recording is approximately 25 minutes long and is based on a technique called Rapid Induction Analgesia (RIA), first proposed by Barber (1977). The script uses several hypnotic techniques to create a state of deep relaxation and receptivity, making the patient open to suggestions about their pain experience. Participants will listen to the recording 5 times and then they will listen to it again twice more, both during their next two dressing changes. Patients will have 2-4 days to listen to the recordings and will listen to them once or twice each day, according to their choice and the time they have available. The dressing changes will be 24 hrs apart. The procedure will take between 30 and 90 minutes depending on the nature of the burn injury. A nurse will assist participants to schedule listening to the recording and will ask them how many times they have done so. 

Mindfulness Recording: This recording is also approximately 25 minutes long. It is based on the Body Scan practice developed by Jon Kabat-Zinn (1982). The script uses instructions for noticing different aspects of present-moment experiencing with a focus on the breath and different parts of the body. Participants will listen to the recording 5 times and then they will listen to it again twice more, both during their next two dressing changes. Patients will have 2-4 days to listen to the recordings and will listen to them once or twice each day, according to their choice and the time they have available. The dressing changes will be 24 hrs apart. The procedure will take between 30 and 90 minutes depending on the nature of the burn injury. A nurse will assist participants to schedule listening to the recording and will ask them how many times they have done so. </interventions>
    <comparator>2 active control conditions will be used. 

One will be a "distraction" condition where the participant will listen to an audio book 5 times and then they will listen to it twice more, during two dressing changes. Patients will choose from a selection of adventure, romance, comedy, science fiction and drama genres. All books will be screened for traumatizing material.

One will be a "treatment as usual" condition where the participant will receive usual care while listening to recorded music during dressing changes. 

Measurements will also be taken during one dressing change prior to any intervention/control condition, to act as a baseline measure for all participants.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Intensity
Assessed using Visual Analogue Scales and the McGill Pain Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before, during, after dressing change 
1. Immediately prior to the dressing change
2. 15 minutes into the procedure
3. Within 1 minute of the end of each dressing change procedure
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety
Assessed by Visual Analogue Scales and the State Trait Anxiety Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before, during, after dressing changes.
1. Immediately prior to the dressing change
2. 15 minutes into the procedure
3. Within 1 minute of the end of each dressing change procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication consumption
Assessed by review of hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>From start of procedure until 2 hours post end of procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in catastrophizing frequency
Assessed using the Pain Catastrophizing Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measure taken when the person consents to participate in the study and then immediately after the second post-surgery dressing change</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult - over 18
Burn injury that requires surgery
1-20% TBSA</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Intellectual disability
Psychotic disorders
Extreme emotional distress
Deafness
Muteness
Substance use withdrawal
Non-English speaking</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be approached within 48 hours of their admission by the lead researcher, Kathryn James, who will discuss the project, answer any questions and obtain written consent. 

Participants will then complete a series of questionnaires that assess thinking styles and emotional state. They will then be allocated to a treatment condition by an associate investigator so that the lead researcher is blind to their allocation. The lead researcher will collect outcome measures during the dressing changes. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Results will be analysed using repeated measures ANOVA to investigate the efficacy of the hypnosis and mindfulness conditions and correlation calculations to investigate the relationship between different thinking styles, emotional state and outcome variables. 

Sample size was calculated using a G Power program, with power set at 0.8, p-value of 0.05 and effect size at 0.2. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>152</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Suspended</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fiona Wood Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Fiona Stanley Hospital
Level 4, Burns Outpatient Clinic
11 Warren Smith Drive
Murdoch 6150 WA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>90 South Street
Murdoch 6150 WA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fiona Stanley Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>11 Warren Smith Drive 
Murdoch 6150 WA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Burn injuries and treatment often cause excruciating pain for patients. Hypnosis and mindfulness have demonstrated benefits in treating pain in addition to pharmacological pain management. However, psychological pain management techniques are not currently used in standard pain management protocols on burns units. 

Audio recordings could be an efficient way for patients to access these treatments, and nurses may be well-positioned to assist patients to use them, as they spend more time with the patient than other clinicians and are usually present during wound dressing changes. 

The aims of this project are:

1. To explore the feasibility of using audio recordings of hypnosis and mindfulness as an adjunct to pharmacological treatment of burn pain. 
2. To explore the feasibility of nurses assisting with the administration of hypnosis and mindfulness recordings. 
3. To explore personality variables, such as trait anxiety, that may influence how people are able to benefit from hypnosis and mindfulness. 

Adults over 18 years of age who are admitted to the burns unit with an injury that requires surgery will be screened and those who are eligible will be invited to participate in the study. 

Participants will complete 5 questionnaires (30-45 minutes total time to complete) that ask about anxiety, thoughts about pain, how in control the person feels and imaginative experience. Then pain, anxiety and relaxation will be measured for all patients during a dressing change to give baseline information. Then patients in 2 experimental groups will be asked to listen to a 25 minute recording of hypnosis or mindfulness 5 times to practice before using the recording in 2 further dressing changes. Those in one control group will listen to an audio book 5 times before continuing to use it in 2 further dressing changes, and those in a second control group will receive standard care while listening to recorded music during their dressing changes. During the dressing changes patients will be asked to rate their pain, anxiety and relaxation experience. Nurses will administer the recordings. 

The experiment will follow a repeated-measures between groups design, which means that pain, anxiety and relaxation ratings and personality measures can be compared between the groups before and after treatment. 

Results will provide information about the benefits of hypnosis and mindfulness audio recordings for patients on the burns unit, and the feasibility of using nurses to administer these. They will also provide valuable information about personality variables that influence how well someone will benefit from either treatment, which will assist with treatment planning. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WA Department of Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Harry Perkins Institute
11 Warren Smith Drive
Murdoch 6150 WA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15-140</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn James</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Exercise Science
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch 6150 WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 458620032</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate@go.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn James</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Exercise Science
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch 6150 WA</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 458620032</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate@go.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn James</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Exercise Science
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch 6150 WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 458620032</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate@go.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn James</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Exercise Science
Murdoch University
90 South Street 
Murdoch 6150 WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 458620032</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kate@go.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>