<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369645">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000406404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving Magnetic Seizure Therapy in Major Depressive Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Clinical Trial comparing two alternate forms of Magnetic Seizure Therapy for major depressive disorder</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Treatment Resistant Major Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Magnetic Seizure Therapy (MST).

MST uses magnetic stimulation to induce a seizure for therapeutic purposes. Magnetic stimulation is a non invasive technique for stimulating neural tissue. A rapid change in magnetic field induces a current in the neural tissue. If the current is of sufficient amplitude and duration it will excite nerve tissues.

All patients will initially undergo a dose titration procedure to establish their convulsive stimulation threshold. Single stimulation trains will be applied at 25 Hz to the prefrontal cortex. 

Patients will undergo a maximum of 15 treatment sessions over approximately 5 weeks. Treatment will be administered a psychiatric medical registrar with an anesthetist present. Number of treatment sessions will be determined by Professor Paul Fitzgerald (CI) on the basis of consultation with participant regarding their wishes and mental state. 

Stimulation is applied using the Magstim Magnetic Seziure Therapy device. Treatment duration is between 20-30 mins. Each treatment will be recorded (date, time of treatment and duration) by a research nurse.</interventions>
    <comparator>Magnetic Seizure Therapy (MST).

All patients will initially undergo a dose titration procedure to establish their convulsive stimulation threshold. Single stimulation trains will be at 100 Hz to the vertex.

Patients will undergo a maximum of 15 treatment sessions over approximately 5 weeks.

Stimulation is applied using the Magstim Magnetic Seziure Therapy device. Treatment duration is between 20-30 mins.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antidepressant effect.

Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)

Response is defined as a reduction of at least 50% from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>MADRS will be assessed at baseline, weekly during treatment, at treatment end, and for responders at 2, 4 and 6 months following treament end.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive side effects.

A comprehensive cogntive battery will be administered. The battery will include the Autobiographical Memory Interview, Rey Verbal Auditory Learning Test , Verbal Paired Associates (WMS-R), Logical Memory (WMS-III), and the Brief Visual Spatial Memory Test. We will also include a number of assessments of information processing, i.e. Digit Span, Digit Symbol Coding, and Trail Making Test. Finally, we will look at general intellectual functioning (Wechsler Test of Adult Reading), as well as aspects of executive functioning and language (Rey Complex Figure Test, Stroop, Verbal Fluency and Boston Naming Test). 

Post treatment Orientation will also be assessed. Patients will be repeatedly asked to provide their name, date of birth, age, place and day of week. Orientation will be considered to be present when the patient provides correct answers to 4 of these questions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Cognitive battery will be administered at baseline and endpoint. Endpoint will be post 12 or 15 treatments, the total number of treatments is dependent on consultation by psychiatrist and participant)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Electrovestibulography (EVestG)

EVestG measures neural responses via probes placed in the ear canal.  It involves having an electrode placed in the ear which measures brain activity while the participant sits in a chair that is slowly being tilted forward and back as well as side to side. 

This assessment will allow us to investigate whether MST results in changes in brain activity. </outcome>
      <timepoint>EVestG will be conducted at baseline and following treatment 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 18-75 and a DSM-IV diagnosis of a major depressive episode (uni or bipolar depression) (diagnosis made using the standard structured clinical interview for the DSM-IV (SCID I) instrument). Patients with psychotic symptoms as part of their mood episode will not be excluded if able to give informed consent.

?Montgomery Asberg depression rating scale (MADRS) score of &gt; 20(moderate  severe depression). 

Have treatment resistant depression at Stage II of the Thase and Rush classification. This requires failure to respond to adequate courses of several courses of antidepressants. 

Demonstrated capacity to give informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are too unwell to undergo general anesthetic.  

Patients with metallic implants in the head, cardiac pacemakers, cochlear implants or other implanted  electronic devices

Treatment with ECT in the last two months 

Presence of another DSM-IV Axis I psychiatric disorder (on MINI) other than bipolar disorder

Presence of substance abuse or dependence during the last six months 

Current pregnancy

Past history of stroke, neurodegenerative disorder or other major neurological illness 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment occurs through central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Individuals are randomized (single non stratified sequence) via a computer-generated list</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Paul Fitzgerald</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre (MAPrc): Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alfred Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>55 Commercial Road
PO Box 315 Prahran
Victoria 3181 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this project is to investigate whether an optimised form of Magnetic Seizure Therapy (MST) is a successful treatment for patients with treatment resistant depression compared to the standard form of MST that has been used to date. MST involves the induction of a seizure for therapeutic purposes.  It is similar to electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) but with MST the seizure is induced through the use of magnetic stimulation rather than direct electrical currents as occurs with ECT.  By avoiding the use of direct electrical current when inducing the seizure, it is thought that MST will result in an improvement in depressive symptoms whilst reducing memory related side effects (i.e. difficulties in remembering recent events) which can occur with ECT.  

The standard from of MST that has been investigated to date is 100Hz MST to the vertex, or the motor area of the brain. 100Hz MST has been shown to improve depression in some people and to not have any of the memory side effects often seen with ECT.  We will be comparing this form of MST to 25Hz MST to the prefrontal cortex, or the front part of the brain to investigate whether this type of MST results in greater improvement in depression than the 100Hz MST. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research &amp; Ethics Unit
Linay Pavilion

55 Commercial Road
PO Box 315 Prahran
Victoria 3181 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>485/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>MAPrc Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 6552</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8545</fax>
      <email>paul.fitzgerald@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>MAPrc Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 6552</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8545</fax>
      <email>paul.fitzgerald@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>MAPrc Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 6552</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8545</fax>
      <email>paul.fitzgerald@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kate Hoy</name>
      <address>MAPrc Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 5034</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8545</fax>
      <email>kate.hoy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>