<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347514">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001027909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes in the portal flow after Heiling`s pumping technique of liver  to individuals with hemorrhoid syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Changes in the portal flow after Heiling's pumping technique of liver to 50 individuals with hemorrhoid syndrome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1124-7285</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nill</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hemorrhoids</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Portal flow</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Two groups: patients with hemorrhoidal syndrome is submitted to the pumping technique of the liver (Group 1) and patients with syndrome hemorrhoidal those who perform a maneuver placeblo (Group 2):

Group 1:
Subject position: supine (Tredelemburg) with knees bent
Position of Therapist: Standing at the patient's left, at the height of the abdomen.

Hand position:
The left hand goes below the costal margin to lift the chest wall
The right hand rests on the lower right side of the chest to compress the liver through the chest wall.

Running technique
The bottom hand up the ribs while the top has a compression
The manipulation is done by following the movement
breathing. In this study technique asking the patient to breathe deeply, during expiration to compress costal with our hands and let our contacts deep breath.
Be repeated for 10 respiratory cycles, the technique will last for 2 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2: Maneuver placebo: Ask the patient to breathe, our lower and upper hand accompany respiratory motion without exerting any pressure on the rib cage.
Be repeated for 10 respiratory cycles, the technique will last for 2 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Demonstrate the variation of portal venous flow after technical
liver pumping hemorrhoidal syndrome Doppler ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine differences vertebrae algometer pre and postintervention. Using a pressure algometer to measure pain intensity in the cervical and thoracic spinous processes.
The algometer is a measuring device calibrated with a pressure of 1 cm2 circular base, so that measurements are given in Kg/cm2 or Newton (Nw)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and women aged between 18 and 65.
Subjects diagnosed with hemorrhoids.
Tolerating supine.
Informed consent signed.
Do not meet any criteria for exclusion</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects with recent rib fractures who can not tolerate compression matter.
Pregnant women.
Cancer primitive or metastatic.
Intra-abdominal infection or inflammation in acute appendicitis, acute cholecystitis and hepatitis, gastrointestinal bleeding.
Polycystic liver or heart hepatobiliar.
Chronic liver disease of any cause: jaundice, hepatomegaly,
splenomegaly, portal hypertension.
Heart failure descompensada.
liver transplantation.
Subjects with chemotherapy and / or radiotherapy.
Subjects with psychotic problems.
Abdominal circumference greater than 88 cm in women and 102 cm in the man.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This trial is is randomised controlled trial. 
Participants who meet the inclusion criteria were divided into groups through random sampling sealed envelope.  Will be prepared "X" envelopes, which half will be the number 1 and half the number 2. Are mixed, and participants randomly removed, being removed from the rest chosen on envelopes. Be so formed two groups: an intervention group and a control group.</concealment>
    <sequence>This trial use simple randomisation. Are mixed, and participants randomly removed, being removed from the rest chosen on envelopes. Be so formed two groups: an intervention group and a control group.
Ultimately obtained two groups: patients with hemorrhoidal syndrome is submitted to the pumping technique of the liver (Group 1) and patients with syndrome hemorrhoidal those who perform a maneuver placebo (Group 2)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A randomized clinical trial, ie an experimental study
intervention and random assignment (randomized) prospective,
longitudinal.
It aims to conduct a randomized clinical trial design
explanatory in nature, so experimental, triple blind, blind.
The masking technique used is the triple-blind
assessor blind strategy, the individual in any known
technique or group membership control or intervention, and
as the statistic ignores the subject's group assignment. On the other hand, there is any relationship between the evaluator and the
controller, giving this area more strength to the study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Elena Sonsoles Rodriguez L0pez</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/ La zarza,20
Casarrubios del Monte
45950 Toledo</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hitachi</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sistemas integrales Medica. S.a.
Avda. Sistema Solar, 25
San Fernando de Henares
28030  Madrid</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hitachi</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sistemas integrales Medica. S.a.
Avda. Sistema Solar, 25
San Fernando de Henares
28030  Madrid</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Spain</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>For this study subjects were taken hemorrhoidal syndrome. Through ultrasound flow measurement algometry portal and the thoracic and cervical intended objectify the impact of pumping technique on liver portal flow.
So our hypothesis is that the osteopathic treatment of liver improves the speed of the portal vein flow, measured Doppler ultrasound, and modifies the tenderness of the vertebra cervical thoracic and correspondence, as measured algometry pressure.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Escuela de Osteopatia de Madrid</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/Saturnino Calleja, 1
28002 Madrid</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>elena rodriguez lopez</name>
      <address>C/ La zarza, 20
Casarrubios del Monte 
45950 Toledo</address>
      <phone>0034-679336394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenasonsolesrodriguez@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Elena rodriguez lopez</name>
      <address>C/ La zarza, 20
Casarrubios del Monte
45950 Toledo</address>
      <phone>0034-679336394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elenasonsolesrodriguez@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>