<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372853">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000857303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Enhanced community case management to increase access to pneumonia treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Enhanced community case management to increase access to pneumonia treatment in children under 5 years of age in sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1196-2094</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EMPIC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute respiratory infections</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pneumonia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In a cluster randomised controlled trial (RCT), in addition to standard Integrated Community Case Mangement (iCCM), (i) young infants 7 to 59 days of age with fast breathing without hypoxaemia and (ii) children 2-59 months of age with chest indrawing without hypoxaemia will be managed by Community Level Health Workers (CLHWs) with oral amoxicillin, 90 mg/kg/day divided into two doses. For this study oral dispersible amoxicillin in 250 mg scored tablets will be used for both age groups. The dispersible tablets would have to be dispersed in clean water and in expressed breast milk for exclusively breastfed young infants. The WHO recommends 5 days of amoxicillin for chest indrawing pneumonia. For young infants less than two months 7 days therapy will be used. The trial strategy will enhance the existing standard iCCM, which currently recommends referral to hospital for these children. Access to pneumonia treatment will be increased to many children whose families cannot access treatment at hospitals due to various reasons. The proposed intervention is to train CLHWs and maintain their skills to manage infants with fast breathing and children with chest indrawing. Commodities including dispensible amoxicillin tables 250 mg, pulse oximeters, and ARI timers will be regularly provided. All enrolled children will be followed up for up to two weeks and their outcomes will be documented by independent assessors.

Before the commencement of original enrolment, 6-8 days standard and enhanced iCCM training will be given to CLHWs in control and intervention clusters, respectively. In standard iCCM training group, CLHWs will be trained on current WHO/UNICEF iCCM. In enhanced iCCM training group, CLHWs will be trained to provide treatment with oral amoxicillin either for 7 days in case of young infants &lt;2 months of age with fast breathing (&gt;=60 breaths per minute) or for 5 days in case of children 2-59 months of age with lower chest indrawing pneumonia. Further, CLHWs will also be trained in pulse oximetry to measure oxygen saturation at the time of enrolment and during subsequent visits. Two day refresher trainings will be provided to all CLHWs every six months during the study period. Training sessions will be conducted by iCCM master trainers at each site. These master trainers have undergone separate trainings under WHO facilitators. 

Pulse oximeters will be provided to all CLHWs in the intervention clusters. They will be trained to assess hypoxaemia in children with pneumonia through standard training and using standard protocols for use and interpretation of pulse oximetry results. Hypoxaemic children will be referred to the hospital for further management including oxygen therapy. In intervention clusters where enhanced iCCM will be provided by CLHWs, feasibility, acceptability and accuracy of pulse oximetry as used by CLHWs will be assessed. Impact on referral rates will also be compared between intervention and control clusters.  The outcomes of all children with signs of pneumonia will be compared between the intervention and control clusters. Outcome will be assessed by independent outcome assessors (nurses) which will be hired and trained to evaluate children on day 6 for primary outcome measure and on day 14 for secondary outcome measure. The total duration of intervention is up to 2 years. 

CLHWs are based at health posts in Ethiopia in community, village clinics in the community in Malawi, at their homes in India and in community clinics in Bangladesh. All enrolled children are treated at their homes except those who are referred to a hospital as per protocol. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>In control clusters, standard iCCM will be implemented for (i) young infants 7-59 days of age with fast breathing without hypoxaemia and (ii) children 2-59 months of age with chest indrawing without hypoxaemia. Sick children will be identified by CLHWs in the community through passive surveillance. All sick young infants will be referred to hospital by CLHW. Children with danger signs will be referred by CLHWs. Supervisors will also review young infants identified by CLHWs with fast breathing and 2-59 months old children with chest indrawing to provide comparative data with the intervention clusters.  All enrolled children in control clusters will be followed up for 14 days. Outcomes for all pneumonia patients receiving treatment in community, health facilities and hospitals will be documented.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment failure rate within day 1-6 of enrolment will be the primary outcome.

Definition of treatment failure
1.	Death at any time within day 1 to day 6 of enrolment (and 7-14 days as secondary outcome).
2.	Child hospitalised for any reason or has any indication of hospitalisation on day 6. 
3.	 Persistence of fast breathing in young infants 7-59 days of age or persistence of chest indrawing in children 2-59 months of age on day 6 of enrolment.
4.	Development of serious adverse effect of the study antibiotics (anaphylactic reaction, severe diarrhoea, disseminated and severe rash).

Outcome will be assessed by independent outcome assessors (nurses) which will be hired and trained to evaluate children on day 6 for primary outcome measure and on day 14 for secondary outcome measure. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome will be assessed at day 6 and for deaths also at day 14 after enrolment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluating the feasibility of using a pulse oximeter by CLHWs. 
We will use indepth qualitative interviews and structure observations to evaluate the feasibility of using a pulse oximeter by CLHWs. In all intervention clusters CLHWs will use pulse oximeter to measure oxygen saturation in young infants &lt;2 months of age with fast breathing and children 2-59 months of age with lower chest indrawing. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be a continuous process to capture information about the feasibility of using a pulse oximeter by CLHW throughout the trial duration. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>In selective districts in Bangladesh, Ethiopia, India and Malawi, first level health facilities (with catchment population of 10,000 to 25,000 each)  will be randomised either to control or intervention arm. All CLHWs attached to the first level health facility will provide treatmentment to the following children based on intervention status (control or intervention):  
- 7-59 days old infants in intervention or control clusters who develop fast breathing (respiratory rate &gt;60 breaths per min).
- 2-59 month old children infants in intervention or control clusters who develop chest indrawing pneumonia. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>7-59 days old infants in intervention and control cluster who develop severe chest indrawing or danger signs or fast breathing in &lt;7 days old young infants and if consent not provided for enrolment for eligible young infants.
2-59 month old children infants in intervention or control clusters who develop danger signs or if consent not provided for enrolment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Cluster will be randomised using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cluster RCT</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size for young infants 7-59 days of age

Assuming that clusters have a population of about 5000 and a birth rate of 3%, each cluster will have about 300 births and therefore 300 young infants over the 2-year study period. It is expected that about 5% of young infants will develop fast breathing during the first two months of life, yielding 15 cases of fast breathing pneumonia per cluster in two years. For sample size calculations, it is assumed that of the above, 10 cases of fast breathing pneumonia among young infants will be enrolled in one cluster. Assuming a 10% treatment failure rate +/- 5% similarity margin, 90% power and 95% confidence level, design effect of 1.2 (ICC 0.02) and attrition of 10%, 990 cases will be needed each in intervention and control clusters, to test non-inferiority of the enhanced iCCM strategy vs. the current standard of care. Since there are 10 expected cases per cluster, 198 clusters (99 clusters per group) for this age group would be required for random allocation.

Sample size for children 2-59 months of age

Assuming that clusters have a population of about 5000 and a birth rate of 3%, each cluster will have about 300 births and around 750 under-five children at any point in time over a two year period. Assuming a pneumonia incidence of 0.25 episodes of pneumonia/child/year, it is expected that there will be about 375 cases of pneumonia among children of 2-59 months of age, of which about 50 will have chest indrawing pneumonia in a cluster (15%) over a two year period. It is assumed that about 30 children with chest indrawing pneumonia would be enrolled. Assuming a 10% treatment failure rate +/-5% similarity margin, 90% power and 95% confidence level, design effect of 1.6 (ICC 0.02) and attrition of 10%, 1340 cases each will be needed in intervention and control clusters to test non-inferiority of the enhanced iCCM strategy vs. the current standard of care. Since there are 30 expected cases per cluster, 90 clusters (45 clusters per group) for this age group would be required for random allocation.

Enrolment of young infants with fast breathing and children 2-59 months of age with chest indrawing will be carried out concurrently by the same CLHWs at all sites. It will be difficult to operationalize a shorter trial for chest indrawing pneumonia although theoretically it is possible. Furthermore, the cost of the trial will not be reduced much as CLHWs will continue to enrol fast breathing pneumonia patients. As the sample size is higher for the young infants (99 clusters per group), we will conduct enrolment of children 2-59 months of age with chest indrawing in all the clusters. This will give us the ability to show non-inferiority with +/-3% margin for the 2-59 months age group. Thus enrolling more patients of chest indrawing pneumonia will provide us with greater precision in assessing the effectiveness of its treatment by CLHWs.

Statistical analyses
Each age group will be powered to perform specific analyses. Secondary analyses will also be performed to look for gross differences between sites, but such analyses will only be able to detect large differences in treatment failure rates between sites. 

Simple comparisons of means and proportions by intervention and control clusters will be used to check whether the randomisation has in fact resulted in baseline comparability of the two comparative groups. The primary analyses will be for non-inferiority between the treatment outcomes such as treatment failure (including deaths and deterioration) between intervention and control clusters. This will be conducted on an intention-to-treat, and would provide the possibility of differences in adherence to treatment. In addition, per protocol analysis will also be done. The treatment outcomes between control and intervention clusters will be compared and the difference in the risk of treatment failure together with a 95% confidence intervals will be calculated. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>4700</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bangladesh</country>
      <state>Barisal</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ethiopia</country>
      <state>Gondar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Haryana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malawi</country>
      <state>Central Region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>World Health Organization</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avenue Appia 20, Geneva 1211</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Switzerland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>500 Fifth Avenue North
Seattle, WA 98109
(206) 709-3100
 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Save the Children International, Bangladesh</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Save the Children, Bangladesh
House no CWN (A) 35, Road No 43, Gulshan  2, Dhaka  1212
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Bangladesh</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Gondar College of Medicine and Health Sciences (CMHS), Gondar, Ethiopia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Gondar College of Medicine and Health Sciences (CMHS), Ethiopia
P.O.Box 196
Gondar,
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Ethiopia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Centre for Health and Research Development, Society for Applied Studies (SAS), New Delhi, India</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Centre for Health and Research Development, Society for Applied Studies (SAS), India
45 Kalu Sarai, New Delhi-110016
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>India</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Save the Children International, Malawi</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Save the Children, Malawi
Ngerengere House, Off Mchinji Road
P.O Box 30374, 
Lilongwe
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malawi</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pneumonia is the number one killer of under-five children. Around 90% of pneumonia deaths in children occur in sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia. Efforts are being made to increase access to good quality care at health facilities in many LMICs, but progress is slow, in particular in Sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia. As a complementary strategy, where access to health facilities is low and referral advice is not usually accepted by families, WHO/UNICEF recommend management of pneumonia, diarrhoea and malaria by community-level health workers (CLHWs) through integrated community case management (iCCM) at the community level. 

The overall goal of the project is to rigorously assess the benefits of an enhanced approach to community case management for pneumonia, contributing to the evidence base for revision of WHO/UNICEF integrated community case management (iCCM) tool and its harmonization with the integrated management of childhood illness (IMCI) tool, and using lessons learned during implementation to help accelerate subsequent program scale-up. The enhanced pneumonia component of iCCM is the standard iCCM approach PLUS

a)	Treatment of chest indrawing pneumonia to children 2-59 months old by CLHWs 
b)	Treatment of fast breathing pneumonia to infants 7-59 days of age by CLHWs
c)	Use of pulse oximetry to identify hypoxaemic infants and children by CLHWs

A cluster randomised open-label non-inferiority trial will be conducted, to enrol young infants 7-59 days of age with fast breathing and children 2-59 months of age with chest indrawing, each in four countries in Africa and Asia. The primary question is whether failure rates of pneumonia treatment with enhanced iCCM strategy are non-inferior to failure rates of pneumonia treatment with standard iCCM strategy.  The trial will have adequate sample size and power to answer the primary study question in each age group. The trial will (i) compare treatment failures of lower chest indrawing pneumonia in 2-59 months old with oral amoxicillin by CLHWs in community to current management at the health facility and (ii) compare treatment failures rates of fast breathing pneumonia in 7-59 days young infants with oral amoxicillin by CLHWs in community to current management at the health facility/hospital. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WHO ERC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Avenue Appia 20, Geneva 1211</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MCA00315</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shamim Ahmad Qazi</name>
      <address>Department of Maternal, Newborn, Child and Adolescent Health
World Health Organization
Avenue Appia 20, Geneva 1211
</address>
      <phone>+41-22-791-2547</phone>
      <fax>+41-22-791-4853 </fax>
      <email>qazis@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shamim Ahmad Qazi</name>
      <address>Department of Maternal, Newborn, Child and Adolescent Health
World Health Organization
Avenue Appia 20, Geneva 1211
</address>
      <phone>+41-22-791-2547</phone>
      <fax>+41-22-791-4853 </fax>
      <email>qazis@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shamim Ahmad Qazi</name>
      <address>Department of Maternal, Newborn, Child and Adolescent Health
World Health Organization
Avenue Appia 20, Geneva 1211</address>
      <phone>+41-22-791-2547</phone>
      <fax>+41-22-791-4853 </fax>
      <email>qazis@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasir Bin Nisar</name>
      <address>Department of Maternal, Newborn, Child and Adolescent Health
World Health Organization
Avenue Appia 20, Geneva 1211
</address>
      <phone>+41-22-791-5595</phone>
      <fax>+41-22-791-4853</fax>
      <email>nisary@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>