<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363720">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000220763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Innovation in stroke rehabilitation: Determining the feasibility and effectiveness of customised active computer games to improve outcomes following stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot investigation of the feasibility and effectiveness of custom-designed active computer games for physical rehabilitation of adult stroke survivors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1138-6629</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase 1: 40 participants will complete one testing session of 40 minutes duration to investigate feasibility and safety of the gaming activities, which utilise a motion-sensing camera and custom-written software. Participants will be randomly assigned to one of four gaming activities. Three of these games primarily involve tracking of hip and shoulder movements to perform actions on the television screen. The remaining game involves tracking of upper limb movements. Participants will work through a protocol of testing which involves using the games in sitting and standing, and through varying levels of difficulty. All sessions will be undertaken on an individual basis under the supervision of a physiotherapist. 

Phase 2: Of these 40 participants, 16 will take part in a randomised study. Phase 2 participants will be recruited consecutively from Phase 1 until 16 participants have been recruited. The intervention group will participate in 8 gaming sessions of 40 minutes duration over a 4 week period, in addition to their usual care. During each session participants may interact with all four gaming activities and sessions will be individualised for each participant with guidance from the supervising therapist. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment.
The control group will continue with usual care for 4 weeks and will attend assessment sessions only. The amount of usual care will be provided on a case-by-case basis as determined by the rehabilitation team. As participants will be recruited from either the inpatient or outpatient therapy services, usual care may vary from one physiotherapy session per week to daily therapy. The amount of standard physiotherapy and occupational therapy attended will be documented.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility. This will include evaluation of recruitment and attrition (screening log and participant flow), gaming activity time, acceptability (5-point Likert scale rating of enjoyment and perceived benefit; and verbal feedback from participants), and safety (11-point VAS rating of pain and fatigue; BORG rating of perceived exertion; and monitoring of adverse events, e.g falls or near misses, and complaints of other symptoms such as dizziness)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recruitment and attrition will be monitored throughout the study. Gaming activity time, acceptability and safety data will be collected during each intervention session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Reach Test. A measure of dynamic balance which evaluates forward reach ability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step Test. A measure of dynamic balance which involves tapping one foot on and off a step.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 minute walk test. A measure of walking endurance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor Assessment Scale. A measure of mobility and upper limb function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Haemorrhagic or ischaemic stroke; 
Able to sit unsupported a minimum of 10 seconds 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Medically unstable or other medical condition or neurological impairment that could confound the results; 
Severe receptive or expressive dysphasia;
Significant cognitive deficit (MMSE &lt;20)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be consecutively sampled by screening all stroke admissions to the inpatient rehabilitation ward and outpatient therapy service. Screening will be undertaken by the ward physiotherapists and a screening registry kept. 
Allocation will be concealed to the research therapists and assessors. The randomisation schedule will be maintained by a therapist not involved in the trial.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Phase 1 (40 participants): Computer generated permuted block randomisation with stratification based on participants Functional Independence Measure (FIM) walking item &gt; 4

Phase 2 (16 participants): Simple randomisation using computerised sequence generation. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In Phase 1 (40 participants), we will describe the population, detail the time spent and number of movement repetitions performed in each game, their view of its acceptability and any safety issues. Non-parametric statistics will be used to explore utility according to functional impairment at time of testing (based on participants Motor Assessment Scale). 

In Phase 2 (16 participants), in addition to the summaries performed in Phase 1, we will describe the participants changes in balance and mobility over the 8 sessions. Independent t-tests or Mann-Whitney U tests will be used to compare normally and non-normally distributed data respectively. Repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be used to compare changes over time and between group changes in data for the outcome measures. The level of significance will be set at 0.05. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/04/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Florey Neuroscience Institiutes</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Brain Centre, 245 Burgundy Street, Heidelburg, VIC 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Stroke Foundation of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7, 461 Bourke Street, Melbourne, VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Melbourne Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park Campus, 34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Current Circus</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Suite 6, 322 St Kilda Road, St Kilda, VIC 3182</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Active gaming technologies are rapidly evolving and increasingly being used in therapeutic environments. The current range of commercially available software is of limited use in the context of stroke rehabilitation. This research study will investigate the safety, feasibility and effectiveness of a suite of customised gaming activities in a stroke population. We hypothesise that the gaming activities will be safe and feasible to use in a stroke population and will improve physical outcomes when used in additional to usual care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research, Level 6 East, Main Building, 300 Grattan St, The Royal Melbourne Hospital, Carlton VIC 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011.210</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kelly Bower</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, The Royal Melbourne Hospital Royal Park Campus, 34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>kelly.bower@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kelly Bower</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, The Royal Melbourne Hospital Royal Park Campus, 34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>kelly.bower@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kelly Bower</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, The Royal Melbourne Hospital Royal Park Campus, 34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>kelly.bower@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kelly Bower</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, The Royal Melbourne Hospital Royal Park Campus, 34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>kelly.bower@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>