<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367105">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001038684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study examining the analgesic effect of ascending buprenorphine doses in opioid dependent people</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study examining the analgesic effect of ascending buprenorphine doses in opioid dependent people</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1161-8062 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Opioid dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Examining the effect of administering a participants usual daily dose of sublingual buprenorphine (range 4-16mg)(in the form of buprenorphine-naloxone) compared with 150% and 200% of the usual daily dose, in buprenorphine maintained participants on experimental pain threshold and tolerance using the cold pressor test. Each dose condition will be tested once (single-dose only). Participants will have three wash out days in between each study session. To maintain the blind participants will receive the balance of their double dose, i.e. 100%. 50% or 0% of their usual dose at the end of the session so that participants receive a full 'double dose' (i.e. twice their usual maintenance dose) on the study day. Consistent with usual double dosing procedures, they will not receive a dose of buprenorphine on the day following the session. On the next two days of the washout period the participants usual dose will be administered. Study medication will be administered under supervised conditions and urine drug screening will be used to confirm substance use prior to each session.	</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants usual maintenance buprenorphine dose will be the control condition, and the comparator will be 150 and 200% of their buprenorphine dose. Depending on the dose administered at the start of the test day (100%, 150% or 200%) participants will the balance of their usual 'double dose' (100%, 50% or 0% of their dose) at the end of the test session so that participants receive their usual maintenance dose over the two day period. Administering double a buprenorphine dose to cover two days is part of standard treatment guidelines. On the next two days of the washout session the participants usual dose will be administered.The study is a within patient design so each participant will act as their own control and receive all three conditions. To maintain the blind placebo films will be administered so that total number of films in each session will be the same. Further, to maintain the blind participants will receive a blinded dose of buprenorphine+naloxone film dose at the end of the session which will contain the balance of their dose so that participants receive their usual maintenance dose in the form of a 'double dose' over the two day period.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain threshold (time with arm in the cold pressor bath until participant reports pain detection)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours following buprenorphine dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain tolerance (total time with arm in the cold pressor bath until participant removes their arm)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 hours after buprenorphine dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiration (breaths per minute)  observation visually</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1h 50min, 2h 10min </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective effects of medication on 0 - 100mm Visual Analog Scale. Items measured on the scale include strength of drug effect, liking of drug effect, sedation, bad effects and intoxication. These measures are commonly assessed in drug administration studies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One hour 50 minutes after buprenorphine administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure measures using a blood pressure machine</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1h 50min, 2h 10min </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen saturation measured with a pulse oximeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1h 50min, 2h 10min </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive effects measured with pen and paper test (DSST, Cancellation of 4s)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and one hour and 50 minutes </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported pain measured with visual analog scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>2h</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Placebo/blind assessment (participant reports on a pen and paper form which condition they think they received on a study day)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2h 20 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Being at least 18 - 60 years of age
2.	Being of general good medical and psychiatric health
3.	Female participants must not be pregnant or nursing, and must have agreed to use an acceptable method of birth control. 
4.	Be stable buprenorphine treatment, including being on a stable dose of buprenorphine (4-16mg/day) at least 10 days. 
5.	Be willing to and capable of signing an informed consent.
6.	Primary language spoken is English 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential participants must not:
1.	Be dependent on alcohol, benzodiazepines, cannabis or other drugs of abuse that require immediate medical attention or be unsafe in the context of the study.
2.	Be actively involved in another clinical trial.
3.	Have a physiological, neurological or psychiatric illness (e.g. schizophrenia, Raynauds disease, urticaria, stroke) that would affect pain responses.  
4.	Be currently taking analgesic medication for a painful condition on a regular basis.
5.	Be currently taking a medication known to affect pain response (e.g. antidepressants)
6.	Be taking medications, herbal or vitamin supplements or other dietary supplements (eg grapefruit juice) that may interfere with the metabolism of the study medication.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants that provide informed consent will be enrolled and randomized. The study pharmacist will dispense medications for each of the three study sessions according the randomization schedule. Study medication and placebos will be matched for appearance and dispensed in identical packaging so that the researchers and participants will not know what dose is administered on each session.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomization schedule for the nine participants will be developed in advance using computer generated schedule. The study pharmacist will then dispense medication according to the randomization schedule in the order that participants are enrolled (from participant one to participant nine). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Within-patient design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome measures will be change in pain tolerance and threshold. Differences in pain tolerance and threshold will be examined using two-way repeated measures ANOVA, or mixed models if there is missing data.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>9</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>4</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Langton Centre, 591 South Dowling St, Surry Hills, NSW, 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Drug and Alcohol Services, South Eastern Sydney Local Health District, Departmental funds.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>591 South Dowling St
Surry Hills
NSW, 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC Research Fellowship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of New South Wales, National Drug and Alcohol Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>22-32 King St, Randwick, NSW, 2052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to examine the effect of buprenorphine for pain in opioid dependent people. Most research with buprenorphine for pain has been conducted using doses that are at least 10 times lower than those used in opioid dependent people. This study aims to examine if increasing doses of buprenorphine result in improved pain response in the dose ranges used for treatment of opioid dependence.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee South Eastern Sydney Local Health District </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room G71, East Wing, Edmund Blacket Building 
Prince of Wales Hospital 
Cnr High &amp; Avoca Streets 
RANDWICK  NSW  2031 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>141088 (HREC/14/POWH/208)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Nielsen</name>
      <address>University of New South Wales
National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
22-32 King St
Randwick 2031 NSW</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8936 1017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.nielsen@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Nielsen</name>
      <address>University of New South Wales
National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
22-32 King St
Randwick 2031 NSW</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8936 1017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.nielsen@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Nielsen</name>
      <address>University of New South Wales
National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
22-32 King St
Randwick 2031 NSW</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8936 1017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.nielsen@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Nielsen</name>
      <address>University of New South Wales
National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
22-32 King St
Randwick 2031 NSW</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8936 1017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.nielsen@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>