<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363816">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000296730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Having more fun: Increasing enjoyable activities to improve mood in nursing home residents with Alzheimers disease: A pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Having more fun: Increasing enjoyable activities to treat depression in nursing home residents with Alzheimer's disease: A pilot study. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1140-2349 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is an 8-week trial of activity scheduling to improve symptoms of depression in nursing home residents with Alzheimer's disease.  The intervention has two important components: (A) participants will work individually with a therapist (once per week for approximately 30-40 minutes) to identify enjoyable activities that are feasible and practical within the nursing home environment and the residents abilities, and develop an individually tailored plan to increase the availability and frequency of those events.  Enjoyable activities are defined simply as activities the resident reports he or she would enjoy doing or enjoy doing more of and may be as simple as wearing a favourite piece of clothing, watching a TV show or going on an outing. 
(B) Involvement of facility staff - The therapist will simultaneously work with facility staff (particularly activities staff) to implement the enjoyable activities and educate them about depression in the nursing home context.  One three  hour training session regarding depression in older people will be conducted immediately prior to commencement of the intervention.  In addition, one staff member (ideally an activities staff member) will be nominated to be actively involved as a co-therapist for each participant who will be asked to support and encourage him/her to achieve their planned enjoyable activity each week. The therapist will liase with the co-therapist weekly (5-10 minutes will be all that is required) to inform them of the planned enjoyable activities for each participant for the following week and to identify any potential barriers to their implementation and identify possible solutions.
The trial will be conducted in 2 residential aged care facilities sequentially.  Residents in facility A will receive the intervention for 8 weeks while residents in facility B receive treatment as usual.  At the end of 8 weeks, residents in facility B will receive the intervention for 8 weeks while residents in facility A receive treatment as usual.  There will be no wash-out period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual.  Participants in the control group will continue to engage in all activities provided by the residential care facility in which they live but will receive no input from research staff for the control period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression (as measured by the Geriatric Depression Scale (12R))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8 (following intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (as measured by the Quality of Life - Alzheimer's Disease - Nursing Home version)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8 (following intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agitation (as measured by the Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory - short form)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8 (following intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must have a diagnosis of mild to moderate probable Alzheimer's Disease (AD), or Vascular Dementia (VAD) mixed AD/VAD;
Participants must have evidence of symptoms of depression as measured by the Geriatric Depression Scale (12R);
Participants must reside in a Residential Aged Care facility </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Profound deafness;  
Severe dementia (MMSE scores &lt;10);
Non-english speaking;</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants from 2 residential care facilities in Queensland will participate in the study.  Participants from facility A will receive the intervention first while participants in facility B will receive treatment as usual.  A cross-over design will be used and following 8 weeks of the intervention, the intervention will be implemented in Facility B while participants in Facility A receive treatment as usual.  There is no wash-out period.  The Research Assistant responsible for recruiting participants into the study will be a different person to the perosn who will be   acting as the therapist for the study and will be unaware regarding group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The allocation of the two facilities: A and B will depend on the toss of a coin. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Differences in groups will be assessed by comparing outcomes following the intervention (weeks 8 and 16) with baseline values.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>25/02/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Catherine Travers</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Room 612, N Block
Queensland University of technology
Victoria Park Rd.,
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>JR &amp; JR Wicking Trust &amp; Mason Foundation (one source)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ANZ Trustees
GPO 389
Melbourne, Victoria 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Deb Parker
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>UQ Blue Care Research &amp; Practice Development Centre
Sylvan Rd.,
Toowong Qld 4066
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to assess the feasibility and effectiveness of an intervention, recently shown to have promise in the US, in Australia. The intervention targets depression by increasing nursing home residents involvement in simple, enjoyable activities. The pilot project will be conducted in two Brisbane Residential Aged Care (RAC) facilities and will involve working with residents and staff to increase resident involvement in enjoyable activities.  The intervention is inexpensive and relatively simple to implement and will be assessed for effectiveness, feasibility and acceptability. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Victoria Park Rd., 
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Travers</name>
      <address>Room 612, N Block
QUT
Victoria Park Rd.,
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3138 3882</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.travers@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Travers</name>
      <address>Room 612, N Block
QUT
Victoria Park Rd.,
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3138 3882</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.travers@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Travers</name>
      <address>Room 612, N Block
QUT
Victoria Park Rd.,
Kelvin Grove Qld 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3138 3882</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.travers@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Travers</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.travers@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>