<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368682">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000622505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Atrial fibrillation (AF) screening using a smartphone electrocardiogram (ECG): pilot study to test implementation in the primary care setting.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Identifying atrial fibrillation (AF) in patients aged 65 years and over by opportunistic screening during the annual influenza vaccination using a smartphone electrocardiogram: pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>GP SEARCH AF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Five General practices will participate in the pilot intervention. Nurses at the participating practices will attend a two-hour training session with a trained cardiac nurse specialist. The practice nurse will receive training regarding the research protocol and the use of an approved handheld ECG monitoring device (AliveCor Heart Monitor, ARTG Identifier 208100). This is a special cover that attaches to smartphones, and enables a single lead ECG to be taken using an application on the phone (iECG). Practice nurses will use the ECG device to screen for AF during the period of observation of the patient after the administration of the annual flu shot in general practice. The patient will be asked to hold the smartphone ECG for approximate one minute, to record their heart rhythm. The smartphone application immediately analyses the ECG rhythm for the presence of AF using a validated algorithm, and provides an immediate provisional diagnosis on the smartphone. The ECG recording and provisional diagnosis are directly imported into the general practice software and attached to the patient notes.

The nurse will facilitate a general practitioner review for all patients with a provisional diagnosis of AF, if they have no previous known history of AF. The general practitioner will review the patient and determine subsequent management. 

The screening intervention will run for the entire 2015 flu-vax period, approximately 2-3 months in total. Following completion of the intervention, structured interviews will be conducted with the participating nurses, practice managers and a selection of general practitioners from each practice to determine the barriers and enablers of the screening intervention and thereby inform refinement of the larger scale intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Implementation success as assessed through process measures including: the proportion of eligible patients at each practice who attended for their flu vaccination and were screened according to the protocol; time taken to complete the intervention (measured and reported by the participating practice nurses); barriers affecting implementation of screening including competing demands for practice nurse time (measured using semi-structured interviews with the participating practice nurses, practice managers and a selection of general practitioners from each practice); and enablers and benefits of screening (measured using semi-structured interviews with the participating practice nurses, practice managers and a selection of general practitioners from each practice).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of the screening intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the intervention according to the general practice staff involved in the intervention (measured using semi-structured interviews with the participating practice nurses, practice managers and a selection of general practitioners from each practice)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of screening intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of people screened with newly diagnosed AF, identified on the smartphone ECG and confirmed with a subsequent 12-lead ECG (reported as number identified and percentage of total screened)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of screening intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients aged 65 years and over, who are eligible for an annual flu shot. 

A convenience sample of General Practice will be selected from those who respond to the expression of interest for participation in the pilot study. General practices will need to offer annual flu-vaccination administered by a practice nurse, and need to have onsite wi-fi and a computerized patient management system to be considered eligible for participation. The first 5 eligible practices that respond to the expression of interest will be recruited to the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Insufficient cognitive capacity to understand the consent process</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A detailed process evaluation using mixed methods will be undertaken to evaluate iECG screening process. Realist evaluation will be used to analyse the interaction of context, mechanisms for change and the outcomes that are produced. A selection of GPs, practice nurses and patients from each practice will be asked to participate in semi- structured interviews, tailored to each group. In this way we will piece together a detailed understanding of how the intervention influenced the capacity, opportunity and motivation of providers and patients to improve detection and evidence based treatment of AF.

New episodes of AF will be expressed as true positives divided by total number screened with accompanying 95% confidence intervals. Continuous variables will be reported as means +/- standard deviations (SD), and categorical variables as numbers and percentages. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>24/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1044</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>City Road, Darlington NSW 2008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Anonymous philanthropic medical foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Not applicable</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common heart arrhythmia, affecting 1 in 4 adults worldwide, and at least 240,000 Australians. Prevalence rises with age from approximately 1% of the whole population to 5% in those over 65 years. People with AF are up to seven times more likely to have a stroke than the general population. Almost one in every three strokes is AF-related, and AF-related strokes are likely to be more severe, with a whole of life cost of each stroke estimated at $103,566. However, strokes in AF can be effectively prevented using oral anticoagulants.

Many people in the general population are unaware that they have AF, with first diagnosis being made when they are admitted to hospital with a stroke or transient ischaemic attack. The diagnosis of unknown AF can be easily made using a 30 second ECG rhythm strip obtained with a TGA approved smartphone ECG (iECG). Using this device, unknown AF can be identified and treated, thus reducing the number of strokes due to AF. We have previously shown that community screening for AF to prevent stroke is likely to be cost-effective, but the magnitude of the benefit in terms of numbers of strokes prevented, is determined by the proportion of the population screened. 

The current study therefore explores screening for AF in primary care, by performing iECG screening during annual influenza vaccination currently administered to over 70% of patients aged 65 years and over in general practice. This opportunistic method of screening, through its reach, would approximate systematic population screening for AF. Screening will be performed in a small number of practices in this pilot study to optimize the process and inform any refinement of a larger scale study of implementation. The pilot will also ensure the tools are ready for the larger implementation study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Sydney
City Road Darlington NSW 2008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/962</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lis Neubeck</name>
      <address>Level 2, Building  D17
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 0291</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lis.neubeck@sydney.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>S Ben Freedman</name>
      <address>Level 2, Building  D17
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9767 7358</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ben.Freedman@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lis Neubeck</name>
      <address>Level 2, Building  D17
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 0291</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lis.neubeck@sydney.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nicole Lowres</name>
      <address>Level 2, Building  D17
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 4 07256613</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.lowres@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>