<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336271">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000031965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Droperidol for rapid sedation of acute behavioural disturbance</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cardiac safety study of droperidol for rapid sedation of acute behavioural disturbance in the emergency department</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DORM II Observational study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute behaviour disturbance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Droperidol 10 mg given by intramuscular injection administered for rapid sedation will be followed by a strict regime of monitoring of vital signs and an ECG recording The ECG will be obtained as soon as possible directly after the sedative has been given and at 4 hours or discharge Sedation scoring will be recorded throughout on a regime of 5 minutely for 20 minutes, again at 10 minutes, then half hourly until the patient wakes up or is calm. Any adverse drug effects will be noted and recorded.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients who have abnormal  QT interval based on the QT nomogram following the administration of droperidol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the first hour after the administration of droperidol 10 mg IMI and at 4 hours or discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to sedation as determined by a reduction in the Sedation Assessment Tool (SAT) by 2 points or a score of zero.</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 minutes and 30 minutes and 60 minutes post administration of Droperidol 10 mg IMI</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients who have an adverse effect. These include respiratory depression requiring intubation, TdP and other cardiac arrhythmias, severe extra pyramidal side effects, Severe hypotension or other other major unexpcted side effects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 2 hrs of administration of Droperidol 10 mg IMI</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement of additional sedation defined as if the patient remains agitated as scored on the SAT at +2 or +3 after 15 minutes and receives further medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within one hour of the initial administration of Droperidol 10 mg IMI</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for Re-sedation defined as a repeat acute behavioural disturbance after being initially sedated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After one hour has elapsed without the need for any sedation for up to 4 hours post droperidol</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Injuries to the patient, staff or other patients or property</outcome>
      <timepoint>Any time point within the study period of 4 hours post droperidol 10mg</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Acute behaviour disturbance and is scoring +2 to +3 on the sedation assessment tool, defined as aggresive/violent loud outbusts and combative. 
The patient is at risk to themselves or others and requires physical restraint for safety.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>99</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under the age of 18 years.
Is able to be talked down. 
Has agreed to the offer of oral medication with good result.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4215</postcode>
    <postcode>2305</postcode>
    <postcode>2320</postcode>
    <postcode>2330</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof. G.K.Isbister</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dr G.K.Isbister
Department of pharmocology and Toxicology
Level 5 New Med building
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Edith Street
Waratah 2298
NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>N/A</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>N/A</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The recent randomised controlled trial of Droperidol versus Midazolam for acute behaviour disturbance (ACTRN 12607000527460) resulted in the drug type being droperidol as effective at sedation as Midazolam but with significantly less adverse effects. There was no significant QT abnormalities. With ethics approval an extension to this trial followed and we have introduced  a protocol of sedation with inclusion criteria and guidelines with the recommendation to give droperidol in a set dose and route as an observational study  in the emergency department. This extension of the original trial has resulted in positive outcome for both patients and staff. The patient cohort is over 250 patients to date with no serious adverse effects. We now wish to extend this observational study to include rural regional and metropolitan hospitals to increase the sample size of the safety study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.star.ferntree.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Isbister GK, Calver LA, Page CB, Stokes B, Bryant JL, Downes MA. Randomised comparison study of intramuscular droperidol versus midazolam for violence and acute behavioural disturbance  the DORM study. Ann Emerg Med. 2010 Oct;56(4):392-401

Calver LA, Downes MA, Page CB, Bryant JL, Isbister GK. The impact of a standardised intramuscular sedation protocol for acute behavioural disturbance in the emergency department. BMC Emerg Med. 2010 Jun 28;10:14

Chan A, Isbister GK, Kirkpatrick CMJ, Duffull SB. Drug-induced QT prolongation and Torsades de Pointes: evaluation of a QT nomogram. QJM. 2007 Oct;100(10):609-15.

Isbister GK, Calver L, van Gorp F, Stokes B, Page CB. Inter-rater reliability of manual QT measurement and prediction of abnormal QT,HR pairs. Clin Toxicol (Phila). 2009 Nov;47(9):884-8

Downes M, Healy P, Page CB, Bryant JL, Isbister GK. Code Black: A Structured Approach to the Agitated Patient in the Emergency Department. Emerg Med Australas. 2009 Jun;21(3):196-202</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Geoffrey Isbister</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Toxicology/ Pharmacology
Level 5 New Med Building
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Edith Street 
Waratah 2298
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 1627</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 1870</fax>
      <email>geoff.isbister@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Geoffrey Isbister</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Toxicology/ Pharmacology
Level 5 New Med Building
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Edith Street 
Waratah 2298
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 1627</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 1870</fax>
      <email>geoff.isbister@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Leonie Calver</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Toxicology/ Pharmacology
Level 5 New Med Building
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Edith Street 
Waratah 2298
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 1312</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 1870</fax>
      <email>leonie.calver@calvarymater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>