<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364868">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001108707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study to measure the efficacy of a manualised oral narrative intervention programme for school-age children with narrative delay</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For school-age children with narrative delay is a manualised oral narrative intervention programme more effective than typical practice as measured by narrative macrostructure, microstructure and quality: A pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oral language delay</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase One: Designing, Manualising and Piloting the Treatment Programme
1.	Design narrative programme structure and develop manual to include scope and sequence of intervention targets and parameters of intervention.
2.	Map structure to intervention sessions and goals/targets for each session.
3.	Develop teaching scripts for each narrative element, to include a definition, model and examples. 
4.	Develop scripted contingent responses for macrostructure and microstructure elements.
5.	Create scoring procedure to evaluate participants performance for macrostructure and microstructure as well as a pre and post measure of narrative quality.

Intervention sessions will consist of a range of activities such as book sharing, story generation, picture sequencing, story re-tells and character maps. These activities are commonly used in Speech Pathology sessions with young children. Each intervention session will last for 45 minutes. 

The programme will be piloted with 6 monolingual English speaking participants, aged between 5.5 and 6.5. Intervention will be carried out in 2 groups of three, 3 times a week for 6 weeks. Changes to the programme will be made as needed, based on participant engagement and clinician judgment. Reasons for changes will be documented for future reference. </interventions>
    <comparator>Single subject repeated measures multiple baseline across participants research design</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre- and post-treatment data collection will use the Test of Narrative Language. Narratives will be analysed according to the test guidelines, utilizing SALT. Samples will be scored on narrative quality, using a like-ert scale. Measures of narrative quality include; amount of scaffolding and support required, use of paralinguistic features and engagement. 

Gillam, R. B., &amp; Pearson, N. A. (2004). Test of Narrative Language. Austin, TX: Pro-Ed.
Miller, J., &amp; Iglesias, A. (2008). Systematic Analysis of Language Transcripts (SALT) [Computer Software]: LLC. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment will be carried out in the week prior to intervention commencing and post-treatment will be carried out in the week following intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures of narrative macrostructure and microstructure, will use a researcher generated analysis method to profile the samples in more detail. Measures will be collected during each intervention session. 
Repeated measures analysis of the DVs will be completed using the macro and microstructure measures collected during baseline and treatment to determine change, and determine if changes are related to onset of treatment. Visual and statistical methods will be used to evaluate clinical and statistical significance. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During each intervention session (3 times per  week for 6 weeks).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Six monolingual English-speaking children between the ages of 5.5 to 6.5 with narrative delay will be selected from a metropolitan mainstream school.  The school will be implementing typical classroom practice that does not include explicit teaching of narrative. A parent/teacher questionnaire will be used to ensure all participants are typically developing with no evidence of significant hearing, vision, behavioural, language and educational or medical issues present. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Evidence of significant hearing, vision, behavioural, language and educational or medical issues. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>6</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA
6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA
6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will design, develop and investigate efficacy of a manualised theoretically driven oral narrative programme. Intervention will involve explicitly teaching macrostructure to 12 Pre-Primary children with narrative difficulties in small groups in a mainstream school. Multiple baseline repeated measures single-case design will be used to evaluate changes. Measures will include narrative macrostructure, microstructure and quality. The relationship between vocabulary and memory and response to intervention will also be investigated. This study has practical and theoretical significance as it will add to evidence for narrative intervention focusing on macrostructure and investigate the influence on vocabulary and sentence development.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Office of Research &amp; Development
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>