<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336806">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000284662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Central Australian Heart Protection Study: A Randomised Trial of Nurse-Led, Family Based Secondary Prevention of Acute Coronary Syndromes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Central Australian Heart Protection Study: A Randomised Trial of Nurse-Led, Family Based Secondary Prevention of Acute Coronary Syndromes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-7348</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CAHPS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Coronary Syndromes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this study is to test the effectiveness of a culturally appropriate, integrated family based secondary prevention (SP) program in reducing the incidence of major adverse coronary events (MACE) in indigenous and non-indigenous patients discharged from Alice Springs Hospital following an Acute Coronary Syndrome ACS.

Key features of the study intervention will include:
 
1.	A 90minute comprehensive, home-based assessment of factors likely to positively or negatively impact on the longer-term CV health of the patient within 14 days of hospital discharge. This assessment will occur at baseline, and protocol driven management and education will be delivered by individual case-managers focused on medical therapy, cardiac education and awareness, symptom recognition, necessary follow up and guideline based stepped care to target. 

2.	A computerised decision support system incorporating all clinical and demographic data relative to local evidence-based guidelines (CARPA Standard Treatment Manual) will be used to guide individual case management, delivered by outreach nurses at baseline, 6 months, 12 months with final close out visit at 24 months. Visits last for approximately 1 hour. Individual follow up may vary according to predefined risk, clinical stability and the achievement of secondary prevention targets in blood pressure, lipid levels and psychosocial status (depression scores). Those individuals at elevated risk or clinically unstable will be visited at weekly to three monthly intervals (in addition to standard visit follow up) until clinically stable. 

3.	Repeated application of the decision support tool over twelve months of active nurse-led stepped care, to identify key therapeutic targets and treatments necessary to achieve them for optimal risk reduction (secondary prevention) in patients with ACS.

4.	A family-based clinical and education intervention will also applied by a trained cardiac nurse and Aboriginal Health Worker (AHW) tailored to the patients health assessment (as specified above). This will occur once at the first home visit, and last approximately 30-60 minutes. </interventions>
    <comparator>Usual Care will consist of standard care as provided by the patients general practitioner/Primary care providers. All such therapy is outlined in the CARPA standard treatment manual for secondary prevention of Coronary heart disease. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major Adverse Cardiovascular Endpoint (MACE) - death, non-fatal ACS, stroke, or unplanned revascularisation. Hospitalisation (hospital separation ICD-10) and vital statistics data (NDI propensity matched mortality data) will be collated on each individual at study close out, and according to standardised hospitalisation and event forms to be completed prospectively by individual case managers. Each event will have details collated and will be reviewed by a blinded outcome adjudication committee according to standardised outcome definitions.    </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Receipt of evidence based care (recorded from patient interview and medical records and collated on case report forms). 

   </outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CVD-related and all-cause hospital admissions will be recorded from review of NT hospitalisations database/clinical records within local hospital. Interstate hospitalisations will be identified through patient interview and primary care record review at close out. ICD-10 primary and secondary hospitalisation codes will be reviewed, medical records reviewed and blinded end-point committee will determine CVD/non-CVD related events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of family buddies with CV risk factors (hypertension, dyslipidaemia, abdominal obesity, elevated BMI and smoking). Individual buddies will have explicit Case report forms for collation of individual risk at baseline and close-out. Close visits will involve direct clinical assessment and review of behavioural factors by clinical staff.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Achievement of clinical targets (BP, lipid fractions (TC, HDL-C, LDL-C, and triglycerides), and glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c), Each individual will have a close-out assessment at 2 years to determine their cardiovascular risk status (in the same manner as at baseline). Proportions of individual achieving evidence based practice guideline (NHF, CARPA STM, NHMRC, KHA) directed targets for lipid sub-fractions and HBA1c will be determined</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometric measures (weight, waist and hip circumference); </outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychosocial status (depression score).</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients admitted to the Alice Springs Hospital with the admission diagnosis of ST elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI), Non ST segment elevation ACS, or angina.

Aged over 18 years

Able to provide informed consent

Resident of Central Australia </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they do not survive to discharge, have a discharge diagnosis inconsistent with ACS, who are not residents of Central Australia (i.e. Interstate or international visitors), or who have a significant neurological/cognitive impairment that prevents informed consent being obtained</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Stratified randomisation (based on Indigenous versus non-Indigenous status and on a 1:1 intervention to control basis) will occur following consent and via a blinded protocol at the time of discharge from hospital. To reduce contamination, we will ensure that individuals from the same household (in the event that two eligible patients are recruited from the same family) will be randomised to the same arm of the trial. Allocation is not concealed. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generated randominsation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/11/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alice Springs Hospital - Alice Springs</hospital>
    <postcode>0870 - Alice Springs</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Central Australia
W&amp;E Rubuntja Building
Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Rd, Alice Springs 0870, NT</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Melinda Carrington</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Baker IDI
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC, 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sandra Eades</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Baker IDI
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC, 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>David Thompson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian Catholic University
Locked Bag 4115
Fitzroy MDC
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Christopher Zeitz</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Adelaide University
C/O Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Road
Woodville West SA 5011</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite the high burden of cardiovascular diseases among Indigenous Australians, few intervention trials have sought to evaluate novel approaches to reducing differential outcomes in this vulnerable group. The Central Australian Heart Protection Study seeks to test the effectiveness of a nurse-led, family based education and assessment program in reducing the incidence of poor outcomes in indigenous and non-indigenous patients following an Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Australian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/- Centre for Remote Health
PO Box 4066, Alice Springs, NT 0871
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/05/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alex Brown</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Central Australia
W&amp;E Rubuntja Building
Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Road
Alice Springs, NT 0870</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8959 0111</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8952 1557</fax>
      <email>alex.brown@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alex Brown</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Central Australia
W&amp;E Rubuntja Building
Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Road
Alice Springs, NT 0870</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8959 0111</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8952 1557</fax>
      <email>alex.brown@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alex Brown</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Central Australia
W&amp;E Rubuntja Building
Alice Springs Hospital
Gap Road
Alice Springs, NT 0870</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8959 0111</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8952 1557</fax>
      <email>alex.brown@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alex Brown</name>
      <address>Level 9, 121 King William Street Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81164427</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alex.brown@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>