<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369622">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000326493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does a performance-focused swimming training program improve health, fitness and functioning in people with cerebral palsy?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Performance-focused Swimming Training for People with Cerebral Palsy: Evaluation of Clinical Outcomes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1176-5481</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The first 15 weeks of the intervention will be an introductory swimming program, which will comprise of low to moderate intensity aerobic, strength, neuromotor and flexibility training. This training will include swimming, but also gym-based resistance training using machines and/or free weights, stretching exercises and bodyweight exercises which will be assisted if required. These sessions will also include individualised balance, proprioception and motor control exercises. Swimming training in this phase will focus on developing confidence in the water, stroke technique and aerobic capacity. 

Training intensity in this phase will be recorded using heart rate monitors, activity monitors and RPE scales. The training program in this phase will be designed to be moderately challenging, and to elicit a score of between 3 and 6 on the OMNI Rate of Perceived Exertion scale. During the training sessions, the participants target heart rate will be between 30% and 60% of their heart rate reserve. 

The frequency and duration of training sessions which will depend on the participants exercise tolerance and baseline physical activity levels. The duration and intensity of training in this program will be slowly and safely increased until the participant is able to meet national physical activity guidelines (150 minutes of moderate intensity activity per week including 2 strength sessions). 

The introductory program will be followed by a 15-week performance-focused training program, the aim of which will be to enhance swimming speed. The program will comprise low to high intensity aerobic, strength, neuromotor and flexibility training which is individually tailored to optimise swimming performance. This will involve a combination of gym-based training and pool-based training sessions. Within the land-based sessions, a combination of resistance training, stretching exercises and bodyweight exercises will be continued. Balance, proprioception and motor control training will also continue. Swimming training in this phase will aim to improve aerobic and anaerobic endurance, speed and in-water power, race starts, and ability to swim at race pace

 The intensity of training in this phase will aim range from easy to challenging, and will aim to elicit an RPE score of between 3 and 10 depending on the aim of the session. During the training sessions, the participants target heart rate will be between 40% and 100% of their heart rate reserve. There will be a combination of land-based training in a gym setting and pool-based training during this phase.

The frequency and duration of training will depend on the participants exercise tolerance and physical fitness levels. The intensity and duration of training sessions will be steadily increased further in this phase until the participant is consistently exceeding moderate levels of physical activity i.e. completing more than 150 minutes of moderate intensity activity per week including 2 strength sessions.  

Throughout the intervention (during both the introductory program and the performance-focused program) adherence to the program will be logged using a training diary which is completed by the participant. This will include: frequency, intensity, duration, type of training, level of enjoyment, pain and fatigue. Semi-structured interviews will also be conducted on an 8-weekly basis to ascertain participant's perception of the program.

The training program will be administered by a combination of swimming coaches, accredited exercise physiologists and physiotherapists. Participants will be partnered with a non-disabled 'buddy', who will train with them, therefore the intervention will be administered face to face in pairs.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The study will adopt an n-of-one design, and will include a 15-week baseline testing period consisting of at least 5 data collection points. Therefore participants will act as their own control.

The 'A' phase will be a 15 week baseline phase, in which participants will continue to complete the habitual level of physical activity. Following the intervention (Phases B and C), the 'A' Phase will be repeated  - participants will return to completing their habitual level of physical activity. This Phase will act as an off-season lasting for 15 weeks, and will mirror the baseline phase. During this time, testing will continue until the trial is concluded.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health: SF-36 score </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 2, 5, 8, 11, 14, 17, 20, 23, 26, 29, 32, 35, 38, 41, 44, 47, 50, 53, 56, 59</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fitness: V02 max test on arm crank ergometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 2, 5, 8, 11, 14, 17, 20, 23, 26, 29, 32, 35, 38, 41, 44, 47, 50, 53, 56, 59</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function: Gross Motor Function Measure 66 Item Set</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, 30, 33, 36, 39, 42, 45, 48, 51, 54, 57, 60</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Athletic Identity: The athletic identity measurement scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Life Satisfaction: The satisfaction with life scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self Efficacy: Self Efficacy Questionnaire

Source: Motl, R. W., Dishman, R. K., Trost, S. G., Saunders, R. P., Dowda, M., Felton, G., Ward, D. S., Pate, R. R.. (2000). Factorial validity and invariance of questionnaires measuring social-cognitive determinants of physical activity among adolescent girls. Preventative Medicine. 31 (5), 584-594.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attitude: Attitude Questionnaire

Source: Motl, R. W., Dishman, R. K., Trost, S. G., Saunders, R. P., Dowda, M., Felton, G., Ward, D. S., Pate, R. R.. (2000). Factorial validity and invariance of questionnaires measuring social-cognitive determinants of physical activity among adolescent girls. Preventative Medicine. 31 (5), 584-594.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Behavioral Control: Perceived Behavioral Control Questionnaire

Source: Motl, R. W., Dishman, R. K., Trost, S. G., Saunders, R. P., Dowda, M., Felton, G., Ward, D. S., Pate, R. R.. (2000). Factorial validity and invariance of questionnaires measuring social-cognitive determinants of physical activity among adolescent girls. Preventative Medicine. 31 (5), 584-594.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function: the functional independence measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resilience: resilience scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 2, 5, 8, 11, 14, 17, 20, 23, 26, 29, 32, 35, 38, 41, 44, 47, 50, 53, 56, 59</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue: fatigue severity scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 2, 5, 8, 11, 14, 17, 20, 23, 26, 29, 32, 35, 38, 41, 44, 47, 50, 53, 56, 59</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strength: 3 repetition max test in the following exercises
1)	Shoulder press
2)	Leg press
3)	Lat pull down
4)	Seated leg extension
5)	Bench press
6)	Hamstring curl
7)	Seated Row</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 2, 5, 8, 11, 14, 17, 20, 23, 26, 29, 32, 35, 38, 41, 44, 47, 50, 53, 56, 59</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition: Skinfold Thickness</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition: dexa scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 1, 15, 30, 45, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric strength: developed for this study and measured using a load cell. Participants will be in a standardised position and will perform the following isometric actions:
1) Shoulder extension in supported sitting
2) Hip flexion in side lying
3) Hip extension in side lying

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active and passive range of movement will be measured using goniometers and digital inclinometers. Tests were developed for this study and will measure:
1) Shoulder flexion, extension, internal and external rotation.
2) Shoulder horizontal extension at 90 degrees of abduction
3) Elbow extension
4) Pronation and supination
5) Cervical and thoracic rotation
6) Hip extension
7) Knee extension
8) Plantarflexion and dorsiflexion</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reciprocal tapping tasks to assess speed and accuracy of movement - developed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 1, 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19, 22, 25, 28, 31, 34, 37, 40, 43, 46, 49, 52, 55, 58</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postural stability: modified functional reach test and sitting assessment scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, 30, 33, 36, 39, 42, 45, 48, 51, 54, 57, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen cost of arm cranking at self-selected speed, tested by measuring volume of oxygen consumption during walking/wheeling for 6 minutes at a self-selected, comfortable speed using gas analysis equipment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, 30, 33, 36, 39, 42, 45, 48, 51, 54, 57, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Swimming performance: time trial (developed for this study)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, 30, 33, 36, 39, 42, 45, 48, 51, 54, 57, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Swimming skill acquisition: modified amateur swimming association level (developed for this study)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, 30, 33, 36, 39, 42, 45, 48, 51, 54, 57, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Swimming Skill Acquisition: Water Orientation Test-Alyn</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, 30, 33, 36, 39, 42, 45, 48, 51, 54, 57, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Composition: DXA scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 1, 15, 30, 45, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Life History Description: Semi Structured Interview</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 15, 30, 45, 60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Aged greater than or equal to 12 years and &lt;30 years.
2) Insufficiently active for health at the time of enrollment.
3) Moderate-to-severely impaired (GMFCS II, III and IV). 
4) Are water safe but unable to swim for fitness. 
5) Medically fit to participate in a graduated swim for fitness program. 
6)Intellectual level sufficient to engage in supervised exercise.
7) Willing to be interviewed about their reasons for wanting or not wanting to participate in an organised swim for fitness program with a buddy without a disability..</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Recent serious musculoskeletal injury, illness or operation.
2) Cardiovascular risk.
3) Compromised Skin integrity. 
4) Pain levels which will prevent engagement in exercise programmes.
5) Significant intellectual impairment which affects ability to engage in exercise programs.
6) Dysphagia which may increase risk of aspiration
7) uncontrolled seizure disorder or regular seizures which constitute an unacceptable safety risk in water</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study will adopt an A-B-C-A Single Subject Research Design (SSRD) with data collection at 20 time points:
-	5 baseline, taken prior to the intervention over 15 weeks.
-	5 peri/post a introductory swimming intervention over 15 weeks.
-	5 peri/post a performance-focused swim intervention over 15 weeks
-	5 peri/post an off-season/maintenance phase over 15 weeks
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In consideration of the commitment required from participants, the population of interest, the length of the study and the volume of testing, it was deemed not feasible to conduct a sufficiently statistically powered randomised controlled trial at this time. Instead, given the above conditions, we aim to conduct intensive investigations in between 3 and 5 individuals using an n-of-1 research design. Randomised n-of-1 trials are ranked as Level 1 evidence for treatment decision purposes in individual patients (Tate et al., 2013), and permit intensive investigations of individual participants during baseline and at least one intervention phase. Outcomes will be repeatedly measured during all phases to determine the effects of the intervention.

Visual analysis of graphed data, following standard conventions, will be the primary method used to evaluate the differences between baseline, intervention and withdrawal phases. Features of graphed data will be examined within- and between-phases, evaluating the following:
1) Level
2) Trend
3) Variability
4) Immediacy of effect
5) Data overlap
6) Consistency of data patterns across similar phases

Tate, R. L., Perdices, M., Rosenkoetter, U., Wakim, D., Godbee, K., Togher., L., McDonald, S. (2013). Revision of a method quality rating scale for single-case experimental designs and n-of-1 trials: The 15-item Risk of Bias in N-of-1 Trials (RoBiNT) Scale. Neuropsycholigical Rehabilitation, 23(5), 619-638.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>5</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
The University of Queensland
Brisbane 
QLD 
4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Paralympic Committee </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>l7/320 Adelaide St
Brisbane
QLD 
4000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Swimming Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 3286 
Belconnen 
ACT 
2617
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Academy of Sport</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Queensland Sport and Athletics Centre
Kessels Rd
Nathan 
QLD 
4111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Queensland 
St Lucia
QLD
4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>International Paralympic Committee</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Agitos Foundation
Adenauerallee 212-214 
53113 Bonn
Germany</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Germany</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is known that moderate-intensity physical activity enhances health, fitness and functioning in people with cerebral palsy (CP). Anecdotal evidence indicates high training loads designed to develop Paralympic swimmers may elicit excellent clinical outcomes. The primary aim of the program of research will be to evaluate the therapeutic benefit of a performance-focused swimming intervention for people with cerebral palsy who have high support needs. We hypothesise that outcomes of the study will substantiate the anecdotal evidence. Specifically, that high training loads will improve health, fitness and functioning in people with cerebral palsy who have high support needs.

A small number (3-5) of young people with moderate to severe cerebral palsy who are insufficiently active for health, but are interested in participating in competitive sport, will be recruited. The study will adopt an A-B-C-A N-of-1 design lasting 60 weeks in total. This will comprise of a baseline testing phase, a training intervention phase and a withdrawal phase. Testing will be conducted throughout these phases on a 3 weekly basis, therefore there will be 20 data collection points within the trial.

Initially, there will be a 15-week baseline testing phase. Then the intervention will begin with a 15-week introductory swimming program, which will comprise of low to moderate intensity aerobic, strength, neuromotor and flexibility training. The intensity and duration of training in this program will be slowly and safely increased until the participant is able to meet national physical activity guidelines (150 minutes of moderate intensity activity per week including 2 strength sessions). 

The introductory program will be followed by a 15-week performance-focused training program, the aim of which will be to enhance swimming speed. The program will comprise of moderate to high intensity aerobic, strength, neuromotor and flexibility training which is individually tailored to optimise swimming performance. Once again the intensity and duration of training sessions will be steadily increased until the participant is consistently exceeding moderate levels of physical activity. Following this, there will be a 15-week withdrawal period during the off-season which will reflect the baseline testing phase.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Office
The University of Queensland
Cumbrae-Stewart Building
St Lucia 
Qld 
4072
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015000831</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cerebral Palsy League</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>21 Whitley St, Mount Gravatt East QLD 4122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CPL-2015-003</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sean Tweedy</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
The University of Queensland
Brisbane 
QLD 
4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6638</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>s.tweedy@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Iain Dutia</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
The University of Queensland
Brisbane 
QLD 
4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 4998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>i.dutia@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sean Tweedy</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
The University of Queensland
Brisbane 
QLD 
4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.tweedy@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Iain Dutia</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
The University of Queensland
Brisbane 
QLD 
4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 4998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>i.dutia@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>