<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347858">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/12/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000096853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of electroacupuncture in postanaesthetic shivering during regional anaesthesia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>electroacupuncture prevent postanesthetic shivering in patient undergone reginal anesthesia for ureteroendoscopy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-4344</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital Institutional Review Board: 99-0358A3</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>postanesthetic shivering</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1.In active acupuncture group, trained and accredited acupuncturist performed acupuncture on ST36 and ST37 bilaterally in a depth not over 0.5 cun before anaesthesia. Then an electro-stimulator NihonRiko TOKKI MOEL III (NihonRiko Medical Co., Ltd., Nagasaki, Japan) was connected to the needles with a current of 1 mA and a frequency of 3 Hz for 30 minutes.
2. Subarachnoid anaesthesia was instituted at either L3/4 or L4/5 interspaces. Hyperbaric bupivacaine, 5 mg/ml, 15 mg was injected using a 25G Quincke spinal needle (B. Braun Melsungen AG, Melsungen, Germany). Both the intervention group and the sham group received spinal anaesthesia.</interventions>
    <comparator>In control group, needles were inserted at 4 points that are remote from any classically described meridian or extraordinary acupoint and (2) no current was applied to the needles. These 4 points were located as follows: 3 cm lateral to the ST36 and ST37 respectively bilaterally.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shivering was graded using a scale similar to that validated by Tsai and Chu*: 0 = no shivering, 1 = piloerection or peripheral vasoconstriction but no visible shivering, 2 = muscular activity in only one muscle group, 3 = muscular activity in more than one muscle group but not generalized, and 4 = shivering involving the whole body.

*Tsai YC, Chu KS. A comparison of tramadol, amitriptyline, and meperidine for postepidural anesthetic shivering in parturients. Anesth Analg 2001; 93: 1288-92.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5-min intervals during surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>tympanic temperature as assessed using an infrared noncontact ear thermometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intrathecal injection and 5-min intervals during the peri-operative period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>blood pressure assessed using DINAMAP XL VITAL SIGNS MONITOR</outcome>
      <timepoint>before intrathecal injection and thereafter at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>heart rate assessed using Electrocardiography monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint>before intrathecal injection and thereafter at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>artirial O2 saturation assessed using pulse oximeter</outcome>
      <timepoint>before intrathecal injection and thereafter at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>subjects (ASA grade I or II) scheduled for elective ureterorendoscopy (URS) surgical procedures performed under spinal anaesthesia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects with experience in acupuncture, with history of hypo- or hyperthyroidism, cardiopulmonary disease, psychological disorders, a need for blood transfusion during surgery, an initial body temperature &gt;38.0°C or &lt;36.0°C, a known history of alcohol or substance abuse, or receiving vasodilators, or medications likely to alter thermoregulation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A total number of 85 patients scheduled for elective ureteroendoscopy(URS) surgical procedures of either sex under spinal anaesthesia between June 2010 and May 2011 were prospectively included in the study.
All participants were randomly assigned to group A (electroacupuncture) or group P (placebo) on the basis of a concealed allocation approach (according to the computer random number table allocation group) using opaque sealed envelopes containing the randomization schedule. These envelopes were opened immediately before electroacupuncture. There were no restrictions on randomization. Two separated groups were invited to the study. The sealed envelopes were accessible only to the first group of acupuncturists who were to perform electroacupuncture. The second group of anesthetists who were to perform spinal anesthesia and patients were blinded to the electroacupuncture allocation. Another nursing staff unware of the electroacupuncture study were responsible for collection the necessary data.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer random number table allocation group</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/08/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state>Taoyuan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Yi-Chun Hsu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesiology, Chang Gung memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan
Tel: +886-3-3281200
Fax: +886-3-3280097</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Yi-Chun Hsu</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anaesthesiology, Chang Gung memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan
Tel: +886-3-3281200
Fax: +886-3-3280097</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bo-Yan Yeh</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Acupuncture and Traumatology, Chang Gung memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan
Tel: +886-3-3281200
Fax: +886-3-3280097</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: The aim of the present study was to verify the effect of electroacupuncture in the prevention of shivering caused by regional anaesthesia.

Methods: In this prospective, randomized, single-blind study, 80 ASA I and II patients undergoing urological surgery were included. Spinal anaesthesia was performed in all patients with bupivacaine 15 mg. The patients were randomly allocated to receive placebo acupuncture (Group P, n = 40) or electroacupuncture (group A, n = 40) for 30 min before spinal anaesthesia. Shivering score was recorded at 5 min intervals. Heart rate, arterial pressure and tympanic temperatures were recorded using standard non-invasive monitors before intrathecal injection and thereafter at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min.

Results: After 15 min, the number of patients with observed shivering above 3 was 13 in group P and 3 in group A. The number of patients with a shivering score above 3 was statistically significantly higher in group P compared with the other group.
Conclusion: The prophylactic use of electroacupuncture was effective in preventing shivering developed during regional anaesthesia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital Institutional Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Chang Gung memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan
Tel: +886-3-3281200
Fax: +886-3-3280097</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yi-Chun Hsu</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology, Chang Gung memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886-3-3281200</phone>
      <fax>+886-3-3280097</fax>
      <email>megamanx@adm.cgmh.org.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yi-Chun Hsu</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology, Chang Gung memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886-3-3281200</phone>
      <fax>+886-3-3280097</fax>
      <email>megamanx@adm.cgmh.org.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yi-Chun Hsu</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology, Chang Gung memorial Hospital, Taoyuan, 333, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886-3-3281200</phone>
      <fax>+886-3-3280097</fax>
      <email>megamanx@adm.cgmh.org.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>