<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82937">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000333314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised Controlled Trial of Chiropractic Care to Improve Risk of Falls and Sensorimotor Function in Older People</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised Controlled Trial of Chiropractic Care to Improve Risk of Falls and Sensorimotor Function in Older People</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Chiropractic and Sensorimotor Introduction</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postural stability, sensorimotor function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention was twelve weeks of chiropractic care. Chiropractic care involved the ongoing provision of care, whether a subjective complaint was present or not, with the intention of correcting spinal dysfunction, which is termed vertebral subluxation by chiropractors. Chiropractic care was provided at no charge by licensed chiropractors who have volunteered to assist with this study and who have at least five years clinical experience and practice in Auckland, New Zealand. On average each chiropractic visit will take approximately 20 minutes. The frequency of care was left up to the discretion of the chiropractor providing care.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group will receive usual care as well as a pamphlet that is produced by the New Zealand Accident Compensation Corporation about prevention of falls in older adults. Usual care will include any health care options that the participants wish to engage in during the course of the study including allopathic or other complimentary care. Usual care will continue throughout the nine and a half months that participants are involved in the trial.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study will be to assess the effect of chiropractic care on objective markers of sensorimotor function. The objective measures of sensorimotor function that were included in this study were choice stepping reaction time, postural stability, joint positions sense of the ankle, and the sound-induced flash illusion. All assessments were conducted at the New Zealand College of Chiropractic in Auckland, New Zealand.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcomes were measured at baseline then at 4 weeks and 12 weeks (at the completion of the intervention programme).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life measured using the SF36 version 2 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Community dwelling adults aged 65 years or older who permanently reside in or near the Ellerslie / Mount Wellington region of Auckland, New Zealand will be eligible to participate in this trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Volunteers will be ineligible if they are wheel-chair bound, or unable to remain standing unassisted for a minimum of one minute, as they will be unable to complete the required balance testing. Other exclusion criteria include presence of absolute contraindications to chiropractic care, being unable to comprehend the study information or consent processes, the known presence of severe cognitive, somatic or psychiatric impairment or disease, presence of a terminal illness and being unavailable to participate for one week or more during the study period due to planned travel arrangements or other commitments. A risk assessment for vertebrobasilar insufficiency / vertebral artery dissection (VBI / VAD) will also be conducted and at risk volunteers will be ineligible for inclusion until specialist referral confirms no  VBI/VAD exists.  Volunteers will also be ineligible if they have received chiropractic care within the previous six months or if they have received spinal manipulation during the previous six months from another healthcare provider.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be concealed by using an off-site schedule at a central adminsitration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation will be used</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Assessors will be blinded but subjects will be aware of which group they're assigned to.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/05/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>22/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand College of Chiropractic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>6 Harrison Rd
Mount Wellington
Auckland
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand College of Chiropractic and the Australian Spinal Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6 Harrison Rd 
Mount Wellington
Auckland
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Auckland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Falls are a major health concern for older adults. They are a significant cause of death, injury and loss of quality of life. In people over the age of 65, falls account for over 80% of injury related hospital admissions and they are the leading cause of unintentional injury related death in older adults. 

Falls often occur due to a decline in nervous system function with advancing age. This can lead to a loss of balance, or poor control of the limbs which dramatically increases the risk of falling. In the past ten years researchers have demonstrated that chiropractic adjustments can improve aspects of nervous system function including muscle reflexes, reaction time and the speed at which the brain processes information. This study will investigate the relationship between chiropractic care and components of the nervous system important for maintaining balance and preventing falls in older adults. To study this relationship the researchers will follow and assess two groups of older participants at regular intervals over a 16 week period. One group will be under regular chiropractic care for sixteen weeks and the other group will receive no chiropractic care during the study but will be offered the programme at the completion of the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Holt K, Haavik H, Murphy B, Chi Lun Lee A, Elley CR. Effectiveness of Chiropractic Care to Improve Sensorimotor Function Associated with Falls Risk in Older People: A Randomized Controlled Trial. J Manip Phys Ther. Approved for publication.

Holt K, Haavik H, Lee ACL, Murphy B &amp; Raina Elley R. (2014) Effectiveness of Chiropractic Care to Improve Sensorimotor Function Associated with Falls Risk in Older People: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Association of Chiropractic Colleges Research Agenda Conference, Meeting in Orlando, Florida, USA, March.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
P.O. Box 1030
Hamilton 3204</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTY 11/06/63</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/01/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropratic
6 Harrison Road
Mount Wellington
Auckland
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64-9-526-6789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelly.holt@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropratic
6 Harrison Road
Mount Wellington
Auckland
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64-9-526-6789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelly.holt@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic
6 Harrison Road
Mount Wellington
Auckland 1060
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelly.holt@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>