<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335446">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000390088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot study for the rapid alleviation of depression in depressed alcohol dependent persons using ketamine</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study for the rapid alleviation of depression in depressed alcohol dependent persons using ketamine</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>alcohol dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is utilising ketamine at sub-anaesthetic doses. Dose range of ketamine is 0.1 to 2mgs/kg intramuscular (IM).
All subjects are scheduled to receive 4 separate infusions of blinded ketamine/saline placebo, with each administration separated by ~7 days. IM doses of ketamine in cohort 1 will be 0.1, 0.25 and 0.5mg/kg. In cohort 2, doses will be 0.5, 1, and 2 mg/kg (note: there is a common dose level between groups). Placebo will be inserted randomly into the dosing sequence. Clinic visits for each subject are the ketamine dose procedure, Follow-up visits at day1, day 3 &amp; day 7 post infusion (a total 4 visits per participant). For each participant there is an ascending dose subject to safety and tolerability of preceding dose. As above the 2nd cohort has a higher dose range.</interventions>
    <comparator>Saline 0.9% IM as a bolus of 1ml</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects showing remission indicated by a  Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRAS) &lt;7.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The timepoints for the primary outcome are 2, 4, 24, 48, 72 and 168hrs post infusion of ketamine</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in alcohol consumption. Assessed at interview with timeline follow-back recording, Leeds Dependency Questionnaire, Negative Alcohol expectancy Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>2, 4, 24, 48, 72 and 168hrs post infusion of ketamine</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability based on self-report by interview and on Medication Side-effects Questionnaire by interview</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, post-infusion, 2, 4, 24, 48, 72 and 168h post infusion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychiatric symptoms: Symptom Checklist (SCL-90R), Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (M.I.N.I.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2, 4, 24, 48, 72 and 168hrs post infusion of ketamine</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnostic Statistical Manual - fourth edition, text revision (DSM-IV-TR) alcohol dependence; major depression with Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) scores &gt;20 able and willing to give informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current chaotic multiple substance use (excluding alcohol, and tobacco  see medication below); currently in active moderate to severe alcohol withdrawal; actively suicidal or homicidal; pregnancy, nursing or refusal to use a reliable method of birth control in female subjects; severe psychiatric symptoms for which hospitalisation is being seriously considered; evidence of significant cerebral, renal, thyroid or cardiac disease; severe liver disease or liver failure.
Medication: Disallowed medication: lamotrigine, memantine, amantadine, riluzole, N-acetylcysteine within 2 weeks; Monamine Oxidase Inhibitors (MAOIs) within 4 weeks; escalating doses of opioids.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrollment by referrals of eligible individuals at the local alcohol and drug service by the Principal Investigator (PI). The off-site research clinician administers the ketamine or placebo by numbered container which have been randomly allocated by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation created by a computer number sequence generator</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Stage 1: Open label IM ketamine 0.5mg/kg (single dose).
Stage 2: Double blind, randomised, placebo-controlled administration of single dose IM ketamine; doses 0 (saline placebo), 0.1, 0.5 or 1mg/kg.  All subjects in this stage are scheduled to receive 4 separate administrations of blinded ketamine/saline placebo, with each administration separated by ~7 days. Saline placebo will be inserted randomly into the dosing sequence</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Otago
Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 913
Dunedin 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago Research Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Otago
Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 913
Dunedin 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The co-existence of alcohol dependence and depression is common in clinical populations. The use of antidepressant drugs to treat depression is widespread however effects are modest and onset of effects are delayed. Availability of antidepressants with alternative pharmacological mechanisms, and potentially faster onset of action might be of particular benefit to this group of patients. One approach to developing novel antidepressants is via targeting the central glutamate system using Ketamine, a well established anaesthetic agent. Ketamine has the potential to rapidly alleviate depression and reduce alcohol consumption. This pilot study is to characterize the best use of ketamine for the rapid antidepressant treatment in depressed alcoholics. To date, most antidepressant data has been collected in patients without concomitant alcohol dependence, and therefore it is important to establish an appropriate dose-response and safety profile for ketamine in an alcohol-dependent population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lower South Ethics Committee
229 Moray Place
PO Box 5849, Dunedin 9001, NZ</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/05/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gavin Cape</name>
      <address>Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Otago 
P.O. Box 913, Dunedin 9054, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 3 474 7989</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 474 7934</fax>
      <email>gavin.cape@stonebow.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gavin Cape</name>
      <address>Dept of Psychological Medicine
University of Otago 
P.O. Box 913, Dunedin 9054, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 3 474 7989</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 474 7934</fax>
      <email>gavin.cape@stonebow.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>