<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367914">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000371594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Repeatability and diurnal variation of eye responses measured with Neuro-Ophthalmic Device (NODe)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Intra-participant repeatability and diurnal variation of eye movements and pupil size response using the Neuro-Ophthalmic Device (NODe) in healthy population </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI) or concussion</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>medically diagnosed psychiatric disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>epilepsy or any type of seizure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The NODe is a pre-release, prototype table top imaging device that consists of visual stimulus presentations through a standard tablet (iPAD like) and imaging hardware mounted inside of an enclosure which includes a nose-bridge and a chin-rest for patient alignment. The device intends to test neuro-pathology such as mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI or concussion) by assessing eye movements and pupil reactions in response to different visual stimuli presented on the tablet screen. 
The NODe has several features, including a very high frame capture rate that permit acquisition of highly-detailed data on direction of eye gaze and pupil diameter. The operator will instruct the participant on how the NODe exam will occur, including what to expect from the visual stimuli and how long the exam should take. Each test consists of a series of targets that the subject must follow with their gaze or a series of light flashes that will be presented while the participant focuses on a static target. 
The study will be conducted in two phases with each phase including 10 participants. The initial visit will include the participant performing the NODe tests repeatedly for 10 times, while the remaining 6 visits (2 visits per day) will test diurnal variation and will run NODe set of tests once in each visit.  The initial visit may take up to 2 hours, while the remaining 6 visits will take up to 15 minutes each to complete. The visits need not necessarily be on consecutive days, but will be conducted within the time period of a fortnight.</interventions>
    <comparator>It is a study to test repeatability and diurnal variation between measurements using the NODe. Therefore, there is no active control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Collection of a full set of NODe data including:
- pupil diameter (mm), pupil constriction velocity (deg/sec) and  latency (msec), pupil dilatation velocity (deg/sec) and  latency (msec), and duration (sec);
- saccadic amplitude (mm), accuracy (mean), velocity (deg/sec), latency (msec), number of damping saccades;
- relative pupillary response differences; and 
- relative saccadic response differences. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Ten times in the first visit and once at each of the remaining 6 visits.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective fatigue / anxiety ratings using a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to data collecting with NODe, at each of the 6 visits in each study phase.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective fatigue / anxiety ratings using a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following data collecting with NODe, ten times in the first visit and once each at the remaining 6 visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- 18 to 60 years of age 
- Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- medically diagnosed psychiatric disorder, with or without current medication
- history of significant head trauma or concussion or any known neurological problem
- medically diagnosed epilepsy or history of seizure
- In the medical examiners opinion, be intoxicated (alcohol or drugs) or have had more than 2 standard alcoholic drinks in the 4 hours prior to study visit
- Have undertaken any recreational drugs in the last 48 hours</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>none</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation: Approximately 10 participants are required within each phase in order to demonstrate a statistically significant difference between repeat days and between time points of at least 1x the within-subject standard deviation of each NODe eye response variable at the 5% level of significance and 90% power. The sample size is not adjusted for dropout rate. The sample size is determined non-statistically based on an empirical approximation of the number of participants necessary to draw conclusions about the data. These conclusions, including inter- and intra-subject variability, will be used to inform future study sample sizes.  
Data analysis: NODe derived pupil response and eye movements measurements will be recorded on a numeric continuous scale. Data will be summarised as means +/- standard deviations. Log or square root transformation may be required prior to data analysis. The pupil response and eye movement variables will be compared between repeat days and repeat visits within a day using, e.g. repeated measures ANOVA or Linear mixed model with repeated effects. Interactions will be tested and, if present, the significance will be determined within each visit / day using, e.g. paired t-test or repeated measures ANOVA based on the number of levels. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Percy Lazon de la Jara</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 5, 
Rupert Myers Building, North Wing, 
University of New South Wales, 
Gate 14, Barker Street, Kensington, 
Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Diagnostics Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>437, Miller Valley Road, Suite A, Prescott, AZ 86301</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study designed to determine intra-participant repeatability and diurnal variation of various eye reflexes using a Neuro-Ophthalmic Device (NODe). The NODe is a pre-release, prototype table top imaging device that consists of visual stimulus presentations through a standard tablet (iPAD like) and imaging hardware mounted inside of an enclosure which includes a nose-bridge and a chin-rest for patient alignment. The device intends to test neuro -pathology such as mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI or concussion) by assessing eye movements and pupil reactions in response to different visual stimuli presented on the tablet screen.   
The aim of this investigation is to determine the repeatability of this device in healthy participants with no previous history of concussion and diurnal variation of eye movements and pupil reaction. 
The study will be conducted in two phases with each phase including 10 participants. The initial visit will include the participant performing the NODe tests repeatedly for 10 times, while the remaining 6 visits (2 visits per day) will test diurnal variation and will run NODe set of tests once in each visit. The initial visit may take up to 2 hours, while the remaining 6 visits will take up to 15 minutes each to complete.
The instrument has not yet been released commercially, but does not contain any components that could potentially cause eye or other injury.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bellberry Limited. 229 Greenhill Road, Dulwich, South Australia, 5065 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 4, 
Rupert Myers building, North Wing,
Gate 14, UNSW, Barker Street, 
Kensington, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 6165</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 7401</fax>
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Eric Papas</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 4, 
Rupert Myers building, North Wing,
Gate 14, UNSW, Barker Street, 
Kensington, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 7489</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 7401</fax>
      <email>e.papas@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Eric Papas</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 4, 
Rupert Myers building, North Wing,
Gate 14, UNSW, Barker Street, 
Kensington, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 7489</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 7401</fax>
      <email>e.papas@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nisha Yeotikar</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute, Level 3, 
Rupert Myers building, North Wing,
Gate 14, UNSW, Barker Street, 
Kensington, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9385 7537</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 7401</fax>
      <email>n.yeotikar@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>