<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1425">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000274572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Postcard Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Suicide prevention amongst help-seeking adolescents: a postcard intervention study designed to reduce suicide risk among young people at risk of suicide who have been referred to a public mental health service.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Suicide risk</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Suicide</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomized controlled trial.  The intervention is receipt of a postcard enquiring about well-being, reminding about individual sources of help in times of crisis and containing a simple health promotion message. The postcard is received once a month for 12 months.  The treatment group will receive the monthly postcard plus any treatment required. </interventions>
    <comparator>The comparison group will also receive treatment as required but no postcard.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced risk of suicide as measured by reduced rates of suicidal behaviour and reduced rates of suicidal ideation.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 12 months (ie the end of the intervention) and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved self-esteem; improved help-seeking; improved sense of perceived social support; reduced rates of hopelessness and reduced symptoms of depression. </outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be measured at baseline, 12 months (ie the end of the intervention) and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Young people referred to ORYGEN Youth Health with a non-psychotic diosorder (Both males and females will be included in the study). 2. A recent or lifetime history of suicide risk as indicated by suicidal ideation or behaviour (including suicide attempts). 3. Resident in the Northwestern metropolitan region of Melbourne.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Known organic cause for presentation2. Intellectual disability3. Inability to speak English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be done by the statistician using a computer program. The trial researchers will not be involved in this.</concealment>
    <sequence>A simple randomisation using computer generated random numbers will be used</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>295</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 3455
Parramatta, NSW 2124
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 3455
Parramatta, NSW 2124
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of this study are to reduce suicidal behaviour and improve self-esteem amongst a cohort of adolescents identified as being at high-risk of suicidal behaviour, who are referred to ORYGEN Youth Health.   We aim to do this by replicating previous intervention studies which have shown that sending a regular postcard to adults at high risk of suicide enquiring about their well being has reduced subsequent suicidal behaviour. We further intend to add individually tailored information regarding sources of help to each postcard, as well as some basic information about self-help strategies aimed at reducing depression and anxiety.The overall hypothesis is that receipt of a regular postcard enquiring about well being and informing the young person about appropriate, previously identified sources of help will reduce suicidal behaviour, over the study period.
Specific hypotheses to be examined are that the receipt of a regular postcard will result in: 1) Decreased suicidal behaviour and ideation 2) A reduction in factors associated with suicide such as hopelessness and depression 3) Improved self-esteem and 4) An increase in perceived social support. We further hypothesise that: 5) There will be a positive association between reductions in suicidal behaviour and improved self-esteem and perceived support and 6) There will be a positive association between reduced suicidal behaviour and a reduction in hopelessness and depression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mental Health Research Ethics Committee; Royal Melbourne Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MHREC 2006.001</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jo Robinson</name>
      <address>ORYGEN Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville
Vic
3052</address>
      <phone>03 9342 2866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jo.robinson@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jo Robinson</name>
      <address>ORYGEN Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville
VIC
3052</address>
      <phone>03 9342 2866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jo.robinson@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>