<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363898">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000429752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Screening Education And Recognition by primary Care pHysician of Atrial Fibrillation for prevention of stroke (SEARCH-AF II)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In an ambulatory population over 65 years of age attending general practices, is a handheld single-lead ECG attached to an iPhone an acceptable and effective screening tool to identify atrial fibrillation?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SEARCH-AF II</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial fibrillation
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Receptionists in general practice clinics will be trained to screen eligible patients for atrial fibrillation using a handheld single-lead ECG (the AliveCor Heart Monitor for iPhone). This will be a one-off screening of approximately 30 seconds duration. Following the screening, the iPhone will transmit a pdf of the ECG recording to a secure website toghether with an automated computer diagnosis of whether the patient is likely to have atrial fibrillation or not. During the patient's consultation, the GP will log in to the secure website and review the ECG. The GP will advise the patient if any additional treatment is required.

The screening trial will be conducted over a 6 month period.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The feasibility and acceptability of screening for AF using a hand-held single-lead ECG device in people aged 65 years and over in the general practice setting. A detailed process evaluation will be undertaken to assess these outcomes. As part of this evaluation, selected patients, GPs and reception staff will be asked to participate in semi-structured interviews. The audio from these interviews will be recorded, then coded and analysed using grounded theory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of screening period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The satisfaction of GPs, reception staff and patients with the screening process in the general practice setting. As noted above in relation to primary outcome 1, this will be assessed through semi-structured interviews of selected GPs, reception staff and patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During and after the screening process.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Process measures, such as the time taken to complete the intervention, competing demands for practice reception staff time, and the attitudes of patients and staff involved in the intervention. As noted above in relation to primary outcome 1, this will be assessed through semi-structured interviews of selected GPs, reception staff and patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During and after the screening process.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Barriers (including technological barriers), enablers and other information relevant to the process of developing a larger-scale implementation study. This will be assessed through semi-structured interview data together with any other information gathered by the research team during the conduct of the study either directly or from any of the involved general practices.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of screening period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People will be eligible to participate if they are attending the general practice for a consultation with their GP and are aged 65 years or over.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria include:
a. diagnosis of a severe coexisting medical condition that would prevent participation (eg, dementia, terminal illness); or
b. the inability to read/understand the consent form and participant information statement in English.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/10/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute for Global Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bristol-Myers Squibb Company</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>345 Park Avenue
New York, New York
10154</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common heart arrhythmia affecting at least 240,000 Australians. Prevalence rises with age from approximately 1% of the whole population to 5% in those over 65 years. People with AF are up to seven times more likely to have a stroke than the general population, and AF related strokes are also likely to be more severe. In addition, one in every six strokes is AF related.

Stroke is highly preventable in AF with the use of appropriate thromboprophylaxis. Therefore early identification and appropriate evidence based management of AF could lead to subsequent stroke prevention, significant reduction in the overall stroke burden and substantial savings to the health system.


The study is designed to examine the feasibility of screening to identify undiagnosed AF in a primary care setting. Our hypothesis is that a simple primary care screening program may be effective in detecting those
with undiagnosed AF. The specific aims are to:
1.	Assess the feasibility and acceptability of screening for AF using a hand-held single-lead ECG device in people aged 65 years and over in the general practice setting.
2.	Assess the satisfaction of GPs, reception staff and patients with the screening process in the general practice setting.
3.	Examine process measures, such as the time taken to complete the intervention, competing demands for practice reception staff time, and the attitudes of patients and staff involved in the intervention. 
4.	Identify barriers (including technological barriers), enablers and other information relevant to the process of developing a larger-scale implementation study.

We propose a cross-sectional study offered in up to 5 general practices in the Sydney metropolitan area. People aged 65 and over, attending general practices will be invited to volunteer for the screening.

The screening will consist of an assessment with a handheld single-lead ECG device attached to an iPhone by the practice receptionist. This ECG will be transmitted to a secure website and reviewed by the patient's GP during their consultation.

The primary outcome measure will be the acceptability of the screening process. A process evaluation will also be undertaken to better appreciate factors that might influence sustainability beyond the trial setting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics
University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/135</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lis Neubeck</name>
      <address>Senior Research Fellow, Cardiovascular
Adjunct Senior Lecturer, Sydney Nursing School, University of Sydney
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8507 2521 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lneubeck@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jessica Orchard</name>
      <address>Project Officer, Cardiovascular
Adjunct Lecturer, School of Public Health, University of Sydney
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99934535 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jorchard@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lis Neubeck</name>
      <address>Senior Research Fellow, Cardiovascular
Adjunct Senior Lecturer, Sydney Nursing School, University of Sydney
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8507 2521 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lneubeck@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jessica Orchard</name>
      <address>Project Officer, Cardiovascular
Adjunct Lecturer, School of Public Health, University of Sydney
Level 10, King George V Building
83-117 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99934535 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jorchard@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>