<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335781">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000805077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>RESTORE: Recovery exercises and Stepping On after fracture.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Self-managed home exercise plus group-based discussion compared with usual care to improve physical functioning and prevent falls in older people who have completed rehabilitation for a lower limb or pelvic fracture: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RESTORE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Northern Sydney Central Coast Health (NSCCH)
Local Reference: Protocol 0905-089M</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lower limb and pelvic fracture in older people</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomised to the intervention group will receive home visits of 45-60 minutes duration from a physiotherapist. The physiotherapist will prescribe an individualised exercise program and use motivational interviewing and goal setting to encourage behaviour change with regard to exercise. The physiotherapists will conduct ten home visits throughout the 12-month study period and provide fortnightly phone calls. Participants will be encouraged to continue the exercises three times weekly at home. The program will involve the following features: exercise will be individually prescribed based on assessment of physical abilities; there will be an emphasis on functionally-relevant weight-bearing exercise designed primarily to reduce falls and disability by enhancing balance and functional abilities; and exercises will include repetitions of the sit-to-stand movement, semisquats from a standing position, reaching in standing, forward, backward and sideways walking and stepping up onto blocks. The exercise intervention is suitable for people after lower limb or pelvic fracture on the basis of previous work led by Investigators Sherrington, Moseley, Lord and Cameron. 

Intervention group participants will also be offered fall prevention education through individualised advice from the physiotherapist or attendance at the group based Stepping On program. The Stepping On program was developed by Chief Investigator Clemson as implemented by the NSW Department of Health: weekly 2-hour group discussion sessions for seven weeks. The Stepping On content will be relevant to people with fall-related lower limb or pelvic fracture and will cover coping with visual loss and regular visual screening, medication management, environmental and behavioural home safety, and community safety. Group sessions will be held in rooms at local community centres or hospitals. Transport will be provided for those who would otherwise be unable to attend the sessions. Each program will be attended by up to 13 people. The group sessions will be facilitated by a occupational therapist or other health professional. The group sessions will be completed within the 12-month study period, with the timing depending on availability of a Stepping On program. Individualised fall prevention advice from the study physiotherapists will cover similar topic areas and will provided to participants who are unable or unwilling to attend the Stepping On groups, those for whom no local group is available and those who do not meet eligibility criteria for the NSW health Stepping On programs eg those who use walking aids. The individualised fall prevention advice will be provided at each physiotherapy home visit.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care for the duration of one year. Usual care is a 
combination of aged care and health services that are 
routinely provided. They may include referral to a physiotherapist or falls clinic.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility-related disability will be assessed with the Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) and the computerised version of the Boston University Activity Measure for Post Acute Care (AM-PAC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation The AM-PAC will also be administered by phone at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The life role participation aspect of functioning will be assessed using the Late Life Functioning and Disability Instrument, Disability Component.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of falls</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed as the total number of falls occurring in the 12 months after randomisation as assessed by monthly calendars and phone calls.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital re-admission rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly via calendars for the first 12 months after randomisation. With data linkage at 2 and 4 years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls risk using physiological Profile Assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frailty will be assessed using a continuous scale based on the Fried criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance and mobility will be assessed with individual components of the Physiological Profile Assessment (PPA), Short Physical Performance Battery (SBBP) and the Step Test, maximal balance range, co-ordinated stability, choice stepping reaction time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional status will be assessed indirectly using Body Mass Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity will be assessed using the Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain will be assessed on a 7-point scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls efficacy will be assessed with the short version of the Falls Efficacy Scale-International.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood will be assessed using the Geriatric Depression Scale and the Positive and Negative Affect Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life will be assessed using the European Quality of Life-5 dimensions (EQ-5D) and the Short Form 12-item Survey(SF-12).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after randomisation. The EQ-5D will also be administered by phone at 3, 6, and 9 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Questions about self-rated fear of falling and balance. The Questions about self-rated fear of falling and balance were designed by CI Lord and have been used in previous trials. The participant is asked to report how they feel their balance is, using a 5 point scale (excellent, very good, good, fair, poor), and to report how afraid they are of falling, using a 5 point scale (not at all, little bit, moderately, quite a lot, extremely).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Stages of Change Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of walking aid, assessed via participant self-report of a walking aid a) usually used indoors and b) usually used outdoors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assistance from others with daily tasks. Measured as the number of times the participant has received assistance from any agencies to do each of 7 tasks, and the number of times the participant has received regular assistance from family or friends  to do each of the 7 tasks</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mini Nutritional Assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-system and community-service contact. These are assessed via participant self-report on monthly calendars. The participant records all appointments with a GP, medical specialist, allied health, paid agency services. Inpatient hospital and emergency department contact will be assessed using data linkage via the NSW CHeReL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 month period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of fallers. Participants will be asked to record falls on 12 one-month calendars and to return completed calendars in pre-paid envelopes to the research centre each month. If calendars are not returned, participants will be telephoned to ask about their fall history for that month. Any fall reported on the calendars will be followed up with a phone call to obtain further information about the details and consequences of the fall.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People with a fall-related lower limb or pelvic fracture who have completed active physiotherapy and/or rehabilitation and who are living at home or in a hostel</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Residing in nursing home, Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) under 24, insufficient English language skills, inability  to walk 10 metres despite assistance from another person or  walking aid, a progressive neurological disease e.g. Parkinsons disease and a medical condition precluding exercise  e.g. unstable cardiac disease, uncontrolled hypertension, uncontrolled metabolic diseases, large abdominal aneurysm</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The research assistant screens for inclusion criteria. If the person satisfies criteria the research assistant completes baseline assessment then contacts the lead investigator who will determine group allocation. The lead investigator will not be directly involved in participant recruitment. Allocation therefore involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be determined using a computer generated random number schedule with randomly permuted block sizes. The schedule will be developed by the lead investigator who will not be directly involved in participant recruitment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/11/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>350</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>336</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2067</postcode>
    <postcode>2095</postcode>
    <postcode>2217</postcode>
    <postcode>2250</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Cathie Sherrington</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The George Institute for Global Health, 
PO Box M201, Missenden Road, NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Lindy Clemson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Sydney, Corner City Road and Butlin Avenue, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Stephen Lord</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA) - Formerly known as the Prince of Wales Medical Research Institute. Barker Street, Randwick, NSW, 2031</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Kirsten Howard</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Sydney, Corner City Road and Butlin Avenue, Camperdown, NSW, 2050.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Anne Moseley</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The George Institute for Global Health, 
PO Box M201, 
Missenden Road,  NSW 2050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Constance Vogler</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Geriatrician, 
Royal North Shore Hospital, Reserve Road, St Leonards, NSW 2065</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Ian Cameron</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Royal Rehabilitation Centre Sydney, Rehabilitation Studies 
Unit, 
PO Box 6 Ryde NSW 1680</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Assoc. Prof Jacqueline Close,</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Geriatrician
Prince of Wales Hospital, Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof David Sonnabend</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Orthopaedic Unit 
Royal North Shore Hospital, Reserve Road, St Leonards, NSW 2065</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)funded clinical trial will assess the effect of an exercise-based self-management program for older people who have suffered a lower limb or pelvic fracture in the last two years. The intervention involves a combination of physiotherapy home-visits to establish a home-exercise program and the group-based the Stepping On program. Motivational interviewing and goal setting will be used to encourage behaviour change with regard to exercise and safe community mobility. Three hundred and fifty participants will be recruited from hospitals, health professional practices and general advertising. Primary outcomes are mobility-related disability, community participation and falls. Cost-effectiveness analysis will be undertaken for the primary outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HARBOUR Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) of Northern Sydney Central Coast Health (NSCCH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Reserach Office, Level 4, Vindin House, Royal North 
Shore Hospital, St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/05/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/HARBR/57</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/04/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health,
PO Box M201, 
Missenden Road, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9657 0300</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9657 0301</fax>
      <email>csherrington@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, 
PO Box M201, 
Missenden Road, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9657 0300</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9657 0301</fax>
      <email>csherrington@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health,
PO Box M201, 
Missenden Road, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>csherrington@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
PO Box M201
Missenden Rd NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9657 0386</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>csherrington@george.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>