<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365950">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000319673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation and comparison of Autonomic Nervous System function with neurophysiological interventions such as pupillometry and Mangina Test in patients with Myasthenia Gravis and healthy subjects

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the cholinergic hypothesis with neurophysiological interventions such as Pupillometry and Mangina-Test in Myasthenia Gravis patients (MG)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-3871</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>‘Nil known’ </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>patients with Myasthenia Gravis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All subjects underwent pupillometric measurements. All participants were assessed on a single occasion only. Pupillary measurements were taken with a monocular and fully automated system.Participants remained for 2 min in darkness, and 5 flashes were administered afterwards (inter-stimulus interval was 30sec). Stimulus duration was 20 msec, and the luminance 24.6 cd/m2. Each eye was tested separately. The flash was placed at a distance of 30 cm from the eye.</interventions>
    <comparator>The original psychophysical paper-and-pencil version of the Mangina-Test was used. The Mangina-Test was administered according to the steps described in the Manual for the Mangina Diagnostic Tool of Visual Perception. This test is composed of 44 simple and 44 complex original geometrical visual stimuli, presented with an increasing degree of difficulty. One simple and one complex stimulus are presented simultaneously. The task consists of exactly identifying and tracing completely with a fine marker the simple stimulus which is masked within a complex configuration of stimuli varying in direction, spatial orientation, size, dimension, and shape in a limited span of time.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Two pupillometric indices Maximum Velocity of Constriction (VCmax) and Maximum Acceleration of Constriction (ACmax) are governed mainly by the action of the Parasympathetic Nervous System, through Acetylcholine. The Myasthenic patients showed decreased VCmax and ACmax compared to healthy controls and significant decreased scores in the Mangina-Test as compared to healthy controls. Accordingly, the results of this study demonstrate that the Central Nervous System is affected and that MG has central cholinergic effects manifested by cognitive dysfunction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at time of pupillometric measurements and the original psychophysical paper-and-pencil version of the Mangina-Test were performed on the participants.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>From the pupillometric results we assumed that the iris sphincter smooth muscle is affected in Myasthenia Gravis patients</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at time of pupillometric measurements and the original psychophysical paper-and-pencil version of the Mangina-Test were performed on the participants</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients were diagnosed with MG (mean time from the diagnosis was until the beginning of the study 2.9+/-0.2 years) using the established and diagnosis criteria. Specifically, their diagnosis was based on one hand on the clinical symptoms (fatigue during the day, etc), and on the other hand, on the laboratory findings (presence of positive antibodies for the AchR, positive response at the repeated stimuli test). Apart from these, MG patients showed an improvement of the muscle strength following the intake of edrophonium chloride and reacted positively to Mestinon. It was a key inclusion criterion that participants previously showed an improvement of the muscle strength following the intake of edrophonium chloride and reacted positively to Mestinon because from this we were sure that the Myasthenia Gravis Diagnosis was correct.
All patients were free of any other neurological, ophthalmological, physical or mental disease and their visual acuity, corrected or not, were 20/20. Moreover, they had symmetrical pupils and no past history of ocular operations or diseases affecting the pupil and were not being treated at that time with anticholinergics, steroids, sympathomimetics, beta-blockers or other agents affecting the Pupil Light Reflex (PLR). Also, the basic precondition for participation was a mini mental score greater than or equal to 22. All measurements were performed between 09.00 and 10.00 hours after the participants had had a full eight-hour sleep.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>34</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> If MG patients do not show an improvement of the muscle strength following the intake of edrophonium chloride and reacted positively to Mestinon. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data were analyzed with Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS, Chicago, Illinois, USA), version 20.0 software for Windows. The  number of participants needed to achieve study objectives was determined with G*power analysis. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was used to examine the normality of the distribution. Changes of variables within the groups at baseline and the end of the study were evaluated by a One-Way ANOVA with group being the independent variable. The significance level was p&lt;0.05. Finally, the Pearson correlation was calculated between each pair of pupillometric parameters for each patient group and for the total group of the healthy people. Moreover, the correlation of each pupillometric parameter with age was also estimated. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>26/06/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state>Thessaloniki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Antonia Kaltsatou</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AHEPA University Hospital of Thessaloniki
1 Kyriakidi Street, Thessaloniki, 54636, Greece</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Greece</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Antonia Kaltsatou</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>22, Dim. Gounari Str
PC 54621, Thessaloniki</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Greece</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dimitris Fotiou</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dimitris Fotiou
1 Kyriakidi Street, Thessaloniki, 54636, Greece</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Greece</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many studies have demonstrated that the central cholinergic system is important in mediating cognitive processes of learning and memory. Nonetheless, many studies have supported the hypothesis of Central Nervous System cholinergic involvement in Myasthenia Gravis.More specifically, there is some evidence that Myasthenia Gravis has central cholinergic effects manifested by cognitive dysfunction. Hence, the aim of this study was to investigate with established psychophysiological methods such as pupillometry and concomitantly with the Mangina-Test, the hypothesis of Central Nervous System cholinergic involvement in patients with Myasthenia Gravis. All participants were informed about the study procedure and provided written informed consent and all the experiments were approved by the Ethical Committee of the AHEPA University Hospital based on the Helsinki Declaration.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> the Ethical Committee of the AHEPA University Hospital based on the Helsinki Declaration</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> 1 Kyriakidi Street, Thessaloniki, 54636</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonia Kaltsatou</name>
      <address>Aristotle University of Thessaloniki,
AHEPA Hospital,
 1 Kyriakidi Street,
 Thessaloniki, PC 54636</address>
      <phone>+306938767967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>akaltsat@phed.auth.gr/ kaltsatou@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonia Kaltsatou</name>
      <address>22, Dim. Gounari Str
PC 54621
Thessaloni, GREECE

Aristotle University of Thessaloniki,
AHEPA Hospital,
 1 Kyriakidi Street,
 Thessaloniki, PC 54636</address>
      <phone>+306938767967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>akaltsat@phed.auth.gr/ kaltsatou@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonia Kaltsatou</name>
      <address>22, Dim. Gounari Str
PC 54621
Thessaloni, GREECE

Aristotle University of Thessaloniki,
AHEPA Hospital,
 1 Kyriakidi Street,
 Thessaloniki, PC 54636</address>
      <phone>+306938767967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>akaltsat@phed.auth.gr/ kaltsatou@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>