<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370274">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000750482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of intra-articular steroid injection for inflamed atlantoaxial joint in patients with rheumatoid arthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with rheumatoid arthritis and inflamed atlantoaxial joint, is intra-articular steroid injection,compared with systemic steroid administration effective and safe?  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>atlantoaxial joint arthritis in rheumatoid patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>(AS) group, received intra-articular steroid injection for atlantoaxial joint following failure of systemic steroids (prednisolone, oral tablet, 5 mg/3 times daily for 2 weeks) administration as part of the trial to resolve inflammation of the atlanto-axial joint assessed by MRI , (adherence to treatment is confirmed by empty drug packet return), in addition to intramuscular methotrexate 12.5 mg per week and hydroxychloroquine, oral tablet 200 mg, 2 tablets per day (regular treatment for patients with rheumatoid arthritis that continues for life).Injection technique: With the patient placed in the prone position and a pillow under the chest to allow for slight neck flexion, the C-arm is brought to the head of the table in an anteroposterior direction. The C-arm is rotated in a cephalad-caudad direction to better visualize the lateral atlantoaxial joint (AAJ). The needle insertion site is marked on the skin overlying the lateral third of the AAJ. The skin is prepped and draped in the usual sterile fashion, and a skin wheel is raised with 3 ml of lidocaine 1 % at the insertion site. Then, a 22 G 3 and 1/2 inches blunt needle is advanced towards the posterolateral aspect of the inferior margin of the inferior articular process of the atlas (C1). Then, a lateral view is obtained. The needle is withdrawn slightly, directed towards the posterolateral aspect of the (AAJ), and advanced for 2 millimetres. Usually a distinctive pop is felt signalling entering the joint cavity. After careful negative aspiration for blood or cerebrospinal fluid, 0.2 ml of omnipaque dye is injected to verify intra-articular placement of the tip of the needle under direct real-time fluoroscopy to check for inadvertent intra-arterial injection. Anteroposterior and lateral views are obtained to insure that the contrast agent remained confined to the joint cavity without escape to the surrounding structures and finally, 1.0 ml of a mixture of bupivacaine 0.5 % and 20 mg of triamcinolone is injected. The injection will be performed once (will not repeated) bilaterally ( both AAJ). The injection will be done by senior staff pain clinician.</interventions>
    <comparator>(SS) group, following failure of systemic steroids (prednisolone, oral tablet, 5 mg/3 times daily for 2 weeks) as part of this trial to resolve inflammation of the atlanto-axial joint assessed by MRI, patients received systemic steroid with oral prednisolone, tablet, 5 mg, 2 tablet/8 h/ for 2 weeks tapered by 10 % reduction every 3 days as part of this trial, adherence to treatment is confirmed by empty drug packet return, in addition to intramuscular methotrexate 12.5 mg per week and hydroxychloroquine, oral tablet 200 mg, 2 tablets per day (regular treatment for patients with rheumatoid arthritis that continuess for life).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resolution of MRI findings of inflammation of AAJ</outcome>
      <timepoint>after 3 month from the procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck pain intensity assessed by VAS score reported by rheumatologist, on behalf of the participants. </outcome>
      <timepoint>every 2 weeks for 3 month following injection procedure.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck mobility assessed by rheumatologist using Oswestry cervical pain quetionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>every 2 weeks for 3 month following injection procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Side effects of AAJ injection procedure e.g. intrathecal or epidural spread of injectate and nerve injury assessed by the injectionist (senior pain clinitian)using fluroscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>during injection and immediately following the injection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with rheumatoid arthritis with MRI findings of atlantoaxial joint inflammation and failure of resolution after 2 weeks systemic steroid administration</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Coagulopathy, allergy to contrast material, pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Assuit</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Diab Fuad Hetta</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>south egypt cancer institute, 2 el methaque st., assuit university, assuit city, 71111, egypt</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diab Fuad Hetta</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>south egypt cancer institute, 2 el methaque st., assuit university, assuit city, 71111, egypt</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rheumatoid arthritis  is a chronic inflammatory disease involving multiple joints. The cervical spine is often affected, and cases involving atlantoaxial joint can lead to instability. Anterior atlantoaxial subluxation in RA patients can lead to posterior neck pain or occipital headache. intraarticular steroid injection of AAJ could stop the joint destruction </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical comittee of faculty of medicine,Assiut university</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>faculty of medicine, 1 university st., assuit university, assuit city,71111, egypt</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ASSMED20161125</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Diab Fuad Hetta</name>
      <address>south egypt cancer institute, 2 el methaque st., assuit university, assuit city, 71111, egypt</address>
      <phone> +201091090009 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>diabhetta25@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Diab Fuad Hetta</name>
      <address>south egypt cancer institute, 2 el methaque st., assuit university, assuit city, 71111, egypt</address>
      <phone> +201091090009 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>diabhetta25@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Diab Fuad Hetta</name>
      <address>south egypt cancer institute, 2 el methaque st., assuit university, assuit city, 71111, egypt</address>
      <phone> +201091090009 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>diabhetta25@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>