<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373259">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001026314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Measurement of Physical Activity during General Inpatient Rehabilitation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of hospital-based interventions to increase physical activity in patients on a general rehabilitation ward</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-9753</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Orthopaedic conditions - joint replacement</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Orthopaedic conditions - fracture(s)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Deconditioning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lower limb amputation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Brain dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Neurological conditions</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pain syndromes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Orthopaedic conditions - all other</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac conditions</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary conditions</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Major Multiple Trauma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Cord Dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Occupational therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group
The study intervention is to implement changes in ward practices and culture to increase the physical activity of participants during inpatient rehabilitation. Interventions aimed at increasing participants physical activity on the rehabilitation ward. The interventions - specific frequency and components - are determined by the treating physiotherapist based on participant preference and level of physical function. The interventions will include, but not be limited to, current inpatient rehabilitation standard care plus having meals (breakfast, lunch and dinner) in a common dining room; walking a lap of the ward prior to attendance in the dining room or therapy gym; increased group therapy (balance, community access and gardening) during the week; and increased therapy on weekends (individual and group exercise sessions). Balance groups will occur three times a week, at least one of which will be in addition to the current exercise group and community access groups will occur weekly. 

Materials
Participants who consent to participate in the study will have an activity monitor (ActivPAL micro) attached to their thigh with a water proof dressing, preferably on the less disabled lower limb. The activity monitor will be removed and reapplied weekly, so that data can be uploaded onto computer and the activity monitor can be recharged. This will be repeated until the participant has been discharged from inpatient rehabilitation. 

Rehabilitation/procedures/activities
Participants will undergo rehabilitation. As a consequence, they may be involved in a number of activities delivered by a multidisciplinary team. Medical ward rounds, meals and activities (education sessions, games, Diversional Therapy) in the dining room, group therapy, individual therapy sessions delivered by allied health disciplines.

Who will deliver the intervention
All members of the rehabilitation team (medical, nursing and allied health) will deliver interventions that aim to increase each participants standing and walking time. For example, based on the level of physical function of participants as assessed by the treating physiotherapist, will be encouraged by staff to walk a lap of the ward prior to and following attendance in the dining room (for meals and/or education sessions) or the therapy room/gym. In addition, participants therapy schedule will be on a centralised timetable mounted on a wall (within the ward) that participants will be able to view by walking to view the timetable. This timetable will be completed by the rehabilitation team. Furthermore, additional groups will be run by physiotherapists, allied health assistants and /or occupational therapists such as - but not limited to - balance, community access, and gardening groups. Finally, therapy will also occur on weekends delivered by physiotherapists and/or physiotherapy assistants for approximately a total of 24 hours over the weekend.

Mode of delivery
Some therapy will occur in as individual sessions and others will be in the form of group therapy.

Dosage/duration/intensity
The intervention will occur during the participants inpatient rehabilitation admission. There will not be any specific dose, duration or intensity. Participants will be treated by physiotherapists and/or the physiotherapy assistant at least daily, often twice daily, in individual and/or group sessions. 

Location
Inpatient rehabilitation ward</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group
Current inpatient rehabilitation standard care. This involves assessment and management by the multidisciplinary team (medical, nursing and allied health). Specifically, interventions such as strengthening exercises, group exercise classes, weekly garden group and breakfast club, upper limb therapy, lunch in the dining room for less than half the ward and weekend physiotherapy of up to 16 hours (individual and group exercise sessions).

Materials
Participants who consent to participate in the study will have an activity monitor (ActivPAL micro) attached to their thigh with a water proof dressing, preferably on the less disabled lower limb. The activity monitor will be removed and reapplied weekly, so that data can be uploaded onto computer and the activity monitor can be recharged. This will be repeated until the participant has been discharged from inpatient rehabilitation. 

Rehabilitation/procedures/activities
Participants will be undergoing rehabilitation. As a consequence, they may be involved in a number of activities delivered by a multidisciplinary team. Medical ward rounds, meals and activities (education sessions, games, Diversional Therapy) in the dining room, group therapy, individual therapy sessions delivered by allied health disciplines.

Who will deliver the control intervention
Current inpatient rehabilitation practice involves therapy delivered by allied health practitioners (occupational therapists, physiotherapists, physiotherapy assistant, speech pathologists and dietitians).

Mode of delivery
Currently, therapy occurs in as individual sessions and/or group therapy. Specifically, physiotherapy groups occur daily (Monday to Friday) and a garden group occurs weekly.

Dosage/duration/intensity
Current therapy practice will occur during the participants inpatient rehabilitation admission. There will not be any specific dose, duration or intensity. Participants will be treated by physiotherapists and/or the physiotherapy assistant at least daily, often twice daily, in individual and/or group sessions. 

Location
Inpatient rehabilitation ward</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step count using activity monitors (ActivPAL micros) taped to the less disabled lower limb during the participant's admission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Five days post admission</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the motor component of the Functional Independence Measure (m-FIM)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission and discharge (m-FIM)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inpatient length of stay utilising data from the Sydney Local Health District Performance Unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission and discharge dates</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in sedentary, standing and stepping time using activity monitors (ActivPAL micros) taped to the less disabled lower limb during the participant's admission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission and discharge dates</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the number of transitions (sit to stands) using activity monitors (ActivPAL micros) taped to the less disabled lower limb during the participant's admission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission and discharge dates</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cadence using activity monitors (ActivPAL micros) taped to the less disabled lower limb during the participant's admission.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission and discharge dates</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People admitted to the inpatient rehabilitation ward</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants who are unable to consent, or who's valued other (family, carer, guardian) is unable to consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>No</concealment>
    <sequence>No</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Prospective pre-post study. 
This research will compare current practice, with changes in ward practice aimed at increasing physical activity </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Participant numbers: 322 (161 in each group)

The typical improvement in step count across the first 5 days of an admission with current management is approximately 482 steps. We consider that an additional improvement in step count of 400 steps would make the intervention worthwhile. We calculate that a sample size of 322 participants (161 per group) will be sufficient to identify a treatment effect on improvement in step count of 400 steps or more as statistically significant, given: 
- an anticipated SD of 1176 (based on an audit of activity monitor data for 97 patients from the unit);
- power of 80% and a statistical significance threshold of 0.05;
- worst-case loss to follow-up rate of 15%.

Data will be analysed using the statistics software package SPSS. For outcomes with normally distributed data, we will perform an ANOVA with adjustment for baseline values and any other strongly associated variables as covariates. If the data are not normally distributed we will use a non-parametric equivalent.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>322</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/07/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Balmain Hospital - Balmain</hospital>
    <postcode>2041 - Balmain</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sandeep Gupta</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Balmain Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Indu Nair</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Jane Linton</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Bridget Canham</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Garry Jones</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the project is to measure the physical activity of participants on the rehabilitation ward over their inpatient hospital admission.

The research design is a prospective pre-足post study.

Data will be collected on 161 participants (control group) over their inpatient rehabilitation admission. Changes to ward practice will be then be implemented. These changes include, but are not be limited to, increased group therapy (balance, community access, gardening), meals in the dining area and education sessions. Data will then be collected on another 161 participants (treatment group) over their inpatient rehabilitation admission.

An activity monitor (ActivPAL micro) will be taped and a waterproof dressing applied to one thigh on each participant's mid足thigh. The activity monitor measures sedentary (lying/sitting), standing, stepping and metabolic equivalent time (MET); as well as step and transition (sit to stand) counts and cadence. The activity monitor will removed weekly, data uploaded to computer and into Sydney Local Health District Targeted Activity and Reporting System (STARS) in the late afternoon, charged and reapplied the following morning. Data from the activity monitors will be matched to participant data from STARS. Specifically, Australian National Subacute and Non足acute Patient (AN足-SNAP) classification, change in motor Functional Independence Measure (m-FIM) and length of stay.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>AU/1/007D218; X17-0132; HREC/17/RPAH/195</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373259-Ethics Approval letter.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373259-Master Protocol - Physical activity.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373259-Master Consent Form Participant- Physical Activity.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373259-Master Information for Participants V1.1- Physical activity.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Sandeep Gupta</name>
      <address>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9395 2099</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9395 2119</fax>
      <email>Sandeep.Gupta@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Sandeep Gupta</name>
      <address>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9395 2099</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9395 2119</fax>
      <email>Sandeep.Gupta@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Sandeep Gupta</name>
      <address>Balmain Hospital
29 Booth St
Balmain NSW 2041</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9395 2099</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9395 2119</fax>
      <email>Sandeep.Gupta@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>