<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362427">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000466842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Carbetocin vs Oxytocin at Emergency Caesarean Section</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Carbetocin vs Oxytocin (Syntocinon) to Improve Uterine Tone at Emergency Caesarean Section</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>post partum haemorrhage at emergency caesarean section</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>100 microgram intravenous(IV) injection of carbetocin will be given immediately after delivery of the baby at emergency caesarean section.</interventions>
    <comparator>two groups will be included in the trial. both will receive treatment immediately after the baby is born at emergency caesarean section. control: 5 unit syntocinon bolus IV Intervention: 100 micrograms carbetocin IV</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for further uterotonics: which ones.
the operator will subjectively judge if the uterus is atonic. when atony is identified the normal protocol for post partum haemorrhage will be initiated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after delivery of the fetus and administration of the chosen oxytocic, before closure of the rectal sheath at caesarean section</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative haemoglobin  compared to pre-op</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 1 post caesarean section</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for uterine massage for &gt;5minutes
This will be subjectively asessd by the operator</outcome>
      <timepoint>after delivery of the fetus and administration of the chosen oxytocic, bofore closure of the rectal sheath at caesarean section</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total subjective estimated blood loss in theatre. Suction is used to suck the excess blood into a measuring container. this amount will be recorded and any swabs soaked with blood will be weighed. this amount will be added to the suction amount to give the estimated blood loss</outcome>
      <timepoint>after closure of the skin at caesarean section</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-op blood loss (ie not from EBL in theatre).
any swabs/pads will be weighed to estimate the amount of blood lost.</outcome>
      <timepoint>from leaving theatre post caesarean section until 24 hours post caesarean section ( ie primary post partum haemorrhage)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fundal height above/below the umbilicus day 1</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 1 post caesarean section</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>anyone having an emergency caesarean section at Frankston Hospital who have given consent to be part of the trial. Age&gt;16. &gt;37 weeks gestation. &lt;3 previous caesarean sections. epidural or spinal anaesthesia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>previous adverse reaction to carbetocin/syntocinon. History of vascular, hepatic or renal problems. Lack of consent. &lt;37 weeks gestation. Placenta praevia. Placental abruption. &gt;2 caesarean sections. Patients having an elective caesarean section. general anaesthetic</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>a  list of numbers which are randomly assigned either syntocinon or carbetocin will be generated by a computer programme. patients will receive each number in consecutive order. the patient will receive the corresponding vial which has been blinded at pharmacy level.</concealment>
    <sequence>the sequence will be produced from a computer programme that generates random lists. this will be done at pharmacy level and none of the oprating or anaesthetic doctors will have access to this.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Carole-anne Whigham</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Womens Health Unit
Frankston Hospital
Hastings Road
Frankston
3199
Vic</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Frankston Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hastings Road
Frankston
3199
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor A Trivedi</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Womens Health Unit
Frankston Hospital
Hastings Road
Frankston
3199
Vic</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Reducing maternal mortality rates has been a worldwide goal for many years. Post partum haemorrhage is the main cause of obstetric haemorrhage accounting for 14 million cases worldwide. It is the leading cause of maternal death throughout the world. In Victoria, Australia, in 2002 the post partum haemorrhage rate was 9.2%. Post partum haemorrhage is associated with ICU admission, the need for blood transfusion and a longer hospital stay, which is at considerable cost. The majority of post partum haemorrhage is caused by uterine atony, so finding an effective agent to prevent uterine atony is paramount in reducing maternal morbidity and mortality. Operative delivery is a known risk factor for PPH therefore improving uterine tone at caesarean section is an important parameter if rates are to be reduced. Carbetocin is a synthetic long-acting analogue of oxytocin used to improve uterine tone. Studies have shown that a single intra-muscular injection of carbetocin is more effective than syntocinon infusion for preventing uterine atony at elective caesarean section, and this is the current practice at Frankston Hospital. Carbetocin is currently licensed in Australia to reduce uterine atony at elective caesarean section, however the efficacy at emergency caesarean section is unclear. In this prospective randomised trial we aim to discover if carbetocin 100 micrograms iv or Syntocinon 5 unit iv bolus, is more effective at improving post partum haemorrhage rates in emergency caesarean sections, by measures of need for further uterotonics, need for &gt;5 minutes uterine massage and haemoglobin drop.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peninsula Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mount Eliza Centre
    Jacksons Road
    Mt Eliza VIC 3930</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC/12/PH/28</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/04/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carole-Anne Whigham</name>
      <address>Womens Health Unit
Frankston Hospital
Hastings Road
Frankston
3199
Vic</address>
      <phone>+61404644029</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.a.whigham@doctors.net.uk</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Amar Trivedi</name>
      <address>Womens Health Unit
Frankston Hospital
Hastings Road
Frankston
3199
Vic</address>
      <phone>+61427215515</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ATrivedi@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>