<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335908">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001027000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MindWise - Promoting mental health literacy at Victoria University</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>MindWise - an evaluation of an educational campaign to raise mental health literacy amongst students and staff of Victoria University</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>alcohol misuse</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The following intervention elements will carried out at intervals throughout the study period of two years. 


MindWise stalls at pre-existing Victoria University campus events (such as Orientation Week, Safety Week and Wellness Day). Each event will last for between one and five days and there will be several such events throughout the study period.

MindWise website/Facebook page will be available throughout the study period for participants to access when they wish.

Mailout of Taking Care of Yourself and Your Family to staff members. Mailout 12-hour Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) course via e-learning CD to interested parties. These will be done twice during the study period.

Links to MindWise student factsheets on student electronic learning portal (always available).

Monthly emails to staff containing MindWise factsheets.


The following resources or information will be provided. Participants can access these at their own pace: mental health factsheets from beyondblue, Reachout and MindWise, National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) alcohol guidelines, MindWise coffee mugs with mental health message and MindWise showbags containing beyondblue materials and Victoria University services for students and staff, check your drinking quiz, pour a standard drink activity and self-care ideas activity. 

 

The overall duration of the study is two years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Campuses not given the intervention (active no-treatment group)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>depression and anxiety levels (using K6 questionnaire measure of psychological distress)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>alcohol usage (using Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT))</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>recognition of mental health problem (using depression vignette from Kitchener &amp; Jorm, 2002b)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>help-seeking actions for mental health problem (using depression vignette from Kitchener &amp; Jorm, 2002b)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>beliefs about which interventions are helpful for mental health problems (adapted from Kitchener &amp; Jorm, 2002b)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>social distance towards people with mental health problems (using scale by Link et al, 1999)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>stigmatizing attitudes towards people with mental health problems (personal stigma) (using scale by Griffiths et al, 2004)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>help-seeking actions for own mental health problem (scale adapted from Kitchener &amp; Jorm, 2002b)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mental health first aid actions given to anyone in your family or close circle of friends (assessed by questionnaire dapted from Kitchener &amp; Jorm, 2002b)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>perceptions of how well the Victoria University community supports students/staff with mental health problems (assessed by questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>knowledge of NHMRC alcohol guidelines (assessed by questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>help-seeking for alcohol misuse (assessed by questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, at end of year 1 and end of year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>student or staff member of Victoria University</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants undertaking a course equal to or less than 3 months duration. If parental consent was denied for participants aged between 16 to 17. Students who did not feel proficient in English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A cluster randomized controlled design will be used, with campuses constituting the clusters. Reply paid registration forms were given out by researchers to students and staff at 9 Victoria University campuses. Potential participants across all campuses were given a standardized introduction to the project and encouraged to register for the trial on the spot, without knowing whether their campus was intervention or control. Allocation was not concealed from the researchers.</concealment>
    <sequence>Nine of Victoria University’s campuses have been paired (some pairs contain a cluster of several campuses) on the basis of similar size and course type. One of the researchers used Random.org to assign random numbers for each campus cluster. These random numbers (without campus codes) were given to a second researcher, who used a coin flipper option from Random.org and ascertained that 'heads' determined that the first campus of a pair was randomly assigned to the intervention group, while the second campus of the pair was randomized the control group. A 'tail' determined that the second member of the pair was randomized to the intervention group (and the first member of the pair was randomized to the control group). Both researchers emailed their information to a third researcher, who was also given the campus codes from the first researcher. The third researcher matched the codes to the randomization sequence. The study will follow the requirements of the CONSORT statement for cluster randomized trials (Campbell, Elbourne et al. 2004).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3020</postcode>
    <postcode>3030</postcode>
    <postcode>3015</postcode>
    <postcode>3000</postcode>
    <postcode>3021</postcode>
    <postcode>3011</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre 
Centre for Youth Mental Health 
35 Poplar Road
Parkville VIC  3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC Australia Fellowship awarded to Professor Anthony Jorm</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Program Management Branch 
NHMRC
MDP 100
GPO BOX 1421 
CANBERRA ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Victoria University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 14428
Melbourne Victoria 8001
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>beyondblue</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West 3122</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Social Research Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 1, 262 Victoria Street
North Melbourne Vic 3051</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The overall aims of the project are to design, implement and evaluate an educational campaign, known as MindWise to help raise mental health literacy in higher education students and staff. Data will be collected on mental health problems (anxiety, depression and alcohol misuse), knowledge of and beliefs about mental health problems, stigmatizing attitudes, self-help and help-seeking behaviours at baseline, at the end of the 2010 academic year and the end of the 2011 academic year. Data will be collected via telephone interviews carried out by the Social Research Centre.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.mindwise.org.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Victoria University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research 
Victoria University 
PO Box 14428
Melbourne VIC 8001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HRETH 09/145</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Anthony Jorm</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
Centre for Youth Mental Health 
The University of Melbourne 
35 Poplar Road 
Parkville  VIC   3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9342 3747</phone>
      <fax>+613 9342 3745</fax>
      <email>ajorm@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nicola Reavley</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
Centre for Youth Mental Health 
The University of Melbourne 
35 Poplar Road 
Parkville  VIC   3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9342 3769</phone>
      <fax>+613 9342 3745</fax>
      <email>nreavley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nicola Reavley</name>
      <address>Orygen Youth Health Research Centre
Centre for Youth Mental Health 
The University of Melbourne 
35 Poplar Road 
Parkville  VIC   3052</address>
      <phone>+613 9342 3769</phone>
      <fax>+613 9342 3745</fax>
      <email>nreavley@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>