<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372352">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000347369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>HOMeCare: Caring for the Dementia Caregiver and their Loved One via the HOMeCare Exercise and Mindfulness for Health Program</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>HOMeCare: Caring for the Dementia Caregiver and their Loved One via the HOMeCare Exercise and Mindfulness for Health Program to Improve Functional Capacity and Wellbeing</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HOMeCare</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Caregiver burden</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dyads will be randomised after baseline assessment, stratified by level of SPPB (&lt;8; 8-10) by an offsite statistician and concealed until allocation by interventionist. The experimental program consists of an adaptation of an 8-wk Mindfulness Training Program for the caregiver followed by a 16-wk home-based balance and strength training program for the participant with dementia, during which time the Mindfulness practice will continue to be reinforced and monitored.

All experimental dyads will have a home visit by the interventionist after the baseline assessment is complete, at which time they will receive an iPad, and detailed in-person instruction in use of the iPad for viewing the instructional materials, downloading videos and written materials, and Face Time videoconferencing. The materials will all be accessible via a single HOMeCARE website which has been purpose-built for this study, with the needs of the older adults caregiver specifically in mind. All software and hardware and Internet data packages needed for the delivery and monitoring of the intervention components will be supplied to the participants at no cost for the duration of the trial.

Mindfulness Training for the Caregiver:
The Mindfulness training course will utilise the internet-based Palouse Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction (MBSR) course materials and home practice program. This online MBSR training course has been modelled on the program founded by Jon Kabat-Zinn in 1979 at the University of Massachusetts Medical School. The 8-week program comprises of recorded video lectures on the topic of Mindfulness, practice tips, guided audio recordings for daily practice, and publications on mindfulness including media coverage. We encourage participants to allocate between 30 minutes  1 hour daily session for formal mindfulness practice.

Throughout the mindfulness program, participants are encouraged to log in their experiences. Formal practice forms are used to record their feelings during the guided practice sessions, while informal practice forms are used to reflect and record how mindfulness was applied during their daily activities. Caregivers will be asked to log their daily Mindfulness practice into the HOMeCARE website on their iPads, and these logs will be set for automatic uploading to the study interventionist so that adoption and adherence are optimized and relapse prevented

Due to the specific and significant stressors imposed by dementia caregiving, the basic Palouse course will be supplemented by targeted materials developed for the unique stresses experienced by dementia caregivers by the investigators of this project. The supplementary materials form the 16-week mindfulness program for the caregiver which runs concurrently with the 16-week exercise program. 

The supplemented materials are sourced from the Palouse website and comprises of optional reading materials outside the formal 8-week program. Additional materials were sourced from dementia care and caregiver organizations with their consent. These include resources from the Presence Care Project and the Aged Care Channel (ACC). Resources included media publications, reflections, video interviews, and caregiving tips for dementia. All materials will be delivered through the dedicated HOMeCARE website on their iPads.
We will augment the internet course with Face Time interaction with a trained Palouse Mindfulness Based Stress Reduction (MBSR) facilitator on a weekly basis during the first 8 weeks, and fortnightly during the next 16 weeks. Estimated duration of the face time sessions will be set to one hour however this may vary on a case by case basis. The session includes an opportunity for the caregiver to discuss the person with dementias progress with the exercise once commenced, tips on coaching and training the person with dementia, the caregivers own progress with the mindfulness materials, and an opportunity to report any adverse events during the week. The facetime session will also allow the interventionist to modify exercise programs for the person with dementia as appropriate.

Exercise program for the person with Dementia:
The study investigators will be training the caregivers to deliver the HOMeCARE exercise program to their loved ones once they have finished the 8-wk Mindfulness course. 
Free weights and resistance bands will be provided as well as online pictures and instructional booklets, which can be downloaded along with video demonstrations of all exercises through the dedicated study website.

The exercise will involve 3 sessions per week of progressive moderate-to-high intensity resistance training for 8 major muscle groups of whole body, as well as progressively challenging static and dynamic balance training exercises suitable to their current level of stability. 

The exercises may be broken up into sessions as short as 1 minute over the course of the day, and to enhance feasibility, integration into daily activities will be encouraged. For example, while watching TV, leg lifts and chair stands may be inserted during
commercial breaks, and progressively increased in difficulty. One-legged stands can be practiced while standing in front of kitchen and bathroom counters during hygiene and meal preparation activities. 

Caregivers will be encouraged to perform the movements with their loved one, so that mimicking movements is all that is needed. One session per week will be viewed in real time by the remote trainer using Face Time on the iPad to allow direct feedback on form, triage questions, and provide health coaching. Daily exercise activities will also be logged on the HOMeCARE website on the iPad by the caregiver, which will have been programmed for automatic upload to the trainer.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group dyads will continue to receive all usual care from their health care providers. They will be advised at the beginning of the study that those randomised to the control group will be on a waiting list to receive the experimental program at the end of 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional mobility via Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) for the adult with Dementia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks, and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>State Mindfulness Scale score for the caregiver</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measures done at baseline, 8 weeks, and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Zarit Burden Interview score for the caregiver</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measures done at baseline, 8 weeks, and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life of the adult with dementia using the Dementia Quality of Life Measure (DEMQOL - Carer), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Caregiver depression measured through the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver movement and activityies measured through an Actigraph accelerometer worn over 1 week</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver quality of life through the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver cognition through the Telephone Interview for Cognitive Status (TICS) assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive symptoms for adult with dementia via the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS), 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional capacity and daily activity measures for adults with dementia using the Katz Index of Independence in Activities of Daily Living (KATZ ADL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognition of the person with dementia through the NIH TOOLBOX adult cognition </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical capacity of the adult with dementia through a one repetition maximum muscle strength testing leg press, knee extension, triceps, and seated row)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For the person with dementia, habitual and maximal gait velocity with and without dual tasking. The variety of tasks will be used dependent on the level of cognitive impairment in the participant. These may include things such as set tests (animal naming), numerical or alphabet sequences, or calculations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quality and quantity measured through an Actigraph accelerometer worn over 1 week for the person with dementia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver sleep quality via the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver sleep quality measured through Insomnia Severity Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Executive function of person with dementia through the Trail Making Test (TMT) A and B</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Memory impairment of the person with dementia through the Hopkins Verbal Learning Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive impairment of the person with dementia through the Mini-metal State Exam </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver's affect through the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (PANAS) mood states scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver cognitive function through the Telephone Interview for Cognition (TICS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive function, daily activity measures and instrumental daily activities of the adults with dementia using the Bayer Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (BAYER IADL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility of the adults with dementia using the Life-Space Assessment (proxy report via the caregiver)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Each dyad will be composed of one caregiver and one participant with mild to moderate dementia for whom they provide care. 

The participant with dementia must: 
1) Live in the community,
2) Have at least one informal caregiver, 
3) Have diagnosed mild-moderate dementia of any type (Mini-mental State Exam score 12-24/30), 
4) Have mild deficits in functional mobility (walking, balance, chair stand) via the Short Physical Performance Battery [(SPPB) score &lt;10/12], 
5) Ambulatory over short distances without the assistance of a person. 

The informal caregiver in the dyad (family or friend) must:
1)  Live with the participant with dementia and/or providing some portion of their daily care including Activities of Daily Living in an informal capacity. 
2) Be able to speak and understand English
3) Residence within 30 km of the clinic sites. 
4) Adequate vision, hearing, cognition and manual dexterity sufficient to use the iPad programs developed for the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Either the person with Dementia or the caregiver must not have an unstable disease or rapidly progressive or terminal illness, resulting in their inability to perform any of the interventions.

For the participant with dementia:
1) Severe dementia (Mini-mental State Exam score &lt;12)
2) Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB) score of &gt;10/12</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation using concealed, sequentially numbered envelopes opened by the participant after baseline assessment completed. Sequencing and randomization will be done by an external staff member not involved with the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Dyads will be randomised after baseline assessment, stratified by level of SPPB (&lt;7; 7-9) and MMSE (12-19, 20-24). Concealed, sequentially numbered envelopes will be opened by the participant after baseline assessment completed. Sequencing done by an external staff member not involved with the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An intention-to-treat analytic strategy will be used, allowing inclusion of all participants regardless of adherence or dropout without need for imputation. A mixed model analysis of covariance will be used to assess the main effects of changes over time and group x time interactions in both members of dyads, adjusted for age, gender, baseline function and burden and other characteristics found to be related to the variable of interest.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Sydney
Cumberland Campus
75 East Street, Lidcombe, 2141
NSW, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dementia Collaborative Research Centres (DCRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychiatry
Faculty of Medicine
Level 3, AGSM Building
UNSW
Sydney, NSW 2052
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Home-based care is generally seen as the most humane and cost effective means of providing dementia care. Such ageing-in-place is supported by 2.5 million informal caregivers in Australia, however, increasing cognitive and physical frailty are a threat to ageing-in-place, and exacerbate caregiver burden. Importantly, caregiver depression and stress markedly increase the risk of institutionalisation of their loved one, independently of the actual level of disability or behavioural difficulties. 
Increasing interest has been given recently to Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction (MBSR), which has shown promise for improving caregiver burden. Notably, such stress reduction efforts do not directly address a large component of the strain: the progressive physical dependency or behavioural disturbance of the frail elders themselves. Slowing this decline is thus critical. This is the explicit purpose of the HOMeCARE project.
Research have demonstrated that exercise programs for those with dementia may improve physical and cognitive function, behavioural disturbance, sleep, and thus caregiver stress, although results and interventions varied. One study found that promotion of regular walking in dementia caregiver/cared for dyads did not improve the behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia, but attenuated caregiver burden. However, uptake of this community-based walking was suboptimal and not sustained.
What is missing is an evidence-based, sustainable program that can integrate these disparate approaches by simultaneously targeting modifiable functional and behavioural disturbances in the individual with dementia, while providing caregivers the means to cope with stress and improve their own health. In other cohorts, Internet delivery of Mindfulness training is efficacious for a variety of mental health outcomes, although this approach has never been tested in dementia caregivers specifically. Internet delivery would markedly extend reach and viability, given the difficulties inherent in traveling to a centre. Similarly, delivery of robust exercise in the home setting would also be a leap forward in terms of translation of successful exercise trials to the community.
We will conduct the first randomised controlled trial investigating the efficacy of HOMeCARE: a completely novel e-Health system for the dementia caregiver/cared-for dyad. HOMeCare begins with a Mindfulness-based Stress Reduction Training program for the caregivers. This will be followed by home-based, strength and balance training intervention, designed to improve functional mobility and psychological wellbeing in the person with dementia, during which time the Mindfulness practice will continue to be reinforced. We hypothesize that together, these 2 complementary, remotely monitored interventions will combine to reduce caregiver burden and improve function in the participants with dementia compared to usual care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Research Integrity &amp; Ethics Administration</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Integrity &amp; Ethics Administration, Research Portfolio
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 2 Margaret Telfer Building (K07)  
The University of Sydney / NSW / 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/795</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372352-HOMeCare PIS version 3_Caregiver_04.01.17CLEAN.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372352-HOMeCare_PIS version 4_Person with dementia_04.01.17CLEAN.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372352-1. Ethics Summary of Proposal HOMeCare.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Maria A. Fiatarone Singh, MD, FRACP</name>
      <address>University of Sydney
K221, Cumberland Campus
75 East Street, Lidcombe, 2141
NSW, Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9755 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351-9204</fax>
      <email>maria.fiataronesingh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Daniel</name>
      <address>University of Sydney
K220, Cumberland Campus
75 East Street, Lidcombe, 2141
NSW, Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9655</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kenneth.daniel@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Maria A. Fiatarone Singh, MD, FRACP</name>
      <address>University of Sydney
K221, Cumberland Campus
75 East Street, Lidcombe, 2141
NSW, Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9755 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351-9204</fax>
      <email>maria.fiataronesingh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Daniel</name>
      <address>University of Sydney
K220, Cumberland Campus
75 East Street, Lidcombe, 2141
NSW, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9655</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kenneth.daniel@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>