<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366461">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000618651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Indwelling urinary catheter during epidural anesthesia in labour for preventing postpartum urinary tract infection</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized control trial of continuous indwelling urinary catheter versus intermittent urinary catheter in pregnant women during epidural anesthesia in labour to prevent severe post partum urinary retention</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-5392</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postpartum urinary retention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Epidural anesthesia for pain control during labor is know to inhibit natural voiding and is high risk factor for postpartum urinary retention. There has not enough evidence to help Obstetricians and Midwives choose indwelling urinary catheter or intermittent straight urinary catheter for bladder care during labor. The aim of this study is to know does indwelling urinary catheter help to reduce the rate of postpartum urinary retention for women who have epidural anesthesia and vaginal delivery. 
Intervention group: pregnant women after performing epidural anesthesia as her own request, indwelling urinary catheter will be kept in place until the time of delivery. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group (standard care): pregnant women after performing epidural anesthesia as her own request are using intermittent urinary catheter as needed during the course of labor.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Midwives will measure bladder residual volume by bladder scanner. Severe postpartum urinary retention will be diagnosed if bladder residual volume equal or more than 400mL. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within giving birth 6 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(1) Postpartum urinary retention will be defined if bladder residual volume equal or more than 150 mL by midwives using bladder scanner.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After delivery baby 6 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(2) Urinary tract infection is identified if pregnant women have the symptoms of urinary tract infection and have positive microbiology culture result. The symptoms of UTI are complained by women or doctors ask information include one of those: fever, dysuria, voiding urgency, frequency, subrapubic tenderness, costovertebral angle pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 48 hours of delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(3): Satisfaction of pregnant women during labor with epidural anesthesia and her feeling of bladder care during labor (indwelling or intermittent urinary catheter), using five - point Likert scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within delivery baby 48 hours, at postpartum department.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant women have singleton pregnancy, head presentation admit to Hung Vuong hospital, and who are anticipated to undergo vaginal delivery during current condition and
require epidural anesthesia during labor.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women pregnant have planned cesarean section
Previous Cesarean section
Women have indication for indwelling urinary catheter postpartum such as: severe preeclampsia, eclampsia, severe postpartum haemorrhage, sever internal medical diseases
Women have urinary tract infection within 2 weeks of admission</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All pregnant women who meet the inclusion criteria will be approached for written informed consent by midwives, after they sign the requirement for epidural anesthesia. The midwives will contact with hospital telephone operator to open sealed opaque envelope which contained the allocating treatment has been created by statisticians using block randomization.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomization. Participants will be randomized in 2 study group for 1:1 ratio</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome is postpartum urinary retention (PUR) have bladder residual volume (BRV) from and over 400ml. The  expected PUR rate with BRV equal or greater than 400ml is 18%. In order to detect the differences between 2 groups is 6%, and cesarean section rate is 20%, we have to rule out cesarean section cases, we need to enrol 738 pregnant women to each arm. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1515</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/11/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <state>Ho Chi Minh City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Phan Thi Hang</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hung Vuong hospital, 128 Hong Bang street, district 5th, Ho Chi Minh City</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Viet Nam</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hung Vuong hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>128 Hong Bang Street, District 5th, Ho Chi Minh City, Viet Nam</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Viet Nam</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ho Chi Minh City Department of Science and Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>244 Dien Bien Phu street, Ward 7th, District 3rd, H? Chí Minh City, Viet Nam</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Viet Nam</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Huynh Nguyen Khanh Trang</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Ho Chi Minh City of Medicine and Pharmacology University, 217 Hong Bang, district 5th, Ho Chi Minh City</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Viet Nam</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Tran Son Thach</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Garvan Institute of Medical Research
384 Victoria Street, Darlinghurst, NSW 2010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Epidural anesthesia for pain control during labor is know to inhibit natural voiding and is high risk factor for postpartum urinary retention. There has not enough evidence to help Obstetricians and Midwives choose indwelling urinary catheter or intermittent straight urinary catheter for bladder care during labor. The aim of this study is to know does indwelling urinary catheter help to reduce the rate of postpartum urinary retention for women who have epidural anesthesia and vaginal delivery. The study have 2 arms: arm1 (intervention arm) using indwelling urinary catheter after women receive epidural anesthesia, this catheter remain in place until delivery time. Arm 2 (control arm) using intermittent urinary catheter as needed during labour. The primary outcome is postpartum retention urinary with bladder residual volume equal or more than 400ml, which measure by using bladder scanner at 6 hour after giving birth. The secondary outcome are: (1) the rate of PUR with BRV is equal or more than 150ml; (2): the rate of catheter associated urinary tract infection; (3): the satisfaction of pregnant women after giving birth and the sensation of catheterization during birthing. The study expect to enrol 750 pregnant women for each arm, time expected to completed this study is 20 months. The methodology of this study is randomized control trial, planed to take place at Hung Vuong hospital, maternal hospital, located in Ho Chi Minh city, Viet Nam.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>We have not published any results related to this trial yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ho Chi Minh City of Medicine and Pharmacy ethics commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>217 Hong Bang street, District 5th, Ho Chi Minh City</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>62/DHYD-HD</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Viet Nam</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phan Thi Hang</name>
      <address>Hung Vuong Hospital, 218 Hong Bang street, district 5th, Ho Chi Minh City</address>
      <phone>+84908220676</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>phanhangbvhv@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phan Thi Hang</name>
      <address>Hung Vuong Hospital, 218 Hong Bang street, district 5th, Ho Chi Minh City</address>
      <phone>+84908220676</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>phanhangbvhv@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phan Thi Hang</name>
      <address>Hung Vuong Hospital, 218 Hong Bang street, district 5th, Ho Chi Minh City</address>
      <phone>+84908220676</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>phanhangbvhv@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Phan Thi Hang</name>
      <address>Hung Vuong Hospital, 218 Hong Bang street, district 5th, Ho Chi Minh City</address>
      <phone>+84908220676</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>phanhangbvhv@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>