<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364244">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001207707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Compass Trial: A Randomised Controlled Trial of Primary Human Papillomavirus (HPV) Testing for Cervical Cancer Screening in Australia: Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot Study for a trial in Human Papillomavirus (HPV) vaccinated and unvaccinated women presenting for cervical screening of 6 yearly HPV screening versus 3-yearly cytology screening to assess the feasibility via recruitment rates, cross sectional positivity rate and laboratory implementation. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Compass</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cervical cancer </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Human Papillomavirus (HPV)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cervical (cervix)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention Arm 2: Five -yearly HPV screening with types 16/18 (+/-45 in pilot study) genotyping and cytology triage of intermediate risk women with other oncogenic HPV infection; The sample collected from participants in intervention arm 2 will be a Liquid Based Cytology (LBC) Pap test and collection should take 15 minutes and 

Intervention Arm 3: Five -yearly HPV screening with types 16/18 (+/-45 in pilot study) genotyping and dual-stained (DS) cytology (with p16/Ki67) triage of intermediate risk women with other oncogenic HPV infection. The sample collected from participants in intervention arm 3 will be a Liquid Based Cytology (LBC) Pap test and collection should take 15 minutes</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1: Two and a half -yearly image read cytology screening with reflex HPV triage testing for low grade (p/d LSIL) smears. The sample collected from participants in Arm 1 will be a Liquid Based Cytology (LBC) Pap test and collection should take 15 minutes</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1). To assess participant acceptance of the randomisation process and use of longer routine screening intervals, via recruitment rate. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2). To confirm the operational feasibility of laboratory processing procedures for each of the two HPV test platforms. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months

Total laboratory processing start time will be defined as time and date a sample is received and logged at specimen reception to the time when the final report is entered into the laboratory electronic database. Total sample processing time (TPT) will be defined as the time from specimen load to HPV result being available on the manufacturers output. For hands-on time (HOT), an RA will observe and record the start and stop of the hands-on processing times. A minimum of three sample runs/batches per test (up to ~90 test samples per run) will be conducted. The average results across the three runs will be taken to derive averages of the three key measures for each technology. 

The time and motion study will be conducted after suitable run in and lab verification has been performed for each technology. In the pilot study it is unlikely that the full batch capacity will be utilised, due to the need to report in a timely fashion. Therefore adjustments will be made to allow for components of the processing time that are dependent on the number of individual samples versus automated components of the processing time that are independent of the number of samples being processed. 

For DS, HOT for preparation of the stain using an immunostainer will be quantified. Reading/scanning with microscopy time will also be quantified. 

Similar processes will be followed for quantifying HOT and TOT in the cytology arm.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3). To assess positivity rates for the primary screening test in each arm, and estimate the cross sectional sensitivity and specificity of each screening approach for the detection of CIN 2+ and CIN 3+.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline

Using participants Round One screening test results, obtained from VCS Pathology, we will estimate the test positivity rates by age (overall, &lt;30 and 30+) for the primary screening test in each arm (Cytology: HPV: HPV).

Using test result data from screen negative women that were referred for colposcopy as part of the verification colposcopy arm we will estimate the cross-sectional sensitivity and specificity of each primary screening test (Cytology: HPV: HPV). These data will be collected at the time of colposcopy, by attending specialists, and recorded by the VCCR. 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4). To estimate the sensitivity and specificity of DS testing, in women positive for HPV
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Australian female resident of Victoria
Aged 25-64
Attending for routine cervical screening at a participating health care practice</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Total hysterectomy (uterus and cervix)
Presence of symptoms for which cervical cancer must be excluded
Currently undergoing treatment for cervical pre-cancer, or cancer
Attending for follow-up of a prior cervical abnormality, including repeated "test of cure" procedures in which the woman has not yet been discharged back to routine screening
Known pregnancy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Practitioners will approach patients during regular cervical screening visits.

Prior to performing the cervical screening examination, the practitioner will assess patient eligibility and where appropriate, seek consent for participation in the study. The Practitioner will provide participants with an information sheet to read and ask questions. 

Women who provide consent will have a cervical smear collected using a Liquid Based Cytology ThinPrep PreservCyt vial. The LBC sample will be labelled with the woman's name and date of birth, placed in a sample bag, along with the consent form, and returned to a centralised processing laboratory at VCS Pathology.
  </concealment>
    <sequence>Upon receipt and logging of the sample at VCS pathology, individual subject allocation to one of three study arms will be performed. Randomisation will be performed using a computer-generated randomisation sequence which will be overseen by the NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre. Randomisation will be at 1:2:2 ratio (cytology:HPV:HPV)

Randomisation will only be performed once subject eligibility has been confirmed. Automatic checks will also be made against the laboratory database that the woman has not previously been enrolled in the trial. 

Neither the participant nor practitioner will be aware of subject allocation at the time of recruitment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The pilot study will involve recruiting 5,000 women aged 25-64 years. In early 2012, the Victorian Cytology Service (VCS) Pathology Liaison Physicians provided a comprehensive list of all general practices with close links to VCS. Pathology. From the list, 6 eligible practices were identified and have agreed to participate in the trial. These clinics report approximately 6,300 Pap tests from age eligible women per year. We will be actively recruiting new clinics over the duration of the pilot. 

Using data on the number of cervical screening samples sent to VCS Pathology in 2012 by each participating clinic, we estimated the expected number of women aged 25  29 and 30  64 years that would be enrolled in the pilot study if the recruitment rates were 65% and 50% overall, and if these recruitment rates were also sustained by each individual clinic.

The target recruitment rate for participating individual practitioners will be 50% or greater, and if overall recruitment in the pilot is less than 50%, study materials will be reviewed and additional focus groups may be held with practitioners and patients during the course of the pilot</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/12/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>5000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>5001</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3068 - Clifton Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3442 - Woodend</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3107 - Templestowe Lower</postcode>
    <postcode>3437 - Gisborne</postcode>
    <postcode>3146 - Glen Iris</postcode>
    <postcode>3053 - Carlton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Roche Molecular Systems Inc. and </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>4300 Hacienda Drive, Pleasanton, California 94588, USA 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Cancer Research Division- Cancer Council New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cancer Council New South Wales, 153 Dowling Street, Woolloomooloo, NSW 2011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Cytology Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>265 Faraday Street Carlton, VIC 3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ventana Medical Systems</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>1910 E.Innovation Park Drive, Tuscon, Arizona, 85755, USA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Karen Canfell (co-PI)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cancer Council New South Wales, 153 Dowling Street, Woolloomooloo, NSW 2011</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is evaluating whether testing for certain types of Human Papillomavirus (HPV) is a more effective cervical cancer screening test than the Pap Smear test. 
Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are female, aged between 25 years and 64 years, an Australian resident in Victoria, and attends routine cervical screenings at one of the studys participating health care practice. 
Trial details
Participants in this study will be randomly (by chance) divided into one of three groups. Participants in one group will undergo three-yearly image read cytology screening with reflex HPV triage testing for low grade Possible/Definite Low-Grade Squamous Intraepithelial Lesion (p/d LSIL) smears. Participants in the second group will undergo six-yearly HPV screening with types 16/18 (+/- 45 in pilot study) genotyping and cytology triage of intermediate risk women with other oncogenic HPV infection. Participants in the third group will undergo a six-yearly HPV screening with types 16/18 (+/- 45 in pilot study) genotyping and dual-stained (DS) cytology (with p16/Ki67) triage of intermediate risk women with other oncogenic HPV infection. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.compasstrial.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Health, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC, 3004 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/Alfred/1 Local Project 111/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Australian College of General Practitioners, National Research and Evaluation Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>100 Wellington Parade, East Melbourne, Victoria 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NREEC 13-005</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood, South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-08-579</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Marion Saville (co-Principal Investigator)</name>
      <address>Marion Saville
Victorian Cytology Service
265 Faraday Street, Carlton, VIC, 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9250 0322</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msaville@vcs.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jessica Darlington-Brown</name>
      <address>Cancer Council New South Wales, 153 Dowling Street, Woolloomooloo, New South Wales, 2011 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9334 1419</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jessica.DB@nswcc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Canfell</name>
      <address>Cancer Council New South Wales, 153 Dowling Street, Woolloomooloo, New South Wales, 2011 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9334 1726</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.canfell@nswcc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Chloe Jennett</name>
      <address>Cancer Council New South Wales, 153 Dowling Street, Woolloomooloo, New South Wales, 2011 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9334 1418</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chloe.jennett@nswcc.org.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>