<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370976">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000879460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Making the most of plain packaging: using self-efficacy messages printed on cigarette packaging to help smokers to quit. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Making the most of plain packaging: using self-efficacy messages on cigarette packaging to promote smoking cessation.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-7314</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MMOPP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>tobacco use</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will recruit a community sample of smokers for a three week trial assessing the effect of adding self-efficacy messages to the graphic warning images displayed on tobacco packaging.  The trial consists of a baseline phase of one week, during which all participants smoke from packaging displaying the current government mandated health warning labels (HWLs), and a two week experimental phase wherein participants will be randomly assigned to a control or an experimental group and will be exposed to different HWLs accordingly.  All participants will be required to stick an adhesive label over the warning label on the packaging of their tobacco (which they have purchased as usual) at the time of first opening.  Those in the control group will have labels identical to the standard HWLs currently in circulation.  Those in the experimental group will have labels with the same graphic images, but will have a study-specific self-efficacy message in place of the usual text warning.  All participants will be required to carry a hand-held computer with them at all times for the duration of the study and will complete frequent assessments recording their smoking- related cognitions and behaviours as well as take photographs of their tobacco packaging with study-specific HWLs in place in order to monitor compliance. .  Participants will also visit a laboratory at the University of Tasmania three times during the course of the trial and provide samples of exhaled air to verify their self-reported smoking behaviour by measuring carbon monoxide levels. These visits would be scheduled at the beginning of the baseline phase, at the conclusion of the baseline phase and at the end of the experimental phase.  Efficacy message labels will target response efficacy, self-efficacy and control perceptions and will feature an alternative warning statement (the large, bold text above the graphic image) and and alternative explanatory message (the smaller, more detailed text below the image on the back of the package).  Efficacy messages will vary according to the nature of the graphic image with which they are combined. For example, a warning statement combined with and image of a damaged heart might say "DONT SMOKE THIS ONE AND UNCLOG YOUR ARTERIES.Use nicotine patches and gums in combination to beat cravings" and feature an explanatory message such as: "If you quit smoking now, your risk of coronary heart disease will drop by half in a years time. Its not too late.  You can talk to your GP to get nicotine patches to overcome your cravings.  Quitting at any age is well worth the effort". 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Half of the participants will be assigned to a control group.  During the baseline phase, the control group will smoke their tobacco as usual from original packaging with standard government mandated health warning labels.  During the experimental phase of the study, the control group will be issued with sets of adhesive health warning labels identical to those required by law to be printed on tobacco packaging and will be required to stick these over the original health warning labels.  This will control for the possibility of extraneous effects in the experimental group associated with the attentional processes involved in sticking warning labels to the tobacco packaging. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>level of intention to quit smoking as assessed using two questions with numerical rating scales on the hand-held computer device  and also via questionnaires with numerical rating scales at lab visits.  The questions comprising these scales have been used in previous studies which have investigated intention to quit (e.g. Orbell, et al. (2009). Socialcognitive beliefs, alcohol, and tobacco use: A prospective community study of change following a ban on smoking in public places. Health Psychology, 28(6), 753.; Schuez, et al.. (2016). Immediate effects of plain packaging health warnings on quitting intention and potential mediators: Results from two ecological momentary assessment studies. Psychology of Addictive Behaviors, 30(2), 220.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Daily:both after exposure to warning labels (each time a participant logs a cigarette);  in response to random prompts from the device (which occur 4-5 times each day); when completing a scheduled evening report. 
2. At lab visits: at the end of the baseline (day 7) and experimental (day 21) phases.   </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with a reduction in the number of cigarettes smoked daily as assessed by the number of cigarettes logged on the hand-held computer and on questionnaires  at lab visits.  The reported number of cigarettes participants smoke daily will be verified by measuring the carbon monoxide levels in exhaled air.  This method of measuring smoking behaviour has been validated previously and shown to be associated with high levels of participant compliance  ( Schuez, et al.. (2014). Compliance with an EMA monitoring protocol and its relationship with participant and smoking characteristics. nicotine &amp; tobacco research, 16(Suppl 2), S88-S92.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Daily: recorded on hand held devices. 
2. Lab visits: at the end of the baseline phase (day 7) and at the end of the experimental phase (day 21). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>level of risk perception as assessed with numerical rating scales on hand held devices and on questionnaires at lab visits. The questions comprising these scales have been used previously to assess risk perception (e.g.  Orbell, et al. (2009). Socialcognitive beliefs, alcohol, and tobacco use: A prospective community study of change following a ban on smoking in public places. Health Psychology, 28(6), 753; Schuez, N., &amp; Ferguson, S. G. (2015). Australian smokers and nonsmokersexposure to anti-smoking warnings in day-to-day life: A pilot study. Nicotine &amp; Tobacco Research, 17, 876  881)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. daily: after exposure to warning labels (each time participants log a cigarette). 
2. lab visits: at the end of the baseline phase (day 7) and the end of the experimental phase (day 21). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>none</outcome>
      <timepoint>none</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Current smokers from the greater Hobart area, who have smoked a minimum of ten cigarettes daily for the past three years. They must have an adequate grasp of the English language and not be interested in quitting in the next month</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, cognitive impairment, intellectual disability, mental illness. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The proposed sample size (n=60; 30 participants per group) was determined by the requirements of the primary research questions  namely, detecting differences in intention  quitting behaviours and risk perception scores between the modified warning label and the control group  at the end of the treatment period. Estimates of the expected effect sizes are based on two systematic reviews examining the combination of fear appeals and self-efficacy. Pooling these effect sizes in a random-effects meta-analytic model yields a combined effect size of d = .76. In order to detect an effect of this size with a power of .8 and an alpha of .05, 58 participants are needed.  Moreover, Montecarlo simulation studies suggest that 60 participants with the intended number of assessments are sufficient for random effects analyses (assessments [level-1] nested in participants [level-2]) yielding unbiased standard errors and variance components.  

Multilevel (linear mixed effect) models will be used to analyse the experimental data and the moderated mediational pathways of the intervention. These analyses allow for an unequal number of observations across individuals. Thus, we will be able to use all available data and do not need to exclude data based on level of completeness. We will run latent growth curve models to test for within-person changes in intention and the suggested mediators across the baseline and experimental phases. We will test for differences in slopes between the experimental groups (according to the hypotheses, the slopes for intention and its predictors should not be different from zero in the control group, whereas the slopes will be higher in the experimental group). 
We will compare participants quit intentions and their mediators after encountering a warning  to intentions and mediators at random times of the day. For this, we will run a multilevel moderated mediation model with intention to quit as dependent variable, type of assessment (immediately post-cigarette vs. random prompt) as the independent variable, and defensive reactions as moderator, risk appraisal and self-efficacy as mediators. The experimental group will be treated as moderator to model differential intervention effects. Overall self-efficacy ratings and nicotine dependence/number of cigarettes per day will be tested as moderators of the effects of the intervention on threat management resources and intentions and the effects of intentions on smoking.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Natalie Schuez</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Tasmania
School of Health Sciences
Private Bag 135
Hobart, TAS. 7000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Tasmania</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Office of Research Services, University of Tasmania, Private Bag 1, Hobart, TAS, 7001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Benjamin Schuez</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Tasmania
Psychology, School of Medicine, Faculty of Health. 
Private Bag 30.
Hobart, TAS, 7001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Stuart Ferguson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Tasmania
Pharmacy, School of Medicine, Faculty of Health
Private Bag 34,  Hobart   TAS  7001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Lillian Brinken</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Tasmania
Psychology, School of Medicine, Faculty of Health. 
Private Bag 30.
Hobart, TAS, 7001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed study would investigate the effectiveness of the graphic warning labels currently featured on tobacco products and whether they can be enhanced by adding messages which target self-efficacy. Self-efficacy can be understood as the level of confidence to which a person believes in their own capacity to carry out a given action, despite potentially arising difficulties. Manipulating self-efficacy beliefs and has been observed to enhance the effectiveness of confronting or threatening health messages (fear-appeals), which are often found to backfire. The current tobacco warning labels used in Australia make extensive use of fear-appeals.

This study would measure whether sticking self-efficacy messages onto current warning labels (while ensuring the graphic images remain visible) can influence intentions and behaviours observed to be related to quitting smoking among a group of sixty tobacco smokers. A study-provided smartphone would be used to assess perceptions of personal health risks due to smoking, intentions and behaviours several times a day over a three week period.

The first week of the study would be a baseline phase in which all participants report their risk perceptions, intentions and behaviours while continuing to smoke from the standard tobacco packaging. The second and third week would be the experimental phase, during which participants would be randomly divided into two groups. The experimental group would smoke from packages with self-efficacy messages attached and the control group would smoke from packages with current warning labels. All participants would continue to report their risk perceptions, intentions and behaviours, allowing researchers to assess changes between the two groups as well as changes within individual participants by comparing the baseline phase to the experimental phase. 

Participants would visit the laboratory three times during the course of the study: an induction visit at the beginning; a visit at the end of the baseline phase during which randomisation will take place, and a visit at the end of the experimental phase. At each visit they would be required to give a sample of exhaled breath for the measurement of carbon monoxide content. Carbon monoxide levels provide an indication of how much a person smokes and allows researchers to check how reliably participants report their smoking behaviour. Moreover, they will complete a brief assessment of their overall risk perceptions, intention and smoking behaviour during the last week. This will allow us to compare stable measures of the proposed determinants of behaviour with real-time measures.

During the final visit, participants will be debriefed and asked to provide feedback. Moreover, at this time, participants in the control group will receive the same set of study-specific labels the experimental group received during the experimental phase, thus they will have access to the same intervention material after the study is completed. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
Hobart TAS 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0015696</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Schuez</name>
      <address>University of Tasmania
School of Health Sciences
Private Bag 135
Hobart TAS 7000
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62264606</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.schuez@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Schuez</name>
      <address>University of Tasmania. 
Psychology, School of Medicine, Faculty of Health
Private Bag 30, 
Hobart TAS 7001
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6226 7471</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>benjamin.schuez@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Schuez</name>
      <address>University of Tasmania. 
Psychology, School of Medicine, Faculty of Health
Private Bag 30, 
Hobart TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6226 7471</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>benjamin.schuez@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lillian  Brinken</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>lbrinken@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>