<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370592">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000676415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase I study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of single and multiple doses of intranasal pentosan polysulfate (Rhinosul 'Trademark') in healthy subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of single and multiple doses of intranasal pentosan polysulfate (Rhinosul 'Trademark') in healthy subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>PARA_002
(Assigned Trial Protocol Number)
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Allergic Rhinitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hay fever</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Daily treatment with nasal spray, administered to subjects by Phase 1 unit clinical staff
Two dose levels to be evaluated in 2 cohorts in an ascending dose design
Study medication (Pentosan polysulfate sodium nasal spray) will be administered once daily to 2 groups of participants (40 mg cohort and 80 mg cohort) in 2 sequential stages,  A safety review will be conducted before each dose escalation
Stage 1 - Single dose (2 sprays per nostril, once a day) on day 1
Stage 2 - 7 day multiple dose (2 sprays per nostril, once a day) on days 5-11
Subjects will be admitted to the Phase 1 unit on day -1, and confined to the unit for the duration of dosing, including monitoring days where no treatment is given (day 2, 3, 4, and 12).</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo controlled, double blinded, randomised.
The placebo is supplied as a nasal spray consisting of the vehicle, minus the active ingredient.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability.

Qualified medical staff in the trial unit will conduct daily general physical examinations on dosing days, and on the day subsequent to dose cessation.  The following will be assessed:
- General examination
- Vital signs
- ENT assessments
- Adverse events </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose and post-dose on the following days: 

Day 1 (day 1 of dosing, single dose)
Day 2 (non dosing monitoring day)
Day 5 -11 (7 day repeat dose)
Day 12 (non dosing monitoring day)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety assessment: 12-lead ECG monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-dose, and 1hr and 4hr post dose
Day 1, 5 and 11</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety - Blood results (haematology)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day -1 baseline
Day 2, 4, 6, 12, 15</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety assessment: measurement of APTT (Activated partial thromboplastin time - blood clotting time)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-dose, and then at, 2, 4, 6 and 8 hours following dosing on Days 1, 5 and 11</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome
Safety - Blood results (Serum Biochemistry)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day -1 baseline
Day 2, 4, 6, 12, 15</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Able to speak, read and understand English sufficiently to understand the purposes and risks of the study and to provide written informed consent.
2. Healthy males or females aged 18 to 65 years inclusive at the time of consent.
3. Body Mass Index (BMI) of greater than or equal to 18.0, and less than or equal to 32.0 kg/m2
4. Normal nasal examination as per Ear, Nose and Throat (ENT) assessment
5. Subjects must be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, laboratory tests and other study procedures.
6. Suitable venous access
7. Subjects who are
a. females of non child-bearing potential OR
b. females who are not pregnant, breast feeding or planning to become pregnant AND willing to comply with the medically acceptable contraceptive requirements of the study 
c. males who are willing to comply with the medically acceptable contraceptive requirements of the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Medical history or clinically significant disease as judged by the investigator or sponsor 
2. History of idiopathic nose bleeds, more frequently than once in the previous 12 months
3. Subjects who have a positive urine cotinine test at Screening or Day -1.
4. Smokers (i.e. no cigarette or tobacco use at any time during the last 12 months)
5. Use of caffeine-containing foods/beverages/dietary supplements, or alcohol within 24 hours prior to admission to Day -1 and/or unable to refrain from their use during the study.
6. Use of prescription or non-prescription (over-the-counter) or complementary medicines, within 14 days prior to Day -1, 
7. Respiratory tract infection within the previous four weeks or any infection within 7 days prior to Day -1.
8. Any clinically significant abnormalities on clinical chemistry, haematology, urinalysis, physical examination, medical history, 12-lead ECG, or vital signs as judged by the investigator or sponsor (at Screening and/or Day -1).
9. Activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) outside normal range 
10.Clinically significant abnormality of renal function as judged by the investigator or sponsor
11.Clinically significant abnormality of hepatic function 
12.History or evidence of, or positive test for HIV, hepatitis B or hepatitis C.
13.Positive urine drug screen or alcohol test during Screening or on Day -1, or history of drug or alcohol abuse and/or dependence within the year prior to Day -1.
14.Administration of any investigational agent within 8 weeks or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to Day -1.
15.History of significant hypersensitivity to any of the IMPs or drugs of a similar class.
16.Surgical or medical conditions which could significantly alter drug absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion.
17.Major surgery within 3 months prior to Day -1 or anticipated surgery in the study period.
18.Blood or plasma donation of more than 500 mL during the 3 months prior to Day -1.
19.History of, or current clinically-significant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, cardiovascular, respiratory, endocrine, oncological, immunological, neurological, ophthalmological, haematological or psychiatric disorder or any other condition, which in the opinion of the investigator or sponsor would jeopardize the safety of the participant or the validity of the study results.
20.History of fainting during phlebotomy
21.Unable to refrain from strenuous activity 48 hours prior to Day -1 and for the duration of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Computer generated randomisation schedules will be prepared by a statistician prior to the start of the study. Subjects within a given dose level cohort will be randomised to receive Rhinosul or Placebo in a ratio of 2 to 1 respectively.
Subjects will then be allocated a corresponding pre-prepared bottle labelled with the same randomisation number. Bottles containing active and placebo will be indistinguishable apart from the randomisation number on the label</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation schedules will be prepared by a statistician prior to the start of the study for each dose level cohort</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistical analyses will be reported for all study endpoints by stage and sampling time within each dose. Results for those on placebo will be combined. Summary statistics for the categorical variables will include counts and percentages. The descriptive summary for the continuous variables will include number of subjects (n), means, medians, standard deviations, and minimum and maximum values. All data will be listed.
This study is descriptive in nature, and no formal hypothesis testing will be performed. Any confidence intervals (CIs) generated will be 95% using exact methods, unless stated otherwise.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>18</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>21/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Linear Clinical Research - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Paradigm Biopharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2
517 Flinders Lane
Melbourne
VIC, 3000
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Paradigm Biopharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2
517 Flinders Lane
Melbourne
VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomised, double blind, placebo-controlled study in healthy subjects.  As a phase 1 study, it is designed to evaluate the safety and tolerability of intranasal pentosan polysulfate sodium (Rhinosul 'Trademark') in healthy subjects, following single and repeat dose administration.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>belberry ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> 129 Glen Osmond Road 
Eastwood 
South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Redfern</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research Limited
1st Floor Block B, Hospital Ave
Nedlands, 
WA 6009 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6382 5100 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Aredfern@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Kaufman</name>
      <address>Paradigm BioPharmaceuticals Ltd
Level 2, 517 Flinders Lane
Melbourne VIC 3000 
</address>
      <phone>+61 413421160</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ckaufman@paradigmbiopharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Kaufman</name>
      <address>Paradigm BioPharmaceuticals Ltd
Level 2, 517 Flinders Lane
Melbourne VIC 3000 </address>
      <phone>+61 413421160</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ckaufman@paradigmbiopharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>