<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369342">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001079538p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Patient preferences for receiving an early intervention after critical illness to improve psychological recovery </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Patient preferences for receiving an early intervention after critical illness to improve psychological recovery </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1174-5837</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PRINCIPLE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Posttraumatic stress symptoms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intensive Care Unit (ICU) diary intervention: in addition to standard care participants will receive a narrative account of their clinical condition and progress prepared jointly by the ICU staff and family members throughout the patients ICU stay. The ICU diary will be retained by ICU staff when the participant is discharged to the ward and will be provided to the participant when she/he indicates readiness to receive the diary (between five days and three months after ICU discharge). The diary will be given to the patient in the form of a booklet containing narrative text from staff and family members. The patient will be made aware of the diary 5 days post ICU discharge or as soon after as possible when they are in the hospital wards. The diary will be checked for appropriateness prior to being given to the patient. The number of entries will be monitored (as this is a pilot study).

Individualised care intervention: provision of an individualised summary of the ICU experience prepared by ICU staff and based on the User Centred Critical Care Discharge Information. The ICU experience summary will include the following information: reason for ICU admission, date of ICU admission, length of ICU stay, how the patient arrived to the ICU (by ambulance, transferred from another hospital, family member or friend brought them, etc.), discharge location (medical ward, surgical ward, home, etc.) and a summary of the important elements of the patients ICU journey such as the patients diagnosis, treatments and procedures.
 This summary will be given to the participant in hospital after consenting, and when each participant considers he or she is ready to receive the information. Each participant will be followed up with at least one telephone call 2 weeks post hospital discharge. The purpose of the telephone call is to discuss any problems that the patient may be experiencing and attempt to address these. The ICU Registered Nurse or Research Assistant (with training from psychologist) will perform the phone call. Additional strategies that will be available to the participant include a supported visit to ICU, discussion of challenges the participant is currently experiencing, psychological counselling and provision of detailed information outlining additional support options available. The information regarding the additional support options available will be provided as part of the telephone call and individualised written information.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment: this will incorporate usual practice. Specific information provision or psychological care is extremely limited at Princess Alexandra Hospital ICU and is dependent on individual assessment and referral for specific services. This is usually arranged by the GP post-hospital discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to hospital discharge, 3 and 6 months after ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder Checklist  Civilian Version 5 (PCL-5)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to hospital discharge, 3 and 6 months after ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Health Questionnaire  9 (PHQ-9) score. The PHQ-9 is a screening instrument that contains 9 questions assessing depression symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days after ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) score. The GAD-7 is a screening instrument that contains 7 questions assessing anxiety symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days after ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intensive Care Psychological Assessment Tool (IPAT). The IPAT ) is a screening instrument designed to detect acute distress and the risk of future psychological morbidity in critically ill patients so that appropriate interventions can be implemented. </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days after ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of Intervention Acceptability 

Assessment of acceptability: patients and family members will be invited to complete the Assessment of Intervention Acceptability questionnaire that is based on that used Gwadry-Sridhar and colleagues (1) to measure acceptability of information provision. The Assessment of Intervention Acceptability questionnaire has been developed specifically for use in this study. Questionnaires will be mailed at 3 and 6 months for participant to complete.
(1) Gwadry-Sridhar, F., et al., Instruments to measure acceptability of information and acquisition of knowledge in patients with heart failure. Eur J Heart Fail, 2003. 5(6): 783-91.
Interviews to assess acceptability: interviews will be conducted via telephone by the ICU Research Nurse or Research Assistant with participants from each of the relevant groups including patients, family members and clinicians. Themes will be broad, with open-ended questions aimed at exploring perceived benefits and disadvantages of the intervention and associated facilitators and barriers of receiving and using the intervention. Interviews will be audiotaped and transcribed verbatim to enable thematic analysis. Interviews will be carried out at 3 and 6 months after ICU discharge.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months after ICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients: Consecutive patients who meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria will be invited to participate. 
Inclusion criteria: 
1. ICU patients with expected ICU LOS &gt;48 hours 
2. Able to speak and understand English
3. Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) 14  15 prior to leaving ICU
4. Expected survival beyond hospital (in consultation with the ICU clinical team) of at least 1 month

Family members: Family members of the patients who meet the above inclusion criteria will be invited to participate in the study. 

Clinicians: Clinicians who care for patients in the intensive care and have been involved in contributing to the ICU diary or the ICU discharge summary will be invited to participate in the study. 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: 
1. Patients who are not able to receive the intervention or be followed up post discharge (e.g. overseas patients, prisoners) 
2. Patients with active psychotic impairment of a history of organic impairment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patient participants and/or family members will be approached by the ICU Research Nurse within 48 - 96 hours of ICU admission for initial consent regarding participation in the study. Informed consent will be then be obtained from the patient after discharge from the ICU to the ward.

The purpose of gaining initial consent from the patient (if able) or the family member is to receive an indication of whether the patient is likely to wish to participate in the study. All patients who indicate a likely desire for participation (or have their family members indicate) will have an ICU diary commenced for them and also have an ICU Discharge Summary prepared on their discharge to the ward, however neither of these items will be provided to the patient until after they have consented to participate in the study. Diaries or discharge summaries of those patients who choose not to participate will be disposed of in a secure manner.  
Screening for psychological compromise will occur approximately 5 days after ICU discharge and will be performed using the recognised instruments of the Patient Health Questionnaire – 9 (PHQ-9), the Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) scale and the recently developed Intensive Care Psychological Assessment Tool (IPAT).

Patient participants will be allocated to study groups using a partially randomised process based on the results of the screening process and patient preferences. Screening, registering of participants in the web-based randomisation portal and allocation to group based on randomisation will be conducted by the ICU Research Nurse. 

Patient participants who are screened as being ‘distressed’ will be offered a choice of the intervention they receive, while patients who are screened as ‘not distressed’ will be allocated to study groups following computer-generated random assignment using a 1:1:1 ratio. This dual process of randomisation will help to ensure that:
-patients who are experiencing psychological distress are not exposed to an intervention that they do not wish to receive
-by having some participants who are randomised to group allocation this will enable assessment of whether the belief in a specific intervention increases the effectiveness of that intervention. 

Allocation concealment will be achieved through use of an online randomisation service offered by Griffith University. Blinding of patient participants, family members and healthcare team providers to the intervention is not possible. Research personnel conducting all long term follow-up will be blinded to group allocation, as will those undertaking statistical analysis. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Patient participants who are screened as being ‘distressed’ will be offered a choice of the intervention they receive, while patients who are screened as ‘not distressed’ will be allocated to study groups following computer-generated random assignment using a 1:1:1 ratio. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size: 
Patients: Based on previous studies, we estimate approximately one-third of patient participants will have psychological compromise after critical illness, and that we will retain approximately 75% of participants in the study at 6 months. A final cohort (at 6 months) of 30 patient participants in each group is desired to ensure adequate data for assessment of feasibility, therefore a total sample size of 120 patient participants at enrolment is required. The PAH ICU admitted 659 patients in the 2013/14 year with length of stay &gt;48 hours, therefore recruitment within the time period is feasible.
Family members: a convenience sample of 30  40 family members will be sought to complete the acceptability questionnaires with a sub-sample of approximately 20 family members invited to participate in the interviews to provide more detailed data regarding the acceptability of the interventions. 
Clinicians: a convenience sample of 20 clinicians will be sought to provide their perspective of the acceptability of the interventions. 

Data analysis: Feasibility and acceptability measures will be assessed using descriptive statistics and identification of problematic points in the research process or content of the interventions. Data from the interviews assessing acceptability will be analysed thematically, and will be used to explain and enhance our understanding of acceptability and further refine the interventions. Baseline group comparisons of outcomes will use both instrument scores and frequency of psychological compromise, with relative counts, percentages and odds ratios used to summarise treatment impact and enable calculation of sample size for a future efficacy study.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/10/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>19/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>237 Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health 

</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Health
Level 1, 15 Butterfield Street 
Herston Qld 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Griffith University </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>170 Kessels Road, Nathan QLD 4111</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Survivors of critical illness experience significant physical, psychological and cognitive compromise during recovery. ICU diaries have been proposed as one intervention that may be effective in helping survivors recover psychological function. Despite support by some members of the intensive care community, there is a lack of empirical work investigating diaries and subsequent concern regarding the potential harm of such an intervention exists. This study is designed to determine feasibility of two proposed psychological interventions for survivors of critical illness: (1) the use of ICU diaries and (2) the provision of an individualised summary of the ICU experience prepared by ICU staff and based on the User Centred Critical Care Discharge Information. The effect size of each psychological intervention to reduce psychological compromise (anxiety, depression, posttraumatic stress symptomatology) will also be determined to inform sample size calculations for a larger efficacy randomised control trial. Other aims of this pilot study are to determine the feasibility of early screening for psychological health for survivors of critical illness, and to validate the Intensive Care Psychological Assessment Tool (IPAT) against recognised depression and anxiety screening instruments in an Australian ICU population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health Service District Human Research Ethics Commitmee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PAH Centres for Health Research
Level 7, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent Street
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC/15/QPAH/535 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leanne Aitken </name>
      <address>Nursing Practice Development Unit
Building 15
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Wooloongabba QLD 4012 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (7) 3176 7256</phone>
      <fax>+61 (7) 3176 7356</fax>
      <email>l.aitken@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Maria Castillo</name>
      <address>Nursing Practice Development Unit
Building 15
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Wooloongabba QLD 4012 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (7) 3176 7291</phone>
      <fax>+61 (7) 3176 7356</fax>
      <email>m.castillo@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Maria Castillo</name>
      <address>Nursing Practice Development Unit
Building 15
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Wooloongabba QLD 4012 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (7) 3176 7291</phone>
      <fax>+61 (7) 3176 7356</fax>
      <email>m.castillo@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Maria Castillo</name>
      <address>Nursing Practice Development Unit
Building 15
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Wooloongabba QLD 4012 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (7) 3176 7291</phone>
      <fax>+61 (7) 3176 7356</fax>
      <email>m.castillo@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>