<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365393">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001378718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effect of a Multi-strain Probiotic on Metabolic Biomarkers in Adults with Pre-diabetes and Recently Diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effect of a Multi-strain Probiotic on Metabolic Biomarkers in Adults with Pre-diabetes and Recently Diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Insulin resistance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to take either a multi-strain probiotic preparation or a placebo for 12 weeks duration and will be provided with supplementation every 6 weeks. 
The product contains 8 probiotic strains (3 Lactobacillus, 3 Bifidobacterium, Streptococcus thermophilus and 1 yeast (500 mg per capsule equating to 50 billion cfu). Two capsules of the probiotic/placebo will be prescribed to be taken twice a day. The probiotic has to be consumed orally with cold non-carbonated water. The product should not be taken with hot and carbonated drinks.
Participants must return the remaining study supplement and a diary provided to record trial supplement intake every 6 weeks. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will take a placebo which contains inactive ingredients that will look, smell and taste like the probiotic but without any medical benefit. Participants randomised to the control group will take 2 capsules of the placebo preparation (200 mg of microcrytalline cellulose and excipients) twice a day for 12 weeks. 
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting plasma glucose </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum endotoxin quantified by the chromogenic Limulus amebocyte lysate assay


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Faecal microbial profiles (16S rRNA gene sequences)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Faecal metabolomics profiles (SCFA, bile acids and choline will be assessed by GC-MS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gut permeability (serum zonulin analysed by using the Human Haptoglobin Elisa kit)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity measured by the Stanford Leisure-Time Activity Categorical Item (L-cat)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Triglycerides, cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, HDL cholesterol and hs-CRP will be assessed by serum assays. Plasma free fatty acids will be measured using a quatification kit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diet changes will be assessed by a 7-day food diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastrointestinal Symptoms Rating Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c determined by HPLC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin resistance using HOMA and the insulin sensitivity index of matsuda</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks after intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Overweight adults (BMI greater than or equal to 25 kg/m2) with pre-diabetes (impaired fasting glucose, IFG and/or impaired glucose tolerance, IGT) or recently diagnosed with T2DM (less than 12 months)

- Treated by diet alone or diet plus metformin
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Subjects with type 1 diabetes.
- Taking oral blood glucose-lowering medications or anti-obesity drugs (other than metformin)
Pregnant, breast feeding or planning on becoming pregnant
- Concomitant GI disorders.
- Taking antibiotics and dietary supplements including fish oil, probiotics, prebiotics, multivitamins, minerals, herbal preparations etc. 4 weeks before commencing the trial and for the duration of the trial.
- Alcohol abuse and the use of any illicit drug
- Any psychiatric disorders by history or examination that would prevent completion of the study or result in possible adverse events for the participant
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be provided by a holder of the allocation schedule who is off site from the study location. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be screened using the Boden Institute's database and by advertisements through the University of Sydney. 

Potential participants will be invited to phone or email their interest to the clinical trial co-ordinator who will assess their initial eligibility. If eligible, potential participants will be asked to attend the Charles Perkins Centre at the University of Sydney to have an oral glucose tolerance test (prediabetics) or fasting glucose (T2DM). If the participants have IFG or/and IGT or T2DM for less than 1 year and meets all other eligibility criteria they will be invited to enrol in the study.

Participants and study investigators will be blinded to treatment allocation. The study coordinator will perform randomization though a computer randomization tool. As recruitment progresses, participants will be allocated to a treatment group that will be provided to the study investigator on a per-participant basis.

</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size:
From a clinical trial assessing the efficacy of a probiotic in adults with pre-diabetes (Heiman et al., unpublished data) we calculated the effect size using the outcome measure of blood glucose levels during a 2-hour OGTT. With a one-sided alpha set at 0.05 and power set at 0.85, the estimated sample size calculated using two-sample means test based upon Satterthwaites t-test is approximately 24 participants per group. Assuming a drop-out rate of 25%, the sample size should be inflated to 30 per group for a total sample size of 60.

Data analysis:
All data will be summarized descriptively using n, mean, median, standard deviation and 95% confidence intervals for continuous data, and frequency and percent for categorical data. Comparisons between the proportion of patients with IFG, IGT and T2DM will be made using Chi-square tests. Between group comparisons of glucose levels, triglycerides, free fatty acids, total cholesterol, HDL-c, LDL-c, zonulin, endotoxin, hs-CRP, BP, waist to hip ratio, and BMI will be conducted using ANOVA, with sex and baseline levels as covariates.  Changes in gastrointestinal symptoms, quality of life and physical activity will be assessed according to the GSRS, SF-12v2 and IPAQ scoring manuals, respectively.

No adjustment for multiple comparisons will be made.  All tests will be conducted two-sided and p values of less than 0.05 will be considered statistically significant.

Data will be analysed on an intent-to-treat basis using STATA MP v13 for Mac.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>19/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2006 - The University Of Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building D17, The University of Sydney, Camperdown NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medlab Clinical Ltd </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>66 MacCauley Street, Alexandria NSW 2015 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to assess the efficacy of a probiotic preparation in improving glucose metabolism and metabolic markers in adults with pre-diabetes and recently diagnosed with T2DM. Moreover, gut permeability, faecal and metabolomic profiles will be measured to evaluate a potential mechanisms of action of the multi-strain probiotic. We hypothesize that the administration of an evidence based probiotic preparation may modulate the GI microbiota from a dysbiotic to a balanced state improving blood glucose levels, decreasing inflammatory markers and endotoxaemia, and improving lipid profiles.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Palacios T, Coulson S, Butt H, Vitetta L. The effect of microbiota-based interventions and metformin in metabolic and inflammatory biomarkers in adults with type 2 diabetes mellitus. The Science of Nutrition in Medicine, 4rd International Conference. Gold Coast, Australia, 2-4 May, 2014. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Human Reserach Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 8, Building 14, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Camperdown NSW 2015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X14-0369 &amp; HREC/14/RPAH/492</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Caterson</name>
      <address>Level 2 W80, Charles Perkins Centre D17, The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006
 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1944 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ian.caterson@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Talia Palacios</name>
      <address>Level 2 W80, Charles Perkins Centre D17, The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006
 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1962</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8627 0141</fax>
      <email>talia.palacios@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Luis Vitetta</name>
      <address>66 McCauley St, Alexandria NSW 2015</address>
      <phone>+61 4 0226 3316</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luis.vitetta@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Talia Palacios</name>
      <address>Level 2 W80, Charles Perkins Centre D17, The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006
 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1962</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8627 0141</fax>
      <email>talia.palacios@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>