<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362156">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000301864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prehabilitation and Rehabilitation Nursing: Balance/ fall risk in the community-dwelling older adults - Randomized Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prehabilitation and Rehabilitation Nursing: Balance/ fall risk in the community-dwelling older adults - Randomized Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-9522</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ProBalance</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Balance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Functional mobility</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gait</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fear of falling</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Health related quality of life</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fall prevention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following the baseline assessment (of all studied variables/outcomes), the experimental group will receive a multidimensional rehabilitation nursing intervention.
Intervention includes a multiple risk approach, namely, an exercice program (tailored for older adults with moderate to high risk for falling) and an educational component addressing fall prevention and home hazards at the beginning of the intervention period. Rehabilitation sessions will have 90minutes duration, 2 days per week, during 12 weeks. It will include: (1) multisensory training (approaching visual, somatosensory and vestibular systems); (2) center of gravity control Training; (3) proactive and reactive postural strategy training; (4) gait pattern enhancement and variation training; and (5) strengthing and flexibility training. 
The intervention will be administered on a group basis by one trained rehabilitation specialist nurse.
Note that the participants of the initial pilot study (http://www.anzctr.org.au/ACTRN12611001164987.aspx) will not be included in this randomised controlled trial.</interventions>
    <comparator>Waiting list control group. The control group will receive no intervention, only assessments and standard/usual care. After the end of the trial, the intervention will also be available for the control group, because of ethical issues.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance Measured: FAB Scale score (Rose, 2010).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strength (Upper and lower body) Measured: 30 second chair stand, arm curl (Rikli &amp; Jones, 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait parameters Measured: 30-foot walk - Gait stability ratio, gait velocity, cadence (Rose, 2010).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional mobility Measured: 8 Foot Up and Go (Rikli &amp; Jones, 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Home environment modification Measured: Questionnaire based on Lord, Sherrington, Menz &amp; Close (2007).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of falling Measured: Falls Efficacy Scale [FES] - Portuguese version, questionnaire (Melo, 2011).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life Measured: SF-36 - Portuguese version (Ribeiro, 2005).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of fallers (self-reported by the participant, through diary and telefone contact established by the research team)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of falls (number of events, self-reported by the participant, through diary and telefone contact established by the research team)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 12 week intervention.
After follow-up - 12 weeks after the intervention finish.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Community-dwelling older adults; 
FAB score higher than 25/40 and equal or lower than 30/40; 
FAB score betwen 20 and 25/40, if not reporting falls in the last year; 
Able to walk independently.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Cognitive impairment (assessed by the MMST). 
Significant co-morbidities that would preclude participation (acute illness, progressive neurological disease, stroke, unstable chronic conditions, etc.)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Advertisement will be done in the community, using posters, and the media, and dessiminating writting information in social institutions and social networks. The volunteers will be received in the project's laboratory and the assessments on inclusion and exclusion criteria will be done, after informed consent. 
After the first selection of those with inclusion criteria, participants will be randomized and allocated to the groups, and the baseline assessments will be done. A simple randomization process, using computer random number generator, will be used to allocate the participants to one of the two similar groups (1. treatment and 2. control group). Clusters will be considered in the randomization for couples and relatives.
The person who determined if a subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial was unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the subject would be allocated.
This procedure will be done and recorded by an independent person, who is not part of the project's research team.</concealment>
    <sequence>Numbers will be randomly selected to form group 1 and group 2, using a random number generator software.
This procedure will be done and recorded by an independent person, who is not part of the project's research team.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/03/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/04/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>52</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state>Madeira Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bruna Raquel Gouveia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Escola Superior de Enfermagem São José de Cluny
Rampa de Quinta de Sant' Ana, 22.
9050-535 Funchal - Portugal</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Portugal</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bruna Raquel Gouveia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Escola Superior de Enfermagem São José de Cluny
Rampa de Quinta de Sant' Ana, 22.
9050-535 Funchal - Portugal</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Portugal</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ARDITI - Agência Regional para o Desenvolvimento da Investigação, Tecnologia e Inovação</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Edif. Madeira Tecnopolo, Piso 2
Caminho da Penteada
9020-105 Funchal 
Portugal</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Portugal</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade da Madeira</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Colégio dos Jesuítas - Rua dos Ferreiros
9000-082 Funchal - Portugal</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Portugal</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>European Science Foundation Research Networking Programme ‘REFLECTION’</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Europe</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Porto - ICBAS</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Largo Prof. Abel Salazar, 2
4099-033 Porto</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Portugal</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Maria Helena Jardim</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Universidade da Madeira
Centro de Competencia Tecnologias da Saude
Campus Universitario da Penteada
9020-105 Funchal
Madeira</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Portugal</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Maria Manuela Martins</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Escola Superior de Enfermagem do Porto
Rua Dr. Antonio Bernardino de Almeida 
4200-072 Porto</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Portugal</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Debra Rose</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>California State University,Fullerton
800 N. State College Blvd.
Fullerton, CA 
92831-3599</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Élvio Rúbio Gouveia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Madeira</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Portugal</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Duarte Luís de Freitas</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Madeira</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Portugal</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>José António Maia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Porto</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Portugal</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project incorporates a randomized controlled trial aimed to:
(1) Investigate of the effect of a gerontological rehabilitation nursing program in a group of community-dwelling elderly, living in Madeira, Portugal, on balance (FAB Scale scores), muscular strength (30 second chair stand, arm curl), functional mobility (8 Foot Up and Go), gait parameters (30-foot walk), health related quality of life (SF-36 - Portuguese version, Ribeiro (2005)), fear of falling (FES  Portuguese version, Melo (2011)), home environment (based on Lord, Sherrington, Menz &amp; Close; 2007), and number of falls (number of fallers and falls rate), when compared to a control group. 
(2) Describe the relationship between potential confounders and balance/incidence of falls in older adults involved in the rehabilitation program, when compared to a control group. 
This research is based on three hypotheses: (1) A rehabilitation nursing program designed to approach balance and mobility, as well as multiple risk factors, can improve balance in a group of older-adults, when compared to the control group, after a 3 month duration intervention and during follow up; 
(2) A rehabilitation nursing program designed to approach balance and mobility, as well as multiple risk factors, can reduce the risk of falling in a group of older-adults, when compared to the control group, after a 3 month duration intervention and during follow up; and 
(3) The group of older-adults involved in a specific rehabilitation program present higher levels of balance/lower risk for falling, higher levels of strength and functional mobility, better results in gait parameters, higher levels of health related quality of life (SF-36 - Portuguese version, Ribeiro (2005)), reduced fear of falling (FES  Portuguese version, Melo (2011)), and less risk factors in home environment, when compared with the older-adults included in the control group, after a 3 month intervention and 3 month follow up.
An initial pilot study was developed before this trial. Further information on the pilot study is available in the ANZCTR link: http://www.anzctr.org.au/ACTRN12611001164987.aspx.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentations:

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H; Martins, MM;  Gouveia, ER., Freitas, DL., Maia, JA., Rose, DJ. (2014). Impact Of The ProBalance Program On Balance In Community-dwelling Older Adults From Madeira Island, Portugal. 61th Annual Meeting and 5th World Congress on Exercise is Medicine of the ACSM. Florida, USA.


Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H.; Martins, M; &amp; Rose, DJ. (2014). ProBalance  Uma intervenção multidimensional centrada na promoção da funcionalidade do idoso - Seminário Dimensões físicas do Envelhecimento e Exercício  1º ciclo de EDFD, 28 de Fevereiro de 2014, Funchal, Madeira.

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H.; Martins, M; Gouveia ER; Freitas DL; Maia JÁ; Rose D (2013). Equilíbrio e risco de cair em adultos idosos residentes na comunidade, na Região Autónoma da Madeira. II Colóquio Olhares sobre o Envelhecimento, 14 e 15 de Novembro 2013, Universidade da Madeira, Funchal, Madeira.

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H.; Martins, M; &amp; Rose, DJ. (2013). Apresentação do Projeto de Investigação Probalance - Seminário de Envelhecimento e Saúde  1º ciclo de EDFD, 17 de Abril de 2013, Funchal, Madeira.

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H; Martins, M; Gouveia, ER. (2013). O perfil do adulto-idoso aderente a um programa de intervenção para melhorar o equilíbrio e prevenir quedas - Congresso Internacional Género(s) e Saúde: (In)Determinações e Aproximações, Coimbra, Portugal.

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H; Martins, M; Gouveia, ER; Rose, DJ. (2013). ProBalance - Preabilitação e Enfermagem de Reabilitação: Equilíbro/risco de queda em adultos-idosos residentes na comunidade - Ensaio Clínico Controlado Randomizado - V Congresso Envelhecimento(s): a Arte de Viver, 3 e 4 de Outubro, Ponta Delgada Açores.

Gouveia BR; Jardim H; Martins M; Gouveia ER; Freitas DL; Maia JÁ; Rose D. (2012). Balance and fall risk in community-dwelling older adults from Madeira, Portugal. The 8th World Congress on Active Ageing. 14 a 17 de Agosto, Glasgow, Scotland.

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H.; Martins, M; &amp; Rose, DJ. (2012). Apresentação do Projeto de Investigação Probalance, Workshop Envelhecer na actualidade Que desafios?, 1 de Outubro de 2012, Ordem dos Enfermeiros  Secção Regional da Madeira, Funchal, Madeira.

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H.; Martins, M; Gouveia ER; Rose D (2012). ProBalance - Preabilitação e Enfermagem de Reabilitação: Equilíbro/risco de queda em adultos-idosos residentes na comunidade  Ensaio Clínico Controlado Randomizado. Colóquio Olhares sobre o Envelhecimento, 11 e 12 de Outubro 2012, Universidade da Madeira, Funchal, Madeira.

Publications:

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H; Martins, MM;  Gouveia, ER., Freitas, DL., Maia, JA., Rose, DJ. (2015). An evaluation of a nurse-led rehabilitation programme (the ProBalance Programme) to improve balance and reduce fall risk of community-dwelling older people: A randomised controlled trial. Int. J. Nurs. Stud. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2015.12.004

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H; Martins, MM;  Gouveia, ER., Freitas, DL., Maia, JA., Rose, DJ. (2014). Impact Of The ProBalance Program On Balance In Community-dwelling Older Adults From Madeira Island, Portugal. Medicine &amp; Science in Sports  &amp; Exercise, 46 (5), S105.

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H; Martins, M. (2013). Cinesioterapia em Reabilitação Gerontológica: uma análise da literatura. Referência, 11, 133-142. 

Gouveia, BR; Jardim, H; Martins, M; Gouveia, ER. (2013). O perfil do adulto-idoso aderente a um programa de intervenção para melhorar o equilíbrio e prevenir quedas, Referência. [Suppl],10 (3). p.130. 

Gouveia BR; Jardim H; Martins M; Gouveia ER; Freitas DL; Maia JÁ; Rose D. (2012). Balance and fall risk in community-dwelling older adults from Madeira, Portugal. Journal of Aging and Physical Activity. 20. S1  S369.

Gouveia B, Jardim H, Martins M, Fernandes D, Silva B, Vieira L, Bettencourt R, Quintal C, Pinto A, Rodrigues R, Gouveia ER. (2012). O perfil do idoso que cai: Um estudo de caracterização em idosos residentes na comunidade. Livro de Atas do Seminário Internacional de Desporto e Ciência, Universidade da Madeira, 2 a 3 de Março (in press).

Gouveia, B.R., Jardim, H., &amp; Rose, D.J. (2011). Prehabilitation and rehabilitation nursing: Balance/fall risk in community-dwelling older adults. Referencia [Suppl], 2(4). p.432.

Gouveia, B.R., Jardim, H., Martins, M.M. (2011). Foundation of gerontological rehabilitation nursing: applicability of the functional consequences theory . Referencia [Suppl], 1(4). p.475.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comissao de etica para a Saude do Servico de Saude da Regiao Autonoma da Madeira (Ethics commitee of the Health System of the Autonumous Region of Madeira)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hospital Dr. Nelio Mendonca
Avenida Luis de Camoes
9004-154
Funchal
Madeira</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/06/2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Portugal</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruna Raquel Gouveia</name>
      <address>Escola Superior de Enfermagem São José de Cluny
Rampa de Quinta de Sant' Ana, 22.
9050-535 Funchal - Portugal</address>
      <phone>+351291743444</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bgouveia@esesjcluny.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruna Raquel Gouveia</name>
      <address>Escola Superior de Enfermagem São José de Cluny
Rampa de Quinta de Sant' Ana, 22.
9050-535 Funchal - Portugal</address>
      <phone>+351291743444</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bgouveia@esesjcluny.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruna Raquel Gouveia</name>
      <address>Escola Superior de Enfermagem São José de Cluny
Rampa de Quinta de Sant' Ana, 22.
9050-535 Funchal - Portugal</address>
      <phone>+35291743444</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bgouveia@esesjcluny.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bruna Raquel Gouveia</name>
      <address>Universidade da Madeira Centro de Competencia Tecnologias da Saude Campus Universitario da Penteada 9020-105 Funchal Madeira</address>
      <phone>+351291743444</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bgouveia@esesjcluny.pt</email>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>