<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320894">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000118000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Multicentre, Controlled Trial to Determine the Safety and Efficacy of Hypertensive Extracorporeal Limb Perfusion
(HELP) in Treating Patients with Critical Limb Ischaemia (CLI)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In treating patients with Critical Limb Ischaemia (CLI) using Hypertensive Extracorporeal Limb Perfusion
(HELP) when compared to conventional treatments the study evaluates Safety and Efficacy via a multicentre, controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1112-6971</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Hypertensive Extracorporeal Limb Perfusion (HELP)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CTN 036/2010</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critical Limb Ischemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Hypertensive Extracorporeal Limb Perfusion (HELP)  procedure involves the temporary surgical implantation of two large bore access ports (Peripheral Access Devices - PAD) in to the femoral artery (thigh). The devices will be implanted (2hour procedure duration) for a maximum duration of 28 days after which the devices are removed.
Pressure and Flow are then generated by an extracorporeal pump taking the patients blood from one device and returning it in to the the treatment limb. This increased flow allows an improvement in perfusion to the diseased/occluded limb. Pumping sessions will last for around 24 hours at a time and may be repeated every other day for the total treatment period (28 days)</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical Data of CLI Amputees determined by a literature review (worldwide meta analysis of published papers)(taken from within previous 10 years) along with a review of the investigative teams own patient databases</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine safety and efficacy of Hypertensive Extracorporeal Limb Perfusion in preventing major limb amputation by examination for harm (Serious Adverse Events - including Minor Amputations ,Significant infection. haematoma or haemorrhage, Clinically significant thrombosis,	Haemolysis) or further treatment (amputation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after explantation of the PAD devices</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relief of symptoms of peripheral vascular disease - determined by thermography, ultrasound, physical examination, questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after explantation of the PAD devices</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Healing of ulcers determined by photographic records and physical examinations</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after explantation of the PAD devices</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased distal perfusion determined by ankle brachial index (ABI) and also by ultrasound exam</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after explantation of the PAD devices</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Only alternative treatment is imminent (within 8 weeks) major limb amputation
2) At least two vascular surgeons must agree that the treatment is the only remaining option for the patients
3) Patients must be over 18 years of age 
4) Patients have critical limb ischaemia
5) Patients must be able to understand the risks and benefits of the trial and give written informed consent to participate
6) Patients must be fit for anaesthesia 
7) Patients must have suitable anatomy determined by pre-operative imaging and physical examination</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Patients must not be in a concurrent clinical trial
2) Patient must not have compartment syndrome
3) Patients must not have an active systemic infection
4) Patient must not have serum abnormalities or high Creatine Phosphokinase (CPK) (greater than 3x the upper limit of normal for the testing laboratory) as deemed by the clinical investigator
5) Patients must not have general advanced debilitation or intercurrent organ failure
6) Patients must not have a serious wound infection (for example, Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) of the ulcer) that in the opinion of the Clinical Investigator may impede the response to treatment
7) Patients must not have disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) as deemed by the clinical investigator</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients are end stage referrals with no other options.
They are approved to the trial by two independent co-investigators.
All recruited patients if deemed suitable will be treated.</concealment>
    <sequence>There are no randomisations</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/11/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Dalcross Adventist Hospital - Killara</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Advanced Surgical Design and Manufacture</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2/12 Frederick St, St Leonards, NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Advanced Surgical Design and Manufacture</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/12 Frederick St, St Leonards, NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The HELP treatment implants two Peripheral Access Devices (PAD) in to a patients thigh. The devices are connected to a pump (outside of the body). Blood is taken from the upper device and pumped at higher pressure back in to the lower device. The higher pressure increases perfusion in to the diseased limb, reducing pain and promotes growth of new vessels.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Lane RJ, Phillips M, McMillan D, Huckson M, Liang SW, Cuzzilla M,"Hypertensive extracorporeal limb perfusion
(HELP): A new technique for managing critical
lower limb ischemia" J Vasc Surg. 2008 Nov;48(5):1156-65


Khin NY, Dijkstra ML, Huckson M, Phillips M, McMillan D, Itoh S, Roger G, Lane RJ. "Hypertensive extracorporeal limb perfusion for critical limb ischemia"J Vasc Surg. 2013 Nov;58(5):1244-53</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Central Coast Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 2, Building 51,
Royal North Shore Hospital
ST. LEONARDS NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/HARBR/160
HREC Protocol Number 0911-306M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Rodney Lane</name>
      <address>AllVascular Pty Ltd
Suite 13, Greenwich Square, 130-134 Pacific Highway, St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9438 5228</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9906 1573</fax>
      <email>HELP-Trial@asdm.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Rodney Lane</name>
      <address>AllVascular Pty Ltd
Suites 13, Greenwich Square, 130-134 Pacific Highway, St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9438 5228</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9906 1573</fax>
      <email>HELP-Trial@asdm.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jari Hyvarinen</name>
      <address>2/12 Frederick St,
St Leonards,
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9439 4448</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9439 4441</fax>
      <email>jari.hyvarinen@asdm.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rodney Lane</name>
      <address>AllVascular Pty Ltd
Suites 13, Greenwich Square, 130-134 Pacific Highway, St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9438 5228</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>HELP-Trial@asdm.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>