<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362250">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000405819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Fish oil for mood stabilization during pregnancy in women with bipolar disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Long-chain omega-3 fatty acids for mood stabilization during pregnancy in women with bipolar disorder - A randomized controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-5796</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Stabil Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar disorder in pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>5 g concentrated omega-3 triglycerides from fish (containing 1000mg docosahexaenoic acid and 1500mg eicosapentaenoic acid)
Taken as an oral capsule once daily from enrollment (up to 10 weeks of pregnancy) till 12 weeks postpartum.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive: 1 g concentrated omega-3 triglycerides from fish (containing 430 mg docosahexaenoic acid and 90 mg eicosapentaenoic acid) plus 4 g medium chain fatty acids from coconut. Taken as an oral capsule once daily from enrollment (up to 10 weeks of pregnancy) till 12 weeks postpartum.

There will also be a comparator group who have chosen to maintain their mood stabiliser medication. These women will be automatically allocated standard dose fish oil. They will receive: 1 g concentrated omega-3 triglycerides from fish (containing 430 mg docosahexaenoic acid and 90 mg eicosapentaenoic acid) without additional placebo.
Taken as an oral capsule once daily from enrollment (up to 10 weeks of pregnancy) till 12 weeks postpartum.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of mood episode recurrences.
Mood episode recurrence will be defined by DSM-IV criteria for major depression, hypomania or mania, or the need for rescue medication to be provided by the treating clinician due to deteriorating mood.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From baseline to childbirth.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to onset of first mood episode recurrence.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From baseline to childbirth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of depressive and manic symptoms.
The Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) and Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) will be used to assess the severity of mood symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly follow-ups throughout pregnancy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Pregnant women (up to 10 weeks of pregnancy).
2.	Must have a clinical diagnosis of Bipolar Disorder I or II.
3.	Must be using MS medication with an intention to either continue or discontinue MS medication throughout pregnancy (for entry into comparator and experimental groups respectively).
4.	Must not have experienced a mood episode reaching DSM IV-TR criteria within 4 weeks of recruitment.
5.	Must be prepared to continue regular visits to their personal treating medical professional/s throughout study period for ongoing psychiatric and antenatal care.
6.	Must be able to give written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Under 18 years of age.
2.	Poor written and/or spoken English.
3.	Diagnosed with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder.
4.	Taking any daily supplement containing more than 120 mg EPA or more than 500mg EPA + DHA. 
5.	At high risk of suicide.
6.	Participating in another clinical trial.
7.	Current drug or alcohol problems.
8.	Unstable medical condition, unstable thyroid dysfunction, lipid metabolism disorder.
9.	Current use of anticoagulant therapy.
10.	Have a bleeding disorder. 
11.	Fish/seafood allergy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The holder of the allocation schedule will be an independent member of staff that is in no other way invovled in this study.  The research assistant responsible for recruiting the participant will obtain the treatment allocation ('A' or 'B' - blinded)  from the holder of the allocation schedule. Both of these parties are blinded as to the identity of treatments A and B.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated simple random number sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study will also incorporate a 'comparator' group comprising participants who have chosen to maintain MS medication during pregnancy.  These participants will be automatically assigned to receive Standard Omega-3 supplements.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Univeristy of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health and Aging, Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848,
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Black Dog Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hosptial Road
Randwick NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with bipolar disorder (BD) experience recurrent, extreme highs and lows in mood, which can severely affect their health, career and relationships.  BD can often be effectively treated with long-term mood stabilizer (MS) medications.  Unfortunately though, MS medications can cause birth defects and complications if taken during pregnancy.  If women with BD stop taking MS medications during pregnancy however, they run a very high risk of relapse, and unstable maternal mental health during pregnancy is associated with poor outcomes for both mother and child.  In this study, we aim to determine if a natural dietary supplement (omega-3 fatty acids), which is safe for both mother and baby, has the potential to offer women with bipolar disorder an effective alternative to MS medication during pregnancy.   

Long-chain omega-3 fatty acids (LC-omega-3 FA) comprise a family of essential nutrients which have a variety of vital actions in the body.  In particular, LC-omega-3 FA have important effects on brain development and function. Recent studies indicate that LC-omega-3 FA supplementation can affect mood, particularly to reduce depression. In this project, we will undertake a clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy of LC-omega-3 FA supplementation to reduce the occurrence of mood episodes in bipolar women who discontinue their use of MS medication during pregnancy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Secretariat
UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3 (M15)
The University of New South Wales 
Sydney, NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC11506</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Bronwyn Hegarty</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute
Hospital Rd
Randwick, NSW
2031</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9382 3707</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.hegarty@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amelia Paterson</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute
Hospital Rd
Randwick, NSW
2031</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9382 8509</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amelia.paterson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amelia Paterson</name>
      <address>Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9382 8509</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amelia.paterson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>