<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373862">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001514392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving neural function through targeted exercise in older adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A time-course analysis of acute and chronic neurophysiological and functional adaptations and retention following one session (acute) or 12 weeks (chronic) of externally-paced strength training, challenging balance training, or visuomotor training in older adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ageing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Maladaptive neuroplasticity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Impaired functional performance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a randomised controlled trial targeting community dwelling men and women aged 65+ years. The study consists of four groups: 1) Challenging balance; 2) Visuomotor (skill training); 3) Externally-paced strength training; and 4) Usual care control group. Due to limited availability of training facilities and human resources, the study will be conducted over two years, Data collection and the intervention will occur between January and June of 2013 and 2014, respectively. Participants recruited during year 1 will be randomly allocated to either intervention group 1 or 2, while participants recruited during year 2 will be randomly allocated to either intervention group 3 or 4. 

Participants randomised to intervention group 1-3 will be asked to complete three 45-minute supervised training sessions per week for 12 weeks in a purpose-designed facility at Deakin University, Burwood, Victoria. All sessions will be administered as group training sessions, and supervised by the Principle Investigator (Bach Ex Sci (Hons)). Testing for the acute effects of the training sessions will occur at baseline, 5-minutes, 30-minutes, and 60-minutes post-completion of training session 1. Testing for the chronic effects of the training interventions will occur at baseline; and weeks 4, 8, and 12 throughout the intervention period, as well as at week 16 to evaluate the residual effects of the interventions.

Group 1 will be asked to complete four rounds of 12 x 30-second functional balance tasks with varying stance conditions (i.e. single or double-legged), vision (i.e. eyes open or eyes closed), and surface stability (i.e. rigid ground surface or dura-disc). Challenges in the form of a physical perturbation will be introduced to progressively overload the balance requirements of the tasks throughout the intervention period. This mode of training will involve approximately 24 minutes of 'work time' and 21 minutes of 'rest time' during the 45 minute session.

Group 2 will complete five rounds of eight visuomotor tracking conditions requiring participants to match dorsiflexion and plantarflexion ankle movements of varying ankle joint ranges of movement (from 60 to 120 degrees) and movement frequencies (from 0.2 to 1.4 Hz) to a target reference limb as displayed on a monitor. This mode of training will involve approximately 24 minutes of 'work time' and 21 minutes of 'rest time' during the 45 minute session.

Group 3 will complete four sets of five functional lower-limb strengthening exercises at a load of 8-12 repetition maximum in a dual-task condition involving external pacing with an audible metronome set to 60Hz. Four sets of 12 repetitions per exercise will involve approximately 24 minutes of 'work time' and 21 minutes of 'rest time' during the 45 minute session.

All training sessions will be conducted by the principle investigator, and adherence will be recorded on individual data record cards for each participant by the researcher.</interventions>
    <comparator>The usual care control group (group 4) will be a 'no treatment' group, thus participants will undergo testing at equivalent time points, whilst continuing their normal everyday activities. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Motor Evoked Potential (MEP) amplitude measured using transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) to the tibialis anterior (TA) muscle of the dominant limb.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute effects: Baseline, 5 (primary), 30 and 60-minutes post-training session
Long-term effects: Baseline, 4 (primary), 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short-interval intracortical inhibition (SICI) measured with TMS targeting the TA muscle of the dominant limb.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute effects: Baseline, 5 (primary), 30 and 60-minutes post-training session
Long-term effects: Baseline, 4 (primary), 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal compound muscle action potential (MMAX) of the tibialis anterior muscle measured with percutaneous peripheral nerve stimulation to the peroneal nerve.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute effects: Baseline, 5, 30 and 60-minutes post-training session
Long-term effects: Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle thickness of the left and right tibialis anterior muscle measured using an ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional muscle power measured using an unassisted stair climb task (18 stairs with a 19 cm rise and 30 cm run).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aerobic endurance measured using the six minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic knee extensor strength (1 repetition maximum) measured on a leg press machine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric dorsiflexion strength measured using an isokinetic dynamometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isokinetic dorsiflexion torque measured using an isokinetic dynamometer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Static balance measured using single-leg conditions with eyes open or closed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute effects: Baseline, 5, 30 and 60-minutes post-training session
Long-term effects: Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dorsiflexion / plantarflexion movement variability measured with a single-axis goniometer and specialised visuomotor tracking software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute effects: Baseline, 5, 30 and 60-minutes post-training session
Long-term effects: Baseline, 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Community dwelling men and women who are right leg dominant (as determined by the Waterloo Footedness Questionnaire); free of any musculoskeletal injuries or neurological impairments; Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) score &gt;25 (no cognitive impairment); not taking any medications known to influence neurological function (e.g. antipsychotic, antidepressant, anxiety medications); and not participating in any organised training activities including strength training in the past 12 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Left leg dominant (as determined by the Waterloo Footedness Questionnaire); musculoskeletal injuries or pain that may be exacerbated by inclusion in the study; any medical condition that may be contraindicated for TMS (e.g. migraines, seizures); neurological impairments that may alter assessment of neurological function, including cognitive impairment (MMSE score &lt;25); the use of medications known to influence neurological function (e.g. antipsychotic, antidepressant, anxiety medications); and participation in organised training activities including strength training within the last 12 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation performed using computerised sequence generation in Microsoft Excel software. Randomisation was stratified according to gender.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All the data will be analysed on a modified intention-to-treat basis, including all randomly assigned participants, regardless of exercise compliance, with at least one follow-up observation, using Stata (version 15). All data will be checked for normality prior to analysis. Time, group and group-by-time interactions will be examined using generalised linear mixed models with random intercepts fitted for each outcome, including fixed effects for time and an interaction between group and time. A secondary analysis will be run adjusting for baseline value of the outcome variable. 

Sample size: Sample size estimates are based upon effect sizes observed for MEP amplitude and SICI in other studies, either performed in young adults or with a different mode of exercise (Cirillo et al. 2011, McDonnell et al. 2013) due to the lack of relevant studies in older adults or these particular interventions. A priori sample size calculations were performed for a repeated measures within-between group interaction analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) using G*Power version 3.1.9.2 (Kiel, Germany) . The number of groups arebadjusted from four (EP-ST; BAL; VIS; CTRL) to five (four experimental groups plus one covariate of baseline data); and it was estimated that a total of 10 per group would provide an actual power of 81% and 89% for the acute and chronic conditions respectively, to detect a moderate effect size of 0.4 between the training groups and controls for changes in MEP amplitude and SICI, assuming a type I error probability of 0.05 and based on four repeated observations (baseline, 5-minutes post; 30-minutes post; and 60-minutes post) and five repeated observations (baseline; 4-weeks; 8-weeks; 12-weeks; and 16-weeks), with a non-sphericity epsilon (e) correction of 1.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>29/06/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>41</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>13/06/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3125 - Burwood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria
3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria
3125</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to identify and compare the efficacy and time-course of three different centrally demanding interventions (challenging balance; visuomotor; and externally-paced strength training) at inducing use-dependent neuroplasticity and driving functional improvements in community dwelling older adults aged 65 years and over. 

It is hypothesised that a single training session (independent of training type) will induce transient increases in corticospinal excitability and reductions in inhibition, and that older adults will experience use dependent neuroplasticity over the 12-week intervention period compared to a control group, It is further hypothesised that changes in the performance of lower-limb physical tasks will be dependent on the specific training group; and that neurological adaptations and changes to lower-limb task performance will decay after four weeks of no training.

The results from this trial will provide insight into the potential for centrally demanding interventions to exploit the flexibility of the central nervous system's of older adults, and induce positive training related improvements in functional ability.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Moreland, A, Teo, W. P. Daly, R, and Kidgell, D. (2016). A time-course analysis of neurological and functional adaptations following 12 weeks of externally paced strength training in older adults. Exercise and Sport Science Australia Conference, Melbourne, Australia.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>70 Elgar Road 
Burwood 
Victoria
3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-103</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ashleigh Moreland</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
School of Exercise Science, Sport and Health
Panorama Avenue
Bathurst
NSW 2795</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6338 4442</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amoreland@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ashleigh Moreland</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
School of Exercise Science, Sport and Health
Panorama Avenue
Bathurst
NSW 2795</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6338 4442</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amoreland@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ashleigh Weier</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
School of Exercise Science, Sport and Health
Panorama Avenue
Bathurst
NSW 2795</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6338 4442</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amoreland@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ashleigh Moreland</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
School of Exercise Science, Sport and Health
Panorama Avenue
Bathurst
NSW 2795</address>
      <phone>02 6338 4442</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amoreland@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>