<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368118">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000648527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>5% Aciclovir or Honevo(Trademark) as a treatment for cold sores</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adult patients with cold sores will topical medical grade honey reduce healing time compared to topical 5% aciclovir alone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-1537</utrn>
    <trialacronym>KH10</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Herpes Labialis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Topical medical grade Kanuka honey applied to the affected area five times daily for fourteen days or until skin returns to normal, whichever is sooner. A participant diary will record applications during the treatment period. </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment is 5% topical aciclovir cream. Participants in the control arm will apply 5% topical aciclovir to the affected area five times daily for fourteen days or until the skin returns to normal. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Healing time (from randomization to the return to normal skin) as measured daily by participant reported cold sore stage from a pictorial chart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily up to fourteen days. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total healing time, defined as the time from development of first sign or symptom to the return to normal skin, as measured daily by participant reported cold sore stage from a pictorial chart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily up to fourteen days. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total healing time stratified by stage of the lesion at onset of treatment, as measured daily by participant reported cold sore stage from a pictorial chart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily up to fourteen days. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Highest pain severity as recorded daily by participants using the scale 'o - 10' with 0 being no pain and 10 being most pain. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily up to fourteen days. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to pain resolution (defined as the time from first experiencing pain to total resolution of pain), as recorded daily by participants using the scale '0 - 10' with 0 being no pain and 10 being most pain. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily up to fourteen days. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 16 years or over at the time of enrolment.
Presentation to a pharmacy for treatment of a cold sore.
First cold sore symptoms (including prodromal symptoms e.g. tingling/pain) within 72 hours.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any participant who is pregnant or breastfeeding.
Known or suspected allergy to honey, bees, aciclovir and/or glycerin.
Any other condition which, at the investigators' discretion, it is believed may present a safety risk or impact the feasibility of the study or the study results.
Patient has used oral aciclovir or other antiviral medicine, or any topical treatment, medical or complementary, on the current sore.
Participants planning to take or use any concomitant medications, which in the opinion of the investigator, could affect the cold sore during the course of the trial. This includes any topical product, medical or complementary, on the cold sore, oral aciclovir or other antiviral medicine, oral complementary medicines for cold sores, such as lysine supplements.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants will be randomised into the study in a 1:1 ratio, one arm receiving topical medical grade Kanuka honey and the second arm receiving topical 5% aciclovir. Both groups will apply their specific treatment five times a day. Each pharmacy site will be provided an allocation of randomised patient packs containing the treatment allocation and patient diary. Pharmacists will dispense the appropriate treatment as randomised to the participant upon opening of the concealed envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Biostatistitian to generate randomisation schedule.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants and study site staff will not be blinded to the allocated treatment due to the nature of the investigational product. Data analysis will be conducted by a statistician blinded to the allocation. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Assuming that the median control duration of symptoms is five days and looking to achieve a one day median difference, with associated Hazard ratio of 1.25, 423 participants would be needed per arm of treatment, therefore the total required is 846. As this is a short study lasting only for the duration of one cold sore episode, then drop-outs from the study should be low, and so assuming that the drop-out rate is around 10%, then 950 participants will be randomized. This study size is consistent with similar 2-arm or 3-arm cold sore studies have required around 300-350 patients per treatment arm. Kaplan-Meier survival plots and estimates of median healing times and Cox Proportional Hazards with a random effect for participants to take into account the parallel design, compared time to healing and pain duration between treatments. Paired t-tests will be used to compare the continuous variables.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/07/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>950</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Honeylab Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>HoneyLab Ltd
Queens Wharf Business Centre
PO Box 10-799
Wellington, 6011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Honeylab Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>HoneyLab Ltd
Queens Wharf Business Centre
PO Box 10-799
Wellington, 6011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A recent pilot study has shown that medical grade Kanuka honey is an acceptable treatment for cold sores. This large-scale randomised controlled trial has the potential to demonstrate a combination product of Kanuka honey and aciclovir (the current topical standard treatment) as an effective treatment for cold sores. In this study 950 participants seeking over the counter treatment for a cold sore will be randomised to receive either topical medical grade Kanuka honey or topical 5% aciclovir alone. Participants will apply their treatment five times a day for fourteen days or until the skin returns to normal, whichever is sooner. Participants will complete a paper or online diary recording the number of applications, the pain suffered that day and the stage of the cold sore based on a pictorial chart. At day fourteen each participant will receive a follow up telephone call to record adverse events and obtain narrative feedback. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/NTB/93</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368118-HDEC Letter 15NTB93 Approved FULL Application with Non Standard Conditions.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Private Bag 7902 Wellington
6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050147</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alex Semprini</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Private Bag 7902 Wellington
6242</address>
      <phone>+648050260</phone>
      <fax>+64 (0) 9 353 1800</fax>
      <email>coldsore@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alex Semprini</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Private Bag 7902 Wellington
6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050147</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 8050147</fax>
      <email>coldsore@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alex Semprini</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Private Bag 7902 Wellington
6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050147</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>coldsore@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>