<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343216">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000791932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The CKD-FIX Trial: Controlled trial of slowing of Kidney Disease progression From the Inhibition of Xanthine oxidase</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, double-blind, controlled trial to assess the effect of xanthine oxidase inhibitor, allopurinol, on the glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) in patients with stage 3-4 Chronic Kidney Disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CKD-FIX trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease stages 3 and 4</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to either allopurinol or matching placebo after informed consent.  The starting dose will be 1 tablet daily of allopurinol (100mg) for 4 weeks.  If tolerated, the dose will be increased to 2 tablets daily for another 4 weeks. If tolerated the dose will be further increased to 3 tablets daily thereafter.  The maximally tolerated dose (1 or 2 or 3 tablets daily will be continued during the remaining follow up period (total follow up of 104 weeks).</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will be randomised to either allopurinol or matching placebo (indistinguishable from the active treatment but containing no active ingredients) after informed consent.  The starting dose will be 1 placebo tablet daily(100mg) for 4 weeks.  If tolerated, the dose will be increased to 2 tablets daily for another 4 weeks. If tolerated the dose will be further increased to 3 tablets daily thereafter.  The maximally tolerated dose (1 or 2 or 3 tablets daily will be continued during the remaining follow up period (total follow up of 104 weeks).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) at 104 weeks.  The Chronic Kidney Disease Epidemiology Collaboration (CKD-EPI) equation will be used to estimate eGFR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>reduction in GFR &gt;30% from baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>progression to End Stage Kidney Disease requiring dialysis or kidney transplantation; (i.e. if the participant commences dialysis or requires a transplant in the trial follow-up period of 104 weeks).</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in Cystatin C-based eGFR</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>all-cause death</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>composite of reduction in GFR &gt;30% from baseline, End Stage Kidney Disease, and death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>blood pressure The average of three blood pressure readings is calculated by adding the three systolic or diastolic readings together and dividing by 3</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of proteinuria, measured via a 24 hour urine collection </outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>fatal or non-fatal cardiovascular events during course of follow-up period of 104 weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>all-cause hospitalisation - assessed by the collection of data from serious adverse events, Medical Benefits Scheme and Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme, and the Health Costs Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life, as assessed using the Short-Form 36 health survey (self-report)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum uric acid concentration</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness and economic analyses</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events (especially adverse drug reactions such as severe cutaneous adverse reactions- Erythema Multiforme, Stevens-Johnson Syndrome, Toxic Epidermal Necrolysis, minor skin rash, hypersensitivity syndrome, aplastic anaemia, thrombocytopenia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>104 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Adult (age greater than or equal to 18 years) 2. CKD stage 3 or 4 (eGFR 15 to 59 mL/min/1.73 m2) 3. Random urine albumin to creatinine ratio greater or equal to 30mg/mmol OR Evidence of progression of CKD (decrease in eGFR greater than or equal to 3.0 mL/min/1.73 m2 during the preceding 12 months, calculated as the difference between the first and last tests, based on minimum of 3 blood tests with each test done at least 4 weeks apart).

For diagnosis of CKD and determination of eGFR decline, eGFR estimates by wither MDRD or CKD-EPI equation can be used according to the local practice. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Past history of clinically established gout 2. History of hypersensitivity to allopurinol 3. Kidney transplant recipients 4. Concurrent treatment with azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine, theophylline, cyclophosphamide, cyclosporine, probenecid, phenytoin or chlorpropamide 5. Indication for allopurinol, including history of frequent attacks of gout, tophus or tophi on clinical examination or imaging study, uric acid nephropathy, uric acid nephrolithiasis or urolithiasis 6. Current non-skin cancer malignancy 7. Unresolved acute kidney injury in last 3 months 8. Current pregnancy, breast feeding 9. Any psychological illness or condition which interferes with their ability to understand or comply with the requirements of the study 10. Elective or imminent initiation of maintenance dialysis or kidney transplantation expected in the next 6 months. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Screening will occur when subjects come for their usual visit to their treating physician. The patient will have an initial consultation with a study renal physician to discuss study participation. This will include a preliminary eligibility check. Randomisation will occur on the day that trial consent is obtained or within 1 month of consent being obtained. This will include a check to ensure that the patient is still eligible. Randomisation will be conducted utilising a web-based database to allocate the patient to a trial arm using dynamically allocated methods. Medication kits will be numbered and allocated on randomsiation. The medication treatment allocation lists will be prepared by the unblinded trial statistician, and will be programmed into the central web-based randomisation system. This will maintain the allocation concealment for all users of the randomisation system and those handling the medication, including participant, phyisican, study nurse, pharmacist and central clinical research associate. </concealment>
    <sequence>Stratification will occur for study centre, CKD stage (stage 3 vs. stage 4), albuminuria (random urine ACR greater or equal to 60 mg/mmol vs. less than 60 mg/mmol), and presence/absence of diabetes mellitus.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis of change in eGFR will be based on a linear mixed-effects regression model. Change from baseline in the other outcome measures with continuous data (uric acid, blood pressure, proteinuria) will be analysed by the same method. These analyses are based on several assumptions (normally distributed errors and random effects, linear change) which will be tested on blinded data. Where assumptions are not met, appropriate modifications will be made to the models. Binary endpoints will be analysed using the chi-square test with frequencies and percentages per treatment arm and odds-ratios or other measures of treatment effect reported along as summary measures. Treatment differences between subgroups defined by age, CKD stage, proteinuria, diabetes status, cause of CKD (diabetic nephropathy vs. non-diabetic kidney disease vs. polycystic kidney disease), use of diuretics, renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) blockade (ACE inhibitor or ARB vs. no RAAS blockade), gender, racial origin, BMI, and presence of metabolic syndrome, will be assessed via tests for interaction using regression models appropriate for the type of outcome. The predictors of adverse events will be analysed by multinomial logistic regression. The predictors of CKD progression (dependent variable slope of eGFR decline) will be analysed by multivariate linear regression. The predictors of response to uric acid-lowering therapy will be analysed by multinomial logistic regression.

Assuming an annual decline in eGFR of 3 mL/min/1.73 m2,113 loss to follow-up of 5%, drop-in and drop-out rates of 5% (from the treatment arm to the control arm and in the opposite direction), 310 patients per arm or 620 patients in total will have 90% power to demonstrate a 20% attenuated decline in eGFR (change in eGFR of 1.2 +/- 4.0 mL/min/1.73 m2) after 2 years of follow up. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>620</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital Royal Newcastle Centre - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Orange Health Service - Orange</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Tamworth Rural Referral Hospital - Tamworth</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Hervey Bay Hospital - Pialba</hospital>
    <hospital>Logan Hospital - Meadowbrook</hospital>
    <hospital>Nambour General Hospital - Nambour</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
    <hospital>Williamstown Hospital - Williamstown</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunbury Day Hospital - Sunbury</hospital>
    <hospital>Danila Dilba Health Service - Darwin</hospital>
    <hospital>Simon Roger Gosford Renal Research - Gosford</hospital>
    <postcode>2145</postcode>
    <postcode>3168</postcode>
    <postcode>4102</postcode>
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>6009</postcode>
    <postcode>2606 - Woden</postcode>
    <postcode>2800 - Orange</postcode>
    <postcode>2750 - Penrith</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2340 - Tamworth</postcode>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>4655 - Pialba</postcode>
    <postcode>4131 - Meadowbrook</postcode>
    <postcode>4560 - Nambour</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3021 - St Albans</postcode>
    <postcode>3016 - Williamstown</postcode>
    <postcode>3429 - Sunbury</postcode>
    <postcode>0800 - Darwin</postcode>
    <postcode>2250 - Gosford</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Kidney Trials Network (University of Qld)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital,
Bldg 33, Ground Floor,
Ipswich Road,
WOOLLOONGABBA QLD 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601

*Please note: funding pending*</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic kidney disease (CKD), defined as an eGFR &lt;60 ml/min/1.73 m2 and/or the presence of kidney damage (albuminuria or proteinuria) for at least 3 months, is a major public health problem affecting approximately 1.6 million Australian adults. Of these affected individuals, approximately 930,000 have stages 3-4 CKD (eGFR 15-60 mL/min/1.73 m2). CKD patients have a greatly increased risk of adverse renal and cardiovascular (CV) outcomes, even in its early stages. CKD patients are at increased risk of progression to end-stage kidney disease (ESKD). The incidence of ESKD is increasing in Australia by 6% per annum. Apart from an increased risk of ESKD, the presence of CKD is one of the most potent known risk factors for cardiovascular disease (CVD), such that individuals with CKD are more likely to die, mostly from CVD, than survive to the point of needing dialysis or kidney transplantation. A reduction in eGFR &lt;60 ml/min/1.73 m2 is associated with increased risks of all-cause and CV mortality.
The CKD-FIX trial aims to critically examine the efficacy and safety of allopurinol as an agent to slow the progression of chronic kidney disease (CKD).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.aktn.org.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Metro South Hospital and Health Service HREC
Princess Alexandra Hospital 
Centres for Health Research Centres for Health Research
Level 7 Translational Research Institute 
37 Kent Street 
WOOLLOONGABBA QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QPAH/685</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 11 Woden ACT 2606</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.2.14035</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Hyman Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road
Eastwood
SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-02-074</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/RAH/501</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania) Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Tasmania
Private Bag 1
Hobart
TAS 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0014160</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2 A Block
Hospital Ave
Nedlands
WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-072</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Commitees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
C/- MEDSAFE Level 6 Deloitte House 
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington NZ 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/NTA/144</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof David Johnson</name>
      <address>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Renal Department
ARTS building (31)
Princess Alexandra Hospital,
199 Ipswich Road,
WOOLLOONGABBA QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.johnson2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Laura Robison</name>
      <address>Australasian Kidney Trials Network (UQ) Level 4, Bldg 1 Princess Alexandra Hospital, 199 Ipswich Road, WOOLLOONGABBA QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 7716</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 5663</fax>
      <email>ckdfix@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Laura Robison</name>
      <address>Australasian Kidney Trials Network (UQ) Level 4, Bldg 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital, 199 Ipswich Road, WOOLLOONGABBA QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 7716</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 5663</fax>
      <email>ckdfix@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Johnson</name>
      <address>Princess Alexandra Hospital Renal Department ARTS building (31) Princess Alexandra Hospital, 199 Ipswich Road, WOOLLOONGABBA QLD 4102 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5080 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.johnson2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>