<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373657">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001433392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>My Hip Journey : A virtual program for patients undergoing a total hip replacement</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Recovery outcomes after a total hip replacement for patients receiving a Virtual Program (VP) compared to a Standard Program (SP)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1201-7319 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>MHJ</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Total Hip Replacement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The virtual program developed for total hip replacements has been designed to inform patients, support persons and relatives what to expect pre-operatively, while in hospital, post operatively and after discharge. Participants access the virtual program via a web link through the My Hip Journey  Go Well Health. It was designed to give access to information without the patient having to come to the hospital and at a time that suits them 24/7 and it is anticipated that participants use the program on a daily basis commencing two week prior to surgery through until 30 days post-surgery, however they have access to the program up to 12 months post-surgery. The program provides a suite of educational resources including fact sheets, videos, exercise videos and email reminders. The resources change as the patient progress through the program with focus on personal wellbeing and the importance of this in the pre-operative and post-operative periods some example include eating a well-balanced diet, continuing to exercise without increasing pain, medication management and bowel management. Each day the patient home screen when they login is their My Program window lists the videos, information and exercises that have been allocated for them to view/complete that day. Exercises are listed with number of sets and repetitions that the patient is required to do. Participants have access to the health professional team via the program email for 4 weeks post discharge, and can also invite their regular health care providers and/or support person to be part of the team. The health professional team can personalised the participants program and exercises by adding in number of sets and reps for each exercise. 
Intervention fidelity will be assess using the website site analytics. After a participants watches a video or reads information they rate the information, the program marks it as read and provides information on how long the participant spent on that piece of information. Additionally, the exercise videos are marked completed by the participant once done.  Automatically generated emails with the program are sent to the participants on a regular basis to inform participants of the information available on the platform. The professional care team have access to the platform and can view the website analytics for each participant.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator, the standard program consists of participants receiving paper-based information, attending a one hour hospital based pre-operative education session and post- discharge phone follow-up. The education session that is presented by a Nurse, Occupational Therapist, Pharmacist and Physiotherapist, and participants are encouraged to bring their support person to session. The educational booklet in the standard program contain the same content as the intervention program but is delivered via paper. Examples of the content includes  falls prevention, wound care, showering, healthy eating, returning to work, pain management and selecting a personal alarm. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Hip Dysfunction and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (HOOS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-admission, 6 weeks, 3 months &amp; 6 months post-surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5-level 5-dimension EuroQoL (EQ-5D-5L) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-admission, 6 weeks, 3 months &amp; 6 months post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-Efficacy for Managing Chronic Disease (SEMCD)- 6 item</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-admission, 6 weeks, 3 months &amp; 6 months post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Satisfaction Survey. Developed by the research team to see how satisfied patients were from the program they received. Patients in the virtual program will receive additional questions on the usability of the application.</outcome>
      <timepoint> 6 weeks post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Web-based analytics for VP participants only. This will included utilization of web-based application such as modules entered and length of time spend on each module and satisfaction ratings within the application. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness analysis from a funders perspective conducted on an intention to treat basis.
If non-inferiority is shown, a cost effectiveness analysis comparing VP to SP will be conducted from a funders perspective on an intention to treat basis. Direct costs will include the service delivery costs associated with each programme (brochures, photocopying and web-based application fees) as well as the cost of follow-up care (i.e. email, telephone and face-to-face contact time with health professionals). Cost data will be collected from pre-admission through to 6 months post discharge using hospital medical records. Outcomes will include changes in HOOS and quality of life (measured using the EQ-5D-5L). Incremental cost-effectiveness ratios (i.e. comparing the difference in cost between VP and SP with the difference in the outcome) will be calculated for HOOS and Quality Adjusted Life Years, and sensitivity analysis conducted on the key parameters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Commencing from 2 weeks prior to surgery to 6 months post-discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: A participant will be eligible to participate if they are undergoing a primary elective THR, can provided informed consent and have a minimum of a 3 week lead up time prior to surgery. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: A participant will be exclude from the study they are having a revision of the THR, is booked in for either an anterior surgical approach, a bilateral THR or are having a THR following a fractured neck of femur or resurfacing hip or super pathway, has had a previous THR, unable to converse in written or spoken English, has no access to a web based device or a risk assessment and prediction score less than 6.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be conducted 'off site' only after consent has been obtained, in order of recruitment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomization will be conducted to ensure equal number of participants are allocated each week using statistical software. This will be in weekly blocks of 10.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation were conducted based on the primary outcome the HOOS. A non-inferiority method was applied using existing data from Paulsen 2014 (minimal clinically important improvement) and Duivenvoorden 2013 (standard deviation). The calculations were conducted for 3 out of the 5 HOOS subscales and the QOL subscale required the largest sample size. Based on a power of 90% and 5% significant level 42 patients per group is needed. To allow for a dropout rate of approximately 15%, a sample size of 50 per group is required. Therefore, the estimated sample size for the study is 100 participants. 
Data will be reported in accordance with the Consolidated Standards of reporting Trial (CONSORT) for non-inferiority trials. Data analysis will be completed using the principle intention to treat (ITT). Mean (SD), median (IQR) and percentages will be used to describe the characteristics of the study group. 
An analysis of covariance will be used to address the primary outcome, comparing the two groups in terms of change in regards to hip function. If the treatment effect of the VP is within minimally clinical important improvement values of the control group non-inferiority will be implied. Treatment effects will be calculated on the pre-post intervention outcomes at 6 weeks. Further analysis will be performed on the post treatment to 3 month and 6 months post-surgery. The clinical treatment effect of each intervention group will be also analysed using independent t-test, tests of medians, non-parametric test and chi-squared tests on pre-to-post intervention changes across the range of outcome measures and patient satisfaction. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Hollywood Private Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Edith Cowan Univeristy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Edith Cowan University, 270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hollywood Private Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hollywood Private Hospital, Monash Avenue, Nedlands, WA, 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A private hospital in Western Australia introduced a pilot Enhanced Recovery Program (ERP) for THR in 2012 based on an orthopaedic recovery program established in United Kingdom (Wainwright &amp; Middleton, 2010). The ERP for THR included a range of strategies to support the pre-admission, peri-operative, post-operative and post-discharge patient care.  After an extensive evaluation of the pilot program the ERP was introduced as part of standard care in 2013 and has continued as standard care.  The education components of the ERP include information book, hospital based pre-operative education session and post-operative phone follow-up. Patient feedback of the ERP was positive but for patients living in rural locations it was difficult to attend the pre-operative education session.  The private hospital recognised a virtual platform as a solution to provide information for all patients undergoing a THR and also provide a patient clinician interface in the post-discharge period. The private hospital commissioned the development of a virtual program for THR and plan to implement a pilot study to compare the effects of the virtual program versus the standard program for patients undergoing primary THR replacement on patient outcomes.
The aim of this study is to compare a virtual program versus standard program as part of care for primary total hip replacement (THR) on patient outcomes.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hollywood Private Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hollywood Private Hospital Monash Avenue, Nedlands, WA, 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HPH505</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Edith Cowan Univeristy Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Innovation, 270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA 6027</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/09/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>19065</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rosemary Saunders</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University, Building 21, 270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA, 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 3513</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rosemary.saunders@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rosemary Saunders</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University, Building 21, 270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA, 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 3513</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rosemary.saunders@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rosemary Saunders</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University, Building 21, 270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup, WA, 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 3513</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rosemary.saunders@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>