<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373408">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001156370p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate online memory specificity training for the treatment of depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate online memory specificity training for the treatment of depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The online Memory Specificity Training program (e-MeST) comprises 11 modules based on content from validated methods of improving the retrieval of specific autobiographical memories (memories of events that occurred within a specific day and place in someone's life) and reducing depressive symptoms.

Initially, the aims, rationale, structure, and process of the intervention are presented to participants. In each module participants are provided with examples of specific memories. They are then provided with a series of cue words and sentences and asked to retrieve memories from their past relating to these cues. These include positive, neutral, and negatively-themed cue words (e.g., proud, sorrow, table), as well as prompt questions to elicit memories. Participants responses are fed into an algorithm which has been tuned to identify whether the participants response is a specific memory or not. Feedback is then given to help participants learn how to correctly retrieve specific memories. There is no limit to how long participants can take to complete the modules, although previous pilot research has shown they take approx. between 10 and 45 minutes each.
To assess adherence to the training program protocol, the researchers will have information about how many modules were completed and how much time they took to complete .

Once baseline assessment is complete the participants will have a total of two weeks to access and complete the modules at their leisure. Following this they will no longer be able to access the training program. The training program is fully online and automated and does not require therapist guidance, although the participants will be able to contact the researchers if they encounter any issues while using the training program. Participants can complete the training program anywhere that they can access the internet.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will not receive at any intervention. At the cessation of the study follow-up period, three months following the end of the two-week active treatment period, they will have access to the e-MeST training program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of Major Depression as assessed by the e-PASS system, an online, automated, self-report diagnostic tool for mental health disorders</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Training Intervention, one month, and three-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in Centre for Epidemiological Studies Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Training Intervention, one month, and three-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change on the Ruminative Responses Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Training Intervention, one month, and three-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in Problem-Solving as assessed by the Means-End Problem-Solving Task
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Training Intervention, one month, and three-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in Self-Efficacy as assessed by the New General Self-Efficacy Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Training Intervention, one month, and three-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change on the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7 scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Training Intervention, one month, and three-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) greater than or equal to 18 years
(ii) residing in Australia
(iii) a current diagnosis of a Major Depressive Episode
(iv) access to the internet
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) non-fluency in English
(ii) likely alcohol use disorder</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation will involve central randomisation by a computer, and will occur once participants complete the baseline assessment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple 1:1 randomisation, using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Using G*Power 3.1, it was calculated that a total sample of 125 participants will be needed; 105 for the main analyses and 20 for the pilot sample. This will account for an attrition rate of 35% between baseline and follow-up. This sample will provide 80% power to detect a moderate group by time interaction effect (d = .60) with 5% Type I error (two-sided tail). This effect is conservative relative to previous findings of the MeST training delivered in a face-to-face format (Cohen's d = .97).
Analyses will be on an intention-to-treat basis, with supplementary per protocol analyses. Linear mixed models will assess differences between conditions at each time-point, and allow inclusion of participants with missing data. Condition, time-point, and their interaction will be modelled as fixed effects. Participants will be modelled as random effects at time-points. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>125</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Impairment in the ability to recall detailed autobiographical memories (AM) of in ones life is a factor in the onset and maintenance of clinical depression. This is due to the critical role that specific AM play in healthy psychological functioning. For example, an impaired ability to retrieve specific AM is associated with poorer problem-solving, imagining, planning, and prediction, inaccurate appraisals of past events, and faulty decision-making. Without the ability to draw on our experiences in a detailed way, our capacity to adapt in the world is clearly impaired. 
Interventions designed to improve AM specificity involve training in retrieving memories. Preliminary studies of a face-to-face training program indicate it can produce significant improvement in AM specificity and depressive symptoms. Improving AM specificity appears to be a promising means by which to reduce depressive symptoms. Further, such interventions need not be delivered by a clinician, which provides the opportunity to test its delivery via the internet. Online mental health interventions are clinically- and cost-effective, with good equity of access given the majority of Australians use the internet regularly (83%), and almost all from home (97%). As over 1.1 million Australians meet criteria for a Major Depressive Episode, yet approximately 50% do not access services and 30% do not respond to current first-line treatments, there is clear scope for more accessible and effective interventions. 
The objective of this project will be to conduct the first randomised controlled trial of this online memory specificity training intervention to treat clinical depression. The study will also examine the mechanisms of change of this intervention, with implications for its broader use
It is hypothesised that:
- Individuals that receive the intervention, relative to those that don't, will report a lower incidence of depressive disorders at post-intervention and follow-up, and reductions in depressive symptoms; 
- the intervention group, relative to the non-intervention group, will report improvements in psychological resources at post-intervention and follow-up.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>TBC</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee (DUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David John Hallford</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, Faculty of Health, Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 421 763 436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.hallford@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David John Hallford</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, Faculty of Health, Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 421 763 436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.hallford@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David John Hallford</name>
      <address>School of Psychology, Faculty of Health, Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 421 763 436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.hallford@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David John Hallford</name>
      <address>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 421 763 436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.hallford@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>