<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343162">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000812998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise-based videogames for stroke rehabilitation at home: a single subject randomised trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The feasibility and efficacy of exercise-based videogames for upper and lower limb stroke rehabilitation at home: a single subject randomised trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-6771</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A crossover study design will be used. There will be 4 two-week intervention periods. During each intervention period, the participant will use exercise-based videogames (X-Box Kinect and Apple I-pad) independently at home. These videogames will be setup in the participant's home 2 weeks prior to beginning the first intervention period to enable a 2-week unblinded 'run-in' period. During each intervention period, either upper limb or lower limb videogame exercise will be undertaken. There will be no 'washout period' between the intervention periods. The participant will be asked to perform as much practice using the videogames as possible within their normal daily routine, and to progress to more physically challenging games as able. The videogames used and their intensity or difficulty will be participant selected, however an experienced clinical physiotherapy neurology specialist will be available via phone to assist the participant with any exercise-related questions. A technology specialist will also be available to assist with any videogame hardware issues.</interventions>
    <comparator>The order of upper limb and lower limb exercise periods will be randomised to ensure two upper limb and two lower limb intervention periods. i.e. The 2 week upper limb intervention periods will serve as a control for the 2 week lower limb intervention periods and vice versa.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Choice stepping reaction time (Lord and Fitzpatrick 2001)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10 days (at least) of each 14 day intervention period, and at 8 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Upper limb reach time. The average time of 3 trials will be used at each timepoint. This test will measure the time it takes the participant to reach with their affected upper limb to click a computer mouse positioned on a table in front of them while seated in response to the illumination of a red light. The test is commenced by the participant clicking a 'start button' with their intact hand. The participant then tries to reach with their affected arm as fast as they can, from a starting position of palm down on their affected thigh, to click the mouse positioned on the table in front of them at a standardised distance, approximating full elbow extension. The mouse is connected to an electronic timer which will display the time elapsed from the illumination of a red light to the pressure of the participant's index finger on the mouse key. The time it takes for the red light to illuminate after the start button is pressed is random.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10 days (at least) of each 14 day intervention period, and at 8 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>High-level Mobility Assessment Tool total score (Williams et al, 2010). This tool quantifies high-level mobility tasks such as walking on toes, running and hopping.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step Test (Hill et al 1996). The number of steps in 15 sec of 1)the affected, 2)unaffected, and 3)both legs alternately will be assessed using a 7.5 cm step.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Six-minute walk distance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3 metre forward tandem (heel-to-toe) walk  time</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Action Research Arm Test total and subgroup scores (Yozbatiran et al 2008)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Summed score of the Motor Assessment Scale upper limb items (6, 7, and 8) (Pickering et al 2010).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Box and Block Test (Mathiowetz et al, 1985).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>System Usability Scale (Digital Equipment Corporation, 1986). The System Usability Scale is a 10-item Likert scale that provides a global view of subjective assessments of usability. It will be used to determine the participant's subjective assessment of usability of 1)lower limb videogames, and 2)upper limb videogames used in this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 Weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total time spent engaged in upper limb and lower limb exercise-based videogames. The participant will keep a daily recording log of time spent using each exercise-based videogame for the lower limb. The upper limb exercise-based videogame duration will be captured by the software automatically.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average time/day, as well as 2 week, and 8 week totals will be analysed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective video assessment of walking, and running by an experienced neurological physiotherapist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Functioning. 
This will be assessed using the Basic Mobility and Daily Activity domains of the Computer Adaptive Testing version of the Boston University Activity Measure for Post Acute Care (AM-PAC) (Haley et al 2004). The AM-PAC measures functional outcome by using Item Response Theory. The AM-PAC Basic Mobility domain includes 101 items that address basic movement and physical functioning activities, such as bending, walking, carrying, and climbing stairs. The AM-PAC Daily Activity domain includes 70 items that address basic self care and instrumental activities of daily life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The single participant is a long-term adult stroke survivor. He has ongoing lower limb and upper limb motor coordination problems on his affected side. He is able to walk independently and use his affected arm for daily tasks. He lives independently within the community.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>51</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>51</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>N/A</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation of the participant to the sequence of upper and lower limb intervention periods will be carried out by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is 'off-site'. The investigators did not know the order of UL/ LL conditions when  determining the participant's eligibility. 
The participant is active in the Stroke Recovery Association. A colleague (Professor Lindley) met the participant at Stroke Recovery Association events and introduced him to the investigators. The investigators have designed the study in consultation with the participant.</concealment>
    <sequence>The order of 2 week upper limb and lower limb exercise-based videogame periods will be randomised using a blocked randomisation schedule to ensure two upper limb and two lower limb intervention periods over an 8 week period.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Single-subject randomised controlled trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mr Bradley Lloyd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bankstown Lidcombe Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
Locked Bag 1600
Bankstown
NSW 2200</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bankstown Lidcombe Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bankstown Lidcombe Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
Locked Bag 1600
Bankstown
NSW 2200</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ingham Institute for Applied Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ingham Institute
Locked Mail Bag 7017
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neuroscience Research Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
PO Box 1165
Randwick NSW 2031
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Catherine Sherrington</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The George Institute for Global Health
PO Box M201
Missenden Road
Sydney
NSW 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr Karl Schurr</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Bankstown Lidcombe Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
Locked Bag 1600
Bankstown
NSW 2200</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Stuart Smith</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
PO Box 1165
Randwick NSW 2031
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aims of the study include 1)to determine whether 8 weeks of exercise-based videogame exercise performed at home independently by a chronic stroke survivor is feasible; and 2) to determine whether exercise-based videogames used at home independently by a chronic stroke survivor improve upper and lower limb motor coordination. A single-subject randomised controlled trial design will be used. The participant is an independently-living 51 year old long-term male stroke survivor with ongoing lower limb and upper limb motor coordination problems on his affected side. The participant will practise upper limb and lower limb exercise-based videogames independently at home over an 8-week period (2 x 2 weeks of upper limb exercise-based videogames, and 2 x 2 weeks of lower limb exercise-based videogames). The order of the upper limb and lower limb exercise periods will be randomised. The participant will practise the games as much as possible during his normal daily routine. The primary outcomes include choice stepping time (lower limb) and arm reach reaction time (upper limb). Secondary outcomes include the High-level Mobility Assessment Tool, tandem walk, step test, 6-minute walk, upper limb items of the Motor Assessment Scale, Box-and-Block Test, Action Research Arm Test, System Usability Scale, and subjective gait video assessment. This study will provide valuable information on the feasibility and efficacy of using exercise-based videogame exercises in the home after stroke</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building - G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 AUSTRALIA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06-2011 / 13887</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/06/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Bradley Lloyd</name>
      <address>Bankstown Lidcombe Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
Locked Bag 1600
Bankstown
NSW 2200</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9722 7095</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lloyd.bd@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Bradley Lloyd</name>
      <address>Bankstown Lidcombe Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
Locked Bag 1600
Bankstown
NSW 2200</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9722 7095</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lloyd.bd@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Bradley Lloyd</name>
      <address>Bankstown Lidcombe Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
Locked Bag 1600
Bankstown
NSW 2200</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9722 7095</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lloyd.bd@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>