<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364114">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000546752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A trial to test reduction in renal nerve activity as a possible treatment for heart failure. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study of Renal Denervation for Heart Failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction to reduce left atrial volume index (LAVi) and/or left ventricular mass index (LVMi) on cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (cMRI).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The RESPECT-HF Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Renal Denervation (RDN) is a simple catheter procedure removing excess nerve signals to and from the kidneys. The  renal denervation system consists of a small steerable treatment catheter and an automatically-controlled treatment delivery generator. The treatment does not require open surgery.
A guiding catheter is inserted through a tiny incision in the groin into the femoral artery to direct the treatment catheter to the renal arteries. The treatment catheter delivers high-frequency radio waves, called RF waves, to 46 locations within each of the two renal arteries. The energy delivered is about 8 watts. This energy delivery aims to disrupt the nerves and lower blood pressure over a period of months. The procedure takes 40 -60 minutes. RDN has been able to reduce Blood Pressure (BP) in patients with high BP resistant to multi-drug treatment. Through removing excess nervous drive to the kidneys, heart and circulation this treatment has promise in Heart Failure (HF). </interventions>
    <comparator>Continued medical management will comprise management of all cardiovascular risk factors (hypertension, diabetes, dyslipidaemia) in accord with international guidelines. As there is no established evidencebased pharmacotherapy for Heart failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction (HFPEF) per se, therapy aimed at HF specifically will adopt treatments recommended for HFREF with prescription of diuretic, ACE inhibitor/ARB, beta blocker and mineralocorticoid antagonist accordingly.    

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in left atrial volume index (LAVi) and/or left ventricular mass index (LVMi) on cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (cMRI) in Heart Failure with Preserved Ejection Fraction (HFPEF). </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise capacity and functional status as assessed by maximal oxygen consumption (VO2max) on cardiopulmonary exercise testing and by 6-minute walk test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced chocardiographic grade of diastolic dysfunction  as assessed by Tissue Doppler E/e, (a non-invasive estimate of left atrial filling pressure).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of  biomarkers of cardiac load and interstitial fibrosis as assessed by plasma assays of markers of ventricular and atrial haemodynamic load and other neurohormones contributing to HF pathophysiology as well as cytokine markers of inflammation and remodelling and markers of cardiac fibrosis and  a marker of cardiomyocyte loss. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in ventricular-vascular function as evaluated by echocardiographic measures of arterial elastance, Left Ventricular (LV) end-systolic elastance, LV filling pressure, and LV diastolic stiffness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as assessed by the Minnesota Living with Heart Failure (MLWHF) scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in the composite end-point of death or re-admission with Heart Failure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The benefits listed above for renal denervation will apply to those with and without hypertension</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Patients with HFPEF (based upon ESC diagnostic criteria) 
a.        Symptoms and signs of heart failure; NYHA Class II or higher
b.       Left ventricular ejection fraction 50% or greater on echocardiography
c.        Echocardiographic evidence of left ventricular diastolic dysfunction (echo-Doppler E/e                  &gt; 15 ) AND/OR  plasma NTproBNP &gt; 220pg/ml.
*Episode of acute decompensation (ADHF)  requiring hospital admission within the 12 months prior to recruitment 
*Patients with and without background hypertension may be recruited. In the case of patients with background hypertension (ie history of fulfilling the diagnostic WHO criteria for hypertension: SBP &gt; 140 mmHg and/or DBP &gt; 90 mmHg) those with both controlled (&lt;140/90mmHg by 24 hour ambulatory BP) and inadequately controlled BP (on 3 anti-hypertensive drugs including a diuretic) can be recruited. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Known secondary cause of hypertension 
*Renal artery stenosis &gt;30% or anatomy otherwise unsuitable for RDN.
* Heart failure with reduced LV ejection fraction (LVEF &lt; 50%).
*Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) of &lt; 30mL/min/1.73m2 (MDRD calculation).
*Systolic blood pressure &lt; 105mmHg.
*Implanted pacemaker, prosthetic heart valve or other precluding cMR scanning.
*Medical condition adversely affecting safety and/or effectiveness of the participant (including peripheral vascular disease, abdominal aortic aneurysm, thrombocytopenia or uncontrolled atrial fibrillation).
*Pregnant, nursing or planning to be pregnant.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited by regular systematic screening, by a local study coordinator, of ward admissions, clinic attendees and referrals of patients fulfilling inclusion but not exclusion criteria. Participants will provide informed, written and signed consent and the study protocol will be approved by local Institutional Review Boards. All initially eligible patients will undergo comprehensive echocardiography and if satisfying echo criteria and all inclusion criteria will proceed to a magnetic resonance (MR) study of renal artery anatomy. If unsuitable the procedure concludes and the patient is excluded. If anatomy is suitable the patient is then randomized  (with allocation concealment by sealed opaque envelopes) to RDN or medical management  (Those randomized then undergo blood flow measurements and renal perfusion studies and proceed to cardiac MR in the same session. </concealment>
    <sequence>Using a  randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation, participants will be assigned assigned  1:1 to renal angiography proceeding to RDN or to continued medical management. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary inter-group comparisons will be of change in Left Atrial volume index and Left Ventricular mass index between baseline and 6 month cardiac Magnetic Resonance Image scans. Primary and secondary continuous outcomes will be compared between randomised groups using a general linear model. This model will compare changes in the outcomes using baseline level as a covariate and stratum (Centre) and randomised group as fixed factors. Survival analysis (Cox regressions) will be used to compare the time to key clinical events (death, Heart Failure admission, other cardiovascular admissions including acute coronary syndromes, arrhythmia and all admissions) with randomised group and stratum as factors. Interaction analyses will be conducted for the possible influence of baseline blood pressure (hypertensive or normotensive).
The primary analysis will be undertaken on the intention to treat patient population with sensitivity analyses using the per-protocol population.    
Sample size and power have been considered by our biostatistician co-investigator Associate Prof Chris Frampton. Given a standard deviation of LAVi of 5 ml/m2 and two-tailed alpha set to 0.025 (for dual primary end-points); group sizes of 60 provide 90% power to detect a difference in change between groups of 4 ml/m 2 and similar power to detect as little as 5gm inter-group difference in change in LVM. 
For MVO2 given an SD of 5ml/min/kg this group size provides 90% power to detect a 3ml/min/kg difference. Given prior reports from a trial in HFPEF 26  we also anticipate adequate power to detect a 3 unit change in E/e , a 10 point fall in MLWHF score and 30% change  in NTproBNP levels.
We will therefore recruit a total of 144 patients in expectation of 120 completing the protocol.
Documentation of clinical event rates will provide indicative information to power a phase 3 trial for cardinal clinical morbid and mortal endpoints although the current proposal is unlikely to have sufficient power to detect statistically significant effects for these endpoints.
      
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>144</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christchurch Heart Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 5541, Wellesley Street, Auckland 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic International Ltd.
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>49 Changi South Avenue 2
Nasaco Tech Centre
Singapore 486056
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Singapore</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary> We will test a new approach to a form of heart failure (HF) with no current treatment proven to reduce death rates or hospitalisations. Over a third of HF cases have preserved ejection fraction (HFPEF) often on a background of high blood pressure (BP). These stiff hearts pump strongly but fill inefficiently resulting in poor exercise capacity and high death rates.  Treatments that help when heart pumping action is poor are of no benefit in HFPEF.  Recently a simple catheter procedure removing excess nerve signals to and from the kidneys (renal denervation; RDN) has been able to reduce BP in patients with high BP resistant to multi-drug treatment. Through removing excess nervous drive to the kidneys, heart and circulation this treatment has promise in HF. We will compare effects of RDN and standard medical treatment on heart function, exercise capacity and quality of life in 144 patients with HFPEF.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health &amp; Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 the Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/CEN/64/AM01</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Richards</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345 
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+643 364 1063</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark.richards@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lorraine Skelton</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345 
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+643 364 1063</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lorraine.skelton@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Richards</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345 
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+643 364 1063</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark.richards@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lorraine Skelton</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345 
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+643 364 1063</phone>
      <fax>+643 364 1115</fax>
      <email>lorraine.skelton@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>