<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="361974">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000094875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial to improve depression in family carers through a physical activity intervention</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to improve depression in family carers through a physical activity intervention</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IMPACCT Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Carers with depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Six month physical activity program -
An individualised home based strength, balance and walking programme (based on the Otago programme) for care recipient/carer dyads (that they can do together). It will be prescribed by the intervention physiotherapist for both the carer and the care recipient during a home visit within two weeks of baseline assessment. Although the functional levels are likely to vary, the intervention physiotherapist will aim to select several common exercises for the carer and care recipient with variation in elements  to modify the specific difficulty of the exercise to the individual. In this way the carer/care recipient dyad will be able to have some common elements to share as they exercise together.  Each participant will receive 4-8 exercises, to be performed at least five days each week at home (average duration around 20 minutes), and a walking program (where possible, the carer and care recipient will walk together). The intervention physiotherapist will perform a further four home visits over the 6-month duration of the exercise program, to review exercises, change exercises if indicated, and to encourage and support ongoing participation and adherence to the program.</interventions>
    <comparator>Six month social visits - 
To ensure an equivalent level of contact to the intervention group, participants in the social visit control group will receive an initial home visit and four further home visits from a RA. The topics of conversation will be structured and standardised. 

A third arm will also be included. The usual care control group will receive an initial phone call to explain group allocation and data collection.  Usual care is defined as as would normally accur if participiant was not involved in the research study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carer Depression - Geriatric Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>0,6,12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carer Activity level as measured by Human Activity Profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>0,6,12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Care recipient depression as measured by Geriatric Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Care recipient activity level as measured by the Human Activity Profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether the intervention is cost effective by a health economic evaluation. It will considers the efficiency of the intervention in reducing the proportion of carers who are depressed (GDS &gt; 5) at the final follow-up assessment compared to the control conditions.  Direct health costs (using Medicare and Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme databases, patient log and interview at assessment points), costs of providing the intervention, non-health costs , and indirect costs (eg productivity losses incurred by care-givers having to take time off other work in order to care for participant will be considered from the societal perspective.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Carer aged over 55 years
Care Recipient aged over 60 years
Both live at home
Care recipient is dependent in at least one activity of daily living
Carer has 5 or more depressive symptoms as measured on the GDS</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Carer less than 55 years
Care recipient less than 60 years
Care recipients who do not have an informal co-resident carer
Carers who do not live with the care recipient
Carers who do not have 5 or more depressive symptoms
Either declining consent to participate
Carers who do not have the cognitive capacity to give informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/05/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>9/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>546</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>212</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>12/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Ageing Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>P.O. Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
VIc 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research Administration Section
National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra City ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Most older people with disabilities live in the community with support from informal carers. Whilst carers are generally willing to take on the caring role, it often has an adverse impact on their physical and emotional health, particularly depression. There is evidence that the lower the care recipients function, the more their carer experiences these problems. Whilst the effectiveness of exercise interventions for older individuals has been demonstrated, to our knowledge this is the first RCT that targets both the care recipient and the carer. This study will address the question of whether an individualised physical activity program for care recipient/carer dyads (that they can do together) can improve both the physical and psychological wellbeing of the care recipient and their carer. It will also examine whether the intervention is cost effective.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville Victoria 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-41</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Briony Dow</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Vic 3050</address>
      <phone> +61 3 8387 2639</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.dow@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sue Malta</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2614</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.malta@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sue Williams</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2614</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.williams@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Briony Dow</name>
      <address>P.O. Box 2127 Royal Melbourne Hospital Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>61 3 83872639</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.dow@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>