<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365250">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001223729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Implementing care coordination plus early rehabilitation in high-risk chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients in transition from hospital to primary care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Implementing care coordination plus early rehabilitation in high-risk chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients in transition from hospital to primary care: investigating outcomes of pilot intervention on feasibility, fidelity, patient and carer satistaction; documentation of and progress toward patient goals; collaboration with general practice; physical activity levels and readmission.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>none</utrn>
    <trialacronym>none</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The care coordination plus early rehabilitation intervention (flexible duration 1-2 months depending on patient needs) will be implemented by a specialist respiratory Nurse Practitioner (NP) and a research assistant physiotherapist (RPT) and include the following components:
(1) Liaison with existing Sub-acute Respiratory Service (SRS) inpatient hospital COPD coordinator for streamlined transition into SRS.
(2) Care coordination by weekly home visit (NP) to patient (30 min- 1 hour each week during 1-2 month intervention) with additional phone contact as required, including the following components:
Needs assessment, problem identification, goal setting and care planning with the patient (using the Flinders Program). The patients carer will be invited to participate in care planning discussions. 
Facilitation of referrals across all health sectors in collaboration with the patient/carer and relevant members of the health care teams involved.
(3) Early rehabilitation by weekly visit (research assistant physiotherapist; 30 min visits weekly during 1-2 month intervention) including the following components:
Walking program: commence at 2 x10 min walks/day prescribed at 40% of peak speed in 2 minute walk test prior to hospital discharge; optimal walking aid prescription
Interrupt daytime sedentary periods of &gt;1 hour with sit-stand. Use of self-report exercise diary.
(4) Collaboration with patient/carer, local primary care practice nurse and GP to integrate care using existing MBS items (Team Care Arrangement/Case Conference).
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in an existing observational study Time spent in sedentary and physical activity in people with COPD during and after a hospital admission will comprise the control group. This study included patients admitted to hospital with a primary diagnosis of COPD, confirmation of COPD diagnosis by previous pulmonary function testing and length of admission at least 48 hours. Potential participants are excluded if they have (a) insufficient English language or cognition to give informed consent; (b) been unable to walk during the previous 3 months. Recruitment commenced in March 2013 and will continue until October 2013. These patients all received standard treatment (eg discharge letter to usual GP, services organised for transitional care by hospital staff as required). Participants in the control group have had physical activity levels measured and hospital readmissions monitored at one month after discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Documentation of agreed patient goals and progress toward them using Flinders Program Problems and Goals Assessment, Flinders Program Care Plan, documentation of service facilitation
</outcome>
      <timepoint>End intervention (ie 1 month after hospital discharge)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generation of Team Care Arrangement or other evidence of GP collaboration (documented by nurse practitioner)</outcome>
      <timepoint>End intervention (1 month post hospital discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of pilot intervention feasibility (by examination of recruitment rate, retention rate, and resource capability)</outcome>
      <timepoint>End intervention (1 month post hospital discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of pilot intervention fidelity (care coordination and early rehabilitation components delivered as planned; exercise sessions completed as planned by participant diary)</outcome>
      <timepoint>End intervention (1 month post hospital discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels as documented by accelerometer and inclinometer worn for one week, compared with control group</outcome>
      <timepoint>one month after hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital readmissions compared with control group</outcome>
      <timepoint>one month after hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients admitted to hospital with a primary diagnosis of COPD; confirmation of COPD diagnosis by previous pulmonary function testing; length of admission at least 48 hours. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential participants are excluded if they have (a) insufficient English language or cognition to give informed consent; (b) been unable to walk during the previous 3 months. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible participants will be receive the pilot intervention, and comparison in two secondary outcomes (physical activity level and hospital readmissions) will be made with a similar group of patients enrolled in an observational study already conducted.</concealment>
    <sequence>n/a</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Number of participants in this pilot study intervention was determined by the anticipated recruitment capability of suitable patients during the available time frame (Nov 2013-May 2014).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kylie Johnston</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Primary Health Care Research Institute, Australian National University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Barry Dr, Acton ACT 0200 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mrs Mary Young</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sub-Acute Respiratory Service
Level 4, North Wing 
Room 2D54
Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to pilot the implementation of care coordination plus early rehabilitation in a high-risk COPD population in transition from hospital to primary care. This intervention will dovetail with the existing Sub-Acute Respiratory Services (SRS) of the Central Adelaide Local Health Network (CALHN) and the Central Adelaide and Hills Medicare Local (CAHML) COPD Project. Stronger partnerships will be created to improve the clinical handover of patients and address gaps identified by both services.

This study will determine whether this model of care coordination plus early rehabilitation is feasible, acceptable, carried out with fidelity and effectiveness (compared with a no-intervention control group). If so, this model could be implemented in a larger Australian cluster randomised trial and outcomes examined over a longer duration. If effective, the role of specialist Nurse Practitioners as community care coordinators could be implemented as effective links between primary and acute hospital care of people with chronic lung conditions.

Study Hypotheses
(a) Implementation of the pilot intervention (care coordination plus early rehabilitation) is feasible, satisfactory to patients and carers and can be delivered with fidelity.
(b) Care coordination plus early rehabilitation will result in (i) documentation of agreed patient goals and (ii) demonstrated progress toward them assessed by the four major Flinders Program Care Planning Tools: Partners in Health / Cue and Response / Problems and Goals assessment and Self-Management Plan in at least 85% of cases. 
(c) Care coordination plus early rehabilitation will involve collaboration with the patient's GP/practice nurse with generation of a Team Care Arrangement in at least 85% of cases. 
(d) People with COPD who participate in care coordination plus early rehabilitation will have lower hospital readmission rates at 28 days and greater physical activity levels at 28 days after discharge than a control group of similar patients.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of SA
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>31990</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>131004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Johnston</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2086</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8302 2853</fax>
      <email>kylie.johnston@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Johnston</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2086</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.johnston@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Johnston</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2086</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.johnston@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>