<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82068">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000310460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Soltab Understanding Patient Preferences in ORal Therapy (SUPPORT) survey</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients stabilised on mirtazapine therapy for depression, does the new orally disintegrating formulation rate more highly in terms of patient preference?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SUPPORT</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participation open to patients with depression stabilised on conventional tablet formulation of mirtazapine.
Usual maintenance dose of mirtazapine is 30-45mg/day (max 60 mg/day). The dosage is identical for both the conventional and orally disintegrating formulations.
Both the conventional and orally disintegrating formulation is taken once a day, before bed.
Patients complete entry survey regarding attitudes, preferences and satisfaction wtih current antidepressant therapy.

Patients commence one-month trial of treatment using mirtazepine orally disintegrating tablet formulation.

One month later, patients complete exit survey on attitudes, preferences and satisfaction after trial of mirtazepine orally disintegrating tablet formulation.

Randomly selected group of patients approached for follow-up telephone survey at six months after completion of exit survey.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of patient satisfaction with mirtazapine orally disintegrating formulation to that of mirtazapine conventional tablet formulation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Satisfaction with conventional mirtazapine tablets is measured at baseline and comparison is made to satisfaction with mirtazapine orally disintegrating formulation at 1 month. A randomly selected group of patients is followed up at 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identification of factors that patients consider a priority in choosing their antidepressant therapy.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Attitudes regarding priorities in antidepressant choice are examined at baseline. Comparison is made at one month. A randomly selected group of patients will be surveyed at 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether patients' perception of control over their therapeutic decisions influences their likelihood of medication adherance.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients perceptions of level of control and self-reports of treatment adherance are measured at baseline. Comparison made at 1 month. Randomly selected group of patients followed up at 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Routine presentation of patients treated with conventional oral tablet mirtazapine- opportunistic assessment of patient suitabiltiy for participation in survey- identified patient categories likely to prefer orally disintegrating tablet formulation- after conducting risk-benefit analysis, patients who are likely to have a positive benefit are offered the opportunity to participate- patients must be agreeable to trial of mirtazapine orally disintegrating tablet formulation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients not consenting to participation, or unable to provide valid consent- children aged &lt; 18 years- depression not stabilised- duration of mirtazapine therapy &lt; 3 months- known allergy or adverse effects to inactive ingredients in orally disintegrating formulation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Adrenalin Strategics</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Adrenalin Strategics</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Unconditional project grant provided by Organon (Australia) Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Depressive disorders are associated with more functional disability than most chronic medical illnesses. Despite the availability of several treatment options for depression with similar effectiveness, suboptimal treatment is common, often as a result of poor adherence to medication. The chronic nature of depressive illness, together with the availability of several viable treatment options, increases the importance of patient attitudes and preferences. Improvements such as more comfortable routes of administration have the potential to enhance convenience, tolerability and acceptability for the patient, which may in turn lead to improvements in health-related quality of life. Research suggests that adherence to medication and treatment outcome can be improved if patients perceive greater control over their treatment choice. The SUPPORT Survey gives patients currently treated with regular mirtazapine tablets the opportunity to try the new, fast, orally disintegrating form of mirtazapine known as Avanza SolTab. The SUPPORT Survey aims to provide psychiatrists with valuable feedback from within the Australian community on how satisfied patients really are with regards to their mirtazapine therapy for depression, and gain a better understanding of what patients want from their therapy. Participating psychiatrists will each select up to 10 patients who have been attending their practice for treatment of depression already prescribed conventional mirtazapine tablets. These patients will have already demonstrated a positive clinical response to mirtazapine tablets and be stabilised on therapy. After information has been provided to the patient and informed consent obtained. Patients will be requested to perform a simple survey focussing on their experiences with and preferences for treatment. The survey will either be completed in the clinic waiting room and handed to the receptionist prior to leaving, or completed at home and mailed back to the survey provider via reply-paid post. Treating psychiatrists continue to provide usual care for each patient. One month later, the survey provider (Adrenalin Strategic) will send a similar survey asking about patients' experiences and comparison of the new orally disintegrating formulation of mirtazapine with the conventional tablet. Subsequently, a random sample of patients will be approached to participate in a follow-up phone survey approximately 6 months after the completion of the exit survey.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central North Adelaide Health Service (Queen Elizabeth Hosptial and Lyell McEwin Hospital), Ethics of Human Research Committee.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2007055</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Frank Barbagallo</name>
      <address>Adrenalin Strategics
Suite 1
237 Young Street
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94120555</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94120500</fax>
      <email>fbarbagallo@adrenalinstrategics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Frank Barbagallo</name>
      <address>Adrenalin Strategics
Suite 1
237 Young Street
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94120555</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94120500</fax>
      <email>fbarbagallo@adrenalinstrategics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>