<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370921">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000830493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>REDUcing the burden of dialysis Catheter ComplicaTIOns in patients with kidney disease: a National approach
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>REDUcing the burden of dialysis Catheter ComplicaTIOns in patients with kidney disease: a National approach

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>NA</utrn>
    <trialacronym>REDUCCTION</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>End stage kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Haemodialysis Catheter complications</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Stepped cluster wedge randomised implementation project
The Project will be carried out in 4 phases:
Phase I: Study site set up Dec 2015-Aug 2016
Phase II: Baseline data collection  Sep 2016-Aug 2017
Phase III: Implementation (stepped wedge randomisation) Sep 2017-Aug 2018
Phase IV: Post implementation data collection phase Sep 2018-Aug 2019

The individual components of the intervention are broken into three milestones in catheter use:
1.	Interventions employed at the time of dialysis catheter insertion such as in operating theatres/radiology/renal units/ICU:
a.	Ensuring hand hygiene at the time of catheter insertion
b.	Use of full barrier protection at insertion
c.	Cleansing of the insertion site with antiseptic solution
d.	Avoidance of the femoral site for catheter insertion
e.	Preference given to the use of subcutaneously tunnelled catheters
2.	Interventions employed during the dialysis catheter maintenance phase bu nursing staff on dialysis wards:
a.	Use of a standardised catheter insertion site dressing technique using topical antimicrobial preparations (+/- intraluminal catheter locks/topical antimicrobial preparations) and standardised frequency of dressing change
b.	Provision of standardised nurse-delivered training to patients and their caregivers on the importance of catheter care, along with provision of a patient information sheet on dialysis catheter care
c.	Protocol driven training in the aseptic techniques for connection and disconnection of the catheter for each haemodialysis treatment
d.	Training and provision of education materials to patients that enhance their skills in managing dialysis catheters
3.	Interventions associated with dialysis catheter removal on dialysis wards by nursing and medical staff:
a.	Ensure the timely removal of catheters when no longer required

Please note that the details of the interventions have not been finalized yet. The interventions will be implemented in late 2017 and these will be finalized next year. Furthermore, they need to be based on the best available evidence at the time of implementation.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a stepped cluster wedge randomised implementation project. All sites in the study will function as a control group before they are randomized to receive the suite of interventions. All sites will receive the interventions as part of the implementation phase.
Participating Renal Units will continue their current processes of care around dialysis catheter insertion and management until they are randomised during the implementation phase. This will be governed by existing hospital policies and procedures.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of dialysis catheter related bacteraemia.
The endpoint will be determined by review of routine hospital laboratory tests performed on the participants (blood, catheter tip, swab cultures)
Dialysis catheter related bacteraemia is defined as meeting one of the following criteria: 
*Culture of the same organism from both the catheter tip and at least one percutaneous blood culture. 
*Culture of the same organism from at least two blood samples (one from a catheter hub and the other from a peripheral vein or second lumen) meeting criteria for quantitative blood cultures or differential time to positivity. 
*Bacteraemia in the absence of another source 
*Rate unit is measured per 1000 catheter days. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed 2 weeks post catheter line removal for each participant to enable all test results to be collected.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Suspected or probable catheter related bacteraemia defined as catheter removal for the reason of suspected infection with negative blood cultures 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post catheter removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of the burden of exposure to central venous dialysis catheters 
The burden of exposure will be measured using line days and bacteraemia rates. 
Dialysis catheter related bacteraemia is defined as meeting one of the following criteria: 
*Culture of the same organism from both the catheter tip and at least one percutaneous blood culture.
*Culture of the same organism from at least two blood samples (one from a catheter hub and the other from a peripheral vein or second lumen) meeting criteria for quantitative blood cultures or differential time to positivity.
*Bacteraemia in the absence of another source
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post catheter removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of Economic burden that arises from dialysis catheter exposure and infection and the economic case for investing in the multi-faceted intervenions.
This will be determined through state-specific linkage to hospitalisation and death datasets and this aspect of the study will be finalised once the data linkage component is finalised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be collected and assessed once data linkage is performed on state hospitalisation, mortality and morbidity data.
Data linkage is intended to be performed once at the end of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients requiring a NEW central venous catheter for receipt of dialysis for:
*Initiation of maintenance haemodialysis
*Provision of acute haemodialysis for acute kidney injury (where the care of the dialysis catheter is under the auspices of the participating renal unit)
*Interim haemodialysis due to failure of an existing dialysis access (e.g.: failure of peritoneal dialysis, thrombosis of an existing arterio-venous fistula).  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Data from any period where the care of catheter is under the auspices of a unit other than the renal unit</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>No allocation concealment</concealment>
    <sequence>The REDUCCTION Project will randomise the study intervention at the unit, rather than the patient, level. The suite of interventions will be rolled out in three successive tranches. 

The timing of the implementation of the suite of interventions will be randomised at a unit level using a sequence generated by the Statistics Division, within The George Institute for Global Health (TGI). The Study staff at TGI will then communicate this to the primary contact person at the individual sites. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Stepped Wedge Cluster Randomised trial. All units will be randomised to receive the intervention and the random factor is the timing of randomisation. 
There will be 3 successive tranches of site randomisation over a 12 month period, whereby approximately 10 sites at each time-point will be allocated to the study intervention suite.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A formal statistical analysis plan will be derived for the study prior to analysis and publication of study results. The expected baseline rate of dialysis catheter related bacteraemia is 2.5 per 1000 catheter days, derived from Concord data and the published literature and the number of intervention points (n of steps) planned is 3. The powering is based upon the intervention resulting in a 50% reduction in the risk of catheter related bacteraemia. An additional consideration is the inter-cluster correlation co-efficient (ICC) which is conservatively estimated at 0.07 (this study design is robust to an increase in ICC), when the rate seen in a large US study from 2014 was 0.03. On the basis of these figures, the project has a power of over 0.9 to detect a 50% reduction in the bacteraemia rate using a proposed sample of 30 Renal units following 100 patients per step in the stepped-wedge design. This is likely a conservative figure as the ICC in other studies has been substantially lower and the number of patients per step is likely to be more than 100 as the duration of follow up post intervention is longer for some units.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>3000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute for Global health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Renal and Metabolic Division,
Level 10, KGV
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 16 Marcus Clarke Street Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ANZDATA Registry</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>SAHMRI Building
Level 4 South
North Terrace
ADELAIDE
SOUTH AUSTRALIA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health &amp; Human Services, Victorian Government</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Lonsdale Street
Melbourne, Victoria, Australia 3000 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>KHA-CARI Renal Guidelines</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>KHA-CARI Guidelines Office
Centre for Kidney Research
Kids Research Institute
Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Rd
Westmead NSW 2045</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kidney Health Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 9, 913 Young Street, Sydney NSW 2000
GPO Box 9993, Sydney NSW 2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sunshine Coast Hospital and Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nambour General Hospital
Hospital Road
PO Box 547
Nambour QLD 4560</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Healthcare associated infections (HAI) threaten the safety of patients and cause significant and life-threatening harm to patients and bring major additional costs to already stretched health budgets. Patients with kidney disease are especially susceptible to HAI, and most prominent among these is the harm associated with central venous haemodialysis catheter use. The absence of a systematic approach to the challenges arising from dialysis catheter use means one of the major patient safety challenges in this susceptible patient group remains very real, poorly measured and the subject of large variations in practice.

The REDUCCTION Project Objectives:
1.	To define the clinical and economic burden of dialysis catheter exposure and bacteraemia across Australia and New Zealand at a facility level
2.	To reduce dialysis catheter related bacteraemia through implementation of an evidence-based and systematic intervention package 
3.	To establish a framework from the evidence implementation project for monitoring dialysis catheter related bacteraemia and sustaining improvements from the intervention phase
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.reducction.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee – CRGH</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Road, 
Concord
NSW 2134</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/CRGH/76</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Gallagher</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health,
PO BOX M201 
Missenden Road,
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61299934500</phone>
      <fax>+61299934504</fax>
      <email>mgallagher@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sradha Kotwal</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health,
PO BOX M201 
Missenden Road,
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61299934500</phone>
      <fax>+61299934504</fax>
      <email>skotwal@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sradha Kotwal</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health,
PO BOX M201 
Missenden Road,
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61299934500</phone>
      <fax>+61299934504</fax>
      <email>skotwal@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sradha Kotwal</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>