<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369571">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001220550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy and safety of faecal microbiota transplantation for recurrent or relapsing Clostridium difficile in Western Australia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Faecal Microbiota Transplantation (FMT) in recurrent or relapsing Clostridium difficile (CDI) in Western Australia, assessment of efficacy and safety</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Recurrent or relapsing Clostridium difficile infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Affected patients will be screen for CDI by stool toxin PCR and if positive will be offered FMT. They can opt for a related donor or use a frozed sample from an unrelated donor. Donors (related or unrelated) will be screen by a gastroenterologist and an infectious disease consultant. They must be aged 18 to 65 years old, not had any antibiotics for 6 months, viral gastroenteritis for 3 months, travel outside of Australia within the last month, or any past history of gastrointestinal diseases including irritible bowel syndrome and colonic polyps, or if there is a significant family history of bowel cancer then they must have had a colonoscopy within 3 years. There must be no evidence of active infection with hepatitis viruses and other selected blood borne virus plus no history of significant autoimmune disease or severe environmental allergy. Their stool will be screen for CDI as well as a braod spectrum of bacterial, viral or parasitic infections. Unrelated donors will be excluded if there is evidence, physical or biochemical, of metabolic syndrome, cardiovascular disease, depression or serological evidence of HTLV1 or 2.

Donors will provide a whole fresh stool in a clean container. the stool will be homogenised  by a gastroenterologist in a fumigated cabinet. Each stool sample will be divided into 80-100g alliquots, suspended in normal saline, filtered to remove particulate matter and made up to a volume of 250ml with more normal saline. For fresh related donors the sample is then taken to the endoscopy room where it is delivered into the right colon of the recipient via a colonoscope after the recipient has undergone standard bowel preparation for colonoscopy.

For Frozen sample the the filtered faecal microbiota suspension will be centrifuged a 5,000g for 15 minutes and then re-suspended in half the volume of normal saline with 10% sterile pharmaceutical grade glycerol added to aid bacterial survival during freezing. Samples are then stored for upto 104 weeks at -80 degrees C. Thawing of samples occurs over 2 hours in an ice bath prior to FMT as described above. 

A register of samples will be kept for the purpose of clinical governance and a single sample from each unrelated donnor will be kept for the duration of the study incase of need for retesting.

Patients who have contraindications for colonoscopy can be given the FMT via a nasogastric tube. The route of FMT administration will be recorded for each patient.

The FMT will be a once only treatment. However if patients fail to respond as judged by clinical improvement and positive stool CDI toxin PCR, a second FMT can be offered after 1 week.. If the patient fails to respond to a second FMT, no further FMT will be offered.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group or similar</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients cured of clostridium difficile infection as defined by resolution of symptoms, reduction in inflammatory markers and negative microbiology stool analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assement will occur at 2, 12, 26,and 52 weeks post FMT</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life assessment as documented at by EQ-5D-5L questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>2, 12, 26 and 52 weeks post FMT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients aged &gt;18 yr old within the Western Australian Health system
Symptoms of diarrhoea (Bristol Stool Scale &gt; 5) with 1 &gt; bowel movements per day above their usual bowel frequency
Stool examination is positive for Clostridium difficile toxin PCR
Have completed at least two courses of standard antibiotic therapy for Clostridium difficile infection within 6 months of recruitment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No diarrhoea or gastrointestinal symptoms
Negative stool Clostridium difficile toxin PCR
Not completed 2 standard courses of antibiotic therapy for clostridium difficile infection within 6 months of recruitment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/12/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>15</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service - Fremantle</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Alma Street, Fremantle, WA 6160</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Alma Street, Fremantle, WA 6160</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fiona Stanley Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Barry Marshall Parade, Murdoch, WA 6050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fiona Stanley Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Barry Marshall Parade, Murdoch, WA 6050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recurrent or relapsing Clostridium difficile infection (CDI) is a significant and increasing health problem within Australia and a leading cause of gastrointestinal death within western countries. Standard antibiotic therapy has a high failure and relapse rate with further relapses becoming more likely. High quality studies published out of Europe have shown that faecal microbiota transplantation (FMT) for relapsing or recurrent CDI is highly efficacious and appears to be safe. However there is no data available for the use of FMT within an Australian population. We aim to recruit patients within Western Australia who have symptomatic recurrent or relapsing CDI having failed at least two courses of standard antibiotic therapy and offer them either a related fresh screen FMT or unrelated frozen screened FMT. FMT donors will be screen for a wide variety of infectious and non-infectious disease by a gastroenterologist and infectious diseases consultant. Their faecal microbiota will then be suspended, filtered and resuspended before delivery to the recipient's colon either via a colonoscope or via a nasogastric tube if the recipient has contraindications for a colonoscopy. Recipients will then be reassesed in the outpatient clinic at weeks 2, 12, 26 and 52 to assess their response to FMT and its safety.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Health Service Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Fremantle Hospital and Health Services, Alma Street, Fremantle, WA 6160</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/60</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/12/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Oliver Waters</name>
      <address>Gastroenterology Department CD09, Fiona Stanley Hospital, Barry Marshall Parade, Murdoch WA 6050 </address>
      <phone>+61861522222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>oliver.waters2@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Oliver Waters</name>
      <address>Gastroenterology Department CD09, Fiona Stanley Hospital, Barry Marshall Parade, Murdoch WA 6050 </address>
      <phone>+61861522222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>oliver.waters2@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Oliver Waters</name>
      <address>Gastroenterology Department CD09, Fiona Stanley Hospital, Barry Marshall Parade, Murdoch WA 6050 </address>
      <phone>+61861522222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>oliver.waters2@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>