<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364625">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000853741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of a single iron infusion versus oral iron tablets in the treatment of pregnancy anaemia among Tasmanian women </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Treatment of Iron Deficiency Anaemia of Late pregnancy with a single intravenous iron versus oral iron sulphate: A Prospective Randomized Controlled Study (TIDAL)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>TIDAL: Treatment of Iron Deficiency Anaemia of Late pregnancy with a single intravenous iron versus oral iron sulphate: A Prospective Randomized Controlled Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>http://apps.who.int/trialsearch/trial.aspx?trialid=ACTRN12613000853741</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy anaemia </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1 and 2 a single iron ifusion either with carboxymaltose infusion 15mg/Kg body weight once only or 1000 mg iron polymaltose followed by oral iron maintenance. Arm 3 oral iron sulphate will be given with elemental iron of 100 mg daily  from enrolment until delivery. All treatments will be given at enrolment once the patients have been randomised. 

Compliance will be measured by drug return and also by picking up the monthly script at the Pharmacy Department. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive treatment as per standard care at the LGH (Arm 3) encompasses iron treatment tablet. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>assess the improvement in haemoglobin (Hb) and ferritin levels after treatment with the standard care of oral iron or IV iron polymaltose versus newly available intravenous iron carboxymaltose therapy in Australia. 

By Hb check and serum iron studies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hb level and iron studies 4 weeks post treatment and immediate pre-delivery as well as 3 months post delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the practical benefits of a new shorter intravenous iron therapy regime in treating iron deficiency anaemia in pregnancy. 

This will be measured through cost effectivness analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To assess cost effective of all treatments after the treatment until delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the prevalence of pregnancy anaemia among Tasmanian population 

By screening pregnant women at their first antenatal visit with Hb and iron studies</outcome>
      <timepoint>At first antenatal visit </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess patient outcome and quality of life via SF-36 Quality of Life Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, 4 weeks after treatment pre-delivery and psot delivery at 3,6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To obtain additional information on the blood transfusion needs of pregnant women during and after pregnancy in relation to their iron status.

by assessing the hospital case notes of the patients and blood bank data at our institution. </outcome>
      <timepoint>by post delivery time</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess other complications of pregnancy anaemia such as tiredness, lethargy and downheartiness.

This will be assessed by quality of life suervy (SF36)</outcome>
      <timepoint>By end of pregnancy up to 42 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant women who are 18 years old and above and found to have Hb less than 120 and greater than 85 g/L with ferritin level less than 100mcg/L. 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Megaloblastic anaemia
Myelodysplasia 
Aplastic Anaemia 
Haemolysis 
Bone marrow diseases 
Malignancy 
First trimester of pregnancy  
Other disorders as documented by clinician that may be affected by iron therapy. 
Documented iron overload status. 
Allergic reaction to iron. 

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This study is aiming to recruit patients with iron deficiency anaemia according to the trial criteria from the LGH Antenatal Clinic. 
randomisation occurs with a simple computer program through pharmacy department, which will be given in sealed opaque envelopes. The professional and ethical actions of the investigators along with detailed participant information sheet and study consent form will enable patients to understand the implications of becoming a participant and ensure that potential participants are fully informed. 
The patients who will be asked should understand clearly that their voluntary participation will not affect their relationship with the treating physician or hospital by any means. 
Subjects will be provided with the contact details of the research team with concise directions to contact them if they wish to discuss any aspect of the project. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation). this will be given to the research assistant in sealed opaque envelopes.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The results will be reported on an intention-to-treat basis. Effectiveness of randomisation to the treatment groups will be assessed by: (i) general linear modelling for continuous variables, (ii) ordinal logistic regression for number of live births, and (iii) logistic regression for binary variables. The mean levels of Hb and serum ferritin (with standard deviations) and the differences [with 95% confidence intervals (CI) and P values] between the IV and the oral iron only groups at trial entry, subsequent intermediate time points, and at delivery, will be estimated by mixed methods linear regression with correction for repeated measures, and adjustment for maternal age, weight, gestational age and corresponding iron status value at trial entry. Further testing strategy will be implemented with sequential hierarchical approach to analysis.  P-values will be corrected for multiple comparisons by the Holm method. All analyses will be performed using Stata / IC 10.1 for Windows (Stata Corp LP, College Station, TX,USA).  The primary end points will be Hb and Ferritin levels 4 weeks after treatment pre-delivery. The study design is a randomised controlled trial. Multivariate analyses will be conducted to compare the outcomes in the three treatment groups, unadjusted and adjusted for actual and potential confounding variables (e.g. age, gender, initial Hb, body weight, final post-delivery Hb and iron studies where relevant): pre-delivery Hb levels by repeated measures ANOVA using general linear modelling; postnatal blood transfusion volumes by Poisson regression. It is estimated that we would screen about 2000 patients over a 12 month period, and that 20% of these would fit the inclusion criteria. Sample size calculations indicate a requirement for 52 completed patients per treatment group for both outcomes based on assumptions: i) a minimum effect size detection of 2g/l increase in pre-delivery Hb and a 45% reduction in units of blood transfused; ii) an untreated rise in Hb of 0g/l and SD 2.8g/l, and an expected untreated transfusion rate of 2.2 units per patient SD 1.8g/l  iii) alpha value of 0.05 and power of 80%. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>7/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>156</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>246</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Launceston General Hospital - Launceston</hospital>
    <postcode>7250 - Launceston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Launceston General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Charles Street, Launceston, 7250
Tasmania</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clifford Craig Medical Trust Fund     
 

 </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5
Launceston General Hospital
Charles street
Launceston, Tasmania 7250
 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clifford Craig Medical Trust Fund  
 

</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Address:  Level 5
Launceston General Hospital
Charles street
Launceston, Tasmania 7250
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is aiming to show that by having normal haemoglobin and iron studies at the time of delivery, the patients will not only feel better, but will perform better during and after pregnancy. It is hoped that their pregnancy will be less eventful without any complications. 
By improving antenatal haemoglobin, we expect to reduce the incidence or necessity for blood transfusions in this cohort of patients thereby relieving the strain on the supply of blood from an already stretched Blood Blank and also to avoid the risks/complications of transfusion. 
Because of its national and global significance, this project merits significant health improvement for pregnant women. 
To identify the best treatment approach to iron deficiency anaemia in pregnancy. 
Effective management of iron deficiency anaemia has a major impact on the health, educational and economic potential of populations in Tasmania and Australia. This and future work may lead to replacement of iron as first line therapy of the worlds most common nutritional disorder, affecting more than 2 billion people. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>A Khalafallah, CR Chilvers, M Sexton, E Ingram, CM Chilvers, M Vialle, B Kirkby, B Einoder, T Brain ASSESSMENT OF INTRAVENOUS FERRIC CARBOXYMALTOSE VERSUS ORAL IRON SULPHATE IN THE MANAGEMENT OF PREOPERATIVE ANAEMIA: A PROSPECTIVE RANDOMIZED CONTROLLED TRIAL. HAEMATOLOGICA, 2015, Volume 100, Pages 334-33.

https://scholar.google.com.au/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;hl=en&amp;user=7Ntik6EAAAAJ&amp;cstart=20&amp;citation_for_view=7Ntik6EAAAAJ:kJDgFkosVoMC </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
Hobart, Tas 7001
Australia </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0013323</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>A/Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>A/Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>A/Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital, Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>A/Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah </name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>