<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370651">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000612415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Yoga for Stress Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a Hatha Yoga practice on factors related to chronic stress in middle-aged women reporting psychological distress</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic stress and psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Immunity (inflammation)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Yoga Intervention conducted by certified yoga instructor (Yoga Australia, Level 2) with 7 years teaching experience. Classes were conducted at a centrally located community centre (public transport and ample parking is available nearby).Composed of 8 weeks of twice-weekly hour long yoga classes (16 classes total), which follow the structure listed below. Classes were scheduled for Monday and Friday evenings and participants were assigned to a flexible 1730-1830 or 1900-2000 timeslot (the maximum class-size feasible = 30 participants). 

1) Active mindfulness mediation
2) Warm-up postures on floor
3) Sun Salutations (series of postures that 'flow together') 
4) Standing postures
5) Floor postures
6) Savasana (lying down, relaxation)

Prior to class participants were asked to complete a self-reported check-list of attendance, this was confirmed by instructor's observation/headcount. Additionally, participants completed the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (PANAS) before and after each class.</interventions>
    <comparator>Randomised, stratified by level of distress, wait-list-controlled (received the yoga intervention 12 weeks after the intervention group).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K10) (Kessler &amp; Mroczeck, 1994)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Stress Scale (PSS) (Cohen, Kamarck, &amp; Mermelstein, 1983)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotional based mood-states assessed using the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (PANAS) (Watson, Clark, &amp; Tellegen, 1988)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention; additionally, pre- and post-yoga class measures at each of the 16 classes administered</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Personal Wellbeing Index- Adult (PWI-A)(International Wellbeing Group, 2006)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Mindfulness Attention Awareness Scale (MASS) (Brown &amp; Ryan, 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) (Craig et al., 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motives for Physical Activity Measure - Revised (MPAM-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>State Trait Anger Expression Inventory-2 (STAI-2) (Spielberger, 1999)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>UCLA Loneliness Scale (Russell, 1996) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Revised Helping Alliance Questionnaire (HAq-II) that is modified to assesses the extent to which the participant experiences their yoga instructor as helpful</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mid-point of Intervention (after the 8th yoga session) and Post-Intervention (after the 16th yoga session)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A Course Satisfaction Questionnaire, that asks questions about participants satisfaction with the yoga classes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mid-point of Intervention (after the 8th yoga session) and Post-Intervention (after the 16th yoga session)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart Rate as measured by OMRON HEM-7203</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure as measured by OMRON HEM-7203</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sit-and-reach test, which is a measure of flexibility (Lopez-Minarro, Muyor, &amp; Alacid, 2011)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>high sensitivity C-reactive protein (hsCRP) as measured by serum assay (assessed in a subset of 35 participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammatory cytokines (Tumor necrosis factor alpha [TNFa], Interleukin 6 [IL-6]) as measured by serum assay (assessed in a subset of 35 participants)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) methylation measured in wholebloods (assessed in a subset of 28 participants). QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN) was used to extract DNA, and bisulphite-converted using MethylEasyTM Xceed Kit  (Genetic Signatures, Darlinghurst, Australia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ribonucleic acid (RNA) gene expression will be measured in wholebloods (to be assessed in a subset of 28 participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist-to-Height Ratio (height was measured in cm using the lab's permanently secured tape-measure, and weight was measured in kg by a digital scale placed on a solid surface)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Intervention, 1-month follow-up, and at wait-list control group's post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Healthy and free from acute infections for at least two weeks prior to biochemical or psychological assessments as indicated by self-report.
2) Refrain from drinking alcohol in the last 48 hours prior to biochemical or psychological assessments.
3) Refrain from eating or drinking (other than water) for 12 hours prior to biochemical or psychological assessments.
4) Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K10) score of 16+, for at least one month (Kessler &amp; Mroczeck, 1994)
5) Able to commit to attendance at 2 yoga classes a week for the duration of the intervention (8 weeks).
6) Able to provide own transportation to and from the assessment sessions at SA Pathology.
7) Agreement to withhold commencement of a yoga practice until after the follow up testing session, if allocated to the waitlist control.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Anaemia
2) Diabetes
3) Cardiovascular diseases such as coronary heart disease
4) Blood cancers such as leukaemia and lymphoma
5) Inflammatory bowel diseases such as Crohns disease
6) Autoimmune diseases such as autoimmune thyroiditis and lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, pernicious anaemia
7) Asthma and being treated with steroids
8) Known immunodeficiency diseases such as HIV and infectious mononucleosis
9) Smoking
10) Alcoholism
11) On immune effecting medication
12) Serious psychological illness
13) Serious physiological illness
14) Presently practicing yoga, or having engaged in a regular yoga practice within the past year
15) Foreseeable acute stressors arising during the course of the intervention and follow-up period (e.g. university exams)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation (web-based) was used for allocation concealment</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants were stratified according to their K10 (psychological distress) score (Moderate, High or Very high). Then randomisation was conducted on the computer utilising Research Randomizer.

Urbaniak, G. C., &amp; Plous, S. . (2013). Research Randomizer (Version 4.0) [Computer software] http://www.randomizer.org/. Retrieved April 10, 2013, from http://www.randomizer.org/</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>After completion of follow-up testing, the yoga intervention was administered to the waitlist-control group and post-test assessment was completed at  conclusion.

All participants provided data for psychological (i.e. questionnaires) and physiological (e.g. blood-pressure, flexibility) outcomes (N = 116).

Biochemical markers of inflammation: Due to resource availability the achievability of a within-subjects, longitudinal design, random-effects modelling can be used, making it necessary to only take blood samples of a subset of the participants (n = 30). The study is designed to collect biochemical measures at three time points (pre, post, and follow-up), using all of these observations and time-varying covariates, the intra-patient variability of the biochemical measures will be decreased relative to a cross-sectional or a between-subjects experimental design, thus increasing the feasible statistical power.

Pilot genetic factors study: the addition of genetic factors to this study came following the baseline time-point, thus data (n = 28) was collected at the following time points: post-test, follow-up, and follow-up after the waitlist control's yoga intervention. Thus this small pilot study will conduct a cross-sectional analysis at post-test (yoga intervention completer vs control) and longitudinal analysis on the control group.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A power analysis (0.80) conducted (repeated measures, between factors ANOVA, p = .05) shows that for the RCT a total of 86 participants for the two groups will be required for this study to obtain a medium effect size (f = 0.25). Due to common drop-outs in exercise interventions, this study planned to obtain a minimum of 96 participants. This target insured power to find medium effects on psychological variables utilizing ANOVAs. Mixed-models will conducted, such testing can control for nesting and covariates (e.g. physical activity). Application of both analysis allows for more complex designs coupled with clear effect sizes.

The reliable change index (RC) and the clinically significant change index (CSC) will be applied to participant's in the yoga group to indicate if improvement or decline for an individual is greater than might be due to measurement error, and if the cut-off point for the participants score is within the normal range, rather than the clinical.

As the biochemical and genetic samples are smaller, mixed-models will be used when appropriate. Additionally ANOVA's and t-tests will be performed to corroborate findings (and derive effect sizes).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>14/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>96</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>116</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/06/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5005 - The University Of Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The School of Psychology
The University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA, 5005</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The School of Psychology
The University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA, 5005</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Levels of perceived stress have indeed been found to have increase considerably over the past decades. Chronic stress is considered to be incredibly toxic, resulting in long-term psychological and physiological changes such that maladaptive emotional states, like depression, increase along with inflammation, while immune functioning decreases. Consequently, stress is among the leading causes for the global burden of disease, entailing heavy costs for both health care systems and the private economy. 

Alongside this stress-epidemic the popularity of yoga is growing exponentially. In addition to reported stress relief, Hatha yoga has been suggested to decrease levels of inflammation as advanced practitioners were found to have lower levels of inflammation than beginners (Kiecolt-Glaser et al., 2010). A randomised control trial on heart failure patients suggested that the practice of Hatha yoga significantly lowered inflammation within a two month period (Pullen et al., 2008). While the empirical evidence for the practice of yoga as a therapeutic technique is promising (Chandratreya, 2011), the literature has reported methodological limitations. Such limitations include small sample sizes (insufficient to obtain power); a lack of standardised protocols in conducting interventions (making studies difficult to replicate); and a general lack of the use of biological markers (considered to be more objective than psychological measures alone). In order to be able to definitively conclude that yoga offers a benefit to chronically stressed individuals biomedical studies that are adequately powered, and use standardised protocols, are required. Hence, this investigation has been designed to address the aforementioned limitations in a randomised controlled trial (RCT).

A standardised protocol of yoga will be administered for 16 sessions. We hypothesise that yoga participation in the yoga intervention will benefit participants psychologically, physiologically, and biochemically.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://theyogaforstress.wordpress.com/</trialwebsite>
    <publication> Harkess, K. N., Delfabbro, P., Mortimer, J., Hannaford, Z., Cohen-Woods, S. (2016). "Brief Report on the Psychophysiological Effects of a Yoga Intervention for Chronic Stress." Journal of Psychophysiology. http://dx.doi.org/10.1027/0269-8803/a000169</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Adelaide Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Ethics, Compliance and Integrity
Research Branch, Level 7, 115 Grenfell St
The University of Adelaide,  AUSTRALIA   5005
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2013-001</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370651-H-2013-001.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370651-Outline of Yoga Session Structure.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Delfabbro</name>
      <address>The School of Psychology
The University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 831 34936</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.delfabbro@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kaitlin Harkess</name>
      <address>The School of Psychology
The University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8313 7402</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kaitlin.harkess@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kaitlin Harkess</name>
      <address>The School of Psychology
The University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8313 7402</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kaitlin.harkess@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kaitlin Harkess</name>
      <address>The School of Psychology
The University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8313 7402</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kaitlin.harkess@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>