<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83198">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000523303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of combined neoadjuvant chemotherapy and letrozol in Postmenopausal Women with locally advanced breast cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized Phase III Trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of neoadjuvant chemotherapy +/- letrozol in Postmenopausal Women with locally advanced breast cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>New secondary ID. Please modify. no secondary ID</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Two arm randomized placebo controlled phase III study evaluating the efficacy and safety of the concurrent neoadjuvant chemotherapy and letrozol in patients with locally advanced breast cancer.
 One hundred eligible women with pathologically proven locally advanced breast cancer were enrolled. 
Study arm: 
Chemotherapy consisting of a median 3 cycles (range 2-4 cycles) of CAF regimen [(intravenous  Cyclophosphamide 600 mg/m2, doxorubicin 60 mg/m2 and 5-Fluorouracil (5-FU 600 mg/m2 )] every three weeks. Patients in this arm (n=50) receive daily oral letrozol 2.5 mg combined with neoadjuvant chemotherapy and up to the time of surgery [for a median time of nine weeks (range 6-12 weeks)].  All patients undergo modified radical mastectomy 2 weeks after the last cycle of chemotherapy.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control arm:
Chemotherapy consisting of a 3 cycles of CAF regimen [(intravenous Cyclophosphamide 600 mg/m2, doxorubicin 60 mg/m2 and 5-Fluorouracil (5-FU) 600 mg/m2] every three weeks. Patients in this arm (n=50) receive daily oral placebo (sugar pills) combined with neoadjuvant chemotherapy and up to the time of surgery (for 12 weeks).  All patients undergo modified radical mastectomy 2 weeks after the last cycle of chemotherapy.
The duration of intervention is 12 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pathologic response rate   is the primary end-point of the study.
According to the size of residual disease in the primary disease, a pathologic response will be assessed after the neoadjuvant treatment.  Standard international union against cancer (UICC) criteria will be used for definition of pathologic response. Reduction of 50% or more in the product of the two maximum perpendicular diameters of breast mass is described as partial response and disappearance of tumor is taken as complete response. No change is defined as no response or reduction of mass less than 50%, and new lesion or more than 25% increasing in size is described as progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Response will be measured 2 weeks after the 3rd cycles of chemotherapy (i.e. 8 weeks after enrolling in the study)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute treatment-related toxicities will be measured by clinician and paraclinical assessment and graded according to the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group/European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (RTOG/EORTC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute treatment-related toxicities will be assessed at baseline, after each cycle of chemotherapy and weekly up to the time of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute treatment-related toxicities will be measured by clinician and paraclinical assessment and graded according to the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group/European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (RTOG/EORTC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Acute treatment-related toxicities will be assessed at baseline, after each cycle of chemotherapy and weekly up to the time of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Postmenopausal women with pathologically proven locally advanced breast cancer
2. No prior therapy 
3. No clinical or imaging evidence of distant metastasis at the time of study enrollment 
4. Karnofsky performance status = 70 
5. Written informed consent
6. Normal or acceptable liver, kidney and bone marrow function</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Prior therapy 
2. Clinical or imaging evidence of distant metastasis 
3. Patients with a known contraindication or allergy to aromatase inhibitors 
4. Patients with severe heart, cardiovascular, liver, renal, inflammatory intestinal or blood coagulation disorders,</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization is performed by computer at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by using a randomization table from a statistic book</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Shiraz University of Medical Sciences</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz 71936, Iran</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Shiraz University of Medical Sciences</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz 71936, Iran</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Breast cancer is the most common cause of cancer and cancer mortality in women worldwide. Despite early detection of breast cancer, locally advanced breast carcinomas account for a remarkable fraction of all breast carcinomas. The optimal management for these patients remains a major therapeutic challenge. Neoadjuvant chemotherapy is now considered the standard of care for these patients. Adjuvant and neoadjuvant endocrine therapy with aromatase inhibitors has an established role in the postmenopausal women with hormone receptor-positive invasive breast cancer. This two arm randomized clinical study aimed to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the combined neoadjuvant chemotherapy and letrozol in postmenopausal women with locally advanced breast carcinoma.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.sums.ac.ir</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>It is under reveiw by the Ethical Review Committee of Shiraz University of Medical Sciences</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethical Review Committee of Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz 71936, Iran</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/09/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mohammad Mohammadianpanah</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology, Namazi Hospital, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz 71936-13311, Iran</address>
      <phone>+98 711 6474320</phone>
      <fax>+98 711 6474320</fax>
      <email>mohpanah@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mohammad Mohammadianpanah</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology, Namazi Hospital, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz 71936-13311, Iran</address>
      <phone>+98 711 6474320</phone>
      <fax>+98 711 6474320</fax>
      <email>mohpanah@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mohammad Mohammadianpanah</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology, Namazi Hospital, Shiraz University of Medical Sciences, Shiraz 71936-13311, Iran</address>
      <phone>+98 711 6474320</phone>
      <fax>+98 711 6474320</fax>
      <email>mohpanah@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>