<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336137">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000907044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective, bilateral, open label study to evaluate the on-eye perfomance of Proclear (registered trademark) 1 Day contact lenses.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, open-label, daily wear study of Proclear (registered trademark) 1 Day contact lenses to evaluate product performance in both experienced and new contact lens wearers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nill</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contact lens wear performance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>performance of commercially available contact lens, Proclear (registered trademark) 1 Day used in daily disposable modality will be evaluated and compared to other daily wear contact lenses.  Evaluation of those daily wear contact lenses are from previous studies done in BHVI.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control will be historic data from previous daily disposable and silicone hydrogel lens studies conducted at the Brien Holden Vision Institute (1985-Now).  The historic data include lens fitting and ocular physiological variables collected by examiners and questionnaires completed by participants.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the on-eye performance of Proclear 1 Day contact lenses. Lens fitting and ocular physiological variables are measured by various optometric equipment such as slit-lamp biomicroscope.  Subjective ratings are completed by participants in the form of questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months with 4 visits : Baseline, 2 Week, 1 Month &amp; 3 Month.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare performance of Proclear 1-day to other daily wear contact lenses from historic data via statistical analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months with 4 visits : Baseline, 2 Week, 1 Month &amp; 3 Month.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be able to read, comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
Be at least 18 years old;
Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses;
Have vision correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses;	
May be experienced or inexperienced at wearing contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including keratoconus and herpes keratitis) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosis. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
An active corneal infection or any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 (Pharmacy only) and above ocular medication up to 12 weeks prior to and during the trial;
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse manner or risk of providing a false positive;
N.B. Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial;  
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
Previous corneal refractive surgery;
Contraindications to contact lens wear;
Known or suspected allergy to ingredients in contact lenses;
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial;
Participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks or participation in a short-term clinical trial within the previous 48 hours;
Be pregnant* or plan to become pregnant during the trial or is currently breastfeeding.
The Investigator may, at his/her discretion, exclude anyone else who they believe may not be able to fulfil the study requirements, or if it is believed to be in the participants best interests.
 * Formal testing of pregnancy is not required. A participants verbal report is sufficient.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney, NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney, NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Proclear's Phosphorylcholine (PC Technology TM ) has given Proclear lenses FDA clearance for the claim: may provide improved comfort for contact lens wearers who experience mild discomfort or symptoms relating to dryness during lens wear. Such claim was debatable in previous literature. 
The purpose of this study is to evaluate clinical performance of Proclear 1-day contact lenses in terms of fitting, physiological and subjective responses. Such that comparison with other daily wear lenses especially new silicone hydrogel lenses can be made.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>VIHEC Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, UNSW, Sydney, NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/10/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennie Diec</name>
      <address>Level 5 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 93856230</phone>
      <fax>+612 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.diec@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennie Diec</name>
      <address>Level 5 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 93856230</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.diec@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennie Diec</name>
      <address>Level 5 North Wing Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14 Barker Street, UNSW Sydney, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 93856230</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.diec@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>