<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367011">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001004651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Individualised neuromodulation with transcranial direct current stimulation for motor recovery after stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>GABA-ergic intracortical function and its modulation by real and sham transcranial direct current stimulation during the sub-acute phase of recovery after ischaemic stroke</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>POLARIS: Personalised NeurOmoduLation And Recovery In Stroke</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ischaemic stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be recruited within 14 days of stroke. Assessments will be made at baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months, and 6 months after stroke. These assessments will measure motor function and intracortical GABA function within primary motor cortex, to observe the evolution of GABA function over the first 6 months after stroke. Motor function will be measured with clinical assessments of upper limb impairment (Fugl-Meyer scale) and function (Action Research Arm Test), at all 4 time points. Primary motor cortex function will be assessed on both sides of the brain using single and paired pulse transcranial magnetic stimulation, to measure the excitability of the corticomotor pathway and intracortical GABAergic inhibitory networks. Transcranial direct current stimulation will be applied at baseline, 6 weeks and 3 months after stroke, to see whether the excitability of the corticomotor pathway and intracortical GABAergic inhibitory networks can be temporarily modulated at these time points. Patients will be randomised to receive either real or sham transcranial direct current stimulation, to control for potential non-specific effects. Each participant will receive the same TDCS protocol (either real or sham) at all three time points. Real transcranial direct current stimulation will be delivered for 20 minutes at an intensity of 1.5 milliamps. Sham stimulation will involve initially ramping up to 1.5 milliamps, then the stimulation will be switched off for the remainder of the 20 minutes. Both real and sham stimulation will be delivered via a pair of saline-soaked sponge electrodes, inside a 'MindCap' worn by the participant. The electrodes will be located over the primary motor cortices. This is not a clinical trial of transcranial direct current stimulation, as it is being used to probe motor cortical function at three time points, rather than to produce clinical benefits over multiple sessions. Motor cortex activation and GABA concentration will also be assessed using magnetic resonance imaging at baseline and 6 weeks after stroke. Participants will receive usual and standard rehabilitation care during the study, delivered by their clinical team. Therapy dose (therapist contact time) will be recorded for each participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>This study will observe the effects of transcranial direct current stimulation on motor cortex function applied once at each of three different time points after stroke. It is necessary to randomly assign patients to real or sham stimulation. This will control for non-specific effects of the stimulation. Real stimulation will be delivered for 20 minutes at an intensity of 1 milliamp. Sham stimulation will involve initially ramping up the stimulation to 1 milliamp, and then switching the stimulator off for the remainder of the 20 minute period. The temporary effect of transcranial direct current stimulation on the excitability of corticomotor pathways and intracortical GABAergic inhibition networks will be determined by comparing data from patients who received real and sham stimulation. The stimulation will be applied once at each of 3 time points (baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months) and is not expected to have any effects on patients' motor recovery. It is an experimental probe rather than a treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in paretic upper limb Action Research Arm Test score between baseline and 6 weeks post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post-stroke</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between the change in motor cortex GABAergic inhibition, measured with transcranial magnetic stimulation at 2 and 6 weeks post-stroke, and the change in paretic upper limb Action Research Arm Test score between 2 and 6 weeks post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between 2 and 6 weeks post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between the change in motor cortex GABAergic inhibition, measured with magnetic resonance imaging at 2 and 6 weeks post-stroke, and the change in paretic upper limb Action Research Arm Test score between 2 and 6 weeks post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between 2 and 6 weeks post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in paretic upper limb function measured with the ARAT between baseline and 3 months post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in paretic upper limb function measured with the ARAT between baseline and 6 months post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in paretic upper limb impairment measured with the Fugl-Meyer (FM) scale between baseline and 6 weeks post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in paretic upper limb impairment measured with FM between baseline and 3 months post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in paretic upper limb impairment measured with the FM between baseline and 6 months post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between the change in motor cortex GABAergic inhibition, measured with transcranial magnetic stimulation at 2 weeks and 3 months post-stroke, and the change in paretic upper limb Action Research Arm Test score between 2 weeks and 3 months post-stroke</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks and 3 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>First-ever mono-hemispheric ischaemic stroke within the previous 14 days.
Upper limb symptoms requiring rehabilitation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not requiring upper limb rehabilitation
Contraindications to transcranial magnetic and direct current stimulation, including: epilepsy, history of seizures, cardiac pacemaker, metal implanted in the head or brain, pregnancy, medications that lower seizure threshold.
Contraindications to magnetic resonance imaging, including: cardiac pacemaker, metallic fragments in the eyes, ferromagnetic metals in the head or body.
Cognitive or communication impairment precluding informed consent or compliance with study assessments.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will provide written informed consent and will then be randomised to receive either real or sham transcranial direct current stimulation, using custom software to minimise between-group differences in age, gender, initial stroke severity, and potential for upper limb recovery using the PREP algorithm. The PREP algorithm combines clinical measures, transcranial magnetic stimulation, and magnetic resonance imaging, to evaluate the extent of damage to descending motor pathways in the stroke side of the brain. This information is then used to stratify patients into one of four predictions for recovery of upper limb function. 
By using custom software to randomise (and minimise), allocation will be concealed, and known only to the researchers. Participants and clinical assessors will remain blinded to allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Linear regression will be used to determine associations between variables such as motor cortex GABA concentration and GABAergic inhibition, rate of recovery (change in clinical scores between 2 and 6 weeks, and between 2 weeks and 3 months post-stroke), and therapy dose. The temporary effects of transcranial direct current stimulation on corticomotor excitability and inhibition with RM-ANOVA with factors stimulation (real, sham) and time (baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months).
Stastical power calculations have been based on our previous research using similar measures of GABAergic inhibition with patients at the sub-acute stage of recovery. With an alpha = 0.05 and beta = 0.08, 96 participants will be required to detect an effect of transcranial direct current stimulation on GABAergic inhibition, with 24 patients in each PREP stratification.  120 patients will be recruited to allow for potential drop-out.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>96</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 5541
Wellesley Street
Auckland 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Auckland District Health Board</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Private Bag 92024
Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke is the leading cause of adult disability worldwide. Inhibitory tone in the brain is altered by
stroke and dictates how plasticity and recovery of function occur after stroke, but this varies from one
individual to the next. Our objective is to identify factors that predict how best to apply noninvasive
brain stimulation to modulate inhibitory tone and facilitate motor recovery in the initial days and weeks
after stroke. To fuflill this objective advanced neuroimaging and neurophysiological assessments will
be undertaken to establish links between inhibitory function, effects of brain stimulation on recovery,
and patient outcomes. This project will increase the understanding of the molecular, cellular and
neurophysiological mechanisms of recovery of motor function in human patients after stroke, and
reduce inequalities in stroke outcomes for people who are more likely to suffer stroke earlier and live
with disability longer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Winston Byblow</name>
      <address>Movement Neuroscience Laboratory
Dept of Sport &amp; Exercise Science
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 599 ext 86844</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.byblow@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cathy Stinear</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>64 9 923 3779</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.stinear@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Winston Byblow</name>
      <address>Movement Neuroscience Laboratory
Dept of Sport &amp; Exercise Science
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737 599 ext 86844</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>w.byblow@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cathy Stinear</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>64 9 923 3779</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.stinear@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>