<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371921">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000162314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Electromyographic evaluation of the effect of pelvic floor muscle training to improve the function of the lower urinary tract in women with ischemic stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Electromyographic evaluation of the effect of pelvic floor muscle training to improve the function of the lower urinary tract in women with ischemic stroke: a prospective, randomized study with a control group.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>urinary incontinence</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>ischemic stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two comparison groups: A group - group, which will be used pelvic floor muscle training and B group (control) - a group without specialized training of the pelvic floor muscles. In group A will be applied the pelvic floor muscle training. Therapy will be held for ten days (two weeks at five sessions per week) and each will last about 30 minutes a day. The whole therapy will be carried out under the supervision of a therapist at the hospital. Participants will be recruited from among patients of the hospital  Selection of exercises will be individual determined, in depends on the function of the lower urinary tract and the condition of the tested women (physiotherapist decision). Training will take into account the contractions of the pelvic floor muscles. Participants will perform contraction lasting a few seconds (depending on the condition of the patient, with a break lasts twice as long). They will also be carried out short, rapid contraction of this muscle. In this training, a electromyograph with the function of the visual biofeedback will be used. Feedback on muscle contraction provided via a screen for participants throughout each session via sEMG sensors. Each training session will be supervised and managed by a physiotherapist.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group without specialized pelvic floor muscle training</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting and functional bioelectrical activity of pelvic floor muscle assessed by electromyography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, on completion of intervention and 10 days after completion of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of subjective symptoms of urinary incontinence by ICIQ </outcome>
      <timepoint>Before intervention, on completion of intervention and 10 days after completion of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ischaemic stroke episode for at least 6 months previously, the incidence of symptoms of lower urinary tract (urinary incontinence), consent to participate in research, permission doctor and general well-being of the survey</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>aphasia sensory, significant abdominal obesity (BMI&gt; 30), previous surgery within the abdominal wall and / or pelvic, people with limited abilities functional (Barthel index &lt;60), age over 75 years, incontinence grade III, fecal incontinence, gynecological surgeries, the lack of consent of the person tested and the lack of consent doctor to perform measurements, malaise on the study, contraindications measurements - infection, menstruation, allergic to nickel, the occurrence of pain during the study period, the resignation during the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Wroclaw Medical University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wybrzeze L. Pasteura 1, 50-367 Wroclaw
Poland </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wroclaw Medical University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wybrzeze L. Pasteura 1, 50-367 Wroclaw
Poland </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname> Regional Specialist Hospital in Wroclaw</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rehabilitation Department of Neurology, Regional Specialist Hospital in Wroclaw, ul. Poswieckiej 8, 50-001 Wroclaw,</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Poland</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of the study is  electromyographic assessment of the impact of pelvic floor muscle training (MDM) to improve the function of the lower urinary tract in women after ischemic stroke. 
The research will be carried out in the Department of Neurological Rehabilitation in Regional Hospital in Wroclaw. Participants in the study will be randomized to one of two comparison groups: group A - group, which will be used PFM training and group B (control) - a group without specialized training of PFM. All patients will be performed evaluation parameters included in the project at the beginning of your stay in the hospital after ten days (in group A after ten days of treatment) and after 20 days (follow up). 
Resting and functional bioelectric activity of PFM will be assessed by the electromyographic device MyoSystem 1400L.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Bioethical committee at the Wroclaw Medical University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Wroclaw Medical University
Wybrzeze L. Pasteura 1, 50-367 Wroclaw
Poland </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>KB-367/2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kuba Ptaszkowski</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Biomechanics and Physiotherapy in Motor System Disorders, Faculty of Health Science, Wroclaw Medical University, address: Grunwaldzka 2, 50-355 Wroclaw, Poland</address>
      <phone>(+48) 606816161</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kuba.ptaszkowski@umed.wroc.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kuba Ptaszkowski</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Biomechanics and Physiotherapy in Motor System Disorders, Faculty of Health Science, Wroclaw Medical University, address: Grunwaldzka 2, 50-355 Wroclaw, Poland</address>
      <phone>(+48) 606816161</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kuba.ptaszkowski@umed.wroc.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kuba Ptaszkowski</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Biomechanics and Physiotherapy in Motor System Disorders, Faculty of Health Science, Wroclaw Medical University, address: Grunwaldzka 2, 50-355 Wroclaw, Poland</address>
      <phone>(+48) 606816161</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kuba.ptaszkowski@umed.wroc.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>