<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366919">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000978662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of lung protective ventilatory strategy on systemic and pulmonary inflammatory responses during laparoscopic surgery: is it really helpful?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> A prospective randomised trial to evaluate the effect of intraoperative tidal volume ventilation with 6ml/kg (Ideal Body weight) and positive end expiratory pressure (PEEP) of 8 cm H2O versus 12ml/kg (Ideal Body weight) on systemic and pulmonary inflammatory responses in adult patients undergoing laparoscopic surgery </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1160-3894 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inflammatory stress in patients undergoing laparoscopic gynaecological surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 12 ml/kg ventilation (according to ideal height and weight of the patients) and 0 cmH20 PEEP were performed to the patients in group I, 6 ml/kg ventilation (according to ideal height and weight of the patients) and 8 cmH20 PEEP were performed to the patients in group II patients continuously throughout laparoscopic surgery . The ideal body weight of patients was estimated with the formula as follows; 45.5 +/- 0.91 x (cm of height - 152.4) 
To assess the systemic inflammatory responses, venous blood samples were taken via veni-puncture. To assess the pulmonary inflammatory responses of both groups, flexible bronchoscopy was performed through the endotracheal intubation tube and bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) was obtained from right middle lobe or lingula. Second bronchoalveolar lavage was obtained from the contralateral lung (right middle lobe or left lingular segment). </interventions>
    <comparator>12ml/kg tidal volume and 0 cmH2O PEEP</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>inflammatory stress is measured by serum cytokine tumor necrosis factor-alpha, serum Interleukin-1, serum Interleukin 6 and  serum Interleukin 8</outcome>
      <timepoint>within the first 5 minutes after endotracheal intubation (T1), 60 minutes after the initiation of mechanical ventilation (T2) and in the postanaesthesia care unit at 30 minute after tracheal extubation (T3)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>inflammatory stress is measured by bronchoalveolar lavage  cytokine tumor necrosis factor-alpha , bronchoalveolar lavage Interleukin-1 beta,  bronchoalveolar lavage  Interleukin 6 and bronchoalveolar lavage Interleukin 8</outcome>
      <timepoint>within the first 5 minutes after endotracheal intubation (T1)and  in the postanaesthesia care unit at 30 minute after tracheal extubation (T3)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1-elective laparoscopic gynecological surgery 
2- ASA 1-2 patients </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1-history of pulmonary diseases 2- thoracic surgery 3- immune deficiency 4-morbid obesity (body mass index greater than 35) 5-previous history of mechanical ventilation or surgical procedure during general anesthesia (lesser than one year) </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>ASA 1-2 patients older than 18 years-old who were candidate for elective laparoscopic gynecological surgery were included in this study. All patients were informed and written informed consent was obtained from all the participants in the study. Sequentially-Numered,Opaque,Sealed Envelopes(SNOSE) were used as allocation concealment method. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization was based on computer-generated codes that were maintained in opaque envelopes until the anesthesia began </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/02/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Afyonkarahisar</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Afyon Kocatepe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No: 22 Izmir Road, Afyonkarahisar, 03200,Turkey</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Afyon Kocatepe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> No: 22 Izmir Road, Afyonkarahisar, 03200,Turkey</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Laparoscopic surgery is performed by carbon dioxide (CO2) insufflation, but this may induce stress responses. The aim of this study is to compare the level of inflammatory mediators in patients receiving low-VT versus traditional-VT during gynecological laparoscopic surgery. Fourty ASA physical status 1 and 2 subjects older than 18 years-old undergoing laparoscopic gynecological surgery were included. Systemic and pulmonary inflammatory responses (IL6, TNF-alpha, IL8 and IL1B) of patients receiving intraoperative low-VT and traditional-VT during laparoscopic surgery were assessed in blood serum [within the first 5 minutes after endotracheal intubation (T1), 60 minutes after the initiation of mechanical ventilation (T2) and in the postanaesthesia care unit at 30 min after tracheal extubation (T3)] and bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) within T1 and T3. Increase in the serum levels of IL6, TNF-alpha, IL8 and IL1B were observed in both groups during the time periods of T1, T2 and T3. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Serdar Kokulu</name>
      <address> Afyon Kocatepe University Faculty of Medicine,Department of Anaesthesiology and Reanimation, Izmir road  Street No 22 Afyonkarahisar Postalcode: 03200</address>
      <phone>+905053918498</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serdarkokuu@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>ELif Dogan Baki</name>
      <address>Afyon Kocatepe University Faculty of Medicine,Department of Anaesthesiology and Reanimation,Izmir road  Street No 22   Afyonkarahisar Postalcode: 03200</address>
      <phone>+905308739908</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elifbaki1973@mynet.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>ELif Dogan Baki</name>
      <address>Afyon Kocatepe University Faculty of Medicine,Department of Anaesthesiology and Reanimation, Izmir road street No 22  Afyonkarahisar Postalcode: 03200</address>
      <phone>+905308739908</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elifbaki1973@mynet.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>