<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82986">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000343303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can a peer support program for women with an altered cancer gene reduce distress?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In women identified as carrying the BRCA1/2 gene fault: Is a telephone-based peer support program as good or better than usual care for reduction of psychological distress?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychosocial effects of testing positive for a mutation of the BRCA1/2 gene</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Telephone-based peer support delivered by trained volunteers over a 4-month period.  In the first instance, peer support volunteers will contact women receiving the peer support.  Subsequent contacts may be initiated by either the recipient or peer support volunteer, but there is a minimum requirement of at least 6 telephone contacts over the 6-month period.  The duration of sessions will be determined by the number of issues the support recipient wishes to discuss at that time.  Peer volunteers will provide information and emotional support.  One of their main roles will be to normalise the responses and experiences of support recipients.  Peer support volunteers will be provided with a manual to help them provide information on the main issues surrounding a positive test for the BRCA1/2 gene fault, including: discussing genetic risk with family members; communicating with children about their potential risk and need for genetic testing; feelings of anxiety/depression; feelings of guilt about passing the risk on to children; sense of social isolation; risk management strategies such as mammograms, ultrasounds, MRI, CA125 measurement; implications of surgical management of risk e.g. mastectomy, oophorectomy, such as body image and fertility issues.  Other topics such as privacy issues surrounding the collection of genetic material during testing, as well as insurance and work place discrimination issues.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care (no peer support).  The usual care group will be advised of the telephone number for the helpline operated by the Cancer Information and Support Service at The Cancer Council in their state and will be advised to call this service if they want to discuss any issues or find out about services that might be available to them.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distress measured by the Impact of Events Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then at 4-months and 6-months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social isolation, measured by a modified version of the UCLA Loneliness Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then at 4-months and 6-months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women testing positive for the BRCA1/2 gene fault between 2004 and 2011.  Women may participate if they have had a diagnosis of cancer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A diagnosis of advanced/metastatic cancer</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Women who indicate on the baseline survey that they have an unmet need for information and support will be randomised to either the usual care or intervention group.  As it is likely that more than one member of a family will be invited to take part in the study (e.g. mother/daughter, or siblings), a cluster randomisation method will be used based on family membership.  The first member of a family to enter the study will be allocated to either the intervention or usual care groups using computerised sequence generation.  Any members of the same family that subsequently enter the study will then be allocated to the same study group as the first family member. This is necessary to prevent contamination between the intervention and usual care groups within family clusters. Allocation will be concealed using central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computerised sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2000-2999</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Cancer Council Victoria</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Rathdowne Street, Carlton, VIC, 3053</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Breast Cancer Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 18-20 York Street, Sydney, NSW, 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Women identified as carrying a gene fault that increases their risk of developing breast or ovarian cancer (BRCA1/2) live with the fear that they are likely to develop these cancers.  They also experience feelings of guilt about passing the gene onto their children, anxiety over informing family members, and grief.  Research has found that BRCA1/2 gene fault carriers experience similar levels of distress to breast cancer patients within a year of their diagnosis and that distress among carriers does not decrease with time. Currently in Australia formal support services for cancer gene mutation carriers outside the Familial Cancer Centres (FCCs) are lacking. The NHMRCs, Familial aspects of cancer: a guide to clinical practice calls for research to identify effective intervention strategies to reduce morbidity associated with genetic testing.  BRCA1/2 gene fault carriers have an unmet need for support, and for help in reducing their sense of isolation, guilt, fear of the future and concerns about communicating test results with family members. 

We propose to address these unmet needs with a peer support program for women identified as carrying the BRCA1/2 gene fault  and examine whether this intervention can reduce psychological distress. 

The projects aims are:

1.	To determine the effectiveness of a telephone based peer support program for women with a BRCA1/2 gene fault on psychological distress using a randomised controlled trial. 
2. 	To determine how feelings of isolation, unmet needs for information and confidence in risk management decisions relate to psychological distress and how these factors are influenced by the intervention. 
3.	To explore the impact of providing support among support providers. 

The design will be a prospective randomised controlled trial with female BRCA1/2 gene fault carriers.  Participants will be recruited through Familial Cancer Centres in Victoria and NSW.  Participants will complete a baseline survey that will allow the identification of those with unmet support needs.  This group will then be randomised to receive either the intervention (peer support program) or usual care.  Women in the intervention group will be assigned a peer support provider and will have telephone contact with the peer at least 6 times over a 4-month period.  Women who report no unmet needs for support at baseline will remain in the study and provide useful information about issues affecting people with this genetic mutation.  All participants will complete follow-up questionnaires at 4-months and 6-months post study entry.  Women who indicate on the baseline survey that they have no unmet needs for information and support will remain in the study and follow the same procedure as the usual care group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Cancer Council Victoria Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 Rathdowne Street, Carlton, VIC, 3053.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 0807</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Victoria White</name>
      <address>Deputy Director, Centre for Behavioural Research in Cancer, The Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne Street, Carlton, VIC, 3053.</address>
      <phone>(03) 9635 5197</phone>
      <fax>(03) 9635 5380</fax>
      <email>Vicki.White@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Victoria White</name>
      <address>Deputy Director, Centre for Behavioural Research in Cancer, The Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne Street, Carlton, VIC, 3053.</address>
      <phone>(03) 9635 5197</phone>
      <fax>(03) 9635 5380</fax>
      <email>Vicki.White@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Hayman</name>
      <address>Project Manager, Centre for Behavioural ,The Cancer Council Victoria, 1 Rathdowne Street, Carlton, VIC, 3053.</address>
      <phone>(03) 9635 5622</phone>
      <fax>(03) 9635 5380</fax>
      <email>Jane.Hayman@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>