<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373131">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000895381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of implementation of the Goal-directed Medication review Electronic Decision Support System (G-MEDSS) into Home Medicines Review (HMR) to deprescribe medications in older adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Implementation of the Goal-directed Medication review Electronic Decision Support System (G-MEDSS) into Home Medicines Review (HMR) to deprescribe medications in older adults - a cluster randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Medication burden</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Goal-directed Medication review Electronic Decision Support System (G-MEDSS) (accessible from gmedss.com) is a validated electronic platform that has been designed to provide clinical decision support for healthcare practitioners when completing a medication review for their older patients, to tailor care to meet their goals and preferences. The G-MEDSS is designed to produce patient-specific deprescribing reports for a patients GP.

The G-MEDSS contains three tools: 
1)	The Goals of Care Management tool allows the patients goals of care to be identified and aligned with their medication strategies. 
2)	The Drug Burden Index Calculator© is a validated tool that identifies medications with anticholinergic and sedative effects (measured by the DBI) and provides information and recommendations for physicians. 
3)	The revised Patients Attitudes Towards Deprescribing questionnaire (rPATD) was developed and validated to explore peoples attitudes, beliefs, and experiences regarding the number of medications that they are taking, and how they would feel about cessation of one or more of their medications. 

The G-MEDSS deprescribing report for an individual patient includes the patients global goal of care, a summary of the patients current medications, the patients DBI score and information about interpreting the DBI, information about the rPATD, and a summary of the patients responses to the rPATD. The G-MEDSS system also allows accredited pharmacists to enter medication recommendations and actions on the G-MEDSS reports to allow for the GP to comment on deprescribing recommendations. The G-MEDSS system also allows for a patient summary report (or carers summary report) to be produced that can be provided to patients or carers at the time of the Home Medicines Review (HMR).  

Accredited pharmacists are specially trained pharmacists who are able to conduct medication management reviews (such as a HMR) for patients, under the referral of a general practitioner. Accredited Pharmacists are usually registered with the Australian Association of Consultant Pharmacy or the Society of Hospital Pharmacy. The HMR service is an Australian government-funded community-based collaborative service between the patient, general practitioner (GP) and accredited pharmacist. As part of the service, an accredited pharmacist receives a referral for a patient from the GP (either directly or through the patients community pharmacy), conducts an interview with the patient (usually in the home) to gain a comprehensive medication profile, and documents medication review findings and recommendations in a report for the GP, which can then be used to formulate the patients medication management plan. 

Accredited Pharmacists in the intervention group in this study will produce G-MEDSS reports for their HMR patients to send together with the HMR report to the patients GP. This will be done once at baseline.</interventions>
    <comparator>The Accredited Pharmacists enrolled in the control group will only conduct HMRs for their patients (usual care), which involves the accredited pharmacist writing a HMR report to the patient's GP. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure changes in drug burden index (DBI, measure of anticholinergic and sedative medication burden) after HMR/GMEDSS intervention between control and intervention groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of deprescribing any medication after HMR/GMEDSS intervention between groups (by assessment of medication list by accredited pharmacist at 3-month home visit)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attitudes towards deprescribing, assessed using the Patient's Attitudes Towards Deprescribing (PATD) questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility, usability and acceptability (composite outcome) of the intervention in pharmacy practice using qualitative surveys (designed for the study) completed by accredited pharmacists in the intervention arm</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure changes in clinical outcomes - physical function after HMR/GMEDSS intervention between groups using the Short Physical Performance Battery and the independent activities of daily living questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure changes in clinical outcomes - cognitive function, after HMR/GMEDSS intervention between groups using the MiniCog tool</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure changes in clinical outcomes - falls, institutionalisation and GP/specialist visits (Composite outcome) after HMR/GMEDSS intervention between groups - using a patient self-reported calendar</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure changes in clinical outcomes - medication adherence after HMR/GMEDSS intervention between groups using the Morisky, Levine and Green adherence scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>As this is a cluster randomised study, there are two tiers of recruitment: a) Australian registered accredited pharmacists who have conducted at least 24 HMRs in the last 12 months, and conduct 2-20 HMRs per month, will be eligible to participate in this study. b) eligibility for individual patients (with and without dementia) include: aged 65 years and older who can speak English, are eligible for a HMR (according to eligibility listed on http://6cpa.com.au/medication-management-programmes/home-medicines-review/), and are able to provide informed written consent (patient or carer). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pharmacists that are not accredited to conduct medication reviews, or conduct fewer than 24/year. 
Patients &lt;65 years old
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be conducted using the randomisation module in REDCap (https://apps.icts.uiowa.edu/confluence/display/REDCapDocs/REDCap+Randomization+Module) </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by Excel</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a cluster randomised trial. The clustering will occur at the level of the accredited pharmacist. Using the randomisation module in REDCap, the pharmacist will be assigned to the intervention or control group. The patients that the pharmacists recruit will/will not receive the intervention in addition to usual care Home Medicine Review (HMR) service depending on the assignment of the pharmacist in the group. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics will be used to report the demographics of the study population. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test and histogram will be used to test the distribution of DBI in the study population. Previous studies have demonstrated that DBI is not normally distributed, as there are usually high proportions of patients who have a DBI score of 0. If this is the case, the Mann-Whitney non-parametric tests will be used to analyse continuous variables and Chi square tests for categorical variables to compare characteristics between groups. Multivariate logistic regression analyses will be used to estimate the odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI) to investigate the associations between changes in DBI with clinically measured outcomes. All statistical tests will be two-tailed, and p values of &lt;0.05 will be deemed statistically significant. All data will be analysed using IBM SPSS Statistics Version 24 statistical software.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 12 Laboratory of Clinical Pharmacology and Ageing
Sydney Medical School - Northern
Kolling Building, Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards
NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cognitive Decline Partnership Centre (CDPC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, Old Leighton Lodge (Building 8 via Gate 6)
Department of Rehabilitation and Aged Care (RACS)
Hornsby Ku-ring-gai Hospital
Palmerston Road
Hornsby NSW 2077</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: This project is a cluster randomised clinical trial investigating the implementation of a computerised clinical decision support system into the Home Medicines Review (HMR) service to deprescribe inappropriate medications in older adults. Older Australians aged 65 years or over are commonly prescribed multiple medications and the doctor may arrange for a HMR. This service is a way for the pharmacist and doctor to help manage medications in the home. This project is investigating to see whether adding a computerised system into HMR will help to use medicines effectively and to avoid any unwanted side effects.
Hypothesis: We hypothesise that the combination of pharmacist-led medication review (HMR) and a computerised clinical decision support system intervention that incorporates validated deprescribing tools and guides (e.g. drug burden index (DBI), patients attitudes towards deprescribing (PATD) and Goals of Care, i.e. G-MEDSS) may reduce the proportion of older adults using anticholinergic and sedative medications, and improve clinical outcomes in community-dwelling older adults.
Purpose: This study aims to test the efficacy of the addition of GMEDSS in HMR to:
	Reduce anticholinergic and sedative medication use (as measured by the DBI) in patients who are exposed to these medications
	Measure the effect of these medication changes on clinical and functional outcomes (adherence, cognitive and physical function, falls, institutionalisation, mortality)</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office
Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/09/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017/538</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sarah Hilmer</name>
      <address>Level 12 Kolling Building 
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards
NSW
2065</address>
      <phone>+61299264481</phone>
      <fax>+61299264053</fax>
      <email>sarah.hilmer@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sarah Hilmer</name>
      <address>Level 12 Kolling Building 
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards
NSW
2065</address>
      <phone>+61299264481</phone>
      <fax>+61299264053</fax>
      <email>sarah.hilmer@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mouna Sawan</name>
      <address>Level 12 Kolling Building 
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards
NSW
2065</address>
      <phone>+61299264927</phone>
      <fax>+61299264053</fax>
      <email>mouna.sawan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mouna Sawan</name>
      <address>Level 12 Kolling Building 
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards
NSW
2065</address>
      <phone>+61299264927</phone>
      <fax>+61299264053</fax>
      <email>mouna.sawan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>