<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367713">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000080527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cognitive control training for treatment resistant depression: application, evaluation and augmentation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cognitive control training for treatment resistant depression: application, evaluation and augmentation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is trialling a new behavioural therapy called Cognitive Control Training (CCT).  CCT involves repeated practice of targeted cognitive activities that are specifically designed to activate areas of the brain that allow us to control and direct our attention. This study is additionally investigating whether the effectiveness of CCT can be further enhanced using a form of mild brain stimulation called transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS). tDCS is a safe, non-invasive, painless technique which has the capacity to temporarily alter cortical excitability.  In this study it is delivered to the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. 

Participants will be randomised to one of the following four conditions and receive a 25 minute intervention session on fifteen consecutive week days: 
 
(a)	25-minutes of CCT and active tDCS (2 mA)
(b)	25-minutes of CCT and sham tDCS (tDCS that we believe will have no effect)
(c)	25-minutes of a different cognitive training and active tDCS (2 mA)
(d)	25-minutes of a different cognitive training and sham tDCS

Stimulation and cognitive training are administered simultaneously. They will be administered by a trained research staff member. Participants will not be informed which condition they have been allocated to until the end of the study. </interventions>
    <comparator>There is a placebo condition in place. The placebo involves 25-minutes of a different cognitive training and sham tDCS Participants initially randomised to the placebo condition will be given the opportunity to be re-randomised to the active intervention upon completion of the sham controlled phase. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale will be used as a primary outcome measure for depression severity. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week and 3 weeks after intervention commencement, and 2 months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 2-back working memory task will be used as a secondary outcome measure of cognitive control. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week and 3 weeks after intervention commencement, and 2 month post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Are voluntary and able to provide full informed consent, 
2.	Are currently in the midst of a Major Depressive Episode as confirmed by structured diagnostic interview with the Mini-International Interview for DSM-IV, 
3.	Are between the ages of 18 and 65 years. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Have a DSM-IV history of substance abuse or dependence in the last 6-months,
2.	Have a concomitant major and/or unstable medical or neurologic illness;
3.	Are currently taking carbamazepine or benzodiazepines,
4.	Are currently pregnant or lactating,
5.	Have metal anywhere in the head, except the mouth.  This includes metallic objects such as screws and clips from surgical procedures

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation occurs via central randomised computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised via a computer generated randomisation schedule. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>52</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>6/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100 Hawthorn West
Victoria, Australia 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wellington Road, Clayton VIC 3800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sir Edward Dunlop Medical Research Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 5444
Heidelberg West, VIC 3081
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this project is to explore whether cognitive control training can help alleviate some of the symptoms of depression. Depression is associated with changes in both emotions and cognition (i.e. thinking skills). Research has shown that the emotional and cognitive symptoms of depression interact with each other, and these interactions can contribute to the severity and length of depressive episodes. Examples of these interactions include preferential memory for negative memories and paying greater attention to negative thoughts or negative environmental stimuli. We are interested in whether targeting the cognitive symptoms of depression may also help to improve the emotional symptoms. 

We are exploring this using cognitive control training (CCT). CCT involves practicing a thinking activity that has been designed to improve attentional processing. The type of attention that CCT is designed to improve is subsumed by activity in a frontal area of the brain called the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC). Research has shown that a mild form of brain stimulation called transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) administered to this brain region can enhance cognitive processing. tDCS involves the application of gentle electrical currents to the scalp though electrodes, and can increase activity in various parts of the brain, depending on where it is applied.  We are also interested in whether tDCS may be a useful means of augmenting CCT in depression.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.maprc.org.au/psychiatric-neurotechnology-treatment-studies</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital
Commercial Rd
Prahran, VIC
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>26/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Segrave </name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre 
Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd
Prahran, VIC, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 5030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.segrave@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Cassandra Thomson</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre 
Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd
Prahran, VIC, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 6592</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cassandra.thomson@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Segrave</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre 
Level 4, 607 St Kilda Rd
Prahran, VIC, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 5030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.segrave@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>