<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363434">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000107729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of intermittent versus continuous androgen deprivation therapy  in Chinese patients with advanced prostate cancer: A prospective controlled Trial from China</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Androgen Deprivation Therapy in Treating Patients With Prostate Cancer:A prospective controlled Trial from China</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1138-1814 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>prostate cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients recruited received the LHRHa goserelin acetate(Zoladex  3.6mg) subcutaneously every 28 days and bicalutamide(Casodex 50mg) orally once daily for 8 months(run in) before randomization. Patients in whom PSA decreased to less than 4.0ng/ml were randomized to  intermittent androgen deprivation(IAD) or  continuous androgen deprivation(CAD) at a 1:1 ratio. In the IAD arm all the medicine was withheld after randomization and was resumed for at least 8 months whenever PSA increased more than 20.0ng /ml with metastatic(M1) prostate cancer[10.0ng/ml with non-metastatic(M0)] and withheld again by the same criteria as for randomization.The overall duration of the intervention is 3 years. And treatment required in the IAD arm  is the same as that received prior to randomisation.
</interventions>
    <comparator>All patients recruited received the LHRHa goserelin acetate(Zoladex  3.6mg) subcutaneously every 28 days and bicalutamide(Casodex 50mg) orally once daily for 8 months(run in) before randomization. Patients in whom PSA decreased to less than 4.0ng/ml were randomized to  intermittent androgen deprivation(IAD) or  continuous androgen deprivation(CAD) at a 1:1 ratio. In the CAD arm patients continued with goserelin acetate and bicalutamide or underwent bilateral orchiectomy. The duration that participants in this arm continue with goserelin acetate and bicalutamide is for 3 years. Whether patients in the CAD arm will continue with goserelin acetate and bicalutamide or undergo bilateral orchiectomy depends on the will of patients. Because the operation is simple and the price is low.But it can make a difference on the psychology of patients.

 </comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time To Progression (TTP)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time To Progression (TTP) is difined as appearance of any new or worsening of existing bone metastases;increase in dimensions(by 25% or more)of any existing or appearance of any new extraskeletal metastases; ureteral obstruction either by primary tumor or pelvic nodal disease;lymphedema of lower extremities due to pelvic nodal involvement; recurrent vesical obstruction, bleeding(macroscopic hematuria) or pain due to growth of primary tumor</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> prostate cancer-specific survival</outcome>
      <timepoint> Prostate cancer-specific survival was defined as Death from prostate cancer. And the followup is 5 years post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time to treatment failure</outcome>
      <timepoint> treatment failure is difined as death; adverse drug reaction requiring cessation of the randomized treatment; cancer progression;patient unwilling or unable to continue according to the protocol; patient refused the randomized treatment; administration of any additional systemic therapy or radiotherapy for prostate cancer, patient lost to followup; investigators decision in the patients best interest to stop the randomized therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life</outcome>
      <timepoint>QoL was assessed using the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) QLQ-C30 and prostate module for Quality of life annually for 5 years post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>.Inclusion Criteria (run-in period):
1)Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate
2)T1-T4, metastatic (M1) prostate cancer, T1-T4, non-metastatic (M0), N+ prostate cancer
.Inclusion criteria to the randomised period:
All patients recruited received the LHRHa goserelin acetate(Zoladex  3.6mg) subcutaneously every 28 days and bicalutamide(Casodex 50mg) orally once daily for 8 months(run in) before randomization. Patients in whom PSA decreased to less than 4.0ng/ml were randomized to IAD or CAD.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>.Exclusion Criteria (run-in period):
Any previous or concurrent treatment of prostate cancer, except TURP, 5-alpha reductase inhibitor, radical prostatectomy or radiotherapy Any medication/treatment affecting sex hormone status
.Exclusion Criteria:
Patients in whom prostate specific antigen decreased to no less than 4ng/ml were excluded
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>serially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes.When researchers identified the conformity of subjects, the envelopes are opened and the subjects are assigned to the corresponding test group</concealment>
    <sequence>enter the website which is 'http://www.random.org/integers' to get the computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state> Shanghai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname> Changhai Hospital, Second Military Medical University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>168 Changhai road yangpu district Shanghai (200433)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Changhai hospital' s" 1255"construction plan</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>168 Changhai road yangpu district Shanghai (200433)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Prostate cancer (PCa) is one of the most common malignant tumors in older men, endocrine therapy as the standard treatment of advanced prostate cancer, has become an important part of the clinical work of PCa. In 2 to 3 years, almost all patients with continuous androgen deprivation(CAD) progress to androgen-independent prostate cancer. At the same time, CAD treatment has also been associated with significant side effects, leads to the decline in the quality of life of patients and increase costs. In order to delay the emergence of androgen-independent prostate cancer, prolong the survival time of the patients, and improve quality of life, intermittent androgen deprivation(IAD) may be the Effective treatment. IAD perform well in animal models, but Prostate cancer is with a high degree of ethnic specificity (black and white incidence was significantly higher than the yellow race), Endocrine therapy may also have a similar heterogeneity. In other words, the foreign study results might does not apply to Chinese prostate cancer patient. Since there is no such prospective clinical study in China, we conducted the RCT in order to develop the Chinese intermittent hormonal therapy for prostate cancer patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Changhai Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Changhai Hospital, Second Military Medical University,168 Changhai road yangpu district Shanghai 200433</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gaoxu</name>
      <address> Department of Urology, Changhai Hospital, Second Military Medical University 168 Changhai road yangpu district Shanghai(200433)</address>
      <phone>+8602131161718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gaoxu.changhai@gmail.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>LU Xin</name>
      <address> Department of Urology, Changhai Hospital, Second Military Medical University 168 Changhai road yangpu district Shanghai(200433)</address>
      <phone>+8602131161718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luxin_smmu@163.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wang Hai-feng</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Changhai Hospital, Second Military Medical University 168 Changhai road yangpu district Shanghai(200433</address>
      <phone>+8602131161718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> 	whfcmm91@gmail.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fang ziyu</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Changhai Hospital, Second Military Medical University 168 Changhai road yangpu district Shangha(200433)</address>
      <phone>+8602131161718</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fzy230858@126.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>