<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371258">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001183471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>How does the neck contribute to post-concussion symptoms?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>How does the neck contribute to post-concussion symptoms?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>concussion</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>neck conditions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will observe people who have had a concussion presenting to a concussion provider through the New Zealand Accident Compensation Corporation (ACC) Concussion Service, when it is suspected the neck is contributing to their symptoms, at the time they present to a Physiotherapist for neck assessment and treatment. 
Participants will complete neck Physiotherapy as normal. This will involve a detailed assessment of the neck including movements, palpation and tests. Treatment will be decided by the participant in collaboration with the Physiotherapist and may include hands-on therapy, exercise, education, advice etc. Treatment will typically span several sessions (e.g. 6 sessions), and is expected to be completed within 2 months of their first appointment. Again, this will be decided by the participant along with the Physiotherapist and healthcare team. 
Standardised outcomes will be measured at the initial Physiotherapy visit, and again at the final Physiotherapy visit. This will involve questionnaires, clinical measures of symptoms and function, clinical findings in the neck, and saliva samples. Descriptive findings, treatment and outcomes will be retrieved from the clinical notes at the end of their neck Physiotherapy treatment. </interventions>
    <comparator>No intervention or control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Description and change in symptoms measured by the Rivermead post-concussion symptoms questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of neck problem as measured by the Neck disability index</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of dizziness as measured by Dizziness Handicap Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache category based on Physiotherapy assessment, simply recorded as cervicogenic or non-cervicogenic. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache sidedness, categorised as bilateral, unilateral with side shift, or unilateral without side shift. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache frequency, recorded as number of headache days in the last week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache duration (typical episode), recorded in minutes or hours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache severity (typical episode), recorded on an 11-point numeric rating scale (0-10). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dizziness frequency recorded in seconds or minutes. 
Then categorised on a six point categorical scale (0=no dizziness, 1=&lt;once/month, 2=1-4 episodes/month, 3=1-4 episodes/week, 4=once daily, 5=&gt;once daily or constant).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dizziness duration (typical episode), recorded in seconds or minutes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dizziness severity/intensity as measured by an 11 point numeric rating scale (0-10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck pain severity using the 11-point numeric pain rating scale (0-10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck range of motion, including flexion-rotation test. Measured using a CROM and modified CROM device respectively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Segmental assessment of the neck - pain. This is a manual examination by the Physiotherapist recording the cervical spine levels that are painful and/or stiff. Pain will be measured using the numeric pain rating scale (0-10). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Segmental assessment of the neck - stiffness. This is a manual examination by the Physiotherapist recording the cervical spine levels that are painful and/or stiff. Stiffness will be measured using a 7-point scale indicated by hypermobile (1-3), normal (4), hypomobile (5-7).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other key relevant qualitative desciptors of the participant's neck findings or response to Physiotherapy treatment as recorded in the clinical notes (e.g. behaviour of symptoms).
Key findings will be highlighted (*) or repeated in follow-up sessions, and considered on a case by case basis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial neck assessment by Physiotherapist, then after Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salivary cortisol levels using passive drool test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to and after the initial neck treatment by Physiotherapist, then prior to and after the final Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salivary testosterone levels using passive drool test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to and after the initial neck treatment by Physiotherapist, then prior to and after the final Physiotherapy neck treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>These are: Patients presenting through the ACC Concussion service to APM Limited OR Advantage South concussion assessors with persistent (&gt; 10 days) headaches, dizziness and/or neck pain; subjective history suggesting the neck may contribute to their symptoms*; who accept and follow through with a referral for neck assessment and treatment by a Physiotherapist with postgraduate manual therapy training.
*Potential for the neck to contribute to patients symptoms will be informed by:
1.	Increased neck pain or stiffness since their concussion injury OR
2.	Headache consistent with symptoms arising from the neck: headache triggered by neck movement/positioning, or external pressure to the neck/head; restricted neck range of movement; neck, shoulder or arm pain on the same side (Sjaastad, Fredriksen, and Pfaffenrath 1998) OR
3.	Dizziness consistent with symptoms arising from the neck: non-rotatory dizziness described as imbalance or unsteadiness; and triggered by neck movements or positions (Reid et al. 2014).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>These are: Contraindications to manual therapy for the neck (e.g. fracture, inflammatory joint conditions, and infection); other significant neurological conditions; patients under the age of 16 years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>In line with recommendations for a prospective case series the main analysis will be descriptive rather than statistical (Carey and Boden 2003; Kooistra et al. 2009). Patient characteristics and flow through the study will be reported, including loss to follow-up and other potential areas of bias. 
Outcome measures will be tabulated for easy comparison of cases, and common clinical features of the neck contributing to peoples symptoms will be discussed. Changes in outcomes pre and post manual therapy will be reported, identifying and discussing common themes. Where appropriate, basic statistical analysis comparing pre and post manual therapy outcomes may be performed (e.g. paired t-test). Note that statistical analysis is not designed to establish causal effects or treatment efficacy, but to identify areas where manual therapy has an impact on participants symptoms. 
For these purposes a target study sample of 30 participants was discussed and agreed upon by the research team. Note that as this is a descriptive case series this number is not based on power calculations for statistical analysis, but numbers considered achievable and appropriate for descriptive purposes. 
The levels of cortisol and testosterone in all the salivary samples will be measured using commercially available ELISA kit (Salimetrics, USA) according to the manufacturers instruction. This will be performed at the Department of Physiology, University of Otago. 
The feasibility aspects of the research will be reported and discussed based on the quality and quantity of data collected over the study period. This will also inform service delivery. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/10/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mr Dusty Quinn</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Back in Motion Ltd
27-29 Albany Street
Dunedin 9016</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Cathy Chapple</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Physiotherapy
325 Great King Street
University of Otago
Dunedin 9016
New Zealand</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Steve Tumilty</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Physiotherapy
325 Great King Street
University of Otago
Dunedin 9016
New Zealand </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research is designed to address two questions. 
1. How does the neck contribute to persistent (&gt;10 days) post-concussion symptoms? (With particular attention to headaches, dizziness and/or neck pain). 
2. What changes in post-concussion symptoms are observed after treatment of the neck?

Concussion (also known as mild traumatic brain injury) is increasingly recognised as an injury with significant consequences. Recent New Zealand research shows that following a concussion nearly half (47.9%) report significant persistent symptoms a year later. Some of these symptoms potentially arise from the neck, as there appears to be significant overlap in post-concussion and neck-related symptoms. However, original research to describe the contribution of the neck to post-concussion symptoms is lacking. 
Participants for a prospective case-series will be recruited from two existing concussion service providers involved in assessing cases under the Accident Compensation Corporation (ACC) Concussion Service. Those with a potential neck contribution to their symptoms, and referred to a Physiotherapist with training in manual therapy for further neck assessment and treatment will be eligible for the study. In line with normal practice participants will be excluded if manual neck assessment is inappropriate, if they have other significant neurological conditions, or are under 16 years old. No additional exclusions will apply, ensuring the results are generally relevant.
Following patients through their neck assessment and treatment will allow us to describe the contribution of the neck to their symptoms, and outcomes from neck treatment. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee (Health)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H19/089</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACC Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ACC Corporate Office
Justice Centre
19 Aitken Street
PO Box 242
Wellington 6140</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>#314</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ewan Kennedy</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
325 Great King Street
University of Otago
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4795424</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ewan.kennedy@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ewan Kennedy</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
325 Great King Street
University of Otago
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4795424</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ewan.kennedy@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ewan Kennedy</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
325 Great King Street
University of Otago
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4795424</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ewan.kennedy@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ewan Kennedy</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
325 Great King Street
University of Otago
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4795424</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ewan.kennedy@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>