<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364699">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001053718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of Turmeric and Kalongi in Metabolic syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Turmeric, Kalongi and its combination in improving the parameters of Metabolic syndrome in adults -a randomized controlled trial.  TAK-MS Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TAK-MS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Four parallel groups will be given intervention or placebo for 8 weeks. Look alike capsules will be used and the dose will be administered in 2 divided doses. Compliance will be encouraged by daily phone messages and it will be measured by drug diary. Refilling will be done when patients return the blister packs of capsules on a weekly basis.

Group 1: Kalongi (Nigella Sativa) group (2 gm/day)
Group 2: Turmeric (Curcuma Longa) group (3.2 gm/day)
Group 3: Combination of Turmeric and Kalongi group (1.6 gm +1 gm/day)
Group 4: Placebo (Wheat) group (2gm /day)</interventions>
    <comparator>The Placebo (Wheat) group (2gm /day) will receive look alike capsules just like the other 3 groups in 2 divided doses for 8 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in multiple parameters of Metabolic syndrome 
( Body weight/ waist circumference reduction and Blood pressure control measured by mercury sphyngmomanometer, Triglycerides, fasting blood sugar and serum HDL measured by cobas c111)</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at baseline, 4 and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in insulin resistance measured by fasting serum insulin levels measured by ELECSYS Insulin Assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at baseline and 8 weeks of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>improvement in inflammatory markers like C-reactive protein  measured by cobas c111</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at baseline and 8 weeks of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> body fat, muscle, bone percent (measured through bio impedence).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2, 4, 6 and 8 weeks of Randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse effect of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>questions will be asked for any complains every week for 8 weeks monitoring adverse effects like nausea, dyspepsia, intolerance etc by a physician. participants will also be given an emergency contact number for any urgent symptoms they would like to report.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Obese males residing and permanent residents of Hijrat colony with a waist circumference of or &gt;90 cm with any 2 more features of Metabolic syndrome (MS) who are not on any regular medications for Diabetes (pre-Diabetic), Dyslipidemia, blood pressure (pre hypertensive) or obesity and do not require any medications as per ATP III guidelines and American Diabetic Association guidelines for control of Diabetes or Hypertension.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Patients with known Diabetes, Hypertension or Coronary Heart disease or who require immediate pharmacological treatment.
*Patients with wheat allergy.
*Patients already taking Herbal supplements.
*Patients on medications for Hyperlipidemia or Obesity.
*Debilitated patients or patients on regular medications for chronic diseases like steroids, immunosuppressants and Warfarin will also be excluded.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted Block randomization</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size is calculated for a 5 % level of significance and a power of 80%. Assuming the population standard deviation of 3.62 from a previous study (Bhatti A, Berntorp K, Rehman F. Effect of prophetic medicine Kalonji on lipid profile of human beings, an in vivo approach. W Appl Sci J. 2009;6:1053-7), a sample of 52 in each group will be required to determine an effect size of 40%. Assuming a 20% non- participation rate, 62 subjects in each group will be approached. 

Data will be entered and analyzed on SPSS version 20.0 and Graph pad prism. Means for quantitative data and frequencies, proportions and percentages for categorical data will be calculated. For quantitative data, paired and unpaired students t test will be used to compare the means within and between groups respectively. One way Anova will be used to compare the means between various groups followed by Tukeys and Dunetts tests for multiple comparisons. For categorical data, chi-square will be used to compare differences between groups. If the data is not normally distributed, to compare means, Wilcoxin signed rank sum test will be used for paired data and Mann Whitney U test for unpaired data. P values &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant (Confidence interval of 95%).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>248</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state>Sindh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Aga Khan University Medical College, </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Aga Khan University Hospital, Stadium Road, Karachi-74800,Pakistan.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Pakistan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Aga Khan University Medical College, </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Aga Khan University Hospital, Stadium Road, Karachi-74800, Pakistan</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Pakistan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Anwar-ul-Hassan Gilani</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Professor of Pharmacology, Department of Biological and Biomedical Sciences, Aga Khan University Medical College, Stadium road, Karachi-74800,Pakistan.
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Pakistan</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The metabolic syndrome is a combination of certain metabolic abnormalities including Obesity, Diabetes, Dyslipidemia and Hypertension. These in combination are associated with increased risk of coronary heart disease, stroke, and cardiovascular mortality. South Asian countries including Pakistan contribute to the highest proportion of cardiovascular disease burden when compared with any other region globally. The management of early metabolic syndrome without overt Hypertension, Dyslipidemia and Diabetes is based on increasing physical activity and dietary modifications, which is a challenge for many patients. Complementary medicines including herbs like Turmeric and Kalongi are widely accepted and are a part of diet in many Asian countries. These can be used to prevent or as an adjuvant to control chronic diseases like Metabolic syndrome with fewer side effects, better acceptability and cost effectiveness. Therefore this study was done to determine the effectivenees of commonly used herbs like Kalongi and Turmeric in improving the parameters of Metabolic syndrome.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical Review Committee (Aga Khan University Hospital)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Aga Khan University Hospital, Stadium Road, Karachi 74800,Pakistan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2042-BBS-ERC-11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Pakistan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Faridah Amin</name>
      <address>Dept. Biological and Biomedical Sciences,
Aga Khan University Hospital, Stadium Road,
Karachi-74800,Pakistan.</address>
      <phone>+92 21-34864566</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>faridah.amin@aku.edu</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Faridah Amin</name>
      <address>Contact person is the principal investigator and PhD scholar in Aga Khan University.
A32/3, street 9, BathIsland, Clifton, Karachi- 75600, Pakistan</address>
      <phone>+92 3212701086</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>faridah.amin@bluedotpk.com</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Faridah Amin</name>
      <address>Dept. Biological and Biomedical Sciences,
Aga Khan University Hospital
Stadium Road, Karachi-74800, Sindh, Pakistan</address>
      <phone>+92 21-34864566</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>faridah.amin@aku.edu</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>