<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365056">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001078741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Postpartum Motivational Interviewing Group Intervention for Women with a History of Gestational Diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to evaluate the effect of a postpartum motivational interviewing group intervention on motivation, exercise and eating habits in women with a history of gestational diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>UTN: U1111-1148-3995</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A motivational interviewing group which involves reflection on the experience of gestational diabetes, what the women know about life after gestational diabetes, a discussion on their current lifestyle and encouraging intrinsic motivation to make changes if appropriate. This one off session will take 2 hours and can be followed up with additional support at home or via telephone if deemed useful. </interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care (no treatment)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motivation- measured using readiness rulers for importance, confidence and readiness to change: fat intake, sugar intake, portion size, exercise, fruit and vegetable intake, keeping a healthy weight.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, end of group session and 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eating habits (rapid eating assessment for participants shortened version)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical exercise (International physical activity questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and follow-up (1 month)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>women with a history of gestational diabetes in their last pregnancy, 3-12 months postpartum; 18 years or over; able to give informed consent; fluent in English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>major psychiatric disorders; severe cognitive dysfunction.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A local PHO will recruit participants through their database. They will make telephone contact with them and ask if they would like to be part of a study. Interested individuals will have their details passed onto the researcher who will then make contact with them and provide additional information. Participants will be allocated a participant number on recruitment, and then randomized to the control group or intervention group through an internet number randomizer. Allocation will be consealed as the person recruiting participants will not know which group they will be part of until the complete number of participants have been recruited. </concealment>
    <sequence>Internet number generator</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size selected in this study is 20 participants. This is based on recommendations of not having more than 5-7 participants per group session if it is facilitated by one facilitator. We have decided to over recruit slightly in case some participants are unable to attend the group session on the day. Given this study is a pilot study we did not recruit based on power calculations. We realise that this will impact on the statistical tests that we run. We plan to use one way repeated measures ANOVA or Friedman's ANOVA.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Diabetes Projects Trust</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Alexander Crescent 
Otara
Auckland 2159
NZ</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetes Projects Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Alexander Crescent 
Otara
Auckland 2159
NZ</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Research has shown that women with a history of gestational diabetes are at a much higher risk of getting gestational diabetes in future pregnancies and type 2 diabetes in the future than those who have not had gestational diabetes. Furthermore, these risks can be ameliorated by maintaining a healthy lifestyle i.e. regular exercise and healthy eating. Modifying lifestyle factors is often a challenging task and can take considerable time, commitment and motivation. It is therefore not surprising that patients often experience a sense of ambivalence around whether they want to make changes or not, regardless of the health benefits.

Health practitioners have generally encouraged patients to make lifestyle changes through persuasive advice giving. However, the research shows that while this is an effective means of eliciting behaviour change for some patients, it does not appear to be effective for the majority of patients. Patient centred approaches to lifestyle modification (in which the patient does most of the talking and the patient and health practitioner work collaboratively) have produced more promising results. Furthermore, motivational interviewing (a patient centred approach) has shown significant effects on a range of physiological measures (including BMI) and a range of health problems e.g. diabetes and weight-related problems.

In this pilot study a between groups experimental design will be used as part of a PDSA cycle to explore the efficacy of a 2-hour motivational interviewing group for women with a history of gestational diabetes. Process data will be collected in addition to outcome data on perceived risk of diabetes, motivation for change, physical activity levels, and eating habits</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Regional X Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Heidi Baxter</name>
      <address>Diabetes Projects Trust
100 Alexander Crescent
Otara
Auckland 2159</address>
      <phone>649 273 9650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdm@dpt.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Heidi Baxter</name>
      <address>Diabetes Projects Trust
100 Alexander Crescent
Otara
Auckland 2159</address>
      <phone>649 273 9650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdm@dpt.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Heidi Baxter</name>
      <address>Diabetes Projects Trust
100 Alexander Crescent
Otara
Auckland 2159</address>
      <phone>649 273 9650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdm@dpt.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>