<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335368">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000608066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Healthy Dads, Healthy Kids Community Program: A community effectiveness trial evaluating a community-based healthy lifestyle program for overweight fathers and their children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Healthy Dads, Healthy Kids Community Program Randomised Controlled Trial: Evaluation of a community based healthy lifestyles program for overweight fathers and their children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity in fathers and their children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is the first phase of a two phase project. During phase 1, the intervention was delivered at the school sites of Singleton and Maitland and evaluated using a RCT design. The duration of the intervention is 7 weeks. The intervention involves fathers attending seven 90 minute face to face information sessions (including 3 interactive sessions with their children). The program includes: physical activity components; dietary and nutritional information; a self-monitoring component. More specifically program sessions focus on: 1) sustainable weight loss for men; identification of healthy and unhealthy lifestyle behaviours and explanation of the use of role modelling and positive reinforcement; 2) the importance of fathers for children's physical activity levels; strategies for encouraging physical activity in children; 3) father and child engagement in a variety of physical activities to develop child's confidence and ability in performing various fundamental movement skills; 4) nutritional information to encourage healthy eating for fathers and children; 5) another session for father and child engagement in a variety of physical activities; 6) sustaining healthy eating patterns for the family; 7) father and child engagement activities and closure. Fathers will also receive behavioural procedures over the course of the program via the use of the online website www.calorieking.com.au. The key constructs of social cognitive theory will be operationalised in the sessions (self efficacy, self monitoring, goal setting and social support). 
Phase 2, a larger scale community roll out of the program evaluated using a non-randomized, prospective design - will be described in more detail elsewhere.</interventions>
    <comparator>A wait-list control group was utilised for 3 months in the Phase 1 trial at Singleton and 6 months at Maitland.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fathers' body weight (kg) as measured on a set of electonic scales which are regularly checked and calibrated as necessary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and 3 month follow up.
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference for fathers and children (cm) using non-extensible steel tapes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and 3 month follow up.
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children's body weight (kg) will be measured using the same protocol as for the fathers and height of fathers and children will be calculated using a portable stadiometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and 3 month follow up.
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure for fathers and children using an automated blood pressure monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and 3 month follow up.
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3 and 6 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity using pedometers for fathers and children</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and 3 month follow up.
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary intake (kilojoules and macronutrient profile) for fathers. Fathers will complete the Australian Eating Survey 2010. Dietary intake for children, completed by mothers  using the Australian Child and Adolescent Eating Survey - Version 1.2 and the Child Feeding.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and 3 month follow up.
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart rate for fathers and children using an automated blood pressure monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and at 3 month follow-up. 
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3 and 6 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting strategies: Parental engagement is measured using a specifically designed Parental Engagement survey in Phase 1.  Parenting strategies for physical activity and nutrition are measured during phase 1 (Maitland only) using a validated questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the questionnaires:
Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and at 3 month follow-up. 
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child feeding behaviours: using a survey completed by mothers to assess behaviours associated  with child feeding.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and at 3 month follow-up. 
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting behaviours related to child's eating and physical activity using the Parental Eating and Behavioural Activitiy Survey (PEAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and at 3 month follow-up. 
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behaviour as indicated by self-reported for fathers and proxy report for children (completed by mothers during Phase 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1 (Singleton): At baseline and 3 month follow up.
Phase 1 (Maitland): At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Overweight or obese (Body Mass Index (BMI) 25 and 40 kg/m2) fathers from the Hunter Valley region who have a 5-12 year old child. In addition participants will be required to not participate in other weight loss programs during the study; pass a health-screening questionnaire; and have access to a computer with Internet facilities.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of major medical problems such as heart disease in the last 5 years, diabetes or orthopaedic or joint problems that would be a barrier to physical activity, taking medications that might interfere with weight loss and children with extreme obesity (BMI z-score &gt;= 4).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomized controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will complete a phone eligibility screen with a research assistant and also a pre-exercise screening questionnaire. Participants over 40 years will be required to receive doctor's clearance prior to commencement of the study. To ensure concealment, the random allocation sequence will be generated by a statistician and given to the project manager. Allocation will be concealed as (1) person who determines subject eligibility is unaware of group allocation (2) the use of sealed opaque envelopes (3) randomization will be completed by a research assistant who is not involved in the assessment of participants and the allocation sequence will be concealed when enrolling/randomising participants in Phase 1 and Phase 2.</concealment>
    <sequence>The random allocation sequence will be generated by a computer-based random number-producing algorithm in equal block lengths to ensure an equal chance of allocation to each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants will be blinded at baseline assessment only during Phase 1.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/08/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/05/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Philip Morgan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Education 
Faculty of Education and Arts 
University Dve
University of Newcastle 
Callaghan NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hunter Medical Research Institute (HMRI) Clinical Research Centre John Hunter Hospital Lookout Road, New Lambton Postal address: Locked Bag 1 Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Coal &amp; Allied Community Development Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rio Tinto
19 Bridge Street 
Muswellbrook 
NSW 2333</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is well established that parents of primary school aged children substantially influence the food and physical activity home environment through behaviours, attitudes, feeding styles and role modelling. However, the contribution of fathers influence on childrens physical activity and eating behaviour is often overlooked.The Healthy Dads Healthy Kids (HDHK) project is based on research that shows the eating habits and exercise routine of fathers and father figures influence the ways in which the whole family approaches their health. The program was developed and successfully trialled at the University of Newcastle, with trial results showing that the major aims of HDHK were achieved. These were (i) to help overweight/obese fathers achieve a healthy weight, and (ii) to improve the activity and eating behaviours of their children (using fathers as the key agents of behaviour change). The intention of the current project is to research the effectivenss of the HDHK program in a community setting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.healthydadshealthykids.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle, Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services/Research Office

University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan New South Wales 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2010-0045</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/02/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Philip Morgan</name>
      <address>School of Education Faculty of Education and Arts University of Newcastle University Dve Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49217265</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>philip.morgan@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Morgan</name>
      <address>School of Education Faculty of Education and Arts University of Newcastle University Dve Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 29217265</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 7407</fax>
      <email>philip.morgan@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Morgan</name>
      <address>School of Education Faculty of Education and Arts University of Newcastle University Dve Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49217265</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>philip.morgan@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Morgan</name>
      <address>School of Education 
Faculty of Education and Arts 
University of Newcastle 
University Dve
Callaghan NSW
2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 7265</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 7407</fax>
      <email>philip.morgan@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>