<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372719">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000650392p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Electric Nerve Stimulation to Enhance Functional Outcomes After Peripheral Nerve Injury Repair</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Electric Nerve Stimulation to Enhance Functional Outcomes After Peripheral Nerve Injury Repair</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1195-3205</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ENSPN</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral Nerve Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will undergo microsurgical coaptation of injured peripheral nerves by the standard surgical technique with interrupted monofilament nylon suture of the epineruium. In our experimental group the repaired nerve will be stimulated by applying low frequency electric pulses to the nerve for 1 hour.  After standard microsurgical repair of median or/and ulnar nerve injury is performed, two sterilized, stainless steel wires are placed proximal and distal to the coaptation site. These are secured to the skin with surgical suture material. The proximal wire is connected to the cathode and the distal wire to the anode port of the source of current calibrated to 20Hz  balanced biphasic pulses, voltage: 3 volts, 1mA to 5mA current, duty cycle of 0.2%, continuous. Patients included in the trial will receive Low frequency continuous electric stimulation of the nerve for 1 hour as per protocol. In the placebo group, subjects will receive 5 seconds of similar intensity ES but the stimulator will be turned off for the remainder of the hour. In the mean time, surgical repair of other injury structures is performed. It is well documented that isolated traumatic nerve injury is frequently associated to vascular and musculoskeletal injuries.   Standard closure of skin is performed . Electric stimulation wires are removed and standard dressings and immobilization applied. The entire procedure is performed under a general anaesthetic.
</interventions>
    <comparator>All patients will receive current standard of care microsurgical repair of severed ulnar or median nerves. In the control group the electostimulation apparatus will be prepared and and applied as with the experimental group, but the machine will be turned off after 5 seconds of electrostimulation. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcomes assessed in this project will seek to quantify the effects of electric stimulation on motor and sensory nerve regeneration. This will be accomplished by assessing the following:

1) Motor Function - Hand Therapy assessment of motor function on a standard 0-5 power grading system for all relevant muscle groups / actions 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will collect data at 3 months , 6 months, 12 months and 24 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> 2) Sensory function --&gt; Hand therapy assessment. Examination by formal SWME  testing (semms - weinstein monofiliment examination ) </outcome>
      <timepoint>We will collect data  at 3 months , 6 months, 12 months and 24 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) Neurophysiology --&gt; Nerve conduction studies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will collect data at 3 months , 6 months, 12 months and 24 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Patient Reported Outcomes (PRO) --&gt; Michigan Hand Disability Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will assess patient reported outcomes at 3, 6, 12 and 24 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) Pain and discomfort --&gt; Hand therapy assessment. Standardised survey by  assessment of pain on standard 0-10 analogue scale with 0 being no pain and 10 being the worst pain imaginable </outcome>
      <timepoint>We will assess pain discomfort in immediate postoperative setting 6h then at 3, 6, 12 and 24 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age 18 to 70 years
2. Complete transection of the medial or/and ulnar nerve proximal to the wrist level.
3. Receiving surgery within 72 hours after injury.
4. Standard primary end-to-end nerve repair
5. Clinical indication for surgery under general anesthesia.
6. Informed, voluntary verbal and written consent obtained from patients.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Devascularization or amputation
2. Multilevel or segmental nerve injury
3. Diabetic and other polyneuropathies.
4. Cognitive impairment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be concealed by central randomization. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Dandenong Hospital - Dandenong</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Casey Hospital - Berwick</hospital>
    <postcode>3175 - Dandenong</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3806 - Berwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Jeremy Wiseman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Health, Dandenong Hospital
135 David Street, Ward 1N, Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery
Dandenong, Victoria 3175</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Avant Mutual Group Limited - Avant medical Scholorship 2017</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NSW State Office - Level 28 HSBC Centre 580 George Street, Sydney NSW, 2000 PO Box 746 Queen Victoria Building NSW 1230
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Functional outcomes of peripheral nerve injury using standard microsurgical repair alone are extremely poor despite the tremendous advances in surgery and medicine. These poor outcomes are due to the slow nerve regeneration process through the injury site and further growth to the target sites (muscle motor units, sensory and propioreceptors). In simple language, the muscle is an electric motor that needs continual supply of electricity to keep it running in good condition. The nerve is the electric wire and the nerve impulse is the electricity. When there is an injury to the nerve the electric wire is divided and the motor cannot work. The motor will deteriorate and weaken irreversibly if the re-establishment of electricity supply is too slow.  When the electricity supply is re-established within a time interval short enough to prevent irreversible damage of the motor, the reconditioned and weaken motor will run again.  We hypothesise that the process of regeneration can be enhanced and sped up by electrical stimulation of the repaired nerve intraoperatively.  We plan to test this hypothesis in patients suffering from ulnar and median nerve injury. They will undergo microsurgical repair of the nerve under general aesthetic as routine practice and then receive intra-operative low frequency electric stimulation of the repaired nerve for 1 hour. Functional outcomes of patients randomised to receive the experimental treatment will be compared with controls (patients who receive nerve repair alone) over the course of a 24 month follow up period allowing us to determine if the added therapy translates into clinically beneficial outcomes.    
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication>none</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Services I Monash Health
Level 2, I Block, Monash Medical Centre, Clayton, Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372719-PatientInformationSheetElectricStimulationV1.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372719-Protocol.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeremy Wiseman</name>
      <address>Dandenong Hospital
135 David Street 
Dandenong, Victoria 3175</address>
      <phone>+61402605292</phone>
      <fax>+613 97927728</fax>
      <email>jeremy.wiseman@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeremy Wiseman</name>
      <address>Dandenong Hospital
135 David Street 
Dandenong, Victoria 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 402605292</phone>
      <fax>+613 97927728</fax>
      <email>jeremy.wiseman@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeremy Wiseman</name>
      <address>Dandenong Hospital
135 David Street 
Dandenong, Victoria 3175</address>
      <phone>+614 02605292</phone>
      <fax>+613 97927728</fax>
      <email>jeremy.wiseman@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeremy Wiseman</name>
      <address>Dandenong Hospital
135 David Street 
Dandenong 3175</address>
      <phone>+61402605292</phone>
      <fax>+613 97927728</fax>
      <email>jeremy.wiseman@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>