<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372868">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000835347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes in movement quality and physical performance in response to an 8 week individualised movement quality assessment informed exercise intervention in apparently healthy adults: A randomised trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The changes in movement quality and measures of physical performance in healthy active adults (28-55 y) in response to an 8 week individualized movement quality assessment driven exercise intervention, in comparison to an 8 week traditional resistance training regime.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1196-2999 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Movement Quality</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical Performance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants within the intervention group will undertake an 8 week individualized exercise regime to improve strength and quality of movement, which will be based upon the results of their individual movement quality assessment outcome score. The exercise intervention will be based around the results of their movement quality assessment, and will be targeting improvements in movement quality. Exercise selection and progression will be  determined at the discretion of the trainers providing the intervention based upon their movement quality assessment results.

The Movement quality assessment will involve the evaluation of 9 movements that occur commonly in gym settings, and allow the identification of movement dysfunction and potential muscular imbalances. These movements include the following: a bilateral squat; a forward lunge; a dead-lift with a bent over row; a single leg squat; an overhead reach; a seated thoracic rotation; a 4 point hold with opposite arm and leg lifts (also known as a bird dog); a push up; and an active straight leg raise test. Poor performance on any one (or more) of these test will identify areas of muscular imbalance or dysfunction that will be used to guide subsequent exercise prescription.

The control group will undertake an 8 week traditional resistance training exercise regime to improve strength and aerobic fitness. The trainers providing the training regime to the control group will not have access to their movement quality assessment information, and will not be targeting improvements in movement quality.

Each exercise regime will consist of 2 sessions per week, lasting 60 minutes each session, for a total time commitment of 16 hours per participant over 8 weeks. Every session, for both the intervention and control group, will be one-on-one with a trainer. These sessions will be performed at The University of South Australia's City East Campus Gym facility.

The training performed on both the control and intervention group will be made progressively more challenging by incorporating the principle of progressive overload (increments of 2-10% weekly). All training will be supervised by accredited exercise trainers. The sessions will be performed at a moderate to vigorous intensity, with sessional RPE being set to 8-9 (in accordance to a 10 point scale).

All sessions will be recorded to provide information on the exercises performed each session, with the loads used for those exercises. The programs will be structured in accordance the ACSM guidelines for exercise prescription, in which each core muscle group will be trained for 3 sets of 8-12 repetitions per session. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>This study will use a traditional resistance training regime (based upon the principals of the ACSM guidelines for exercise prescription) as the control group. This group will not receive any information from their baseline movement quality assessment.

Based upon these recommendations, each individual in the control group will be performing resistance training using a full body training program, 2 times per week. Each major muscle group of the body (eg. legs, shoulders, chest, back, abdomen, and hips) will be trained each session. There will be at least 48 hours between each session (eg. Monday and Wednesday, Monday and Thursday, Tuesday, and Thursday, Tuesday and Friday, Wednesday and Friday). Compound movements using free weights will be prioritized over machine based and isolation exercises. Exercise progression and selection within this framework will be up to the discretion of the trainers.


</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in movement quality as assessed by the movement quality assessment tool MovementSCREEN PRO 'Trademark' (score range from 0-100 points, measured as a percentage)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3 repetition maximum trap bar deadlift (measured in kilograms) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3 repetition maximum high bench row (measured in kilograms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3 repetition maximum bench press (measured in kilograms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Single leg hop distance (measured in centimetres)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>vertical jump height (measured in centimeters)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>broad jump distance (measured in centimeters)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal oxygen uptake as estimated by the Chester step test (reported in ml/kg/min)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post intervention (at the completion of the 8 week training period)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People will be eligible for participation if they are considered low risk in accordance with the Exercise and Sports Science Australia (ESSA) adult pre-exercise screening tool.  Participants will be excluded if they have any barriers restricting their ability to perform vigorous physical activity, such as pre-existing injury or inadequate time to commit to the intervention.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Are classified as moderate or high risk in accordance with the Exercise and Sports Science Australia (ESSA) adult pre-exercise screening tool.
Have barriers restricting their ability to perform vigorous physical activity, such as pre-existing injury or inadequate time to commit to the intervention.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will not be made aware as to whether they have been placed in the intervention or control group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised into one of the two groups using minimisation to balance the groups for age, gender, and current exercise training status. Randomisation and allocation to treatment will be performed by an investigator in a separate building who is not involved in the intervention, data collection or statistical analysis. The primary outcome measure will be undertaken by an independent researcher. The secondary outcomes will be undertaken by the lead investigator due to funding and resource constraints.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Groups will be balanced for age, gender, and current exercise training status.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Treatment effectiveness analysis will be blinded and by intention-to-treat. Continuous data will be explored for normality to satisfy assumptions for parametric statistical analyses. The differences
between groups for primary and secondary outcomes will be assessed using a linear mixed effects model, with intervention group, time and the interaction between these two entered as independent variables. In case of significant missing data, sensitivity analysis will be conducted using imputation where reasonable. A secondary analysis will be conducted to assess the influence of training adherence (as measured by attendance and session completion) on training outcomes. Effect sizes and 95% confidence intervals for the primary and secondary outcomes will also be presented. The level of significance for analyses will be set at p &lt;0.05. Statistical analyses will be performed using Stata software (v14, Statacorp, TX).

A set of pre-specified analyses to investigate potential mechanisms for changes in movement quality and physical performance will be performed. Univariate correlations and separate multiple regression models will be used to explore the relationship between the baseline scores and changes in movement quality as measured by MovementSCREEN (independent variable) and changes in physical performance (dependent variables). Standard assumptions and checks for regression will be followed for all analyses, which will be conducted in STATA (Statacorp, TX, USA).

A total of 60 participants (30 per group) will provide 80% power to detect a difference at a two-sided 0.05 significance level, of 0.8 times the standard deviation, allowing for 13% dropout.   There are no pre-existing data on intervention effect sizes from movement quality training specific to that being tested in this study. Therefore, the calculation was performed considering the best available intervention effect size from previous research (Bodden et al 2015), and we have conservatively taken a smaller effect size for this trial.
Recruitment
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5001 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences.
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001
Australia.
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences.
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001
Australia.
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Corrective Exercise Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Corrective Exercise Australia
9 Kensington Rd 
Norwood SA 5067
Australia.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Corrective Exercise Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Corrective Exercise Australia
9 Kensington Rd 
Norwood SA 5067
Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Movement quality has been described as an individuals ability to perform a specific movement pattern in an optimal manner. Poor movement quality is typified by the inability to perform basic, or
fundamental, movement tasks in a balanced and well-coordinated manner, which is underpinned by a disruption to the way muscles normally move and support joints during these movement tasks. Poor
movement quality has been shown to significantly alter the loading of individual joints, reduce an individuals ability to express strength and power, and limit the ability to complete movement tasks effectively. Conversely, good movement quality has been said to allow the safe and effective loading of joints, subsequently improving performance capabilities. The assessment of movement quality is therefore said to provide an indication of muscular dysfunction.

We suggest that this information can then be used to design an appropriate exercise intervention targeting improvements in that dysfunction, and therefore improvements in movement quality.

The proposed research will look to see whether a specific training intervention can yield improvements in movement quality and physical performance, and whether those improvements occur to a greater degree in comparison to a more traditional resistance training program. 

To achieve these aims, healthy adults (18-55 y) will undergo 1 of 2 interventions, either 1) an individualized exercise intervention guided by a movement quality assessment, or 2) a standard resistance training program in accordance to the ACSM guidelines. Each training protocol will involve 2 60 minute training sessions per week, for a duration of 8 weeks. Primary (movement quality score) and secondary (physical performance measures) outcome measures will be recorded at baseline, and at the completion of the 8 week intervention.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia's Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences.
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001
Australia.
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000036267</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hunter Bennett</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences.
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61433377222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hunter.bennett@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hunter Bennett</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences.
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61433377222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hunter.bennett@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hunter Bennett</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences.
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61433377222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hunter.bennett@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hunter Bennett</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
School of Health Sciences.
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61433377222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hunter.bennett@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>