<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368042">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000254594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of spinal cord stimulation on weekly step count of patients with back and leg pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of spinal cord stimulation on weekly step count of patients with back and leg pain
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-4985 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>SCS Activity Monitoring</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Back and leg pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Spinal cord stimulation (SCS) is used to treat patients with long term nerve pain by applying an electrical current to the spinal cord or peripheral nerves. This is done via small metal contacts called electrodes which are fixed to a cable called a lead. When a pain specialist wants to use a spinal cord stimulator in a patient, the patient has a surgical operation to put one or more leads into the body. These leads are then connected to an external battery which is worn by a patient using a belt. After a trial period lasting 1-2 weeks, the effectiveness of the stimulation is assessed and if the trial deemed successful a permanent system is implanted.

The stimulators will be programmed by company technicians as per manufacturer guidelines. 

Participants will wear a Vivofit (Garmin Ltd) fitness band for 2 weeks before and 1-2 weeks after insertion of the spinal cord stimulator leads.

Patient data from the Vivofit monitor, walking tests and questionnaire responses will be collected during the routine twice weekly outpatient clinic visits used to monitor the clinical progress of the trial of stimulation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patient acts as own control pre and post spinal cord stimulator lead results will be compared.

The primary endpoint will be comparing Vivofit baseline (pre institution of neurostimulation therapy) total step count for 1 week prior to lead insertion to weekly total step count in the last week of the trial. 

Secondary endpoints will compare Vivofit baseline step counts, sleep and activity patterns to self-report questionnaires (BPI, Dass21, ESS, PCS, PSEQ, SF36, OSW), TUG, 6MWT, in addition to medication usage at the same time points.
</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in weekly daily step count before and after insertion stimulator leads. Data will uploaded from the Vivofit fitness band by a research assistant at  twice weekly routine clinic visits to monitor clinical progress. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Back and leg pain as assessed using the BPI questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, anxiety and stress as assessed using the DASS21 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleepiness as assessed using the ESS questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Catastrophising as assessed using the PCS questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy as assessed using the PSEQ questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before trial lead insertion v last week of trial leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical and mental health as assessed using the SF36 questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Back and leg pain as assessed using the OSW questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility as assessed using the TUG test</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional exercise capacity as assessed using the 6MWT</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>medication usage will be recorded at baseline and trial on the concomitant medication (ConMed) worksheet.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline week before lead insertion v last week of leads before implant/removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Patients with chronic, intractable back pain, with or without radicular symptoms to one or both legs (with or without prior back surgery) indicated for spinal cord stimulation trial (post spine surgery, neuropathic pain)  
- Is a new or existing patient of Frankston Pain Management, Frankston Hospital pain medicine or PainCare clinics
- Has chronic, intractable pain
- Appropriate clinical diagnosis
- Positive psychological evaluation
- No pending lawsuit or economic compensation related to the pain
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>patients who are contraindicated from receiving a spinal cord stimulator, 
are likely to be non-compliant or 
dont want to participate. 

Specific criteria for exclusion include:
-	Patients for dorsal root ganglion stimulation
-	Patients having full system implanted without prior period of trial stimulation
-	Inability to give informed consent, 
-	Inability to understand English (most pain assessment tools are validated for English language speakers only),
-	Contraindicated for spinal cord stimulation; i.e.: are unable to operate the SCS system, are poor surgical risks, are pregnant 
-	Non-compliance with stimulator usage and/or stimulation parameter settings
-	Unable to wear activity monitor on wrist
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This is a first time study to compare a new method of outcome evaluation with standard clinical evaluation.  

The expected outcome is that 40 patients will allow for a degree of correlation to be established between the 2 measurement methods at each stage of assessment.  The degree and nature of any correlation will form the basis for a larger study based on the information gained from this pilot.  

Power calculations 
We are planning a study with 40 subjects.  Prior data indicate that the difference in the response of matched pairs is normally distributed with standard deviation 3000 steps.  We will be able to detect a true difference in the mean response of matched pairs of -1363.081 or 1363.081 steps with probability (power) 0.8.   The Type I error probability associated with this test of the null hypothesis that this response difference is zero is 0.05.

Statistical methodology
Primary endpoint analysis
The change in step count will be assessed using student paired T-test with each individuals before and after scores.

Secondary endpoints analysis
The data will be analysed using Wilcoxon Rank sum test or Pearson correlation coefficient, subject to data meeting the appropriate criteria as gathered.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Frankston Hospital - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Beleura Private Hospital - Mornington</hospital>
    <hospital>Bethesda Hospital - Claremont</hospital>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>3931 - Mornington</postcode>
    <postcode>6010 - Claremont</postcode>
    <postcode>6011 - Cottesloe</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Murray Taverner</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Frankston Pain management
Suite 7, 20 Clarendon Street
Frankston, Victoria 3199</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Boston Scientific</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 332
Botany  NSW,  1455</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Jude Medical</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>650 Lorimer St
Port Melbourne Vic 3207</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr John Salmon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PainCare
2/89 Forest Street 
Cottesloe WA  6011</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr John Monagle</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Frankston Pain Management
Suite 7, 20 Clarendon Street
Frankston, Vic, 3199</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>General activity level in patients being considered for spinal stimulation and the improvement in activity levels after stimulator insertion have not been documented and both are unknown. 

In this study physical activity measurements, as measured by the Garmin Vivofit device, will be compared to usual questionnaires that you complete for assessment of pain, pain relief and functional improvement before and after the insertion of spinal cord stimulator leads.

This study involves wearing a wrist band (Vivofit, Garmin Ltd) for 2 weeks before and 1-2 weeks after the insertion of the spinal cord stimulator lead.

The primary endpoint will be comparing Vivofit baseline (pre institution of neurostimulation therapy) total step count for 1 week prior to lead insertion to weekly total step count in the last week of the trial of stimulation.

Secondary endpoints will compare Vivofit baseline step counts to self-report questionnaires (BPI, Dass21, ESS, PCS, PSEQ, SF36, OSW), TUG, 6MWT, in addition to medication usage at the same time points.
 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peninsula Health </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 52 
Frankston, Vic, 3199
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/PH/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Murray Taverner</name>
      <address>Frankston Pain Management
Suite 7, 20 Clarendon Street
Frankston, Vic, 3199</address>
      <phone>+61397700522</phone>
      <fax>+61397700944</fax>
      <email>mtaverner@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Adeline Taverner</name>
      <address>Frankston Pain Management
Suite 7, 20 Clarendon Street
Frankston, Vic, 3199</address>
      <phone>+61397700522</phone>
      <fax>+61397700944</fax>
      <email>info@fpmx.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Murray Taverner</name>
      <address>Frankston Pain Management
Suite 7, 20 Clarendon Street
Frankston, Vic, 3199</address>
      <phone>+61397700522</phone>
      <fax>+61397700944</fax>
      <email>mtaverner@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Murray Taverner</name>
      <address>Frankston Pain Management
7/20 Clarendon Street
Frankston, Vic, 3199</address>
      <phone>+61397700522</phone>
      <fax>+61397700944</fax>
      <email>mtaverner@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>