<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362369">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000435886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Local Warming versus Local Cooling on Injection Pain After Propofol Administration During Anaesthesia Induction</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Local Warming versus Local Cooling on Injection Pain After Propofol Administration During Anaesthesia Induction in those Scheduled for Elective Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>propofol injection pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After obtaining local research ethical committee approval and patients informed written consent, 120 patients were studied between age groups of 18 and 65 years old, of ASA groups I and III, and who were scheduled for elective surgery under general anesthesia . The exclusion criteria were; being  pregnant and breastfeeding women, having a medical history of epilepsy, having cardiac conduction failure,having lipid metabolism disorder, receiving  antiarrhytmic or analgesic drugs, having  liver or kidney failure, being  allergic to propofol and  difficulty for iv cannulation.
Without any  premedication, the patients  were  given, 5 ml/kg/hour crystalloid solution, through a 20 G iv cannule which is attached on the dorsum of the hand. Patients in the operation room were monitored for; standard electrocardiography (ECG), blood pressure non invasively and peripheral oxygen saturation (Drager;Infinity delta MS13466E539D,USA). The patients were randomly allocated, using sealed envelopes, to one of following 3 groups of 40 each: 
1.	Local warming group , (Group I):  Before anesthesia induction patients were  subjected to 40 degrees C hot application for 2 minutes with a bair hugger device (a device blowing hot air through a blanket to be worn over the body), through the vein trace which the cannula were  attached. 
2.	Local cooling group (Group II):  Before anesthesia induction patients were subjected to +2-4 degrees C cooling application for 2 minutes with cold water bags kept  in refrigerator, through the  infusion vein trace.  
3.	No intervention group (Group III): Patients in this group were accepted as control group and were not subjected to any procedure.
Propofol prepared  in room temperature (10 mg/ml ampoule, Fresenius) were  administered  as  2,5 mg/kg dose and  within one minute to all  groups. On the 15th second with the start of injection,  the patients were asked about suffering any  pain. Findings observed until the injection finished and the response was recorded according to the 5-point Verbal Rating Scale (VRS) (0= no pain, 1= mild pain, 2= moderate pain, 3= severe pain, 4= severe pain accompanied by facial grimacing and arm withdrawal).. After propofol injection, opioid and muscle relaxant (only for patients who will be intubated) were given Then  the operation  progressed  with  an intubation  or a laryngeal  mask. Hemodynamics were  measured and recorded at control (T0), 1.(T1), 2.(T2), 3.(T3) minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>In Group III (Control); no intervention was applied.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the effect of local warming and cooling on pain induced by propofol.Findings observed until the injection finished and the response was recorded according to the 5-point Verbal Rating Scale (VRS) (0= no pain, 1= mild pain, 2= moderate pain, 3= severe pain, 4= severe pain accompanied by facial grimacing and arm withdrawal).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients were asked about any discomfort at the 15th seconds of injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in hemodynamics; patients in the operation room were monitored for; standard electrocardiography (ECG), blood pressure non invasively for measurement of the hemodynamic variables</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hemodynamic variables were  measured and recorded at control (T0), 1.(T1), 2.(T2), 3.(T3) minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ASA groups I and III, and who were scheduled for elective surgery under general anesthesia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Being  pregnant and breastfeeding women, having a medical history of epilepsy, having cardiac conduction failure,having lipid metabolism disorder, receiving  antiarrhytmic or analgesic drugs, having  liver or kidney failure, being  allergic to propofol and  difficulty for iv cannulation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After obtaining written informed consent , the patients were randomly assigned to one of the three groups as the responsible anesthesiologist opened the next envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>114</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Serdar Koseoglu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ministry of Health, Ankara Training and Research Hospital, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, Ulucanlar Cad. 06340, Ankara, Turkey</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose: Various drugs and techniques have been proposed in order to prevent propofol induced pain. Local warming or warming of propofol has been reported to be effective in reducing the pain but local cooling has not been studied yet. In this study we aimed to investigate the effect of local warming and cooling on pain induced by propofol.

Materials and methods: One hundred and twenty patients undergoing elective surgery were included in this randomized, prospective, single-blinded study. Patients were divided into 3 equal groups. In Group I; warming at + 40 degrees C applied for 2 min prior to propofol administration at the site venous access, in Group II; cooling at + 4 degrees C was applied for 2 min prior to propofol administration at the site venous access. In Group III (Control); no intervention was applied. In each patient, propofol was injected over a period of 1 min at a dose of 2,5 mg/kg. Patients were asked about any discomfort at the 15th seconds of injection. Findings observed until the injection finished and the response was recorded according to the 5-point scale.  
Results: Demographic data were comparable between groups. The frequency of pain at propofol injection was lower in Group I (47.5%) compared to Group II (77.5%) and III (82.5%)  (p= 0.006),( p = &lt;0,001) The frequency of pain did not differ statistically between Group II and III. 
Conclusions: Application of local warming prior to propofol administration effectively decreased the pain induced by propofol, whereas local cooling had no impact.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ministry of Health, Ankara Training and Research Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health, Ankara Training and Research Hospital, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, Ulucanlar Cad. 06340, Ankara, Turkey</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/08/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hale Yarkan Uysal</name>
      <address>Ministry of Health, Ankara Training and Research Hospital, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, Ulucanlar Cad. 06340, Ankara, Turkey</address>
      <phone>+903125953175</phone>
      <fax>+903123633396</fax>
      <email>haleuysal@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hale Yarkan Uysal</name>
      <address>Ministry of Health, Ankara Training and Research Hospital, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, Ulucanlar Cad. 06340, Ankara, Turkey</address>
      <phone>+903125953175</phone>
      <fax>+903123633396</fax>
      <email>haleuysal@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hale Yarkan Uysal</name>
      <address>Ministry of Health, Ankara Training and Research Hospital, Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care, Ulucanlar Cad. 06340, Ankara, Turkey</address>
      <phone>+903125953175</phone>
      <fax>+903123633396</fax>
      <email>haleuysal@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>