<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343275">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000806965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to find out if the drug Vessel Dilator is absorbed from an injection under the skin and, whether it improves heart function in people diagnosed with chronic heart failure and a moderate degree of kidney function loss.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of subcutaneously administered vessel dilator peptide in stable patients with chronic heart failure and moderate renal impairment.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-2828</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Made02
The Sponsor - Madeleine Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Renal Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will receive the Study Drug, Vessel Dilator peptide ('VSDL' or Atrial Natriuretic Peptide (ANP)[31-67]).
A lead group of 2 patients will receive a single dose of 250 microgram on day 1 and 500 microgram on Day 2 by subcutaneous bolus.  Following review of pharmacokinetic and safety data, a further 6 patients will receive the same doses or up to 2 fold higher if plasma concentrations from the lead group were insufficient to characterise the concentration-time profile.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics of vessel dilator peptide following subcutaneous administration in stable patients with chronic heart failure.
Pharmacokinetic parameters Cmax, Tmax, AUC, CL/F, Vz/F and t1/2 will be determined by standard non-compartmental methods.  Cmax and Tmax will be taken directly from the observed data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On each of the two dosing days (Day 1 &amp; Day 2):
Blood samples are taken for VSDL assay at -5 minutes pre dose and post dose at 10, 20, 30, 45, 60 min and at hours 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 18, 24.
Continuous urine collections for measurements of VSDL assay at 0-6, 6-12 and12-24h are collected.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the tolerability and non-invasive haemodynamics of vessel dilator peptide following subcutaneous administration in stable patients with chronic heart failure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On each of the two dosing days (Day 1 &amp; Day 2):
Non invasive BP, HR, respiratory rate, temperature and pulse oximetry will be assessed (using a Philips Intellivue MP5 Bedside Monitor) pre dose and then every 10 mins for first hour post dose, 15 minutely until 4 hours, 30 minutely to 8 hours, then 2 hourly to 14 hours post dose and again at hour 24 and, approximately 1 week post-dosing.
ECGs will be collected pre dose (within 30 minutes of dose administration) and at hour 24 post dose and, approximately 1 week post-dosing.
Transthoracic echocardiography (using a Philips IE33 machine) will be performed to measure estimated EF% (3D and 2D Simpson's), systolic and diastolic strain estimation (speckle tracking, E/E' and tissue doppler) and estimates of PA pressure (PA acceleration time, TR jet peak velocity) at predose (within 1 hour of dose administration) and at hours 2,4 and 6 post dose on each study day.
NT pro-BNP and Troponin will be assessed at baseline, 24 and 48 hours and, approximately 1 week post-dosing.
Biochemistry and a Full Blood Count will be assessed at hour 6 and hour 24 (including CK-MB) post dose on Day 1 and Day 2 and, approximately 1 week post dosing.
Physical examination will be performed one week after dosing.
Monitoring for Adverse Events, for example, hypotension, at all time-points throughout the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the pharmacokinetic results when the plasma samples are assessed by radio immunoassay compared to LC/MS/MS assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On each of the two dosing days (Day 1 &amp; Day 2):
Blood samples are taken for VSDL assay at -5 minutes pre dose and post dose at 10, 20, 30, 45, 60 min and at hours 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 18, 24.
Continuous urine collections for measurements of VSDL assay at 0-6, 6-12 and12-24h are collected.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether vessel dilator peptide has effects on renal function as assessed by changes in plasma creatinine and a panel of renal safety biomarkers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On each of the two dosing days (Day 1 &amp; Day 2):
Biochemistry and a Full Blood Count will be assessed at hour 6 and hour 24 (including CK-MB) post dose on Day 1 and Day 2 and, approximately 1 week post dosing.
Continuous urine collections for measurements of urine creatinine, Na+, K+ and renal safety biomarkers (Kidney Injury Molecule -1; Neutrophil Gelatinase Lipocalin) at 0-6, 6-12 and12-24h will be collected. Urine volume will also be recorded to observe for urine volume reduction. Urinalysis and Biomarkers will be assessed at Baseline, 24 hours and, approximately 1 week post dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients with a history of stable, symptomatic chronic heart failure, with a left ventricular ejection fraction of less than or equal to 45% measured by echocardiogram or nuclear imaging (measurement within 90 days prior to screening).
2. Signed Informed Consent.
3. Aged 18 years or older.
4. Non-pregnant females, as evidenced by serum pregnancy test at screening and negative urine pregnancy test pre dose at Day 1 (for women of child bearing potential only). Women of child bearing potential must agree to use a medically acceptable method of contraception (as determined by the Investigator) for the entire study duration. Females of non child bearing potential are defined as having amenorrhea for at least 2 years prior to study entry or have been surgically sterilized.
5. GFR greater than or equal to 25 ml/min/1.73m2 and less than 70 ml/min/1.73 m2(MDRD method).
6. Patients on a stable (defined as no alteration to dose/type/frequency within the previous 6 weeks), background therapeutic doses of a beta-blocker, ACE-I or ARB, unless contraindicated and documented as such.
7. Patients on a stable (defined as no alteration to dose/type/frequency within the previous 6 weeks) background therapeutic dose of a diuretic and/or aldosterone receptor inhibitor (e.g. spironolactone) unless contraindicated and documented as such.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Evidence of myocardial infarction (MI) or high risk acute coronary syndrome within past 6 weeks, as determined by creatinine kinase (CK)/creatinine kinase a muscle-brain isoenzyme (CK-MB) greater than or equal to 3 times upper limit of normal (as defined by Institute of Medical and Veterinary Science (IMVS) or elevation of troponin T at baseline &gt;0.1.
2. Evidence of Acute MI (ST elevation and/or elevation of Troponin T), as determined by a 12-lead ECG. 
3. Hypotension (Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP)&lt;90 mmHg), cardiogenic shock, volume depletion or any other clinical condition that would contraindicate administration of an agent with potent vasodilatory effects. 
4. Persistent, uncontrolled hypertension (SBP&gt;180 mm Hg).
5. Presence of any Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) contra-indication (includes Permanent Pacemaker (PPM), cerebral aneurysm clips).
6. Congenital heart defects.
7. Cardiac surgery within past 4 weeks 
8. Severe valvular heart disease: aortic stenosis (AS), idiopathic hypertrophic subaortic stenosis (IHSS), hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy (HOCM), acute aortic Incompetence (AI) or mitral regurgitation (MR). 
9. History of cerebrovascular accident within past 4 weeks. 
10. Acute or chronic active infection, including pneumonia and urinary tract infection.
11. Significant renal impairment as determined by a creatinine clearance of &lt;25 ml/min/1.73 m2 (MDRD).
12. Presence of hepatic impairment (defined as ALP, ALT, AST, GGT, Bilirubin  &gt;2x ULN) and/or the presence of ascites.
13. Other clinically significant findings on any of the screening laboratory tests, as determined by the Investigator, including but not limited to: hyponatremia, hyperkalaemia, acidosis, anaemia (defined as Hb &lt;9g/dL).
14. Diagnosis of SIADH, Addisons disease or renal salt wasting disease.
15. Receipt of Investigational Drug within 30 days of screening or current enrolment in a clinical trial. 
16. History of clinically significant drug or alcohol abuse within the past 12 months  as judged by the Investigator.
17. History of renal or cardiac transplantation. 
18. Insufficient venous access. 
19. History of current malignancy or malignancy requiring chemotherapy/radiotherapy within 2 years of enrolment.
20. History of nephrotic syndrome or clinically significant proteinuria.
21. Known history of infection with Hepatitis C, B or HIV.
22. Use of NSAIDS.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients with stable chronic heart failure will be recruited from outpatient cardiology sources, as coordinated by the Principal Investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study is a within-patient dose escalation, adaptive design.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/12/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Madeleine Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 1474
Mount Barker
SA 5251</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Madeleine Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1474
Mount Barker
SA 5251</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to find out if the drug Vessel Dilator (VSDL) is absorbed from an injection under the skin and whether it improves heart function in people diagnosed
with stable chronic heart failure and a moderate degree of kidney function loss. additionally, the study will find out if Vessel Dilator has effects on kidney function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>No trial related citations for this study, not published as yet.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>110828</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/07/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Stephen Worthley</name>
      <address>Cardiovascular Investigation Unit
Level 6, Theatre Block
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5608</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2454</fax>
      <email>stephen.worthley@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Christine Edwards</name>
      <address>SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8168 4511</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8128 4004</fax>
      <email>christine.edwards@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Christine Edwards</name>
      <address>SAHMRI
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8128 4511</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8128 4004</fax>
      <email>christine.edwards@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Worthley</name>
      <address>Cardiovascular Investigation Unit Level 6, Theatre Block Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5608	</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.worthley@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>