<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335818">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/12/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001064099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Paramedic Assessment and Referral to Access Medical care at Home</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate the cost and acceptability of paramedic referral to a home-based treatment service compared with transport to hospital for people with a low-risk injury or illness who call an ambulance.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PARAMed Home</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low risk injury suitable for home care (Low risk mechanism of injury with no apparent sequelae or only minor apparent injury. Examples: soft tissue injury; simple laceration; single limb fracture excluding the femur).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low risk infection suitable for home care (Uncomplicated infection in a well immunocompetent patient. Examples: below knee unilateral leg cellulitis; wound infection; flu-like illness; gastroenteritis.)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low risk hardware complication suitable for home treatment (Simple hardware complications. Examples: IDC, NGT, PEG change/replacement).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Paramedics will assess for suitability for home care following agreed inclusion and exclusion criteria and will confirm this with the call centre which will provide randomisation. Those randomised to the treatment arm will be referred by the paramedic to the home-based treatment by home hospital team instead of the standard care which is to transport to hospital. The paramedic will provide a clinical assessment, a telephone  handover, and clinical documentation which stays with the patient until the home hospital team arrives within 4 hours. The paramedic will also ensure clinical stability and safety and inform participants that they can call the ambulance again if they are concerned prior to the arrival of the home hospital team. Recruitment into the trial will take place over a 6 month period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Paramedic transport to hospital emergency department (standard treatment)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-benefit: the costs of healthcare provision for that episode of care. 

Costs will be measured through fixed costs (total equipment costs will be sourced from St John Ambulance, Western Australia and Silver Chain Nursing Association and will be depreciated over the life of the equipment giving annual costs) and variable costs (labour costs for the Home Hospital program service provided as per recorded time sheets and hourly appropriate Silver Chain salary rates and paramedic training costs sourced from St John Ambulance Australia WA Inc.).

Benefits will be measured through ambulance usage (average ambulance transport cost via St John Ambulance Australia WA Inc. applied to the difference between usage for the control and intervention groups), hospital separations (daily average hospital cost (from WA Department of Health annual reports or similar) applied to the difference between lengths of stay for the control and intervention groups), emergency department visits (average emergency department visit cost from WA Department of Health annual reports or similar applied to the difference between visits for the control and intervention groups).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months from the start of the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction will be assessed through the use of a telephone survey. Participants will be asked to report on satisfaction with the timeliness of the services, the explanation received, the care received, convenience of the service, follow up arrangements, staff attitudes and overall service. They will also be asked about their perception of safety within the service, perception of adequate diagnosis and symptom relief, and their preference for treatment at hospital or home hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month from the start of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety will be assessed through the number of unplanned presentations to primary care services and hospital, adverse events and mortality in the month following the intervention. Information on safety will be obtained through hospital, Silver Chain and St John Ambulance records and the patient telephone questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months from the start of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clinical inclusion: low risk injury, uncomplicated infection in immunocompetent patient, or medical equipment complication (eg. blocked catheter).

Capable of providing informed consent or is cognitively impaired and has the support of a parent/guardian/carer/relative who agrees to his/her participation.

Medicare eligible</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not at own residence at time of call-out, lives in an unsafe environment or lives alone.

&gt;22 wks pregnant

Abnormal vital signs

Pain requiring narcotics

Safe and suitable to wait up to 4 hours for the arrival of the home hospital team</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>If the patient meets the inclusion criteria and has no exclusion criteria, the paramedic will obtain informed consent for the trial. On confirmation of written informed consent, the paramedic contacts the call centre to be given the computerised randomisation. Data collected is based on intention to treat.

Participants have a 50/50 chance of being in the intervention or control arm. There is allocation concealment as the paramedic is unaware of the randomisation outcome.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation is performed at the call centre.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Moira Sim</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Systems Intervention Research Centre for Health
Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>State Health Research Advisory Council, Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>C/o Research Development Unit 
Department of Health Western Australia
PO Box 8172, 
Perth Business Centre, WA 6849</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Glenn Arendts</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Western Australian Institute for Medical Research
University of Western Australia
Level 5 &amp; 6, MRF Building
Rear 50 Murray Street
PERTH WA 6000
AUSTRALIA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>St John Ambulance WA Inc</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 183 
BELMONT WA 6984</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Silver Chain</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Silver Chain House
6 Sundercombe Street
Osborne Park WA 6017</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will compare treatment at home versus treatment in hospital for low-risk conditions. We wish to find out if treatment at home is better/worse/same in terms of clinical outcomes, acceptability to patients and healthcare costs.

The hypotheses tested are that a pathway for paramedic referral of patients to a home-based treatment service for community management of low-acuity injury or illness will:
a) lead to clinical outcomes that are equivalent to ED based care;
b) have a cost benefit, reducing the costs of healthcare provision for that episode of care; and
c) be acceptable to patients and meet high levels of patient satisfaction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Edith Cowan University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5249 SIM</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Health Western Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1st Floor, C block
189 Royal St
East Perth 6004
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/11/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010/45</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Silver Chain Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>6 Sundercombe St
Osborne Park 6017
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/11/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC App 066</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Moira Sim</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University 
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 63043504</phone>
      <fax>+618 63042323</fax>
      <email>m.sim@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Moira Sim</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University 
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 63043504</phone>
      <fax>+618 63042323</fax>
      <email>m.sim@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Moira Sim</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University 
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup 6027
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+618 63043504</phone>
      <fax>+618 63042323</fax>
      <email>m.sim@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>