<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370877">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000819426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A parent-delivered intervention for infants with social and communication delay</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating the efficacy of a parent-mediated behavioural intervention for mitigating autistic symptom severity among infants with social and  communication delay</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-0848 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>The Australian Infant Communication and Engagement Study (AICES)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Developmental Language Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Learning disabilities</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention, called iBASIS-VIPP (Green et al.,, 2013; 2015), focuses on enriching social and communication exchanges between an infant and their caregiver. The manualised intervention will be delivered in family homes by a Research Therapist (Speech Pathologist/Psychologist). One parent will be asked to participate in all of the therapy sessions. They will receive 10 X 1.5-2 hours sessions over five months.  During therapy sessions, parent and infant are videotaped during daily interactions. Video feedback provides the opportunity to focus the caregivers attention on the infants communicative signals and expressions, thereby stimulating skills for observing and empathising with the child. Core methods include:(1) a focus on the communicative aspects of the particular parent-infant dyad; (2) viewing successful excerpts from videotaped interactions, providing positive examples of sensitive parenting; and (3) involvement of a trained therapist to frame observations to assist self-reflection, and to focus behavioural change. Intervention content focusses on enhancing parental observation, attributing communicative intent to infant behaviours that may be difficult to interpret, and facilitating responses that will build infant interaction. To this foundation, we have added components that have been tested in our previous ASD intervention studies, focusing on promoting early social communication skills, such as joint attention and turn-taking. Parents will also be asked to undertake 30-mins daily home practice in interacting with their infant using the newly learned skills, and document the quantity of home practice they undertake. As with the Treatment as Usual group, we will also quantify and qualify any contact the families have with other health professionals.

References: 
Green J, Wan M, Guiraud J, Holsgrove S, McNally J, Slonims V, et al. Intervention for infants at risk of developing autism. J Autism Dev Disord. 2013;43(11):2502-14.
Green J, Charman T, Pickles A, Wan MW, Slonims V, et al. Parent-mediated intervention versus no intervention for infants at high risk of autism. Lancet Psychiatr. 2(2):133-40.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Families in the "treatment as usual" group will receive current treatment protocol offered within the community, which may comprise a 'parent information workshop', the provision of reading material on infant development, or developmental monitoring. Within the "treatment as usual" group, we will quantify all contact with health professionals by asking parents to complete a monthly diary. We will also quantify the nature of this contact by directly contacting the health professional(s) involved.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Autism Observation Scale for Infants (AOSI) will be used to measure the severity of autistic symptoms. 
Method of Assessment: Researcher-administered semi-structured play assessment with infant. Scored from video by researcher with demonstrated high level reliability, who is blind to treatment group. 

Reference: 
Bryson S, Zwaigenbaum L, McDermott C, Rombough V, Brian J. The Autism Observation Scale for Infants: Scale development and reliability data. J Autism Dev Disord. 2008;38(4):731-8.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment will occur within 2 weeks of ascertaining study eligibility. 

The primary outcome will be assessed at: 
Follow-up assessment 1 (6 months post-baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Toddler Module of the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule  Second Edition (ADOS-2) will be used to measure the severity of autistic symptoms. 
Method of Assessment: Researcher-administered semi-structured play assessment with toddler. Scored from video by researcher with demonstrated high level reliability, who is blind to treatment group.

Reference: 
Luyster R, Gotham K, Guthrie W, Coffing M, Petrak R, Pierce K, et al. The Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule - Toddler Module. J Autism Dev Disord 2009;39(9):1305-20.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment will occur within 2 weeks of ascertaining study eligibility. 

This secondary outcome will be assessed at: 
Follow-up Assessment 2 (12 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assesment 3 (18 months post-Baseline Assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Manchester Assessment of Caregiver-Infant Interaction (MACI) will be used to measure the quality of parent-infant interactions. 
Method of Assessment: Parent-Infant free play interaction sample. Scored from video by researcher with demonstrated high level reliability, who is blind to treatment group.

Reference: 
Wan MW, Brooks A, Green J, Abel K, Elmadih A. Psychometrics and validation of a brief rating measure of parent-infant interaction: Manchester assessment of caregiverinfant interaction. International Journal of Behavioral Development. 2016.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment will occur within 2 weeks of ascertaining study eligibility. 

This secondary outcome will be assessed at: 
Follow-up Assessment 1 (6 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assessment 2 (12 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assesment 3 (18 months post-Baseline Assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Mullen Scales of Early Learning (MSEL)  will be used to assessed general developmental ability 
Method of Assessment: Researcher-administered standardised developmental assessment.
Scored live by researcher administering the assessment.

Reference: 
Mullen EM. Mullens scales of early learning. Circle Pines, MN: American Guidance Service;1995.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline assessment will occur within 2 weeks of ascertaining study eligibility. 

This secondary outcome will be assessed at: 
Follow-up Assessment 1 (6 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assessment 2 (12 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assesment 3 (18 months post-Baseline Assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales  2nd edition (VABS-II) will be used to assess daily functional skills. 
Method of Assessment: Parent-report standardized questionnaire, scored by researcher.

Reference: 
Sparrow SS, Cicchettii DV, Balla DA. The Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales, 2nd Edition (VABS-II). NCS Pearson Inc. 2005. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up Assessment 1 (6 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assessment 2 (12 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assesment 3 (18 months post-Baseline Assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The MacArthur-Bates Communicative Development Inventory (MCDI) will be used to assess early language development.
Method of Assessment: Parent-report questionnaire, scored by researcher.

Reference: 
Fenson L, Dale PS,  Reznick JS. The MacArthur Communicative Development Inventories: Users Guide and Technical Manual. San Diego, CA: Singular Publishing Group; 1993.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up Assessment 1 (6 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assessment 2 (12 months post-Baseline Assessment)
Follow-up Assesment 3 (18 months post-Baseline Assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants will be offered participation in this trial if they:
(a)	Are between 9 and 14 months of age; 
(b)	Endorsement of three or more of the key items on the 12-month old SACS-R screening questionnaire (Barbaro &amp; Dissanayake, 2010): absent/atypical pointing, waving, imitation, eye contact, response to name.
(c)	The primary caregiver involved in the trial speaks sufficient English to: (i) understand the requirements of the study, and (ii) is deemed to be able to participate fully in the therapy sessions.

Reference:
Barbaro J, Dissanayake C. Prospective identification of ASD in infancy and toddlerhood using developmental surveillance. J Dev Behav Pediatr. 2010;31(5):376-85</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>9</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded from the study if they meet either of the following characteristics:
(a)	The infant has a diagnosed comorbidity known to affect neurological and developmental abilities (e.g., preterm birth &lt; 32 weeks, cerebral palsy, Down syndrome, Rett syndrome, other chromosomal abnormality, hearing/visual impairment), and/or
(b)	The family does not intend to remain living in the Perth/Melbourne areas for the next two years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is at a central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Group allocation of participants will be by minimization method, stratified (with blocking) by: 

Childs age (based on age at the eligibility screen):
1.. 9 to 11 months inclusive (covers 9.00 months to 11.99 months) 
2.. 12-14 months inclusive (covers 12.00 to 14.99 months)

Sex:
1.. Male
2.. Female

SACS-R severity score:
1. Score total 3
2. Score total 4
3. Score total 5

Site: 
1. Perth
2. Melbourne</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analyzed via intention to treat by the study biostatistician. Baseline data will be examined to determine the success of randomization, comparing group mean scores on the AOSI, MACI, MSEL, VABS-II and MCDI through separate independent-samples t-tests. Lack of statistical significance for each comparison at a = .2 will imply successful randomization. Should this not be achieved, the analysis techniques described below will be modified to adjust for baseline differences.

The primary outcome will be AOSI Total Score at Follow-up Assessment 1 (infant ages: 15-20 months). Our power analyses are based on our pilot study (Green et al., Lancet Psychiatry, 2015). A sample of 66 per group provides a two-sided independent-samples t-test 85% power to detect a 0.52 SD change in AOSI Total Score from baseline to follow-up (a = .05). This represents a group difference in change scores of between 2.46 (for SD = 4.67) and 3.70 (for SD = 6.98) points. We have argued previously that a change in AOSI scores of two points or more is clinically significant (Green et al., Lancet Psychiatry, 2015), and this trial is adequately powered to detect this difference.

The secondary outcomes will be ADOS-2 Total Algorithm Score at Follow-up assessments 2 and 3. Using a two-tailed independent samples t-test with 66 participants in each group, we will have 79% power to detect a mean difference between groups of 2.5 points on the ADOS-2, with the assumption of the variability being 46% of the mean (a = .05). This a difference between a mean (SD) of 12.5 (5.7) in the Treatment as Usual Group and 10 (4.6) in the iBASIS Group (Cohens d = 0.48).

Tertiary outcome variables  MACI, MSEL, VABS-II, MCDI scores  will be assessed as change scores (baseline to each follow-up assessment) within an analysis of covariance framework, adjusting for baseline scores. An additional independent variable of interest in the Treatment as Usual group will be the number of contact hours each family has had with health professionals. Each type of service (e.g., counseling, speech pathology etc.) will be weighted and summed into a continuous measure. We will examine the distribution of this variable and determine whether a mathematic adjustment or categorization is required prior to analysis. 


Reference:
Green J, Charman T, Pickles A, Wan MW, Slonims V, et al. Parent-mediated intervention versus no intervention for infants at high risk of autism. Lancet Psychiatr. 2(2):133-40.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>9/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>132</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Telethon Kid's Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Roberts Rd, 
Subiaco WA 6008
Australia
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telethon-Perth Children's Hospital Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Western Australian State Government
Research Development Unit
Department of Health
PO Box 8172
Perth Business Centre
PERTH WA 6849
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Angela Wright-Bennett Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rokeby Centre
Suite 3, 254 Rokeby Road
Subiaco WA 6008
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University: RFA understanding Disease</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>La Trobe University
Melbourne VIC 3086
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>La Trobe University </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>La Trobe University
Melbourne VIC 3086
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is a lifelong developmental disorder affecting more than 1% of people. Social and communication therapies during early childhood are critical for promoting favourable longer-term outcomes in ASD. However, until very recently we have not had interventions tailored towards infants (&lt;14 months of age) who are at increased risk for ASD. iBASIS-VIPP is a parent-mediated intervention in which therapists use video-feedback to help parents adapt to their infants interactive styles and promote optimal social and communicative development. Previous research has also shown that the iBASIS-VIPP protocol has preliminary efficacy for improving the developmental outcomes among infants who are at high risk of developing ASD because an older sibling had the condition. The next stage of this research programme is to test the iBASIS-VIPP intervention with infants presenting to a clinical setting with ASD risk-behaviours, such as social and communication delays.

The study design is a two-site (Perth, Melbourne), two-arm (Treatment as Usual, iBASIS-VIPP'), single-blind (rater) randomized controlled trial (RCT). We will recruit 132 infants (n = 66 at each site) who are between 9 and 14-months of age and showing ASD-risk behaviours (social and/or communication difficulties). Consenting families will be randomized into receiving either the iBASIS-VIPP Therapy (n = 66) or Treatment as Usual. Families in the iBASIS-VIPP Therapy group will receive 10 home-based sessions with a Speech Pathologist or Psychologist over five months, and undertake 30-minutes daily home practice. Families in the Treatment as Usual group may receive a parent information seminar, the provision of reading material on infant development, or developmental monitoring, which is the current best practice protocol for these infants. Infants in both groups will be re-assessed follow-up points, time-locked to baseline assessments: (1) 6 months post-baseline (i.e., immediately post treatment period), (2) 12- months post-baseline, and (3) 24-months post-baseline. The primary outcome will be autistic symptom severity immediately post treatment (measured by the AOSI). Secondary outcomes will be a range of social and communicative behaviours relevant to ASD at each of the three follow-up points.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Green J, Wan M, Guiraud J, Holsgrove S, McNally J, Slonims V, et al. Intervention for infants at risk of developing autism. J Autism Dev Disord. 2013;43(11):2502-14.
Green J, Charman T, Pickles A, Wan MW, Slonims V, et al. Parent-mediated intervention versus no intervention for infants at high risk of autism. Lancet Psychiatr. 2(2):133-40.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital
Roberts Road, Subiaco, Perth
Western Australia 6008
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016008EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Whitehouse </name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Rd
Subacio WA 6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Andrew.Whitehouse@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Kandice Varcin</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Rd
Subacio WA 6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Kandice.Varcin@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Kandice Varcin</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Rd
Subacio WA 6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Kandice.Varcin@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Whitehouse</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
100 Roberts Rd
Subacio WA 6008
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9489 7700</fax>
      <email>Andrew.Whitehouse@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>