<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335327">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000382077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Determining the docosahexaenoic acid dose to obtain plasma and erythrocyte phospholipid fatty acid profiles in preterm infants comparable to term infant profiles: a dose response pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In preterm infants born less than 33 weeks gestation will a tuna oil emulsion containing 121 mg/ml or 76 mg/ml of docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) compared with 37 mg/ml of DHA achieve an erythrocyte phospholipid fatty acid profile comparable to a term infant profile?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DINO-II pilot study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preterm infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Infants are randomised to receive one of three solutions:
Aqueous emulsion of 19.5% DHA oil:
1) Containing 11.4 mg DHA. This will carry 121 mg of DHA for each ml of emulsion.
2) 66:33 blend of DHA and soy oil to give an emulsion that will carry 76 mg of DHA for each ml of emulsion.
3) Control (details in control field)
Administration for all three solutions: 1 ml/kg/day (given via feeding tube in 3 divided doses, 8 hourly) for 28 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Aqueous emulsion of 19.5% DHA oil:
33:66 blend of DHA and soy oil to give an emulsion that will carry 37 mg of DHA for each ml of emulsion.
Administration for all three solutions: 1 ml/kg/day (given via feeding tube in 3 divided doses, 8 hourly) for 28 days.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood (erythrocyte and plasma) phospholipid DHA levels analysed using gas chromotography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0, 7, 14, 21, 28</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerance of the enteral emulsions will be determined by comparing the number of days to reach full enteral feeds (&gt;=150 mls/kg/day) and number of days in which one or more feeds were stopped.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from study start to end (28 days)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants born less than 33 weeks gestation after one but before five days of commencing any enteral feeds and with parental/guardian consent.  Multiple births will be eligible and will be randomised individually.  Women providing breast milk for their infant not taking DHA supplements or willing to stop taking supplements for duration study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants with major congenital or chromosomal abnormalities.  Infants likely to be transferred to remote locations where weekly blood tests cant be done.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The parent/s of eligible infants will be approached to enter the trial by the study neonatologist, or nominee; follow-up for consent will be by the study nurse.  This will occur when the infant is nearing readiness to commence feeds.  Upon consent, infants will be randomised to one of the three study emulsions and assigned a unique study ID.  The Clinical Trials Pharmacist (who is not involved in study recruitment or conduct) holds the allocation schedule and assigns the study group.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation schedule using variable block design was generated by statistician independent of study conduct.  Stratification occurrred for sex, gestational age &lt;28 weeks and 28 to 32 weeks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women's and Children's Health Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide SA 5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Women's and Children's Health Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide SA 5006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Adelaide</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Adelaide SA 5005</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Infants born before 33 weeks are at high risk of developmental disorders and learning disabilities.  We confirmed the importance of dietary docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) in preterm infants born &lt;33 weeks gestation in a large, National Health and Medical Research Council funded (ID 250322), multi-centre randomised controlled trial (the DINO trial; ACTRN 12606000327583; JAMA. 2009;301:175-82).  We demonstrated that DHA given at a dose designed to approximate the in utero accumulation rate (3 times the standard dietary dose) resulted in fewer preterm children with significant mental delay at 18 months corrected age compared with control.  The effect of DHA-supplementation was most pronounced in girls born &lt;33 weeks gestation and in infants born weighing &lt;1250g.
Despite this some children (boys, infants born &gt;1250g) failed to respond leading us to suspect that higher doses of DHA may be required.  This was confirmed when we observed that the DHA level of preterm infants did not achieve levels seen in term infants.  This was most likely caused by a number of factors:  biological variability and compliance variation influenced the amount of DHA that appeared in breast milk, delay in reaching target infant milk volumes and losses due to oxidation for energy.  A randomised controlled trial of higher-dose is warranted.  Before undertaking such a trial a pilot study is needed to determine the effect of a higher DHA dose on plasma and erythrocyte phospholipid levels, and to assess the feasibility of giving DHA directly to the infant rather than as an addition to milk or formula.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children, Youth and Women's Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide SA 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REC2169/5/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carmel Collins</name>
      <address>Child Nutrition Research Centre
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park  SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5755</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 6296</fax>
      <email>carmel.collins@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carmel Collins</name>
      <address>Child Nutrition Research Centre
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park  SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5755</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 6296</fax>
      <email>carmel.collins@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carmel Collins</name>
      <address>Child Nutrition Research Centre
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park  SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5755</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 6296</fax>
      <email>carmel.collins@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>