<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369218">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001213538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ultrasound in the second stage of labour for fetal position  a randomised controlled trial

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the clinical examination versus use of ultrasound with the clinical examination for assessing fetal head position on maternal and neonatal outcomes in women having a vacuum assisted birth.

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>suction cup malposition</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Digital vaginal examination will be as per current care.
The ultrasound will be performed by a senior obstetrician using a hand held transducer on the maternal abdomen to assess fetal head position. The procedure would take no more than a couple of minutes. Adherence will be noted on the study sheet completed for all women having a vacuum birth.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: current care that involves assessment by abdominal and digital vaginal examination prior to instrumental delivery. The clinician will notify the midwife of the fetal position prior to the vacuum and who will record the position on the chart provided as either direct OA or OP, left OA, right OA, left OP and right OP, left OT or right OT position. The rest of the information will be as is routinely collected on the instrumental delivery form currently used in the unit.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>i)	Position of the baby as assessed by the midwife ascribing the vacuum birth</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at  time of birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ii). Position of the cup placement noted at birth  this will be noted from the instrument markings on the neonatal head by the paediatric Registrar who is always present at these births </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at time of birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>i). a composite outcome:
             a. Neonatal trauma (bruising, laceration, cephalohaematoma, su bgaleal haemorrhage, retinal haemorrhage) as assessed by the paediatric Registrar
             b.  fetal acidosis (arterial pH below 7.10 and base excess greater than-12.0 mmol)
             c.  admission to the neonatal unit.</outcome>
      <timepoint> At time of birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ii). Maternal: compare the incidence of&gt;3 pulls- each pull is recorded by the scriber during the procedure with time of application of each pull as well</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time o fbirth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>iii). number of pop offs - as recorded by scriber present during procedure</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of birth-</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>iv). Third and fourth degree perineal tears- a mandatory requirement when  perineum is examined after procedure on the assisted birth template</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>v). Maternal satisfaction of the instrumental delivery process.- assessed using a simple survey form with Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>The day following the birth by a member of the Research team.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sequential use of instruments - as recorded by the scriber present during the procedure
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>caesarean section for failed instrumental delivery - as recorded in teh birth Register</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestational age 37 weeks or above, singleton, cephalic presentation and need for instrumental delivery.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Need for urgent delivery for fetal distress.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation: Allocation to intervention or the control group will be by opening a sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelope that will contain the allocation. Randomisation will be concealed in serially numbered sealed opaque envelopes kept locked in the ward and only opened immediately before a decision has been made to perform a vacuum birth and after recording the name and UR number of the participant in the research register. After randomisation the participant will remain in that group irrespective of the actual method used for of induction; intention-to-treat.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be done by using a computer generated list of random numbers with a variable block size.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>a. Sample size - If we assume the rate of inaccurate diagnosis (difference of more than 45 degrees) to be 20% in the control group based on previous studies, to demonstrate a rate of incorrect diagnosis of 5%  in the intervention group, we would require 175 women in each group to have a power of 80%  at an alpha value of 5%. 

b. Data analysis and reporting will proceed according to CONSORT guidelines for randomised controlled trials, and will be conducted blinded to group status by the trial researcher. All analyses will use appropriate regression models, with results presented Relative risks with their respective 95% confidence intervals
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>20/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>350</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Ipswich Hospital - Ipswich</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>kassam mahomed</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ipswich Hospital
1 Chelmsford Avenue
Ipswich
Qld. 4305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A RCT to compare clinical examination alone versus clinical examination and ultrasound for accuracy of fetal head position prior to vacuum birth.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>West Moreton District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee EC00184
The Park  Centre for Mental Health
Locked Bag 500
Sumner Park BC, QLD 4074
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QMWS/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kassam mahomed</name>
      <address>Dept of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Ipswich Hospital
1 Chelmsford Avenue
Ipswich
Qld 4305.</address>
      <phone>+61738101111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kassam_mahomed@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kassam Mahomed</name>
      <address>Dept of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Ipswich Hospital
1 Chelmsford Avenue
Ipswich
Qld 4305.</address>
      <phone>+61738101111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kassam_mahomed@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kassam mahomed</name>
      <address>Dept of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Ipswich Hospital
1 Chelmsford Avenue
Ipswich
Qld 4305.</address>
      <phone>+61738101111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kassam_mahomed@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kassam Mahomed</name>
      <address>Dept of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Ipswich Hospital
1 Chelmsford Avenue
Ipswich
Qld 4305.</address>
      <phone>+61738101111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kassam_mahomed@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>