<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367522">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000483550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Buccal versus Vaginal (200 microgram) Misoprostol for Second Trimester Abortion Termination</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical randomized trial to compare efficacy and safety of vaginal and buccal misoprostol in second trimester abortion due to intrauterine fetal death</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Missed Abortion</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intrauterine fetal death</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Abortion</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patients were interviewed at the outpatient clinic or the delivery ward ,where full detailed history was taken and examination confirming the pregnancy and gestational age based on the last menstrual period or documented early ultrasound report. Abdominal ultrasound was performed in the clinic to determine gestational duration using femur length as parameter (Hadlock system), after having confirmed the pregnancy, the gestational age and fetal death, women were informed about the nature of the study and of the possible risks and benefits. Informed written consent was obtained from each participant.

Intervention
The study had 2 treatment groups . group I received a dose of misoprostol (200 microgram)(one tablet of Misotac 200 ug ; Sigma co.,Cairo, Egypt)   every 4 hours buccally (and the subject was instructed not to swallow it for one hour) till expulsion of the fetus for maximum 24 hours .
Group II received a dose of moistened misoprostol (200 microgram) (one tablet of Misotac 200 ug ; Sigma co.,Cairo, Egypt)  every 4 hours vaginally(tablet was put into the posterior fornix)till expulsion of the fetus for maximum 24 hours.
Follow up
Subjects were asked about onset and degree of pain and examined every 4 hours for blood pressure , pulse and temperature, and were examined vaginally every 4 hours to assess progress of cervical opening and presence of vaginal bleeding up to fetal expulsion .
Once fetal expulsion occurred, the patient received a dose of oxytocin , 10 U in 500 mL of lactated Ringers by iv infusion till delivery of the placenta. Removal of the placenta by surgical dilatation and evacuation was performed immediately in case of heavy bleeding ,or if it was retained following fetal expulsion more than half an hour (as recorded by E Alston RM, 2012).
Antibiotic therapy prescription as a part of the hospital protocol was given to all women post abortive before discharge and antibiotic plus treatment for inhibition of lactation drug was prescribed as a home treatment .
hemoglobin level was done for all women before ,and 12 hours after complete expulsion.
Data collection include the demographics ( the women's age, gestational age, gravidity, parity and previous misscariage) , number and timing of misoprostol doses and the induction-expulsion time interval. 
All women were followed for side effects such as nausea, vomiting , diarrhea and fever and reported.
</interventions>
    <comparator>active control which is the buccal group </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is the induction interval, the time from the initial misoprostol dose until complete fetal expulsion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at time of complete fetal expulsion </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of side effects of misoprostol (such as nausea, vomiting, fever, chills, diarrhea, tachycardia, and headache)</outcome>
      <timepoint>untill complete fetal expulsion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>number of misoprostol doses</outcome>
      <timepoint>till time of expulsion for maximum 24  hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1-Women who are pregnant between 13 and 27 weeks.
 2- Termination of  pregnancy is indicated due to intrauterine fetal death.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>42</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1-Pregnancy before 13 weeks.
2-Pregnancy beyond 27 weeks.
3- Scarred uterus.
4-Known hypersensitivity for misoprostol.
5-Refusal of the woman to participate.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size Calculation
According to a recent study the median time to expulsion in the vaginal misoprostol and buccal misoprostol groups was 12 and 15 hours respectively with difference 3 hours in time interval 
A power calculation estimated that in order to detect an effect size of 0.3 of the regression of time interval of abortion with misoprostol via vaginal compared to buccal route among women indicated for abortion in the second trimester of pregnancy with a p value &lt; 0.05 and 95% power, a sample size of 180 patients (90 for each group) is needed. G*Power software was used for sample size calculation 

Analysis of the data was performed by SPSS, version 8 for windows (10). Categorical and ordinal data were presented as ratios, whereas continuous data were presented as means + standard deviation. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>27/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>women health hospital of assuit university</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>egypt- assuit city -assuit university street -assuit university -women health hospital -postcode 71111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>women health hospital of assuit university</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>egypt- assuit city -assuit university street -assuit university -women health hospital -postcode 71111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mohammad Sayed Abdellah</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>egypt- assuit city -assuit university street -assuit university -women health hospital -postcode 71111</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Egypt</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim Of The Work
To compare the efficacy and safety of buccal and vaginal misoprostol in a dose of 200 microgram every 4 hours for the induction of abortion in the second trimester gestation in cases of interauterine fetal death.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>national research center of egypt</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Address
El Buhouth St., Dokki, Cairo, Egypt.
postcode 73333</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mohammad Sayed Abdellah</name>
      <address>EGYPT - ASSUIT CITY - Assuit University Street - Assuit University - Women health hospital - postal code 71111</address>
      <phone>+20 1006801036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msayed21@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adel Gamal Osman </name>
      <address>EGYPT - ASSUIT CITY - Assuit University Street - Assuit University - Women health hospital - postal code 71111</address>
      <phone>+201122281431</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>adelgamal683@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mohammad Sayed Abdellah</name>
      <address>EGYPT - ASSUIT CITY - Assuit University Street - Assuit University - Women health hospital - postal code 71111</address>
      <phone>+20 1006801036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msayed21@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adel Gamal Osman</name>
      <address>EGYPT - ASSUIT CITY - Assuit University Street - Assuit University - Women health hospital - postal code 71111</address>
      <phone>+201122281431</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>