<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364102">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000500752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot study assessing the effects of poorly absorbed sugars in enteral formula on colonic gas production and symptom induction in healthy subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study assessing the effects of poorly absorbed sugars in enteral formula on colonic gas production in healthy subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Enteral nutrition-associated diarrhoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will ingest (orally) one dose of the following fasted (on waking) before a minimum of two-day washout period before crossing over to all other arms:  
Arm 1 - 15g lactulose made up to 100mL solution
Arm 2 - 500mL of enteral formula Isosource'Registered Trademark' HN 
Arm 3 - 500mL of enteral formula Isosource'Registered Trademark' 1.5

Arm 1 will be ingested first in all participants, then Arm 2 and Arm 3 will be allocated in random order determined by a computer-generated sequence.  Someone who is not a study investigator will label the two enteral formulas as 'Blue formula' and 'Red formula' so that both the study investigators and participants are blinded to the formulas.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1 - Active control:  15g lactulose made up to 100mL solution ingested orally in one dose on waking.  

Lactulose is an osmotic laxative or a sugar that is unabsorbed in the small intestine, thereby reaching the large intestine.  Here it will be fermented by bacteria and produce gases including hydrogen (which can be measured on breath) and possible gut symptoms such as diarrhoea.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breath hydrogen after ingestion of lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark' HN and Isosource'Registered Trademark' 1.5</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 hours after ingestion of lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark' HN and Isosource'Registered Trademark' 1.5</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breath methane after ingestion of lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark' HN and Isosource'Registered Trademark' 1.5</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 hours after ingestion of lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark' HN and Isosource'Registered Trademark' 1.5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of overall gut symptoms and specific symptoms of bloating, pain and satisfaction with stool consistency rated by a 100 mm visual analogue scale following ingestion of lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark'1.5 and Isosource'Registered Trademark'HN</outcome>
      <timepoint>The day after ingestion of lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark'1.5 and Isosource'Registered Trademark'HN</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consistency of bowel motions rated by the Bristol Stool Chart following ingestion of lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark'1.5 and Isosource'Registered Trademark'HN</outcome>
      <timepoint>The day following ingestion of  lactulose, Isosource'Registered Trademark'1.5 and Isosource'Registered Trademark'HN</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy subjects or subjects with functional gut symptoms such as irritable bowel syndrome over the age of 18 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Organic disease or condition predisposing the patient to diarrhoea (e.g. inflammatory bowel disease, bowel resection, untreated coeliac disease)
2.	Non-breath hydrogen producer after lactulose ingestion
3.	Use of antidiarrhoeal medications for one week prior to study commencement
4.	Probiotic or prebiotic use for two weeks prior to study commencement
5.	Antibiotic use for two weeks prior to study commencement</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Healthy subjects and subjects with functional gut symptoms will be recruited through word of mouth.  Potential subjects will have the study described to them by a study investigator and by the trial explanatory statement.  If the potential subjects are happy to participate, they will sign the consent form and be randomised to receive one of the trial enteral formulas before crossing over to the other trial enteral formula.  Randomisation will occur via computer-generated randomisation which will allocate each subject to their first formula ingestion.  This will be conducted by a study investigator, however the formulas will be coded as 'Blue formula' and 'Red formula'.  Both the study investigator and subjects will be blinded to formula identification.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software to identify which formula the subject will receive first.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The statistical tests performed for the comparison between the three treatment arms include:  one-way repeated measures ANOVA for continuous variables and the Chi-squared test will be used for categorical variables.  Area under the curve for breath hydrogen and methane will also be assessed.  

Sample size to estimate a difference in the primary endpoint of breath hydrogen cannot be determined as there are no known studies comparing breath hydrogen after ingestion of one bolus of varying FODMAPs doses.  The formulation of Isosource'Registered Trademark'1.5 and Isosource'Registered Trademark'HN which were previously investigated has recently been changed, therefore accessibility of the original formulations within a reasonable expiry date for use in this study is limited.  We currently possess enough Isosource'Registered Trademark'1.5 and Isosource'Registered Trademark'HN to supply a maximum of 34 participants.  This will be the study sample size.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>21/04/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>34</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School, Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School, Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Diarrhoea amongst hospitalised patients receiving enteral formula (tube-feeding) is common.  Previous research has suggested that one possible reason for this is the high content of poorly absorbed sugars called FODMAPs (Fermentable Oligosaccharides, Disaccharides, Monosaccharides And Polyols) in the formula.  FODMAPs enter the large intestine where they get fermented by bacteria, produce gas and draw water in to the large intestine.  In large enough doses, this may contribute to diarrhoea.  We hypothesise that giving a formula we believe is high FODMAP compared to a formula we believe is low FODMAP will produce different amounts of large intestinal gas.  This can be measure by collecting the breath after drinking these formulas and measuring the levels of gas in the breath.  We will then compare this to a the FODMAP lactulose, which is a sugar that is known to produce gas in everyone.  This will show us if there are FODMAPs in the formulas and a rough estimation of quantity.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Clayton Campus
Wellington Rd
Clayton VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF13/269 - 2013000108</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/01/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Gibson</name>
      <address>Head of Gastroenterology
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0189</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Gibson@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Emma Halmos</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Emma.Halmos@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Emma Halmos</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Emma.Halmos@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>