<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363768">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000517774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Telerehabilitation treatment of aphasia across the World Health Organisation International Classification of Functioning Disability and Health (WHO-ICF)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Telerehabilitation treatment of people with aphasia: determining the communication and quality of life outcomes following online treatment </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111111398563</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Aphasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>People with aphasia will receive any combination of three aphasia treatments via telerehabilitation including
1) Constraint Induced Language Therapy (CILT)
2) Group aphasia therapy
3) Communication partner training.
The type of treatment received will be determined collaboratively with the client by the treating clinician according to the language difficulties they are experiencing, ability to commit to the time periods required and their support networks. 
Telerehabilitation is the delivery of medical rehabilitation services at a distance using electronic information and communication technologies. Telerehabilitation technology allows patients to access assessment and treatment services remotely. In this study, the treatment will be provided via multi-point videoconferencing over the internet using computer based software downloaded onto the participant and clinicians computers. 
The first treatment, Constraint Induced Language Therapy (CILT)  has been demonstrated to have substantial and stable improvements of language function in people with chronic aphasia with evidence of successful carryover of improved language function to everyday life. Participants will receive 3 hours of therapy a day, 5 days a week for two weeks. Two participants are treated concurrently  by one clinician. The primary therapy activity is a dual card game between participants where the objective is to collect matches until the participant has no cards remaining- similar to Go Fish. Each participant takes turns verbally requesting a card from the other who must provide a response. The requests are constrained to verbal output only with other forms of communication such as gesture or writing not permitted. The therapy will be delivered online using a web based version of the Go Fish card game developed by the research team and multi-point videoconferencing software to connect video and audio.

In the second treatment, Group Therapy, participants will participate  in tasks that incorporate activity and participation level treatment goals. Participants will attend one 1.5 hour treatment session per week for 12 weeks and will be engaged in activities that are functionally relevant and require spoken language to be the main route of communication. Clinician to patient ratios for groups will be one speech pathologist to four patients. The clinician and participants will be connected to each other using web-based videoconferencing software with video and audio. The clinician will use this software to also display electronic treatment materials such as maps, photos and videos. 

For the third treatment, Communication Partner Training, participants with aphasia may identify 1 -3 communication partners to be involved in communication partner. The participant and their communication partner will be involved in five 2 hour training sessions, fortnightly over 10 weeks, via the Internet in which they are: provided with education regarding the role of the communication partner in successful communication interactions; recorded participating in a conversation and then provided with feedback; trained in communication strategies and re-recorded and provided with feedback on implementation of the strategies.  The strategies that are most relevant and successful with the person with aphasia will be identified and the clinician will provide support to problem solve any difficulties. The clinician will be connected to the participant with aphasia and their communication partner over the internet using web based videoconferencing software. </interventions>
    <comparator>People with aphasia will receive three aphasia treatments face to face
1) Constraint Induced Language Therapy
2) Group aphasia therapy
3) Communication partner training
The type of treatment received will be determined collaboratively with the client by the treating clinician according to the language difficulties they are experiencing, ability to commit to the time periods required and their support networks.
The first treatment, Constraint Induced Language Therapy (CILT)  has been demonstrated to have substantial and stable improvements of language function in people with chronic aphasia with evidence of successful carryover of improved language function to everyday life. Participants will receive 3 hours of therapy a day, 5 days a week for two weeks. Two participants are treated concurrently  by one clinician. The primary therapy activity is a dual card game between participants where the objective is to collect matches until the participant has no cards remaining- similar to Go Fish. Each participant takes turns verbally requesting a card from the other who must provide a response. The requests are constrained to verbal output only with other forms of communication such as gesture or writing not permitted.

In the second treatment, Group Therapy, participants will participate  in tasks that incorporate activity and participation level treatment goals. Participants will attend one 1.5 hour treatment session per week over 12 weeks and will be engaged in activities that are functionally relevant and require spoken language to be the main route of communication. Clinician to patient ratios for groups will be one speech pathologist to four patients. 

For the third treatment, Communication Partner Training, participants with aphasia may identify 1 -3 communication partners to be involved in communication partner. The participant and their communication partner will be involved in five 2 hour training sessions, fortnightly over 10 weeks, in which they are: provided with education regarding the role of the communication partner in successful communication interactions; recorded participating in a conversation and then provided with feedback; trained in communication strategies and re-recorded and provided with feedback on implementation of the strategies.  The strategies that are most relevant and successful with the person with aphasia will be identified and the clinician will provide support to problem solve any difficulties. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measures is discourse analysis of six connected speech samples. This involves recording participants responses to six stimuli including two static picture descriptions, two sequenced picture descriptions, one request for personal information "What do you like to do on Sundays?" and one request for procedural information "How would you write and send a letter?". These samples are tape recorded and transcribed. The samples are then analysed to determine the number of words, time taken for each sample and the amount of correct information conveyed in each sample. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of Living with Aphasia (ALA) which is a questionnaire that measures the impact of aphasia on everyday life. The ALA corresponds with the areas of functioning of the World Health Organization International Classification of Functioning and provides information regarding the impact of the communication impairment across a number of domains including language impairments, participation in everyday life, communication environment and personal factors.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comprehensive Aphasia Test (CAT) which is an assessment battery that includes a cognitive screen, a language battery and a disability questionnaire. The cognitive screen provides information about a range of factors that may affect performance. The language battery provides a profile of performance across all modalities of language production and comprehension. This assessment will provide an outcome measure of the impairment domain in the ICF.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The eligibility criteria are as follows:
Inclusion Criteria
diagnosis of aphasia according to standardised assessment caused by an acquired brain lesion 
Eighteen years of age or older
Able to provide consent to participate in the study
English speaking
At least 12 months post stroke and willing to cease any outpatient treatment during the study
Sufficient vision and hearing to operate computer equipment 
Broadband Internet connection in their home
Naming and Repetitions scores on Comprehensive Aphasia test &gt; 5 at initial assessment

For the intensive therapy participants there is this additional inclusion criteria: 
Able to commit to a 2 week block of intensive aphasia treatment involving 3 hours of therapy per day for 5 days of the week
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria:
Diagnosis of any concomitant cognitive disorders such as dementia or progressive aphasia
Concomitant severe apraxia or dysarthria of speech as identified on initial screening assessment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be concealed by using consecutively numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes which are stored centrally</concealment>
    <sequence>The random allocation process will be performed by a researcher not involved in the treatment of participants and will employ an off-site, computer-generated random number sequence. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Both intention-to-treat and per-protocol analyses will be performed as per CONSORT guidelines for non-inferiority trials. Non-inferiority of the telerehabilitation intervention will determined by computing the within-group differences from baseline and the 95% confidence interval (CI) of these differences. Treatment effects will be calculated pre- to post-treatment. In addition to intention-to-treat and per-protocol analyses, a sensitivity analysis to account for missing data and their potential effect on the observed results will be performed. In this analysis a last observation carried forward approach will be used to replace missing data at either baseline or post-treatment assessment points. Where data from both post-treatment assessments are missing, the participants existing data will be excluded from the study. Consistent results between the initial and sensitivity analyses will be indicative of robust findings. Further analyses of the clinical treatment effect of each intervention group will be conducted using a linear mixed model which is appropriate for comparing means in independent samples and has the added advantage of adjusting for baseline differences and being tolerant of missing data. As baseline differences are adjusted for with this approach, it is possible to compare pre and post-treatment scores between groups, rather than their change scores. The statistic will be computed with observed outcomes as the dependent variables and with fixed factors of treatment group (Tele, FTF) and assessment time (pre- and post-intervention). Interactions among these factors will also be determined. Fixed predicted values and residuals from these analyses will be used for data inspection purposes. The outcome of primary interest is the interaction effect between groups and time. An alpha level of 0.05 will be used for this analysis. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Redcliffe Hospital - Redcliffe</hospital>
    <hospital>Toowoomba Hospital - Toowoomba</hospital>
    <hospital>Caboolture Hospital - Caboolture</hospital>
    <hospital>Warwick Hospital - Warwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Dalby Hospital Health Service - Dalby</hospital>
    <postcode>4055 - Ferny Grove</postcode>
    <postcode>4005 - New Farm</postcode>
    <postcode>4000 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4070 - Moggill</postcode>
    <postcode>4011 - Clayfield</postcode>
    <postcode>4030 - Wooloowin</postcode>
    <postcode>4059 - Kelvin Grove Bc</postcode>
    <postcode>4020 - Redcliffe</postcode>
    <postcode>4350 - Clifford Gardens</postcode>
    <postcode>4370 - Leslie Dam</postcode>
    <postcode>4361 - Clifton</postcode>
    <postcode>4360 - Nobby</postcode>
    <postcode>4510 - Caboolture</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Rachelle Pitt</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Queensland
Sir Fred Schonell Drive
St Lucia QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Queensland
Sir Fred Schonell Drive
St Lucia QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Speech and language therapy results in positive communication and psychosocial outcomes for people with
aphasia. However, access to services is difficult and research into alternative service delivery models is needed.
One such alternative is telerehabilitation which allows access to treatment remotely. This project will investigate the
feasibility of telerehabilitation treatment of aphasia.
AIMS:
This research project has the following specific aims:
1.To determine the feasibility of using telerehabilitation to provide intensive aphasia therapy, group therapy and
communication partner training to people with aphasia using computerbased
multipoint videoconferencing.
2.To describe the perceptions and experiences of people with aphasia and their communication partners
participating in telerehabilitation aphasia treatment programs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Behavioural and Social Sciences Ethical Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Queensland
Sir Fred Schonell Drive
St Lucia QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20050000530</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Rachelle Pitt</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
University of Queensland
Sir Fred Schonell Drive
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>61411789490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.pitt1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Rachelle Pitt</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
University of Queensland
Sir Fred Schonell Drive
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>61411789490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.pitt1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Rachelle Pitt</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
University of Queensland
Sir Fred Schonell Drive
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>61411789490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.pitt1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Rachelle Pitt</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
University of Queensland
Sir Fred Schonell Drive
St Lucia QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>61411789490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.pitt1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>