<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="711">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000661673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Seronegatives And Metabolic Abnormalities Protocol 2 (SAMA 002)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A three arm, prospective study to compare the effect of six weeks exposure to the combination of lopinavir (LPVr)/Combivir (AZT/3TC) versus lopinavir alone or Combivir alone in HIV-negative healthy subjects on the development of abnormalities of lipid and glucose metabolism.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SAMA 002</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>HIV 
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lipid metabolism</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Glucose metabolism</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic abnormality</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lipodystrophy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS / HIV)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A three arm, prospective study to compare the effect of six weeks exposure to the combination of lopinavir (LPVr)/Combivir (AZT/3TC) versus lopinavir alone or Combivir alone in HIV-negative healthy subjects on the development of abnormalities of lipid and glucose metabolism.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of six weeks antiretroviral therapy with LPVr and CBV, alone and in combination, in HIV negative healthy subjects with respect to changes from baseline in genes related to mitochondrial and lipid metabolism in adipocytes.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of six weeks antiretroviral therapy with LPVr and CBV, alone and in combination, in HIV negative healthy subjects with respect to changes from baseline in genes related to mitochondrial and lipid and glucose metabolism in monocytes.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of six weeks antiretroviral therapy with LPVr and CBV, alone and in combination, in HIV negative healthy subjects with respect to changes from baseline in adipocyte structure.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of six weeks LPVr and CBV, alone and in combination, in HIV negative healthy subjects with respect to changes in serum lipids and glucose.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effects of six weeks therapy with LPVr/CBV on the parameters listed above with six weeks of LPVr alone or CBV alone in HIV negative subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety of LPVr and CBV, alone and in combination,in HIV negative healthy subjects by evaluating the incidence and severity of adverse events and abnormal laboratory values.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess changes in body composition and plasma concentrations of LPVr over the course of the trial in subjects taking LPVr and CBV, alone and in combination, and compare them to changes in gene expression in monocytes and/or adipose tissue.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess possible increased risk of cardiovascular disease (CVD) by measurements of changes in brachial artery endothelial reactivity over the course of the trial in individuals taking LPVr and CBV, alone and in combination.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the reversibility of any abnormalities developing during the course of the six weeks of dosing, by performing repeat assessments at weeks 12 and 24.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be able to provide written consent to perform in the trial. - HIV antibody negative and HIV DNA negative at time of entry to the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any history of, or ongoing, mental or physical condition (including suspected or known diagnosis of ischaemic heart disease), which, in the opinion of the investigator, would impede the subjects ability to participate in the trial.- History of type I or type II diabetes mellitus or previous treatment with antidiabetic medication. - Prior use of testosterone, oestrogen, growth hormone or other oral glucocorticoid or anabolic steroid products within the previous six months. - Alcohol or substance abuse which in the opinion of the investigator would affect the subjects ability to participate in the trial. - Prior use of anti-retroviral agents (including protease inhibitors, nucleoside or non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors, investigational antiretroviral agents or fusion inhibitors either in a previous study, as treatment or as part of post-exposure prophylaxis).- Prior use of any retinoid-containing compound within the previous six months. - Abnormal coagulation. - Previous allergic reaction or known allergy to local anaesthetic. - Previous use of psychotropic medications. - Concomitant use of medications, including those metabolised by CYP3A4 enzyme system (appendix C), which, in the opinion of the investigator, would affect the subjects ability to participate in all activities involved in the trial. - Any grade-three laboratory abnormality recorded from screening bloods. - Any grade-two laboratory abnormality recorded from screening bloods, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would impede the subjects ability to safely complete all study requirements. - Gastrointestinal disorders, which may affect drug absorption. - Any finding on screening clinical examination, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would impede the subjects ability to participate in the rest of the trial.- Pregnancy - Evidence of acute or chronic active hepatitis B virus infection by serology performed at baseline. - Evidence of hepatitis C infection by serology performed at baseline.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation sequence was generated centrally and kept at a central location in sealed envelopes grouped according to age of potential study participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequences were generated centrally to ensure a 2:2:1 randomisation stratified to age group to ensure equal recruitment to each arm across a range of ages. Computer generated randomisation cards, specifying a treatment allocation, were then grouped according to age (age groups a-d) and each individual card placed in an envelope marked with the age group. Envelopes remain at a central location and study staff request a treatment allocation based on potential study subject⿿s age from administrative staff not directly associated with the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Heart Lung and Blood Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>US National Institutes of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St Vincents Hospital Sydney Limited</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Heart Lung and Blood Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Institutes of Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Metabolism and Diabetes Research Group, The Garvan Institute of Medical Research.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomised study of the effect of treatment with Combivir (zidovudine [AZT] and lamivudine [3TC]) and Kaletra (lopinavir [LPVr]), alone and in combination, on the development of abnormalities in lipid and glucose metabolism in HIV negative healthy subjects</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew D Carr</name>
      <address>The National Centre in HIV Epidemiology and Clinical Research
Level 2
376 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83823359</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>acarr@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Patrick WG Mallon</name>
      <address>The National Centre in HIV Epidemiology and Clinical Research
Level 2
376 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83823107</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pmallon@nchecr.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>