<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82308">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/09/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/10/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000509460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Reflex effects of a spinal adjustment on autonomic nervous system function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Autonomic nervous system changes in chiropractic patients following chiropractic adjustement or sham adjustment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>No problem will be studied. We are going to investigate reflex autonomic nervous system changes in 'normal' individuals.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single chiropractic adjustment to the spine. The data collection session will last approximately 20 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Set up for chiropractic adjustment with no thrust</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short term change to autonomic nervous system function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 minutes post adjustment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>NA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible to participate in this study volunteers must be an active patient at the New Zealand College of Chiropractic student health centre. Active is defined as receiving care at the student health centre within the previous six weeks. Volunteers must have no known contraindication to receiving a chiropractic adjustment and have experienced no previous significant adverse reactions to spinal adjustments</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>-2147483648</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>N/A</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>-2147483648</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>N/A</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Volunteers will not be eligible to participate in this study if they are currently taking blood pressure medication or if their blood pressure is classified as moderate or higher hypertension (systolic 160mmHg or greater or diastolic 100mmHg or greater) on the day they are to participate in the study. They will also be ineligible to participate if their blood pressure is less than 90/60mmHg on the day they are to participate in the study.

Volunteers will be asked not to take or consume any substance that is likely to have a significant effect on blood pressure on the day they will be involved in the study. This will include caffeine, tobacco, tea, coffee, cola, drugs or alcohol. They will also be asked not to partake in any significant physical exercise for at least 2 hours prior to their participation in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be approached during routine visits at the NZCC student health centre. Group allocation will be made centrally using a computerised random number generator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Rando number generator will assign each participant to a group. Group allocation will not be revealed to investigators prior to data collection.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand Coillege of Chiropractic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>15 Margot Street
Newmarket
Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand College of Chiropractic</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15 Margot Street 
Newmarket
Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate the effect a spinal adjustment on the autonomic nervous system (ANS). A spinal adjustment is the term chiropractors use for spinal manipulation. This study will investigate whether a single spinal adjustment results in short term changes to the ANS. Measures of ANS activity will include blood pressure, heart rate variability and other non-invasive modalities associated with autonomic function. This study will be conducted as a randomised controlled trial. Each trial will take place during a routine chiropractic visit at the New Zealand College of Chiropractic (NZCC) student health centre.The first trial we aim to conduct will involve monitoring blood pressure. During each trial participants will have their blood pressure taken and then have their spine checked by an experienced chiropractor. If assigned to the experimental group they will receive a spinal adjustment based on their palpation findings, the control group will be set up for an adjustment but no manipulation will take place. The groups will then have their blood pressure monitored immediately post intervention. Following this the participant will receive any further spinal adjustments deemed necessary based on their chiropractic analysis. Volunteers will be sought from active patients currently presenting to the NZCC student health centre. 
Research Question: Does a spinal adjustment result in a short-term change in autonomic nervous system (ANS) activity? If so, does the nature of this change depend on the region of the spine adjusted?

Null hypothesis: That a spinal adjustment will cause no short-term change in ANS activity.
Hypothesis 1:  That a spinal adjustment will cause a short term change in ANS activity.
Hypothesis 2: That the nature of the change in ANS activity following a spinal adjustment will be dependent on the region of the adjusted.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
3rd Floor
BNZ Building
354 Victoria Street
Hamilton</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTY/07/07/083</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/07/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>NZCC
15 Margot Street
Newmarket
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 522 5530</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>spineworks@ihug.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>NZCC
15 Margot Street
Newmarket
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 522 5530</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>spineworks@ihug.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>NZCC
15 Margot Street
Newmarket
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 522 5530</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>spineworks@ihug.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>