<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371278">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001464459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Success rate of upper gastrointestinal endoscope insertion directly into the oesophagus through a dedicated channel in the laryngeal mask airway (LMA) called the LMA GASTRO (Trademark)  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Utility of a modified laryngeal mask airway (LMA) called the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) for upper gastrointestinal endoscopic procedures</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LMA GASTRO (Trademark) trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Upper gastrointestinal endoscopic procedures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After induction of anaesthesia with Propofol  the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) is inserted into the upper airway with the patients head placed in the sniffing position. The standardized method of insertion include lubricating the devise, before grasping it along the integral bite block and advancing into the mouth in the direction towards the hard palate whilst gliding downwards and backwards along the hard palate until definite resistance is felt. A maximum of three attempts by an anaesthetist is allowed before considered a failure of the laryngeal mask airway (LMA GASTRO Trademark). A breathing circuit is then connected to a dedicated channel for airway control
This is followed by the insertion of an upper-gastrointestinal endoscope, through  a separate dedicated channel in the LMA GASTRO (Trademark), directly into the oesophagus  by a gastroenterologist. A maximum of three attempts to insert the upper-gastrointestinal endoscope is allowed before considered a failure.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endoscopic insertion success rate (binary outcome). The number of endoscopic attempts will be noted and considered a failure if the insertion was not successful in three attempts </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be recorded after LMA GASTRO (Trademark) insertion with the insertion of the endoscope</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endoscopic first attempt success rate (binary outcome)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be recorded after LMA GASTRO (Trademark) insertion on insertion of the endoscope. Defined successful insertion of endoscope into the oesophagus on first attempt. A second attempt will be recorded if the endoscope is removed from the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) device</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of endoscope insertion (binary outcome) graded as easy or difficult by the attending gastroenterologist. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Graded as easy or difficult (binary outcome) on insertion of the endoscope. If the device could be inserted without any manipulation or requiring 1 manipulation, it is graded as 'easy. If there was more than one manipulation required, it is graded as difficult</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LMA GASTRO success rate (binary outcome). The number of LMA GASTRO (Trademark)attempts will be noted, and considered a failure if the insertion was not successful in three attempts </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will recorded after induction of anaesthesia at insertion of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>First attempt LMA GASTRO (Trademark) success rate defined as a successful insertion on first attempt (binary outcome). A second attempt will be recorded if the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) is removed from the upper airway and reinserted</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will recorded after induction of anaesthesia at insertion of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of  LMA GASTRO (Trademark) insertion by the attending anaesthetist. Insertion graded as easy or difficult (binary outcome). This grading is based on manipulations required for insertion. The following maneuvers are included: (i) chin lift, (ii) jaw thrust, (iii) head extension and (iv) neck flexion</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will recorded after induction of anaesthesia at insertion of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lowest oxygen saturation intraoperatively (continuous outcome) measured using pulse oximetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded intraoperatively before patient transfer to postoperative recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sore throat defined as painful (binary outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded after removal of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) in the postoperative recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood on LMA GASTRO (Trademark) . Defined as the visualisation of macroscopic presence of blood on the device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded after removal of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark)  in the postoperative recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Airway compromise (binary outcome) defined as an airway event requiring airway intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded after removal of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) in the postoperative recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative laryngospasm defined as stridor which may progress to complete obstruction, increased respiratory effort, tracheal tug, paradoxical respiratory effort, oxygen desaturation with or without bradycardia, or airway obstruction which does not respond to a Guedel airway</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded after removal of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) in the postoperative recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absence of audible LMA GASTRO (Trademark) leak by applying positive pressure of 20cm H2O for a minimum of 3 seconds    </outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be recorded after the insertion of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark) and connection to breathing circuit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fully inflated LMA GASTRO (Trademark) cuff volumes </outcome>
      <timepoint>Cuff volumes will be recorded directly after insertion of the LMA GASTRO (Trademark)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total propofol dose (mg) </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be the total intraoperative propofol dose measured from induction of anaesthesia until the end of the endoscopic procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ASA I II, older than 18 years of age, fasted at least 6 hours for solids and 2 hours for clear liquids, undergoing elective upper gastro-intestinal endoscopic procedures requiring deep sedation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients at significant risk of pulmonary aspiration will be excluded based on anaesthetic clinical judgment after performing a clinical risk assessment. The clinical risk assessment will be performed based on patient history (focussing particularly on risk factors for aspiration) and physical examination to establish the risk of aspiration prior to enrolment. Possible risk factors for aspiration include:  
1. Increased gastric content: delayed gastric emptying including lap band in situ, gastric hyper secretion, overfeeding, lack of fasting (less than six hours solids and two hours for clear fluid).
2. Increased tendency to regurgitate: symptomatic or uncontrolled gastro-oesophageal reflux, oesophageal strictures, Zenker Diverticulum, achalasia.
3. Laryngeal incompetence: Emergency surgery, head injuries, cerebral infarct, neuromuscular disorders (Parkinsons disease, Gullian Barre), muscular dystrophies (cerebral palsy, cranial neuropathies)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Nil</concealment>
    <sequence>Nil</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will be performed using SPSS version 21 and R-studio. Mean,standard deviation values will be estimated for continued outcomes while frequency and percentage will be computed for binary outcomes including sex, 95% Confidence intervals around the poiont estimate will be caculated where appropriate for the primary and secondary outcomes. Descriptive statistics will be used to present the results. P-value =0.05 are considered significant. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>12/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>292</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Hobart Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>48 Liverpool Street, Hobart, Tasmania, 7000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Hobart Hospital Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ground Floor, Ray White Building, 25 Argyle St, Hobart TAS 7000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The overall aim of the project is to demonstrate the utility of the newly developed novel laryngeal mask airway (LMA) device called the LMAGastro (Trademark) which is a first for laryngeal mask airway (LMA) use in upper gastrointestinal endoscopy procedures. The devices novel design features include firstly a dedicated endoscopic channel for entry into the oesophagus and secondly, a dedicated airway channel and cuff to protect the airway. 

The hypothesis is: the LMAGastro (Trademark) will have a high endoscopic success rate and provide a clinically satisfactory protected airway during upper gastrointestinal endoscopy procedures under anaesthesia.

Gastroenterologists wont change practice unless endoscopic success rates are very high.  We are anticipating that the modified airway device (being developed with TELEFLEX and in collaboration with the Gastroenterology Department of the RHH) will not only provide reliable and superior upper gastro-intestinal access, but also provide airway protection and better anaesthesia monitoring of the patient, both significantly enhancing patient safety leading to a change in practice. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
Hobart TAS 7001
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0014514</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nico Terblanche</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, Royal Hobart Hospital, 48 Liverpool Street, Hobart, TAS, 7000</address>
      <phone>+61361667866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nico.terblanche@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Robyn Seale </name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, Royal Hobart Hospital, 48 Liverpool Street, Hobart, TAS, 7000</address>
      <phone>+613 6166 8977</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.seale@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nico Terblanche</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, Royal Hobart Hospital, 48 Liverpool Street, Hobart, TAS, 7000</address>
      <phone>+61361667866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nico.terblanche@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nico Terblanche</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, Royal Hobart Hospital, 48 Liverpool Street, Hobart, TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61361667866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nico.terblanche@ths.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>