<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83683">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000190202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of public health education on Taenia solium transmission</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of pig farmers' health education intervention against monitoring alone on the incidence rate of cysticercosis in sentinel pigs in Mbulu district, Tanzania</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cysticercosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Taeniosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Health education intervention.  A health educational package was developed with community participation.  The intervention package consisted of a training manual, a video programme, two posters, a leaflet and booklet.  In the first stage, local livestock/agricultural extension agents and health workers were updated on Taenia solium cysticercosis and taeniosis by the principal investigator, and practised on how to educate smallholder pig farners on the problem.  This training lasted for two days, approximately two hours each day.  In the second stage, a trained extension agent addressed smallholder pig farmers on Taenia solium using the training manual and posters in a special seminar.  Thereafter, seminar participants watched a 14-minute video on Taenia solium.  The video was produced locally and acted by the local people.  Finally, each participant was given a booklet and a leaflet to take home.  Pig farmers' training was a one-day intervention that lasted for approximately two hours.  The health education package informed smallholder pig farmers on the mode of transmission, impact, prevention and control of Taenia solium, a zoonotic parasite that was highly prevalent in Mbulu district, northern Tanzania.  Pig farmers' education was administered at village level.  Assessment of specific knowledge, practices and incidence of porcine cysticercosis was done before the intervention and one to two times after the intervention for a median of 4 months (range: 2-9 months).</interventions>
    <comparator>Monitoring alone.  The smallholder pig farmers in the control villages were not given any health education.  However, monitoring of specific knowledge, practices and incidence rate of porcine cysticercosis was done parallel to that in the intervention group, and compared with the baseline levels.  Like for the intervention group, assessment of knowledge, practices and incidence of porcine cysticercosis was done before the intervention and one to two times after the intervention for a median of 4 months (range: 2-9 months).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence rate of porcine cysticercosis in sentinel pigs (as an indirect measure of the risk of human cysticercosis).  The incidence rate of porcine cysticercosis was determined using lingual examination and antigen enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay methods.  The rates were later adjusted for the baseline prevalence of porcine cysticercosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ten to twelve months after intervention randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge and practices related to Taenia solium transmission.  Knowledge on the transmission of T. solium infections was assessed using face-to-face structured questionnaire interviews of household leaders or their representatives.  Practices related to T. solium were assessed using structured questionnaire interviews and direct observations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 10-12 months after intervention randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Pig-keeping villages not extensively studied for cysticercosis, and independent from other villages;
(2) A random sample of smallholder pig-keepng households in each study village;
(3) Willingness of the household head to participate in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Villages not keeping pigs;
(2) Villages overly studied for porcine cysticercosis previously, including the pilot study village;
(3) School children.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Intervention randomisation was done at village level.  Following identification of eligible villages based on the predetermined eligibility criteria, the 42 selected villages were numbered serially.  These numbers were then used in the intervention randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified allocation using a random number table from a statistic book.  The factor used to stratify the intervention allocation was the baseline village-level prevalence of porcine cysticercosis.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/04/2002</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>836</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Tanzania, United Republic Of</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Helena A. Ngowi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sokoine University of Agriculture, Department of Veterinary Medicine and Public Health, P. O. Box 3021, Morogoro</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Tanzania, United Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Danish International Development Agency (DANIDA), which is under the Ministry of Foreign Affairs</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Asiatisk Plads, DK-1448 Copenhagen K</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Denmark</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ayub A. Kassuku</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sokoine University of Agriculture, Department of Veterinary Microbiology and Parasitology, P. O. Box 3019, Morogoro</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Tanzania, United Republic Of</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this randomised controlled field intervention trial was to determine the effectiveness of health education in reducing porcine cysticercosis, with an overall objective of reducing human taeniosis and cysticercosis caused by the zoonotic tapeworm, Taenia solium, which is transmitted primarily between human and pigs.  The tapeworm causes serious neurological syndromes (commonly epilepsy) in human.  It was hypothesized that educating smallholder pig farmers on the causes, impact, and ways to control Taenia solium infections, would reduce the incidence rate of porcine cysticercosis and improve people's knowledge and practices related to the transmission of the parasite.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Ngowi HA, Carabin H, Kassuku AA, Mlozi MRS, Mlangwa JED, et al. (2008) A health-education intervention trial to reduce porcine cysticercosis in Mbulu District, Tanzania.  Prev Vet Med 85: 5267.

2. Ngowi HA, Mlangwa JED, Carabin H, Mlozi MRS, Kassuku AA, et al. (2007) Financial efficiency of health and pig management education intervention in controlling porcine cysticercosis in Mbulu District, northern Tanzania.  Available: http://www.cipav.org.co/lrrd/lrrd19/5/ngow19062.htm.  Accessed 30 May 2007. 

3. Ngowi HA, Tolma EL, Kassuku AA, Mlozi MRS, Mlangwa JED, et al. (2007) Using the PRECEDE model to plan a health promotion strategy for control of Taenia solium infections in northern Tanzania. Int J Health Promot Educ 45: 41-48.

4. Ngowi HA, Mlangwa JED, Mlozi MRS, Tolma EL, Kassuku AA, et al. (2009). Implementation and evaluation of a health-promotion strategy for control of Taenia solium infections in northern Tanzania.  Int J Health Promot Educ 47: 24-34.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Institute for Medical Research (NIMR)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2448, Ocean Road, P. O. Box 9653, Dar es Salaam</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/10/2001</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NIM/HQ/R.8a/Vol IX/88</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Tanzania, United Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helena A. Ngowi</name>
      <address>Sokoine University of Agriculture, Department of Veterinary Medicine and Public Health, P. O. Box 3021, Morogoro</address>
      <phone>+255232604542</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hngowi@suanet.ac.tz</email>
      <country>Tanzania, United Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helena A. Ngowi</name>
      <address>Sokoine University of Agriculture, Department of Veterinary Medicine and Public Health, P. O. Box 3021, Morogoro</address>
      <phone>+255232604542</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hngowi@suanet.ac.tz</email>
      <country>Tanzania, United Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>