<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371106">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000402347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Endoscopic ablation of dysplastic Barretts oesophagus</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Endoscopic ablation of dysplastic Barretts oesophagus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1185-4732</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Barrett's oesophagus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>oesophageal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Oesophageal (gullet)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Therapeutic intervention for patients with dysplastic barrett's oesophagus or early oesophageal cancer. Patients will undergo hybrid-Argon plasma coagulation during gastroscopy to ablate the dysplastic tissue. This will involve removal of visible lesions of Barretts Oesophagus that will be confirmed by microscopic assessment as part of clinical care. During the gastroscopy a salt-water solution will be injected into the submucosa of the oesophageal wall and thereafter the affected area will be treated with Argon Plasma Coagulation. 

The procedure will be performed by dr Saxena, who is a highly qualified gastroenterologist and specialized in the treatment of barretts oesophagus. The procedure will approximately take 30 minutes. Thereafter patients will be followed during a follow-up period of 5 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Remission of barrett's neoplasia and metaplasia. This will be assessed by taking biopsies during follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary timepjoint is one year after treatment.

Patients undergo endoscopic follow-up after treatment at 3, 6, 12, 18, 24, 30, 36, 42, 48, 54 and 60 months in which biospies will be obtained to review any recurrence of dysplasia. 

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The total number of procedures carried out with Hybrid Argon Plasma Coagulation (HAPC) per participant. 
It is a prospective trial with a follow-up of 5 years. Review of medical records will be used during follow-up period. </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 year follow-up post initial ablation procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the rates of minor and major complications in patients undergoing HAPC for the treatment of dysplastic Barretts Oesophagus '(BO). This is a composite secondary outcome.
a.	Minor complications include pain, dysphagia, gastrointestinal bleeding without need for blood transfusion and a significant drop in hemoglobin (Hb &lt; 2 g/dl), and fever during the first 24 hours. 
b.	Major complications include strictures that cause dysphagia and require dilatation, perforation, gastrointestinal bleeding with a drop of hemoglobin values (Hb &gt; 2 g/dl) or requiring transfusion and fever persisting for more than 24 hours.

The outcomes will be assessed by the patient charts and questions during follow-up visit</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years follow-up post initial ablation procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the recurrence rates of dysplasia and IM with HAPC. This will be assessed during follow-up by taking biopsies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years follow-up post initial ablation procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess cost per patient of HAPC for the removal of residual BO.  The costs will be assessed  based on the costs of equipment that is used, the costs for the procedure, and the costs of complications assessed from hospital medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years follow-up post initial ablation procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Barrett's oesophagus with low grade dysplasia, high grade dysplasia or T1a adenocarcinoma</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a)	C value greater than 6 cm using the Prague criteria
b)	Prior ER for adenocarcinoma with histological diagnosis of greater than or equal to T1b; 
c)	Presence of endoscopically visible abnormalities at the time of initial APC treatment (additional endoscopic resection is allowed);
d)	Presence of cancer in random biopsies obtained at the mapping endoscopy, 8-12 weeks before initial HAPC treatment without endoscopic resection of cancer lesion for staging; 
e)	Pregnancy
f)	Patients in whom complete eradication is not considered a relevant treatment goal or in whom additional treatment is contraindicated;
g)	Patients with incomplete healing post-endoscopic resection despite adequate PPI-medication;
h)	Prior ablative therapy in the oesophagus;
i)	Significant oesophageal stenosis prior to initial HAPC treatment defined as a stenosis that cannot be passed by a therapeutic endoscope or a stenosis that has been dilated endoscopically before.
j)	Presence of esophageal varices
k)	Anticoagulant therapy (apart from aspirin or NSAIDS) that cannot be discontinued prior to HAPC or incorrectable hemostatic disorders 
l)	Life expectancy less than 2 years</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>pilot study</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd, Camperdown NSW 2050, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd, Camperdown NSW 2050, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this pilot trial is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of Hybrid-APC ablation for the treatment of Barrett's oesophagus.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to participate in this trial if you are aged 18-85 years and have been diagnosed with Barrett's oesophagus with low grade dysplasia, high grade dysplasia or T1a adenocarcinoma.

Study details
All participants enrolled in this trial will receive the Hybrid-APC ablation procedure which involves an gastroscopy with use of so called Hybrid-APC ablation. This means that a saline solution (NaCl 0.9%) will be injected into the submucosal lining of the affected area and thereafter the affected tissue will be coagulated using APC.  Participants will then be followed up every three months during 5 years of follow-up to assess disease progression and whether any additional procedures are required.

It is hoped that the findings from this pilot trial will provide preliminary information regarding the safety and efficacy of ablation for Barrett's oesophagus, which may be used to inform larger clinical trials in the future.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Review Committee Royal Prince Alfred hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research ethics and governance office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW  2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Payal Saxena</name>
      <address>Dr Payal Saxena, BE(Hons), M Biomed E, MBBS (Hons), FRACP
Gastroenterologist and Interventional Endoscopist
Suite G10, 100 Carillon Ave Newtown 2042 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61295162033</phone>
      <fax>+61295160778</fax>
      <email>psaxena1@jhmi.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Payal Saxena</name>
      <address>Dr Payal Saxena, BE(Hons), M Biomed E, MBBS (Hons), FRACP
Gastroenterologist and Interventional Endoscopist
Suite G10, 100 Carillon Ave Newtown 2042 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61295162033</phone>
      <fax>+61295160778</fax>
      <email>psaxena1@jhmi.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Payal Saxena</name>
      <address>Dr Payal Saxena, BE(Hons), M Biomed E, MBBS (Hons), FRACP
Gastroenterologist and Interventional Endoscopist
Suite G10, 100 Carillon Ave Newtown 2042 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61295162033</phone>
      <fax>+61295160778</fax>
      <email>psaxena1@jhmi.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Payal Saxena</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>