<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364166">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000516785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Use of Navigation to Achieve Soft Tissue Balance in Total Knee Arthroplasty  A Randomised Clinical Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Use of Navigation to Achieve Soft Tissue Balance in Total Knee Arthroplasty  A Randomised Clinical Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1142-5684 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>knee arthropathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients receive a Triathlon posterior stabilised, fixed bearing total knee replacement (Stryker Orthopedics, Mahwah, NJ) inserted via a standardised medial para-patellar approach. In the navigated group, initial gaps, at 135N of tension provided by the tensiometer, are recorded after the tibial cut at 90 degrees flexion and full extension. The Stryker version 4.0 software is able to calculate the size of the femoral component after registration of the epicondyles and registration of the bony morphology of the anterior and posterior femoral condyles. Based on the initial gap measurements, the surgeon has a number of options to equilibrate the flexion and extension gaps. These include downsizing the femoral prosthesis or modifying the position of the femoral prosthesis in the anteroposterior or proximodistal planes. The software uses algorithms that take a mean value of the registered femoral transepicondylar axis and the registered femoral anteroposterior axis (Whitesides line) to determine axial rotation of the femur. The surgeon aims for the femoral bony cut to have a value of 0+/-2 degrees external rotation based on the software measurement. After the femoral cuts, the gaps at 135N are measured again. The surgeon then makes further soft tissue releases as necessary to try and equalise the mediolateral gaps to within 2mm of each other. Final gap measurements (without the trial components in place) are recorded once again at 135N of tension. 135N was chosen as the tension force as it was felt that this level of tension produced sufficient strain to overcome any laxity in the soft tissues to allow reliable measurement of gaps.
The duration of this procedure is approximately 80 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>In the non-navigated group, a standard total knee replacement procedure is carried out without the use of navigation (other than for data recording purposes). When the surgeon is satisfied by means of feel that he has achieved a balanced knee arthroplasty, then the joint gaps are recorded (without the trial components in place) at 90 degrees flexion and at full extension. Measurements are recorded by an unscrubbed assistant using the navigation software with the navigation screen hidden from the surgeon. All measurements are carried out with a fixed tension of 135 Newtons provided by the tensiometer across the joint.
The duration of this procedure is approximately 80 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Final gap measurements (without the trial components in place) were recorded via the navigation software at 135N of tension. Tension was applied and maintained by the tensionometer. Final readings were taken from the navigation software which is used in both groups for this purpose. In the non-navigated group, this information is used purely for data recording as no figures are fed back to the surgeon. Gaps (in millimetres) measured are mediolateral difference in full extension and 90 degrees flexion and difference in flexion and extension gap.</outcome>
      <timepoint>intra-operatively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In a similar way, the accuracy of bony cuts in terms of coronal plane alignment in the femur and tibia and femoral rotation is recorded in both groups via the navigation software. Measurements (degrees) are recorded for resection of the distal femur and proximal tibia as well as femoral rotation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>intra-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Final overall limb alignment is also measured via the navigation software in both groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>intra-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Initial and final on table range of motion are also recorded via the navigation software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>intra-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome scores for pain, function and disability will be recorded pre-operatively and again at routine review at 6 weeks, 6 months and 5 years post surgery using the Knee Society Score, Oxford knee score, SF-12 and WOMAC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 5 years post-operatively at routine review</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>all patients presenting for primary total knee replacement</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>previous bony surgery on the operated knee</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients provided with information sheets and informed consent obtained to enter this study at the time of being listed for the procedure. Following randomisation, allocations stored in theatre by means of envelopes allocating patients to either a non-navigated or navigated group. Envelopes were opened sequentially in theatre prior to the incision being made. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation was performed by a statistician using the Sampsize program with a block size of 4 and allocation ratio of 1:1.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed with either parametric or non-parametric methods according to data type after normality testing. Levene's test will be used to examine homogeneity of variance.
Power analysis indicates that with 80% power, 5% significance level and a standardised difference of 1.0, a minimum of 17 patients are needed in each group. To ensure this minimum requirement was met, we aimed for 20 knees per group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/05/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Holy Spirit Northside - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Hugh English</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brisbane Orthopaedic Specialist Services
Holy Spirit Northside Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this clinical study we aim to assess the difference, if any, in intra-operative soft tissue balancing in computer  navigated and conventional total knee replacement (TKR). Computer navigated TKRs have been shown to produce better alignment of the components compared to  conventional TKR. Whether there is any long term advantage of computer navigated TKR in terms of function and durability and patient satisfaction is as yet not proven.
In this prospective, randomised, patient blinded study, we  shall measure the ligament balancing in both groups intra-operatively. This will be done using a tensiometer instrument. There is no morbidity associated with the use of this device which gives an instantaneous reading.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's and Holy Spirit Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Holy Spirit Northside Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/08/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00324</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Health Service District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/08/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00168</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hugh English</name>
      <address>Brisbane Orthopaedic Specialist Services
Holy Spirit Northside Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 1300 436454</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hugh@boss.net</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Whitehouse</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3139 6672</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.whitehouse@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Whitehouse</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3139 6672</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.whitehouse@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Whitehouse</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside
QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3139 6672</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.whitehouse@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>