<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336655">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000742976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Stand Up Victoria: a trial to determine whether environmental modification and behavioural counselling can lead to reductions in workplace sitting time in office workers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In office workers, does environmental modification combined with behavioural counselling, compared to no change, lead to reductions in workplace sitting time.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prolonged workplace sedentary (sitting) time</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention lasts for 3 months and consists of four distinct components: (1) an initial Unit Representatives Consultation involving a broad range of Unit Representatives. This consultation will include an explanation of the role of organisational, environmental, and individual factors in determining occupational sitting time. Furthermore, unit representatives will be asked to workshop appropriate strategies to reduce sitting time at their workplace; (2) a whole-of-workplace Information Session. The session will (a) outline recent research findings on the health consequences of too much sitting, (b) provide a summary of what emerged in the Unit Representatives Consultation and (c) provide summary feedback of sedentary and activity time generated from the baseline assessment; (3) Environmental Modification  involving installation of sit-to-stand workstations for individual participants. The sit-stand workstation allows the employee to easily alternate their working posture between sitting and standing; and (4) Support for Behavioural Change which includes (a) an initial one-on-one individual consultation with project staff (i.e. health promotion and allied health professionals) trained in motivational interviewing techniques and (b) four telephone support calls over 3 months in support of initiation and maintenance of sedentary behaviour change.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants within the control workplaces will be advised that the aims of the study are to examine the patterns of physical activity and sedentary time in office workers, and how these may be associated with cardio-metabolic and anthropometric markers. The control group will receive the same assessments as the intervention group at the same time-points.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A 30 minutes/day reduction in objectively-assessed (using physical activity monitors) workplace sedentary time</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3 months, 9 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>An increase of 5 breaks/day in workplace sedentary time, objectively measured using physical activity monitors</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3 months, 9 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objectively measured non-workplace sedentary time and physical activity time. Sitting time and physical activity levels will be measured using an ActiGraph accelerometer (instensity of activity) and an activPAL inclinometer (posture)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3 months, 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine the effect of the intervention on cardiometabolic markers of health and disease including:
1) body composition inclusing waist circumference, BMI, and percent fat mass using bioimpedance analysis
2) fasting blood levels of glucose, insulin and lipids analysed by an accredited pathology laboratory
3) blood pressure will be measured by an Omron automatic blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3 months, 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore workplace and individual-level mediators (how did the intervention work?) and moderators (for whom did it work?) of change using a specially formulated questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3 months, 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Working at least 0.6 FTE; Aged 18-65 years; Speaking English; Having designated access to a telephone, internet and desk within the workplace</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Being pregnant; Being non-ambulatory and/or have a planned absence from work for &gt; 2 weeks or a planned relocation to another worksite during the 3-month intervention period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This trial involves cluster randomisation of whole workplaces to the Intervention or Control arms, rather than individual partcipants. Stratification will be based on workplace size (small: 20-50 employees, large: 51-70 employees) in order to obtain balanced numbers of sites and employees in the Intervention and the Control arms. Sites will be enrolled and then randomised until the required sample size is reached.

Allocation concealment is done via central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/11/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>320</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>75 Commercial Rd
Melbourne  VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>VicHealth</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15-31 Pelham St (PO Box 154) 
Carlton South VIC 3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Queensland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 2
Public Health Building
School Of Population Health
University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston
QLD 4006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Researchers from the Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute in Melbourne, University of Queensland, University of Melbourne and Deakin University are collaborating with Department of Human Services to measure the physical activity levels of office workers and to investigate the relationship between physical activity and health. Research over the last decade has shown that low overall activity patterns throughout the day increase the risk of many chronic conditions such as type 2 diabetes, heart disease, and some cancers. 
Findings from this project will provide us with valuable information to develop and improve workplace health promotion programs. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Dunstan</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4
99 Commerical Rd
Melbourne, Victoria
Australia 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Dunstan@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Dunstan</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4
99 Commerical Rd
Melbourne, Victoria
Australia 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Dunstan@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Glen Wiesner</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute
Level 4, 99 Commercial Road
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 85321857</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8533 1100</fax>
      <email>glen.wiesner@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Dunstan</name>
      <address>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute Level 4 99 Commerical Rd Melbourne, Victoria Australia 3004   </address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Dunstan@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>