<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362877">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000860864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Maxigesic PE Study: Determining the bioavailaiblity of Maxigesic PE in healthy adult volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Maxigesic PE Study: Comparative, randomised, single dose, three period, cross-over, open-label study to determine the bioavailability of AFT Pharmaceuticals test product Maxigesic PE relative to reference I Maxigesic and reference II phenylephrine in healthy adult volunteers under fasting conditions.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pharmacokinetics of Maxigesic PE in Healthy Volunteers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention:
Maxigesic PE as a single oral dose of two tablets (total dose paracetamol 1000mg, ibuprofen 150mg and phenylephrine 10mg).

Cross-over study with 7 day washout period between dosing.

Note: Maxigesic PE is the brand name of this product. Each tablet of Maxigesic PE contains 500mg paracetamol, 150mg ibuprofen and 5mg phenylephrine.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator 1:
Maxigesic as a single oral dose of two tablets (total dose paracetamol 1000mg and ibuprofen 300mg).
Comparator 2:
Phenylephrine as a single oral dose of two tablets (total dose phenylephrine 10mg).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe the pharmacokinetics of Maxigesic PE and identify whether a pharmacokinetic interaction exists between phenylephrine and paracetamol or ibuprofen when given concomitantly.

This will be assessed by taking blood samples which will be assyed for paracetamol, ibuprofen and phenylephrine concentrations and the pharmacokinetic parameters AUC0-inf, AUC0-t, Cmax, Ke, Tmax and T1/2 will be determined. These pharmacokinetic parameters will be compared between groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples will be collected pre-dose and at 5, 15, 30, 45 minutes and 1, 1.25, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0, 6.0, 8.0, 10.0 and 12.0 hours after study drug administration.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine the safety and tolerability of Maxigesic PE. 

Safety will be evaluated during each study period, and for 7 days following study drug administration.  Acute safety evaluations will be performed during each study period by recording spontaneously reported AE's and by clinical assessments (incl. heamatology &amp; biochemistry). 

Known NSAID adverse effects (i.e. GI ulceration, indigestion/stomach pain, GI bleeding, bronchospasm, water retention, renal failure, skin reactions and thromboembolic events), known paracetamol adverse effects (i.e. clinical evidence of hepatotoxicity) and known phenylephrine adverse effects (i.e. bradycardia, hypertension) will be compared between groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse event reporting will be by spontaneous reporting up to 7 days after dosing, and by a follow up phone call 7 days after the last dose of the study medication.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Provide written informed consent
2) Have Body Mass Index between 18.5 ang 30.0 kg/m2
3) Healty volunteers as determined by medical history, physical examination, ECG, vital signs and laboratory tests</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Women who are pregnant or nursing
2) Women who are unwilling to take adequate contraceptive precaustions or who are unwilling to undergo urine pregnancy testing
3) History of alcohol or drug abuse or dependency
4) Have a history of allergy or hypersensitivity to ibuprofen, aspirin, any other NSAID, paracetamol or phenylephrine
5) Have haemopoetic, renal or hepatic disease, immunosupression. Have a history of gastric ulceration, indigestion, stomach pain, GI bleeding or bleeding disorders. Are currently suffering from dehydration from diarrhoea and/or vomiting. Have a history of severe asthma. Have a history of severe hypertension, ventricular tachycardia or other cardiac disease.  Have insulin dependent diabetes mellitus.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will occur once participant eligability is confirmed. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be generated by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Jordan</country>
      <state>Amman</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to describe the pharmacokinetics of Maxigesic PE and identify whether a pharmacokinetic interaction exists between phenylephrine and paracetamol or ibuprofen when given together.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Jordan Food and Drug Administration</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>P.O.Box  811951 
Amman</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2/4/34/20003</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Jordan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Potts</name>
      <address>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</address>
      <phone>+64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Potts</name>
      <address>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</address>
      <phone>+64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>