<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343033">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/06/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000599976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effective aftercare for patients with substance abuse who have been court-ordered to involuntary care.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The use of case management to promote abstinence and linkage to care in patients with substance abuse who have been court-ordered to care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-0303</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Substance abuse</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Case management according to Comprehensive Case Management for Substance Abuse Treatment,
Treatment Improvement Protocol (TIP) Series 27. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.
The case manager and patient assessed the situation using ten different instruments. The case manager, patient, social worker and institutional staff planned the interventions for the first six months in aftercare. The case manager and patient met at least once a week to plan for the week. The case manager monitored the plans together with patient. The case manager, patient and social worker met with social worker once a month to plan interventions.
The case manager sent in description of interventions to project leader once a week and got weekly feed-back on adherence to manual. Interventions were according to plan and could include relapse intervention, visit to psychiatric out-patient unit, coffee with relatives etc.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual; Conference with patient, social worker and staff at the institution in order to assess and plan for aftercare. Aftercare interventions according to plan which could include conference with social worker once a week to once a month.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abstinence was measured by the following questionnaires; Time-Line-Follow-Back (TLFB), Alcohol Use Disorders Identification test (AUDIT), The Addiction Severity Index (ASI) and by a  predecessor to Drug Use Identification Test (AUDRUG).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After intervention and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Linkage to care; access to out-patient hospital care, in-patient hospital care, social servicesand institutional care. Patients and significant others were asked during interview to specify which type of care the patient had had access to in aftercare.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After intervention and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Court-order to involuntary care, residency in one of nine municipalities, involuntary care in one of three institutions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No exclusion criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>At intake the patient was provided with written and oral information about the study by a research assistant. After consent to participation the patient was interviewed by the research assistant. After the interview the patient was allocated to intervention. 
The person who determined if a subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial was unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the subject would be allocated. Allocation was concealed and performed after information on five variables was sent to an administrator off-site. The administrator used a computerized system - urn randomization (reference: Stout RL, Wirtz PW, Carbonari JP, Del Boca FKJ. Ensuring balanced distribution of prognostic factors in treatment outcome research. Journal of Studies of Alcohol. Supplement, 1994: 12, 70-75).</concealment>
    <sequence>By a computer-based urn randomization(Stout RL, Wirtz PW, Carbonari JP, Del Boca FKJ. Ensuring balanced distribution of prognostic factors in treatment outcome research. Journal of Studies of Alcohol. Supplement, 1994: 12, 70-75. The covariates used in the system were: age groups (18-24, 25-39, 40-), gender (men, women),  housing (yes, no),  substance abuse (alcohol, heroin, others) and MADRS (0-7 points, 8-10 points).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Skane</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Marianne Larsson Lindahl</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clinical Alcohol Research, 108 Skane University Hospital-Malmo, 20501 Malmo</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Sweden</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health and Social Affairs Task Force - Mobilize against Drugs</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Fredsgatan 8, 103 33 Stockholm</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>County administration Lansstyrelsen i Skane lan</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>205 15 Malmo</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The National Board of Institutional Care</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Box 16363
103 26 Stockholm,</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is one of very few randomised trials on case management in a European setting. It examined the impact of case management on substance abuse and access to treatment after discharge from court-ordered institutional care.  Court-ordered patients with substance abuse (n=36) were randomly assigned to either case management or treatment-as-usual during six months in aftercare. Data was collected at intake, at conclusion of intervention and at 6 months follow-up with a follow-up rate of 97%. Significant others and social workers were interviewed about the patients' need and use of care at intake and during aftercare. Significantly more patients in the case management group were abstinent during intervention.  No differences were detected in regard to access to care between study groups. A subgroup analysis showed that patients with a continuous drug abuse had greater access to care and significantly more days in inpatient care. Our findings suggest that case management is useful in order to retain abstinence in aftercare following court-ordered treatment.  The social welfare and hospital care systems seem to provide care irrespective of case manager-intervention. The study design, interventions and assessments instruments were well received by patients with 90% consent to participation but needs to be replicated with a larger population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentation: International Academy of Law and Mental Health (2005) Paris, France. International Academy of Law and Mental Health (2007) Padua, Italy. International conference on Health promoting hospitals and health services (2011) Turku, Finland.
Publication: Case management in aftercare of 
court-ordered substance abusers. A randomised trial. (submitted)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Regional Ethical Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Box 133 
221 00 LUND</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/02/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LU 955-02, Li 03-002</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Sweden</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marianne Larsson Lindahl</name>
      <address>Clinical Alcohol Research,
108 Skane University Hospital-Malmo,
205 02 Malmo</address>
      <phone>+4640336965</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marianne.larsson_lindahl@med.lu.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marianne Larsson Lindahl</name>
      <address>Clinical Alcohol Research,
108 Skane University Hospital-Malmo,
205 02 Malmo</address>
      <phone>+4640336965</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marianne.larsson_lindahl@med.lu.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eva Skagert</name>
      <address>Clinical Alcohol Research,
108, Skane University Hospital-Malmo,
205 02 Malmo</address>
      <phone>+4640332978</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eva.skagert@med.lu.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>