<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369391">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001190594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of a physical activity promotion and fall prevention plan on physical activity and falls in community-dwelling people aged 60+.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of a physical activity promotion and fall prevention intervention compared to a nutrition intervention on physical activity participation and falls in community-dwelling people aged 60 years and over?
 </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CHAnGE trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Falls

</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity participation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Participants allocated to the physical activity and fall prevention intervention arm:
1. Will receive a printed booklet about physical activity and fall prevention for healthy ageing.
2. Will undergo an initial two-hour physiotherapy session (at home), in which:
a) A fall risk assessment will be conducted by a research physiotherapist. This will take approximately 10 minutes to complete and will include assessment of key fall risk factors such as balance, mobility, vision, medication use and sensation.
b) A fall prevention and physical activity plan will be jointly developed by the participant and the research therapist using a motivational interviewing approach. This will involve goal setting and developing strategies to maximise motivation and maintenance of increased physical activity and strategies to prevent falls.
c) A pedometer-based activity monitor and feedback device will be provided to all participants by the research therapist who will also demonstrate its use. Participants will be able to choose a device which is able to connect to the internet (e.g. Fitbit activity tracker) or a simple pedometer that does not connect to the internet. 
3. Participants will receive access to individual, telephone-based health coaching provided by the research physiotherapist. Each health coaching session will last for approximately 30 minutes and will focus on strategies for increasing physical activity and preventing falls, through behaviour modification and goal setting. Participants will be encouraged to access the service approximately once a fortnight for the first 6 months and then on a monthly basis for the remaining 6 months of the study, so the intervention period is one year in total. Access to this service will cease at the conclusion of the study.
Adherence to the intervention will be monitored through records kept regarding the number of health coaching sessions completed and the number of steps taken as recorded by the internet-based activity tracker or by the steps recorded on a paper-based pedometer diary.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2: A nutrition intervention aiming to encourage healthy eating. It involves the provision of a printed booklet containing information about healthy eating based on the Australian Dietary Guidelines and access to the NSW Ministry of Health 'Get Healthy' telephone-based health coaching service. Participants will be encouraged to access the service approximately once a fortnight for the first 6 months and then on a monthly basis for the remaining 6 months of the study. During this time participants will have the chance to set healthy eating goals and discuss strategies for achieving those goals with the health coach who is a qualified health professional. Each health coaching telephone call will last approximately 30-60 minutes as deemed required by the health professional. Access to this service will cease at the conclusion of the study. Adherence to the intervention will be monitored through records kept by the 'Get Healthy' service regarding the number of health coaching sessions completed </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: Physical activity participation assessed as counts/minute over a 7-day period using the Actigraph accelerometer.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Number of falls in the 12 months after randomisation measured with 12 monthly postal fall calendars

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 12 months after randomisation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: The proportion of fallers in the twelve months after randomisation measured with 12 month falls calendars

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: The proportion of Actigraph wear time in sedentary, light, moderate and vigorous physical activity

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint:6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Body Mass Index measured by self-report

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: Goal attainment using The Goal Attainment Scale 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 5: Mobility-related confidence assessed using the Modified Gait Efficacy Scale

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 6: Quality of life, will be assessed using the EQ-5D-5L
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 7:  Fear of falling measured using the 7 item Falls Efficacy Scale International

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 8: Risk-taking behavior assessed using a 5-item self-report tool

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 9: Wellbeing assessed with the 26-item COMPAS-W scale of wellbeing

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 10: Mood assessed with the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 11: Physical activity assessed with the self-reported Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire (IPEQ)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 12: Disability assessed using the World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule II (WHODAS II) 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eating habits assessed with questions from the Australian Health Survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will:
Be aged 60 years and over;
Live in a private dwelling or retirement village and; 
Regularly (at least once every two months) attend meetings or social events at the participating established community-based group 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People will be excluded if they: 
a) are already meeting the Australian Physical Activity Guidelines for older adults (operationalised as 30 minutes of moderate intensity physical activity five days a week assessed using the Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire and have had a falls risk assessment and intervention program in the past year 
b) have a cognitive impairment (a diagnosis of dementia or a Memory Impairment Screen score of less than 5) 
c) have insufficient English language skills to fully participate in the program 
d) are unable to leave the house without physical assistance from another person or
e) have a progressive neurological disease; or a medical condition precluding exercise 

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participating groups will be randomised to either the physical activity/fall prevention intervention or to the nutrition intervention by an independent randomisation service to ensure concealed allocation. Randomisation will occur after all participants in the group have completed all baseline measures to avoid recruitment bias.
</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-based minimisation method will be used. Stratification will be by rurality and socioeconomic status of the groups and whether the group purpose is related to physical activity.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A total of 30 clusters per group with 10 individuals in each cluster (i.e. 600 participants) will provide 90% power to detect a 10% between-group difference in the primary physical activity outcome. This calculation was undertaken in Stata 13 using the cluster sampsi command and assumed a between-group difference of 23 mean counts/min during wear time, standard deviation of 120, dropout rate of 20%, alpha of 5%, 0.6 correlation between baseline and final measures, and an intra-cluster correlation (ICC) of 0.01. The estimates of mean accelerometer counts per minute were taken from a large sample of accelerometer data. The 60 clusters will provide 80% power to detect as significant, at the 5% level, a 30% lower rate of falls in intervention group participants than control participants (IRR = 0.70) i.e. the primary falls outcome. For this calculation we used the user-written simulation-based nbpower command in Stata 13 and coefficients from previous studies: alpha (over-dispersion in the negative binomial regression model) was assumed to be 0.65 based on a previous trial. We assumed: a control group rate of falls of 0.06 per person month over the follow-up period as this was the rate in a study of a similar population; a design effect of 1.09 with an ICC of 0.01; and withdrawal of 6 clusters. An average follow-up period of 11 months was used to account for loss to follow-up. This sample size is also expected to be sufficient to detect between-group differences in the order of 10-15% for the eating habits outcome and the secondary outcome measures.
Intervention effects will be assessed by means of generalised estimating equations (GEE) models using an exchangeable correlation structure to account for correlation between individuals within the clusters. The number of falls per person-year will be analysed using negative binomial regression models to estimate the difference in rates between the groups after one year (primary outcome). For the continuously-scored primary and secondary outcome measures, Gaussian GEE regression adjusted with their corresponding baseline scores will be used to assess the effect of group allocation. Log-binomial GEE regression, or a robust Poisson regression in case of convergency issues will be used to compare groups on dichotomous outcome measures (proportion of fallers, proportion meeting physical activity cut-points). Planned sub-group analyses will assess differential effects of the intervention by baseline physical activity levels and history of falls. Secondary analyses using causal modelling will be conducted to establish intervention effects in people with greater adherence. Analyses will be conducted using the Stata 13 software package. All analyses will be pre-planned, conducted while masked to group allocation and will use an intention-to-treat approach. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute for Global Health, Sydney Medical School, The University of Sydney </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 5389 
Sydney 
NSW 2001 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> NHMRC Project Grant APP1083495</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We will conduct a cluster randomised trial (60 groups of older people) to evaluate two healthy ageing strategies among community-dwelling people who attend established community-based groups. The primary objective is to measure the effectiveness of:
a) a physical activity and fall prevention intervention including telephone-based health coaching and written information on physical activity and falls over a 12 month period, and
b) a nutrition intervention including telephone-based health coaching and written information on eating habits over 12 months.
The trial also aims to establish the impact of the interventions on physical activity guideline adherence, eating habits, body mass index, goal attainment, mobility confidence, quality of life, fear of falling, risk taking behaviour, wellbeing and mood.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>TIEDEMANN A, Rissel C, Howard K, Tong A, Merom D, Smith S, Wickham J, Bauman A, Lord SR, Vogler C, Lindley RI, Simpson JM, Allman-Farinelli M, Sherrington C. Health coaching and pedometers to enhance physical activity and prevent falls in community-dwelling people aged 60 years and over: study protocol for the Coaching for Healthy AGEing (CHAnGE) cluster randomised controlled trial. BMJ Open 2016; 6 (5): e012277</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office
Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Sherrington</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
GPO Box 5389
Sydney NSW 2001 Australia


</address>
      <phone>+61296570386</phone>
      <fax>+61296570301</fax>
      <email>csherrington@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anne Tiedemmann</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
GPO Box 5389
Sydney NSW 2001 Australia


</address>
      <phone>+61296570393</phone>
      <fax>+61296570301</fax>
      <email>atiedemann@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anne Tiedemann</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
GPO Box 5389
Sydney NSW 2001 Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61296570393</phone>
      <fax>+61296570301</fax>
      <email>atiedemann@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anne Tiedemann</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
GPO Box 5389
Sydney NSW 2001 Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61296570393</phone>
      <fax>+61296570301</fax>
      <email>atiedemann@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>