<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370393">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000441415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Buddy Study: Effect of buddy taping vs plaster casts on 5th finger (Boxer's Fractures)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is minimal intervention as effective as routine immobilisation in adults with an uncomplicated closed neck of 5th metacarpal fracture? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL KNOWN</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>5th metacarpal neck (Boxer) fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Comparison of traditional plaster casts vs simple buddy taping for 5th metacarpal neck fractures 

1.	Routine Care Group (Plaster Group): ulnar gutter slab plaster cast in position of safe immobilisation (POSI).  This will either be done by the on call plaster technician, or by a doctor, physiotherapist or nurse practitioner.  The cast will be changed to a fibreglass cast at 1 week (first fracture clinic) and removed at 3 weeks (second fracture clinic).  The patient will be seen again at 6 weeks (third fracture clinic) for repeat X-rays.  They will be followed up by phone at 12 weeks. 

2.	Minimal Intervention Group (Buddy Group): buddy strap between little and ring fingers.  This will either be done by the on call plaster technician, or by a doctor, physiotherapist or nurse practitioner.  This group will be followed up at 1 and 3 weeks (just review clinics with no further intervention) and at 6 weeks for repeat x-rays.  Strapping removed at 3 weeks.  They will be followed up at 12 weeks by phone.  

For both groups, one of the important functions of the fracture clinic follow up is to allow regular patient review.  Also, the patients are being followed up in specific clinics with hand surgeons (Dr Mike Thomas and Prof Randy Bindra) who were involved in the study design.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Control Group is the Plaster Group - this is the current standard of care in our hospital (Gold Coast University and Robina Hospitals) for the management of these injuries.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hand function: Measured using the Shortened Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand Outcome Measure (quickDASH).  Measured at baseline, 3, 6 and 12 weeks. </outcome>
      <timepoint>quickDASH measured at baseline at presentation to emergency.  Then remeasured at 3 and 6 weeks in fracture clinic, and again by phone at 12 weeks (these times reflect time post commencement of intervention).  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to work (days off).  Measured in days to return to work
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 1, 3, 6 and 12 weeks post commencement of intervention.  Specific question on f/u questionnaire.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health economic analysis - using HPQ  measured at 3 and 12 weeks.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 weeks and 12 weeks post commencement of intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grip strength
Objective measurements of strength
Grip strength measured with Jamar dynamometer as per Southampton Protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6  weeks post commencement of intervention with specific questions on questionnaire at weeks 3 and 6.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient pain  - Visual Analogue Scales 0-10.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post commencement of intervention.  Measured at each f/u point at 1, 3, 6 and 12 weeks post commencement of intervention.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fracture angulation - X-rays at baseline and at 6 weeks. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 weeks post commencement of intervention.  Angles to be checked by x2 orthopaedic trainees as well as formal radiologists report. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EQ-5D-3L assessment of health </outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at baseline and at 12 weeks post commencement of intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to sports and activities</outcome>
      <timepoint>Specific question on f/u questionnaire at 1, 3, 6 and 12 weeks.  Measured in days off / days to return to sport / activity </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of motion of hand</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 3 and 6 weeks.  Ability to touch fingertips to thenar eminence and thumb to base of little finger.  Yes/no answers.  Specific questionnaire on f/u at 3 and 6 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction 
VAS 0-10</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post commencement of intervention.  Measured at each f/u point at 1, 3, 6 and 12 weeks post commencement of intervention.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fracture healing - measured at 6 weeks on repeat x-ray</outcome>
      <timepoint>Repeat x-ray at 6 weeks to assess fracture healing at this point (6 weeks post intervention). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A 5th metacarpal neck or Boxers fracture is defined as: 
Fracture of the neck of 5th metacarpal 
Confirmed radiologically in at least 2 planes of view
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients less than 18 and over 70 years of age
Open fracture
Rotational deformity  
Intra-articular fracture
Communted fracture 
Associated tendon injury  
Polytrauma  other significant injuries sustained at the time of injury  
Unable/Unwilling to consent to study  i.e. intoxicated, dementia
Fracture angulation greater than 70 degrees at initial radiology 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sequentially numbered opaque envelopes.  Upon obtaining consent, consenting clinician opens next envelope in sequence (as generated below) and the patient is either allocated to Buddy or Plaster group.  Thus randomised.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomised sequence, to either Buddy or Plaster group.  </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Due to the nature of the intervention, impossible to blind.  </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size required for this study is calculated to be 98 patients (49 in each group) over both hospital campuses combined (Southport and Robina Hospital).  This sample size was based on the ability to detect a clinically significant difference in the quickDASH (score from 0-100) score of 10 points (with a standard deviation of 20 points) at 1, 3 and 6 weeks with 80% power</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>25/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>24/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>98</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Robina Hospital - Robina</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gold Coast University Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gold Coast University Hospital 

1 Hospital Boulevard 
Southport 
QLD 4215 
 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gold Coast University Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>

Gold Coast University Hospital 
1 Hospital Boulevard 
Southport 
QLD 4215 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Metacarpal neck fractures represent the most common hand injury, with 5th metacarpal fractures accounting for the majority   .  Known as Boxers Fractures, these injuries are commonly the result of a closed fist strike, and are seen more frequently  in young males, often associated with an aggressive strike, or a fall onto a fist during sporting activities. 
    
Traditionally, 5th metacarpal neck fractures have been managed with closed reduction and cast immobilisation and followed up in an orthopaedic clinic.   However, due to the nature of the injury and then anatomy of the hand musculature, closed reduction often has little benefit in reducing the fracture and improving angulation.  

Moreover, it has been shown that there is no functional deficit in healed fractures with up to 70 degrees of angulation, provided there is no rotational deformity of the fracture fragments .  Several orthopaedic and emergency departments now manage minimally-rotated Boxers Fractures with buddy strapping alone, thus encouraging mobilisation and an immediate return to work and activities.

Currently, there is no consensus as to the best management of 5th metacarpal neck fractures.  A previous Cochrane review  found insufficient evidence to recommend a particular management course, but reported no adverse outcomes from simple buddy strapping.  More recently, a study comparing closed reduction and plaster, with buddy strapping and soft wrap, suggested no adverse outcome to strapping, and a significant improvement on time to return to work for the buddy strapping group.  

The patient demographic associated with Boxers Fractures (young, male, working) historically have a suboptimal compliance with follow up.   In one study, 10% of patients removed splints themselves and never returned to follow up.   If these injuries can be managed with minimal intervention and community follow up, time would be saved in both the emergency department and orthopaedic outpatients, with a concurrent economic benefit.  

We propose a prospective, randomised study to assess outcomes of 5th metacarpal neck fractures (Boxers Fracture).  The proposed study will compare minimal intervention (buddy strapping of ring and little fingers) with current practice; plaster cast in position of safe immobilisation (POSI).  This study aims to provide an answer to the question regarding the best management of these fractures.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>In kind costs covered by research department.  Actual cost of interventions negligible as current practice and standard of care.  

Trainee grant will be sought for statistical analysis (not yet applied for). 
 
Note recruitment started day after initial submission of ANZCTR registration.  Researcher was not aware that this had to be done 3 weeks prior! </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gold Coast Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee 
Research Unit Clinical Governance, Education and Research
Gold Coast Hospital and Health Service Queensland Government

Level 2, E Block (PED Building) 
1 Hospital Boulevard 

SOUTHPORT QLD 4215




</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>AU/1/3273218</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Pellatt </name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital Emergency Department 
1 Hospital Boulevard 
Southport
4215
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 431620030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rafpellatt@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Pellatt </name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital Emergency Department 
1 Hospital Boulevard 
Southport
4215
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 431620030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rafpellatt@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Pellatt </name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital Emergency Department 
1 Hospital Boulevard 
Southport
4215
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 431620030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rafpellatt@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Pellatt </name>
      <address>Gold Coast University Hospital Emergency Department 
1 Hospital Boulevard 
Southport
4215
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 431620030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rafpellatt@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>