<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364940">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001049763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>To excise or ablate endometriosis? A prospective randomized double blinded trial with 5 years follow-up.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective randomized double blinded controlled trial comparing treatment of endometriosis with excision versus ablation on pain, rates of pregnancy, repeat surgery and use of hormonal medication in the 5 years post-operation.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Endometriosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Interventions - Excision of endometriosis. To excise the endometriosis, spade with monopolar current or scissors are used to cut out the endometriosis. Duration of the procedure depends on the amount of endometriosis present and expertise of the surgeon.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator - ablation of endometriosis. Monopolar or bipolar diathermy is used to ablate and burn the endometriosis. Duration of the ablation on the endometriosis is determined by the surgeon. The duration of the total procedure depends on the amount of endometriosis present.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in pain VAS scores during 5 years post-operation </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years post operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of pregnancy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years post-operation. Assessed via post operative questionnaires.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Repeat Surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years post operation. Assessed via post operative questionnaires.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hormonal medication</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years post operation. Assessed via post operative questionnaires.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women booked to have a laparoscopy to manage pain symptoms suggestive of endometriosis, over 18 years, speak English, not be using or planning to use continuous hormonal medications and give consent to the trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under 18 years and over 50 years.
Do not speak English.
Do not consent.
Use or planning to use continuous hormonal medications.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects are enrolled in pre-admission clinic.
During laparoscopy, if endometriosis is visually diagnosed and it does not involve bowel,  bladder or ureter muscularis, then treatment is randomised to excision or ablation using computer generated randomisation in numbered, sealed, opaque envelops.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated random sequence placed in numbered opaque sealed envelops.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The power calculation assumed a base reduction in overall pain VAS score of 3.7 (estimated from the reduction in mean VAS pain score at 6 months in Suttons study in 1994 [Sutton et al. Prospective, randomized, double-blind, controlled trial of laser laparoscopy in the treatment of pelvic pain associated with minimal, mild, and moderate endometriosis. Fertil Steril 1994;62:696700]); a clinically significant difference between groups being a change of VAS score of 1.0; an SD of 2.0; and a power of 80% and alpha value of 5%. The calculated sample size was N = 49 in each group. To allow for wastage a sample size of 120 (60 in each group) was initially chosen. However, an interim analysis demonstrated a subject loss of 35% at 1 year, the sample size was then increased to 180 to compensate.

Proportions were compared with Chi-squared testing. Continuous variables were compared using the t-test for independent variables and Welchs t-test if the assumption of equal variance was not met. Medians were used to describe rAFS scores and comparison was with the Mann-Whitney U test. Where potential confounding factors were present (defined when p&lt;0.25)  multivariate linear regression analysis was performed with backward removal of variables. Survivor analysis (log rank test statistic) was used for comparing dichotomous events over time such as pregnancy and further treatments (medical and surgical). Repeated measures of continuous variables were analyzed using one way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tamhanes T2 post-hoc test where equal variance was not assumed. Differences were considered significant if p&lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2001</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/07/2001</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/09/2007</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/09/2007</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Martin Healey</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Gynaecological Endoscopy Society Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>282 Edinburgh Road
CASTLECRAG NSW 2068</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>L.E.W. Carty Charitable Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>27 Windsor Place
Melbourne
Victoria 3000 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Women's Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Claudia Cheng</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: To compare reduction of pain following laparoscopy after ablation or excision of endometriosis.
Design: A prospective, randomized, double-blind study. 
Setting: Endometriosis and pelvic pain clinic at a university teaching hospital.
Patients: Women of reproductive age presenting with pelvic pain and visually proven endometriosis.
Interventions: Subjects completed a questionnaire rating their various pains using visual analogue scales (VAS). Following visual identification subjects were randomised to treatment with ablation or excision by supervised training gynecologists as primary surgeon. Follow-up questionnaires documented pain levels every 3 months for 1 year then 6 monthly until 5 years.  
Main Outcome Measure: Change in pain VAS scores during 5 years post-operation and rates of pregnancy, repeat surgery and use of hormonal medication
Results: There was a reduction in all pain scores over the five year follow up in both treatment groups.  A significantly greater reduction in sex pain VAS scores was seen in the excision group at 3 years 6 months (p=0.015); 4 years 6 months (p=0.047) and at 5 years (p=0.031).  More women went on to use medical treatments for endometriosis amongst the ablation group (p=0.004) by 5 years. 
Conclusions:  Surgical treatment of endometriosis provides symptom reduction for up to 5 years. There are some limited areas, such as deep dyspareunia, where excision is more effective than ablation.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Part of the results was presented at the Australasian Gyneacological Endoscopy Society 23rd Annual Scientific Meeting, 7-9th March 2013.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research and Ethics Committees of the Royal Women’s Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/10/1998</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Project 98/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/05/1998</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Healey</name>
      <address>Royal Women's Hospital, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia and Department Obstetrics &amp; Gyneacology, University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia

20 Flemington Road. Parkville. Victoria. 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9425 9833</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mghealey@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Healey</name>
      <address>Royal Women's Hospital, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia and Department Obstetrics &amp; Gyneacology, University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia

20 Flemington Road. Parkville. Victoria. 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9425 9833</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mghealey@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Healey</name>
      <address>Royal Women's Hospital, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia and Department Obstetrics &amp; Gyneacology, University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia

20 Flemington Road. Parkville. Victoria. 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9425 9833</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mghealey@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>