<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="804">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000575639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>RANDOMISED, DOUBLE BLIND, MULTICENTRE,
PLACEBO CONTROLLED PHASE III STUDY OF THE SAFETY AND TOLERABILITY FOLLOWING ADMINISTRATION OF LIVE ATTENUATED JE VACCINE (ChimeriVaxTM-JE)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>RANDOMISED, DOUBLE BLIND, MULTICENTRE,
PLACEBO CONTROLLED PHASE III STUDY OF THE SAFETY AND TOLERABILITY FOLLOWING ADMINISTRATION OF LIVE ATTENUATED JE VACCINE (ChimeriVaxTM-JE)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>N/A - Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine Study</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single injection of either study vaccine ChimeriVaxTM-JE</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (saline)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety by the evaluation of adverse event incidence rates between the 2 treatment groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days after vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. The evaluation of AE incidence rates between treatment groups at intervals.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Day 0 to 7, Day 0 to 14 and Day 0 to 30.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. The evaluation of laboratory abnormalities between groups with respect to the normal reference ranges and changes in laboratory values.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to Day 14 will be performed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. Safety will further be determined by summarising all Day 0 to 30 related AEs, SAEs, AEs leading to withdrawal, physical examinations and vital signs (including oral temperature).</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Written informed consent obtained 2. In good general health 3. Available for the study duration 4. For female subjects: Negative pregnancy tests at Screening and Day 0,  Females of childbearing potential will be required to be correctly using an efficacious hormonal method of contraception or intrauterine device for at least 1 month before randomisation and during the on-study phase to Day 30.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. A history of vaccination against or infection with JE2. Known or suspected immunodeficiency, use of immunosuppressive  or antineoplastic drugs during the study3. History of thymoma, thymic surgery (removal) or myasthenia gravis4. Clinically significant abnormalities on laboratory assessment5. Anaphylaxis or other serious adverse reactions to foods, Hymenoptera (bee family) stings, or drugs (including vaccines).6. Transfusion of blood or treatment with any blood product, including intramuscular or intravenous serum globulin within six months of the Screening Visit or up to Day 307. Administration of another vaccine or antiviral within 30 days preceding the Screening Visit or up to Day 308. Physical examination indicating any clin significant med condition9. Oral temperature &gt;38 degrees C or acute illness within 3 days prior to vaccination10. Seropositive to HCV or HIV or positive for Hepatitis B Surface Antigen11. Lactation or intended pregnancy in female subjects12. Excessive alcohol consumption, drug abuse, significant psychiatric illness13. A known or suspected physiological or structural condition that compromises the integrity of the blood-brain barrier14. Participation in another clinical study within 30 days of the screening visit for this study15. Employee of the study site, Sponsor or CRO involved with the management of the study16. Any other reasons, which in the investigators opinion, makes the subject unsuitable to participate in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Blinded study team.  Non-blinded pharmacist prepares double blind study treatments and holds randomisation codes/lists.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated, block randomistion</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>PPD Development (Australia)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Acambis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Acambis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matt Dobson</name>
      <address>Acambis Research Limited
Peterhouse Technology Park
100 Fulbourn Rd
Cambridge CB1 9PT</address>
      <phone>+44 (0)1223275300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matt.dobson@acambis.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>N/A</name>
      <address>(There is no appropriate contact person for this study - individual study sites will use their own healthy volunteer databases/private practises together with local advertising measures to meet recruitment targets for the study)</address>
      <phone>N/A</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N/A</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>