<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372842">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000669392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Primary school Physical Education and Physical Literacy (PEPL) support system: a quasi randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Introduction of a trained Physical Education Physical Literacy (PEPL) coach into a group of primary schools: its effect on school culture, the teaching of physical education and  on physical literacy of the students. A quasi-randomised controlled trial in Geelong in the state of Victoria, Australia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PEPL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention involves the appointment of a trained physical educator whom we refer to as a Physical Education Physical Literacy (PEPL) coach. The coach will use a socio-ecological framework approach to improve physical activity levels and physical literacy at the child (participant) level by targeting barriers at the teacher, school, family, and community level. Barriers to physical activity and physical literacy will be identified using surveys and questionnaires completed at the start of the study.
The PEPL coach will be assigned to a cluster of 8 geographically linked schools on a full-time working basis for the 10 month study period.
Examples of day to day activities of the Coachr will include:
1) Teacher level: providing assistance, resources, modelling, support and professional development for generalist classroom teachers to improve the planning, quality and delivery of physical education classes.
2) Family level: Encouraging parents (through educational materials) to provide more opportunities and support for their child to by physically active
3) School level: assisting schools to develop and/or improve their school physical activity policy and climate
4) Community level: encouraging sports clubs to receive new participants and facilitating community role models to visit schools to promote physical activity.

Adherence to the intervention will be monitored using school and teacher attendance records</interventions>
    <comparator>The Control is a group of 8 schools of similar socioeconomic, teaching structure and size which continue their usual practice of physical education and sport </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality and quantity of physical education and sport taught by the generalist classroom teacher. Assessed by SOFIT (System For Observing Fitness Instruction Time)</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 months after the quasi-randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Classroom teacher perception of personal PE teaching competence,and confidence. Assessed by a customised questonnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 months after quasi-randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity during Physical Education classes assessed by accelerometers</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 months after quasi-randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Student perceived competence in physical education and sport. Assessed by CY-PSPP (Physical Self-Perception Profile) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 months after quasi-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Day to day physical activity patterns assessed by accelerometers</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 months after quasi-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Student  enjoyment of physical education and sport. Assessed by PACES (Physical Activity Enjoyment Scale) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 months after quasi-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy children in government public schools</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Schools in the study are separated geographically to such and extent that teachers and students are not likely to collaborate and share ideas;</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Our model fits within the general framework of general linear mixed model; similar to the model associated with publications concerning our previous quasi-randomized control trial, the LOOK (Lifestyle of our Kids) Project (search Telford RD for papers)
The design structure involves three levels: Level 1 is the School; Level 2 is the Child within school; Level 3 involves the repeat observations (i.e. longitudinal observations) on a child. 
Consider the variable MVPA (Moderate and Vigorous Physical Activity)as an example of a response variable of interest
MVPA = constant + Group effect+ SES effect + + school random effect + Sex effect + Sex.Group interaction +child random effect + Year effect + Sex.Year effect + Group.Year effect + possible interactions between fixed effects + within-child random error
Group in the intervention or control group
The Group.Year effect is the effect of the intervention
Restricted maximum likelihood is used to estimate variance components and weighted least squares for estimating fixed effects. Statistical significance of effects is assessed by calculating adjusted Wald statistics. General model checking procedures will be routinely used to identify aberrant data and to check the model assumptions. 

With regard to sample size calculations and statistical assumptions, Professor Ross Cunningham (research team member and statistical consultant) makes the following comments: 1) It is not possible to undertake a formal power analysis with sufficient precision for the current study 2) Statistical knowledge gained from the LOOK study indicates that 16 schools will ensure internal validity of the design i.e. there is sufficient information to estimate the 'experimental' error and intervention and control effects with adequate precision 3) At least 20 children in each school is needed to estimate school effects with high precision. Window of opportunity for testing at the start and the end of the year precludes greater numbers of schools and students.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>350</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>340</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>9/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Canberra</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked Bag 1, 
University of Canberra, 
ACT 2601 
AUSTRALIA </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 1, 
University of Canberra, 
ACT 2601 
AUSTRALIA </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Physical Education Physical Literacy (PEPL) project evaluates a support system designed to assist primary schools to create a physically active culture, increase student opportunities for physical activity, and to enhance the content and delivery of physical education. This study continues on from a previous research project conducted in Victoria (ACTRN12615000066583) 

The system is guided by a PEPL coach - an expert physical educator working in a network of 8 schools who tailors the support system to meet individual school needs. The objectives of the PEPL coach include:

1)	Develop a school climate that understands the benefits of PEPL for student learning and development
2)	Provide in-class lesson modelling and professional development for the generalist classroom teacher
3)	Increase opportunities for students to take part in physical education and physical literacy activities outside of physical education time
4)	To develop relationships between schools, community organisations and sporting clubs
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Canberra Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce 
ACT 2617</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16-216</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rohan Telford</name>
      <address>University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce 
ACT 2617 </address>
      <phone>+61 2-62068883</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohan.telford@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rohan Telford</name>
      <address>University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce 
ACT 2617 </address>
      <phone>+61 2-62068883</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohan.telford@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rohan Telford</name>
      <address>University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce 
ACT 2617 </address>
      <phone>+61 2-62068883</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohan.telford@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rohan Telford</name>
      <address>University of Canberra
University Drive
Bruce 
ACT 2617 </address>
      <phone>+61 2-62068883</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohan.telford@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>