<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371511">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001662459p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>In patients with osteoarthritis that will undergo high tibial osteotomy, does the use of two different techniques produce the same change their gait mechanics?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In individuals undergoing high tibial osteotomy for osteoarthritis does computer navigated lateral closing wedge high tibial osteotomy or medial opening wedge high tibial osteotomy improve gait mechanics?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HTO MO v LC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In patients with symptomatic medial compartment (inner side), knee osteoarthritis (OA) and associated genu varum (bowing of the lower limb) performing a high tibial osteotomy (HTO) can provide pain relief by changing the shape of the limb. The shape changes the point at which compressive load crosses the knee. This unloads the painful arthritic side of the knee and transfer load to the undamaged lateral compartment (outside)of the knee. There are two widely used HTO techniques. These are the medial opening wedge (MO) and the lateral closing wedge (LC) HTO. Intraoperative computer navigation can increase the accuracy and precision of the intended correction but has not been used for the LC technique. It is unclear in the literature, which approach yields the highest patient satisfaction as very few studies have been done that compare the two techniques. Additionally, there are even fewer studies that have examined the changes to gait mechanics that take effect as a result of the described procedures. To detect a difference between the two procedures, patients will undergo preoperative and postoperative radiographic (x-ray) and functional joint assessments. In addition, investigators will assess changes to the patients' gait by performing analysis at a Gait Laboratory.

Aims and Hypothesis:
1) That the same correction achieved intraoperatively using two different osteotomy techniques will produce the same correction to standing limb shape and gait mechanics
2) Computer navigated LC wedge is as accurate as computer navigated MO wedge HTO.

Research Design:
The design of this project is a single centre, multi-surgeon, prospective, randomised controlled trial. (Evidence Level II)

Materials and Methods:
Patients planned to undergo a HTO procedure at the investigators' clinic who fit study inclusion criteria, may be approached to voluntarily participate in the study. Patients will be randomised to the MO wedge HTO group or LC wedge HTO group at time of consent. Alignment corrections associated with the procedure will be standardised to 3.5 degrees of valgus. Patients will undergo assessments preoperatively, and postoperatively for followup in clinic at six weeks, six months and yearly.The intervention/procedure that will be performed is called a high tibial osteotomy (HTO). The operation involves changing the shape of the tibia (shin bone) by performing a bone cut (osteotomy) that does not completely finish and then separating the edges with a hinge at one end. The change in shape of the tibia results in changing the way force is transmitted through the knee joint. This accuracy and precision of this surgery is increased by the use of a computer navigation system. The corrections are held in place using a plate and screw fixation device.

Arm 1: Medial Opening Wedge (MO) High Tibial Osteotomy. This procedure makes the aforementioned osteotomy on the medial side (inside edge) of the tibia and separates the edges from each other thus "opening" a wedge of bone. This is the commonest procedure done and will act as the control.

Arm 2: Lateral Closing Wedge (LC) Hight Tibial Osteotomy: This procedure makes two cuts and removes a wedge of bone from the lateral side (outside edge) of the tibia and then the two ends are brought closer together.

The surgical time for each procedure varies, both procedures take similar time from start (knife to skin) to completion (surgical wound closure).  Both procedures can take from 45 minutes up to 1 hour each to complete.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control is as described in Arm 1 above of the interventions/exposures. It is an intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait analysis 
Each patient will have gait analysis preoperatively to create a baseline (whereby we compare the preoperative Gait to postoperative gait).  To analyse gait, the investigators must quantify the moments of force for adduction, abduction and ground reaction during the patients walking pattern.  Trackers are placed on specific 'markers' on the body to measure the feedback movement and force as the patient walks down a path fitted with sensor detectors. This is then repeated 6 months post-operatively when patients have been off crutches for some time and have completed the majority of rehabilitation and thus should be walking close as "normal".</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively and 6 months postoperatively.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of Movement- measured using a digital inclinometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively, 6 weeks postoperatively, 6 months postoperatively and 12 months postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to weight bear, as defined as time in days postoperatively when the patient is able to full weight bear on the operative limb.
Assessment will be carried out at 6 week mark in clinic, also self-reported by patient at anytime outside of the scheduled visits as part of routine care and research protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point will be assessed after 6 weeks postoperatively as this is likely to be the minimum time to full weight bearing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to weight bear without crutches- as defined as time in days to which point the patient is steady to walk without crutches as deemed by physiotherapist or surgeon</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be assessed at least 6 weeks postoperatively as this is the minimum time likely needed to reach this end point.  This will be self reported but assessed by surgeon or physiotherapist.
The patient will return at the 6 month postoperative time point where by self assessment will report walking free with absence of crutches.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>scar size, measured in centimeters. This is the length of the scar for any screw and plate insertion. This does not include scars of any arthroscopy that may be done for computer navigation</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiological Outcomes: Hip Knee Ankle Angle- from long leg weight-bearing anteroposterior radiographs. Measured as the angle subtended by a line through the centre of the head of femur to the highest point in the distal femoral intercondylar notch and a line between the spines of the tibia and midpoint of the talus. (See study protocol attached to ANZCTR form for  clarification)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively and 6 months postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiological Outcomes: Posterior tibial slope- measured by an angle that subtends a line drawn vertically from the posterior edge of the tibial shaft to the tibial plateau, performed by X-ray. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively, 6 and 12  months posteroperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiologial Outcome: Patellar height- as calculated using the Blackburne-Peele method, The imaging will be performed by X-ray.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively,  6 and 12 months postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiological Outcome (performed by X-ray): Time to union- as defined as the time in days at which there is an absence of pain upon local palpation, an absence of swelling in the limb, an ability to talk painlessly without crutches, and an evidence of radiographic bridging callus or trabecula between fragments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time measured after 6 weeks on plain radiograph as seen by consultant surgeons</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Reported Outcome Measure: Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively, 6 weeks postoperatively, 6 months postoperatively and 12 months postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Reported Outcome Measures: Oxford Knee Score (OKS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively, 6 weeks postoperatively, 6 months postoperatively and 12 months postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) pain score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Preoperatively, 6 weeks postoperatively, 6 months postoperatively and 12 months postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 3060 years
Body Mass Index less than 35
Medial compartment Osteoarthritis with medial knee pain
Intact Anterior Cruciate Ligament
Varus malalignment of less than 10 degrees
Normal lateral compartment
Clinically silent patellofemoral compartment
Fixed Flexion Deformity less than 10 degrees
Flexion Range of Movement greater than 110 degrees</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Osteoarthritis of the lateral compartment
Symptomatic  osteoarthritis of the patellofemoral joint
Rheumatoid arthritis
Previous infection in the knee
History of an angulated fracture of the lower extremity
Fixed Flexion Deformity of greater than 10 degrees
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>We will generate a random sequence of numbers using an online random number generator. This sequence will be used to allocate participants to a study group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Given there is no previous study that has looked at navigated HTOs, or any surrogate that we can use to perform sample size calculation, we will initially recruit 10 patients to each arm of the study, and perform interim calculations for statistical difference, if this is insufficient we will recruit a further 10 patients to each arm of the study, giving us a total of 40 patients in the complete study

Statistical analysis will be performed by an independent statistician experienced in biomechanics. The data will be cleared of personal identifiers such as name and hospital reference numbers and sent as raw data to be analyzed. Data will be analysed for normality using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov method, and then either parametric or non-paramentric tests will be applied. Gait analysis data will be compared to normative data that exists in published literature. Numerical data such as ROM, time to weight bear, HKA angle, posterior tibial slope, patellar and scar size will be assesed using repeated measures ANOVA testing. PROM data will be compared using Spearman's Rank Correlation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mater Hospital Pimlico - Pimlico</hospital>
    <postcode>4812 - Pimlico</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland (ORIQL)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>7 Turner St, Pimlico, QLD 4812</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Townsville Hospital and Health Services
Study, Education and Research Trust Account (SERTA)
Townsville Hospital
100 Angus Smith Dr, Douglas QLD 4814</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In patients with symptomatic medial compartment (inner side), knee osteoarthritis (OA) and associated genu varum (bowing of the lower limb) performing a high tibial osteotomy (HTO) can provide pain relief by changing the shape of the limb. The shape changes the point at which compressive load crosses the knee. This unloads the painful arthritic side of the knee and transfer load to the undamaged lateral compartment (outside)of the knee. There are two widely used HTO techniques. These are the medial opening wedge (MO) and the lateral closing wedge (LC) HTO. Intraoperative computer navigation can increase the accuracy and precision of the intended correction but has not been used for the LC technique. It is unclear in the literature, which approach yields the highest patient satisfaction as very few studies have been done that compare the two techniques. Additionally, there are even fewer studies that have examined the changes to gait mechanics that take effect as a result of the described procedures. To detect a difference between the two procedures, patients will undergo preoperative and postoperative radiographic (x-ray) and functional joint assessments. In addition, investigators will assess changes to the patients' gait by performing analysis at a Gait Laboratory.

Aims and Hypothesis:
1) That the same correction achieved intraoperatively using two different osteotomy techniques will produce the same correction to standing limb shape and gait mechanics
2) Computer navigated LC wedge is as accurate as computer navigated MO wedge HTO.

Research Design:
The design of this project is a single centre, multi-surgeon, prospective, randomised controlled trial. (Evidence Level II)

Materials and Methods:
Patients planned to undergo a HTO procedure at the investigators' clinic who fit study inclusion criteria, may be approached to voluntarily participate in the study. Patients will be randomised to the MO wedge HTO group or LC wedge HTO group at time of consent. Alignment corrections associated with the procedure will be standardised to 3.5 degrees of valgus. Patients will undergo assessments preoperatively, and postoperatively for followup in clinic at six weeks, six months and yearly.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Hospital Pimlico Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Chairperson
Human Research Ethics Committee
Mater Health Services North Queensland Ltd
21-29 Fulham Rd
Pimlico, Townsville, QLD 4812.
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>Pending</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371511-Ammended Study Protocol Nav MOvLC Version 2.2  update 15092016.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371511-Ammended FORCE Master Participant Information Form version 1.2 Nav HTO MOvLC update 15092016 AG.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371511-Ammended FORCE Master Consent FORM Nav HTO MO v LC updated 15092016.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371511-NEAF 15092016  AU1EAD827.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter McEwen</name>
      <address>North Queensland Knee, Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland (ORIQL)
Suite 3, Level 2, Mater Medical Centre 21-29 Fulham Rd, Pimlico, QLD 4812</address>
      <phone>+61747794788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter@kneesurgeon.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Andrea Grant</name>
      <address>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland
7 Turner Street, Pimlico, QLD 4812</address>
      <phone>+61747550564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research_coordinator@oriql.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Andrea Grant</name>
      <address>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland
7 Turner Street, Pimlico, QLD 4812</address>
      <phone>+61747550564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research_coordinator@oriql.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Andrea Grant</name>
      <address>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland
7 Turner Street, Pimlico, QLD 4812</address>
      <phone>+61747550564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research_coordinator@oriql.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>