<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370737">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000914460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Simulated Military Land Transit on Physical Performance.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effects of the Whole Body Vibrational Forces as Experienced during Simulated Military Land Transit on the Physical Performance of Healthy Volunteers </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil known</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Exposure to whole body vibration</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be exposed to one of four exposure conditions lasting 120 minutes. Each condition will take place with the participant seated on a seat taken from a Bushmaster PMV. In order to reproduce the forces experienced during military land transit the seat will be located atop a CKAS 6 degree of freedom simulation platform. This platform will be located within the biomechanics laboratory within the University of South Australia, and has been calibrated to accurately reproduce the recorded forces experienced during military land transit. The whole intervention will be administered by the lead researcher (Thomas Debenedictis) with the groups consisting of:

Negative control group  participants will not be required to be secured to the seat with the use of the seat harness. There will be no vibrational forces

Positive control group  Participants will be secured with the use of the harness attached to the seat for the duration of the exposure. There will be no vibrational forces.

Simulation of a 1st class road group  Participants will be exposed to a period of simulated transit that will represent a 1st class road (paved highway) and be secured to the seat with the use of seat harness 

Simulation of a cross country road - participants will be exposed to a period of simulated transit that will represent a cross country conditions and be secured to the seat with the use of seat harness
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition will consist of the participants being seated with no harness or whole body vibration forces.

The comparator group will consist of a 16 participants recruited from the currently active Australian Defence Force population</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>changes in lower limb strength as measured by the peak landing forces during the drop jump</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures peak landing forces will be taken immediately before the 2 hour land transit simulation and immediately following the simulation as part of the physical performance protocol </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in lower limb power as indicated by changes in 20m sprint performance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of 20m sprint performance be taken immediately before the 2 hour land transit simulation and immediately following the simulation as part of the physical performance protocol</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in full body strength as indicated by changes in Isometric mid-thigh pull strength</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of full body strength will be taken immediately before the 2 hour land transit simulation and immediately following the simulation as part of the physical performance protocol</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in arm-hand steadiness as indicated by a change in the number of contacts during a arm hand-steadiness test with participants required to hold a 2mm metal stylus attached to the end of a replica rifle in a 4mm hole. A counter will be set up so that each time the metal stylus makes contact with the inside of the hole the circuit is completed and the contact is counted  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of arm-hand steadiness performance will be completed immediately prior to the military land transit simulation and immediately following the simulation as part of the physical performance protocol</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in lower limb power as indicated by a changes in the rate of force development as measured during the drop jump</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes in the rate of force development during the drop jump will be performed immediately prior to and following the land transit simulation as part of the physical performance protocol</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>changes in flexibility as measured during the sit and reach test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of flexibility will be performed immediately prior to and following the land transit simulation as part of the physical performance protocol</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures of reactive agility will be tested with participants required to react to a light positioned atop two timing gates positioned to form a 'Y' with the 20 m sprint. Upon crossing the end of the 20m sprint the participant will be required to move as fast as possible through the corresponding gate depending on which light activates (left v right)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of reactive agility will be performed immediately prior to and following the land transit simulation as part of the physical performance protocol </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Both the general population and Australian Defence Force cohorts will be required to meet the same inclusion criteria allow. Matching both cohorts demographically and in terms of their physiological fitness will allow for comparison between cohorts. All participants will have to meet the following criteria:
Male
Aged 18-24
Injury free within the last 6 months
Able to complete ADF physical performance entry tests
All participants will be required to perform a familiarisation session and the testing protocol.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not in the 18-24 age range
Injured during the last 6 months
Unable to complete the ADF physical performance entry test</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation via email/computer </concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>In addition to the 60 general population participants that will be recruited for the study, 16 ADF personnel will be recruited as a validation group. These participants will be randomly assigned to either both of the positive or negative control groups or just one, and both the first class and cross country terrain simulations. The decision to randomise this group to only one of the 'control' conditions will be based on the data collected from the 60 general population participants. If analysis indicates that there are no differences in the changes in performance between both the control group then the ADF personnel will only be assigned to the positive control group, first class road simulation and cross country simulation </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will use a 2-way (Time [2 levels] and exposure intensity [4 levels]) repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA). The assumption of normality of dependent variables will be assessed using a Shapiro-Wilk test; data that is not normally distributed will be transformed for example log-transformed. Where a significant main effect is demonstrated, post-hoc pairwise comparisons will be made using Bonferroni adjustment for multiple comparisons. Significance will be accepted at P&lt;0.05. Data will be reported as mean +/- standard deviation with effect sizes quantified using standardised mean differences and interpreted as small (0.20-0.50), moderate (0.5-0.8) and large (&gt;1.2)]. All statistical analysis will be performed in SPSS (v20, IBM, NY, USA).

In order to assess changes in performance in response to periods of simulated military land transit and based on previously provided effect sizes for each of the performance tests, with a one-sided 5% significance level and 80% power, 12 participants would be required for each exposure group or 48 participants would be required to complete the study. With this in mind and accounting for dropout rates of 15% a total of 60 participants will be recruited with 15 participants assigned to each exposure group.

Due to issues the issues associated with recruiting from the military population the maximum number of participants we have been able to secure for this population is limited to 16 participants. With this in mind, the military population will not be used as part of our primary analysis and will only be used as part of an explorative analysis of the differences in any changes in performance between the general population and military population cohorts in response to the exposure.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>11/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/01/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>76</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>76</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/01/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5001 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>108 North terrace
Adelaide
SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Defence Science Technology Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>506 Lorimer Street
Fishermans Bend
Victoria
3207</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the study is to explore the impact of military land transit on the physical
performance of dismounted combatants. Participants will be required to complete a number of
physical performance tests prior to and following a two hour exposure to simulated military land
transit.
Participants are required to complete the following battery of tests prior to and following the two
hour exposure; drop jump, 20m sprint, reactive agility, arm-hand steadiness, isometric deadlift,
and sit and reach test. Data collected in a previous study identified a number of tasks regularly
performed by ADF infantry personnel following dismount that rely on aspects of an individuals
physical abilities to successful complete. As such the battery of tests was design to assess the
physical attributes that underpin each of the tasks.
The two hour exposure will consist of one of four conditions; seated no harness, seated with
harness, seated with harness and 1st class road conditions, seated with harness and cross
country conditions. Data collected in the previously mentioned study indicated that the
Bushmaster PMV is the most commonly used vehicle by ADF infantry personnel and as such
accelerometer data collected from a Bushmaster PMV in transit was used to generate a
military land transit simulation. In addition participants of the previous study indicated that the
most common duration of land transit was two hours and whilst in transit they would regularly
secure themselves into place using the built in seat harness. This data resulted in the design of
the four two hour exposure groups.
In addition to the physical performance tests, participants will have a number of electrodes
positioned on their person to measure the muscle activity of the following muscles; glute
medius, external obliques, and longissiums. It is postulated that the data collected will indicate
if the two hour land transit exposure impacts the muscle activity providing insight into the
mechanisms responsible for any changes in performance.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia's Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>108 North Terrace
Adelaide
SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000034370</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370737-Info sheet 15_10_23.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Thomas Debenedictis</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, 101 Currie Street, Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 883 022083</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thomas.debenedictis@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Thomas Debenedictis</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, 101 Currie Street, Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 883 022083</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thomas.debenedictis@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Thomas Debenedictis</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, 101 Currie Street, Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 883 022083</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thomas.debenedictis@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Thomas Debenedictis</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, 101 Currie Street, Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 883 022083</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thomas.debenedictis@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>