<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364191">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000514707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of vitamin C and grape-seed polyphenols on blood pressure in treated hypertensive individuals</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of vitamin C and grape-seed polyphenols on blood pressure in treated hypertensive individuals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following a 3-week run-in period (during which tea and coffee intake was limited to 3 cups per day and all red wine was ceased), subjects were allocated to a study treatment via block randomization using computer-generated random numbers, devised by the statistician. Volunteers were assigned to receive either (1) 500 mg/day vitamin C and matched grape-seed polyphenol placebo, (2) 1000 mg/day grape-seed polyphenols and matched vitamin C placebo, (3) 500 mg/day vitamin C and 1000 mg/day grape-seed polyphenols, or (4) matched placebo tablets for both grape-seed polyphenols and vitamin C. Participants took assigned tablets during a 6 week intervention period in a double-blind fashion. Tablets were taken twice daily at meal times as 250 mg and 500 mg of vitamin C and polyphenols,
respectively. All tablets were identical in appearance, size.  All study personnel and participants were blinded to treatment assignment for the duration of the study. Outcome measurements were performed at the end of the run-in period (baseline) and again at the end of the 6 week intervention period. </interventions>
    <comparator>Matched placebo tablets for both grape-seed polyphenols (plant cellulose) and vitamin C (plant cellulose) for 6 weeks. Oral tablets were taken twice daily at meal times as 250 mg and 500 mg of vitamin C placebo and polyphenol placebo, respectively.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure

Blood pressure was assessed as 24 h ambulatory blood pressure with blood pressure and heart rate measured every 20 min during the day time and every 30 min at night time. Ambulatory blood pressurewas assessed by a trained researcher who fitted a Spacelabs monitor (Spacelabs Medical Inc. Redmond, WA, USA) and explained its use to the participants. The monitor was fitted to the non-dominant arm approximately 2.5 cm above the antecubital fossa. Participants were instructed to continue their usual daily activities and to avoid any vigorous exercise. Measurements showing an error code or those with a pulse pressure of less than 20 mm Hg were excluded from the analysis. Blood pressure traces were considered complete if more than 80% of the recordings were valid. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks

At 6 weeks from start of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of blood pressure variation

Within-visit rate of variation of systolic and diastolic blood pressure, pulse pressure and heart rate were calculated for day time (08:0020:00) and night time (22:00-06:00) periods from the 24 h ambulatory blood pressure traces. The within-visit rate of measurement-to-measurement blood pressure and heart rate variation was calculated using the slope of the change in systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, pulse pressure and heart rate between each reading over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks

At 6 weeks from start of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All individuals were taking one or more antihypertensive drugs for  3 months, had a mean 24-h ambulatory systolic BP of  125 mmHg and at least one additional cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk factor. Risk factors included previous coronary or cerebrovascular event &gt; 6 months, hyperlipidaemia (total cholesterol &gt; 6 mmol/l), use of lipid-lowering therapy, or smoking &gt; 5 cigarettes/day. All volunteers ceased any vitamin, fish oil or antioxidant supplements for at least 3 weeks prior to study entry. All usual medication was taken as prescribed on the morning of each visit and maintained for the duration of the trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria included: previous coronary or cerebrovascular event  6 months, heart failure or unstable disease, premenopausal, use of nitrate medication, use of oral contraceptive, body mass index &gt; 35 kg/m2, diabetes mellitus, fasting glucose 7 mmol/l, or elevated serum creatinine (men &gt; 110 mmol/l or women &gt; 100 mmol/l). Individuals were asked to limit tea and coffee intake to 3 cups/day, and cease all red wine and commercial fruit juice for the duration of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All study personnel and participants were blinded to treatment assignment for the duration of the study. Tablets were were visually identical and were placed into bottles labelled A to D.  The chief investigator held the code for the tablets in a sealed envelope which was not broken until the end of the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants were allocated to a study treatment via block randomization, using computer-generated random numbers (generated by a biostatistician who was not involved in the conduct of the study) sealed in opaque envelopes. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size was calculated using blood pressure as the primary endpoint. 16 participants in each group provided more than 80% power to detect a 5 mm Hg difference in systolic blood pressure (alpha=0.05).

Outcome variables were analysed using linear mixed models Fixed effects included baseline value, visit (baseline or post), treatment group, hour and treatment group X hour.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2002</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/05/2003</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>74</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>74</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA 6009 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
 GPO Box 1421
 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is evidence that oxidative stress contributes to the pathogenesis of hypertension. The primary objective of the study was to determine if vitamin C and polyphenols, alone or in combination, can lower blood pressure in hypertensive individuals.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Ward NC, Hodgson JM, Croft KD, Burke V, Beilin LJ, Puddey IB. The combination of vitamin C and grape seed polyphenols increases blood pressure: a randomised, double-blind, placebo controlled trial.  J Hypertens 2005; 23:427-434
Hodgson JM, Croft KD, Woodman RJ, Puddey IB, Wu JHY, Beilin LJ, Lukoshkova EV, Head GA, Ward NC. Effects of vitamin E, vitamin C and polyphenols on rate of blood pressure variation: results of two randomised controlled trials. Br J Nutr 2014; 112:1551-62.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>197 Wellington St, Perth WA 6000 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/11/2000</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC2000/055</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Ward</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)8 9224 0391</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Natalie.Ward@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Ward</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)8 9224 0391</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Natalie.Ward@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Ward</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)8 9224 0391</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Natalie.Ward@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jonathan Hodgson</name>
      <address>UWA School of Medicine and Pharmacology, GPO Box X2213, Perth, WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)8 9224 0267</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)8 9224 0246</fax>
      <email>Jonathan.Hodgson@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>