<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367727">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000116527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MATADOR 2: Minimising Adaptive Thermogenesis And Deactivating Obesity Rebound 2</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Intermittent Versus Continuous Energy Restriction on Body Weight, Resting Metabolic Rate and Neuroendocrine Function in Obese Women.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1165-9578 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>MATADOR 2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is secondary to the previously registered MATADOR study (ACTRN12611001017910) which was undertaken in males. The MATADOR 2 study will be undertaken in females with a comparitive cohort of males.

The study will comprise 3 phases: [1] Baseline energy balance, [2] Energy restriction intervention, and [3] Post-intervention energy balance. As we have previously shown that provision of food maximises dietary compliance in the free-living situation (1,2,4), food will be home-delivered weekly to participants in all phases of this study. The aim of PHASE 1 is to determine the baseline values of various parameters of the famine reaction before energy restriction and weight loss. During the 4 weeks of PHASE 1, weight stability will be achieved as we have previously published (1-4), by determining maintenance energy requirements from dietary history and resting metabolic rate (RMR), and then providing participants with a weight maintenance diet. In PHASE 2, participants will be randomised to continuous or intermittent energy restriction interventions. The continuous intervention consists of 16 weeks on a diet at 67% of maintenance energy requirements. The intermittent intervention consists of 16 weeks of total energy restriction administered as 2 weeks of energy restriction on a diet at 67% of maintenance energy requirements followed by 2 weeks of energy balance on a diet at 100% of maintenance energy requirements, for a total of 30 weeks. The interventions are designed to elicit a 10% body weight loss. To account for weight lost, the energy restriction will be indexed to body weight and RMR after every 4 weeks of energy restriction, thereby keeping theoretical relative energy deficit consistent across the 12-week period. In PHASE 3, participants will be placed on an energy balance diet referenced to their reduced-weight state for 4 weeks to examine the time course of recovery of metabolic and neuroendocrine markers. The macronutrient distribution in both energy restriction and energy balance diets will be maintained within the range of 2530% of energy as fat, 15-20% as protein, and 5060% as carbohydrate. As we have previously shown that provision of food maximises dietary compliance in the free-living situation (1,2,4), food will be home-delivered weekly to participants in this study.

1.	Weinsier RL, Hunter GR, Desmond RA, Byrne NM, Zuckerman PA, Darnell BE. Free-living activity energy expenditure in women successful and unsuccessful at maintaining a normal body weight. Am J Clin Nutr. 2002; 75(3):499-504. 
2.	Byrne NM, Hills AP, Wood RE. Does body composition, relative energy deficit or adaptive thermogenesis explain differences between predicted and actual weight loss in obese adults? Obesity Reviews. 2010;11(Suppl.1):35-36. 
3.	Byrne NM, Weinsier RL, Hunter GR, et al. Influence of distribution of lean body mass on resting metabolic rate after weight loss and weight regain: comparison of responses in white and black women. Am J Clin Nutr. 2003;77(6):1368-73. 
4.	Wood RE, Byrne NM, Groves AM, Hills AP, King NK. Achieving energy balance in apparently sedentary obese males. Obesity Reviews. 2010;11(Suppl.1):219</interventions>
    <comparator>Continuous energy restriction is the control treatment (females).

A representative sample of males will also be recruited for comparative data to the previous MATADOR study that was undertaken at QUT. This is important for gender response comparisons between the MATADOR 1 study which was undertaken in males at QUT and the MATADOR 2 study in females that will be undertaken at Bond University. Therefore, to ensure the independent variable/confounder (study location) is having no effect, a representative sample of males will be recruited at Bond University for comparitive purposes to the QUT cohort. It is anticipated there will be no difference in response between the 10 recruited males who will all undertake the intermittant protocol in comparision to the intermitant male cohort in MATADOR 1.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight will be measured using digital weighing scales. Digital weighing scales are to be used to monitor body weight of participants at home in times between laboratory visits. These scales will be calibrated regularly, and weight will also be measured at the standard laboratory sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily - 4 weeks energy balance (pre-intervention)
Daily - 12 weeks (continuous) or 22 weeks (intermittent) energy restriction
Daily - 4 weeks energy balance (post-intervention)
12 and 24 week follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting metabolic rate via indirect calorimetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1,2 and 4 - energy balance (pre-intervention)
Week 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 - energy restriction
Week 2, 4 - energy balance (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuroendocrine status: Overnight fasted blood samples will be collected and concentrations of the following analytes in serum or plasma will be determined: free T3, Free T4, reverse T3, TSH, ACTH, cortisol, testosterone, sex hormone binding globulin, IGF-1, and leptin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 and 4 - energy balance (pre-intervention)
Week 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12  - energy restriction
Week 2, 4 - energy balance (post-intervention)
12 and 24 week follow up </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition (Fat Mass and Fat-free Mass) will be assessed using the gold-standard 4-compartment model using air displacement plethysmography (via BodPod), deuterium dilution and Dual Energy X-ray Absorptiometry (DXA) at 5 time points: in energy balance immediately prior to (Phase 1), at start of, mid way and after the weight loss intervention (Phase 2) and after the 4-wk period of energy balance (Phase 3). In addition, BodPod measurements will be taken at week 1, 2 and 4 energy balance (pre-intervention), weeks 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 of energy restriction, and weeks 2 and 4 of energy balance (post-intervention).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1,2 and 4 - energy balance (pre-intervention)
Week 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 - energy restriction
Week 2, 4 - energy balance (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting substrate oxidation via indriect calorimetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1,2 and 4 - energy balance (pre-intervention)
Week 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 - energy restriction
Week 2, 4 - energy balance (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Markers of metabolic health (fasting serum glucose, insulin, triglycerides, cholesterol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 and 4 - energy balance (pre-intervention)
Week 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 and 12 - energy restriction
Week 2, 4 - energy balance (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satiety via visual analogue scales and ad libitum test meal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 and 4 energy balance (pre-intervention)
Week 6 and 12 - energy restriction
Week 4 (post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Sedentary (&lt; 60 mins physical activity per week) 
Class I or II obese (30-40kg.m-2)
Waist circumference &gt;102 cm
Euthyroid, non-diabetic, ambulatory, and weight stable for at least 6 months (+/-2kg)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diabetic or fasting blood glucose &gt; 6.0 mmol/L (from medical screening)
Major surgery that will affect gut function/metabolic rate
Arthritis/musculoskeletal problems that would preclude full participation in all testing/affect activities of daily living
Heart condition
Sleep apnoea
Thyroid condition 
Current smoker or gave up smoking within the last 6 months
Any medications known to affect metabolic rate or neuroendocrine function 
Non-ambulatory 
Currently on a diet or actively losing weight</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be stratified according to BMI (30-34.9, 35-40) and age (25-38.9, 39-55) and then randomly allocated into either the intermittent energy restriction or continuous energy restriction groups.
Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Pemuted block randomisation. Where intermittent energy restriction = 1 and continuous energy restriction = 2.
Where BMI (30-34.9) = A, BMI (35-40) = B, Age (25-38.9) = C, Age (39-55) = D. Each participant will therefore fall into one of four cell options: AC, AD, BC or BD. Each cell will have pair allocations of random sequence 1 or 2.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Nuala Byrne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o Bond Institute of Health &amp; Sport
2 Promethean Way, Robina.
4226, Queensland.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bond University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University Drive
Varsity Lakes
QLD, 4227</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There are more than 7 million overweight or obese adults in Australia and on average only about 5% of this population
achieve permanent weight reduction of any significance to their health. Many questions remain regarding the best way to achieve long-term weight loss, and how a persons metabolic rate is affected both in the short- and long-term during dieting.
The overall aim of this project is to design more effective and sustainable weight loss strategies for overweight and obese adults. This study, funded by the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC), aims to compare changes in weight and health using two different dieting approaches in female participants with a small comparitive male cohort; one in which the energy intake (kilojoule value) changes every two weeks, and the other where the energy intake changes every four weeks. Throughout the intensive phase of the study, participants are provided with a healthy, balanced, energy-regulated diet delivered to their home. Measures of body composition, metabolic rate and energy expenditure, hunger and satiety, blood hormone levels, body fuel usage, and metabolic health will be taken at a number of time points throughout the study</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.matador2.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bond University Human Research Ethics Committee (BUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/o Bond University
University Drive, 
Varsity Lakes, 4227. QLD.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nuala Byrne</name>
      <address>c/o Bond Institute of Health &amp; Sport
2 Promethean Way,
Robina. 4226. Queensland.</address>
      <phone>(07) 5595 2279</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nbyrne@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nuala Byrne</name>
      <address>c/o Bond Institute of Health &amp; Sport
2 Promethean Way,
Robina. 4226. Queensland.</address>
      <phone>(07) 5595 2279</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nbyrne@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nuala Byrne</name>
      <address>c/o Bond Institute of Health &amp; Sport
2 Promethean Way,
Robina. 4226. Queensland.</address>
      <phone>(07) 5595 2279</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nbyrne@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kristen MacKenzie</name>
      <address>c/o Bond Institute of Health &amp; Sport
2 Promethean Way,
Robina. 4226. Queensland.</address>
      <phone>(07) 5595 1018</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kmackenz@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>