<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370534">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000817448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Endotracheal Tube (ETT) Cuff Pressure Monitoring And Regulation  a comparison between conventional, intermittent monitoring method using a handheld manometer and continuous ETT cuff presure monitoring method using the Tracoe Smart Cuff Manager in an adult Intensive Care Unit setting
.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Endotracheal Cuff Pressure Monitoring And Regulation  Continuous (using a Tracoe Smart Cuff Manager) Vs Intermittent Method (using a handheld manometer) to assess the efficacy of the TRACOE smart cuff manager in maintaining continuous endotracheal tube cuff pressure within the normal limit (20 to 30 cm H2O) in critically ill, intubated, adult ICU patients. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-0138</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients requiring mechanical ventilation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of microaspiration</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who are randomized to the  TRACOE Smart Cuff Manager group will have their cuffs connected to the Smart Cuff Manager and the balloon will be inflated with air until it is 2/3 to 3/4 (usually 60ml) the volume of the outer shell. They will be monitored until day 2 post extubation or up to day 15 of ICU admission, whichever is longer</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be managed the conventional way, with ETT cuff pressures measured every 4 to 6 hours</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maintainence of the ETT cuff pressures between 20-30cmH20 using the conventional method or using the Tracoe Smart Cuff Manager. Proportion of time during which the ETT cuff pressure is within the normal limit will be assessed by a handheld manometer measurement taken 6 hourly for all patients. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the patient's intubation period or up to day 15 of intubation, whichever is longer</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the risk of tracheal mucosal injury in patients with continuous cuff pressure control system versus patients on intermittent cuff pressure monitoring by assessing patient's post extubation - patient will be assessed for hoarseness of voice (judged by medical staff), sore throat and post extubation stridor which could indicate tracheal mucosal injury</outcome>
      <timepoint>After extubation of patient</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and tolerability of the continuous cuff pressure control system - via observation of the patient and from nursing records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout patient's intubation period or up to day 15 of intubation, whichever is longer</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare rates of VAP between the continuous cuff pressure control system and the intermittent cuff pressure monitoring method - patient's will be evaluated daily for VAP - VAP will be diagnosed based on increase in ventilator settings with:
- hypothermia or hyperthermia or WBC &gt; 12000 or &lt; 4000 cells/mm3
- a new antimicrobial agent is started and continued for more than 4 days
- purulent respiratory secretions or positive culture from respiratory secretions</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 48 hours post extubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All adult  ICU patients above 18 years old who are intubated with an orotracheal tube or tracheostomy tube.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with upper airway pathology
Patients with underlying chronic lung disease or restrictive lung disease
Patients who may have aspirated during intubation (e.g difficult intubation, food particles in oral cavity during intubation)
Patient who are ventilated in the general ward or who have been ventilated in the general ward for more than 24 hours prior to ICU admission.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed envelope</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization - drawing envelope from a box containing equal number of envelopes for each group</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The quantitative data will be processed and analysed through the use of SPSS version 20. Descriptive and inferential statistic will be used. Repeated measure ANOVA will be used to compare the mean score of knowledge level between pre-test and post-test results. General Linear Model will be used to analyse the results of the patient outcomes between the control and intervention group. 
Qualitative data that generated through focus group interview will analysed by creating a text-file to employ a sorting and classifying process. Content analysis will be applied to the transcribed comments.

We are planning a study of a continuous response variable from independent control and experimental subjects with 1 control(s) per experimental subject.  In a previous study, the response within each subject group was normally distributed with standard deviation 0.2.  If the true difference in the experimental and control means is 0.2 (20%), according to PS sample size calculation software, we will need to study 17 experimental subjects (using mechanical device) and 17 control subjects (traditional method using manual manometer) to be able to reject the null hypothesis that the population means of the experimental and control groups are equal with probability (power) 0.8.   The Type I error probability associated with this test of this null hypothesis is 0.05. However, when we took into account the possibility of dropping of out of cases due to various factors, the number of patients to include was doubled, thus a minimum of 34 in each group. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>68</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Malaya Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Malaya Medical Centre,  Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tracoe Medical</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>TRACOE medical GmbH, Reichelsheimer StraBe 1 / 3, 55268 Nieder-Olm</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Germany</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Vineya Rai</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Anaesthesiology and Intensive Care Unit, University Malaya Medical Centre. Lembah Pantai,59100. Kuala Lumpur</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Malaysia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This RCT will be conducted to establish the most reliable standard method for optimizing endotracheal tube cuff pressure in an intensive care unit - using the conventional, intermittent method or using a Tracoe Smart Cuff Manager. 

We hypothesize that the Tracoe Smart Cuff Manager would be able to maintain the endotracheal cuff pressure in it's normal, accepted range more reliably compared to patients who are managed in the conventional way (intermittent measurement using a handheld manometer)

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20162-2155</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370534-appendix 1-3.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370534-study protocol and product information.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370534-VAP tracking form.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Vineya Rai a/l Hakumat Rai</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+603 79494422</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vineyarai@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Vineya Rai a/l Hakumat Rai</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+603 79494422</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vineyarai@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Vineya Rai a/l Hakumat Rai</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+603 79494422</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vineyarai@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sharini Pillai a/p Vegadharan Pillai</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>