<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365511">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000021673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Total Hip joint Arthroplasty: steristrips vs skin glue for skin apposition. A randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing steristrips and skin glue for skin apposition in patients presenting for primary total hip joint arthoplasty</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>1111-1151-4912</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hip Osteoarthritis requiring total hip joint replacement

</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Skin closure in total hip joint arthroplasty procedures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Steristrips used to oppose the skin. Involves applying steristrips to oppose the skin edges following subcuticular closure with an absorbable barbed suture. Will take 1-2 minutes to apply. Follow up duration is at 10 days and six week marks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Skin glue application to oppose skin. Skin glue applied following subcuticular closure with an absorbable barbed suture. Will take 1-2 minutes to apply. Follow up duration is at 10 day and 6 week marks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prolonged wound ooze.
The post operative day at which wounds stop oozing will be recorded.
The outline of wound ooze will be marked. Wounds will be 
judged to have stopped oozing when there is no extension of theoutline over a 24 hour period. If the ooze is increasing and the dressing soaked the dressing will be changed. The day at which the wound is judged to stop oozing will be recorded. 

If the amount of ooze is judged to be excessive and not settling a negative pressure dressing will be applied. dressing of choice at our institution.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored on a daily basis during the post operative stay.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for negative pressure wound dressing (PICO dressing) application for prolonged wound ooze.

***PICO is the brand name of the dressing****

Binary outcome. The need to apply a PICO dressing is a subjective decision, PICOs will be applied to wounds that are deemed to be peristently oozy. They will not be applied in the first 4 days post operatively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored on a daily basis during inpatient stay.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antibiotic administration for wound erythema/infection.
Review of the patients medical records, and patients will be asked about this retrospectively at 10 day and 6 week folow ups. results will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint> monitored on a daily basis for duration of hospital stay; assessed at 10 day and 6 week follow ups.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to theatre for washout of wound.
review of patients medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monitored on a daily basis for duration of hospital stay, followed up at 10 day and 6 week marks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Deep hip infection involving the joint cavity.
review of patients medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monitored on a daily basis for duration of hospital stay. reviewed at 10 days and 6 weeks post surgery. Not only are 
deep infections rare revents, they usually take longer to develop/declare themselves, we do not expect any cases of deep infection in this study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Persons presenting for primary total hip joint replacement to Hutt Valley Hospital/Boulcott hospital, between February 2014-October 2014. (under the care of the Consultants prepared to be involved in the trial)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Revision hip surgery. Previous history of allergy to steristrips/skin glue.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be invited to participate at pre-assessment clinic by the orthopaedic pre-assessment nurse or at Consultant clinic at the time of booking for THJR (total Hip Joint Replacement). Patients will be randomly allocated to one of two groups: steristrips to oppose the skin edges group or to the skin glue group (ie: a two armed study). Randomisation will occur via opaque envelopes using a sequence that has been generated by a computer random number generator. Allocation to either group will occur in the operating theatre after closure of the deep and superficial layers. Once randomised all patients will remain in the group to which they are allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer generated random sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study has been designed aiming for a minimum power of 80% for the primary outcome. The power calculations are based on statistics from previous studies, which have suggested prevalence in the general population of the measured outcomes. A sample size of 180. Outcomes between groups will be compared using a paired-t test, with 95% confidence intervals.
1)	Wound ooze duration: 
Wood et al (2007) looked at wound ooze length after hip replacement: median time for wounds to be dry 4 days (interquartile range 3-6days). (n=62). A one day variance in our study would be clinically significant as for each day the wound continues to ooze hospital admission is prolonged.
Sample size
If we assume log-normal distribution then the median and interquartile range on the log scale (base e) are, 1.386 (1.099  1.792) and the interquartile range covers 1.349 SD giving SD=0.514, a difference of 1 day, from a geometric mean of 4 days to 3 days.
A sample size 90 in each group has 90% power to find a difference of 1 day between 4.5 and 3.5, based on the study of Wood et al (2007) that found the median time for wounds to be dry 4 days (interquartile range 3-6 days) and assuming a log-normal distribution.
2)	Need for PICO dressing for persistent wound ooze
Osmith et al (2010) meta-analysis found prolonged wound discharge after hip replacement in 2/64 closed with sutures, 3.1% (95%CI 0.4%  10.8%). With 90 in each group the trial will have 80% power to find differences between, say, 0.5% and 11.5% significant

3)	Antibiotic administration for wound erythema/superficial infection.
The rate of infection between the two methods is poorly publicized.
Paediatic study Wilson et al looking at unilateral cleft palate repair, suggested rates of post op infection 4% with steristrips Vs 0% for dermabond. (numbers 121 steristrip, 186 in dermabond).
0% (95%CI 0%2.0%) (0/186) for skin glue and 4% (95%CI 1.4%9.4%) (5/121) for steristrip. With 90 in each group the trial will have 80% power to find differences between, say, 0.1% and 10.5% significant.
4) Return to theatre for wound washout.
I was unable to identify rates of hip wounds requiring washout in the literature. Anecdotally though this is not overly common. Would be an important outcome to record but unlikely to find a statistically significant difference between the two groups.
5) Deep infection involving the joint
Deep infection occurs in 0.2-0.6%. Unlikely to have any of these in this study, and usually occur late (outside the follow up period). However, this is still an important, albeit rare outcome to document.
References
Wood J, Bevis, P, and Bannister, G (2007). Wound oozing after total hip arthroplasty. Annals of the Royal College of Surgeons of England, 89(2), 140.
OSmith T, Sexton D, Mann C, Donell S. Sutures versus staples for skin closure in orthopaedic surgery: meta-analysis. BMJ. 2010; 340: c119doi:10.1136/bmj.c1199.
Wilson, Andrew DH, and Nigel Mercer. "DermabondTM Tissue Adhesive Versus Steri-StripsTM in Unilateral Cleft Lip Repair: An Audit of Infection and Hypertrophic Scar Rates." The Cleft Palate-Craniofacial Journal 45.6 (2008): 614-619.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hutt Valley</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hutt Valley District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>High Street,
Lower Hutt,
Wellington
New Zealand
5040 
Private Bag 31907</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Boulcott Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>666 High Street,
Lower Hutt,
Wellington
5051</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim the of the study is to determine if skin wounds opposed with skin glue results in fewer wound complications compared with wounds opposed with steristrips in hip replacement surgery. It is hypothesised that wounds closed with skin glue will result in relatively fewer wound complications.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Liam Dunbar</name>
      <address>Cardiothoracic Registrar at Wellington Hospital. 57b Broadmeadows Wellington New Zealand 6035</address>
      <phone>+64274914490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lasdunbar@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Liam Dunbar</name>
      <address>Cardiothoracic Registrar at Wellington Hospital. 57b Broadmeadows Wellington New Zealand 6035</address>
      <phone>+64274914490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lasdunbar@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Liam Dunbar</name>
      <address>Cardiothoracic Registrar at Wellington Hospital. 57b Broadmeadows Wellington New Zealand 6035</address>
      <phone>+64274914490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lasdunbar@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Liam Dunbar</name>
      <address>Cardiothoracic Registrar at Wellington Hospital. 57b Broadmeadows Wellington New Zealand 6035</address>
      <phone>+64274914490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lasdunbar@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>