<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373395">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001536358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effetiveness of an new model of shared telephonic patient referral between primary health care and hospital health care.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of a new model of telephonic patient referral from primary health care to Internal Medicine consultation to reduce the waiting list period.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-9475</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DETELCOM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NONE</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>INTERNAL MEDICINE DISEASES</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients referrals were carreid out via telephone consultation so that the General Practitoners were able to consult directly the Internal Medicine doctors by telephone in order to obtain an early diagnosis. The time to access to the General Practitioner for the first consultation was from 1 to 3 days. During this first telephone consult between the General Practitioner and the Internal Medicine specialist, they both reached an agreement concerning the treatment, and the complementary tests and future check-up  were scheduled. The timing for obtaining the results of the complementary tests was 17 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control groups patients were referrred to Internal Medicine consultation by the traditional way, which involves a waiting list of 51 days and having to be moved several times to the nearest hospital with Internal Medicine consultation (Riotinto Hospital), which is about one hour from the participants´ locations.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in waiting list time (number of days) from primary health care to internal consultation, assessed by review of medical records available at "Diraya" (institutional medical record system)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (first visit to the General Practitioner) and first visit to Internal Medicine Consultation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient´s acceptance of this new model of referral, which was assessed asking them about their reasons to abandon the trial. 
Only 9 patients refused to participate in the trial because they preferred the traditional referral way.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (first visit to the General Practitioner consultation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Doctors´ acceptance of this new model of referral, which was assessed asking them about their reasons to abandon the trial. 
Only 8 doctors refused to participate in the trial because they thought this way would involve more dedication to each patient.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (first visit to General Practitioner consultation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Every patient who needed to be referred to Internal Medicine Hospital Consultation according to the Geeral Practitioners´decision.
General Practitioners from the north area of Huelva (Spain) who agreed to participate in the trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Whenever the General Practitioner considered that a patient would not get significant benefit from the telephone referral.
Patients who refused to participate in the study
General Practitioners who refused to participate in the trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer </concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified randomisation: General Practitioners were randomised </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>1.- DESCRIPTIVE ANALYSIS 
2.- KRUSKALL-WALLIS TEST
3.- MANN-WHITNEY TEST (p= 0.01 CI 99%)
4.-HODGES-LEHMAN TEST FOR INDEPENDENT SAMPLES </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>23/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>154</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>12/01/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>SEVILLE</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>LUIS MIGUEL AZOGIL LÓPEZ</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centro de Salud de Valverde del Camino
Plaza de la Constitución, s/n
21600 - Huelva. Spain
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NOT APPLICABLE</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NOT APPICABLE</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>ESTHER MARÍA MEDRANO SANCHEZ</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Seville. Faculty of Nursing, Physiotherapy and Podiatry.
Calle Avenzoar, 6
41009 SEVILLE</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Spain</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>MARÍA DEL VALLE CORONADO VÁZQUEZ</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Departamento de Sanidad. Gobierno de Aragón
Edificio Vía Universitas
Vía Universitas, 36 - 8ª planta
50071  Zaragoza  (Spain)</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Spain</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim: The purpose of this study is to find out whetheror not  telephone referral from Primary Health Care to Internal Medicine Consult manages to reduce waiting days as compared to traditional referral. This study also aims to know how acceptable is the telephone referral to general practitioners and their patients. 
Design: No blind randomized controlled clinical trial. Setting Northern Huelva Health District. Participant 154 patients. Interventions Patients referrals from intervention clinicians were sent via telephone consultation, whereas patients referrals from control clinicians were sent by the traditional method for a face-to-face consultation, 
Measurements: Number of days from referral request to Internal Medicine Consult; Number of telephone and traditional referrals; Number of doctors and patients denied; Denial reasons. 
Results: A statistically significant difference was found between groups, with an average of 27 (21-34) days. Among General Practitioners, 8 of the first 58 total doctors after randomization and, subsequently, 6 of the 20 doctors of the test group refused to engage in the trial because they considered excessive time and effort consuming. 50 % of patients referred by the 14 General Practitioners finally randomized to the intervention group were denied referral by telephone due to patients complexity. 
Conclusions: Telephone referral significantly reduces waiting days for internal medicine consult. This type of referral did not mean an excessive time and effort consuming to General Practitioners and was not all that beneficial to complex patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Fundación Andaluza Beturia para la Investigación en Salud (F.A.B.I.S.)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>4ª Planta Hospital Juan Ramón Jiménez
Ronda Norte s/n 21005. Huelva
T: 959.016.760 - F: 959.016.804/5

http://www.fabis.org</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>LUIS MIGUEL AZOGIL LÓPEZ</name>
      <address>BALTASAR DE ALCAZAR ST, Nº 4,  1ºC
41008 SEVILLE

AFFILIATION: ANDALUSIAN HEALTH CARE PUBLIC SYSTEM (SISTEMA ANDALUZ DE SALUD)</address>
      <phone>+ 34 646 500 778</phone>
      <fax>+34 954 486 527</fax>
      <email>luismiazogil@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ESTHER MARÍA MEDRANO SANCHEZ</name>
      <address>DIEGO ANGULO IÑIGUEZ ST. Nº 6, BLOCK 3, 1º C
41018 SEVILLE

AFFILIATION: UNIVERSITY OF SEVILLE</address>
      <phone>+34  609 076 282</phone>
      <fax>+34 954 486 527</fax>
      <email>emedrano@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ESTHER MARIA MEDRANO SANCHEZ</name>
      <address>DIEGO ANGULO IÑIGUEZ ST. Nº 6, BLOCK 3, 1º C
41018 SEVILLE

AFFILIATION: UNIVERSITY OF SEVILLE</address>
      <phone>+34 609 076 282</phone>
      <fax>+ 34 954 486 527</fax>
      <email>emedrano@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>LUIS MIGUEL AZOGIL LOPEZ</name>
      <address>BALTASAR DE ALCAZAR ST, Nº 4,  1ºC
41008 SEVILLE

AFFILIATION: ANDALUSIAN HEALTH CARE PUBLIC SYSTEM (SISTEMA ANDALUZ DE SALUD)</address>
      <phone>+ 34  646 500 778</phone>
      <fax>+ 34 954 486 527</fax>
      <email>luismiazogil@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>