<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365135">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001181796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The INDIGO Study - A randomised controlled trial of physical activity with individual goal-setting and volunteer mentors to increase physical activity  in insufficiently active older adults at risk of cognitive decline.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The INDIGO Study - A randomised controlled trial of physical activity with individual goal-setting and volunteer mentors to increase physical activity  in insufficiently active older adults at risk of cognitive decline.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>INDIGO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Those at risk of cognitive decline</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Both groups (intervention and control) will receive the same physical activity (PA) program (home-based, emphasis on walking) with a target of 150 minutes of moderate intensity PA/week. The program is progressive in duration and intensity taking 8 weeks to reach moderate intensity (55-65% heart rate reserve) for each individual. Participants will be asked to complete the PA as 3 x 50-minute sessions a week or 5 x 30-minute sessions a week. Intensity will be monitored using the Borg Perceived Rate of Exertion scale (RPE 10-12). All participants will receive a manual including the same information about exercise programs, exercise safety and community PA resource material. As part of the baseline workshop the facilitator will outline the PA program, explain the activities, how often they will be done, the intensity and how to record on their standardised PA diaries. 

The intervention group will receive the Goal Orientation Intervention (GM-PA group).  The participants individual goals will be identified on the Bangor Goal Setting  Interview (BGSI) at baseline, in a face-to-face interview (approximately 60 minutes) with a member of the research team. Participants will be asked to select 5 personal goals from the physical function and PA areas. These goals will be operationalised and worked on during the 24- week intervention period with  the development of individual strategies of how to achieve these goals. This program will be delivered via a participant manual and 3 group workshops conducted by research staff. These will be held in the first 6 months. The first will have a duration of two hours, and the remaining workshops will be of 1-hour duration at 8-weekly intervals. 

Over the 6-month intervention period the mentors will make 6 calls at 4-week intervals starting at week 2 then weeks 6, 10, 14, 18 and 22. Peer mentors will attend a 5-hour training course on how to support the participants and facilitate the problem solving approach of the goal-setting program.Mentors will be assisted with telephone call scripts to carry out this task.

Adherence to the prescribed program will be assessed from self reported PA diaries.  The mentors will also be  monitoring adherence and keeping records via the telephone calls. The type, frequency, duration and intensity of the PA will be determined from these records. Adherence will be calculated as the number of minutes of moderate activity completed relative to the prescribed 150 minutes/week expressed as a percentage. 
 
In the proposed study, a mentor will be an important and relevant source of information and support. We hypothesise that this approach combined with the goal oriented intervention package (goal-mentor, GM-PA) will result in greater improvements in PA and physical function than standard education and peer standard contact (control, CO-PA).

Community volunteers will be recruited and randomised to either  be a peer goal-mentor for the intervention group or a Physical Activity Liaison for the Control group.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Control Group (CO-PA)- In addition to the PA program participants in this group will receive a standard education program including general health education focusing on information on Healthy Ageing delivered via the manual and workshops. There will be three group-workshops in the first 6 months. The first will have a duration of two hours, and the remaining workshops will be of 1-hour duration at 8-weekly intervals.  The workshops for the two groups will be held in different buildings to avoid contamination between the two groups.

The control group participants will also receive the Standard Telephone Contact Support during which the volunteer peer-contact (the Physical Activity Liaison) will follow a script and record progress. Over the 6-month intervention period the mentors will make 6 calls at 4-week intervals starting at week 2 then weeks 6, 10, 14, 18 and 22.  The control group does not receive any feedback or motivational advice on goal setting or orientation. This control group receives the same contact hours with their peer mentor/PAL than the intervention group.

Adherence to the prescribed program will be assessed from self reported PA diaries.  The PALs will also be  monitoring adherence and keeping records via the telephone calls. The type, frequency, duration and intensity of the PA will be determined from these records. Adherence will be calculated as the number of minutes of moderate activity completed relative to the prescribed 150 minutes/week expressed as a percentage.

Instead of a Peer Mentor, the control group participants receive a Physical Activity Liaison - community volunteers who will be recruited and randomised to either  be a peer goal-mentor for the intervention group or this Physical Activity Liaison for the Control group. The PALs will attend a 2-hour training course on how to conduct the standard telephone contact.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be the change in PA at follow-up as measured by the pedometer in steps/day. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Goal-orientation and functional goals. Measured by the BGSI.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - measured by the SF-36. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy of mentors - as measured by the Self-efficacy scale in mentors. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive and Clinical Assessments: Mini-Mental State Examination, The Consortium to Establish a Registry for Alzheimers Disease (CERAD) neuropsychological assessment battery, Alzheimers Disease Assessment Scale 13  cognitive section (ADAS-cog 13), Clinical Dementia Rating Scale (CDR), Behaviour Rating Inventory of Executive Function  Adult Version (BRIEF-A), Short Form 36 Version 2 (SF-36v2), Memory Complaint Questionnaire (MAC-Q), Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), Delis-Kaplan Executive Function System (D-KEFS) - verbal fluency, Stroop Task, Digit Symbol Coding, WAIS III Digit Span (forward and backwards), Cambridge Contextual Reading Test, NEO-PI.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to the prescribed PA program - assessed from self reported PA diaries. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Fitness Assessments: Grip strength, Step Test, Sit-to-Stand Test, Timed Up and Go Test, 6-minute Walk Test. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health assessments: Height, Body weight,  BMI, Girth, Blood pressure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>FOR PARTICIPANTS
1) aged between 60 and 80 years old at last birthday; 
2) community dwelling;
3) fulfils the criteria for Subjective Memory Complainer (SMC) or Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI). 
4) Needs to understand spoken and written English
5) Needs to be able to attend visits to the National Ageing Research Institute (NARI)
6) Inactive (insufficiently active) defined as 30 minutes or less per week of regular moderate intensity leisure physical activity.


FOR VOLUNTEER MENTORS/PHYSICAL ACTIVITY LIAISONS
1) aged 50-85 years 
2) meets the PA guidelines of 150 minutes/week of moderate intensity PA 
3) Needs to understand spoken and written English
4) Needs to be able to attend visits to the National Ageing Research Institute (NARI)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>FOR PARTICIPANTS
1) Telephone Interview for Cognitive Status  Modified (TICS-M) score &lt; 19 (Those scoring lower than this will be excluded due to the likely presence of dementia); 
2) baseline Mini-Mental State Examination score (MMSE) &lt; 24;  
3) diagnosis of dementia; 
4) GDS-15 score &gt; 6 (= no significant depression);
5) unstable or life threatening medical condition; 
6) medical condition that contra-indicates moderate PA; 
7) non-sedentary lifestyle 
 8) Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt; 35;
 9) severe visual or hearing impairment; 
10) history of chronic alcohol abuse within the past five years;
 11) unable to attend the follow-up visits. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>FOR PARTICIPANTS
1) telephone screening to initially determine eligibility
2) approval from primary care physician and the project medical team
3) if eligible, baseline assessment
4) randomisation. Allocation is concealed using sealed opaque envelopes and is drawn by an independent person who is "off-site" and not part of the study team. 

FOR MENTORS/ PHYSICAL ACTIVITY LIAISONS
1) telephone screening to initially determine eligibility
2) if eligible, baseline assessment
3) randomisation (mentor or physical activity liaison). Allocation is concealed using sealed opaque envelopes and is drawn by an independent person who is "off-site" and not part of the study team. </concealment>
    <sequence> 
Generation of Random Numbers for both groups:
A list of consecutive Study IDs will be assigned to either the intervention or control group (in 1:1 ratio). Participants who satisfied the study selection criteria will be assigned the next available ID on this list by an investigator not involved in data collection or intervention. The varying-size blocked random allocation will be computer generated using “ralloc” user-written command implemented in Stata 12 statistical
software
 (Ryan P (2000). Random allocation of treatments balanced in blocks: update. Stata Technical Bulletin 54: 49-53).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>PARTICIPANTS:
- In a previous study (pilot data; unpublished) the response within each subject group was normally distributed with a standard deviation 2174 steps.
- We have also shown that a mean difference of 1200 steps between experimental and control group would have clinical implications.
- Therefore, we will need to study 53 experimental subjects and 53 control subjects. 
We have accounted for a 25% attrition rate and loss to follow-up. We also adjusted for the intra-class correlation generated by having one mentor with more than one participant. We calculated the inflation factor 1+r(c-1), in which, on average, each mentor will have 2 participants (c), and we have assumed an intraclass correlation of 0.15 (r), which is considered of medium size. This would require a minimum of 76 participants, which we rounded up to 80 per group. 

MENTORS/ PHYSICAL ACTIVITY LIAISONS:
We have previously been successful in attracting over 100 potential mentors. The retention rate for mentors from training to the end of the intervention period in our previous study was 84%. If we train 50 mentors at each site and allowing for a 20% withdrawal rate this will give us at least 40 active volunteers who could be assigned two participants each. 

Data Analysis
The efficacy of the intervention will be primarily assessed with an intention-to-treat analysis at the end of the intervention with secondary analysis for the 12-month time point. This effect will be tested as the interaction between the allocation group (intervention and control) and time, on the primary and secondary outcomes. We will apply multilevel regression models (mixed models) given the repeated measures of the dataset. 

The baseline value of each outcome will be included in the model as a covariate. In a complementary analysis, we will apply imputation by chained equations to perform an intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis of primary and secondary outcome measures. Alpha will be set at 5% and all statistical tests reported will be two-tailed. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>20/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3101 - Kew</postcode>
    <postcode>3001 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Research Office
Level 5, Allan Gilbert Building
The University of Melbourne, VIC
3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Ageing Research Institute
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>34-54 Poplar Road
Parkville, VIC
3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Western Australia
</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Medicine and Pharmacology (Royal Perth Hospital Unit)
GPO Box X2213
Perth. WA 6001</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>AIM: The aim of this project is to determine whether a home-based six-month physical activity program with individual goal-setting and volunteer peer mentors can significantly increase physical activity levels in physically inactive older adults at risk of developing Alzheimer's Disease.

HYPOTHESIS: that insufficiently active participants with subjective memory complaints or mild cognitive impairment who are randomised to the goal setting intervention with a mentor compared to participants randomised to a control
group receiving standard education and peer contact will show a
significantly greater increase in their PA at the end of the intervention.

RESEARCH DESIGN: This study is a randomised, single-blind controlled trial.

METHODS: Participants are individuals with subjective memory complaints or mild cognitive impairment and do not regularly engage in more than 30 minutes of moderate intensity leisure time physical activity.

The primary outcome of interest is increase in physical activity as measured by a pedometer (steps/day). We are also  collecting cognitive, personality, physical and clinical parameters. Participants are asked to provide a DNA sample via a saliva sample. 

Participants in both groups are asked to attend three workshops in six months. At the first workshop, they will meet a peer-age volunteer. These individuals are recruited and randomly assigned to provide either telephone mentoring or telephone contact. Volunteers are trained for each role and their self-confidence and level of physical activity are measured.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Level 6 East, Main Building
300 Grattan Street
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  VIC  3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MH Project Number: 2013.020</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Unit
 St Vincents Melbourne
  PO Box 2900
 41 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy VIC 3065
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC-A 100/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicola Lautenschlager</name>
      <address>Academic Unit for Psychiatry of Old Age
The University of Melbourne
St George's Health Service
283 Cotham Rd
Kew VIC 3101</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9816 0485</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicolatl@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Ellen Gaffy</name>
      <address>Ellen Gaffy
PO Box 2127
Royal Melbourne Hospital 
Victoria 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2296</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> e.gaffy@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicola Lautenschlager</name>
      <address>Academic Unit for Psychiatry of Old Age
The University of Melbourne
St George's Health Service
283 Cotham Rd
Kew VIC 3101</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9816 0485</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicolatl@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anita Goh</name>
      <address>Academic Unit for Psychiatry of Old Age
The University of Melbourne
St George's Health Service
283 Cotham Rd
Kew VIC 3101</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9816 0513</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>goha@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>