<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373366">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001143314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A physician-led l(L)ifestyle i(I)nterv(V)entional program with goals of weight loss and e(E)xercise participation in overweight and obese patients with heart failure and reduced (REDUCED) ejection fraction.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A physician-led l(L)ifestyle i(I)nterv(V)entional program with goals of weight loss and e(E)xercise participation in overweight and obese patients with heart failure and reduced (REDUCED) ejection fraction.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LIVE-REDUCED</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is designed as a prospective, local multi-centre randomised control trial. A total of 150 patients will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to enrol in a physician-led interventional lifestyle program (pathway A), or standard medical management (pathway B). At the time of consent, all participants will be assigned either Pathway A or B. Depending upon on recruitment rates, the trial may be expanded to other Australian sites.

Group A (Lifestyle and Weight loss intervention):

For patients randomised to the intervention (Group A), a structured, motivational and goal-directed program using face-to-face physician-led counselling will be used for weight reduction. The overall duration of the intervention is 12 months. This lifestyle intervention clinic will deliver risk factor management to the patient with the help of a research assistant. Patients will be encouraged to utilise support counselling and schedule more frequent reviews as required after the initial intensive phase. Initial weight reduction will be attempted by a meal plan and behaviour modification. Meals plans will consist of high protein and low glycemic index, calorie controlled foods, targeted to a maximum of 1500 calories per day. If patients lose &lt;3% of weight after 3-months they will then be prescribed very-low-calorie (VLCD) meal replacement sachets (Nestle Health Sciences) for 1-2 meals per day with an aim of ~800-1000 calories per day. 

The initial goal is to reduce body weight by 10%. After patients achieve the initial goal, meal replacement will be substituted to high protein and low glycemic index, calorie-controlled foods to achieve a target BMI of less than, or equal to, 25kg per m2. During periods of prescription of very-low-calorie meal replacement sachets, participants will undergo a protocol of electrolyte monitoring. As recommended on the Nestle Health Sciences product information sheet, patients on diuretics may need the dose reduced or the diuretic ceased altogether as postural hypotension may occur. Patients will be monitored closely, preferably under specialist caer and fluid restrictions will be modified if appropriate to suit individual requirements. Electrolytes will be monitored more frequently (twice per week during the intensive phase). If a study participant is prescribed VLCD, the guidance and assistance of a Clinical Dietician will occur and patients will be reviewed by a Clinical Dietician as they are commenced on this protocol.

During the intensive phase of the intervention (the 1st 12 weeks), initially weekly (for the 1st six weeks), and consequently fortnightly visits will be scheduled. The initial visit will be for 45mins to 1 hour, followed by 20 minutes for subsequent visits. After the intensive phase, a tailored program of visits will be scheduled for the duration of the intervention (monthly, or 2-monthly visits).
 
Exercise:

The American Heart Association has previously produced a scientific statement that documents the physiological benefits and safety of prescribed exercise in patients with a diagnosis of heart failure.  Following the performance of the Cardio-pulmonary exercise test (CPET), a scheduled visit will occur with an Exercise Physiologist. This 45 minute consultation will involve a discussion regarding the results of the CPET and formulation of an individualised exercise plan. The personalised exercise plan will be adapted to an individual's musculoskeletal capacity, their baseline level of fitness and their personal ability to adapt to exercise in their weekly routines. In general terms for this study, low intensity aerobic exercise (walking, cycling, swimming), will be prescribed initially for 20-minutes thrice-weekly (with an aim of 60% of the individuals maximum predicted heart rate). This will then increasing to at least 200-minutes of moderate-intensity activity per week (which will include resistance training). The patients will be advised to maintain a lifestyle journal in which patients log their daily food intake, weight, blood pressure and exercise duration. This journal will be utilized for giving necessary exercise advice and assisting as an effective behavioural tool for modification. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>Group B (Controls):
Group B will continue standard of care for HF management and follow-up. Medications will be prescribed by their treating cardiologists and referrals for device therapy will occur (where indicated). They will also have attention to management of comorbidities including sleep disorders, iron deficiency and depression.

A written information sheet will be provided to Group B regarding the standard of care for weight loss advice and exercise for patients with HF and obesity 

Other Management:

All patients (Group A &amp; Group B) enrolled in this study will have ongoing guideline targeted HF management. This will include medical management with up-titration of medical therapy where appropriate, utilisation of diuretic therapy to achieve euvoleumia and lifestyle advice including weight monitoring and fluid restriction where indicated. Referral for cardiac device therapy will occur when appropriate. Attention to monitoring for the presence of iron deficiency will occur and iron infusions will be prescribed in accordance with the latest ESC Guideline recommendations as appropriate. Patients will also be referred for cardiac transplantation assessment if indicated. There will be attention to addressing additional lifestyle factors such as smoking, alcohol and recreational drug use, with referral to multidisciplinary clinics where appropriate. 

All patients will be supplied with a Patient Heart Failure Education Booklet. This is a thorough information booklet produced by The Alfred Hospital Heart Failure Service. It provides clinical information to patients on management of their heart failure, including lifestyle factors. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Composite endpoint of 12 month change in quality of life score (as measured by Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire Score); and change in exercise capacity (as by peak VO2 on CPET).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in six minute walk distance
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in BDI-II (Depression) Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in SF-36 Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in International Physical Activity Questionnaire Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in New York Heart Association Status</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum biomarkers including 
- B-Natriuretic Peptide (BNP) - biomarker of myocardial stretch with prognostic significant in heart failure.
- Galectin 3 levels (biomarker of fibrosis with prognostic value in heart failure).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of device therapy including high voltage device therapies from ICDs (using the data obtained on outpatient device checks periodically and from hospital medical records as well as remote monitoring downloads),</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of hospitalisations (via patient reporting at each visit),</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Echocardiographic measured cardiac structural effects:
Left atrial volume
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in heart rate variability (as assessed from Holter monitoring).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in peak metabolic equivalents of task (METs) - A subgroup will undergo Exercise Stress Testing. 15 randomly selected participants in each sub-group will undergo an exercise stress test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac Magnetic Reasonance Imaging (CMR) will be performed in  30 randomly selected participants from each subgroup. Cardiac MRI enabled measurement of left atrial ejection fraction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in BMI</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement to proceed to cardiac transplantation and/or left ventricular assist device implantation (this will be assessed through data collected at clinical visits and the review of medical records).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 12 month period of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left ventricular ejection fraction measured using echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interventricular septal wall thickness (mm) measured using parasternal long-axis image on trans-thoracic echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Estimated pulmonary artery pressure on echocardiography (including the estimated right atrial pressure).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mitral annulus, e' = cm/sec (average) - measured using tissue Doppler imaging on trans-thoracic echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mitral annular S velocity (as measured using Tissue Doppler Imaging)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months following enrolment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak global longitudinal strain - measured using GE Software (offline) - images obtained with trans-thoracic echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months following enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Employment</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference (measured in centimetres) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI based measurement of LV mass</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI based measurement of left ventricular ejection fraction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI enabled measurement of right ventricular ejection fraction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI enabled measurement of left atrial volume.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI enabled measurement of LV global longitudinal strain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI enabled measurement of LV radial strain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI enabled measurement of LV circumferential strain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Established diagnosis of HF-REF (as defined by the presence of the clinical syndrome of heart failure and documented cardiac systolic dysfunction on cardiac imaging, with a measured left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;45%).
	On established medical therapy (not currently undergoing an active phase or program of up-titration of medical therapy).
	Age &gt;18 and &lt;80 at the time of enrolment.
	BMI &gt;27kg/m2
	New York Heart Association Classification II, III or ambulatory class IV.
	&gt; 1 month following a previous admission to hospital with exacerbation or diagnosis of HF
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Current listing for cardiac transplantation or placement of left ventricular assist device.
	History of myocardial infarction or cardiac surgery within the previous 3 months.
	Frequent hospitalisations with HF (&gt;2 in the previous 6 months).
	Significant cardiac valvulopathy (with the exception of functional mitral and tricuspid regurgitation)
	Active malignancy, active autoimmune or systemic inflammatory disease; severe renal or hepatic failure.
	Acute &amp; potentially reversible causes of HF (eg. Takostubo cardiomyopathy, acute myocarditis).
	Unstable ventricular arrhythmias in preceding 3 months
	Significant chronic disease that prevents enrolment in the program such as active malignancy, severe pulmonary disease, end-stage renal or hepatic failure, other physical disability resulting in inability to exercise.
	Pregnancy.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Adelaide
North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Adelaide</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Adelaide
North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This local-multicentre, prospective, randomised control study will aim to assess the impact of an intentional weight loss and a prescribed exercise program in overweight and obese patients with heart failure and reduced ejection fraction (HF-REF). 

The impact of the program will be assessed by the measurement at 12 months of the change in exercise capacity (as measured by peak VO2 on CPET), and the change in KCCQ score compared with baseline measurements. These two parameters will be the composite endpoints. A number of secondary endpoints will be collected to assess the prognostic significance (including mortality, rate of hospitalisations, changes in New York Heart Association Classification (NYHA)), cardiac structural, functional, mood and cardiac biomarker effects of this program. 

This study aims to assist in clarifying the degree of controversy and uncertainty about the appropriateness of advice to patients with obesity and established HF-REF. This is a result of a recurrently observed, but somewhat controversial obesity paradox in a number of heart failure (HF) studies where patients with HF and higher body mass index (BMI) appear to have improved outcomes including less deterioration of functional class and lower mortality rates compared with those who have HF and a lower BMI. 

There is a paucity of published clinical studies that have assessed the combined effects of an intentional weight loss and prescribed exercise program on heart failure outcomes including functional measures, hospitalisations, mortality, and cardiac structural changes along with measured serum biomarkers. This study will evaluate the effects of a structured lifestyle interventional program compared with standard of care in overweight and obese patients with heart failure and reduced ejection fraction.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Adelaide Local Health Network Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/RAH/56</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorders
Level 5 McEwin Building 
The Royal Adelaide Hospital 
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2723</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82222722 </fax>
      <email>prash.sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorders
Level 5 McEwin Building 
The Royal Adelaide Hospital 
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2723</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82222722 </fax>
      <email>prash.sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorders
Level 5 McEwin Building 
The Royal Adelaide Hospital 
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2723</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82222722 </fax>
      <email>prash.sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Stokes</name>
      <address>Centre For Heart Rhythm Disorders
Level 5 McEwin Building 
The Royal Adelaide Hospital 
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 0403338892</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mbstokes83@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>