<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347614">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001152910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Association between exposure to second-hand smoke and sleep bruxism in children: a randomised control study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Children with sleep bruxism exposed to second-hand smoke, compared to not exposed children with sleep bruxism, increased their bruxing activity.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1125-3539</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Problem studied: sleep bruxism in children exposed to second-hand smoke. Subjects were recruited from a school project about the risks of second-hand smoke. Children found with sleep bruxism and exposed to second-hand smoke were included in the study.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Sleep bruxism was analysed in children of group 1 after six-months of not being exposed to second-hand smoke. The smoking members of the families in group 1 were asked not to smoke in the presence of the child for a period of six months. Parents were told prior to study enrolment that they would not be required to quit smoking as part of study participation; rather they would be asked to eliminate children second hand smoke exposure. The study does not include parents who do not smoke. Children with bruxism exposed to second-hand smoke and then not exposed for 6 months ( same children, same families) were compared with a control group of children with bruxism exposed to second-hand smoke for 6 months. Some families selected in group 1 refused to participate in the trial because, despite being informed about the risks of SHS, they reported that they would not have been able to reduce SHS exposure for their children.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: Sleep bruxism was analysed in children of group 2 after six-months of exposure to second-hand smoke. No treatment or change in behaviour was performed in this group. This part of the trial was observational. Parents were smokers and did not to change their smoking habits. Families selected in group 2 and participating in the trial were those reporting not being able to reduce children exposure to SHS. Those parents of group 2 who decided to reduce children exposure to SHS did not participate.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of sleep bruxism as assessed by by the American Sleep Disorders Association</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at six months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of exposure to second-hand smoke: occasional, low, moderate, heavy. Data were collected by self-reported questionnaire and personal interview. During the interview the interviewer reviewed the answers on the self-reported questionnaire for completeness and internal consistency. Questionnaire are done with both children and parents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at six months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children from elementary schools.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Cleft lip and palate; disability, respiratory disorders; orthodontic and/or orthopaedic treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>We selected from the sample of volunteers those children with sleep bruxism and exposed to second-hand smoke. The children with sleep bruxism and exposed to SHS were randomly divided into two groups. The allocation sequence was concealed from the researcher enrolling and assessing participants in sequentially numbered, opaque and sealed envelopes. In order to prevent subversion of the allocation sequence, the name and date of birth of the participant was written on the envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software. Computer-generated random numbers were used to assign patients to the 2 treatment arms within each stratum.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>116</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Luisa Montaldo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Via De Crecchio
80131
Naples.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The goal of this study was to investigate the association between second hand smoke exposure and sleep bruxism in children. Nicotine is known to induce acetylcholine and glutamate synaptic transmission and enhance dopamine release. In smokers, nicotine accumulates in the body during the time spent awake, decreasing gradually during sleep. Higher levels of smoking, leading to increased levels of nicotine and dopamine release, could thus be related to increased oromotor activity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comitato etico seconda universita di napoli</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Via Costantinopoli 
80138 
NAPOLI</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009-013663-26</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Italy</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Luisa Montaldo</name>
      <address>via de crecchio
80131
Napoli
italy</address>
      <phone>+393483523825</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lmontaldo@libero.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pasquale Esposito</name>
      <address>Pzza garibaldi</address>
      <phone>+393333794889</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>espositop@hotmail.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Monica Rea</name>
      <address>Via Foria
80121
Naples
Italy.</address>
      <phone>+393312141221</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>monicarea@hotmail.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>