<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369975">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000203459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Sleeping Well Trial: enhancing the effectiveness of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) treatment with a weight management program for overweight adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Increasing the effectiveness of treatment with continuous positive airways pressure (CPAP) using a weight-management program in overweight adults with sleep apnoea : the Sleeping Well Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To address aim 1) Primary outcome (weight) as measured during each month during the control and intervention periods of the stepped wedge design will be compared between periods. The main effect of the intervention will be examined using a multilevel, mixed effects, linear mixed model analysis approach. Fixed effects will be included in this model for time and intervention, while a random effect will be included for the effect of participant.
To address aim 2) We will examine the association between lifestyle intervention commencement month and weight at 12 month follow-up (adjusted for baseline weight). This analysis will treat "lifestyle intervention commencement month" as a continuous variable and examine both a linear and quadratic relationship with the outcome. 

CPAP treatment: All CPAP implementation will be provided centrally for all patients by Air Liquide Healthcare. Patients will undergo mask fitting and education regarding sleep apnoea and CPAP use by staff at Air Liquide. Patients will initially be commenced on Autotitrating CPAP using a Resmed S9 CPAP machine. After 1 week of treatment, patients will be switched to fixed pressure CPAP based on the 95th centile pressure determined during the autotitration week. Routine equipment troubleshooting will be provided by Air Liquide, in conjunction with the patients treating physician. Patients will undergo routine CPAP care co-ordinated by their physician. All decisions regarding any treatment changes will be made by the treating physician. Participants are required to use their CPAP devices regularly for 12 months period (beginning from consent date).

Lifestyle Intervention: All participants will be exposed to the 6-month weight management program. The wait list time for starting treatment will differ with subjects randomised to wait 1,2,3,4,5 or 6 months before they commence. The Intervention is a dietitian delivered face to face intervention comprising of a 1 hour initial appointment followed up by monthly 30 minute consultations. Dietary energy will be reduced using a tailored approach with a 12 week active weight loss phase followed by a 12 week transfer to weight maintenance phase the duration of each phase will be dependant on how much weight each participant has to lose and their success, which is monitored monthly by body weight. 
The use of an App to extend the reach of the face to face sessions will be utilised. The App allows the participant to connect virtually with their dietitian to report hurdles, feelings or mood that may affect their progress towards their goals. The dietitian can communicate via a pre-defined pathway of text messages which are sent to the participant to motivate them to continue to meet their 'small steps'.

Activity is encouraged with 3 x 30 minutes per week of light/ moderate physical activity. 

Compliance is measured for activity via a wrist worn monitor (Fitbit) which records minute by minute activity on a website which the participant consents to the research team being able to access. Dietary recording is used to monitor compliance with meal plans and agreed nutrient goals. Compliance with CPAP treatment is recorded individually and is inbuilt into each CPAP machine, as minutes per day that it is used. </interventions>
    <comparator>All participants will have active treatment by CPAP machine for their sleep apnoea through the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Both aims will use weight as the outcome measure (weight in kilograms measured on a digital scale). Weight will be measured monthly during the control and the intervention periods. Different data collection timepoints are used to address both aim 1 and 2.
The stepped wedge design enables many data collection points to contribute to answering aim 1.. To address aim 2 we will examine the association between lifestyle intervention commencement month and weight at 12 month follow-up (adjusted for baseline weight).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weight will be measured monthly for all participants. We will examine the association between lifestyle intervention commencement month and weight at 12 month follow-up (adjusted for baseline weight) to answer aim 2. This analysis will treat "lifestyle intervention commencement month" as a continuous variable and examine both a linear and quadratic relationship with the outcome. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body fat (%) and fat free mass (%) will be measured immediately prior to starting the lifestyle intervention by the reference method of dual energy xray absorptiometry  and after 6 months (on completion of the lifestyle intervention) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to commencing the 6 months of lifestyle intervention and on completion of the lifestyle intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults aged 19-68 years who have been newly diagnosed with moderate-severe untreated OSA with AHI greater than 20 events/hr (AASM alternate criteria) (demonstrated by prior overnight polysomnography [PSG]). Participants must be overweight with a body mass index (BMI) for Caucasians between 25 and 43 kg/m2 and for those of Asian and Indian descent 23 and 43 and self report a sedentary lifestyle ((self-reported exercise less than 2 days/week and a duration of less than 45 minutes per session. Eligible participants are required to be eligible to use Fixed-Pressure Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>68</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnant women
2. Diagnosed with concomitant obesity hypoventilation syndrome,  Diabetes mellitus type 1, severe psychiatric disorder,  and drowsiness
3. Required to use "VPAP" or "BPAP" (variable/bilevel positive airway pressure)
4. Unable to exercise (e.g. due to orthopedic or musculoskeletal problems)
5. Previous surgical or current medical treatment for OSA
6. Previous bariatric surgery
7. Current use of weight loss programs and/or weight loss drugs
8. Recent angina pectoris or atrial fibrillation
9. Insufficient knowledge of English language to be able to consent
10. Unable to provide informed consent
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation known only to study statistician and stored in co-investigators office in opaque sealed envelopes and will be made available only after recruitment of an individual.
Recruiters, outcome assessors and physicians providing care are blinded to group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Conducted by the Study statistician using sequence generated in Excel Randbetween procedure. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Design: Randomised controlled trial utilizing 6 different delay periods between commencement of CPAP and commencement of the lifestyle intervention.  There will be groups with 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 months delay.  
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations:
Our proposed research design has 6 separate steps (delay periods) not including the baseline assessment. If we were to recruit 7 participants into each group, it would provide 82% power to detect a main effect of the intervention of 1.5 Kg difference in weight between intervention and control assessments.  This assumes a standard deviation of 3.09 Kg (based on previously collected local data), uses a conservative ICC of 0.01, and treats each individual participant as its own cluster (as this is the unit of randomisation).  Collecting 10 participants per group will provide coverage within the trial for potential drop-outs and missing data while maintaining adequate trial power.
Statistical analysis plan
The main effect of the intervention will be examined using a multilevel, mixed effects, linear mixed model analysis approach. Fixed effects will be included in this model for time and intervention, while a random effect will be included for the effect of participant.
We will examine whether there is a difference in the rate of change in primary outcome between control and intervention periods using a time-by-intervention interaction effect.
The effect of delay in provision of the lifestyle intervention will be investigated by examining an intervention-by-delay period interaction effect. Both a linear effect of the period of delay and a quadratic effect will be investigated. Statistical adjustment will be made for other relevant variables in each of these analyses.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Be Active Sleep Eat Facility
Monash University
1/264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill 3168
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Food, Nutrition and Dietetics
School of Clinical Sciences
Monash University
1/264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill 3168
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Air Liquide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5 / 476 Gardeners Road
Alexandria
NSW 2015

Provision of CPAP devices and support to all participants in this trial</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Air Liquide Healthcare</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>5 / 476 Gardeners Road
Alexandria
NSW 2015</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study has been designed to elucidate when is the optimal time to introduce weight management to newly diagnosed patients with OSA who are about to commence on standard care which is overnight CPAP. We have designed this trial to have a step wedge element so that each person will be exposed to the intervention over a 12 month period. To address aim 1) Primary outcome (weight) as measured during each month during the control and intervention periods of the stepped wedge design will be compared between periods. The main effect of the intervention will be examined using a multilevel, mixed effects, linear mixed model analysis approach. Fixed effects will be included in this model for time and intervention, while a random effect will be included for the effect of participant.
To address aim 2) We will examine the association between lifestyle intervention commencement month and weight at 12 month follow-up (adjusted for baseline weight). This analysis will treat "lifestyle intervention commencement month" as a continuous variable and examine both a linear and quadratic relationship with the outcome. 

This design has certain advantages over standard randomized controlled trials which include enabling every participant to be exposed to the intervention and that the impact of time is assessed. This design consists of an initial period, where no one is exposed to the intervention. Eventually, at regular intervals (the steps) one cluster (one group) will be randomised to cross from the control to the intervention under evaluation.

 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Services
Monash Health
Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Road
Clayton 3168
Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/MonH/93 Ref 15357A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369975-MHHREC Final approval v2. 20Oct2015.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Truby</name>
      <address>Department of Food, Nutrition and Dietetics
Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat facility
1/264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
Vic 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9902 4261</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.truby@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Truby</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics
Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat facility
1/264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
Vic 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9902 4261</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.truby@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Truby</name>
      <address>Department of Food, Nutrition and Dietetics
Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat facility
1/264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
Vic 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9902 4261</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.truby@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Truby</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition and Dietetics
Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat facility
1/264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill
Vic 3168
</address>
      <phone>+613 9902 4261</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.truby@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>