<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367468">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000838415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Analgesic effect of adding dexmedetomidine and or nitroglycerin (NTG) to lidocaine for intravenous regional anesthesia: a randomized clinical trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Analgesic effect of adding dexmedetomidine and or nitroglycerin (NTG)  to lidocaine for intravenous regional anesthesia in patients scheduled for forearm surgery.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-8062</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition> Intra and post-operative pain with intravenous regional anesthesia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Forearm/hand disorder/accident requiring surgery' </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patients will be randomly allocated into four groups (20 patients in each group): group I (lidocaine group; the control group) will receive 3 mg/kg of Lidocaine alone. The other three groups will receive the same amount of Lidocaine plus 1 microgram/kg dexmedetomidine in group II (dexmedetomidine group), 200 microgram nitroglycrin (NTG) in group III (nitroglycerin group) and 1 microgram/kg dexmedetomidine + 200 microgram NTG in group  IV (dexmedetomidine-nitroglycerin group). In all groups the study drugs will be diluted with 0.9% normal saline to a total volume of 40 ml and will be prepared in identical syringes by an anesthetist not involved in the study protocol.On arrival to operating room, the patients will be monitored for heart rate (using ECG), oxygen saturation (using pulse oximetry), arterial  blood pressure (non -invasive measurement of systolic, diastolic and mean values every 5 minutes) and the baseline values will be recorded. For each patient two intravenous cannulae will be inserted; the first (22-guage or smaller) in a distal vein of the operative hand for slow injection of the study drugs for intravenous regional anesthesia (IVRA) and will be removed immediately after injection of the anesthetic solution, and the second cannula will be inserted in the hand of the contra-lateral side for intraoperative fluid transfusion.  
    An Esmarch bandage will be used for exsanguination  of the operative arm  after its elevation for 5 minutes then, a double cuffed pneumatic tourniquet  will be wrapped around the upper arm. The proximal cuff will be inflated between 30 and 90 minutes at the discretion of the treating anaesthetist to 100 mm Hg above the systolic pressure  of the patient or at least 250 mm Hg. IVRA will be achieved with slow injection of  the study solution according to the patient's group.  After  the onset of sensory and motor block, the distal cuff of the tourniquet  will be inflated to 250 mm Hg, and the proximal cuff will be released. Tourniquet pain, will be assessed using visual analogue scale (VAS) score (where o= no pain and 10 = the most severe pain) will be measured and recorded before and 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min after injection of anesthetic solution if the VAS more than 3 the patient will receive 50 microgram fentanyl intravenous bolus.  After the end of surgery deflation of the cuff will done using a deflation/re-inflation technique for 3 cycles of deflation of the cuff for 5 seconds and then re-inflation for 1 minute.
</interventions>
    <comparator>group I (lidocaine group; the control group) will receive 3 mg/kg of Lidocaine alone diluted with 0.9% normal saline to a total volume of 40 ml.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Duration of analgesia by review of medical records . </outcome>
      <timepoint>from the time of injection of the anesthetic solution to first analgesic requirement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Tourniquet pain, will be assessed using visual analogue scale (VAS) score (where o = no pain and 10 = the most severe pain) </outcome>
      <timepoint>will be measured and recorded before and 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 minutes after injection of anesthetic solution, if the VAS more than 3 patient will receive 50 micrograms fentanyl. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Analgesic consumption by review of medical records </outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 24 h post operation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Arterial blood pressure using digital sphymomanometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min after injection of the anesthetic solution and at 30 min and 2, 4, 6, 12 ,18 and 24 hours after the tourniquet deflation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Heart rate using ECG and pulse oximetry. </outcome>
      <timepoint>before and at 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 and 30 min after injection of the anesthetic solution and at 30 min and 2, 4, 6, 12 ,18 and 24 hours after the tourniquet deflation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of any complication e.g. nausea, assessed by 5-Point Likert Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>in the first 24 hours post-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria> Eighty patients of both sex, aged (20 - 60) years scheduled for hand or forearm surgery, ASA physical status class I and II </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with open fractures of upper limb, sickle cell anemia, peripheral vascular insufficiency,  cardiac disease, hypertensive patients, liver or, kidney disease, patients who are taking any analgesia within the previous 24 h, or history of drug allergy, will be excluded from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients will be randomly allocated </concealment>
    <sequence>closed envelopes  and computer generated random numbers into four groups 20 patients in each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/09/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Tanta, Elgharbia governorate.</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Elgeesh street, Tanta University Educational Hospital, Tanta, Elgharbia governorate.
postal code:31257
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tanta University Educational Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Elgeesh street, Tanta University Educational Hospital, Tanta, Elgharbia governorate.
postal code:31257</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>non</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>non</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to evaluate the effect of adding dexmedetomidine and or nitroglycerin (NTG) to lidocaine on the quality of intravenous regional anesthesia (IVRA) in patients scheduled for  hand or forearm surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics committee of the faculty of Medicine Tanta University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Elgeesh street, Tanta University Educational Hospital, Tanta, Elgharbia governorate.
postal code:31257</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>30935/05/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>Elgeesh street, Tanta University Educational Hospital, Tanta, Elgharbia governorate.
postal code:31257</address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodaezz714@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>Elgeesh street, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University Educational Hospital, Tanta, Elgharbia Governorate.
postal code:31257</address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodaezz714@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>Elgeesh street, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University Educational Hospital, Tanta, Elgharbia Governorate.
postal code:31257</address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodaezz714@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>Elgeesh street, Faculty of Medicine, Tanta University Educational Hospital, Tanta, Elgharbia Governorate.
postal code:31257</address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodaezz714@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>