<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370470">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000444482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Vascular adaptations to 8 weeks of different types of cycling in healthy older adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Vascular adaptations to 8 weeks of different types of cycling in healthy older adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vascular health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vascular function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of three 8 week training interventions. All training sessions will be completed at the Murdoch University Exercise Physiology laboratories and will last approximately 40-75 minutes per session (depending on group allocation). 

Irrespective of the participants group allocation, all exercise sessions will be conducted with groups of up to six participants on a cycle ergometer (WattBike Pro or Trainer, Wattbike Australia, AUS). All exercise intensities will be prescribed according to a predetermined level of perceived exertion, using the Borg 6-20 rating of perceived exertion (RPE) scale, which is associated with a desired percent of aerobic capacity (VO2peak). Each session will begin and end with a 5 minute double-leg cycling based warm-up (intensity; RPE 11-13, 40-60% VO2peak) and cool down (intensity; RPE 8-10, 20-40% VO2peak). The moderate intensity double-leg continuous group will cycle continuously for 40 minutes at an RPE 11-13  (40-60% VO2peak) using normal double-leg cycling. The high intensity double-leg interval cycling group will complete twenty 30 second double-leg efforts at an RPE 15-17 (60-85% VO2peak) with each effort separated by 60 seconds of passive rest (RPE 6; &lt;20% VO2peak). The high intensity single-leg interval cycling group will complete twenty 30 second single-leg efforts at an RPE of 15-17 with each effort separated by 60 seconds of passive rest (RPE 6). At the completion of the first twenty efforts, a short break will be provided (~5 minutes) prior to the participants completing another twenty efforts with the opposite leg.

3 sessions per week will be prescribed and monitored by Miss Nicole Gordon, an ESSA Accredited Exercise Physiologist. Program adherence will be monitored through exercise logs.</interventions>
    <comparator>The moderate intensity double-leg continuous group will be used as the control treatment group as the exercise to be undertaken is recommended by leading sport and exercise groups, such as Exercise and Sports Science Australia and the American College of Sports Medicine, for the improvement and/or maintanence of general health and wellbeing.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in brachial artery flow-mediated dilation will be assessed by noninvasive ultrasound analysis of change in blood vessel size prior to and following occlusion of blood flow using a blood pressure cuff for five minutes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4, 9 and 16 weeks after commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in biomarkers of vascular health and function will be assessed by analysis of a single blood sample for endothelial nitric oxide synthase and vascular endothelial growth factor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4, 9 and 16 weeks after commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in maximal aerobic capacity will be assessed through analysis of expired air during a graded exercise test to volitional exhaustion on a Velotron cycle ergometer (RacerMate, USA). Expired air will be analysed by a Parvo TrueOne metabolic cart (ParvoMedics, USA) .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 9 and 16 weeks after commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in maximal cardiac output will be assessed by an automated impedance cardiograph system (Q-Link,PhysioFlow, France) during the graded exercise test to volitional exhaustion on a Velotron cycle ergometer (RacerMate, USA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 9 and 16 weeks after commencement of intevention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition will be assessed by waist and hip circumference as well as a dual energy xray absorptiometry (DEXA) scan (Discovery Series W, Hologic, USA) for determination of body fat, muscle and bone mineral content. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 9 and 16 weeks after commencement of intevention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in heart structure (left ventricular mass and volumes) will be assessed by a magnetic resonance imaging scan of the heart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 9 weeks after commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in biomarkers of cardiovascular disease risk will be assessed as a composite outcome by a single fasting blood sample analysing total cholesterol, low density lipoprotein cholesterol, high density lipoprotein cholesterol, triglycerides, insulin and glucose. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4, 9 and 16 weeks after commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in physical activity levels outside the structured exercise program being delivered will be assessed by the International Physical Activity Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4, 9 and 16 weeks after commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Healthy older adults between 45 and 75 years old
2. Able to attend Murdoch University Exercise Physiology Laboratory or Curtin University Exercise Physiology Laboratory 3 times per week for 8 weeks for approximately 16 to 30 hours in total (depending on group allocation).
3. Able to attend Murdoch University Exercise Physiology Laboratory for testing sessions at baseline, 4 weeks, 9 weeks and 16 weeks after commencement of the intervention (approximately 7 hours in total).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previously diagnosed with a cardiovascular or metabolic disorder
2. Pregnancy
3. Individuals who smoke regularly or have quit in the last 6 months
4. Must answer no the first seven questions in the Exercise and Sports Science Australia pre-screening tool or have a medical clearance from their general practitioner
5. Currently participating in a structured exercise training program, defined as &gt;90 minutes per week of planned exercise for the purpose of improving health and fitness and/or performance</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation by computer, and then placed into sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation based on changes in flow-mediated dilation prior to and following 12 weeks of either moderate intensity continuous cycling or increased intensity short duration cycling in older individuals with coronary artery disease [Currie KD et al. (2013). Low-volume, high-intensity interval training in patients with CAD. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 45 (8): 1436-1442.]. We used the mean group change for our calculation (effect size = 0.45, a = 0.05 and power = 0.8). Initial results indicate 14 participants per group was necessary; however we will aim to recruit an additional 20% (i.e. 17 per group) to account for possible drop outs.  

All analyses will be conducted on an intention-to-treat basis. Linear mixed modelling will be used to assess differences between interventions for vascular function, endothelial nitric oxide synthase, vascular endothelial growth factor, maximal aerobic capacity, heart strucutre and function, cardiovascular disease risk factors and body composition. Significant main effects or interactions will be analysed using Tukeys post hoc analysis. Statistical analysis will be performed using SPSS v21.0 data analysis software (SPSS, Chicago, IL) with significance set at p &lt; 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/10/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>51</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>57</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>28/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychology and Exercise Science, Murdoch University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Edith Cowan University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent Street
Bentley WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Exercise training is commonly used for the treatment and prevention of many chronic diseases. Of particular interest are the effects of exercise training to prevent many age-related changes, including reduction in blood vessel health and whole body fitness. Healthy older adults will be recruited to participate in an 8 week exercise training program where they will be randomised to one of three different cycle training groups: moderate intensity double-leg continuous cycling, high intensity double-leg interval cycling, or high intensity single-leg interval cycling. Measures of blood vessel function, heart structure and function, fitness and body composition will be obtained at baseline, 4 weeks (blood sample and vessel function only), 9 weeks and 16 weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Murdoch University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 1.006, Chancellery
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicole Gordon</name>
      <address>Room 3.006, Refrectory 
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 448 098 227</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Gordon@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicole Gordon</name>
      <address>Room 3.006, Refrectory 
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 448 098 227</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Gordon@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicole Gordon </name>
      <address>Room 3.006, Refrectory 
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch WA 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 448 098 227</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Gordon@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>