<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369607">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001205426p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Responses to a trauma intervention among Liberian participants who survived Humanitarian Emergencies</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cognitive and Electrophysiological Responses to a Trauma Intervention for Humanitarian Emergencies</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-0347</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A standardized protocol has been designed for the therapeutic intervention proposed for this experiment (App). Audio exercises recorded via a text-to-speech software will be delivered to participants via mobile technology for self-administration at home. There are 48 daily tasks ranging between 20'' to 10 minutes each, to be completed over a 1 week period (90-100 minutes per day for 7 consecutive days). Built as a multimodal approach, the tasks are categorized across seven different blocks.

Blocks 1, 3, 4, and 6 focus on body stabilization. It aims to promote a sense of safety, physiological awareness and regulation of the autonomic nervous system (ANS), optimizing heart rate variability (HRV), restoring parasympathetic tone, and enhancing inhibition ?of automated defense systems in non-life threatening environments. Techniques include somatic experiencing, breath work, biofeedback, muscle relaxation, guided visualization, and bilateral tapping during drumming sounds. Blocks 2 and 7 target the relational domain, introducing effective working models of attachment, self-reflective information processing and positive affect enhancement. Techniques include interpersonal skills development, initiation and engagement of altruistic tasks. Block 5 introduces mindfulness practice. Exercises focus on practice of mindful attention shifting from external surroundings (objects and sounds) to internal body awareness (grounding, sensation tracking, self-attribution, meaning-making, coping resources and positive affect),  with the purpose of enhancing overall executive function capacities and further promote sense of internal safety.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Male and female subjects who meet the DSM-4 or DSM-5 diagnostic criteria for PTSD will be assigned to the PTSD experimental group (EXP_PTSD n=30). Those who do not meet the diagnostic will be assigned to the control group (CON n=30). Both groups will equally receive the same intervention and complete all of the same intake, baseline and post-test assessments.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Dynamical complexity (D2) of the EEG in PTSD patients</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (day 1) and at post test (day 8) when intervention is concluded.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- delete</outcome>
      <timepoint>- delete</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in PTSD diagnostic criteria among experimental group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (day 1) and at post test (day 9) when intervention is concluded.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB) scores.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (day 1) and at post test (day 8) when intervention is concluded.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>
Experimental group (PTSD):
(a) Meets the DSM-4 or DSM-5 diagnostic criteria for PTSD.
(b) Ages 30-50.
(c) Liberian ethnicity.
(d) English proficiency.
(e) Departed Liberia or refugee camps in West Africa during the civil war, ragile peace periods or during the recent Ebola endemic (1989-2015). 

Controls:
(a) Must not meet the DSM-5 diagnostic criteria for PTSD or Sub-threshold PTSD and other psychiatric or neurological disorders.
(b) Must not report any PTSD symptom for the past 10 years.
(c) Ages 30-50.
(d) Liberian ethnicity.
(e) English proficiency.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Experimental group (PTSD):
(a) Current drug/alcohol abuse or dependency.
(b) Current use of psychotropic medication or use in the past 2 months. 
(c) History of severe Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI).
(d) Severe medical condition.
(e) Genetic disorders.
(f) Concurrent psychotherapy for PTSD.
(g) Acute risk of suicide or homicide. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Male and female subjects who meet the DSM-4 or DSM-5 diagnostic criteria for PTSD will be assigned to the PTSD experimental group (EXP-PTSD n=30). Those who do not meet the diagnostic will be assigned to the control group (CON n=30). Both groups will equally receive the same intervention and complete all of the same intake, baseline and post-test assessments. Experimental group subjects will in addition complete the CAPS-5 past week interview at post-treatment.
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The proposed sample size for this study (EXP=30 and controls=30) is based on our primary outcome measure, the EEG Correlation Dimension (D2). We computed the effect size in accordance with D2 values of the EEG in PTSD patients and healthy controls from a previous study of dimensional complexity in PTSD (Chae et al., 2004). Firstly, we calculated a mean of 11.9911 for the non-PTSD group and of 11.1689 for the PTSD group based on EEG leads that yield significant results (Fp1, F8, C4, P4, T3, T4, T5, T6 and O1) in Chae et al. Utilizing these values, we calculated a SD estimate of 0.6120 for control and PTSD groups and a mean difference of 0.822 between PTSD and controls, leading to an effect size of 1.3435 and a 100% statistical power estimation with a sample size of n=30 per condition.
Moreover, clinical studies in PTSD have often achieved large effect sizes with samples of 30 patients per condition in accordance with the recommendations of the International Society of Traumatic Stress Studies Treatment Guidelines (2008). 

Fast Fourier Transformation (FFT) and Cross-Frequency Coupling (CFC) will be utilized to analyse spectral band power across electrophysiological data. The pre to post the intervention design will allow for a multivariate repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) that is aimed to be applied for a comparison of the EXP-PTSD and CON groups in respect to cognitive performance and electrophysiological oscillations. Chi-squared tests will be utilized to compare demographical and clinical characteristics between control and experimental groups. Correlation analysis will be applied to explore associations between the App, PTSD symptomatology, cognitive, and electrophysiological variables. Pair t-tests will be applied to explore changes between baseline and post intervention conditions.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/10/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
New South Wales, 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Sydney
New South Wales, 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Jim Lagopoulos</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 5, 100 Mallett Street Camperdown, NSW, 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Brian O'Toole</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 7, Office 700
94 Mallett Street Camperdown, NSW, 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The central purpose of this research is to measure the efficacy of a self-administered trauma intervention (App) for humanitarian emergencies. The intervention will be initially tested with Liberian refugees currently in Australia that meet the diagnostic criteria for posttraumatic disorder (PTSD). The App was created as part of this project, and comprises of body stabilization, cognitive mindfulness and interpersonal exercises across seven blocks. Objective electrophysiological and cognitive measures have been selected to predict intervention outcome. The data collected will also allow for an investigation of a possible correlation between cognitive deficits and abnormal gamma oscillations mediated via PV GABAergic interneurons, which may provide novel information in delineating the etiological foundation of memory and cognition impairment in PTSD. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney - Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2017/088</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jim Lagopoulos</name>
      <address>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY.  
Level 5, 100 Mallett Street Camperdown, NSW, 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0774</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jim.Lagopoulos@usc.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Janaina Pinto</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre, THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 4 8124 4463</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jpin6516@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Janaina Pinto</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre, THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 4 8124 4463</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jpin6516@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Janaina Pinto</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre, THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 4 8124 4463</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jpin6516@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>