<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363790">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000302752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A phase I study of Dz13 drug targeting the c-Jun gene in subjects with melanoma skin cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase I/Ib study to determine the safety and tolerability of Dz13 DNAzyme targeting c-Jun, administered to subjects with in-transit or satellite melanoma metastases via single intra tumoural injections of 100 mcg twice weekly </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1139-9983</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DISCOVER 2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>in-transit or satellite melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dz13 DNAzyme (100 mcg) complexed with lipids DOPE and DOTAP administered as single intra-tumoural injection twice weekly to cohort 1(total dose 200 mcg) for one week cycle, to cohort 2 for two weeks (total dose 400 mcg) and to cohort 3 for three weeks (total dose 600 mcg as the dose finding Part 1. Part 2 fourth expanded cohort will receive Dz13 DNAzyme (100 mcg) complexed with lipids DOPE and DOTAP administered as single intra-tumoural injection twice weekly for two or three week cycles. Selection of two or three week treatment duration will be dependent on the following conditions as assessed from cohorts 2 and 3 in Part 1:
1. acceptable saftey profile following review of all safety data by a Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) and pharmacokinetic (PK) analysis 
2. evidence of c-Jun (Dz13 treatment target gene) suppression in tumour tissue and/or evidence of tumour response change in tumour size</interventions>
    <comparator>No control treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and tolerability of Dz13 (complexed with DOPE/DOTAP) when administered to subjects with either in-transit or satellite melanoma metastases via single intra-tumoural injections of 100 mcg twice weekly from 1 week escalating to 2 and 3 week dosing cycles by adverse events (AEs), changes in vital signs, changes in clinical laboratory tests, changes in 12- lead electrocardiography (ECG).

Pre-clinical animal studies indicate some skin irritation following injection which was more likely attributable to the lipid component of study drug and thus injection site reaction reactions may be an expected AE. In a previous  Phase 1 study  of single intra-tumoural injection of up to 100 mcg Dz13 in BCC skin tumours, there no drug related serious AEs or clinically significant changes in laboratory safety parameters or ECG. Pharmacokinetic (PK) analysis indicated  no detectable levels of systemic Dz13 up to 28 days post treatment. 

Emergent AEs that might be treatment related was reported by one subject and included injection site discomfort, swelling, wound infection, nausea and blurred vision; two subjects reported phlebitis and erythema all of which were all mild and resolved. 

Monitoring of AEs and PK analysis will continue to be conducted for this next Phase I/Ib study of multiple intra-tumoural injections of Dz13 up to a maximum of six 100 mcg doses over three weeks. 
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3, 6, 24 hours per injection day (2 days/1 week cycle), 4, 10, 14, 25 and 32 days post last injection for cohort 1.
3, 24 hours per injection day (4 days/2 week cycle), 4 14, 25 and 32 days post last injection for cohort 2.
3, 24 hours per injection day (6 days/3 week cycle), 4 14, 25 and 32 days post last injection for cohort 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether six 100 mcg doses given as three week cycle has an acceptable safety profile and can be recommended for use in Phase II studies.
Assessment monitored by adverse events according to CTCAE version 4.0), changes in vital signs, clinical laboratory tests and 12-lead ECG. Safety will be evaluated by Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) at the completion of each dose cohort and on an ad-hoc basis following any dose limiting toxicities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 24 hours per injection day (6 days/3 week cycle), 4 14, 25 and 32 days post last injection for cohort 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure serum levels of Dz13 following administration of twice weekly doses of 100 mcg Dz13 complexed with DOPE and DOTAP via intra-tumoural injection commencing with two injections (1 week cycle) up to a maximum of six injections (3 week cycle).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3, 6, hours per injection day (2 days/1 cycle), 10,  25 and 32 days post last injection for cohort 1.
3 hours per injection day (4 days/2 cycles), 14, 25 and 32 days post last injection for cohort 2.
3 hours per injection day (6 days/3 cycles), 14, 25 and 32 days post last injection for cohort 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare melanoma tumour histopathology and immunohistochemistry 14 days following administration of Dz13 relative to baseline of directly treated and untreated "bystander" lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 days post last injection day.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare melanoma tumour size of treated and  lesions 4 and 14 days following Dz13 administration relative to baseline and to compare melanoma tumour size of "bystander" untreated lesion 14 days following Dz13 administration relative to baseline.

Tumour lesions will be measured in two dimensions by calipers and Solarscan digital dermoscopy imaging</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 and 14 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosed dermal in-transit or satellite metastatic melanoma with at least 3 measurable lesions at minimum distance of 5 cm from each other
ECOG performance status 0-1
Acceptable haematologic, coagulation, renal and hepatic function</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Metastatic/in-transit or satellite lesions located on face, head and neck
Women of child bearing age
Prior or co-existing malignancy
Radiotherapy to &gt;30% bone marrow in previous 3 months
Clinically significant non-malignant disease
Current immunosuppression
History of immune-mediated throbocytopenia or other platelet disease
Enrolment in another clinical study involving any other investigational agent
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed. Subject enrolled into cohorts in  sequential order</concealment>
    <sequence>Study is not randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Dose escalation Part 1: doses cohorts will receive Dz13 injections twice weekly for one week (Cohort 1) , two weeks (Cohort 2 )  and three weeks (Cohort 3). Expansion Part 2 dose cohort will receive Dz13 100 mcg injections twice weekly two weeks (2 cycles) or three weeks (3 cycles) dependent of safety profile and molecular signals of intra tumoural efficacy as determined from Part 1. Each subject will have 3 identified lesions, one control untreated lesion excised pre-Dz13 injection,  treated lesion and an untreated "bystander" lesion excised post Dz13 injection.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data from escalation Part 1 will be presented in a descriptive manner. Continuous measures will be summarised and tabulated using counts (n), mean, standard deviation (SD), median, minimum and maximum. Categorical measures will be summarised and tabulated using counts (n) by frequencies and percentage. The 95% confidence intervals will be provided. 
Plasma concentrations  of Dz13 will be expressed in ng/mL with defined Lower Limit of Quantification (LLOQ) of 1.0 ng/mL. Plasma concentrations of Dz13 will be summarised and tabulated by measurement, cohort and overall.
The primary efficacy measure in expanded cohort Part 2 will be response in  tumoural c-Jun expression. c-Jun expression values prior to and following treatment, and the changes noted, will be summarised and tabulated. 
Tumour size measures and molecular tumoural characteristics prior to and following treatment, and the changes noted, will be summarised and tabulated by cohort and overall for Cohorts 1, 2 and 3 as secondary efficacy endpoints
A mixed models repeated measures analysis will be performed to determine if there are differences in c-Jun expression response across the tumour lesions (control, treated and 'bystander' untreated) and will also be used to analyse tumour size change in all tumours (control, treated and "bystander" untreated) as secondary efficacy endpoints.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>38</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney
NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Institute NSW</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Technology Park
Suite 101
1 Central Avenue
Everleigh NSW 2015</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Sydney
NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Melanoma Institute of Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>40 Rocklands Rd
Wollstonecraft
NSW 2065</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test the safety of multiple injections of the Dz13 (combined with DOPE and DOTAP) drug in patients with melanoma skin cancer. 

Dz13 is a small piece of DNA which binds to an mRNA molecule c-Jun and cuts it into two pieces disrupting the  production of the c-Jun protein and can lead to a reduction in growth and spread of the tumour.

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or more, and have been diagnosed with dermal in-transit or satellite metastatic melanoma. You should have at least 3 measurable lesions at minimum distance of 5 cm from each other. 

Trial details:
There will be 4 different cohorts (or groups) in this study, who are enrolled consecutively. Participants in the first group will receive 2 injections of the drug Dz13 into their tumour over a period of 1 week. Participants in the second group will receive twice weekly injections of Dz13 for two weeks, and group three for three weeks. Based on the findings of the first three groups, the fourth group will then receive twice weekly Dz13 injections for two or three weeks. 

All participants will be regularly assessed to determine safety and tolerability of treatment. The treated and pre-seelcted untreated tumours will  be assessed by investigating the c-Jun levels within the tumour tissue and measuring tumour size. It is thought that Dz13 treatment may reduce the size of melanoma tumours in humans without significant toxicity. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District (SLHD) Ethics review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC001134</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catriona McNeil</name>
      <address>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Sydney Cancer Centre, 
Level 5, Gloucester House
Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9519 5894</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9519 1546</fax>
      <email>Catriona.McNeil@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Levon Khachigian</name>
      <address>Centre for Vascular Research
Lowy Building, Level 3
University of New South Wales
Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 2537</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 1797</fax>
      <email>l.khachigian@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Levon Khachigian</name>
      <address>Centre for Vascular Research
Lowy Building, Level 3
University of New South Wales
Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 2537</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 1797</fax>
      <email>l.khachigian@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marinella Messina</name>
      <address>Datapharm Australia Pty Ltd
56/56A Thompson Street
Drummoyne NSW 2047</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9719 2800</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9719 2811</fax>
      <email>marinella@datapharm.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>