<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369202">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001298505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Mulligan`s  lumbar SNAG on chronic non-specific low back pain

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Mulligan`s lumbar "SNAG" on proprioception, pain, range of Motion and functional level in chronic non-specific low back pain patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-6848</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic non-specific low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1- standard  physiotherapy (including infrared heating of the low back for 15 minutes, stretching exercises for back, hamstrings, iliopsoas muscles - 3 repetitions X 30 seconds hold X 30 seconds rest , strengthening exercises for abdominal muscles 1 set X 10 repetitions X 5 seconds hold.
- frequency of standard treatment sessions: 3 x 40 minutes per week for 4 weeks.
- (estimated total session duration is: 40 mins, 
2- "SNAG" Mulligan technique applied from setting position on the L4, and L5 spinous processes in a cephalic direction for 3 sets X 5 repetitions (for about 10 mins / session . 3 session /week for 4 weeks). SNAG technique will be applied by physiotherapist.
- SNAG will be applied at the end of the session for the study group only (the total study group  session time will be 50 mins. (the 10 minutes lack in control group session time will be filled with examination and history talking to achieve equality in time involved in patients treatment and caring)
Note: first program will be introduced to the control group, the first and second program will be both introduced to the experimental (study) group</interventions>
    <comparator>standard physiotherapy treatment:including infrared heating of the low back for 15 minutes, stretching exercises for back, hamstrings, iliopsoas muscles - 3 repetitions X 30 seconds hold X 30 seconds rest , strengthening exercises for abdominal muscles 1 set X 10 repetitions X 5 seconds hold.
total session time is 40 mins (plus 10 minutes for history taking and talking with the patient and preparation to assure spending the same time in both control and study groups patients) 
3 sessions per week for 4 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>lumbar spine proprioception in the form of measuring the repositioning accuracy</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and immediately after the end of one month of treatment application
measured by Biodex System 3 Pro Isokinetic Dynamometer (Biodex Medical Inc., Shirley, New York, USA). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pain level measured by non-numerical 100mm VAS</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and immediately after the end of the one month of treatment application</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>range of movement of the lumbar spine : flexion and extension
will be measured by inclinometer</outcome>
      <timepoint> immediately after the end of the last session of the one month treatment application (after the 12th session) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>functional level</outcome>
      <timepoint>Oswestry Disability Index
before and immediately after the end of one month of the treatment application</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1- patients diagnosed (by physician) with chronic non-specific low back pain.
2- signs and symptoms lasts more than 3 months.
3- patient must be able to assume at least more than 30 degrees of trunk flexion to be able to perform the task required for repositioning accuracy on the isokinetic machine.
4- patients with moderate Oswestry Disability Index results only will be included.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1-	Any low back pain due to a definite cause as; arthritis, degenerative joint diseases, disc lesion, inflammation and facet joint disease.
2-	Patients with a history of head trauma or other neurological manifestations.
3-	Obese patients with body mass index (BMI) above 25, and pregnant females.
4-	Any patients having the common contraindications for manual therapy as joint hyperlaxity, instability, acute infection.
5-Severe disabling LBP.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>the included subjects will be selected systematically from a list of the patients attending the faculty of physical therapy out-patient clinic, Cairo, Egypt.
after applying the initial assessment and signing the informed consent, each subject will be asked to pick a closed envelop containing a numbered card. this number will determines if the subject will be in the control or the study groups </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>the number of the sample will be based on the results of a pilot study of five patients before starting the actual study. this is because there are no previous study on the effects of the SNAG on  lumbar proprioception
power: 80%
significance level: .95%</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>42</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/01/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Cairo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hisham Mohamed AbdelRaheem Hussien</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Egypt - AlGiza - 6th Ahmed Elsayat street - Faculty of Physical Therapy- Cairo University.
postal code 12611 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hisham Mohamed AbdelRaheem Hussien (the main researcher)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> Egypt - AlGiza - 6th Ahmed Elsayat street - Faculty of Physical Therapy- Cairo University.
postal code 12611 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>this study has the aim of revealing the effect of Mulligan "SNAG" technique on low back priprioception, pain level, ROM, and functional level in patients suffering from chronic non-specific low back pain.

the primary purpose of this study is to investigate if this technique has an effect on the improvement of lumbar spine proprioception which was proved to be affected in study patient population and may be a cause of their condition. 

this study try to investigate a new possible mechanism (effect on proprioception) that can explain the efficacy of SNAG technique reported by previous studies.

this study is considered one of the few available study that tried to think outside the box regarding the effects of snag as one of the mulligan techniques as the majority of the previous studies adopted only the mechanical explanation mentioned by Mulligan himself.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical comitte of faculty of physical therapy cairo university</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Egypt ,  Al-Giza, 6th Ahmad Elzyat st.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>P.T.REC/012/00861</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hisham Mohamed Abdel_raheem Hussien</name>
      <address>Faculty of Physical Therapy, Cairo University, Basic Science Department
Egypt - Al-Giza  - Bein Elsarayat - 6th Ahmad Elzayat street.
post code : 12211</address>
      <phone>+2 01020936303</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drhisham3000@cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ebrahim Mostafa</name>
      <address>Faculty of Physical Therapy, Cairo University, basic Science Department,
Egypt - Al-Giza -Bein Elsarayat -  6th Ahmad Elzyat st.
post code : 12211</address>
      <phone>+2 01227022334</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>EbrahimMostafa@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Omaima Kattabei</name>
      <address>Faculty of Physical Therapy, Cairo University, basic Science Department,
Egypt - Al-Giza -Bein elsarayat- 6th Ahmad Elzyat st.
post code : 12211
</address>
      <phone>+20 1222194545</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>omaima_kattabei@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hisham Mohamed Abdel_raheem Hussien</name>
      <address>Egypt - Al-Giza - 6 of October City - 5th district - 1262 building - flat no 2</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>drhisham3000@cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>