<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362429">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000500853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Type 1 Keystone Flap versus Simple Primary Closure for wound closure - A Prospective Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Type 1 Keystone Flap versus Simple Primary Closure for wound closure in patients undergoing surgical excision of skin lesion - A Prospective Randomised Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wound closure of difficult surgical defects</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Type 1 Keystone flap as described by F Behan.  A type of Perforator island flap - that is a tissue island which is separated from surrounding skin and hence relies on deep perforating vessels for it's blood supply. It is essentially elliptical in shape with its long axis adjacent to the long axis of the defect. The flap is based on randomly located vascular perforators. The wound is closed directly, the mid-line area is the line of maximum tension and by V-Y advancement of each end of the flap, the islanded flap fills the defect. This allows the secondary defect on the opposite side to be closed, exploiting the mobility of the adjacent surrounding tissue. The technique can be found in the book 'The Keystone Perforator Island Flap Concept' by Felix Behan (Churchill Livingstone Australia,
ISBN: 9780729539715. Approximate duration is 30-60 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Simple primary wound closure. Eliptical excision of lesion with approximation of two edges and closure with simple sutures. Duration is approximately 20-40 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ASEPSIS wound score. This is a previously validated post-operative wound score which measures erythema, wound discharge, use of antibiotics, re-operation/drainage, and separation to provide an overall score on which wound healing can be judged and compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operatively at one, two, and four weeks. Again at six months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual analogue pain score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operatively at one, two, and four weeks. Again at six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cosmesis score - photographs judged by patients and non-medical volunteers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operatively at one, two, and four weeks. Again at six months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing surgical excision of skin lesion of which closure is suspected to be difficult. Intra-operative tension measurements will be taken and patients then stratified into tension-level groups for analysis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children, pregnant women, those unable to consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients attending clinic will be assessed for suitability. Consent will be obtained at this time. Randomisation will occur at the time of surgery once excision has occurred. The computer generated randomisation schedule is kept by a third person not involved with the study who will provide allocation arms upon request.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated block randomisation with random block sizes.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Charles Douglas</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Breast Centre
Lake Maquarie Specialist Medical Centre
6-8 Sydney Street
Gateshead
NSW 2290</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Surgical defeects that are predicted to be difficult to close may be considered for type one ketstone closure. The
theoretical advantage of this method is that the release of the longitudinal tension in the wound allows greater
stretch along the transverse axis. There is no reliable evidence in the literature to prove that this is the case in
human models, indeed in our small study the increase in transverse stretch enabled by longitudinal release was
less than 1mm. With this in mind the advantage of a keystone flap over other wound closure techniques is unclear.
We aim to compare the keystone flap with simple primary wound closure, with primary outcome measured as
wound healing, using the ASEPSIS wound score. The type one keystone flap was first described by Behan in
2003, for use in "suitable defects over most areas of the body up to 2cm in width". Patients will be recruited into the
study based upon this selction criteria and then randomised to keystone flap or primary closure. Short and longterm
follow up centered around the ASEPSIS wound score will be used to compare wound healing in the two groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HNEHREC 
Locked Bag 1
New Lambton
2305 NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/02/15/4.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Charles Douglas</name>
      <address>The Breast Centre
Lake Maquarie Specialist Medical Centre
6-8 Sydney Street
Gateshead
NSW 2290</address>
      <phone>+610249424600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Charles.Douglas@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Charles Douglas</name>
      <address>The Breast Centre
Lake Maquarie Specialist Medical Centre
6-8 Sydney Street
Gateshead
NSW 2290</address>
      <phone>+610249424600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Charles.Douglas@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>