<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366150">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000759695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility and efficacy of tobacco treatment interventions for smokers with a history of homelessness.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In smokers with a history of homelessness, does the provision of tobacco treatment interventions enhance access, treatment retention and cessation, if delivered within a residential community setting compared to an outpatient hospital setting.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>"Nil"</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking cessation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Once informed consent is obtained and smoking status is confirmed by CO measurement using a PICO+ Bedfont Smokerlyzer (CO &lt;5ppm indicates a non-smoker), participants will be enrolled on the 12 week treatment trial (with nicotine replacement therapy administration) with 3 monthly follow-up for 9 months. The trial stages are as follows:

1. Participants will attend an initial tobacco assessment at Common Ground with a tobacco treatment counsellor who will administer a number of research questionnaires.

2. Participants will return the following week for the first of 12 x ½ hour, weekly, counselling sessions at Common Ground, with the study counsellor, at which time nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) will be dispensed and motivational intervewing commenced. Participants will commence on 21mg x 24 hour transdermal nicotine patch and/or one of the oral forms of NRT of the participants choice. The starting dose and type of NRT will be determined by an assessment of the patient's nicotine dependency and CO level. The dose of NRT will be titrated up to a maximum of 42mg transdermal nicotine patch in response to symptoms of withdrawal and relapse. Flexible NRT dosing will be provided according to the patient profile and clinician advice, based on the participants severity of dependence and previous experiences in using NRT.

3. At each weekly treatment session participants self-reported smoking level will be assessed and verified by CO measurement, as will NRT use, nicotine withdrawal symptoms and mental health issues. NRT will be dispensed at each weekly treatment session for 12 weeks. Motivational counselling interventions will be used throughout the treatment protocol to enhance motivation and readiness to quit smoking.

4.After 12 weeks of treatment, the provision of free NRT will cease but participants will have the option of obtaining a script for nicotine patches for a further 12 weeks if needed. The script will be provided by their medical practitioner.

5. Face-to-face follow-up interviews will be conducted at 3 monthly intervals for a period of 9 months following termination or treatment completion. Follow-up will include biochemical verification of self-reported smoking status in expired CO measurement, administration of the research questionnaires and a review of participants' medical records. Written consent will be obtained for access to participants medical records.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Once informed consent is obtained and smoking status is confirmed by CO measurement, participants will be enrolled on the 12 week treatment trial, using motivational interviewing counselling interventions only, with 3 monthly follow-up for 9 months. The trial stages are as follows:

1. Participants will attend an initial tobacco assessment with a tobacco treatment specialist who will administer a number of research questionnaires.
2. Participants will return the following week and attend further 12 x 1/2 hour weekly motivational interviewing counselling sessions.
3. At each treatment session, participants' self-reported smoking level will be assessed and verified by CO measurement, as will nicotine withdrawal symptoms, tobacco cravings and mental health.
4. After 12 weeks, participants will cease treatment and follow-up will commence.  Face-to-face follow-up interviews will be conducted at 3 monthly intervals for a period of 9 months following termination or treatment completion. Follow-up will include biochemical verification of self-reported smoking status in expired CO measurement, administration of the research questionnaires and a review of participants' medical records. Written consent will be obtained for access to participants medical records.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported smoking cessation, verified by carbon monoxide (CO) measurement. A score CO&lt;5ppm indicates a non-smoker</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 3, 6 &amp; 9 months after treatment commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attendance as measured by clinic records</outcome>
      <timepoint>13 weeks after commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to relapse as measure by self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 and 9 months after treatment commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental and physical health as measured by self-report and medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 &amp; 9 months after treatment commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Intervention group: 
* Currently smoke cigarettes (verified by CO measurement: CO &gt;5ppm indicates a smoker)
* Assessed as nicotine dependent based on the Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence
*Interested in quitting smoking
* Current resident of Common Ground residential facility for homeless individuals
* Willing to use nicotine replacement therapy
Control group:

* Currently smoke cigarettes (verified by CO measurement: CO &gt;5ppm indicates a smoker)
* Assessed as nicotine dependent based on the Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence
* Interested in quitting smoking
*Current patient of Royal Prince Alfred Hospital's outpatient Opioid Treatment Program</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Women who are pregnant
* Young people under the age of 18 years
* People with cognitive impairment or an intellectual disability who are unable to give informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As a small scale community-based pilot study, 30 participants will be recruited at each site</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Missenden Road</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Drug Health Services
Level 6, King George V Building
Missenden Road
Camperdown  NSW  2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Local Health District</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Executive Unit
Level 11, King George V Building
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown  NSW  2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Common Ground
Mission Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>31 Pyrmont Bridge Road
Camperdown  NSW  2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will explore the feasibility and treatment effectiveness of nicotine replacement therapy and motivational interventions for smokers who have a history of homelessness.  It will evaluate the impact of treatment location on participation, retention and smoking cessation rates.
The trial design involves a treatment period of 12 weeks, with a further 9 months follow-up.  Trial patient will be broken into two groups: (1) Thirty (30) trial participants who smoke and live in a housing facility for homeless people will receive motivationally-based counselling interventions and will commence on 21mg x 24 hour transdermal nicotine patch plus one of the forms of oral nicotine replacement therapy of the participant's choice.  The dose of nicotine patch will be titrated up to a maximum of 42mg in response to withdrawal and relapse.  Treatment will be delivered within the residential facility.  (2) Thirty (30) trial participants attending a hospital-based opioid treatment program at Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, who smoke and have a history of homelessness, will receive motivational counselling interventions to help them to stop smoking.  Treatment will be delivered within this outpatient facility.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone) (EC00113)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Research Development Office
RPAH Medical Centre
Suite 210A, 100 Carillon Avenue
NEWTOWN NSW 2042 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Haber</name>
      <address>Medical Director
Drug Health Services
King George V Building
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown  NSW  2050</address>
      <phone>612 95155779</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.haber@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Louise Ross</name>
      <address>Tobacco Treatment Unit
Drug Health Services
Croydon Community Health Centre
24 Liverpool Road
Croydon  NSW  2132</address>
      <phone>612 9378 1306</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louise.ross@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Haber</name>
      <address>Medical Director
Drug Health Services
King George V Building
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown  NSW  2050</address>
      <phone>612 95155779</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.haber@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Louise Ross</name>
      <address>Tobacco Treatment Unit
Drug Health Services
Croydon Community Health Centre
24 Liverpool Road
Croydon  NSW  2132</address>
      <phone>612 9378 1306</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>louise.ross@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>