<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336506">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000142932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Integrated blood glucose monitoring with insulin pumps versus standard method - a randomised crossover trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact on blood glucose measurement and metabolic control of an integrated blood glucose monitoring system with insulin pumps versus the standard manual system in children/adolescents with type 1 diabetes mellitus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Insulin pumps have been used since the 70s and involve infusion of short-acting insulin from a reservoir in the pump into the subcutaneous tissue via a giving set at preselected programmed rates.This delivers a continuous basal rate of small amounts of rapid-acting insulin throughout the 24 hour period, with larger user-activated bolus doses at meal or snack times.  The basal rate can be programmed to change at various intervals throughout the day, which is particularly useful in regulating overnight blood glucose levels.  Bolus doses are given before meals based on self monitored blood glucose level, carbohydrate content of the meal and anticipated exercise after the meal.  Further correctional bolus doses can be given at any time if the random blood glucose is higher than the target range and there is a need for additional insulin.  All activity is recorded in the pump device which can then be downloaded to a computer to demonstrate a log-book view of various different parameters e.g. time and values of self-monitored blood glucose (SMBG), time and amount of carbohydrate consumed and amount of insulin delivered. This allows for critical analysis of glucose control and enables identification of areas for adjustment to improve control. 
A novel blood glucose meter has been developed which automatically inputs the recorded BGL measurement into a compatible insulin pump via bluetooth shortly after it is taken. It is recommended that pump users check their blood glucose several times a day to enable insulin titration to requirement. The number of glucose values inputted in the pump device has been shown to correlate with an improvement in diabetes control. The primary outcome is therefore the mean number of glucose readings over a six month period.
This trial is planned to comprise two phases, each lasting six months. Participants will be randomised to using either their own pump or the new integrated pump for the first six months. At the end of the first phase, participants will have a clinic appointment where they will be assigned to the second phase. Where they were randomised to using their own pump, they will be introduced to the integrated pump and vice versa, where they started on the integrated device, it will be taken back, stored and they will use their own pump as the standard pump for the second phase. After 12 months, the participant's duration in the trial is complete and they progress to pump upgrade, as is normal practice. They may upgrade to the integrated pump, or another pump of their choosing.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard meters involve titrating insulin requirement to glucose measurements manually inputted into the pump memory. As above, participants use their pump for continual insulin infusion, mimicking physiological insulin delivery as much as possible. During the course of the trial, participants would be randomise to using their own insulin pump as the control for either the first or second six-month phase.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Number of finger-prick blood glucose measurements entered into and recorded in participants' pump</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months and 12 months (after each phase of trial)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic control as measured by HbA1c</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>User device satisfaction as measured by the Insulin Delivery System Rating Questionnaire (IDSRQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information available to download from pump:
-total daily insulin dose
-number of boluses and percentage of dose given as a correction factor
-number of carbohydrate entries
-blood glucose variability
-% of insulin delivered as basal versus bolus
-% of blood glucose measurements within target range</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9 and 12 months
Also assessed at 6 weeks after starting a new phase for assessment of novelty or carryover effect</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of participants' contacts with the support team</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Users due a pump upgrade within next 13 to 24 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Have previously experienced significant skin reactions to pump giving sets, or other reactions which may mean that changing to a different pump may result in similar reaction and/or study withdrawal
2) Non-English speaking users</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Pumps have a four-year duration of warranty, hence youth are automatically entitled to a pump upgrade after 4 years use. All youth due an upgrade in the next 13-24 months will be contacted by post, with telephone follow-up, for inclusion in the trial. Those who choose to participate will then be randomised to continued use of their own standard pump and BGL monitoring (arm A), or to use of the automated integrated pump and BGL monitoring device (arm B) for the first six months (1st phase).  The study groups will cross-over after 6 months.  The figure of 13 months prior to end of warranty is used as a starting point for recruitment to ensure that participants crossing back to their own pump in the second phase do not run out of warranty. 
Individuals will be offered an opportunity to participate by post in the first instance, with telephone follow-up 3-4 weeks later, using contact details from the hospital system/medical records. Interested individuals can register their interest by returning the invitation by post, or by contacting the principal investigator directly by phone.
Participants will be randomly assigned to use of the integrated pump or to remain on their own pump, in the first phase. 
A statistician not directly involved in the analysis of the study results will prepare the randomisation schedule using randomised block randomisation to maintain balance between treatment arms and ensure allocation concealment. This shall be done using sealed envelopes which shall be selected sequentially as participants are recruited by the principal investigator. By its nature, this trial cannot be blinded except to the analysing statistician. Data will be recorded and described in accordance with the CONSORT guidelines on randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomised block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Children's Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flemington Road
Parkville
VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Children's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Flemington Rd
Parkville
VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Roche Australia Pty Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Diabetes Care
Building E, Level 1
24-32 Lexington Drive
Bella Vista
NSW 2153</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Good control of diabetes is essential to reduce the risk of developing diabetes-associated complications such as blindness, amputations or kidney failure. Intensive management of diabetes ensures better control and this is pursued in our population by multiple daily injections, or use of an insulin pump (~30% of population). Insulin pumps better mimic natural insulin delivery, being infused on a constant basis at varying adjustable rates throughout the day. Extra insulin is bolused for meals, or if blood glucose recordings are above target range. Good control on a pump is directly related to the number of blood glucose readings tested so insulin can be titrated to requirement. These glucose readings are optimally used when inputted into the pump, a step which must be done manually by the user. This is suboptimal in our population relative to international data, recently established as a mean of 3.1 readings per day versus 4.8 per day in other centres.
A novel blood glucose meter has been developed which automatically inputs the measurement into the pump via bluetooth shortly after it is taken. This device is TGA approved for use in the paediatric population and widely used in Europe. We wish to examine whether or not it significantly increases the number of blood glucose measurements in a patients pump and if this has an overall effect on diabetes control, as measured by HbA1c.
We aim to randomise 50 users to either using their own regular insulin pump, or the new integrated pump system for the first six months. After the first six months, participants will 'crossover' i.e. people using their own pump will then have the opportunity to use the new pump for six months and those who had the new pump would revert  back to using their own pump. We intend to examine the effects of the different pumps, if any, on the number of blood glucose tests recorded and on overall metabolic control.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HREC, Royal Children's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flemington Road
Parkville
VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Orla Neylon</name>
      <address>c/o Dept of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 5951</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>orla.neylon@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Orla Neylon</name>
      <address>c/o Dept of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 5951</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>orla.neylon@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Orla Neylon</name>
      <address>c/o Dept of Endocrinology &amp; Diabetes
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>