<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362903">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000871842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Maxigesic Metabolism Study: To describe the metabolism of paracetamol when combined with ibuprofen in healthy adult volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Single-centre, single-dose, open-label, randomised, cross-over study of the effect of ibuprofen on the oxidative metabolism of paracetamol when administered as a fixed dose combination (Maxigesic) in healthy volunteers under fasting conditions.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pharmacokinetics of Maxigesic in Healthy Volunteers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention:
Maxigesic as a single oral dose of two tablets (total dose paracetamol 1000mg and ibuprofen 300mg).

Cross-over study with a 7 day washout period between doses.

Participants will be fasted for at least 10 hours overnight before the administration of the study drug. Standardised meals will be provided from 4 hours after study drug administration. Drinking water will be restricted for 1 hour before and after drug administration (not including the standardised 240mL of water given with the study drug.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator: Panadol as a single oral dose of two tablets (total dose paracetamol 1000mg).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe the amount of paracetamol and its metabolites excreted in the urine after a single dose of paracetamol alone or in combination with ibuprofen (Maxigesic).

This will be assessed by measuring the total amount of paracetamol and its metabolites excreted in the urine over 24 hours and the 24 hour extretion rate of paracetamol and its metabolites.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Urine will be collected over the study period (24 hours after dosing).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine the safety and tolerability of Maxigesic. 

Safety will be evaluated during each study period, and for 7 days following study drug administration. Acute safety evaluations will be performed during each study period by recording spontaneously reported AE's and by clinical assessments (incl. heamatology &amp; biochemistry). 

Known NSAID adverse effects (i.e. GI ulceration, indigestion/stomach pain, GI bleeding, bronchospasm, water retention, renal failure, skin reactions and thromboembolic events) and known paracetamol adverse effects (i.e. clinical evidence of hepatotoxicity) will be compared between groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse event reporting will be by spontaneous reproting up to 7 days after dosing, and by a follow up phone call 7 days after the last dose of the study medication.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Provide written informed consent
2) Have Body Mass Index between 18.5 and 30.0 kg/m2
3) Healthy volunteers as determined by medical history, physical examination, ECG, vital signs and laboratory tests</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Women who are pregnant or nursing
2) Women who are unwilling to take adequate contraceptive precaustions or who are unwilling to undergo urine pregnancy testing
3) History of alcohol or drug abuse or dependency
4) Have a history of allergy or hypersensitivity to ibuprofen, aspirin, any other NSAID or paracetamol
5) Have haemopoetic, renal or hepatic disease, immunosupression. Have a history of gastric ulceration, indigestion, stomach pain, GI bleeding or bleeding disorders. Are currently suffering from dehydration from diarrhoea and/or vomiting. Have a history of severe asthma. Have a history of severe hypertension, ventricular tachycardia or other cardiac disease. Have insulin dependent diabetes mellitus.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will occur once participant eligability is confirmed. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be generated by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Jordan</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AFT Pharmacetuicals Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to assess if ibuprofen changes the metabolic profile of paracetamol when given as a fixed dose combination.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Jordan Food and Drug Administration</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>P O Box 811951
Amman</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Jordan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Potts</name>
      <address>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</address>
      <phone>+64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Potts</name>
      <address>Level 1,
Nielsen Building,
129 Hurstmere Road,
Takapuna 
Auckland 0622</address>
      <phone>+64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>