<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371697">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001503415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The feasibility and effectiveness of trauma-focussed imaginal exposure for voice hearing following adverse life experiences: A pilot randomised controlled trial (The RECALL study).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The feasibility and effectiveness of trauma-focussed imaginal exposure for voice hearing following adverse life experiences: A pilot randomised controlled trial (The RECALL study).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-9792</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Auditory hallucinations</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Imaginal Exposure plus treatment as usual: The active intervention will be an 'imaginal exposure' intervention consisting of 6 weekly sessions of 90-minute duration. Imaginal exposure is a common element of several effective trauma-focussed treatments and involves repeated exposure to the trauma narrative through verbal recounting. The treatment will be delivered face to face in a mental health clinic by a doctoral level, registered Clinical Psychologist. Overall supervision will be provided by a senior Clinical Psychologist with extensive experience in psychological interventions for voice hearers. The intervention is manualised. The initial session will involve education regarding trauma and memory processing, a review and elaboration of the clients trauma-voice link formulation established in the baseline assessment, and an explanation of the rationale for imaginal exposure. Sessions 2  6 will follow the protocol for imaginal exposures outlined in the Prolonged Exposure treatment manual (Foa, Hembree, &amp; Rothbaum, 2007). Participants will also be required to listen to audio recordings of their in-session imaginal exposures for homework in sessions 2-5. This will be approximately 30-40 minutes of homework each day during this period. Ten percent of sessions will be  randomly selected for adherence checks by a senior clinician using an adherence checklist. Participants in this group will also continue to receive standard psychiatric interventions such as case management and medication. </interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual: Participants in the treatment as usual condition will not receive any psychological treatment for the duration of the trial, but will be offered the study treatment or a current best practice treatment for their voice hearing (depending on participant preference) at their final follow-up assessment. These participants will continue to receive standard psychiatric interventions such as case management and medication. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability and feasibility of the intervention - measured using a satisfaction questionnaire and uptake and retention rates. These measures will be used as a composite outcome. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Uptake and retention data collected at initial screening and throughout treatment. Satisfaction questionnaire completed at end of treatment (7 weeks following baseline) for the treatment group only.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Voice hearing severity measured using the Psychotic Symptom Rating Scales  Auditory Hallucinations Scale total score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Voice hearing intensity measured ten times per day using ecological momentary assessment over a 6 day timeframe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During week 1 and week 8 following baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client experience of the intervention, measured using an adapted questionnaire version of Elliotts change process interview. </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatment (7 weeks following baseline) - treatment group only.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PTSD symptom severity, measured using the CAPS -5.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Posttraumatic intrusion frequency, measured 10 times per day using ecological momentary assessment  over a 6 day timeframe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During week 1 and week 8 following baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Delusion severity, measured using the Psychotic Symptom Rating Scales  Delusions Scale total score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression severity, measured using the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale  21.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disorganisation of the trauma memory, measured using the Trauma Memory Questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Posttraumatic cognitions, measured by the Posttraumatic Cognitions Inventory. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensory detail in the trauma memory, measured using transcribed trauma narratives from sessions 2 and 6 and analysed using Linguistic Inquiry and Word Count software. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment session 2 and session 6, treatment group only. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 4: Voice hearing distress measured 10 times per day using ecological momentary assessment over a 6 day timeframe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During week 1 and week 8 following baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 5: Voice hearing frequency measured 10 times per day using ecological momentary assessment over a 6 day timeframe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During week 1 and week 8 following baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Posttraumatic intrusion distress, measured 10 times per day using ecological momentary assessment  over a 6 day timeframe</outcome>
      <timepoint>During week 1 and week 8 following baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety severity, measured using the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale  21.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intrusiveness of the trauma memory, measured using the Trauma Memory Questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 8 weeks following baseline, 12 weeks following baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive processing  in the trauma memory, measured using transcribed trauma narratives from sessions 2 and 6 and analysed using Linguistic Inquiry and Word Count software. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment session 2 and session 6, treatment group only. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(a) aged 18-75
(b) persistent voice hearing that has been present for &gt; 6 months and is currently occurring at least twice a week 
(c) a history of criterion A traumatic events, childhood adversity or significant interpersonal victimisation (assessed by standardised trauma checklists) 
(d) has made some conceptual links between their past adverse experiences and their experience of voice hearing and, for this reason, is motivated to undertake a trauma-focussed intervention 
e) has a sufficient level of English language to participate in study requirements
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a) recent (past month) or planned change in psychiatric medication 
b) substance induced voices OR current substance dependence issues that would interfere with participation in the trial 
c) Intellectual disability (Wechsler Test of Adult Reading estimated IQ &lt; 70) 
(d) Acute risk to self or others, defined by the presence of suicidal or homicidal thoughts with current intent. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be conducted using minimisation. A researcher who is external to the trial will conduct the minimisation process using the Qminim online programme (Saghaei &amp; Saghaei, 2011). </concealment>
    <sequence>Minimisation, an adaptive random allocation method, will be used. The minimisation algorithm will be applied using the Qminim online programme. Baseline PSYRATS-AHS and CAPS-5 scores will be used as the factors for minimisation.   </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Since this is a pilot study, the primary aim is to establish effect size estimates and confidence intervals for effectiveness outcomes as well as establishing feasibility. As such, as sample size of 30 was considered sufficient to meet these aims. 

Intention to treat (ITT) analyses using mixed modelling approaches will be used to assess effectiveness outcomes. Estimated between-group effect sizes for each outcome will be computed according to Hedges g and confidence intervals for these effects established. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/08/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>3</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/11/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swinburne University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>John Street, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Swinburne University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>John Street, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4, 607 St Kilda Road, Melbourne VIC 3004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is increasing evidence of a relationship between trauma and psychosis.  Recent evidence also suggests that there are potential shared mechanisms involved in the genesis of posttraumatic intrusions and posttraumatic voice hearing. The RECALL study is a pilot randomized trial aiming to provide initial evidence regarding the acceptability, feasibility and effectiveness of applying established trauma-focussed treatments to voice hearing. In addition, in the spirit of the interventionist-causal approach, the study aims to provide a preliminary assessment of the effects of the intervention on the proposed mechanisms of change. The findings of the pilot study will inform the development of a fully powered RCT that will robustly assess treatment effects and the role of the hypothesised mediators and moderators of treatment response.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.recallstudy.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC, 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>436/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Neil Thomas</name>
      <address>Brain and Psychological Sciences Research Centre
Swinburne University of Technology
PO BOX 218
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+613 9214 8742</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>neilthomas@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Brand</name>
      <address>Brain and Psychological Sciences Research Centre
Swinburne University of Technology
PO BOX 218
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 6564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rbrand@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Brand</name>
      <address>Brain and Psychological Sciences Research Centre
Swinburne University of Technology
PO BOX 218
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 6564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rbrand@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel Brand</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>rbrand@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>