<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336304">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/12/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000061932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of Oxytocin on Social Behavior and Repetitive Behavior in Children with Autism.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Course of Oxytocin To Improve Social Interaction and Repetitive Behaviors In Children With Autism Spectrum Disorders.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1118-3796</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism Spectrum Disorders.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oxytocin nasal spray.
Duration: 5 week treatment. First week, the dose will start at 3 International Units (IU) and increase by 3IU every 2 days. From the 7th day onwards, participants will receive 12IU for the remaining 4 weeks. The nasal spray will be delivered everyday, morning and night, one spray per nostril
This is a crossover study, so after the first course of treatment, participants will have a 4 week washout period and then commence the alternative treatment. The alternative treatment will follow the same dose escalation procedure as the first course of treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo matched nasal spray taken containing all ingredients except the active at the same frequency as the oxytocin nasal spray (twice per day for 5 weeks).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Positive social interaction as indexed by observational tasks, parent and teacher questionnaires and  a coding protocol to tally the frequency of social behaviors during observational assessments and home therapy sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four; pre and post for spray 1 and pre and post for spray 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of repetitive behavior will be measured using the caregiver/guardian and teacher repetitive behavior scale- revised. in addition, a coding protocol will be used to tally the frequency of specific repetitive behaviors during observational assessments and home therapy sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four; pre and post for spray 1 and pre and post for spray 2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eye gaze to dynamic human faces portrayed on a computer screen. Eye tracking equipment will record the duration and frequency of fixations to facial features during a video scene.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four; pre and post for spray 1 and pre and post for spray 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General improvement as indicated by the clinical Global Impressions score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four; pre and post for spray 1 and pre and post for spray 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of executive functioning measured with four behavioral tasks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four; pre and post for spray 1 and pre and post for spray 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preferential attention to social stimuli will be assessed using a visual exploration task and eye tracking equipment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four; pre and post for spray 1 and pre and post for spray 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioral and emotional problems as assessed by the Developmental Behavior Checklist (DBC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four; pre and post for spray 1 and pre and post for spray 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of social interactions as indexed by the quality of social behavior scale (therapist and teacher reports)</outcome>
      <timepoint>reports to be filled out each week for 4 weeks prior to each treatment, then each week the participant is on the full dose of nasal spray (4 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet DSM-IV-TR criteria for ASD</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>8</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not sensitive to preservatives (in particular E 216, E 218, and chlorobutanol hemihydrate)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>enrolling: A flyer advertising the study will be emailed to parents of children who attend the Lizards Children’s centre. Potential participants will be referred to the Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute, The University of Sydney for a medical interview to determine eligibility for the active medication and a diagnostic assessment to confirm autism diagnosis. Caregivers of the participants will provide written informed consent before the assessment begins.

Participants will be randomly allocated either oxytocin or placebo during phase 1 treatment. Then the alternative treatment during phase 2. Each participant is assigned a prepacked numbered container containing either oxytocin or placebo according to the randomization schedule developed by the compounding chemist
randomized allocation:</concealment>
    <sequence>Random number generation using computer software. Each number is labeled with 'a' or 'b' where a or b could represent either oxytocin or placebo. This code has been developed by an independent pharmacist.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/11/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
Sydney
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Oxytocin is a natural hormone which plays a critical role in social behavior such as bonding, cooperativeness, trust, emotion recognition and face processing. Autism is a developmental disorder characterized by profound impairments in social behavior, communication and presence of repetitive behaviors. This study aims to assess the efficacy of oxytocin treatment in ameliorating social impairments in young children with autism. In particular, we aim to assess whether oxytocin treatment can improve the capacity for social interaction, face processing and reduce the occurrence of repetitive behaviors.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6
Jane Foss Russell Building G02
The University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12261</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Adam Guastella</name>
      <address>94 Mallett St
Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute, 
University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0539</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 0881</fax>
      <email>adam.guastella@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Chathuri (CJ) Yatawara</name>
      <address>100 Mallett st,
Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute, 
University of Sydney,
Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 4106</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chathuri.yatawara@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chathuri Yatawara</name>
      <address>100 Mallett st,
Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute,
University of Sydney,
Camperdown, NSW, 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 4106</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chathuri.yatawara@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Adam Guastella</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute, University of Sydney
94 mallett street Camperdown, NSW,  2050</address>
      <phone>+61 293510539</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Adam.Guastella@Sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>