<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372657">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000553370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Ages and Stages Questionnaire - Talking about raising Aboriginal Kids (ASQ-TRAK) developmental screening tool for Australian Aboriginal children. Determining the reliability and face validity of the ASQ-TRAK and exploring the characteristics of developmental delay in Aboriginal children in urban, regional and remote areas of South Australia.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The ASQ-TRAK developmental screening tool for Australian Aboriginal children. Determining the reliability and face validity of the ASQ-TRAK and exploring the characteristics of developmental delay in Aboriginal children in urban, regional and remote areas of South Australia.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>1111-1194-9000</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Developmental delay</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Learning disabilities</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will be using a new developmental screening tool (the ASQ-TRAK) to observe the characteristics of normal childhood development and any deviation from normal childhood development in a cohort of Australian Aboriginal children. Each child is likely to be observed on one occasion only however as the trial will be conducted over a 12 month period it is possible that a child may be observed on 2 or 3 occasions over this time. The ASQ-TRAK is a developmental screening tool that was developed in consultation with Aboriginal communities in the Northern Territory in Australia. It is based on the Ages and Stages Questionnaire 3 (ASQ-3) which is a widely used developmental screening tool that has been validated in the United States and demonstrated feasibility and acceptability across a number of different cultures and language groups. 

Whilst the ASQ-3 has been validated in the United States it has not been validated for use in Australian Aboriginal people. To date, no developmental screening tool exists that has been validated for use for Aboriginal people. The ASQ-TRAK tool was modified from the existing ASQ-3 as part of a pHD project completed by Dr Anita D'Aprano. The project involved taking the ASQ-3 and having meetings and interviews with community representatives (of 2 remote Indigenous communities in the Northern Territory), early childhood experts and linguists as to how the tool could be changed to be more culturally appropriate and relevant for Aboriginal people. Questions were changed to be more culturally relevant and the English used was altered to be simpler and easier to understand. The ASQ-TRAK was then translated into the languages of the 2 communities where the initial study was undertaken and each question was illustrated to help with understanding the question.

The observation for study participants consists of a number of questions, tasks and games that the child undertakes. The tool is designed so that the question, task or game is administered by the parent or caregiver with support from the worker. The tool consists of five domains; communication, fine motor, gross motor, problem solving and personal-social. These domains are assessed in a variety of ways and may include observing how the child talks or communicates, asking the child to stack blocks or draw a picture, observing how a child moves or asking them to jump or catch a ball, observing how a small child may work to retrieve an object out of reach or an older child about concepts such as "big" and "small" and asking a parent about the ways in which a child plays or interacts with people. After each observation the parent or guardian will be asked to complete a questionnaire in order to evaluate what the parents think about the tools usefulness, acceptability and whether it is felt to be culturally appropriate and respectful.

A child may be observed more than once for a number of reasons. Aboriginal children who present to Child and Family Health Services (CaFHS) at any of 4 locations will be approached regarding the study. For the children presenting to the urban and regional sites (but not the remote site) each family will be asked firstly if they consent to take part and then if they would be willing to have the screen re-administered within a 2 week period. The repeat screen could be administered by the same or a different staff member as determined by staff availability. This information will be used to determine intra and inter-observer reliability for the tool. Also, as the trial will run over a 12 month period the same child may be observed at different points of time (and therefore with a different age group questionnaire). I. For example it is routine for CaFHS to encourage parents to present for developmental screening at 6 months of age and at 18 months of age. Therefore a child who, by chance, is 6 months of age at the commencement of the study would be quite likely to be observed on 2 occasions. It is possible that a child for whom there are greater developmental concerns would be offered a developmental screen more frequently and therefore be observed on 3 or more occasions. Any child or family who refuses consent for the trial will be offered developmental screening using the ASQ-3 as is consistent with existing guidelines. 

The assessments will be performed by a small group of workers who have been trained in how to use the tool, via a 2 day workshop and a practical, workplace based assessment. These workers will either be nurses or Aboriginal health workers with CaFHS. Each observation is likely to take around 45 mins with an extra 10 minutes required in order to complete the parent feedback questionnaire. The assessments are observational in nature however the results of the assessments will be used to guide whether further evaluation of development is required, this would be via referral to a paediatrician or allied health practitioners such as speech pathologists or occupational therapists as is appropriate.

Earlier studies of the ASQ-TRAK showed high face validity and the tool was considered to be culturally acceptable and relevant to Aboriginal parents, Aboriginal Health Workers and early childhood development experts in the Northern Territory.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the reliability of the ASQ-TRAK including internal consistency.

Internal consistency of ASQ-TRAK items will be analysed using Cronbachs alpha calculations. A single ASQ-TRAK assessment is all that is required to perform these calculations of correlations between items within a single scale and with the overall scale score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after completing data collection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the reliability of the ASQ-TRAK including test-retest reliability.

Test-retest reliability will be assessed by administering the ASQ-TRAK twice with a child, by the same examiner, within a 1-2 week period. Results will be analysed using intraclass correlation coefficients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the reliability of the ASQ-TRAK including interobserver reliability.

Inter-rater reliability will be assessed by administering the ASQ-TRAK twice with a child, by two different examiners, within a 1-2 week period. Results will be analysed using intraclass correlation coefficients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the prevalence of developmental difficulties in the study cohort.

This will be assessed using the ASQ-TRAK results both overall and each subscale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the face validity of the ASQ-TRAK, from the perspectives of the child health practitioners in urban South Australia using the staff questionnaire.

The staff questionnaire was designed for the purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the face validity of the ASQ-TRAK, from the perspectives of caregivers in urban South Australia using the carer questionnaire.

The staff questionnaire was designed for the purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the face validity of the ASQ-TRAK, from the perspectives of the child health practitioners in regional South Australia using the staff questionnaire.

The staff questionnaire was designed for the purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the face validity of the ASQ-TRAK, from the perspectives of child health practitioners in remote areas of South Australia using the staff questionnaire.

The staff questionnaire was designed for the purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the face validity of the ASQ-TRAK, from the perspectives of caregivers in regional South Australia using the carer questionnaire.

The staff questionnaire was designed for the purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish the face validity of the ASQ-TRAK, from the perspectives of caregivers in remote areas of South Australia using the carer questionnaire.

The staff questionnaire was designed for the purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the completion of data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aboriginal children aged 2, 6, 12, 18, 24, 36 or 48 months who attend any of the four Child and Family Health Service (CaFHS) sites (Port Adelaide, Morphett Vale, Port Augusta and Anangu Pitjantjatjara Yankunytjatjara (APY) Lands</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>4</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The ASQ-TRAK has been developed for children aged 2, 6, 12, 18, 24, 36 and 48 months with a specified age criteria to use each of these questionnaires (eg. 2 month questionnaire is valid from 1 month to 2 months and 30 days). If children should fall out of the specified age range they will be excluded from the trial . These children will be offered an ASQ-III to assess their development as is current procedure.
Children will also be excluded from the study if they do not reside within the specified areas of the trial and if they are not Aboriginal.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics will be used to analysis demographic data and participant characteristics. 
We will also employ qualitative analysis of the parent and staff questionnaire information.
Further, analysis of the primary outcome (identification of proven developmental delay) will occur at the individual infant level and will use multivariate logistic regression. Similar techniques will be used for comparison of acceptability and reliability.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>13/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5162 - Morphett Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>5015 - Port Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5700 - Port Augusta</postcode>
    <postcode>0872 - Amata</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>SA Health - government department of health. Women's and Children's Health Network; Child and Family Health Service (CaFHS)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Child and Family Health Service
295 South Tce 
Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>SA health - government department of health. Women's and Children's Health Service; Child and Family Health Service (CaFHS)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Child and Family Health Service
295 South Tce 
Adelaide SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project aims to establish the reliability and face validity characteristics of the ASQ-TRAK, a culturally adapted version of a developmental screening tool, for use with Australian Aboriginal children. The project also aims to explore the characteristics of developmental difficulty or delay in South Australian Aboriginal children. The project will contribute to an existing study about the validation of the ASQ-TRAK. 

Aboriginal children and their caregivers who attend the Child and Family Health Services (CaFHS) in four South Australian locations will be invited to participate in the project. THe proposed sites are Port Adelaide (urban), Morphett Vale (urban), Port Augusta (regional), and Anangu Pitjantjatjara Yankunytjatjara - the APY lands (remote), Child health staff will be trained to use the ASQ-TRAK.

The project will employ a cross-sectional design and the methods will be as follows:
1. Reliability: for test-retest reliability, the same practitioner will re-administer the ASQ-TRAK within a two week period. For inter-observer reliability, a different practitioner will re-administer the ASQ-TRAK within a two week period. To calculate internal consistency, the ASQ-TRAK only needs to be administered once. In the urban and regional sites, the ASQ-TRAK will be conducted twice and this data will establish test-retest and inter-observer reliability. In the remote site, the ASQ-TRAK will be conducted once. For children who have the ASQ-TRAK, this data will contribute to establishing internal consistency.
2. Face validity: practitioners and caregivers will be surveyed about their experiences with the ASQ-TRAK.
3. Prevalence: rates of developmental difficulties or delay will be estimated for the four locations, using hte cut-off rates determined by the ASQ-3.

The project will provide information about the accuracy and acceptability of the culturally adapted ASQ-3. This will help to fill a gap in providing developmental services to Australian Aboriginal children.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Aboriginal Health Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>220 Franklin St Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>04-16-702</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Health Network Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Secretariat
Level 2, Samuel Way Building
72 King William Road
North Adelaide SA 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/WCHN/185</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne Central Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research Ethics and Integrity
L3, 780 Elizabeth St
The University of Melbourne
Melbourne
VICTORIA 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372657-Protocol.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372657-Participantinformation.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372657-WCHNHRECapproval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372657-AHREC Approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372657-ASQ-TRAK WCHN Parent Questionnaire.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372657-ASQ-TRAK WCHN CaFHS staff Questionnaire.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Deepa Jeyaseelan</name>
      <address>Child Development Unit
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Rd
North Adelaide
SOUTH AUSTRALIA
5006</address>
      <phone>+61 881617000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deepa.jeyaseelan@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Deepa Jeyaseelan</name>
      <address>Child Development Unit
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Rd
North Adelaide
SOUTH AUSTRALIA
5006</address>
      <phone>+61 881617000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deepa.jeyaseelan@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Deepa Jeyaseelan</name>
      <address>Child Development Unit
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Rd
North Adelaide
SOUTH AUSTRALIA
5006</address>
      <phone>+61 881617000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deepa.jeyaseelan@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kimberly Johansen</name>
      <address>Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Rd
North Adelaide
SOUTH AUSTRALIA
5006</address>
      <phone>+61 881617000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimberly.johansen@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>