<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335601">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000695707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Chemoradiation Treatment for Head and Neck Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>TROG 07.04 A Phase I/II Study of Cetuximab, Carboplatin and Radiotherapy for patients with locally advanced head and neck squamous cell carcinoma </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov ID NCT00704639</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Cetuximab. Patients will receive weekly intravenous cetuximab (initial dose 400mg/m2 in the week prior to commencing radiotherapy, then weekly 250mg/m2)for the duration of the radiotherapy
2. Carboplatin. Weekly intravenous carboplatin (Area Under the Curve (AUC) 2) for the duration of the radiotherapy
3. Radiotherapy. The radiotherapy schedule will be the "infield boost" (IFB) regimen, that is 66 Gy in 35 fractions over 5 weeks: daily for 3 weeks, then twice daily for 2 weeks (or 70 Gy in 35 fractions over 7 weeks - 5fractions/ week - for a specific subgroup of patients where IFB is not recommended).</interventions>
    <comparator>n/a</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and Feasibility. Measured as satisfactory completion of the protocol treatment regimen</outcome>
      <timepoint>An initial 6 patients will be treated. Once all these patients have a 2 week post radiotherapy review there will be analysis. If &lt;= 1 patient has a Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT) than the treatment is deemed safe.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Failure Free Survival. Defined as the time from registration to the first failure of any type (local, regional or distant) or death from any cause. Failure will be confirmed via Fine Needle Aspiration (FNA) cytology or biopsy as well as Computed Tomogrphy (CT) image of area of interest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be followed until the last patient enrolled has a minimum follow-up of 2 years post treatment. Patients will be assessed at baseline, then at 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 weeks then 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 28, 32, 36, 42, and 48 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Local and/or regional failure. Failure will be confirmed via Fine Needle Aspiration (FNA) cytology or biopsy as well as Computed Tomogrphy (CT) image of area of interest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be followed until the last patient enrolled has a minimum follow-up of 2 years post treatment. Patients will be assessed at baseline, then at 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 weeks then 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 28, 32, 36, 42, and 48 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival Time. Defined from point of registration to death from any cause.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be followed until the last patient enrolled has a minimum follow-up of 2 years post treatment. Patients will be assessed at baseline, then at 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 weeks then 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 28, 32, 36, 42, and 48 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Site of first Failure. Failure will be confirmed via Fine Needle Aspiration (FNA) cytology or biopsy as well as Computed Tomogrphy (CT) image of area of interest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be followed until the last patient enrolled has a minimum follow-up of 2 years post treatment. Patients will be assessed at baseline, then at 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 weeks then 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 28, 32, 36, 42, and 48 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute and Late Treatment toxicities. Using National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) version 3.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be followed until the last patient enrolled has a minimum follow-up of 2 years post treatment. Patients will be assessed at baseline, weekly during treatment, then at 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 weeks then 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 28, 32, 36, 42, and 48 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Previously untreated Squamous Cell Carcinoma (SCC) of the oropharynx, larynx or hypopharynx. 
2. Stage III or IV, excluding T1N1, and metastatic disease (to be confirmed by a chest CT, and abdominal CT or ultrasound scan if patients with abnormal liver function tests or a bone scan or Flurodeoxyglucose Positron Emission Tomography (FDG-PET) if patients with bone pain). 
3. Histologically or cytologically confirmed Head and Neck SCC 
4. Disease must be considered potentially curable by chemoradiation 
5. Patients medically unfit for cisplatin chemotherapy due to one or more of the following reasons:
- Clinically significant sensori-neural hearing impairment (audiometric abnormalities without corresponding clinical deafness will not be regarded as a contraindication to cisplatin) 
- Severe tinnitus 
- Renal impairment (Glomerular Filtration Rate (GFR) &lt; 60ml/min) 
- Peripheral neuropathy &gt; grade 2 
- Inability to tolerate intravenous hydration eg due to cardiac disease 
- Co-morbidities (based on clinical judgement by the investigator) associated with Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status (ECOG PS) 2 that in the view of the investigator would preclude the safe administration of cisplatin 
6. Performance status ECOG 0, 1 or 2. 
7. Adequate haematological, renal and hepatic functions as defined by:
- Absolute neutrophil count (Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC), segmented cells (segs) + bands)&gt;= 1.5 x 109/L 
- Platelet count &gt;= 100 x 109/L 
- Total bilirubin &lt;= 1.5 x upper normal limit 
- Alanine aminotransferase &lt;= 2.5 x upper normal limit 
- Calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 40ml/min (Cockcroft-Gault formula). 
- If calculated creatinine clearance &lt; 50 ml/min, glomerular filtration rate to be measured with Diethylene triamine pentaacetic acid (DTPA) or Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) scan. If &lt; 40 ml/min not eligible. 
8. Age &gt;18 years 
9. Signed written consent 
10. Suitable for follow-up for 4 years in the view of the investigator</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Distant metastases, i.e., any metastatic disease below the clavicles. Patients with lung nodules &gt;10mm will be excluded unless non-malignancy aetiology is established. Patients with lesions 5-10mm can be included if a flurodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) scan is negative and the investigator considers on clinical grounds that metastasis is unlikely. Patients with lesions &lt; 5mm can be included if the investigator considers on clinical grounds that metastases are unlikely. Patients with multiple lung nodules should not be included unless there is a strong case that these do not represent metastases, e.g., stable on imaging for over 12 months, non-malignant aetiology apparent. The level of clinical suspicion may be influenced by clinical stage, e.g., N3 disease, low neck nodes. In general if there is any doubt patients should be excluded. 
2. Previous radical radiotherapy (RT) to the head &amp; neck region, excluding superficial RT for a non-melanomatous skin cancer. 
3. Patients with prior cancers, except: those diagnosed &gt; 5 years ago with no evidence of disease recurrence and clinical expectation of recurrence of less than 5%; or successfully treated non-melanoma skin cancer; or carcinoma in situ of the cervix. 
4. Significant intercurrent illness that will interfere with the chemotherapy or radiation therapy such as Humman Immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, cardiac failure, pulmonary compromise, active infection 
5. Any history of myocardial infarction, ventricular arrhythmias, or unstable angina within the last 6 months 
6. Pregnant or lactating women. 
7. Weight loss greater than 20 % of usual body weight in the 3 months preceding trial entry 
8. High risk for poor compliance with therapy or follow up as assessed by the investigator 
9. Prior radiation to greater than 30% of the bone marrow 
10. Prior systemic chemotherapy for cancer 
11. Refusal by male or female patients, to use appropriate contraception during the study and for 3 months afterwards 
12. Any condition or circumstance which might prevent the patient being able to give valid informed consent, or from completing participation in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>It is recommended that all potential/eligible patients be notified to the local data manager and to the Trial Coordinating Centre. Registration of eligible patients will be delayed until 2 weeks prior to commencement of radiotherapy (and one week prior to commencement of cetuximab). This two stage procedure will reduce the risk of patients being registered but never commencing treatment (but nevertheless needing to be included in analysis). To register a patient, check the eligibility criteria have been satisfied and complete the registration form.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/04/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/04/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/11/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Central Operations Office
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Locked Bag 7 Hunter Region Mail Centre
NSW 2310</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Merck Onc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Merck KGaA 
Frankfurter Str. 250 
64293 Darmstadt</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Germany</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a Phase II study of cetuximab, carboplatin and radiotherapy (RT) in patients with Locally Advanced Head and Neck Carcinomas (LAHNC) who are unfit for cisplatin.
The aim of this study is to show the feasibility and safety profile of the combination of cetuximab, carboplatin and RT in treatment of patients with LAHNC.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.trog.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne 
VIC 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/01/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07/48</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Christopher Griffiths</name>
      <address>Centre for Biostatistics and Clinical Trials (BaCT)
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 965658289</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.griffths@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Christopher Griffiths</name>
      <address>Centre for Biostatistics and Clinical Trials (BaCT)
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96565829</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christopher.griffiths@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>TROG Administrator</name>
      <address>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group
Central Operations Office
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Locked Bag 7 Hunter Region Mail Centre 
NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4014 3910  </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4014 3902</fax>
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>June Corry</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Center
1 St Andrews Place
East Melbourne, Victoria, 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>June.Corry@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>