<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373187">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000992303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A secondary analysis examining the changes in dietary glycaemic index and glycaemic load in Australian children between 1995 - 2012</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A secondary analysis examining the changes in dietary glycaemic index and glycaemic load in Australian children between 1995 - 2012</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>dietary glycaemic index</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>dietary glycaemic load</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dietary glycaemic index and dietary glycaemic load, as well as the major sources of dietary glycaemic load in 3 Australian population-based nutrition surveys, namely 1995 Australian National Nutrition Survey (1995NS), 2007 Australian National Children's Nutrition and Physical Activity Survey (2007NS) and 2011-12 National Nutrition and Physical Activity Survey (2012NS), were described.

The 1995NS was conducted by the Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) and the Department of Health together with the 1995 National Health Survey. Data were collected between February 1995 and March 1996. Information about food and beverage intake, usual frequency of intake, eating habit, attitudes and physical measurements of Australians population aged 2 year-old or above was collected (n = 13,858) with a 61.4% response rate. Participants were selected randomly from dwellings in different State and Territories. Dietary intake was assessed using a single 24-hour recall, and a subset of the sample (76.2% of those aged 12 and over) also completed a food frequency questionnaire (FFQ). Children aged 15 to 16 years provided their own dietary recall while parents, guardians or close relatives were responsible for providing the information for children aged 14 years or below. Among all the participants in 1995NS, 2,729 (19.7%) were aged between 2 and 16 inclusively.

For 2007NS, information on dietary intake, physical activities and demographic characteristics of randomly selected children and adolescents aged 2 to 16 years (n = 4,837) from all Australian states and territories were collected with a response rate of 40%. Data collection occurred between February 2007 and August 2007. Dietary data were collected using a 24-hour recall during face to face home visit, and the majority of the sample (n = 4,658) also completed a second 24-hour recall during a telephone interview conducted 7-21 days after the home visit. Care-givers provided dietary recall information for children aged 2 to 8 years while children of 9 years or above provided their own dietary recall. 

For 2012NS, respondents were randomly selected from 9,500 private dwellings across Australia except for very remote area and some non-private dwellings, e.g., hotels and hospitals. Dietary and physical activity information of the Australian population aged 2 years or above (n = 12,153) were collected from May 2011 to June 2012 from 12,366 dwellings with a 77% response rate. Dietary data were collected using a 24-hour recall during face to face home visit, and a second 24-hour recall during a telephone interview was collected in ~60% of subjects at least 8 days after the home visit. Adults were responsible for providing full food recall and physical activity question for children aged 2 to 5 years, while children aged 6 to 8 years can assist in the recall. Children aged 9 to 11 years were interviewed directly with adult assisting and children aged 12 to 14 years answered the questions themselves with adults in the same room. Those aged 15  17 years were interviewed personally with parental consent. Among all the participants in 2012NS, 2,548 (20.9%) were aged between 2 and 16 years inclusively.

A published systematic method was used to assign glycemic index values to foods reported in the surveys. Dietary glycemic load is defined as the sum of the products of glycemic index (as %) and the amount of available carbohydrate in the reported serving of the foods, and dietary glycemic index is calculated as dietary GL divided by total amount of available carbohydrate in the diet.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in dietary glycaemic index</outcome>
      <timepoint>1995 vs 2007 vs 2012</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in dietary glycaemic load</outcome>
      <timepoint>1995 vs 2007 vs 2012</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in major sources of dietary glycaemic load</outcome>
      <timepoint>1995 vs 2007 vs 2012</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in inter-individual variations in dietary glycaemic index explained by major contributors to dietary glycaemic load</outcome>
      <timepoint>1995 vs 2007 vs 2012</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in inter-individual variations in dietary glycaemic load explained by major contributors to dietary glycaemic load</outcome>
      <timepoint>1995 vs 2007 vs 2012</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants aged 2-16 years of the 3 national nutrition surveys (1995 National Nutrition Survey, 2007 Australian National Children's Nutrition and Physical Activity Survey and 2011-2012 Australian Health Survey) who provided plausible dietary intake data (as assessed by a published method).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Implausible dietary intake, as determined by the Goldberg cut-off method</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/10/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>8500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>8539</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/10/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Jimmy Chun Yu Louie</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5S-14, Kadoorie Biological Sciences Bldg,
The University of Hong Kong, 
1 Pokfulam Road, 
Pokfulam, Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 City Road, Camperdown NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Hong Kong</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Pokfulam Road, Pokfulam</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Australian Bureau of Statistics</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ABS House 45 Benjamin Way, Belconnen ACT 2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 10
Clayton South Vic 3169</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This secondary analysis aimed at examining the changes and temporal trends in the dietary glycaemic index and glycaemic load of Australian children and adolescents, as well as changes (if any) in the major sources of dietary glycaemic load. It will be performed using data from 3 Australian national nutrition surveys (i.e. 1995 National Nutrition Survey, 2007 Australian National Children's Nutrition and Physical Activity Survey, and 2011-2012 Australian Health Survey). </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not required</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Ethics approval were not required since this is a secondary analysis.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jimmy Chun Yu Louie</name>
      <address>5S-14, Kadoorie Biological Sciences Building, The University of Hong Kong, 1 Pokfulam Road</address>
      <phone>+85222990677</phone>
      <fax>+85225599114</fax>
      <email>jimmyl@hku.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jimmy Chun Yu Louie</name>
      <address>5S-14, Kadoorie Biological Sciences Building, The University of Hong Kong, 1 Pokfulam Road</address>
      <phone>+85222990677</phone>
      <fax>+85225599114</fax>
      <email>jimmyl@hku.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jimmy Chun Yu Louie</name>
      <address>5S-14, Kadoorie Biological Sciences Building, The University of Hong Kong, 1 Pokfulam Road</address>
      <phone>+85222990677</phone>
      <fax>+85225599114</fax>
      <email>jimmyl@hku.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>