<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336453">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000095965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective clinical trial assessing the Nanos short stem femoral prosthesis in patients undergoing total hip replacement surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with non-inflammatory joint disease who qualify for total hip replacement (THR) surgery, does insertion of the Nanos short stem femoral component enhance clinical outcomes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>n/a</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, Perth trial ID
NANOS 2010-090</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non inflammatory degenerative joint disease of the hip and the performance of a short stem femoral insert in the setting of total hip replacement surgery.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A "shorter than usual" femoral component is trialed which requires smaller cuts and therefore less bone loss during THR surgery. THR surgery takes about 2 hours to perform.  This implant is inserted into the upper end of the thigh bone and is part of the artificial hip joint. It remains in the body, hopefully for life. However, according to world medical literature, current implants are generally expected to last about 20 years and patients requiring THR surgery are getting younger. Should therefore revision surgery be needed then the bone stock preserving option of the shorter NANOS insert leaves the revision surgeon more options at the time of a second operation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Prospective trial, results will be compared against known outcome and performance results of long stem femoral components.
Long stem femoral components of varying design have been used worldwide and over more than 40 years ever since Sir Charles Charnley performed pioneering work in the field. Medical world literature contains countless trials and reports on different implants and their performance over this time frame. Over the last 10 to 15 years several countries, including Australia (started in 1999), establish National Joint Replacement Registries which record and track every single implanted device and can therefore serve as a benchmark.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to analyse with Roentgen Stereophotogrammetric Analysis (RSA) the migration patterns and rotational stability of the femoral component.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 3 months, 1 year, 2 years, 5 years and 10 years post operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objective is to assess the changes in bone formation and resorption using DEXA around the implant . Energy X-ray Absorptiometry (DEXA) has been demonstrated as a reliable method for the determination of bone mineral density of hip implants.  This technique provides details about the quality of fixation of the hip prostheses and implant induced bone remodelling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>DEXA scan will be completed preoperatively and at 12 months, 24 months, 5 years and 10 years after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EQ5D surveys will be undertaken.
The EuroQuol Group 5-Dimension Self-Report Questionnaire    scores quality of life and is used in medical research.  It consists of five questions assessing mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and depression/anxiety and a visual analogue scale for overall perception of health state. It was established as a brief and easy to use instrument and allows self-reporting rather than relying on interview-based assessment tools.  Its reliability has been established in various population groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up time points are placed as follows: preoperatively, perioperatively, 1 week, 6 weeks, 3 months, 12 months, 2 years, 5 years and 10 years post operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OHS surveys will be undertaken.
This is a short 12-item questionnaire which patients find easy to complete.  It   provides reliable and valid data regarding their perception of hip problems</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up time points are placed as follows: preoperatively, perioperatively, 1 week, 6 weeks, 3 months, 12 months, 2 years, 5 years and 10 years post operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications
Complications will be assessed and investigated when radiological or clinical examinations are abnormal and of course when the patient raises concern.
Complications include but are not limited to problems such as wound healing issues, deep or superficial infection, nerve damage, thrombosis or pulmonary embolus, septic or aseptic loosening, dislocations, leg length discrepancy and periprosthetic fractures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Complications will be recorded at any given point in time during the study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>6.1	Inclusion Criteria

1. 		The individual has signed a Patient Informed Consent (PIC), specific to this study, and approved by the Institutional Ethics Review Board.
2. 	The individual is between the ages of 21 and 60 years.
3. 	The individual is not classified as obese.
4. 	The individual clinically qualifies for total hip arthroplasty surgery based on physical examination and medical history.
5. 	The individual is diagnosed with Non Inflammatory Degenerative Joint Disease (osteoarthritis, traumatic arthritis, avascular necrosis, dysplasia).
6. 	The individual does not have an active infection within the affected hip joint.
7. 	The individual has not had a previous total hip replacement or hip fusion of the affected hip joint.
8. 	The individual is physically and mentally willing and able to comply with postoperative scheduled clinical and radiographic evaluations and rehabilitation (i.e., not currently being treated for a psychiatric disorder, senile dementia, Alzheimers disease, presence of alcohol or substance abuse).
9. 	The individual does not have a neuromuscular nor neurosensory deficiency, which limits the ability to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the device.
10. 	The individual does not have a diagnosed systemic disease that would affect the subjects welfare or overall outcome of the study (i.e., moderate to severe osteoporosis, Paget's disease, renal osteodystrophy), is not immunologically suppressed, or receiving steroids in excess of physiologic dose requirements.
11. 	The individual is skeletally mature.
12. 	The individual is not pregnant.
13. 	The individual is not a prisoner.
14. 	The individual has no plans to relocate to another geographic area before the completion of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>6.2	Exclusion Criteria 

 1. 	The individual has a neuromuscular or neurosensory deficiency, which limits the ability to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the device.
2. 	The individual has any type of radiologically detected osteopenia.
3. 	The individual has pronounced coxa valga with a femoral neck angle &gt; 145° or coxa vara with a femoral neck angle &lt; 125°.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>individuals who qualify for THR and fit the inclusion criteria and are willing to participate will be recruited from our clinics at the hospital.</concealment>
    <sequence>n/a</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>n/a</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Smith &amp; Nephew</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Smith &amp; Nephew Pty Limited
Suite 7, 567 Newcastle Street
West Perth
Western Australia 6005
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hospital Avenue 
Nedlands 6009
Perth, WA
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We propose to undertake a prospective clinical trial assessing qualities of the short stem cementless femoral prosthesis Nanos by Smith &amp; Nephew Pty Ltd.  We will undertake a 10 year follow up, which will consist of bone mineral density (DEXA) scanning, Roentgenstereometric Analysis (RSA), conventional radiographs and functional assessment.  Functional analysis will be undertaken by using EuroQuol Group 5-Dimension Self-Report Questionnaire (EQ5D) and the Oxford hip score (OHS).  Follow up time points will include the preoperative visit, the inpatient stay, 6 weeks, 3 months, 12 months and 2 years, 5 years and 10 years post surgery reviews.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee at Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Perth</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Diana Forster 
Acting Executive Officer 
Human Research Ethics Committee 
Executive Corridor 
1st Floor 'E' Block 
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital , QE II Medical Centre 
Hospital Avenue, NEDLANDS WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NANOS 2010-090</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Riaz Khan, Principal Investigator</name>
      <address>Suite 8
95 Monash Avenues
Nedlands  WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9386 3933</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rjkkhan@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matt Hofmann</name>
      <address>Orthopaedic Department
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue 
Nedlands 6009, WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9386 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mahof@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matthias Hofmann</name>
      <address>Orthopaedic Department
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue 
Nedlands 6009, WA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9386 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mahof@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>