<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368340">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000474550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Paramedic Initiated Helivac to Tertiary Hospital for Primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Paramedic Initiated Helivac to Tertiary Hospital for Primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention: A Strategy for Improving Treatment Delivery Times for ST-Elevation Myocardial Infarction Patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1161-7421</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>ST-Elevation Myocardial Infarction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This proposed research will be an experimental study trialling a Whangarei-based programme of paramedic initiated helivac of STEMI patients to a tertiary hospital for Primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PPCI) directly from the field. This will be compared to a previous programme where patients were firstly routed through the local receiving hospital's Emergency Department and the decision for patient helivac was made by the treating physician. This programme involves paramedics from St John Ambulance Service, New Zealands largest ambulance provider and occurs without physician oversight. It is also the first programme of its kind to be introduced within the country. We hypothesise that adopting such an approach will lead to improved patient outcomes, with reduced hospital admission times compared to previous physician authorised systems. Economic benefits are also likely.

The inclusion criteria for paramedic initiated helivac of STEMI patients from the field to a tertiary hospital from PPCI include:

1. 12-lead ECG with persistent ST-elevation &gt; 1mm in two or more contiguous limbs leads (I, II, III, aVL or aVF) OR ST-elevation &gt; 2mm in two or more contiguous chest leads (V1-V6) including postyerior leads V7-V9.

2. Monitor interpretation indicates &gt;&gt;&gt; Acute MI &lt;&lt;&lt; OR ***ACUTE MI SUSPECTED*** on two consectutive ECGs

3. Normal QRS width (less than or equal to 0.12secs) OR Right Bundle Branch Block identified on 12-lead ECG

4. Symptoms consistent with myocardial ischemia of &lt; 10 hours duration

5. Ambulance transport time from the patient's location to the helicopter base &lt; 15 minutes.

The exclusion criteria for this pathway includes:

1. Left Bundle Branch Block identified on 12-lead ECG

2. History of serious systemic disease e.g. advanced / terminal cancer, severe liver or kidney disease

3. Severe Dementia

4. Severe dependent living i.e. resident of an aged care facility requiring significant assistance with activities of daily living

5. Ongoing cardiac arrest requiring repeated CPR

Note: those patients who are not candidates for helivac will continue to be transported by ambulance to the normal local receiving hospital which is not PCI capable.

The overall intervention period for this study is 46 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>We will compare two groups of STEMI patients both of which have received PPCI following EMS helicopter transfer from the same non-interventional region but following two different models of patient identification and admission to the Cardiac Catheterisation Lab (CCL). The first group, a historic retrospective cohort, will have received PPCI under a previous model where identification of patient eligibility was first made in the local receiving hospital ED, and admission to the CCL was activated by ED physicians. In contrast, the second group, a prospective cohort, will receive PPCI following direct admission from the field to the CCL by paramedics who will make an autonomous clinical decision as to patient eligibility and will then activate the CCL independently. The difference between these two groups is the experimental intervention  an autonomous paramedic referral protocol that authorises this new model of pre-hospital management of STEMI patients eligible for PPCI. This new protocol has been taught to paramedics in an Education Package and it identifies those patients for whom direct admission from the field to the CCL is indicated / contraindicated.

Data for the historical cohort has already been collected following ethics approval on 23/12/2014 and Northland District Health Board approval on 12/09/2014. Data was sourced from the Northland District Healthboard.

Historic data collected was for all patients transported to Auckland City Hospital (ACH) CCL from Northland Base Hospital (NBH) ED via the Northland Emergency Services Trust (NEST) Helicopter Service for PPCI between the period May 1st 2010 and May 1st 2013 as part of the NBH-ED 'Code STEMI' pathway.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: Time from patient symptom onset and/or call for ambulance assistance until balloon inflation time for PPCI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The timepoint at which this outcome will be assessed will be at the time of PCI balloon inflation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: Patient outcomes - morbidity and all cause mortality as assessed by data linkage to medical records.

Morbidity factors and mortality include:

1. Vessel/s receiving PCI
2. Infarct location
3. Rates of complications post PCI e.g. arrhythmias, bleeding or cardiac arrest
4. Rates of failed PCI plus or minus coronary artery bypass surgery
5. In-hospital and 30-day incidence of death</outcome>
      <timepoint>The timepoint at which this outcome will be assessed will be 30 days following patient enrolment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 3: Patient hospital admission time (days). This outcome will be assessed through patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The timepoint at which this outcome will be assessed will be at discharge from hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1: Accuracy of Paramedic Application of the new Protocol.

The sensitivity and specificity along with PPV and NPV of the paramedics clinical diagnoses will be determined from their identification of patients suitable for PCI or not, and their activation or non-activation of the CCL. This will occur in the prospective cohort. Three independent cardiologists (experts) will review all cases to determine actual field diagnosis. Accuracy of paramedic application of the protocol will be measured against this gold standard. 
In the prospective cohort, the rate of True Positive and True Negative cases, along with Inappropriate Activations, False Positive and False Negative cases will be determined. To clarify further, Inappropriate Activation is defined as patient clinical presentation and/or ECG used to activate CCL does not meet activation criteria or ECG misinterpreted. False Positive is defined as patient clinical presentation and ECG used to activate CCL does meet activation criteria, but no culprit artery was found and negative biomarkers. Each of these five cases will be described as proportions of the total number of clinical decisions made. Causes of False Positives and False Negatives will be investigated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following completion of study at 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a) The retrospective cohort (n = 30) will include: all patients at/or greater than 18 years of age who were transported to Auckland City Hospital (ACH) CCL from Northland Base Hospital (NBH) ED via the Northland Emergency Services Trust (NEST) Helicopter Service for PPCI between the period May 1st 2010 and May 1st 2013 as part of the historic Code STEMI programme.

b) The prospective cohort (n = 30) will include: all patients at/or greater than 18 years of age up to 85 years of age who have been transported to ACH-CCL from Whangarei via the NEST Helicopter Service for PPCI between the period December 23rd 2014 and December 23rd 2017 as part of the paramedic STEMI Bypass programme. The study will also investigate all patients transported by road-based paramedics to the NEST helicopter base over the same time period but who were re-directed to NBH-ED following re-assessment by the Flight Intensive Care Paramedic (ICP).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Key patient exclusion criteria is essentially those that do not meet our inclusion criteria for either the historic or prospective cohort.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be enrolled in the study via two pathways:

1. Historic Cohort: Patients who have been transfered from Whangarei Hospital Emergency Department via ambulance helicopter to Auckland City Hospital CCL for primary PCI following physician referal, or

2. Prospective Cohort: Whangarei-based patients  transported via ambulance helicopter to Auckland City Hospital CCL for primary PCI directly from the field and following autonomous paramedic referal.

Patients in the two observed cohorts will also need to meet the inclusion criteria as previously discussed.</concealment>
    <sequence>n/a</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This proposed study has a prospective analysis of differences design. Data from two separate groups of STEMI patients (an historic retrospective cohort and a prospective cohort) will be collected and analysed and a post-intervention comparison made. The Prospective data analysis enables standardisation of measures used in the study and provides stronger confidence in the design. A true experimental design with randomisation was considered neither ethical nor pragmatic due to the impossibility of blinding the protocol application, as well as the lengthy time frame required to reach statistically significant levels of patient numbers. Therefore, our selected design provides a reasonable alternative with efficient use of available patient data. Data will be collected from patient medical records within the Ambulance Service and the receiving hospital. Medical records provide an abundance of information that can be evaluated in context. However, inconsistencies may exist and information may be incomplete. For these reasons we intend to primarily draw on data in the records that are part of gold standard routine assessments conducted on all patients in context with the study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on the autonomous paramedic primary PCI referral study involving 175 patients by Cheskes et al (2011) and an a priori power analysis using their data, 60 patients are required, resulting in 30 patients within each of the two observed groups.. This was assuming a sensitivity of 70%, an accuracy measure of +/- 10%, and a statistical significance level of a = 0.05, denoting a 95% confidence interval.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Northland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland University of Technology (AUT)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Auckland University of Technology (AUT)
Research and Innovation Office
Private Bag 92006
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clinical Audit and Research Group St John Ambulance Service NewZealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o

Dr Craig Ellis
Deputy Medical Director
Department: Clinical Development


Mailing address:

St John
62 Tait Drive
Napier 4112
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clinical Audit and Research Group St John Ambulance Service New Zealand</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o

Dr Craig Ellis
Deputy Medical Director
Department: Clinical Development

Mailing address:

St John
62 Tait Drive
Napier 4112
New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Heart disease is the second leading cause of death in New Zealand, after cancer. At the acute end of the spectrum of this disease is ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI), a common type of heart attack and the most severe. However, specific treatments are available for STEMI patients, which have high rates of success, especially if they are performed early, within the first hours of symptom onset. Two such treatments are Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PCI), a mechanical procedure, and thrombolysis, a drug therapy. Both treatments are time-dependent, with early provision conferring the greatest clinical benefits and results. 
Paramedics are able to play a key strategic role in achieving this objective, as they are often the first healthcare professionals to encounter the STEMI patient. 

Internationally, autonomous paramedic field activation of the hospital Cardiac Catheterisation Lab (CCL) where PCI takes place, as well as pre-hospital thrombolysis (PHT), have both proven to be the most effective strategies in facilitating expedited delivery of these two treatment modalities. However, within New Zealand ambulance services have been slow to adopt and/or refine such paramedic-based approaches. Current New Zealand models rely on physician authorised telemetry-based systems which have proved problematic, particularly due to technological failings.

This proposed research will be an experimental study trialling a model of paramedic initiated helivac of STEMI patients to a tertiary hospital for Primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention (PPCI). This programme involves paramedics from St John Ambulance Service, New Zealands largest ambulance provider and occurs without physician oversight. It is also the first programme of its kind to be introduced within the country. We hypothesise that adopting such an approach will lead to improved patient outcomes, with reduced hospital admission times compared to previous physician authorised systems. Economic benefits are also likely.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC)

Ministry of Health
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTA/221</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Auckland University of Technology Ethics Committee (AUTEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kate O'Connor
Executive Manager
AUTEC

Room WA505E, Level 5, WA Building
55 Wellesley Street East
Private Bag 92006
Auckland 1010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/04 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul Davis</name>
      <address>c/o St John Ambulance 
43 Western Hills Drive 
Kensington 0112 
WHANGAREI</address>
      <phone>+0064 09 437 2199 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.davis@stjohn.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul Davis</name>
      <address>c/o St John Ambulance 
43 Western Hills Drive 
Kensington 0112 
WHANGAREI</address>
      <phone>+0064 09 437 2199 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.davis@stjohn.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul Davis</name>
      <address>c/o St John Ambulance 
43 Western Hills Drive 
Kensington 0112 
WHANGAREI</address>
      <phone>+0064 09 437 2199 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.davis@stjohn.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul Davis</name>
      <address>c/o St John Ambulance 
43 Western Hills Drive 
Kensington 0112 
WHANGAREI</address>
      <phone>+0064 09 437 2199 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.davis@stjohn.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>