<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83680">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000212257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Internet vs. face to face cognitive behavioural therapy for social phobia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing Internet versus face-to-face cognitive behavioural therapy treatment on severity of symptoms of social phobia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Social phobia (an anxiety disorder)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two groups: 1) Internet based treatment for social phobia or; 2) Face-to-face based treatment for social phobia.
All participants will meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for social phobia. All participants will complete evidence-based materials about cognitive behavioural techniques for managing symptoms of social phobia. The Internet group will complete 6 online lessons over 8 weeks. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with social phobia, taking a further 20 minutes per summary. 

Participants receiving face-to-face treatment will complete 7 lessons of face to face manualised and evidence-based treatment for symptoms of social phobia, over a 7 week period, with one lesson per week. Each lesson will take 3 hours, and participants will be treated in a group format with 6 - 8 participants. Each group will be led by a psychologist or psychiatrist.

Participants will be contacted 3 months post program and asked to complete follow-up questionnaires. Study questionnaires will be administered at immediately pre-treatment, one-week post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment. These will take about 20 minutes to complete.</interventions>
    <comparator>Face-to-face treatment program for social phobia.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social phobia is measured by the Social Phobia Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered immediately pre-treatment, one -week post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social phobia is measured by the Social Interaction Anxiety Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered immediately pre-treatment, one -week post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered immediately pre-treatment, one -week post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured by the Kessler-10 (K-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered immediately pre-treatment, one -week post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability is measured by the Sheehan Disability Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered immediately pre-treatment, one -week post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet DSM-IV criteria for social phobia - Internet access + printer access. - Australian citizen- Males and females.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current substance abuse/dependence- Psychotic disorder- Current or planned psychological treatment during study duration- Change in medications during last 1 month or intended change during study duration.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply at the Anxiety Disorders Clinic, St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney, to receive treatment for social phobia. All applicants receive a psychiatric interview to determine diagnosis and eligibility.

Participants who meet inclusion criteria and wish to participate will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study. Allocation concealment will occur by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is off-site.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation list will be generated prior to the study using computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/04/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/05/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst
NSW2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Institute of Psychiatry</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cumberland Hospital
5 Fleet Street
North Paramatta
NSW2150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The efficacy of treatment for social phobia at the Anxiety Disorders Clinic is proven with benefits in the short and long term exceeding 1 standard deviation (SD) (McEvoy, 2007). Therapy over the internet has also been shown to be efficacious, again with benefits in the short and long term exceeding 1 SD (Titov et al, 2009). Whilst on this basis the two modes of therapy appear comparable in efficacy we cannot know whether people applying for internet therapy are particularly suited to that mode of treatment and whether people applying for face to face therapy are suited to that mode of therapy.  Internet therapy has service delivery advantages in terms of substantial reductions in therapist time and reductions in patient costs in terms of transport to the clinic which averages $30 per visit, and in terms of loss of wages or cost of carers while away from home.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Titov N, Andrews G, Johnston J, Schwencke G, Choi I. The Shyness program: Longer term benefits, cost-effectiveness, and acceptability. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2009;43:36-44. Titov N, Andrews G, Choi I, Schwencke G, Mahoney J. Shyness 3: An RCT of guided versus unguided Internet based CBT for social phobia. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2008;42:1030-1040. Titov N, Andrews G, Schwencke G. Shyness 2: A replication of Shyness 1. Are the results reliable, and who benefits? Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2008;42:595-605. Titov N, Andrews G, Schwencke G, Drobny J, Einstein D. Shyness 1: Distance treatment for social over the Internet. A randomized controlled trial. Aust N Z J Psychiatry 2008;42:585-594. Titov N, Andrews G, Choi I, Schwencke G, Johnston J. Internet-based cognitive behavior therapy for social phobia without clinical input is effective: a pragmatic RCT of two types of reminders. Submitted.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst 
NSW2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/SVH/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>C/- Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety Disorders (CRUfAD) UNSW 299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1726</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8382 1721</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>C/- Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety Disorders (CRUfAD) University of New South Wales (UNSW) 299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1726</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8382 1721</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>C/- Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety Disorders (CRUfAD) UNSW 299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1726</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8382 1721</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, Balaclava Road, North Ryde 
NSW, 2109, Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 2 98509901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>