<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335393">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000553976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of continuing medical education and feedback to altering diabetes at a population level. A randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Rural General Practitioners. Can a rural GP focussed intervention involving continuing medical education, reminders and feedback improve the clinical indicators related to management of Type 2 diabetes when compared to rural GPs who do not receive the intervention.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>1111-1121-8252</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>GPs in the intervention group will receive a multi-component intervention  involving continuing medical education, reminders and feedback over two years. An online module that provides continuing medical education on best practice diabetes care will be available to GPs during the two year intervention period. This module  will take approximately six hours to complete and can be completed at any time over the intervention period. GPs will have access to targeted and specialist advice through the use of the Website consultant enquiry forms. Questions submitted with these forms will be  answered by a endocrinologist.  GPs will receive regular (at baseline and six monthly over the two year intervention) feedback on their individual perfomance and town-based comparative feedback.  This feedback, based upon objective clinical measures obtained from pathology records, will be emailed to GPs.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intervention towns will be compared with towns allocated to usual care that have been matched on population, remoteness, indigenous population, and socio economic index.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic control. Using the most recent HbA1c for each case within each 24 month time frame, the mean HbA1c across the town, and the proportion of all cases whose most recent HbA1c value is 7.0%, will be determined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood lipids and urinary albumin control. Clinical practice guidelines recommend that blood lipids, and urinary albumin levels are tested once every 12 months as part of an annual cycle of care. Using the most recent results for each case within each 24 month time frame, the mean values of blood lipids and urinary albumin, and the proportion of all cases whose most recent values are within the relevant target ranges will be determined</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of HbA1c testing.The data from the laboratory will provide the dates on which each patient had an HbA1c test. Therefore, over each 24 month period, the mean number of HbA1c tests will be determined for each patient. The proportion of cases that have had 1, 2, 3 and 4 or more HbA1c tests will also be determined for each 24 month period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of blood lipid and urinary albumin testing. For each 24 month period (pre and post test), the mean number of blood lipid and urinary albumin excretion tests will be determined for each patient. The proportion of cases that have had 1, 2, 3 and 4 or more of each type of test will also be determined for each 24 month period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Be cost-effective in terms of cost per Quality Adjusted Life Year (QALY) gained as a result of improved clinical outcomes</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Towns defined by Postal Areas (POAs  are Australia Bureau of statistics approximations of postcodes) that are: i) regional or remote according to ARIA plus classification ii) have a population of 10,000 to 30,000; iii) are in Victoria, New South Wales, Queensland or South Australia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Towns that have fewer than 5 fulltime GPs</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Towns that were eligible for inclusion were paired according to relative remoteness, Indigenous population, and total population. Allocation was not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Paired towns were allocated to intervention or control group by a coin flip</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>14</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2429</postcode>
    <postcode>2460</postcode>
    <postcode>2794</postcode>
    <postcode>2446</postcode>
    <postcode>2330</postcode>
    <postcode>4405</postcode>
    <postcode>4700</postcode>
    <postcode>4807</postcode>
    <postcode>4352</postcode>
    <postcode>4860</postcode>
    <postcode>4610</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Notting Hill Campus
Department of General Practice
Building 1, 270 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Newcastle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Newcastle
 Medicine and Public Health, 
Rm 262 David Maddison Building,
 Cnr King and Watt Sts 
Newcastle NSW 2300</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Baker IDI</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 6492
St Kilda Rd Central
Victoria 8008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To test whether population-level effects can be achieved by implementing best-evidence practice change strategies for the care and management of diabetes. The study will test whether a rural GP-focused intervention involving Continuing Medical Education (CME), reminders &amp; feedback can:
i. Improve patterns of diabetes care as measured by frequency of testing for blood lipids, haemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) and urinary albumin
ii. Improve clinical outcomes as measured by glycaemic control, blood lipid control and urinary albumin control.
iii. Be cost-effective in terms of cost per Quality Adjusted Life Year (QALY) gained as a result of improved clinical outcomes</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.diabetesedforgps.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University. Standing committee on ethics in research involving humans (SCERH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University, 
Building 3E, Room 111, Clayton Campus, Wellington Road, Clayton Vic 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF08/3467 - 2008001712</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Newcastle, Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services
Research Offices
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2009-0157</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Leon Piterman</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice
School of Primary Health Care
Bldg 1, 270 Ferntree Gully Rd
Notting Hill Victora  3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9902 4465</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8575 2233</fax>
      <email>Leon.Piterman@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Chris Paul</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
Room 268
David Maddison Building
Cnr King &amp; Watt St
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49138472</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49138779</fax>
      <email>Chris.Paul@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>