<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82298">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/09/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/09/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000495426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can decreasing perfectionism impact on risk factors for eating disorders in adolescent females?  A controlled comparison of perfectionism and media literacy programs.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A controlled comparison of school-based perfectionism and media literacy programs for reducing eating disorder risk factors in adolescent females.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Eating disorders (Anorexia Nervosa and Bulimia Nervosa).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Two interventions were developed, one targeting perfectionism and one targeting media internalisation.  Both of these variables are prospectively identified eating disorder risk factors.  Both programs were 8 school lessons (50 minutes per lesson) in duration, delivered at a rate of 2 lesson per week.  The programs were delivered by two postgraduate clinical psychology students (i.e., one student taught each program), with the regular class teacher also present.

Both programs were designed to be interactive (e.g., small group work, class discussions) as this approach has been found to have a self-esteem enhancing effect (O'Dea &amp; Abraham, 2000) and to thus be more valuable than didactic delivery (Stice &amp; Shaw, 2004).  In addition, collaboration took place between the researchers and class teachers for suggestions regarding content, teaching style and learning activities.  

1. The program targeting perfectionism was developed from an existing text (Adderholdt &amp; Goldberg, 1999) that focuses on differentiating between the pursuit of excellence and being perfect.  Student activities involved identifying the pros and cons of perfectionism, learning to identify perfectionistic thinking styles, "reframing failure" (ie., making mistakes can have benefits), developing coping strategies to cope with perfectionistic tendencies and learning how to change unehlpful behaviours through a graded approach.
   
2. The program targeting media internalisation was constructed around the key concepts of literacy, activism and advocacy and was informed by previous media literacy trials (Eating Disorder Awareness &amp; Prevention, 1999; Wade, Davidson, &amp; O'Dea, 2003) and in particular, a pilot study of the individual lessons with Grade 8 mixed-gender students (Wilksch, Tiggemann &amp; Wade, 2006).  Specific student activities involved learning to identify and challenge stereotypes presented in the media, learning about digital manipulation techniques of magazine images, identifying positive/healthy and negative/unhealthy messages communicated in the meida, and pracitising communicating with the media to express individual opinions regarding advertising techniques.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group received normal school lessons.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examining if a significant change in the following eating disorder risk factors occurred relative to other condition or control group:
Perfectionism.
Media Internalisation.
Pressure to be thin.
Dieting.
Shape and weight concern.
Self-esteem.
Depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-program (4 weeks after baseline), 3-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' ratings of program value and enjoyment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome was assessed in questionnaire format, immediately upon completion of the 8-lesson program.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Year 10 students at 2 randomly selected secondary schools.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None (pariticpants were intact school classes).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Schools were selected at random and invited to participate in the study.  3 classes from each school were randomly allocated to the perfectionism, media literacy and control groups, respectively.  Allocation was not concealed, however the researchers chose intact classes without prior knowledge of students or staff member from individual classes.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/02/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Simon Wilksch</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Flinders University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Tracey Wade</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mitch Durbridge</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Overall, there were two key aims of the current study.  First, to assess the effectiveness of perfectionism and media literacy programs compared to control classes, in attempting to reduce eating disorder risk factors.  Outcomes were examined with the targeted variables (perfectionism, media internalization and perceived pressure to be thin) as well as other eating disorder risk factors (e.g., shape and weight concern, dietary restraint, depression, self-esteem etc).  Second, to qualitatively assess students perceived value and enjoyment of the respective programs.  This was the first time an eating disorder prevention program targeting perfectionism had been evaluated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders University Social And Behavioural Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/02/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00194</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Simon Wilksch</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82012996</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simon.wilksch@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Simon Wilksch</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82012996</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simon.wilksch@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Simon Wilksch</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82012996</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simon.wilksch@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>