<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362102">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000200886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Triple P-Positive Parenting Program for Indonesian Parents</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized-controlled trial of a brief intervention of Triple P-Positive Parenting Program to increase parenting competence of Indonesian parents.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Triple P</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parenting practices</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child emotional and behavioural problems</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A brief intervention of Triple P will be delivered as seminar series, which provides parents with strategies to promote child positive behaviour and to manage child difficult behaviour.  Participating parents will be divided randomly into two groups, intervention group and wait-list control group. The intervention group will immediately receive the Triple P seminar series in three-week period.  There are three seminars that will be delivered: The Power of Positive Parenting; Raising Confident, Competent Children; and Raising Resilient Children. Each seminar will take about 90 minutes. All written materials are translated into Indonesian. The seminar will be presented by a trained practitioner in Indonesian.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparison for the intervention group is a wait-list control group. The wait-list control group will receive the same seminar series once the intervention groups have completed the program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent outcomes, consisting of: (1) Parent confidence as measured by the Child Adjustment and Parent Efficacy Scale (CAPES); (2) Dysfunctional parenting practice as measured by the Parenting and Family Adjustment Scale (PAFAS) and the Parenting Scale; (3) Parenting stress as measured by the Parenting and Family Adjustment Scale (PAFAS); (4) Family relationships , as measured by the Parenting and Family Adjustment Scale (PAFAS); and  (5) Couple relationships as measured by  the Parenting and Family Adjustment Scale (PAFAS). The CAPES and PAFAS are self-report measures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child emotional and behavioural outcome as measured by parent rating on child behavioural and emotional problems in the Child Adjustment and Parent Efficacy Scale (CAPES).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, Post-intervention, and 6-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Service outcome indicating parent acceptability and parent satisfaction with the intervention. This will be evaluated through parent rating (Parent Acceptability Questionnaire and Parent Satisfaction Survey).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be recruited if they are eligible in the following criteria:
-Indonesian parents or carers with a typical developing child aged 2-12 years old;
-Parents or carers currently live with their child;</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Parents or carers having  a child with health problems or disabilities (e.g., physical or intellectual disability, or developmental disorder);
- Parents or carers do not live currently with their child;
- Parents or carers have difficulties with reading and writing;
-Parents or carers receiving on-going support from other program or professionals in regards to their child adjustment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Parents will be voluntarily participated in the study.  Their eligibility will be assessed by the researcher over the telephone. After parents receive a brief explanation of the study and indicate verbal consent to participate, a package of questionnaire (pre-intervention assessment) will be sent to them via internet or mail. Participating parents will be randomly assigned to intervention group or wait-list control group after they complete the questionnaire.  

The procedure for allocating the treatment is as follows: A person who is not involved in the trial will generate the treatment allocation sequence using a computer random generation number. The person will record this in a folded piece of paper and placed it in sequentially numbered, sealed and opaque envelopes. Once parents have completed the pre-intervention assessment, the researcher will open the sealed envelope and informed parents their allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated list of random number will be used to allocate the participants into 1 of 2 groups. The method employed is block randomization.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <state>East Java</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assoc.Prof. Kate Sofronoff (primary supervisor of Agnes Sumargi)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia, 
Brisbane, 
Qld 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia, 
Brisbane, 
Qld 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Agnes Sumargi</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia, 
Brisbane, 
Qld 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Agnes Sumargi (primary investigator)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia, 
Brisbane, 
Qld 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Alina Morawska (associate supervisor of Agnes Sumargi)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia, 
Brisbane, 
Qld 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Research has indicated that evidence-based parenting programs are effective in increasing parenting competence. However the implementation of evidence-based parenting program, such as Positive Parenting Program-Triple P, in Asian countries is relatively limited. Indonesia as one of the largest populated countries in the world has no evidence-based parenting program. The result of a previous study indicated the needs of Indonesian parents for a brief and non-intensive parenting program. Delivering a Triple P seminar series to Indonesian parents, therefore, is likely to meet the parents needs. This research project aims to test the effectiveness of the Triple P seminar series in increasing the parenting competence of Indonesian parents in Indonesia. A randomized control design will be employed. It is expected that in comparison to parents in a wait-list control group, parents that attend the seminar series (intervention group) will show a significant increase in parenting efficacy, couple and family relationships and a significant decrease in dysfunctional parenting practices, parental stress, and child emotional and behavioural problems. These changes are predicted to be maintained at 6-month follow-up assessment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.exp.psy.uq.edu.au/indoseminar</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Ethics Committee (Behavioural and Social Sciences Ethical Review Committee)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Innovation Division,
Research Road,
University of Queensland,
St Lucia, 
QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011000714</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Agnes Sumargi</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Queensland,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia,
Brisbane,
Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61733467689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agnes.sumargi@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Agnes Sumargi</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Queensland,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia,
Brisbane,
Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61733467689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agnes.sumargi@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Agnes Sumargi</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
University of Queensland,
Sir Fred Schonell Drive,
St Lucia,
Brisbane,
Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61733467689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agnes.sumargi@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>