<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369508">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001149550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>iStride: A locomotor training program for children with cerebral palsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of a 6 week  functional electrical stimulation (FES) assisted locomotor training program compared to locomotor training alone on functional mobility in children with bilateral spastic cerebral palsy: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-7012</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bilateral spastic cerebral palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will receive a 6 week FES robotic assisted locomotor training program 3 times a week for 6 weeks. Each session will be 1.5 hours in duration and will be comprised of 3 main parts. The first part will include bilateral neuromuscular electrical stimulation (NMES) to the hamstrings and quadriceps while using the RT600 - an FES robotic locomotor device that synchronises NMES during a gait cycle (30 minutes). The second part will be a treadmill body weight supported locomotor program both with and without physical facilitation (20 minutes). The treadmill program will be based on principles of fitness training using intervals that are determined by individual heart rate responses (aiming for 50-70% HRMax i.e. moderate to vigorous physical activity). Finally, children will practice overground walking in their walking frames with focus on improving functional use through lower limb patterning and steering ability (15 minutes). The remaining 25 minutes will include preparation into the harness, placement of electrodes and transfers between equipment. Attendance will be registered as well as clinical progress notes (as per standard clinical practice) to document  subjective reports, objective observations, individual responses and evaluation of treatment session.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will undergo a locomotor training program using the treadmill and overground walking component only. The treadmill body weight supported locomotor program will be both with and without physical facilitation (50 minutes). The treadmill program will be based on principles of fitness training using intervals that are determined by individual heart rate responses (aiming for 50-70% HRmax i.e. moderate to vigorous physical activity). Children will then practice overground walking in their walking frames with focus on improving functional use through lower limb patterning and steering ability (15 minutes).  The remaining 25 minutes will include preparation into the harness and transfers between equipment. Attendance will be registered as well as clinical progress notes (as per standard clinical practice) to document subjective reports, objective observations, individual responses and evaluation of treatment session.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>10 meter walk test performed in the child's usual mobility device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post treatment i.e. week 6</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Goal Attainment Scale based on ambulation e.g. change in walking ability, change in support or supervision required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Treatment i.e. week 6</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>10 meter walk test performed in the child's usual mobility device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up ( 6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Goal Attainment Scale e.g. change in walking ability, change in support or supervision required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up (6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility score on the WeeFIM</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post treatment i.e week 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility score on the WeeFIM</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up (6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance and Satisfaction scores on the Canadian Occupational Performance Measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post treatment i.e. week 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance and Satisfaction on the Canadian Occupational Performance Measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up (6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gross Motor Function Measure </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post treatment i.e. week 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gross Motor Function Measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up (6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children with bilateral spastic cerebral palsy (may include mixed signs with dyskinesia and hypertonia)
Aged between 5 and 12 years
Able to follow simple instructions (to perform the 10 meter walk test)
Gross motor function classification system Level III, IV or V i.e. those who typically require mobility devices to walk
Accepted to receive iRehab services through Princess Margaret Hospital (tertiary level referral)
Parent identified performance problems that include difficulty with transfers or difficulty with use of walking frame and mobility
Current use of an assistive walking device (must already have one and is currently being used)
Children must have a community therapy provider
Children must be at least 3 months post botulinum toxin injections </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Engagement in activity based rehabilitation locomotor training in the past 6 months
Uncontrolled seizure disorder
Orthopaedic Surgery in the past 12 months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once participants have been confirmed to be eligible for the study, a person uninvolved in the study will provide the allocation using sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>A dynamic random allocation method (i.e. minimisation) will be used. Children will be allocated to the groups using a simple coin toss by a person uninvolved in the study once 2 children have been enrolled that are (a) within 2 years of age and (b) the same GMFCS level. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The program will run for a period of 15 months. During this time, we anticipate that we will be able to recruit 20 children per group. This is based on current referral statistics to the iRehab service at Princess Margaret Hospital for Children with mobility related goals in children with bilateral spastic cerebral palsy between the ages of 5 and 12. This will be sufficient to detect a large effect in favour of the intervention group at a power of 0.80 and an alpha of 0.05 (two tailed test) for the primary outcome of mobility (effect size d=0.8).
Normality will be established for all measures through examining distributional plots, Q-plots and the Shapiro-Wilk test. For data that is normally distributed, parametric tests will be applied with means and standard deviations for each group at each assessment time point reported. For ordinal data, or where data is not normally distributed despite transformations, non-parametric tests will be applied with medians and interquartile ranges reported. Intention to treat analysis will be applied.

Mixed Models will be applied to account for repeated measures between groups over time (post treatment and follow-up) and enable within group comparisons over time (post treatment compared to baseline and follow-up compared to baseline). The advantage of the Mixed Models is that it will account for any missing data. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>28</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dayna Pool</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Level 2, 37-39 Hay Street
Subiaco, Western Australia
6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telethon - Perth Children's Hospital Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Roberts Road, Subiaco, Western Australia 6008 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Jane Valentine</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Level 2, 37-39 Hay Street
Subiaco, Western Australia
6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Catherine Elliott</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Level 2, 37-39 Hay Street
Subiaco, Western Australia
6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cerebral palsy is the most common cause of physical disability in childhood. Physiotherapy is an important patient focused healthcare delivery intervention that is necessary to improve functioning of muscles, walking and in the prevention of deformities. The life-long impact of cerebral palsy is higher than many conditions because of the early age onset. Hence physiotherapy needs to be provided from an early age to influence not only muscular structure (such as strength and flexibility) but also neurological structures such as the brain - which can learn and change when given the right stimulus to do so. There has been a recent paradigm shift in how to train and promote walking in people with neurological conditions. Activity and intensity of training are crucial and much of this has been drawn from neurological research and spinal cord injury research. It is increasingly recognized that teaching the pattern of walking is important to stimulate the central pattern generators  the intrinsic and reflexive pathways in our neurological system that guide movement.  

This approach is not well understood in the area of cerebral palsy but given the theoretical foundation combined with our clinical experience and observations that have demonstrated feasibility and potential efficacy, a controlled larger scale study is necessary. This is particularly relevant because technology is now increasingly available in the community but is supported by limited evidence. Evidence based approaches are necessary to ensure ethical use of limited funds.

The significance of this research recognizes that one in three children with cerebral palsy cannot walk and rely on equipment aides and physical support from carers. Hence programs focusing on walking will address known issues due to sedentary behaviour in children with cerebral palsy and in the prevention of obesity and pain. Such interventions will improve independence and functioning hence reducing the burden of care, which is by far, accountable for the highest economic impact of this condition. Therefore training to walk at an early age even with the use of mobility aides such as walking frames actually translates to increasing and maintaining movement, strength, independence, function, participation and well-being to reduce the burden of care not just for short term gain but well into the future as children become adults.


This approach combines the knowledge and principles needed to improve muscular structures, central pattern generators and an avenue to improve walking speed and endurance in young children with cerebral palsy even though children are classified as having lower gross motor function (GMFCS III, IV and V). 

The primary aim of this research is to determine if robotic assistive rehabilitation improves functional mobility in children with cerebral palsy who usually require assistance to walk and reduced burden of care for their parents and families.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Roberts Road Subiaco, Western Australia, 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dayna Pool</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Level 2, 37-39 Hay Street
Subiaco, Western Australia
6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dayna.Pool@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dayna Pool</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Level 2, 37-39 Hay Street
Subiaco, Western Australia
6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dayna.Pool@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dayna Pool</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Level 2, 37-39 Hay Street
Subiaco, Western Australia
6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dayna.Pool@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dayna Pool</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Level 2, 37-39 Hay Street
Subiaco, Western Australia
6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dayna.Pool@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>