<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366507">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000642684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Characterization of endothelial function, arterial stiffness and inflammation in Atrial Fibrillation: Effect of cardioversion</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Characterization of endothelial function, arterial stiffness and inflammation in Atrial Fibrillation: Effect of cardioversion</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial fibrillation
 </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Electrical cardioversion

Cardioversion will be performed on patients who were fasted for up to eight hours prior to the procedure. Patients will be sedated with midazolam and a 150J biphasic shock will be used to reset SR. Patients will be closely monitored by trained staff for the duration of the procedure and discharged when clinically stable and fully recovered from sedation (within 1.5 hours post cardioversion for all patients). </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The objective of our studies is to evaluate the effects of reverting AF patients (n=60) back to sinus rhythm via cardioversion and the effect this has on endothelial function. 

The EndoPAT device was utilised to non-invasively measure endothelial function. One PAT finger probe is placed on the index finger of the hand undergoing hyperemia testing (right hand), and a second PAT probe was placed on the contralateral index finger (left hand) and is used as a control. Patients will be recumbent and rested prior to endothelial function evaluation. 

Endothelial dependent response relates to flow mediated increase in pulse wave amplitude (PWA) following 5 minute pneumatic cuff occlusion of the brachial artery. The PAT hyperemia ratio is defined as the ratio of the average PWA during the 1-minute period beginning exactly 60 seconds of reactive hyperemia compared with the average PWA during a 210-second preocclusion baseline period. In an effort to decrease confounding variables, including potential systemic effects of unilateral arm ischaemia, this ratio is normalized to the concurrent signal from the contralateral, nonischemic hand. PAT measurements will be analyzed with a computerized, automated algorithm (Itamar Medical Ltd, Caesarea, Israel). 
Endothelial function was also measured with Eliza assays of Asymmetric dimethyl arginine (ADMA) and flow cytometry assessing von Willebrand factor (vWF). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to cardioversion procedure 
Within 6 hours post-procedure 
7 days after procedure 
3 months post-procedure </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The objective of our studies is to evaluate the effects of reverting AF patients (n=60) back to sinus rhythm via cardioversion and the effect this has on inflammation. 

Inflammation will be assessed using ELIZA assays of Soluble CD40L, routine biochemical assays of hs-CRP and flow-cytometry of CD40-CD40L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to cardioversion procedure 
Within 6 hours post-procedure 
7 days after procedure 
3 months post-procedure </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The objective of our studies is to evaluate the effects of reverting AF patients (n=60) back to sinus rhythm via cardioversion and the effect this has on arterial stiffness.

Aortic pulse wave velocity (PWV) and augmentation index (AIx) are commonly used noninvasive measurements of arterial stiffness and wave reflection strength, respectively. We have recently purchased, a new device (SphygmoCor Xcel; AtCor Medical) which measures AIx using a partially inflated brachial cuff and PWV using a partially inflated femoral cuff together with carotid applanation tonometry.
To assess AIx, brachial artery compression waveforms will be obtained by partially inflating a cuff over the brachial artery approximately midway between the shoulder and the elbow. The brachial waveforms are calibrated using cuff-measured brachial systolic and diastolic pressures, and then used to generate central aortic pressure waveforms by applying proprietary digital signal processing and transfer function. The central aortic pulse wave is used to determine AIx: the ratio of wave reflection amplitude to central pulse pressure. To assess PWV, carotid pulse waves are measured by applanation tonometry (high-fidelity micromanometer; Millar  instruments) and femoral pulse waves are simultaneously obtained by a partially inflated cuff over the femoral artery at the leg midway between the hip and the knee. PWV is determined by calculating the ratio of the corrected distance between the pulse measuring sites to the time delay between the carotid and femoral pulse waves. The distance is measured with a nonstretchable tape (1) from the suprasternal notch to the carotid site, (2) from the femoral artery at the inguinal ligament to the proximal edge of the thigh cuff and (3) from the suprasternal notch to the proximal edge of the thigh cuff. Distances 1 and 2 were subtracted from distance 3 and used in the calculation of PWV. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to cardioversion procedure 
Within 6 hours post-procedure 
7 days after procedure 
3 months post-procedure </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This study will consist of evaluating patients who are undergoing a therapy directed at restoring sinus rhythm, ie. electrical cardioversion; patients of both sexes aged &gt; 18 yrs meeting the following criteria will be enrolled. Consecutive patients with AF undergoing elective cardioversion at the Royal Adelaide Hospital or Wakefield Hospital will be eligible for this study. Endothelial function testing will be performed pre and 2 hours post procedure.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they have known causes of acute AF (such as pneumonia or other infections, alcohol excess, pulmonary embolism), significant heart valve disease, acute cardiovascular or cerebrovascular events (myocardial infarction, acute coronary syndrome or stroke) within the last 3 months, malignancy, connective tissue disease, chronic infection, inflammatory conditions, renal or hepatic dysfunction. We will exclude patients who, for any reason, are contra-indicated to undergo cardioversion of AF. As a final exclusion, patients unable to undergo a brief general anaesthetic will not be enrolled.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation not concealed </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Continuous variables will be reported as mean +/- SD and evaluated utilizing an unpaired Students t-test or the Mann Whitney U tests (if non-Gaussian). Categorical variables will reported as numbers and percentage, and compared using the Fishers exact test. Sequential data measurements will be evaluated by 1-way ANOVA with repeated measures followed by the Bonferronis procedure for posthoc analysis. Statistical significance is established at p&lt;0.05.

Sizing calculation: From previously generated preliminary data in patients with atrial fibrillation (n=16). Baseline endothelial function as measured by EndoPAT = 1.6 +/- 0.3 RHI. 2 hours after cardioversion endothelial function as measured by endopat = 1.8 +/- 0.4 RHI. Hence power calculation: to detect an increase in baseline RHI of 1.0xSD by cardioversion at 2 hours at P&lt; 0.05, we approximate that 60 patients will be needed (a=0.8).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>10/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Heart Rhythm Disorders University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Adelaide SA 5000 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Heart Rhythm Disorders University of Adelaide

</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Adelaide SA 5000 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate if restoring sinus rhythm in patients with atrial fibrillation by cardioversion is associated with impairment of endothelial function, arterial stiffness and inflammation.

The hypotheses to be tested include:
1)	Restoration of sinus rhythm by cardioversion will adversely affect endothelial function, arterial stiffness and inflammation. 
2)	The length of time patients remain in sinus rhythm will correlate significantly with changes in endothelial function, arterial stiffness and inflammation.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committee Royal Adelaide Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3 Hanson Institute, IMVS Building, RAH
North Terrace, Adelaide  SA  5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/RAH/206</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Scott Willoughby</name>
      <address>Centre for Heart Rhythm Disorders 
University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5000 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8313 0131</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2722</fax>
      <email>scott.willoughby@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Scott Willoughby</name>
      <address>Centre for Heart Rhythm Disorders 
University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5000 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8313 0131</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2722</fax>
      <email>scott.willoughby@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Scott Willoughby</name>
      <address>Centre for Heart Rhythm Disorders 
University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5000 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8313 0131</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2722</fax>
      <email>scott.willoughby@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Scott Willoughby</name>
      <address>Centre for Heart Rhythm Disorders 
University of Adelaide
Adelaide SA 5000 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8313 0131</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2722</fax>
      <email>scott.willoughby@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>