<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367318">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001178639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Routine Use Of 0.9% Saline Vs. Routine Use Of Plasma-Lyte 148 (Registered Trademark) For Intravenous Fluid Therapy In Emergency Department Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Routine Use Of 0.9% Saline Vs. Routine Use Of Plasma-Lyte 148 'Registered Trademark' For Intravenous Fluid Therapy In Emergency Department Patients: a comparison of kidney function, hospital length of stay, intensive care admission and mortality.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1155-0632</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SPLITED</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intravenous Fluid Management in Emergency Department Patients </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single centre, open label,  before and after audit.

One month prior to the intervention period there will be Emergency Department (ED) staff education and logistic arrangements for changing to Plasma-Lyte 148 'Registered Trademark' as the default IV fluid. During the 12 week intervention period Plasma-Lyte 148 'Registered Trademark' will be used as the default primary crystalloid fluid. The dosing regimen is at the discretion of the treating clinician.

A random sample of 100 patients that received fluid in emeregency department will be assessed to see extact type and amount of given.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Data will be retrospectively collected for a 12 week control period exactly one year prior to the intervention period to allow for minimisation of seasonal effects. During the control period the predominant intravenous fluid prescribed in Wellington Hospital was 0.9 % saline</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is the delta creatinine (the difference between admission and peak serum creatinine in the first seven days in hospital). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The baseline creatinine will be the creatinine measured at ED presentation. The peak creatinine will be the highest creatinine in the first seven days in hospital.  

In the event that the creatinine is not measured again after hospital admission the delta creatinine will be defined as zero. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients with acute kidney injury or failure based on creatinine levels in accordance with RIFLE-criteria during the first seven days in hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>based on the highest value measured during the first seven days in hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients with acute kidney injury or failure based on creatinine levels in accordance with KDIGO stage during the first seven days in hospital. </outcome>
      <timepoint>based on the highest value measured during the first seven days in hospital. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of the proportion of patients: 
- requiring renal replacement therapy
- in-hospital death 
- need for ICU admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>As collected from computerized central hospital databases from from date of ED presentation until hospital discharge or death.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of ICU admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from ICU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Hospital stay </outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients &gt;18 year presenting to ED and subsequently admitted to hospital who have a serum creatinine measured in the ED</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients on renal replacement therapy for end stage renal failure. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This audit will use be an open label, before-and-after design.

The audit will be conducted with two 12 week periods occurring during the same time of the year to minimise seasonal effects. 

Data for the control period will be retrospectively taken for a 12 week period exactly one year prior to start date for intervention period. During this control period patients admitted to Wellington Regional Hospital from ED would have received intravenous (IV) fluid at the discretion of the treating clinician, in which 0.9% saline would have been used as the preferred primary crystalloid fluid therapy.

Prior to the commencement of the 12 week intervention period there will be a 4 week period of staff education and logistic arrangements for fluid switching from 0.9 % saline to Plasma-Lyte148 'Registered Trademark'. During the 12 week intervention period patients in ED will receive Plasma-Lyte148  'Registered Trademark' as the preferred primary crystalloid fluid.  

Both 0.9% saline and Plasma-Lyte 148  'Registered Trademark' will be available in the situations, where, in the opinion of the treating ED specialist, there is a clinical indication for one fluid or the other. Specific fluids will be available for use in rare situations where the treating clinician believes that there is an indication for one fluid or the other. </concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This  project  is  an  audit  of  practice  change  and  is  therefore  exempt  from requirements for informed consent. The audit involves no departure from standard care and does not involve the collection of any data that are not already being collected for clinical and / or quality assurance purposes. In this audit, whether or not ED patients receive 0.9% saline or Plasma Lyte 'Registered Trademark' 148 as default therapy will be determined by the timing of the introduction of change in therapy.

This Audit has been prospectively registered and approved as a clinical audit by the Coast District Health Board Audit Commitee. 

Data will be collected from computerised central hospital and laboratory databases at the completion of the audit. All baseline and outcome data (expect creatinine) is routinely collected and coded as part of the National Minimum Dataset (NMDS). The creatinine on admission and daily creatinine we will be collected from the central laboratory database.   

Details of the volume and type of fluid actually received by each patient will not be collected. However, a random sample of 100 patients in each treatment period who received intravenous fluid in ED and were admitted to hospital will be reviewed to assess the volume and type of fluid administered in ED. The number of patient records reviewed to obtain 100 patients who received IV fluids will be reported</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>No large-scale interventional trial has compared the use of 0.9% saline to a buffered crystalloid solution.  As such, the principal reasons for conducting this program of studies will be to determine feasibility and inform future sample size calculations. All studies are set to run for a specific period of time and have no fixed recruitment number. 

All continuous variables will be assessed for normality and log-transformed where appropriate. Baseline comparisons between groups will be determined using chi-square tests for equal proportion (or Fishers exact tests for small numbers), student t-tests for normally distributed variables and Wilcoxon ranks sum tests otherwise. 
Binomial outcomes will be analysed using poisson regression models with results reported as Relative Risks (95%CI). Continuous outcomes will be analysed using mixed linear modelling with results reported as differences (95%CI) or ratios (95%CI) as appropriate. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>3000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 7901, Wellington 6242</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Baxter Healthcare</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 88, Toongabbie (2146), NSW </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 7901, Wellington 6242</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This will be an audit to provide preliminary data to address whether the use of Plasma-Lyte148 'Registered Trademark' as default intravenous fluid results in better clinical outcomes compared to current standard practice.

The audit will be conducted with two 12 week periods. During the control period patients admitted to Wellington Regional Hospital from ED would have received intravenous fluid at the discretion of the treating doctors, in which 0.9% saline would have been the preferred intravenous fluid. This will be compared a 12 weeks where the preferred fluid will be Plasma-Lyte148 'Registered Trademark'. 

The outcomes that will be recorded will be kidney function, hospital length of stay, intensive care admission and mortality. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This study will be an audit looking at before and after a practice change. As such does not require NZ HDEC ethical approval. 
However this audit has been approved and registered as a clinical audit by Capital and Coast District Health Board. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>See Public Notes section</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>N/a</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sumeet Reddy</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand 
Private Bag 7901, Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0239</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sumeet.reddy@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sumeet Reddy</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand 
Private Bag 7901, Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0239</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sumeet.reddy@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sumeet Reddy</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand 
Private Bag 7901, Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0239</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sumeet.reddy@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sumeet Reddy</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand 
Private Bag 7901, Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0239</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sumeet.reddy@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>