<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366113">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000751673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigation of the Vivosight system for diagnosis and assistance in the management of cutaneous basal cell carcinoma (BCC)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In the diagnosis of cutaneous BCC, how does the specificity and sensitivity of the Vivosight system compare to skin biopsy in differentiating subtypes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cutaneous basal cell carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Vivosight optical coherence tomography is a type of optical scanner that provides high resolution pictures of the superficial tissue by using very low intensity laser beams without causing any injury or having to cut out the tissue. The scan will be taken twice during the research, once at the baseline visit, and once at 6 month follow up. The scan itself will not take more than 1 minute and will not influence the treatment. If patient has a superficial BCC based on biopsy, the treatment will be topical and these patients will be followed up in 6 months. If patients do not have superficial BCC based on biopsy, they will be advised on appropriate treatment option, but will not be required to have 6 months follow up.</interventions>
    <comparator>A skin biopsy is a sample of skin tissue cut out under local anaesthesia. It is the current gold standard in the diagnosis of many skin conditions and is standard clinical practice in the diagnosis of BCCs. Patients will undergo biopsy twice in this study, once at baseline to confirm the diagnosis, and once at 6 month follow up to determine clearance. A skin biopsy takes approximately 5-10 minutes to perform. All patients will undergo both Vivosight optical coherence tomography and skin biopsies.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confirmation that optical coherence tomography (OCT) can diagnose superficial BCC with &gt;95% sensitivity and &gt;75% specificity. This will be done by measuring the frequencies of the OCT features in different BCC cases. Significant differences between superficial BCC and other types of BCCs will be evaluated by means of Chi square test of independence. Multivariate analysis and binary logistic regression will be performed for the identification of the independently significant features and for the validation of the efficacy of OCT in distinguishing between superficial BCC and other types of BCC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary timepoint will be assessed at recruitment or baseline visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantification of how well OCT measures the depth of superficial lesions compared to histology. This will be done by comparing the lesion depth on the OCT scan and the lesion depth on pathology based on the biopsy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at recruitment or baseline visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agreement between OCT and histology at day 1 and day 180 of follow-up for clearance / treatment failure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 180 day follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must be aged 18 years or older; present with pink patch lesions that are suspected superficial basal cell carcinomas; be able to follow trial instructions; and be likely to complete all trial requirements (must be willing to give written informed consent and to allow photographs and images of the selected treatment area).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients unable to give consent or follow trial instructions. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A total sample size of 120 (which includes 6 subjects with nodular BCC) will achieve 94% power to detect a change in sensitivity from 0.6 to 0.99 using a one-sided binomial test, and 100% power to detect a change in specificity from 0.6 to 0.9 using a one-sided binomial test. 80 participants will be recruited from MIA and 40 participants from the Charite Hospital, Berlin.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/03/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2060 - North Sydney</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Berlin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Melanoma Institute of Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Poche Centre 
40 Rocklands Road
North Sydney NSW 2060</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Melanoma Institute of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Road
North Sydney
NSW 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>CMB Collegium Medicum</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Luisenstrasse 54/55, 10117 Berlin</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Germany</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to collect information on the ability of the Vivosight OCT system to distinguish basal cell carcinomas that require surgical treatment from those that would respond to non- invasive therapy based on lesion depth. In the future this might allow the clinician to select the appropriate treatment course without requiring a biopsy to determine how deep the lesion is, preventing possible recurrence in the cases where the lesion is deeper than anticipated. 

Who is it for? 
All patients with pink patches suspicious for superficial BCC will be recruited into the study at their first visit. 

Study details 
During the patients first visit, a clinical photograph, and dermoscopy photograph of the lesions will be taken. The OCT scan will also be taken, which is a non-invasive, optical imaging technique, lasting less than 1 minute. A skin biopsy will then be taken to confirm the diagnosis. With the results from the skin biopsy, patients will be advised on treatment option. If patient has a superficial BCC, the treatment will be topical and these patients will be followed up in 6 months. If patients do not have superficial BCC, they will be advised on appropriate treatment option, but will not be required to have 6 months follow up. At 6 months, all superficial BCC cases will be followed up with clinical photograph, dermoscopy photograph of the treated lesion. The OCT scan and skin biopsy will be taken again to determine the clearance of the treated BCC. Based on the skin biopsy results, further treatment advice will be given. This will not be part of the protocol and is based on best clinical practice.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, deLacy Building,
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst
NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SVH: 14/025</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pascale Guitera</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute of Australia
The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Road
North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 80050012</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pascale@guitera.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sandie Grierson</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute of Australia
The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Road
North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99117200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sandie.grierson@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pascale Guitera</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute of Australia
The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Road
North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 80050012</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pascale@guitera.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hui Mei Cheng</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute of Australia
The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Road
North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>hmeicheng@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>