<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373575">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001345370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Recumbent bike riding for people with fractured neck of femur: A feasibility trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Recumbent bike riding for people with fractured neck of femur: A feasibility trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1201-5610 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>BikeNoF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Fracture Neck of Femur</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention Group.  The intervention group will receive routine care which includes nursing, medical and physiotherapy care.  Care will initially be provided in the acute hospital, but some participants will require additional care in a rehabilitation ward.  Participants in the both the intervention and usual care arms will receive standard physiotherapy care, according to the current Austin Health Fractured Neck of Femur: Physiotherapy Clinical Guideline.    
The intervention will commence once consent has been obtained and the baseline assessment has been conducted; which will occur within 48 hours of surgery.  In addition to usual care, participants in the intervention arm will actively cycle (with a passive back up rate of 5 cycles per minute) on a recumbent bike (Motomed Letto 2).  The bike training sessions will be undertaken once a day on weekdays for up to 60 minutes per session.  The session length will be determined by the treating therapist, based on the exercise tolerance of the individual participant. (As this is a feasibility trial, actual session length will be monitored to inform optimal session length in future trials) They will be delivered to participants in their bed.  Sessions will be supervised by a physiotherapy research assistant.  Participants will be encouraged to work up to a moderate intensity as measured by the BORG rating perceived exertion scale (12-15), within the limits of their medical condition.  Participants will continue to receive the bike training intervention until they meet the mobility criterion of ability to walk a minimum of 15 metres with assistance of one person for two consecutive days, as assessed by the usual care physiotherapist.  The intervention will also be ceased if the treating team decide that there are no further rehabilitation goals.  If the participant is transferred to rehabilitation within Austin Health, the intervention will continue until the mobility milestone is met.  Data on exercise time and intensity and any barriers to training will be recorded by the intervention therapist as indicators of adherence. Pain will also be assessed using a written numerical rating scale at the end of the session. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive routine care which includes nursing, medical and physiotherapy care.  Care will initially be provided in the acute hospital, but some participants will require additional care in a rehabilitation ward.  Participants in the both the intervention and usual care arms will receive standard physiotherapy care, according to the current Austin Health Fractured Neck of Femur: Physiotherapy Clinical Guideline.   </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>intervention feasibility :  number of bike training sessions delivered, reasons for non - delivery of sessions, length of training sessions and feedback from patients on the acceptability of the intervention.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participant discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>intervention safety; number of adverse events throughout the trial, including mortality, post-operative complications, issues with surgical fixation, bleeding, delirium (as measured daily using the Confusion Assessment Method [CAM]), infections, falls and pressure areas.  This information will be collected by usual care physiotherapy staff as they occur.  In addition, the blinded assessor will verify adverse events at each assessment time point (7 days post surgery and hospital discharge) from multiple sources including medical records, staff report and hospital incident reports (Riskman).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Usual care physiotherapy staff will assess the CAM on a daily basis.  The presence of other  adverse events will be documented by usual care staff as they occur (i.e. daily until discharge).

Blinded assessors will verify adverse events at 7 days post surgery and hospital discharge.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>trial feasibility;  participant recruitment and retention, completion of outcome measures, documentation of any trial protocol deviations or variations, and feedback from trial staff about any issues encountered in the delivery of the protocol.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of trial</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Modified Iowa Level of Assistance Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Iowa Level of Assistance Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Discharge destination as documented in the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>gait speed, measured using the 6 m timed walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute length of stay, defined as days between acute hospital admission and acute hospital discharge, as determined from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>acute hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, measured using the Euro-quol 5 D (EQ5D) and EuroQol Visual analogue scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subacute length of stay; defined as days between subacute hospital admission and subacute hospital discharge, as determined from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subacute hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>	Have had surgical correction of a fracture neck of femur,
	Be unable to walk 15 m with assistance at enrolment (within 4 days of surgery). 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Fracture is pathological or result of a high velocity trauma (eg car accident),
	Subtrochanteric fractures
	Other lower limb fractures present,
	Any medical conditions present which would prevent either mobilisation/ recumbent bike riding (including lower limb NWB status),
	surgically managed with Total Hip Replacement.  Post-operatively, these people are managed according to the Total Hip Replacement guidelines, so usual care is different to the care provided to people on the Fracture Neck of Femur guidelines. 
	They were unable to walk &gt; 15 m premorbidly,
	They are pregnant 
	They are not expected to survive &gt; 7 days, as determined by the treating physician.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment> Allocation will be concealed by opaque, sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be blocked and stratified for pre-exisiting dementia, as identifed using the Informant Questionnaire of Cognitive Decline in the Elderly (Short Form).  Randomisation  will be computer generated and performed by a third party. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a pilot trial to demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed protocol, thus formal sample size estimation has not been completed.  Based on our experience with other trials, a sample of 50 participants (with 25 in each arm) will provide sufficient data for us to test the protocol in a robust manner and provide sufficient data for sample size analysis for the definitive trial.  

To determine whether the intervention is feasible, the proportion of scheduled sessions delivered  and median length of session time will be calculated and reasons for non-delivery of sessions inspected by the investigators.  Patient feedback will be examined thematically using a grounded theory approach. 

To determine whether the trial protocol is feasible, data on key project quality indicators will be collated, including data on participant recruitment, participant retention, completed outcome data at each time point.   Trial protocol deviations or variations and trial staff feedback will be reviewed by investigators.

To determine whether the intervention is safe, adverse events will be compared between groups using appropriate statistical techniques.  

Baseline characteristics will be examined for the intervention and control groups, to determine whether the groups are similar.  

Data from the mILOA will be will be examined for normality, and descriptive data calculated for the intervention and control groups using either parametric or nonparametric statistics as appropriate.  Effect size will be calculated and sample size will be estimated for the larger study, with the assistance of a statistician.   Note that as this study will not be sufficiently powered, tests for significance will not be conducted.  
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Catherine Said</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Dept
Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084 Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084 Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms Marisa Delahunt</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084, Vic</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Prof Sue Berney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084, Vic</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mr Andrew Hardidge</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084, Vic</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Early mobilisation post operatively is a key recommendation for people with fractured neck of femur (NOF).  Exercise and early mobilisation may reduce complications post operatively, including delirium, and may lead to shorter length of stay and better outcomes.  However, evidence indicates that as few as 50 % of people are able to be mobilised by day 2 post operatively.  Barriers to mobilisation include confusion and drowsiness, low blood pressure or an unacceptable level of manual handling risk.  Other methods of safely exercising people with fractured NOF who are unable to safely mobilise should be explored.  

Recumbent bike riding has been used for exercise in other bed bound populations including spinal cord injury and patients from an intensive care unit.  Evidence has shown this treatment is feasible and safe in these populations.  There is preliminary evidence that recumbent bike riding is associated with reduced incidence of delirium and reduced muscle wasting in people from Intensive Care Units (ICU).  Recumbent bike riding has potential to allow early exercise in people with a fractured NOF, however to date this intervention has not been used in this population.  Thus the purpose of this study is to demonstrate the feasibility of a trial of recumbent bike riding in people unable to mobilise post fracture NOF.  A secondary aim is to obtain preliminary data on the impact of recumbent bike riding on mobility, delirium and length of stay.  

Fifty people who have received surgical management for a fractured NOF will be recruited within 48 hours of surgery.  They will be randomly allocated to receive either usual care or usual care plus up to an hour active recumbent bike cycling.  They will continue to receive the intervention until they can walk 15m with assistance of one person for two consecutive day.  Primary outcomes include data demonstrating the feasibility of delivering the intervention and conducting the proposed RCT.  The primary clinical outcome is mobility seven days post operatively, as measured using the Modified Iowa Level of Assistance Scale. (mILOA)  Secondary clinical outcomes include mobility at discharge (measured using the mILOA and gait speed), discharge destination, length of stay and quality of life.  

Data from this study will inform the design of a larger RCT which will form the basis of applications to NHMRC and other funding bodies.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084
Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/Austin/274</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Said</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3697</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.said@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Said</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3697</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.said@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Said</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3697</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.said@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Said</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Austin Health
Studley Rd
Heidelberg, 3084
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3697</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.said@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>