<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366691">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000916640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does technology  improve the compliance of daily weight monitoring in community dwelling people who have  chronic heart failure.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In community dwelling people who have chronic heart failure, do the use of scales with memory versus scales with memory and enhanced remote access, improve daily weight monitoring compliance. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1159-0902 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who consent to participate in the trial will be randomised to one of two groups:

(a) Usual Care Group
(b) Enhanced Care Group

(a) Usual Care Group
Participants in the Usual Care Group will receive the usual standard-of-care as provided by their GP and Cardiologists.  Usual care advice and treatment for people with CHF typically involves patient education (eg, importance of daily weight monitoring, fluid restriction monitoring), daily monitoring of body weight, and visits to their GP or other health care providers according to their self-assessment.     As per the usual standard-of-care, patients in the Usual Care Group will be required to monitor their weight on a daily basis and record their weight measurements in a weight diary.  The study team will provide the Usual Care Group with an electronic weight scale with memory for self-monitoring.   The data gathered in the weight scale will be stored in the scales memory and extracted at regular intervals by the research team over a 12 month period. 

(b) Enhanced Care Group
Participants in the Enhanced Care Group will receive a revised model of the usual standard care for chronic heart failure patients as provided by their GP and Cardiologist.   As per the usual standard-of-care, patients in the Enhanced Care Group will be required to monitor their weight on a daily basis.  The Enhanced Care Group will be provided with an electronic weight scale (with memory); however the weight measurements will be recorded in real time via remote monitoring over a 12 month period. 

Participants in the both groups will also complete a series of assessments at baseline, 6-months and 12-months which will involve:   

*	Collection of demographic details 
*	Previous clinical history
*	Risk factor assessment
*	Quality of life assessment
*	Functional or physical capacity
*	Health behaviours
*	Medication management
*	Symptoms 
*	Participant usability evaluation questionnaire (at 12 months only)

</interventions>
    <comparator>As per the usual standard-of-care, patients in the Control Group will be required to monitor and log their weight on a daily basis over 12 months.  To obtain an objective measure of the frequency of weight measurement in the trial patients, the study team will provide the Control Group with an electronic weight scale for self-monitoring.   The data gathered in the weight scale will be stored in memory and downloaded at three monthly intervals by the research team. 

The comparator being studied is the compliance rate of daily weight monitoring and recording of patients in the Control Group compared with the Intervention Group.   The aim is to investigate if there is an improvement in daily weight compliance in the Intervention Group compared with the Control Group. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Compliance rate of daily weight monitoring in Enhanced Care Group versus Usual Care Group.  The patient weight data will be collected from the electronic weight scale and downloaded at regular intervals by the research team.  For the Control Group this will be done manually by the research team at three monthly intervals.  For the Intervention Group this will be done automatically after each weight measurement by the remote monitoring system. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint:  at one year after randomisation as assessed by daily weight measurements between the Enhanced Care Group and Usual Care Group.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Hospital re-admission rate of patients as assessed by data linkage to medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 6-12 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Mortality rate of patients as assessed by data linkage to medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 6-12 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Risk factor management by patients as assessed by data linkage to medical records (eg. hospital admission rate and length of stay) and patient assessment tools including:
(1) Quality of Life Assessments:  EQ-5D-5L Questionnaire and Cardiac Depression Scale.
(2) Self-Management Assessments: Heart Failure Compliance Questionnaire
(3) Physical Capacity Assessments: The Six Minute Walk Test and Clinical Frailty Scale
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 6-12 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: 
Symptoms management by patients as assessed by data linkage to medical records (eg. hospital admission rate and length of stay) and patient assessment tools.

1) Quality of Life Assessments:

a) EQ-5D-5L Health Questionnaire is a questionnaire which asks about health related quality of life.  It asks about patient mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression.



b) The Cardiac Depression Scale assesses depression in adult cardiac populations.  It asks several questions about the sleep patterns and general mood of patients with cardiac problems. 

2) Self-Management Assessments:

a) The Heart Failure Compliance Questionnaire asks for the patients view about how well they follow their medical treatments.  This information helps keep track of how much difficulty a patient has with specific lifestyle behaviours, such as taking medications regularly.  

3) Physical Capacity Assessments:

a) The Six Minute Walk Test measures the distance an individual is able to walk over a total of six minutes on a hard, flat surface. The goal is for the individual to walk as far as possible in six minutes. The test is used evaluate the functional capacity of patients with Chronic Heart Failure.


b) The Clinical Frailty Scale categorises frailty based on physical and functional indicators or health, such as mobility and function, with scores that range from 1 (very fit) to 9 (terminally ill).  

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 6-12 months after randomisation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 5: Medication compliance by patients as assessed by data linkage to medical records (eg. hospital admission rate and length of stay) and patient assessment tools.
a) The Heart Failure Compliance Questionnaire asks for the patients view about how well they follow their medical treatments.  This information helps keep track of how much difficulty a patient has with specific lifestyle behaviours, such as taking medications regularly.  

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 6-12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life of patients as assessed by patient quality of life assessment tools, including:

 a) EQ-5D-5L Health Questionnaire is a questionnaire which asks about health related quality of life.  It asks about patient mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression.

b) The Cardiac Depression Scale assesses depression in adult cardiac populations.  It asks several questions about the sleep patterns and general mood of patients with cardiac problems. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 6-12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychosocial status of patients as assessed by patient quality of life assessment tools, including:

a) EQ-5D-5L Health Questionnaire is a questionnaire which asks about health related quality of life.  It asks about patient mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression.

b) The Cardiac Depression Scale assesses depression in adult cardiac populations.  It asks several questions about the sleep patterns and general mood of patients with cardiac problems. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 6-12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will be patients diagnosed with chronic heart failure. Inclusion criteria are that the participants must:

1.	Diagnosed as having chronic heart failure by a clinician 
2.	Be able to weigh themselves safely
3.	At least 18 years of age
4.	Have regular GP/agree to use GP designated by the patient
5.	Have permanent residential address
6.	Able to individually consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will not be eligible for participation in the project if they 

1.	Have life expectancy less than12 months
2.	Have end stage renal failure on dialysis
3.	Are long term nursing home resident
4.	Have severe cognitive impairment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once patients have signed the Consent Form, they will be provided with a blank envelope by the research nurse containing their designated trial group (Enhanced Care Group or Usual Care Group). The envelope contents will be pre-prepared by CSIRO’s Australian e-Health Research Centre.  

The envelopes will be blank, to ensure that the allocation process is concealed from the person requesting consent (i.e. the research nurse). However, the patient will notify the research nurse which group they have been randomised to, in order to facilitate further care planning.  

</concealment>
    <sequence>The envelope contents will be pre-prepared by CSIRO’s Australian e-Health Research Centre, using a permutated block randomisation system</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Objective:  Evaluate the compliance rate in weight management (number of patients weighting themselves daily / number of patients incompliant with this requirement) between the Enhanced Care Group Group (A0) than Usual Care Group (A1) in the trial.

Allocation Ratio: 1:1 (RCT)

Null hypothesis (H0): the compliance rate in A0 is equal to the rate in A1

Setup variables:

Power (1- Beta): 80% 	(Type II error, false negative)

Statistical Significance Level (a): 5% (Type I error, false positive)

Assumption: Assume we know the following two variables from literature

1.Compliance rate in the Enhanced Care Group is 80%. 
2.Compliance rate in the Usual Care Group is 64%. 
3.Completion rate for analysis (some patients drop out or are discharged due to mortality) is 90%.

Results: The calculated sample size is 148 patients in each group. 



A Chi-squared test will be used to analyse dichotomous data with large sizes, such as the compliance, and readmission. ANOVA will be applied to analyse continuous data such weight variations. A Fishers exact test will be employed, if data size of some measures is small. A Cox proportional hazards model will be performed to analyse the risk of mortality. The influence of risk factors such as aging will be considered in the analysis, and 95% confidence intervals will be estimated</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Frankston Hospital - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Rosebud Hospital - Rosebud</hospital>
    <hospital>St John of God Nepean Rehabilitation Hospital - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>3939 - Rosebud</postcode>
    <postcode>6102 - Bentley</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peninsula Health </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 52
Frankston, VIC, 3199
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of State Development, Business and Innovation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>121 Exhibition Street, Melbourne, Vic, 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Medtech Global</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 2
180 Albert Road
South Melbourne VIC  3205
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>CSIRO (The Australian e-Health Research Centre)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 5, UQ Health Sciences Building
Bowen Bridge Rd
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Hertson  QLD  4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of the clinical trial is to demonstrate that monitoring of weight improves the compliance rate of CHF patients to self-monitor their daily weight, as well as potentially improved quality of life, enhanced management of risk factors and medication, increased cost benefits and reduced hospital readmissions.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peninsula Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 52
Frankston VIC 3199</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC14PH27</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St John of God HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, St John of God House, 
177-179 Cambridge St, 
WEMBLEY WA 6014
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC#779</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance
 Level 3, Colonial House
 Royal Perth Hospital
 Wellington Street, PERTH WA 6000
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>15-081</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Iain Edwards</name>
      <address>Director, Integrated Care &amp; Dental 
Rosebud Community Health
38 Braidwood Avenue
ROSEBUD VIC  3939
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5986 9265</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5986 9251</fax>
      <email>iainedwards@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Iain Edwards</name>
      <address>Director, Integrated Care &amp; Dental 
Rosebud Community Health
38 Braidwood Avenue
ROSEBUD VIC  3939
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5986 9265</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5986 9251</fax>
      <email>iainedwards@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hang Ding</name>
      <address>The Australian E-Health Research Centre (CSIRO)
Level 5, UQ Health Sciences Building 901/16
Bowen Bridge Rd
Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital
Brisbane  QLD  4029
</address>
      <phone> +61 7 3253 3623</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hang.ding@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alison Dowling</name>
      <address>Peninsula Health
PO Box 52 (8-10 Dundas St)
Frankston  VIC  3199</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9784 8962</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ADowling@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>