<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366625">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000755639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Thiamine to improve stem cell function in patients undergoing bypass surgery: a randomised controlled trial
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial comparing high-dose thiamine to placebo in patients undergoing coronary artery bypass surgery with proliferation of resident cardiac progenitor cells as measured by bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) assay as primary outcome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1158-2217 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Coronary artery disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Thiamine two 500mg capsules twice daily for 3-5 days prior to surgery. Treatment starts after the surgical list for the following week has been finalised and continues until the day before surgery. Adherence and adverse effects of treatment will be monitored by a pill count, questionnaire and blood tests prior to surgery.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (maltodextrin) two 500mg capsules twice daily for 3-5 days prior to surgery. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resident cardiac progenitor cell proliferation as measured by BrdU assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of coronary artery bypass grafting</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability of resident cardiac progenitor cells to differentiate into cardiomyocytes, as measured by the number of GATA-4 and connexin-43 positive cells after exposure to differentiation medium</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of coronary artery bypass surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of activation of pentose phosphate pathway as measured by the level of transketolase in resident cardiac progenitor cells</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of coronary artery bypass surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Circulating thiamine levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of coronary artery bypass surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse effects assessment: headache, nausea, irritability, insomnia, rapid pulse, muscle weakness. These are assessed by interview and examination of vital signs.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3 (and day 4 if applicable) of being on study medication.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Patients listed for inpatient coronary artery bypass surgery due to atherosclerotic coronary artery disease and
2.	Aged 50 years and over and
3.	Left ventricular systolic function normal on echocardiography (ejection fraction more than or equal to 50%) performed during this inpatient stay (or within three months if no myocardial infarction has occurred between date of echocardiogram and date of enrollment).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Left ventricular systolic function impaired (echocardiographic ejection fraction &lt; 50%) or
2.	Renal failure with creatinine &gt; 200 umol/l or requiring renal replacement therapy or
3.	Already taking thiamine supplementation or
4.	Previously had an adverse reaction to thiamine, or a supplement or medication containing thiamine or
5.	Previous or current history of alcohol related problems. This refers to a previous diagnosis of a medical condition thought to be caused or exacerbated by alcohol, or harmful use of alcohol (International Classification of Diseases version 10 codes F10.0 to F10.9) or
6.	Other major medical conditions that, in the opinion of the investigator, would make randomisation of the participant to thiamine unsafe or undesirable.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Numbered containers determined by computer-based randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation according to randomization.com</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A standard two-tailed t-test will be used to compare the primary outcome between treated and non-treated groups, using an intention-to-treat analysis. Separate analysis of the primary outcomes stratified by diabetic status will be performed using a t-test. 
For secondary analyses, differences across multiple groups will be assessed using an analysis of variance (ANOVA) test followed by a Sidak-Holm multiple comparison test. Comparison between two groups will be assessed using t-tests. 

Pre-specified subgroup analysis is according to diabetic status.

The sample size has been calculated to provide more than 90% power in the subgroups to detect a two-tailed 30% difference in primary outcome with treatment at a significance level of 0.05.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
Dunedin School of Medicine
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lottery Health Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Local Government and Community Branch
Department of Internal Affairs
PO Box 805
Wellington 6140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cardiac dysfunction is common in patients undergoing coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) surgery. The hearts intrinsic regenerative capability is related to the presence and function of resident cardiac stem cells, but there are limited ways of improving this capability. We have shown that thiamine analogues increase the profileration of resident cardiac stem cells in-vitro, by stimulating the pentose phosphate pathway. In addtion, we have shown that patients with type 2 diabetes have reduced number and less proliferation of resident cardiac stem cells, due to dysfunction of the pentose phosphate pathway. We aim to translate these findings to humans, by randomising patients undergoing CABG surgery to either short-term high dose thiamine or placebo, with a primary endpoint of the ability of resident cardiac stem cells to proliferate. In addition to the valuable findings of the trial itself, if we show that this approach is successful, this study could directly be used to design a larger clinical outcome driven randomised control trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/o Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Williams</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology,
7th Floor, Dunedin Hospital
201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 474 0999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.williams@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mary Blok</name>
      <address>Research Nurse
Department of Cardiology
9th Floor, Dunedin Hospital
201 Great King Street
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 474 0999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cardiology.research@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sean Coffey</name>
      <address>Room B15, Level 0
Cardiac Investigations Annexe
John Radcliffe Hospital
Headley Way
Oxford 
OX3 9DU</address>
      <phone>+44 1865 741166</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sean.coffey@ouh.nhs.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>