<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83559">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000257268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The first randomised, controlled clinical trial of surgical masks compared to fit-tested and non-fit tested N95 masks in the prevention of respiratory virus infection in hospital health care workers in Beijing, China.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised control trial of health care workers using N95 and surgical masks in prevention of clinical and viral respiratory infection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Clinical and viralogical respiratory infection amongst hospital health care workers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: Surgical masks (Arm 1), N95 masks (fit tested, Arm 2), N95 masks (not fit tested, Arm 3), Control (No masks, Arm 4)
Participants will be provided with surgical masks or N95 masks, (depending on which hospital they work in) to be worn for four weeks when working on the ward. Masks will be worn when participants are working in the emergency department or respiratory ward; they will be allowed to remove the mask when: (1) they exit the department/ward; and (2) enter the tea room for meal breaks. 
Subjects recruited to Arm 2 will have the masks correctly fit-tested using a 3M (trademark) FT-30 Bitrex Fit Test Kit according to the manufacturers instructions (3M, St Paul, Minnesota (MN), USA). This kit uses a nebulized solution sprayed into an enclosed chamber and relies on the subject tasting the solution through the mask. If the subject is able to taste the solution, the mask is incorrectly fitted and needs to be re-fitted until the subject cannot taste the solution.
All participants will be followed up for five weeks (which includes four weeks of wearing the masks and an extra week of non-mask wearing)</interventions>
    <comparator>No masks</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical respiratory infection
Outcome will be assessed through daily monitoring by study staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for five weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Laboratory confirmed viral respiratory infection</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for five weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence with mask use, and variance in adherence with duration of enrolment.
Outcome will be assessed through daily monitoring by study staff and by the use of a daily diary completed by the participant</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for four weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time from recruitment of an enrolled subject to infection with an clinical respiratory infection
Outcome will be assessed through daily monitoring by study staff</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for five weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any nurse or doctor who works full time in the selected ward at the study hospitals in Beijing, China.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability or refusal to consent
Males with beards, long moustaches or long facial hair stubble 
Clinical staff with a current respiratory illness, rhinitis and/or allergy 
Part-time worker
Does not work on the abovementioned wards</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study was cluster randomised with the hospital being the unit of randomisation. Health workers in emergency, paediatric and respiratory wards were included. The study coordinator provided information about the study and recruited participants. Consenting staff were evaluated for signs and symptoms of influenza at baseline (against a checklist of standard signs and symptoms used for defining clinical respiratory illness (CRI)). Eligible subjects were then be randomized to the intervention arms (Surgical masks, N95 (fit tested), N95 (non fit tested). Blinding was not possible because of the nature of the intervention, however, laboratory testing will be blinded. Controls were selected prospectively from a convenience sample of health care workers in hospitals where mask wearing was uncommon. This is because mask wearng is very common in Beijing, and a control arm was unacceptable to health workers in most hospitals.
Recruitment commenced on December 1st 2008.
Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation program was designed in Microsoft access</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cluster randomised controlled trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/12/2008</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/12/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1441</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Beijing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Samuels Building, University of New South Wales
Botany St
Randwick, 2031
NSW, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Samuels Building, University of New South Wales
Botany St
Randwick, 2031
NSW, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Beijing Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>No. 16 He Pingli Middle Street, Dong Cheng District, Beijing, 100013, China</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Westmead Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Institute of Clinical Pathology and Medical Research (ICPMR), Westmead Hospital, Westmead,
NSW, Australia 2145</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the study is to determine the efficacy of surgical masks compared to fit tested and non-fit tested N95 masks in health care workers in the prevention of influenza and other respiratory viruses.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>MacIntyre, C.R., Wang, Q., Cauchemez, S., Seale, H., Dwyer, D.E., Yang, P., Shi, W., Gao, Z., Pang, X., Zhang, Y., Wang, X., Duan, W., Rahman, B., Ferguson, N. A cluster randomized clinical trial comparing fit-tested and non-fit-tested N95 respirators to medical masks to prevent respiratory virus infection in health care workers. (2011) Influenza and other Respiratory Viruses, 5 (3), pp. 170-179

MacIntyre CR, Wang Q, Rahman B, Seale H, Ridda I, Gao Z, Yang P, Shi W, Pang X, Zhang Y, Moa A, Dwyer DE.  Efficacy of face masks and respirators in preventing upper respiratory tract bacterial colonization and co-infection in hospital healthcare workers.  Preventive Medicine 2014. 62, pp. 1-7.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Beijing Center for Disease Prevention and Control Medical Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No. 16 He Pingli Middle Street, Dong Cheng District, Beijing, 100013, China</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/2/2</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/07/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Raina MacIntyre</name>
      <address>Samuels Building, University of New South Wales
Botany St
Randwick, 2031
NSW, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 3811</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9313 6185</fax>
      <email>r.macintyre@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Holly Seale</name>
      <address>Samuels Building, University of New South Wales
Botany St
Randwick, 2031
NSW, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 3129</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9313 6185</fax>
      <email>h.seale@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Holly Seale</name>
      <address>Samuels Building, University of New South Wales
Botany St
Randwick, 2031
NSW, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 3129</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9313 6185</fax>
      <email>h.seale@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Raina MacIntyre</name>
      <address>Samuels Building, University of New South Wales Botany St Randwick, 2031 NSW, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 2517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.macintyre@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>