<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370664">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000640404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The 3-Day Malarone Schedule: Acceptability and Tolerability for Malaria Prophylaxis in Adults Travelling to Malaria Endemic Areas.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The 3-Day Malarone Schedule: Acceptability and Tolerability for Malaria Prophylaxis in Adults Travelling to Malaria Endemic Areas</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The trial will assess the use of a 3-day schedule of Atovaquone-Proguanil (250/100mg per tablet) for malaria prophylaxis.  The modified schedule involves taking 4 tablets per day for 3 consecutive days to provide protection for one month.  The 3-day schedule will be completed at least 2-5 days prior to leaving Australia, depending on duration of travel, itinerary, and convenience. A travel medicine nurse will contact the traveller by phone prior to departure from Australia to monitor adherence to the recommended schedule. If a traveller is unable to tolerate the 3-day schedule, alternative malaria chemoprophylaxis will be arranged prior to departure. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability of the 3-day schedule of Atovaquone-Proguanil for malaria prophylaxis.  Tolerability will be assessed using a memory aid and symptom diary (4-point Likert Scale) to record the frequency and severity of adverse events. </outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after travellers return from overseas travel to malaria-endemic area.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the 3-day schedule of Atovaquone-Proguanil for malaria prophylaxis.  Acceptability will be assessed during post-travel telephone interviews to be conducted by travel health nurses.  Travellers will be asked if they would choose to take the 3-day Malarone schedule again if travelling to another malaria endemic area in the future, and the reasons for their decision including considerations related to convenience and cost. </outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after travellers return from overseas travel to malaria-endemic area.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with the 3-day schedule of Atovaquone-Proguanil for malaria prophylaxis.  Compliance will be assessed during pre-travel telephone interviews to be conducted by travel health nurses.  Nurses will call each traveller prior to departure to ask whether the 3-day schedule of tablets had been taken properly. If not, the reasons for non-compliance will be ascertained. If travellers were unable to complete the 3-day schedule because of adverse events, alternative chemoprophylaxis will be arranged prior to travel. </outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after travellers return from overseas travel to malaria-endemic area.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of adverse events from 3-day schedule of Malarone.  The most common adverse events include nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, diarrhoea, headache, and mouth ulcers.  Adverse events will be assessed using a 4-point Likert Scale in a symptom diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One week after travellers return from overseas travel to malaria-endemic area.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Over 18 years of age
2. Travelling to a malaria-endemic area in Asia, Pacific Islands, and South/Central
America for 4 weeks or less
3. Able to give written Informed Consent and sign consent after all aspects of the
protocol explained
4. Subject must agree to participate in all planned follow-up telephone reviews, and to
return their Memory Aid and Diary to their travel clinic.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previous adverse reactions to Malarone
2. Taking other medications that adversely interact with Malarone (metoclopramide,
rifampicin and tetracyclines may decrease the efficacy of Atovaquone; fluvoxamine may
decrease the efficacy of Proguanil).
3. Pregnancy or planning pregnancy.
4. Significant medical conditions including diabetes, heart problems, asthma, epilepsy,
depression, renal impairment, gastrointestinal disorders, and those taking long-term
antibiotics.
5. Travelling to highly endemic countries with a high risk of malaria, e.g Sub-Saharan
Africa.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>222</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Colleen Lau</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Global Health
Research School of Population Health
Australian National University, 
Building 62, Mills Road
Canberra, ACT 0200

Postal address:
Dr Colleen Lau
P O Box 2726,
New Farm, QLD 4005</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Unfunded</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>N/A</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Deborah Mills</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dr Deb The Travel Doctor
5th Floor, 247 Adelaide St,
Brisbane, QLD 4000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms Lani Ramsay</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Travel-Bug Vaccination Clinic
182 Ward St
Adelaide, SA 5006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Andrew Ebringer</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Senior Medical Director
International SOS 
Level 27, 288 Edward St
Brisbane, QLD 4000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Malaria is one of the most common causes of fever in Australian travellers, with approximately 400 cases reported each year in Australia. In addition, some travellers develop malaria and seek treatment while overseas, and are not included in these reported numbers. Most travellers who develop malaria did not take anti-malarial medications, or did not take the medications properly (e.g. forgot to take tablets). Malaria is a serious illness, and could potentially be life-threatening if not treated promptly. Antimalarial medications reduce the risk of malaria by about 90%, and the most commonly used options in Australia are Malarone, Doxycycline, and Mefloquine (Lariam). This research project aims to reduce the risk of malaria in travellers by improving compliance with anti-malarial medications. We propose to test the acceptability and tolerability of a 3-day schedule of a malaria medication called Malarone. Currently, travellers are required to take Malarone daily, starting 2 days before travel to a malaria risk area and continuing until 7 days after leaving the area. With the 3-day schedule, travellers will only need to take medications for 3 days and be protected for 4 weeks. The schedule will likely improve compliance and therefore reduce the risk of malaria. For trips that are of 4 weeks duration or less, travellers will be able to complete their antimalarial medications before leaving home, and not worry about carrying or taking tablets during their trip.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The Malarone tablets will be paid for by each individual traveller (or their employer for work-related trips), just as travellers would normally pay for any malaria chemoprophylaxis.  This study has not received funding for medications from the clinics, doctors, researchers, pharmaceutical companies, or any other third parties. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, Australian National University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Integrity &amp; Compliance,
Research Services,
Ground Floor, Chancelry 10B
Ellery Crescent,
The Australian National University
ACTON ACT 2601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016087</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370664-2016087_Lau_Study Protocol_3MT.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Colleen Lau</name>
      <address>Department of Global Health
Research School of Population Health
Australian National University
Building 62, Mills Road
Canberra, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 402134878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>colleen.lau@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Colleen Lau</name>
      <address>Department of Global Health
Research School of Population Health
Australian National University
Building 62, Mills Road
Canberra, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 402134878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>colleen.lau@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Colleen Lau</name>
      <address>Department of Global Health
Research School of Population Health
Australian National University
Building 62, Mills Road
Canberra, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 402134878</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>colleen.lau@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>