<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364397">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000674730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does a supervised exercise program for claudication have an adverse effect on immune, muscle and
endothelial function?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with symptomatic lifestyle limiting intermittent claudication, does a 12 week treadmill based supervised exercise program result in changes in endothelial function, body composition and energy expenditure, monocyte subpopulations, apoptosis in muscles, lactadherin expression, and microRNA 92-a expression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1144-2088</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peripheral artery disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intermittent Claudication</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study participants will be identified through the regional claudication clinic and referred to a 12 week exercise program if suitable. Participants will undertake 1 hour of supervised treadmill exercise, twice per week for 12 weeks. The exercise will consist of walking on a treadmill at a speed and incline to bring on leg pain caused by intermittent claudication within 3-5 min. Participants will walk until the point of near maximal pain as per current consensus guidelines. Participants will also be prescribed current best medical therapy and receive advice on smoking cessation. For the first six weeks of the program, six consecutive lectures (30min once per week) by a vascular nurse (Topic: Basics of PAD), physiotherapist (Topic: The benefits of exercise), pharmacist (Topic: Understanding your medications), dietitian (Topic: Eating for cardiovascular health), occupational therapist (Topic: Goal setting, work simplification), and podiatrist (Topic: The importance of foot care.) will be presented.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A - This is a single group study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking performance measured by pain-free walking distance and 6-minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of apoptosis in symptomatic muscles using Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) staining for apoptotic nuclei on formalin fixed paraffin-embedded muscle biopsies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Local and whole body skeletal muscle and fat mass using Dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting energy expenditure measured using indirect calorimetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportions of classical, intermediate and non-classical monocytes in peripheral blood using a FACSCanto II flow cytometer. Monocytes will be identified using a gating strategy incorporating side-scatter properties, CD86 and CD45 positivity. Sub-populations will be identified by setting quadrant gates on a CD14 and CD16 dot plot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0, Day 21 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of expression of lactadherin mRNA and protein in symptomatic skeletal muscle using reverse transcription real-time PCR and Western blot assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of expression of microRNA-92a in symptomatic skeletal muscle using reverse transcription real-time PCR</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using Australian vascular quality of life index (AUSVIQUOL) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EndoPAT reactive hyperaemia index (RHI) using Itmar EndoPAT 2000</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Flow mediated dilatation (FMD) is measured using a SonoSite M-Turbo portable ultrasound and high resolution linear array to visualize the distal brachial artery after temporary forearm ischemia induced by inflating a manual sphygmomanometer cuff to 260mmHg for 5min. Following cuff deflation, the brachial artery dilatation is measured for 3min  and is later analysed using the Brachial Artery Analyser software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 and Day 90</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Symptomatic peripheral arterial disease, namely intermittent calf claudication caused by PAD defined by imaging and ankle-brachial pressure index.
Informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No symptomatic peripheral artery disease (normal ABPI or imaging).
Thigh and buttock claudication.
Exercise tolerance limited by neurological, cardio-pulmonary or rheumatological disability.
Therapeutic anticoagulation or blood dyscrasias. 
Post menopausal women on hormone replacement therapy.
Premenopausal women
Critical limb ischemia (rest pain or tissue loss)
Inability to provide informed consent
Patients with recent (&lt;12 months) history of peripheral vascular interventions for symptoms
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients are enrolled from the claudication clinic at the Repatriation General Hospital. This clinic receives referrals from the Adelaide Southern Health area for vascular surgical opinion of lower limb claudication symptoms. Patients deemed to potentially benefit from a supervised exercise program are offered enrollment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non-randomised trial</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Results will be expressed as mean +/- SD. Differences in response to the exercise or training will be assessed with the paired t-test. Statistical significance will be accepted at p-value less than 0.05.

From out unit's experience mean change in pain free walking distance (PFWD) following our 12-week SEP was 44m (SD 80m). For paired t-test analysis with an alpha level of 0.05 and statistical power of 0.8 the required sample size is approximately 26. This is similar to sample size calculations based on published data indicating a range from 6 to 26</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Repatriation Hospital - Daw Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Vascular Surgery, Flinders Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 5042
SA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 5042
SA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Simon Vun
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 5042
SA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with lifestyle limiting intermittent claudication will be offered, in addition to best medical therapy, participation in a 12-week supervised exercise program consisting of two 1 hour sessions per week. The exercise prescription will be based on current evidence of treadmill walking to near maximal pain. They will also undergo two key assessments at baseline (day 0) and at day 90. This will consist of measurement of walking performance (PFWD and 6MWD), body composition (DEXA), resting energy expenditure (calorimetry), endothelial function (FMD and EndoPAT), monocytes and subpopulations (flow cytometry), levels of apoptosis, lactadherin mRNA and protein expression and microRNA-92a expression in ischemic and non-ischemic muscles of the symptomatic leg. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Flats G5  Rooms 3 and 4
Flinders Drive
Flinders Medical Centre, Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>139.10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Spark</name>
      <address>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 5042
SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5445</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 7106</fax>
      <email>Ian.Spark@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Vun</name>
      <address>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 5042
SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 2116</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 7106</fax>
      <email>simon.vun@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Vun</name>
      <address>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 5042
SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 2116</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 7106</fax>
      <email>simon.vun@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Simon Vun</name>
      <address>Department of Vascular Surgery
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park 5042
SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 2116</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 7106</fax>
      <email>simon.vun@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>