<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83427">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/12/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000644369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 2a, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicenter study to evaluate the efficacy, safety, and tolerability of BG00012 when given with methotrexate to subjects with active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to conventional disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drug therapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2a, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicenter study to evaluate the efficacy, safety, and tolerability of BG00012 when given with methotrexate to subjects with active rheumatoid arthritis who have had an inadequate response to conventional disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drug therapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>EUDRA CT No. 2008-004754-33</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rheumatoid arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention (All groups)
Methotrexate as a stabilised treatment regimen between greater than or equal to 7.5mg per week to less than or equal to 25mg per week, as prescribed by their rheumatologist or general care physician. Dosage form either oral or injectable but cannot change through week 12.  The dosage may be decreased if required due to toxicity.

Intervention Group 1
BG00012 240 mg twice daily orally and placebo once daily orally for 12 weeks

Intervention Group 2
BG00012 240 mg 3 times daily orally for 12 weeks</interventions>
    <comparator>Intervention (All groups)
Methotrexate as a stabilised treatment regimen between greater than or equal to 7.5mg per week to less than or equal to 25mg per week, as prescribed by their rheumatologist or general care physician. Dosage form either oral or injectable but cannot change through week 12.  The dosage may be decreased if required due to toxicity.

Control group
Placebo sugar capsule (contains lactose) 3 times daily orally for 12 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: clinical efficacy of BG00012 with methotrexate; specifically, the American College of Rheumatology (ACR20) response. To achieve ACR20 response, a 20% improvement compared to baseline is required for both
swollen and tender joint counts, as well as 3 out of 5 additional parameters: Subject's Global Assessment of Disease Activity, Investigator's Global Assessment of Disease Activity, subject's assessment of pain, Health Assessment Questionnaire-Disability Index (HAQ-DI), and high sensitivity C-reactive protein (hsCRP) or erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of subjects with an American College of Rheumatology (ACR50 and ACR70) response grading</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes from baseline in the individual ACR core set parameters including swollen and tender joint counts, Subject/Investigator Global Assessment of disease activity, Health Assessment Questionnaire-Disability Index and subject's assessment of pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the proportion of subjects with a categorical Disease Activity Score, 28-joint version
(DAS28) response (European League Against Rheumatism [EULAR] response)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the change from baseline Disease Activity Score, 28-joint version (DAS28)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the change from baseline in Quality of Life measures including; Health Assessment Quesstionnaire Disability Index, Short Form 36 questionnaire (SF-36), Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue questionnaire (FACIT-F)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety of BG00012 with methotrexate in this population.  Measures include; physical examinations, vital signs, electrocardiogram (ECG), laboratory parameters including haematology, blood chemistry and urinalysis and monitoring for adverse events, serious adverse events and concomitant therapies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the tolerability of BG00012 with methotrexate in this population. Measures include; physical examinations, vital signs, electrocardiogram (ECG), laboratory parameters including haematology, blood chemistry and urinalysis and monitoring for adverse events, serious adverse events and concomitant therapies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Written informed consent
- Diagnosis of adult onset RA according to the 1987 Revised American Rheumatism Association Criteria for the Classification of Rheumatoid Arthritis (Functional Class I  III)(Section22, Appendix A) for at least 6 months prior to Day 0.
- Must have been treated with, and be tolerating, methotrexate for at least 3 months immediately prior to Day 0.  The dose of mthotrexate must be stable for at least 4 weeks prior to Day 0.
- All subjects of child-bearing potential must practice effective contraception during the study and be willing and able to continue contraception for 1 month after their last dose of study treatment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Medical History
1. Subjects with a history of malignant disease, including solid tumors and haematologic malignancies (except basal cell and squamous cell carcinomas of the skin that have been completely excised and are considered cured).
2. History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions or known drug hypersensitivity.
3. History of clinically significant (as determined by the Investigator) cardiac, endocrinologic, pulmonary, neurologic, psychiatric, hepatic, renal or hematologic insufficiency, or any major disease that could affect any of the efficacy assessments, in particular, joint pain and swelling (e.g., Parkinsons disease, cerebral palsy, diabetic neuropathy).
4. Known active bacterial, viral, fungal, mycobacterial, opportunistic infection or other infection (including atypical mycobacterial disease, but excluding fungal infections of nail beds) or any major episode of infection requiring hospitalization or treatment with intravenous (IV) antibiotics within 4 weeks of Day 0.
5. Nursing mothers, pregnant women, or women who are planning to become pregnant while in the study.
Treatment History
6. Other clinical issues or laboratory results that, in the opinion of the Investigator or Biogen Idec, make the subject unsuitable for enrollment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization will take place across all study sites using a centralized Interactive Voice Response System.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will take place across all study sites using a centralized Interactive Voice Response System. Subjects will be randomized after the Investigator has verified that they are eligible. Randomization will be stratified by screening rheumatoid factor (RF) status and region.  Subjects will be randomized to receive placebo, BG00012 480 mg/day, or BG00012 720 mg/day.  Subjects who are withdrawn from the study may be replaced.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5011</postcode>
    <postcode>4102</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Biogen Idec, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>14 Cambridge Center
Cambridge, MA 02142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Biogen Idec, Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>14 Cambridge Center
Cambridge, MA 02142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Biogen Idec Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Suite 2, Level 4
123 Epping Road
North Ryde NSW 2113</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BG00012 has been shown to be effective in reducing signs and symptoms of psoriasis and multiple sclerosis. BG00012 may be effective in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis (RA) as well. The present study will test this concept in subjects with RA who have not responded adequately to methotrexate (MTX), the standard first-line oral agent for this disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Atsumi Fukui</name>
      <address>Biogen Idec Australia
Suite 2, Level 4
123 Epping Road
North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61288753900</phone>
      <fax>+61298891162</fax>
      <email>atsumi.fukui@biogenidec.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Atsumi Fukui</name>
      <address>Biogen Idec Australia
Suite 2, Level 4
123 Epping Road
North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61288753900</phone>
      <fax>+61298891162</fax>
      <email>atsumi.fukui@biogenidec.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Scott Pilarski</name>
      <address>Biogen Idec Australia
Suite 2, Level 4
123 Epping Road
North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61288753900</phone>
      <fax>+61298891162</fax>
      <email>scott.pilarski@biogenidec.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>