<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371156">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001001482p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cannabidiol (CBD) for Cannabis and Mood Disorders in Adolescence (CCAMDA)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cannabidiol (CBD) for Cannabis and Mood Disorders in Adolescence (CCAMDA)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CCAMDA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mood disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cannabis use</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a double blind placebo controlled RCT consisting of two groups. An intervention and a control group. 
The intervention group will receive 800mg of CBD will be administered in 100mg capsules. Participants will be required to take 400mg (i.e. 4 capsules) of CBD twice a day (morning and night) approximately 12 hours apart for a 12 week treatment period. The active ingredient is fully synthetic (99.6% Cannabidiol powder dissolved in corn oil encapsulated in gelatine). It is the equivalent isomer of naturally occurring Cannabidiol. The active ingredient is produced at BioSynthesis Pharma Group FDA and MHRA approved facility in the UK. 
The matching placebo will be administered in capsules with same appearance and taste and participants will be required to take of the same number of capsules twice daily as participants in the active arm. 
All medications received and dispensed as part of this trial will be inventoried and accounted for throughout the trial on the Investigation Agent Accountability Record (study medication log) by the clinical trials pharmacists. The medication will be dispensed weekly for the first month, and then monthly after that. Patient compliance will be assessed through pill counts when participants return to receive their next lot of medication, as well as through self-report measures and the level of CBD in blood and urine from samples collected at baseline, week 2, week 6 and week 12. At the completion of each participants treatment period, any unused medications will be returned to the trial pharmacist, documented, and then subsequently destroyed.  
All participants will be provided with five 50 minute sessions of cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT), which are offered as part of the study by a trial therapist in the form of cognitive behavioural case management (CBCM), during the 12-week intervention period (approximately fortnightly). Depending on the participants needs, additional sessions may be provided. After the 12 week intervention period (or if any participant meets exit or withdrawal criteria), treatment as usual will be provided by Headspace clinicians. For the purposes of the study analyses, entry will be considered to be the date the participant commences the study medication. 
Participants will also be directed to the Reduce your use website as an adjunct to treatment, which contains six core modules, informed by the principles of cognitive behavioural therapy and motivational enhancement therapy. These are: 1) Feedback and Building Motivation; 2) Managing Smoking Urges and Withdrawal; 3) Changing Your Thinking; 4) Coping Strategies and Skill Enhancement; 5) Activities and Interpersonal Skills; and 6) Relapse Prevention and Lifestyle Changes. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The matching placebo will be administered in capsules with the  same appearance and taste as active participants (400 mg of glucose i.e. 4 capsules twice a day (800mg in total) approximately 12 hours apart for a 12 week treatment period) will be required to take of the same number of capsules twice daily as participants in the active arm. 
Control participants will be treated exactly as active participants and will also receive CBCM and reduce your use. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depressive symptoms from baseline to 12 weeks, assessed with the Quick Inventory of Depression Symptomology, Adolescent Version (QIDS-A17-C). The QIDS-A17-C has been shown to be a reliable tool for assessing adolescent depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline to 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported measures of cannabis use (quantity and frequency) with total days cannabis used (levels of cannabis use, and cannabis related problems at follow up). Cannabis use will be assessed at baseline (cannabis use during preceding 30 days) and at each month during treatment and at follow-up (6 months). The Timeline Followback Method (TLFB) will be used. 
Self-reported cannabis use will be corroborated with serial urinalysis of carboxy-CBD: creatinine ratio using Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (GC/MS) at baseline and each follow-up point.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly for 3 months and then at 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment completion, defined as completing 12 weeks of treatment with CBD under protocol conditions. 
This outcome is assessed by whether or not the patient has finished the full 12 week treatment period. Any exit before this time will be considered as incomplete treatment. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 week end of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>At treatment entry, urine profiles of cannabinoid metabolites (THC and its primary metabolite (THC-COOH) and CBD and its primary metabolite (CBD-7-oic acid)) from prior illicit cannabis use (measured at baseline) will be collected. The same measures will be repeated after CBD has been administered to participants (taken on week 1, 2, 6 and 12). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 1, 2, 6 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether there is evidence of an interaction with the efficacy of CBD and mental health outcomes at end of treatment. This is a composite secondary outcome which will be assessed through;; CPQ, Kessler Psychological Distress Scale, Self-Efficacy for Quitting Cannabis Questionnaire, Overall Anxiety Severity and Impairment Scale, Generalised Anxiety Disorder Assessment, Alcohol Smoking and Substance Involvement Screening Test, Dietary Questionnaire for Epidemiological Studies (Version 2), Altman self-report mania screen, Structural Clinical Interview for Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-V) Axis I Disorders, patient version, Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale, Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS; baseline and since last visit), Comprehensive Assessment of At-Risk Mental State (CAARMS), Young Mania Rating Scale, Social and Occupational Functioning Scale, Clinical Global Impressions Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 week end of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events during the treatment period. This will be assessed by a self-report Adverse Events Checklist administered by a clinician during assessment.
An adverse event is any untoward event that may inconvenience a study participant, staff member or other individual. The event may or may not be related to the treatment received within the framework of the study. This includes the onset of new illnesses and the exacerbation of pre-existing conditions. Additionally, any event that is associated with or observed in conjunction with a product overdose (whether accidental or intentional) or a product abuse and/or withdrawal is also considered an adverse event.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 week end of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. At least 16 years of age &amp; less than 26 years of age at presentation.
2. Male
3. Cannabis use on average 3 days per week (over last 30 days) 
4. Help seeking for psychological distress
5. Moderate to severe depression, indicated by a score between 11 and 20 on the QIDS-A17-C64 at first contact with the service, and again after approximately 1 week
6. A diagnosis of a mood disorder with or without psychotic features at baseline using a structured clinical interview 
7. Fluency in English
8. Ability to give informed consent (for individuals under 18, written informed consent of at least one parent or guardian is required.)
9. Agree to participate in all scans and tests
10. Prepared to take trial medications as requested
11. Agreement to be available for follow-up interview at 6 months
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>26</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. More than weekly use of an illicit drug in the last 30 days (other than cannabis)
2. Female
3. Dependence on a substance other than cannabis and tobacco 
4. Specialist substance use treatment in the last 30 days; 
5. Acute suicidal behaviour or aggressive behaviour (indicated by a CAARMS49 score of 6 on relevant items)
6. Evidence of severe medical (including chronic pain, severe hepatic and or renal impairment or cardiovascular disease).
7. People with current prescriptions (within past month) for antipsychotic, mood stabilising medications (e.g. Lithium) or antidepressants. 
8. Known or suspected allergy to cannabinoids, propylene glycol, ethanol or peppermint oil;
9. Males who are planning on trying for a baby in the following 3 months.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to treatment will be concealed and carried out by a senior researcher uninvolved with the conduct of the intervention or participant assessment. Participants will be randomized to one of two possible treatment groups. The participants, treating clinicians, and research personnel (including research assistants, investigators and project manager) will remain blinded to treatment allocation until database lock. 
The Headspace access team will assist in identifying potential participants. Individuals will be assessed for eligibility at initial contact with Headspace by a clinician as part of routine clinical assessment. Once a participant is randomized, their treatment group allocation will be sent by the senior researcher via a previously prepared email to the trial pharmacist. Access to un-blinding will be available through the senior researcher and available and validated for emergency situations. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary analyses will be undertaken on an intention to treat basis, including all participants as randomized, regardless of treatment actually received. Effectiveness of CBD will be established using a planned contrast of change from baseline to week 12 end point in the active compared with placebo condition on the QIDS-A17-C within a mixed model repeated measure analysis. Stratification variables will be evaluated and retained in analyses where they are significant or quasi significant. Other relevant covariates may be included in the model to adjust for baseline and subsequent group differences. An unconstrained variance-covariance matrix will model within individual dependencies. Transformation of scores, including categorization, may be undertaken in order to meet distributional assumptions and accommodate outliers. Contrasts comparing change on the QIDS-A17-C from baseline to other time points will be undertaken as secondary analysis. Should the number of participants meeting exit/transition criteria be non-eligible (defined as greater than 5% in either treatment arm), transition rates and time to transition will be considered as secondary outcome and be subject to analysis using survival methods. Under these circumstances, analyses of continuous measures that treat exit as a competing outcome will be explored. 
Because this is a small Phase II drug trial, a small sample is needed in order to replicate the initial efficacy of the drug and confirm the absence of adverse drug effects.  This study will then form the basis of a further large scale RCT study into the efficacy of CBD for the management of mood disorders in cannabis smokers. 
Models for binary outcomes analogous to the primary analysis approach will be used to compare the remission rates (MDD status) and other dichotomous outcomes between the two treatment arms at endpoint and other occasions of measurement. Safety data will be compared between treatment arms  in particular the rates of harm and suicide related adverse events  using Fishers exact test. All tests will be conducted using a two sided alpha level of 0.05 and 95% confidence intervals. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>22-32 King Street Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Cannabis Prevention and Information Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>22-32 King Street Randwick NSW 2031</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Brain and Mind Centre, University of Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>94 Mallett St, Camperdown NSW 2050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objectives of the study is to examine the safety and efficacy of cannabidiol (CBD) in the management of mood disorders in adolescent/young adult males with concurrent cannabis use, in a randomized controlled study. Specifically, the study will assess the impact of CBD on mood treatment outcomes and retention rates, the quantity and frequency of cannabis use, and the impact of CBD on patient mental health outcomes and well-being. The study will also explore the cognitive and neurobiological markers associated with CBD response. 
Current treatments for anxiety and depression are of limited efficacy in a considerable proportion of patients (30% of depressed patients are pharmacoresistant) and are associated with troublesome side effects that reduce compliance; the development of novel, improved therapeutic treatments would fill a considerable unmet medical need. CBD has emerged as one of the most promising candidates in treating psychiatric disorders. Research suggests that greater rates of mental health problems in cannabis users are related to increased use of high THC/low CBD varieties of cannabis. In various animal and human laboratory and clinical studies, CBD has been found to reduce the intoxicating and psychotomimetic effects of THC, while CBD given alone has also been found to relieve anxiety and nausea and to have anti-inflammatory and antipsychotic effects.

All young males presenting to participating headspace centres will be screened for eligibility. Twenty participants will be recruited over a period of 6 months. Participants will complete an initial assessment with headspace staff as per normal clinical practice. Eligible participants will be contacted to attend a baseline assessment and consent at the Brain and Mind Centre. Participants will undergo a clinical assessment, provide blood and urine samples, and undergo an MRI. They will be randomized into either a CBD or placebo treatment group for a period of 12 weeks, with a 6 month follow-up. All participants will receive at least cognitive behavioural case management (CBCM) which includes 5 sessions of CBT with a therapist during the 12 week study period. More sessions are available if requested by the participant. All participants will also have access to and be encouraged to use reduce which is an automated website based on Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) and Motivational Interviewing (MI) principles that teach cannabis users the skills and techniques to assist them to cut back or cease their cannabis intake. Built into the program are additional skill building resources and quick assist links that allow participants to access additional information quickly.your use, both based on cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) and motivational interviewing (MI).  Participants will be assessed on symptoms of their mood disorders, retention in treatment and their cannabis use. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW Australia Human Research Ethics Advisory Panel</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW, Sydney, NSW, 2052, </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jan Copeland</name>
      <address>UNSW NCPIC 22-32 King Street Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93850231 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.copeland@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Izabella Pokorski</name>
      <address>UNSW NCPIC 22-32 King Street Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 89361139</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>i.pokorski@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Izabella Pokorski</name>
      <address>UNSW NCPIC 22-32 King Street Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 89361139</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>i.pokorski@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>