<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370357">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000376448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mobile Applications to Reduce Risk of Stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot randomised controlled trial to evaluate the Stroke Riskometer mobile phone application to improve stroke risk awareness and reduce risk of stroke and cardiovascular disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MARS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After participants are randomised into the intervention (Stroke Riskometer) group, a study RA will contact them and they will be provided a link to download the Stroke Riskometer Pro application on their mobile device. If required, they will be guided through the installation process to ensure that the app is working correctly on their device. After this they will be instructed to  open and use the app as they see fit. Participants will not be instructed on how many times they should use the app/how often to use it to determine "real world" usage. The application requires the user to answer 20 health and lifestyle related questions, after which it provides them with a 5 and 10 year risk of stroke. In addition, the users applicable risk factors are identified, and the management section of the app provides additional information on these risk factors and the steps the user can take to minimise their impact. At the end of the study, participants will be asked how often they used the application, as well as their general thoughts about the utility of the application. </interventions>
    <comparator>Those in the control group will continue to receive usual care (as applicable). Usual care for this study is defined as any ongoing care they were receiving at the start of the study, or any new health care interventions prescribed by their health professional while they were enrolled in the study. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in awareness about stroke risk and associated stroke risk factors. Participants will be asked to identify stroke symptoms and risk factors - and the percentage change in correct responses will be calculated. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in stroke risk. Participants complete the Stroke Riskometer questionnaire to measure their absolute 5 and 10 year stroke risk, and any change in the risk between baseline and follow-ups are measured. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in health behaviours related to stroke risk factors. Changes in the Life's Simple 7 health behaviour score are recorded to determine change in behaviour related to modifiable risk factors associated with stroke. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine feasibility of a full-scale RCT using the same intervention. A semi-structured qualitative interview will be used to ask participants about the acceptability of the intervention. This, in addition to the findings of the pilot trial will be used to inform the feasibility of conducting a full scale trial to investigate the efficacy of the Stroke Riskometer app as tool for primary stroke prevention</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) those screened with by their GP with at least 2 modifiable stroke risk factors identified; (2) those who own a Smartphone; (3) those who give informed consent to participate in the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>previous history of stroke, diagnosis of life-threatening conditions (as determined by GP), significant cognitive impairment or other conditions deemed unsuitable by their GP to participate in this research (e.g., psychiatric disorders, alcoholism).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Valery Feigin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote 0627
Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Tertiary Education, Skills and Employment funding reveived by Brain CoRE</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1666 
Wellington 6140 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke is a devastating yet highly preventable disease. There are about 9000 strokes every year in New Zealand, 30% of which are fatal in the first year and a further 70% of survivors are left with some level of disability. While the prevalence of behavioural and other modifiable risk factors of cardiovascular disease (CVD) including stroke has reached epidemic proportions worldwide, there is evidence that modifying health behaviours is feasible, improves health outcomes, reduces healthcare costs and can reduce an individuals risk of stroke by about 70%. However, the level of public awareness of stroke, its risk factors, and how to manage them is low, particularly in communities with low socioeconomic status, in ethnic minority groups and in rural areas. Preventing the occurrence of these conditions will allow individuals and their families to live longer, healthier and more productive lives. If shown to be effective, the Stroke Riskometer will improve peoples awareness about their risk of stroke, and enable better health behaviour to minimise their chances of having one.
This study aims to conduct a pilot randomised clinical trial to test the efficacy of the Stroke Riskometer mobile application (which was a validated tool developed by AUT University) at improving participants awareness about stroke risk factors, and any corresponding changes in health behaviour. The pilot trial will also inform on feasibility issues such as recruitment, acceptability of the intervention, and design and timeframes of the full-scale trial. The findings of the study will also inform power calculations to determine the sample size for the full-scale trial. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disabilities Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
 Ethics Department
 Freyberg Building
 Reception  Ground Floor
 20 Aitken Street
 Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/STH/36</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Valery Feigin</name>
      <address>AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive, 
Northcote 0627
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999 ext 9166</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vfeigin@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Rohit Bhattacharjee</name>
      <address>AUT University
AA254, 90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote 0627
Auckland 
</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 921 9999 ext 7126</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rbhattac@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Rohit Bhattacharjee</name>
      <address>AUT University
AA254, 90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote 0627
Auckland 
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999 ext 7126</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rbhattac@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>