<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82180">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000448448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 2 Two-Center, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Paired Treatment Site Comparison Study to Evaluate the Safety and Preliminary Efficacy of a Topical Antimicrobial (NEO101) in Reduction of Wound Bioburden among Adults Treated with Curettage &amp; Electrodessication for Superficial Basal Cell Carcinomas of the Trunk and Extremities</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2 Two-Center, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Paired Treatment Site Comparison Study to Evaluate the Safety and Preliminary Efficacy of a Topical Antimicrobial (NEO101) in Reduction of Wound Bioburden among Adults Treated with Curettage &amp; Electrodessication for Superficial Basal Cell Carcinomas of the Trunk and Extremities</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NEO101-CLIN-BCC001</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Antimicrobial treatment of wounds</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible subjects will be randomized to receive both NEO101 0.95% gel and vehicle-containing placebo gel.  Treatment (blinded to treatment assignment) will be administered to paired target surface areas twice daily for 7 days.  A 14-day safety and efficacy assessment period will follow the treatment period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo Gel</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the safety and local tolerability of twice-daily topical application of NEO101 gel for 7 days in adult subjects treated with curettage and electrodessication for superficial basal cell carcinomas of the trunk and extremities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and local tolerability will be assessed during the 7-day treatment period and through the 14-day follow-up period.  Physical examinations will be performed at Screening and on Days 1, 8 and 22.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) To make a preliminary evaluation of the efficacy of bid topical application of NEO101 in the eradication of  wound bioburden by Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococci, Proteus or Pseudomonas species, and Escherichia coli or Klebsiella species.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cultures will be performed on Days 1, 2, 8 and 15</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clinical diagnosis of superficial basal cell carcinoma from each of two paired proposed treatment sites; have been treated for basal cell carcinoma with standard curettage and electrodessication (c and e) within 7 days prior to enrollment; have full-thickness epithelial defect with surface area less than or equal to 5 cm squared at the c and e site; have paired positive culture for either Staphylococcus aureus, Strepococci, Proteus species or Pseudomonas species, Escherischia coli or Klebsiella species from both proposed treatment areas in the absence of clinical evidence of tissue infection; compliant with defined birth control.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have concomitant dermatologic or medical condition(s) which may interfere with the investigator's ability to evaluate response to treatment; have immunocompromised status; have a history of malignancy not in remission for at least 5 years excluding basal cell carcinoma; have an active intercurrent infection or poorly controlled medical condition; have used topical antibiotic or antibacterial soap between Screening Visit and Day 1; have used systemic antibiotic within 1 week prior to Day 1; have received systemic corticosteroid treatment within 1 week prior to Day 1; have a history of hypersensitivity or allergic reactions to parabens, sodium sulfite or other ingredient in the vehicle formulation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once a subject is identified as eligible to be randomized into the study, he/she will be assigned a unique subject number, which will correspond to the randomization code indicating which site (paired treatment sites A or B) is to be treated with NEO101, while the other site is to be treated with vehicle.  Each study clinic location will be supplied with blinded numbered study drug kits and a drug dispensation list.  Subjects will be randomized to treatment site using the order established on the drug dispensation list.  Blinding of treatment assignment is achieved using vials distinguished by a green-colored label (to be used ONLY for Treatment Site A application) and a blue label (to be used ONLY for Treatment Site B application).</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be assigned a unique subject number, which will correspond to the randomization code indicating which site (paired Treatment Site A or B) is to be treated with NEO101, while the other site is to be treated with vehicle.  Each study clinic location will be supplied with blinded numbered study drug kits and a drug dispensation list.  Subjects will be randomized to treatment site using the order established on the drug dispensation list.  The randomization schedule was developed using a blocked randomization scheme, stratified for the two planned study sites.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a paired treatment site comparison study.  The investigators, study staff and subjects will be blinded.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/09/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4217</postcode>
    <postcode>4152</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neosil Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5980 Horton Street, Suite 525
Emeryville, California 94608</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neosil Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5980 Horton Street, Suite 525
Emeryville, California 94608</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Skin Centre
Suite 5
AHC House
14 Carrara Street
Benowa, Queensland 4217

Southeast Dermatology
1202 Creek Road
Carina Heights, Queensland 4152

Therapeutics Goods Administration
CTN Number 2007/487</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>First Floor
71 Anzac Highway
Ashford, South Australia 5035</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/08/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>72/07, 72/07a</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andria Langenberg, MD</name>
      <address>Neosil Inc.
Suite 525
5980 Horton Street
Emeryville California 94608</address>
      <phone>+1 510 547 3610, ext. 180</phone>
      <fax>+1 510 547 3604</fax>
      <email>andria.langenberg@neosil.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolyn Nicholls</name>
      <address>The Skin Centre
Suite 5 AHC House
14 Carrara Street
Benowa QLD 4217</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5597 7170</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5597 7370</fax>
      <email>carolynnicholls@ozemail.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael McKown</name>
      <address>Neosil, Inc.
5980 Horton Street, Suite 525
Emeryville, California 94608</address>
      <phone>+1 510 547 3610, ext. 140</phone>
      <fax>+1 510 547 3604</fax>
      <email>michael.mckown@neosil.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>