<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347507">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001010987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy of lumbar extension traction on sagittal alignment in mechanical low back pain: A randomized trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of lumbar extension traction in addition to stretching exercises and infrared radiation on sagittal balance parameters and pain in chronic low back pain patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1124-6440</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>mechanical low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this study 3-point bending traction was used, each subject lied in a supine position; an anterior pull was applied by a posterior padded strap between the upper torso and lower pelvis, which placed under the patient's low back, at the level of lumbar curve. The tension in the strap was the transverse force (part 1 of 3-point bending) and was adjusted to each patient's tolerance, this strap was connected to computerized traction unit. whereas the second strap at the level of the femur heads (part 2 of 3-point bending) constrained the femurs to permit increased forward rotation of the pelvis and the third strap placed at the upper torso (part 3 of 3-point bending). The patints were having traction three times a week for ten weeks. The traction began at three minutes/session, increased one minute/session to 20minutes, at which time traction was applied for 20minutes/session. After they became familiar with the traction, patients were encouraged to use the maximum tolerable force.


Stretching exercises were performed for erector spine muscles and hamstring muscle holding each movement for 30 seconds. Each exercise was repeated 3 times. The stretching program was performed 3 times a week for 10 weeks.

Application of infrared radiation (wave length 800-1000nm). The patient was assumed the prone lying position where the area to be treated (the paraspinal muscles of the back) was adequately exposed, supported and relaxed. The lamp was positioned at distance ranged from (50-75cm). The radiation strikes the surface at or near right angle to achieve maximum penetration. The duration of application was fifteen minutes per session 3 times a week for 10 weeks. The Visual Analog Scale (VAS) was used to assess each patients pain perception.

all treatments were administered simultaneously over the10 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group received stretching exercises and infrared radiation, the same as that administered to the intervention group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>radiographs taken and assessed digitally using surgimap software to measure sagittal balance parameters in terms of lumbar lordosis, thoracic kyphosis, sacral slope, and positioning of C7 plumb line.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before treatment, 10 weeks afterwards and at 6 months follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Visual Analog Scale (VAS) was used to assess each patient?s pain perception</outcome>
      <timepoint>before treatment, 10 weeks afterwards and at 6 months follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1-patients with chronic mechanical low back pain. Duration of symptoms more than 3 months to avoid acute stage of inflammation
2-with defined lumbar hypo-lordosis, lumbar lordosis measured less than 40 degrees.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>spinal canal stenosis, rheumatoid arthritis, osteoporosis, inability to tolerate lumbar extension position, scoliotic deformity and any deformity of lower extremity that may interfere with global alignment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients were randomly assigned into two groups using the roll of a dice, an experimental group (odd number) and a control group (even number). Random permuted blocks of fixed size were employed to achieve a balance of the sample sizes between the two groups. A resident who was blinded to the research protocol and was not otherwise involved in the trial operated the random assignment.</concealment>
    <sequence>The patients were randomly assigned into two groups using the roll of a dice, an experimental group (odd number) and a control group (even number).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>study group and control group</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/12/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Aliaa Attiah Diab</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Physical Therapy, cairo university, Egypt

7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt.

Postal Code: 12612</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Aliaa Attiah Diab</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Physical Therapy, cairo university, Egypt

7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt.

Postal Code: 12612</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study was conducted to investigate the effect of lumbar extension traction on pain and whole spine sagittal balance as represented in lumbar curvature, thoracic curvature, C7 plumb line, and sacral slope.

Eighty patients with chronic mechanical low back pain (CMLBP) with definite hypolordosis were randomly assigned to traction or a control group. The control group (n=40) received stretching exercises and infrared radiation, whereas the traction group (n=40) received lumbar extension traction in addition to stretching exercises and infrared radiation.Main outcome measures: sagittal balance parameters in terms of lumbar lordosis, thoracic kyphosis, sacral slope, and positioning of C7 plumb line were measured for all patients at three intervals (before treatment, after 10 weeks of treatment, and at follow-up of six months).

Results: all sagittal balance variables did not change in the control groups (p&gt;0.05) .In the study group, the paired t test revealed a significant change in all sagittal balance variables in study group (p=0.000), while the control group revealed insignificant changes for all the previous variables. For Pain variable, the paired t test revealed a significant decrease in the pain level for both groups (p=0.000), while the unpaired t test revealed a significant difference between post treatment values for all previous measured variables between both groups (p=0.001).At 6-months follow-up, there were significant differences between both groups for all the previous variables (p&gt;0.05).
Conclusions: Lumbar extension traction in addition to stretching exercises and infrared radiation  is beneficial in improving the pain and sagittal balance parameters in CMLBP.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>faculty counsel for post graduated study and researcher</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Physical Therapy - Cairo University 
7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt.

Postal Code: 12612</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Aliaa Attiah  Diab</name>
      <address>faculty of physical therapy- Cairo university
7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612</address>
      <phone>+20103627375</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ola_1174@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Aliaa Attiah  Diab</name>
      <address>faculty of physical therapy- Cairo university
7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612</address>
      <phone>+20103627375</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ola_1174@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>aliaa attiah diab</name>
      <address>faculty of physical therapy- Cairo university
7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612</address>
      <phone>+20103627375</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ola_1174@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>