<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366371">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000555651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Neurofeedback Training in children with dysgraphia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with dysgraphia, could neurofeedback Training, compared to placebo, reduce the theta/beta1 and theta/alpha1 ratios in C3 and C4 brain channels respectively?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysgraphia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Learning disabilities</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention has been through neurofeedback training. Neurofeedback training (NFT) is a promising alternative or additional treatment without any reported harmful effects. It touches on the self-regulation of ongoing neuronal fluctuations recording by EEG in some frequency bands by an auditory or visual feedback, helping to normalize and/or self-regulate the brain activities. 

Eligible participants were randomly allocated to one of two groups: experimental group and control group.

For both groups: an active scalp electrode, according to the standard 10-20 system, was placed at C3 or C4 channel with the ipsilateral reference and the contralateral ground electrodes on the earlobe. Signals were acquired at 256 Hz, converted by a 14-bit A/D convertor and band-filtered to extract the theta, beta1, and alpha1 components, among others. NFT was conducted over a period of five weeks (three times a week), with each participant receiving fifteen 40-minute training sessions, consisting of 4-6 4-min game periods.

For the experimental group the amplitude of theta (represented by size and speed of game) and beta1 and alpha1 (represented by brightness and speed of game) activities was fed back using an audio-visual online feedback loop. 

We have examined theta/beta1 and theta/alpha1 ratios in 8 normal subjects to compare the experimental group ratios with normal ratios.</interventions>
    <comparator>Procedures has been identical to experimental group except that participants were provided with placebo treatment (a random feedback instead of EEG feedback). </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Electroencephalography (EEG) measured during NFT sessions</outcome>
      <timepoint>During each NFT session</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of dictation errors measured by Dictation test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-neurofeedback and post-neurofeedback for all groups</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Colorado Learning Difficulties Questionnaire (CLDQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-neurofeedback and post-neurofeedback for all groups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Conners Parents Rating Scale (CPRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-neurofeedback and post-neurofeedback for all groups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EEG recording during Dictation test and analysis of signals</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-neurofeedback and post-neurofeedback for all groups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Common Handwriting Errors Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-neurofeedback and post-neurofeedback for all groups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type Disorder Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-neurofeedback and post-neurofeedback for all groups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>IQ&gt;70,
Existence of a problem in writing (dysgraphia),
Be third grade student
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>9</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A personal or family history of mental illness,
The history of vision or hearing disorders,
Brain injury,
Neurological disorders,
Serious medical condition,
A family history of genetic disorders</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A conversation was conducted with more than 30 school’s principal in Mashhad city in Sep 2012 to provide them with information about NFT. Principals asked to introduce third grade students who have serious problems in writing and dictation. With this procedure, 154 dysgraphic Iranian children from third grade were introduced to participate in this study out of more than 30 regular primary schools.
 
Then we held an information session for parents and asked them to fill out a questionnaire regarding the exclusion criteria (including a personal or family history of mental illness, the history of vision or hearing disorders, brain injury, neurological disorders, serious medical condition, or a family history of genetic disorders). By assessing the questionnaire, 69 students were deleted form list.

Afterwards, it was asked from the parents of remained 85 students to sign a consent form and express their permission for participating of their child in the examinations. We have received 64 approval forms. Then we examined the IQ by an IQ test and deleted other 13 students who got IQ score of &lt;70. 

From the 51 remained students, 31 individuals were boys and 20 individuals were girls. Our final goal was to select 6 boys and 6 girls randomly to participate them into neurofeedback training sessions. To achieve the goal, we assigned a number to each student based on the time they submit their consent form (the parents were not aware this role and had no force to submit their forms as soon as possible; there was one month deadline). Numbers were allocated regardless of gender. The first submitted form was allocated the first number in the sequence. Each subsequent participant was allocated the next number in the sequence. Then we separated the numbers of girls and boys and applied a fuzzy random programming for the sequence of numbers in each gender’s group. 12 numbers were selected by this way.

For dividing the selected 12 individuals into experimental group (group 1; 7 persons) and control group (group 2; 5 persons), we applied a fuzzy random forest classifier. Regardless of gender, the subjects were randomly divided into two groups. 

The participants and parents were quite unaware which group the children placed and the information about the classification was kept secret till the end of sessions. </concealment>
    <sequence>For dividing the selected 12 individuals into experimental group (group 1; 7 persons) and control group (group 2; 5 persons), we applied a fuzzy random forest classifier. It was a Simple randomization using a randomization table created by computer software. Regardless of gender, the subjects were randomly divided into two groups. 

First group, the experimental (n = 7; 3 boys and 4 girls), received NFT treatment, and the second group, the control (n = 5; 3 boys and 2 girls), received a placebo treatment. One girl from the experimental group left the experiments after three NFT sessions as a result of sociocultural problems in its family. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>We have examined theta/beta1 and theta/alpha1 ratios in 8 normal subjects to compare the experimental group ratios with normal ratios. In the other words, in order to examine how much are the ratios close to the desired normal values, we randomly selected 8 students by using simple randomisation by coin-tossing from 20 normal students. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The main hypothesis for the project was: Does neurofeedback protocol improve dysgraphia? To analyse this question some variables were selected to analyzed including colorado learning difficulties questionnaire (CLDQ), conners parents rating scale (CPRS), dictation test (DT), EEG, QEEG, common handwriting errors questionnaire (CHEQ), and type of disorder questionnaire (TDQ). 

The conditions tested: neurofeedback in experimental and control groups. 

Time points: Pre intervention and Post intervention for all variables except EEG and QEEG which were tested in each sessions. 

The variables examined between the intervention group and the controls using a paired t-test to check for differences between both groups. Significance level was set at p = 0.05.

We have determined a sample size of 12 based on clinic capacity and funding available. However, the selected sample size (12) has been quite reasonable in the area of neurofeedback particularly in learning disabilities; for example: Fernandez et al. study in 2003 (10 sample size), Walker and Norman study in 2006 (12 sample size), and Butlers study in 2011 (12 sample size).  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>24/09/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/01/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state>Mashhad, Khorasan Razavi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Isfahan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Biomedical Engineering Department,  University of Isfahan, Azadi square, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Isfahan</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Biomedical Engineering Department,  University of Isfahan, Azadi square, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mohammadreza Yazdchi</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Biomedical Engineering Department,  University of Isfahan, Azadi square, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Majid Ghoshuni</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Mashhad Branch, Islamic Azad University, Professor Yousefi Street, Mashhad, Khorasan Razavi, Iran.
Postal Code: 91871-47578</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Peyman Hashemian
</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychiatry, Mashhad University of Medical Science,  University Ave, Mashhad, Iran.
Postal Code: 91388-13944
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hamid Khayyam</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>75 Pigdons Road, Waurn Ponds, Victoria 3216 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Twelve dysgraphic children from third grade were chosen to participate in the study. Our goal in this study was to investigate the effect of NFT on dysgraphic individuals to find out whether it is feasible to improve dysgraphia by NFT. Training lasted fifteen sessions in left and right hemisphere motor regions centered on C3 and C4 respectively.
Besides, 8 normal subjects have also participated in this study for comparison purposes. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics review board of Biomedical Engineering School at University of Isfahan</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Biomedical Engineering department, University of Isfahan, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>891432</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>IAUM ethics review board of Biomedical Engineering Department</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Biomedical Engineering , Mashhad Branch, Islamic Azad University, Professor Yousefi Street, Mashhad, Iran.
Postal Code: 91871-47578</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H385018</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mahboubeh ParastarFeizabadi</name>
      <address>Biomedical Engineering Department, University of Isfahan, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</address>
      <phone>+61 435 306326</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mparastar7@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mahboubeh ParastarFeizabadi</name>
      <address>Biomedical Engineering Department, University of Isfahan, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</address>
      <phone>+61 435 306326</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mparastar7@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mahboubeh ParastarFeizabadi</name>
      <address>Biomedical Engineering Department, University of Isfahan, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</address>
      <phone>+61 435 306326</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mparastar7@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mahboubeh ParastarFeizabadi</name>
      <address>Biomedical Engineering Department, University of Isfahan, Daneshgah Street, Isfahan, Iran.
Postal Code: 81746-73441</address>
      <phone>+61 435 306326</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mparastar7@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>