<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81571">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000125426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Uterine Serous Papillary Cancer (UPSC) Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective, Non-Randomised Phase 2, Open Feasibility Study on the Effect of  Carboplatin plus Paclitaxel with Sequential Radical Pelvic Radiotherapy for Uterine Serous Papillary Cancer with respect to Safety and Efficacy of Treatment and Patterns of Recurrence.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov: NCT00147680</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Uterine Papillary Serous Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Drug: Paclitaxel, Carboplatin
Surgery Total abdominal hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, pelvic and aortic node sampling, omentectomy, peritoneal cytology.  
Chemotherapy 
Chemotherapy commences at the surgeons and the medical oncologists discretion and the time between surgery and start of chemotherapy will be recorded.

One treatment cycle consists of 3 weeks. Paclitaxel and Carboplatin will be administered as follows:

Day 1: Premedications* including:
Diphenhydramine 50 mg IV or po or phenergan 12.5 -25 mg IV
Cimetidine 300 mg or ranitidine 50 mg IV
Dexamethasone 20 mg IV
Paclitaxel 175mg/m2
Carboplatin Area Under Curve (AUC) 6 
Day 22: Repeat the cycle.  This is Day 1 of the second cycle.
Day 43: Repeat the cycle.  This is Day 1 of the third cycle.
Day 64: Repeat the cycle.  This is Day 1 of the fourth cycle.
Day 85:  After the fourth cycle of chemotherapy:
Patients with stage 4 disease will continue with chemotherapy to a total of 6 cycles
Patients with surgical stage 1b to 3c disease will receive whole pelvis external beam radiotherapy  (50.4 Gy Recommended Dose (RD) over 5 and a half weeks +/- paraaortic boost +/- vaginal vault brachytherapy boost). Radiotherapy will start 4 weeks after commencement of chemotherapy and when the haematological count has recovered 

*A patient's premedications can be reduced to diphenhydramine 25 mg/ phenergan 6.25mg and dexamethasone 10 mg or lower after the observation that the patient did not have any allergic reaction to the first and second doses of Paclitaxel.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and efficacy of the combination of Paclitaxel and Carboplatin +/- pelvic radiotherapy in the treatmement of UPSC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before each cycle of chemotherapy, a physical examination, vital signs, performance status, a FBC and a serum biochemistry will be performed. 
During radiotherapy evaluation of toxicity is done on a weekly basis. 
Following completion of therapy, patients will be followed for at least five (5) years) at 3-monthly intervals for the first three (3) years and half-yearly thereafter. 
To observe the patterns of recurrence following the administration of the combination of Paclitaxel and Carboplatin +/- pelvic radiotherapy in the treatment of UPSC</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the Qualtiy of Life (QOL), overall survival and disease free survival.</outcome>
      <timepoint>QOL to be completed at screening (after surgery), at every cycle of chemotherapy (4 to 6 cycles dependant on stage of disease) pre X-ray therapy (XRT) and weekly during XRT until the end of a 5.5 week treatment program.  Overall survival will be defined as observed length of life from entry onto the protocol to death, or for living patients, date of last contact.  Disease free survival will be defined as the date from entry onto the protocol to the date of clinical or radiological evidence of progressive disease</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Before each cycle of chemotherapy, a physical examination, vital signs, performance status, a Full Blood Count (FBC) and a serum biochemistry will be performed. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Before each cycle of chemotherapy up until the 4th or 6th cycle dependant on the stage of disease</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>During radiotherapy evaluation of toxicity is done on a weekly basis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>during X-ray therapy (XRT) each week for the period of treatment (5.5 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Following completion of therapy, patients will be followed for at least five (5) years) at 3-monthly intervals for the first three (3) years and half-yearly thereafter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>follow up for at least 5 years at 3-monthly intervals for the first three years and half-yearly thereafter</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with histologically confirmed Uterine Papillary Serous Carcinoma (UPSC) at surgical stage 1b to 4 disease. The serous-papillary component of the specimen must be at least 30 per cent. Patinets with surgical stage 1a disease should not be enrolled. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0,1,2. Patients may not have received any prior chemotherapy regimens for UPSC.Patients must have adequate bone marrow, renal, hepatic and neurologic function.Patients must be informed of the investigational nature of the study and sign an informed consent form.Patients with previous malignancy are eligible only if the patient has been disease-free for &gt;= 5 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with pre-existing &gt;=grade 2 neurotoxicity.Patients with uncontrolled hypertension, (systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure &gt;100 mm Hg) or uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia or diabetes mellitus. Patients with a history of other malignancy within the last 5 years that could affect the diagnosis or assessment of UPSC.Patients who have a history of serious cardiac disease that is not adequately controlled are not allowed.  Patients with documented myocardial infarction within 6 months proceeding study entry, congestive heart failure, unstable angina, a clinically significant pericardial effusion or arrhythmias are also ineligible.Patients with an active serious infection or other serious underlying medical condition that would otherwise impair their ability to receive protocol treatment.Serious medical or psychiatric illnesses that would prevent informed consent. Dementia or significantly altered mental status that would prohibit the understanding and/or giving of informed consent. Prior significant allergic reactions to drugs containing cremophor, such as cyclosporine, or vitamin K are not eligible.  A significant reaction may be defined as, but is not limited to, the description of grade &gt;= 3 allergic reactions using the Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) Patients with known hypersensitivity to Paclitaxel, carboplatin or Cremophor EL.Patients who have received prior whole pelvis radiotherapy.Patients with uncontrolled pelvic inflammatory disease that would contraindicate pelvic radiotherapy.Patients who are pregnant or breast-feeding.Patients receiving other investigational therapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Centre for Gynaecological Cancer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 Ned Hanlon Building
Butterfield St 
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston Qld  4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bristol - Myers Squibb Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>556 Princes Hwy
Nobel Park North
Victoria 3174</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>n/a</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will be an open, non-randomised, clinical phase 2 trial which will involve 30 women diagnosed with Uterine Serous Papillary Cancer.  We will investigate the effect of four cycles of Paclitaxel / Carboplatin, followed by whole pelvic external beam radiotherapy to a standard pelvis field (50.4 Gy) with or without a para-aortic boost with respect to safety and efficacy of treatment, and patterns of recurrence.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Herston</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2003/200</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Health Services</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>South Brisbane</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/11/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> 906A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Wesley Private Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Achenflower Brisbane </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/09/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2004/35</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Prince of Wales Hospital Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/04/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>05/049</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Greenslopes Private Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Greenslopes Brisbane</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/09/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>04/01</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre East Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/02/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> 05/40</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Christchurch Hospital - Canterbury Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>CTB/04/09/151</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Andreas Obermair</name>
      <address>Queensland Centre for Gynaecological Cancer
Teaching and Research Level 6
Ned Hanlon Building
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston QLD 4026</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36361722</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36361721</fax>
      <email>andreas_obermair@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dan Jackson</name>
      <address>Queensland Centre for Gynaecological Cancer
Teaching and Research Level 6
Ned Hanlon Building
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston QLD 4026</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368522</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36361721</fax>
      <email>dan_jackson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>