<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370005">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000126415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can a seaweed supplement reduce your risk of diabetes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigation of the impact of a polyphenol-rich seaweed extract on postprandial glycaemic control in healthy adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postprandial glycaemic response</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The test product is Maritech (Registered Trademark) Synergy, an extract from the macroagla Fucus vesiculosus that contains 30% polyphenols and 60% fucoidan (a complex carbohydrate). The product will be encapsulated for ease of consumption and dosing. Doses of 500 mg (150 mg polyphenols) and 2000 mg (600 mg polyphenols) will be administered on a single occasion prior to an oral glucose tolerance test. 

Participants will be provided with a standardised commercially available frozen meal to consume between 7 - 9 pm the night before each testing day, then will be asked to fast until testing is complete, drinking only water. Participants are also asked to avoid foods high in polyphenols and strenuous exercise for 24 hours prior to testing. Participants will be asked to come in to the lab at 7 am in the morning following an overnight fast. They will have two initial finger prick tests done to provide fasting levels of blood glucose and insulin (at -45 and -30 minutes), then be given either a low (500 mg) or high (2000 mg) dose of marine polyhpenol supplement. At 0 minutes they will be provided with a 50 g available carbohydrates from bread, which must be consumed within 5 minutes. 

Following completion of the three morning cross overs (high dose, low dose, placebo), all participants will have the option to continue to partake in the evening arm of the study. Participants who choose to complete the evening protocol as well will have a wash out period between the two arms of at least 3 days. Participants will be randomized as to the order they will consume the placebo and 2000 mg dose of the test product, in a 2-way cross-over. The same protocol as for the mornings will be carried out for evening testing, but with participants consuming a standardised commercially available frozen meal between 7 and 8 am and arriving at the testing facility at 6 pm after fasting throughout the day.

Participants will consume the test doses and placebo in a cross-over fashion with at least three days washout in between each treatment. All treatment doses will be administered and supervised on site.  </interventions>
    <comparator>The product acting as the placebo is Medisca (Registered Trademark) Cellulose, NF (Microcrystalline).  It will be administered in a dose of 2000 mg to match the high dose intervention product and will also be encapsulated.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial blood glucose incremental area under the curve</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken at -45, -30, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90 and 120 minutes after test drink.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial blood insulin incremental area under the curve</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken at -30, 30, 60, 90 and 120 minutes after test drink.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial blood glucose 'time to peak'</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken at -45, -30, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90 and 120 minutes after test drink.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial blood insulin 'time to peak'</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken at -30, 30, 60, 90 and 120 minutes after test drink.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>How timing of supplementation, whether administered in the morning (~7 am) or evening  (~6 pm), affects polyphenol impact on postprandial blood glucose and insulin incremental area under the curve and 'time to peak'.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken at -45, -30, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90 and 120 minutes after test drink for glucose.
Blood samples taken at -30, 30, 60, 90 and 120 minutes after test drink for insulin.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intolerance symptoms - assessed by participant completion of a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours from supplement ingestion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Body mass index from 18.5 to less than 28 kg/m2, a fasting blood glucose level below 5.5 mmol/L and blood pressure within the normal range.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Gastrointestinal issues that may affect the absorption and intestinal actions of the polyphenols,
2. Taking medication for blood sugar control,
3. Taking other natural health products known to impact on polyphenols e.g. fish oil,
4. Breastfeeding or pregnant, 
5. Have any of the following serious health conditions: 
i. liver/thyroid issues, 
ii.  hypertension,
iii.  recent major surgery,
6. Consume more than 4 standard drinks per day, or 9 standard drinks per week,
7. Smoker,
8. Have an implanted cardiac defibrillator.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The researcher conducting participant allocation will be separate from the researcher conducting participant screening and allocation will remain hidden from the researcher doing the screening in a secure computer database.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computerised sequence generation will be used to determine the order in which participants receive each treatment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Forty individuals will be recruited with the expectation that at least 36 will complete the whole protocol, which allows for a dropout rate of 10%.  Sample size calculations were performed, assuming 2-sided 0.80 power, with 0.05 significance level, to detect a change of 40 units in postprandial blood glucose iAUC and a change of 2500 units in postprandial plasma insulin iAUC,.  Sample size calculations were based on data from similar studies that also examined these outcomes.

All results will be assessed for normality.  Paired t-tests will be used to compare the difference between intervention and placebo groups for blood glucose and insulin iAUC and blood glucose and insulin time to peak.  Descriptive statistics (number and percentages) will be used to interpret intolerance symptoms.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>38</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>12/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University, Department of Nutrition and Dietetics</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1, 264 Ferntree Gully Rd,
Notting Hill 3168, VIC
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Marinova Biotechnology Company</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>249 Kennedy Drive, 
Cambridge 7170
TAS</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 2 diabetes is increasing worldwide and can cause serious health complications if left uncontrolled.  In 2014 it was estimated that 9% of the global adult population suffered from diabetes, of which 90% could be attributed to type 2 diabetes.  Optimal blood glucose control reduces the risk of diabetes-related complications.  There are currently a number of drugs on the market to control blood sugar levels; however they produce unpleasant side effects.  Marine polyphenols have shown potential to improve blood glucose control without producing side effects.

While polyphenols are found in both terrestrial plants and marine algae, this study will focus solely on those commercially available from marine sources.  Marine polyphenols, or phlorotannins, are most commonly found in brown algae. There are a number of advantages to cultivating marine algae compared with terrestrial plants, and marine-derived compounds are rapidly growing in popularity in the food industry, especially with the current consumer preference for natural health products over synthetic ones.

There is promising research regarding the antidiabetic effects of marine polyphenols in animal and in vitro studies.  However, it is yet to be determined if the same health effects are consistently true in a human population.  If so, marine polyphenols may be useful for controlling blood sugar levels, resulting in fewer side effects and a reduced risk of complications for people with type 2 diabetes.  Marine polyphenols may also be useful for people with prediabetes to lower blood sugar levels and prevent progression to type 2 diabetes.

This study aims to:
1. Determine the effect of commercially available doses of marine polyphenols in supplement form on postprandial blood glucose and insulin following a glucose load, compared to placebo in a human population.

2. Determine how well different doses of polyphenols are accepted through completion of an intolerance symptoms questionnaire.

3. Examine the effects of commercially available doses (Marinova) of marine polyphenols in supplement form on changes in blood glucose and insulin following a glucose load, in the evening.  Blood glucose rises higher and stays high for longer following consumption of carbohydrates in the evening, compared to the morning.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University
Room 111, Chancellery Building E
24 Sports Walk
Clayton Campus
Wellington Rd
Clayton VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF16/53 - 2016000019</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Maxine Bonham</name>
      <address>Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat Facility
Level 1, 264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9902 4272    </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maxine.bonham@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Maxine Bonham</name>
      <address>Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat Facility
Level 1, 264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9902 4272    </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maxine.bonham@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Maxine Bonham</name>
      <address>Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat Facility
Level 1, 264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9902 4272    </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maxine.bonham@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Margaret Murray</name>
      <address>Monash University
Be Active Sleep Eat Facility
Level 1, 264 Ferntree Gully Road
Notting Hill VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 (3) 9905 3460   </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>margaret.murray@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>