<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335726">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000698077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Addition of Trunk Restraint to Home-Based Modified Constraint- Induced Movement Therapy after Stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Addition of Trunk Restraint to Home-Based Modified Constraint- Induced Movement Therapy after Stroke: A randomized controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke survivors</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The experimental group will undertake modified Constraint-induced movement therapy (CIMT) and trunk restraint during two weeks of intensive training, five times a week, three hours daily. They will be required to use a glove which will restrict their less affected wrist and fingers by 90% of the time they are awake during the 14 days. The trunk restraint will be performed by an eight-shape clavicle immobilizer, with a seat belt strap with a buckle that fits to the size of the trunk of each individual. This restraint will not permit upper trunk movements. Training will be performed by 30 minutes of the transfer package exposure and application of the items of the Motor Activity Logo (MAL) (30 or 15 items daily alternately ). This will be followed by two hours and 30 minutes of four shaping tasks, which may vary, depending upon the needs of each individual. The task practice of making a snack, will be the same for all individuals. Between each exercise, individuals will be allowed to rest for at least 30 seconds. Individual adjustments will be made for better adaptation and the training will be supervised by a trained physiotherapist. Blood pressure measurements will be obtained before and after the intervention and their heart rate will be continuously monitored by a Polar heart rate monitor.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive the same intervention, but without trunk restraints.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount and quality of the upper limb function, assessed by the Motor Activity Log</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, post-intervention, and follow-up of one and three months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reaching kinematics, upper limb and grip strength, and quality of life</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, post-intervention, and follow-up of one and three months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stroke survivors will be included if they are over 21 years of age; are within more than six months of their stroke; show inability to use the upper limb (assessed by 2.5 to zero (0) on the Motor Activity Log-Brazil); have a range of motion of at least 45 degrees of shoulder flexion and abduction, 20 degrees of elbow extension, 10 degrees of wrist extension and greater than zero degree in the metacarpophalangeal joints, as confirmed by goniometric active measures; are able to stand for two minutes (with support of their upper limbs, if necessary), can move safely and independently (e.g., in the use of the toilet); can understand and follow the instructions, as determined by Mini-mental state examination (Brucki et al., 2003); have shoulder pain less than three (mild pain) on the Shoulder Q scores (Turner-Stokes and Jackson, 2006), and report enough visual acuity with or without corrections.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals with bilateral hemiplegia or other disabling neurological or musculoskeletal condition and who were submitted to the application of botulin toxin in less than three months (Blanton et al., 2006) will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The sequence of randomisation will be computer generated in random, computed blocks of four to six participants and maintained in sequentially numbered, sealed opaque envelopes. The envelopes will be prepared prior to the study by a trained physiotherapy student who is not involved in the study. Eligible participants will be randomly allocated to either, an experimental or a control group, after the contents of the sealed opaque envelopes are revealed by the treating therapist.</concealment>
    <sequence>The sequence of randomisation will be computer generated in random, computed blocks of four to six participants and maintained in sequentially numbered, sealed opaque envelopes. The envelopes will be prepared prior to the study by a trained physiotherapy student who is not involved in the study. Eligible participants will be randomly allocated to either, an experimental or a control group, after the contents of the sealed opaque envelopes are revealed by the treating therapist.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/02/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/11/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>22</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Minas Gerais</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avenida Antonio Carlos, 6627
31270-901 Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brazilian Government Funding Agencies (CNPq and FAPEMIG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avenida Antonio Carlos, 6627
31270-901 Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Studies which evaluated the effects of trunk restraint demonstrated that the hemiplegics who were trained with trunk restraint, demonstrated better performance in the tasks of reaching and grasping, with smaller displacements of the trunk, greater extension of the elbow, and better coordination between the joints than those who were trained without trunk restraint. Therefore, the aim of this study was to combine trunk restraint with modified CIMT (three hours of intensive training with a transfer package, shaping and task practice with restrictions of the less affected upper extremity of about 90% of the awake hours, during 14 days). The training protocol will be home-based to improve the transfer package. Therefore the specific research questions were:
1.Are two weeks of trunk restraint, plus modified home-based CIMT more effective than home-based modified CIMT alone in improving the amount and quality of the upper limb use and range of movement, smoothness, jerkiness, movement unity and velocity in the kinematics of reaching in chronic hemiplegics? 
2.Are these gains maintained one and three months after the intervention has ceased?</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1) Pereira ND, Ovando AC, Michaelsen SM, Anjos SM, Lima RCM, nascimento LR, Teixeira-Salmela LF. Motor Activity Log-Brazil: reliability and relationships with motor impairments in individuals with chronic stroke. Arquivos de Neuro-Psiquiatria. 2012,70:196-201. 
2)    Pereira ND, Michaelsen SM, Menezes IS, Ovando AC, Lima RCM, Teixeira-Salmela LF. Confiabilidade da versao brasileira do Wof Motor Function Test em adultos com hemiparesia. Revista Brasileira de Fisioterapia. 2011, 15:257-65. 
3)    Lima RCM, Teixiera-Salmela LF, Michaelsen SM. Effects of trunk restraint in addition to home-based modified constraint-induced movement therapy after stroke: a randomized controlled trial. International Journal of Stroke. 2012, 7: 258-64. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica em Pesquisa da Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Avenida Antonio Carlos, 6627 - Unidade Administrativa II
31270-901 Belo Horizonte - Minas Gerais</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0408.0.203.000-09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luci Fuscaldi Teixeira-Salmela</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy
Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais
Avenida Antonio Carlos, 6627 - Campus Pampulha
31270-901  Belo Horizonte - MG</address>
      <phone>55-31-3409-7403</phone>
      <fax>55-31-3409-4783</fax>
      <email>lfts@ufmg.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luci Fuscaldi Teixeira-Salmela</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy
Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais
Avenida Antonio Carlos, 6627 - Campus Pampulha
31270-901  Belo Horizonte - MG</address>
      <phone>55-31-3409-7403</phone>
      <fax>55-31-3409-4783</fax>
      <email>lfts@ufmg.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luci Fuscaldi Teixeira-Salmela</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy
Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais
Avenida Antonio Carlos, 6627 - Campus Pampulha
31270-901  Belo Horizonte - MG</address>
      <phone>55-31-3409-7403</phone>
      <fax>55-31-3409-4783</fax>
      <email>lfts@ufmg.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Renata Cristina Magalhaes Lima</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais Avenida Antonio Carlos, 6627 - Campus Pampulha 31270-901 Belo Horizonte - MG</address>
      <phone>55-31-3409-7403</phone>
      <fax>55-31-34094783</fax>
      <email>renatalima.prof@newtonpaiva.br </email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>