<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362564">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000589886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to evaluate the harmful effects of metal ions on eyesight in patients with an ASR total hip replacement.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study on the ASR metal on metal hip resurfacing: Impact of cobalt toxicity on visual pathways and the presence of soft tissue destruction in the symptomatic hip.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Visual acuity and correlation with metal ion levels (Co/Cr) in patients with metal on metal ASR total hip replacements.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The harmful effects of elevated metal ion levels in the systemic circulation are increasingly being realised.  There have been isolated case reports of disturbance of visual pathways as a result of elevated metal ion levels however this has never been investigated in relation to elevated metal ion levels resulting from a hip replacement.  The ASR total hip replacement used a metal on metal bearing surface and has now been identified as failing early and in the process result in elevated metal ion levels.  This study aims to investigate visual pathways using electrophysiological techniques and then correlate these findings with metal ion levels in a cohort of patients who have undergone an ASR total hip replacement.
The electrophysiological assessments on the eye will take approximately 4 1/2 hours to complete.  The metal ion levels will be taken at the point of recruitment and no long term follow up will be part of this study.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will undergone electrophysiological assessment of their visual fields and again correlate these findings with serum metal ion levels.  The control group will be made up of patients who have undergone a conventional total hip replacement with a metal on polyethylene bearing surface , hence no concerns over metal ions.
The electrophysiological assessments on the eye will take approximately 4 1/2 hours to complete.  The metal ion levels will be taken at the point of recruitment and no long term follow up</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We aim to look at visual acuity by carrying out electrophysiological assessment and correlate these results to serum metal ion levels in order to identify whether serum metal ion levels have any deleterious effect on visual acuity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed at the point of recruitment and metal ions measured and electrophysiological assessment carried out.  This is the only point of assessment on this study as it is beyond the remit of this study to carry out long term follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients recruited will have undergone an ASR total hip replacement or an ASR hip resurfacing.
For the control group patients will have undergone  a total hip replacement with a non metal on metal bearing surface (i.e. metal on polyethylene)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not relevant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Riaz Khan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Orthopaedic Dept 
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital 
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
Perth
Western Australia
6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>De Puy</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>DePuy Australia
Division of Johnson &amp; Johnson Medical Pty Ltd
6-8 Compark Circuit
Mulgrave
Victoria 3170
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Total hip replacement is now a well established operation to reliably alleviate pain from osteoarthritis of the hip joint.  Over the years a number of bearing surfaces have been used in order to minimise the wear within the joint itself.  One such bearing surface is a metal socket articulating with a metal ball.  However we know now that although this provides very low wear rates, it can result in metal ions being released into the blood stream as a result of this wear process.

It is the precise effects of these metal ions within the blood stream that we are beginning to understand more about.  In particular we know very little about the effect that metal ions have on the eyesight and if metal ion levels are high whether this can cause changes in visual acuity.

This study aims to measure blood levels of Cobalt and Chrome in your blood stream and then potentially carry out specific tests to look at the functioning of the cells within the eyes to assess whether this is abnormal.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>There will be no trial website.  Patients will receive printed information booklets.</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairder Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
Perth
Western Australia
6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/07/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Riaz Khan</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
Perth
Western Australia
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rjkkhan@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Riaz Khan</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
Perth
Western Australia
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rjkkhan@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Riaz Khan</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
Perth
Western Australia
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rjkkhan@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>