<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366638">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001087640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Younger Women's Wellness after Cancer program: A pilot study of an E-Health Enabled Lifestyle Modification Intervention.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Younger Women's Wellness after Cancer program: A pilot study of an E-Health Enabled Lifestyle Modification Intervention to Improve the Health and Wellness of Younger Women after Cancer Treatment.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>YWWACP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gynaecological cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Haematological cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cervical (cervix)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a 12 week, e-health enabled, structured health promotion intervention targeted at improving health related quality of life and reducing chronic disease risk factors in women between 20 and 50 years of age who have previously been treated for breast, haematological and gynaecological cancers. All women in the intervention arm will receive health education material, including a Program Journal (in the form of an interactive iBook), and access to an interactive web interface. The iBook includes sections on healthy eating, sleep, exercise advice, tips for managing fatigue and stress, mindfulness, and will encourage women to bring together these various components of the health education provided and incorporate them into their lives over a 12-week period. The iBook includes a weekly exercise planner, where women are encouraged to use this journal daily and to plan ahead for their exercise in the following week. Participants will receive access to self-directed resources (via the website) and personal consultations (via videoconference) with a nurse. Three individual, virtual 30 minute consultations at 0, 6 and 12 weeks will be provided by a registered nurse trained in the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care (post treatment) comprising of general information during clinic visits e.g. diet, exercise, support. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is change in health-related quality of life as measured by The Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General (FACT-G)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometry using standard protocols; including measures of height, weight, waist-to-hip ratio and BMI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual dietary intake will be monitored through the Food Frequency Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity will be measured using the validated International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep activity and quality - Pittsburgh sleep quality index </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stress, anxiety and depression - Perceived Stress, and List of Threatening Experiences (LTE), Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale, Zung self-rated anxiety scale, Centre for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Menopausal symptoms - Greene Climacteric Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body image, sexuality and sexual function. These will be assessed with validated tools incorporated into the online survey (the Body Image Scale, the Female Sexual Function Index, and the Emotional Intimacy Scale). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Internet and technology use. This will be assessed with 13 questions incorporated into the online survey (e.g. how often do you access the internet?; have you ever used health-related mobile apps?; how often to you access health forums?) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health behaviours, including smoking and alcohol consumption, will be assessed in the online survey at baseline (0 weeks), 12 week and 24 weeks. Alcohol consumption is also measured as part of the Food Frequency Questionnaire (described above).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The FACT-Cog tool has been included in the online component of the survey and is a 37 questionnaire assessing cognitive function. </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Completed surgery or chemotherapy (primary or adjuvant) and/or radiotherapy  for blood, breast and/or gynaecological cancer (2) Able to speak and read Level 10 English (3) Must have access to  internet (4) not currently receiving any cytotoxic maintenance treatments</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Metastatic or advanced cancer and inoperable or active loco-regional disease (2) Any clinical, cognitive or psychiatric contraindication identified by treating staff (3) Participants on cytotoxic maintenance treatments will be excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited by site Research Assistants, or will register interest via an online website, and will send consent form via surface mail. Participants will be allocated an ID number by the data manager, and randomised to intervention or control by a blinded third party. All other team members will be blinded to participant ID or intervention group membership. </concealment>
    <sequence>permuted block randomisation using computer generated number sequences </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A difference greater than a five point difference on the FACT-G total score is associated with meaningful differences on clinical and subjective indicators. To achieve 90% power and a 95% confidence interval (a=0.05), the two study arms would require 215 participants each, assuming a standard deviation of 16 and an observed difference of 5 units after the 12 week intervention. Assuming 10% attrition and 15% non-responders the minimum sample size required for each group is 268, with a total sample size of 536. 
The current study is a pilot study, and we are therefore recruiting a minimum of 10% (or 30 to 40 participants for each study condition) into our program.
The extended CONSORT statement for RCTs will be adhered to when reporting. Baseline measures and participant characteristics will be initially compared to assess for imbalances and differences between groups. Baseline and within-group differences over time will be assessed for all variables of interest using paired t-tests for continuous variables and chi-square tests for categorical variables. Primary endpoint (HRQoL): Between group differences at 12 and 24 weeks will be analysed using a linear mixed model and the difference in variables of interest at 12 and 24 weeks of HRQoL. Secondary endpoints: Linear mixed models will be used to analyse secondary outcomes such as energy, macronutrient and micronutrient intake, body fatness, levels of physical activity, alcohol and smoking, after determining the change score in each variable of interest. Secondary stratification analysis by BMI and socio-demographic variables will also be performed. Logistic regression models will be used to examine predictors of quality of life including baseline quality of life, age and socio demographic variables. This includes exploring the rurality of the women according to the classifications of  highly accessible, accessible, moderately accessible, remote and very remote location suggested by the ARIA classification.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>27/01/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>41</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>7/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital  - Diamond Care Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Butterfield St, Herston QLD 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Alexandra Hospital.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Princess Alexandra Research Foundation
Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital,
199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba Qld 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Butterfield street, Herston Qld 4006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Younger Women's Wellness after Cancer Program (YWWACP) will determine the effect of a 12 week, e-health enabled program, on the health-related quality of life (HRQoL) in women who have received treatment for breast or gynaecological cancer. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are a female aged between 20-40 years who has completed surgery, chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy within the past 12 months for early or local breast and/or gynaecological cancer. Study details Participants in this study are randomly allocated (by chance) to one of two groups. Participants in the intervention group are given access to an e-health enabled, structured health promotion program which will include an interactive iBook and website containing health information, planning and goal setting, and three personal conferences with a nurse via video-conferencing over 12 weeks. Participants in the control group will receive usual care which includes only that information and support that is given as part of usual practice through their usual clinic visits. Participants from both groups will be asked to complete questionnaires before the program begins (0 weeks), at 12 weeks, and again at 24 weeks, in order to determine the effect of the program on HRQoL, dietary intake, physical activity levels, sleep quality, levels of stress, anxiety and depression, menopausal symptoms, and sexual function. They will also have their height, weight and other anthropometric measures taken at these timepoints.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.youngerwwp.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Block 7,
Butterfield St, Herston
QLD, 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QRBW/281</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Debra Anderson</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
58 Parklands Dr, Southport QLD 4215, Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 555 28403</phone>
      <fax> +61 7 3138 3814</fax>
      <email>debra.anderson@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Janine Porter-Steele</name>
      <address>Griffith University | Menzies Health Institute 
Gold Coast Campus 
Clinical Sciences 2 (G16), Gold Coast. QLD. Australia. 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55 528935  +61 466 269 562</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.porter-steele@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Debra Anderson </name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Menzies Health Institute Queensland 
Griffith University
58 Parklands Dr, Southport QLD 4215, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 555 28403</phone>
      <fax>+617 3138 3814</fax>
      <email>debra.anderson@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Janine Porter-Steele</name>
      <address>Griffith University | Menzies Health Institute 
Gold Coast Campus 
Clinical Sciences 2 (G16), Gold Coast. QLD. Australia. 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55 528935 +61 466 269 562</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.porter-steele@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>