<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368002">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000246583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Metabolic and dietary composition of ad-libitum Paleolithic vs Australian Guide to Healthy Eating diets.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cardiovascular and metabolic effects and nutrient composition of ad-libitum Paleolithic vs Australian Guide to Healthy Eating diets in healthy females.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The baseline visit included a 20 minute dietary consultation explaining the dietary intervention with a registered Nutritionist. Those in the Paleolithic group were provided with meal ideas obtained from The Paleo Diet book (Cordain, 2011) and advised to consume lean meats, fish, eggs, nuts, fruits and vegetables, and small amounts of olive or coconut oils. Grains, cereals and dairy products, any mixed dishes or processed foods that included these items were not permitted. Dairy products were to be replaced with unsweetened almond milk. Sugarless black coffee and tea were allowed. All vegetables were permitted on the diet, except for corn, white potatoes and legumes. Sweet potatoes were offered as an alternative to white potatoes. To ensure adequate carbohydrate, additional serves of fruit were recommended. Dried fruit was limited to one tablespoon per day. The intervention was 28 days in duration. Participants were advised to consume foods on an ad-libitum basis and eat when hungry. Compliance was assessed with a daily checklist of allowable foods. Additional foods consumed outside those allowable, was recorded and coded with a serving size amount. All checklists were returned and checked for completeness. </interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects randomised to the AGHE group were counselled on how to achieve food variety in line with the five food groups and Australian dietary recommendations by a registered Nutritionist. They were advised to increase intake of vegetables, fruit and whole grain products, reduce fat intake, and consume low fat dairy products. The duration of the intervention was 28 days. Subjects received the AGHE plate poster and fridge magnet (NHMRC, 2013). No serving size amounts were discussed with subjects on either diet. Participants were advised to consume foods on an ad-libitum basis and eat when hungry. Compliance was assessed with a daily checklist of allowable foods. Additional foods consumed outside those allowable, was recorded and coded with a serving size amount. All checklists were returned and checked for completeness. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total Plasma Cholesterol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 28 Days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Weight (kg) measured with a SECA 763 digital column scale and stadiometer (SECA Ltd, USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 28 Days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fat Mass Percentage measured by BIA</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 28 Days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipid levels (Total Cholesterol, LDL Cholesterol, HDL cholesterol and Triglycerides). Fasting venous blood samples were collected by Pathwest WA. The Abbott assay was performed according to standard methods by Pathwest Ltd, Perth WA. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 28 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Palatability. This was assessed using a researcher designed questionnaire administered post intervention. </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility. This was assessed using a researcher designed questionnaire administered post intervention. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily over the 28 period. The checklist contained a list of allowable foods, which were to be ticked for each time the food was consumed. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Markers of Glucose Metabolism (Insulin and glucose). Measured via fasting venous blood samples taken by Pathwest, WA and analysed according to standard methods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 28 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Macro and micronutrient intake</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 28 days via a 3 day weighed food record. Data was analysed for macro and micronutrient composition via the use of FoodWorks Professional. All data was entered by a qualified Nutritionist.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>willingness to change dietary patterns and prepare meals for four weeks; were a non-smoker and were not participating in any other studies. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>already following any special diet including a low carbohydrate or Paleolithic diet; unwilling to change dietary patterns for four weeks;  taking any prescribed medication for blood pressure, blood glucose or blood cholesterol;  presence of any diagnosed gastrointestinal disease; renal or liver disease; cardiovascular disease; diabetes or coeliac disease or allergies to eggs, fish, diary, nuts or wheat.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment done by sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation by simple randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Dietary intervention with comparator group</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An a priori power analysis was performed using G*Power, version 3.1.9.2 prior to subject recruitment (Faul, Buchner, Erdfelder, &amp; Lang, 2014). Our calculations, based on an expected reduction of 16% in total plasma cholesterol in healthy subjects, with an a-error = 0.05, 80% power and a large effect size (0.5), provided a sample requirement of 17 subjects in each group. 

All dietary intake data was entered into FoodWorks v7.0 (Xyris Software, 2012) for analysis of energy and nutrient intakes. Anthropometric and biochemical data were recorded in a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet. Pre and post intervention data and a data set created for the change variables were transferred to SPSS v22.0.0.0 for analysis (IBM Corporation, 2013). Energy, nutrient and anthropometric data were assessed for normality and independent t-tests were conducted to assess differences between groups at baseline. There was a significant difference between groups at baseline for diastolic blood pressure only. A mixed model analysis of variance was used with baseline diastolic blood pressure as covariate to assess changes post-intervention. For all other data sets, a paired t-test was conducted to compare changes within groups. An independent t-test was used for normally distributed data, and a Mann-Whitney independent samples test was utilised for non-normally distributed data, to test for changes between groups.  Univariate analysis of variance was conducted to assess results independent of weight loss, energy and nutrient intake. Significance level for test statistics was set at p&lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>20/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>39</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6027 - Joondalup</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Edith Cowan University, School of Exercise and Health Science</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Edith Cowan University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is an increased awareness in the medical community about the role of diet to prevent and treat cardiovascular disease, diabetes and obesity.
This study will examine two different eating patterns and assess their effect on risk factors for cardiovascular disease, diabetes and obesity. 
The study comprises a 4-week dietary intervention, with data collection occurring at the beginning  and again at the end of the 4-week period. 
We will be comparing the differences in results between the two dietary patterns. This will help us formulate the best dietary pattern to use for future studies, and also to assist the wider community in the treatment and prevention of cardiovascular disease, diabetes and obesity.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>The data analysis is still underway (previous status now amended) - several publications from the study are currently being prepared.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Edith Cowan University Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10176</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368002-Genoni 10176 Ethics Approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Angela Genoni</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University
School of Exercise and Health Science
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 402 171 009</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agenoni@our.ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Angela Genoni</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University
School of Exercise and Health Science
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 402 171 009</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agenoni@our.ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Angela Genoni</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University
School of Exercise and Health Science
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 402 171 009</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agenoni@our.ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Angela Genoni</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University
School of Exercise and Health Science
Building 21.501F
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 402 171 009</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agenoni@our.ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>