<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365565">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000324516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Prospective Double Blinded, Randomised, Placebo-Controlled Study to Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of Two (2) Herbal Formulations in Reducing Menopausal Symptoms in Otherwise Healthy Women.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Double Blinded, Randomised, Placebo-Controlled Study to Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of Two (2) Herbal Formulations in Reducing Menopausal Symptoms in Otherwise Healthy Women.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Menopause</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Menstruation and menopause</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. The Active intervention 1 is a 0 size blue-green hard gelatin capsules containing Tinospora Cardifolia 75mg, Asparagus racemosus 100mg, Withania somnifera 100mg, Commiphora mukul 225mg. (1 capsule, taken twice daily for 3 months)

2. The Active intervention 2 is a 0 size blue-green hard gelatin capsule containing 300mg of a standardised extract of Trigonella foenum graecum (Fenugreek) seed extract and 30mg of the flow agent maltodextrin. (1 capsule, taken twice daily for 3 months)

Compliance is measured by regular follow up (telephone, text and email) and the return of trial bottles (with any unused product) at completion of the trial.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo product is a 0 size blue-green hard gelatin capsule containing maltodextrin.
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of Menopause assessed using the MENQOL questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of Investigational products - serum assays for red blood cells, white blood cells and liver function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Heterosexual females aged between 40 and 65 years Experiencing menopausal symptoms
Otherwise healthy
Written informed consent provided</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women that have been using hormone replacement or herbal medicines for menopausal symptoms for at least 1 month prior to trial.
Women with a previous history, presence, or suspicion of estrogen-dependent neoplasia, neoplastic disease or treatment for any neoplastic disease within the previous 2 years.
Women that have had a partial or total hysterectomy.
Women that have active or a recent history (in the last 6 months) of thromboembolic disease.
Women that have a history of cerebrovascular accident, stroke, or transient ischemia. 
Women that have major depressive disorder, bipolar disorder, psychotic disorder, or generalized anxiety disorder requiring therapy. 
Women that have a known or suspected hypersensitivity to any of the herbal ingredients present in the investigational product.
Women that are taking medication for diabetes, high cholesterol, hypertension, osteoporosis and osteoarthritis, administering laxatives or have digestive disease(s).
Women that are currently using other investigational product(s).
Women that have experienced unintended weight loss of more than 15% of body weight in last six months.
Women with active substance abuse (alcohol or drug dependency).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The potential participants are screened by the medicial monitor for inclusion
in the study.
The eligible participants are enrolled by Investigator and provided with a
"Numbered Container" that is identical to all other containers and contains
the same information on the label, except for the NUMBER.
The investigator is blinded to the product randomized with the numbered
containers labelled prior to delivery to Investigational Site.
Product allocated as participants are enrolled in sequential order (1-180).</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer randomized software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size
Power analysis for frequency of daily hot flushes: p=&lt;0.05, 80% confidence, 25% reduction with SD 4.5 (difference between groups), minimum n= 53 (per group). Taking into account potential drop-outs, 60 will be recruited per group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>180</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4005 - New Farm</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Integrated Health Group Pry. Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit 3, 59 Merthyr Road
New Farm Brisbane 4005 QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gencor Pacific Ltd. Hong Kong</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>21-E, Elegance Court
Hillgrove Village
Discovery Bay</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of two herbal formulations in reducing menopausal symptoms in otherwise healthy women.

Participants will be enrolled in the study between September 2014 and October 2015 and provided treatment for 3 months.

All participants are provided with the treatment pack  which includes the product (active intervention 1, active intervention 2 or placebo), a daily symptom diary and a pre-prepared QML pathology form for safety profiling and hormone assessment.
Participants take the medication daily and complete the symptom diary daily for 1 week/month.
At month 1 and month 2, a telephone interview is conducted to confirm compliance and complete the QOL questionnaires.
At month 3, participants repeat the blood test at a QML collection centre and they return to the clinic for final assessment.
There will be regular communication with all participants during the study.

There will be supervision of the trial by a qualified Medical Practitioner / Endocrinologist, A/Prof Warrick Inder who will monitor any adverse events associated with the trial. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Clinical Trial Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, 88 Jephson Street
Toowong, QLD, 4066</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Rao</name>
      <address>Integrated Health Group Pty Ltd
PO Box 68
New Farm QLD 4005</address>
      <phone>+61 414488559</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@integratedhealthgroup.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Rao</name>
      <address>Integrated Health Group Pty Ltd
PO Box 68
New Farm QLD 4005</address>
      <phone>+61 414488559</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@integratedhealthgroup.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Rao</name>
      <address>Integrated Health Group Pty Ltd
PO Box 68
New Farm QLD 4005</address>
      <phone>+61 414488559</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@integratedhealthgroup.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Rao</name>
      <address>Integrated Health Group Pty Ltd
PO Box 68
New Farm QLD 4005</address>
      <phone>+61 414488559</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda@integratedhealthgroup.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>