<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363265">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001200875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes in anterior chamber characteristics measured with a dual Scheimpflug analyzer and an anterior segment optical coherence tomography after laser in situ keratomileusis for myopia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK) surgery affect anterior chamber characteristics measured with a dual Scheimpflug analyzer and an anterior segment optical coherence tomography in myopic patients?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myopia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this study, all participants undergo standard laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK) surgery in both eyes only once. The LASIK procedures are performed in each eye by first creating a superiorly hinged corneal flap using the Hansatome microkeratome with a 160 micron m head and 8.5 mm ring. The laser ablation is performed using excimer Laser with a goal of emmetropia. The surgery procedures usually takes about 20 minutes for each patient. The central anterior chamber depth (ACD), anterior chamber volume (ACV), average radius of posterior axial curvature (ARPAC) are measured using the Galilei Scheimpflug analyser. Measurements with the dual Scheimpflug analyzer are performed according to the manufacturers guidelines. The
device is brought into focus and the subjects eye is
aligned along the visual axis by a central fixation light. The
subjects are asked to sit back after each measurement,
and the device is realigned before each measurement.The superior, inferior, nasal, temporal anterior chamber angles (ACAs) are respectively measured using Visante anterior segment optical coherence tomography (AS-OCT). Scans of the ACAs of each eye are obtained at the 3 and 9 oclock positions (horizontal), and at the 6 and 12 oclock positions (vertical). Subjects are instructed to blink prior to all measurements and open their eyes wide during scan acquisition. As the eyelids may interfere with AS-OCT image acquisition of the ACA at 6 and 12 oclock positions, the upper and lower lids are gently moved out of the way to image the superior and inferior angle- taking care to avoid inadvertent pressure on the globe. Measurements using the Galilei and Visante AS-OCT are taken before and 2 weeks and 2 months after LASIK. Each measurement needs about 5 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>To compare the postoperative anterior chamber parameters with preoperative values, including central ACD, ACV, ACAs, ARPAC.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in anterior chamber volume after surgery measured by the Galilei Scheimpflug analyer</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks and 2 months after LASIK</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>changes in anterior chamber angles after surgery measured by Visante AS-OCT</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks and 2 months after LASIK</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in central anterior chamber depth after surgery measured by the Galilei Scheimpflug analyzer</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks and 2 months after LASIK</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in average radius of posterior axial curvature after surgery measured by the Galilei Scheimpflug analyzer</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks and 2 months after LASIK</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Myopic patients with stable refraction for at least 2 years, no contact lens wear for 2 weeks prior to the baseline examination</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>history of following diseases: keratoconus or keratoconus suspect, corneal dystrophy, ocular trauma, diabetes, retinal disease, glaucoma and severe dry eye disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Guangdong Province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zhong Xingwu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>54 South Xianlie Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510060</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Guangdong Natural Science Foundation (S2012010008821)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>171 Lianxin Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510033</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Wu Junshu</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>54 South Xianlie Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510060</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Zhongshan Ophthalmic Center</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>54 South Xianlie Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510060</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>China</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Laser in situ keratomileusis (LASIK) has been proven to be safe and effective for correction of myopia and myopic astigmatism. However, postoperative complications such as iatrogenic corneal protrusion occasionally occurred. Given that the position of the lens is unchangeable after refractive surgery, the corneal protrusion should be associated with structural changes of the anterior segment such as deepening of the anterior chamber depth. Most of the previous studies mainly focused on the central or midperipheral anterior chamber structure, but ignored the changes of peripheral anterior chamber parameters post-LASIK. In the present study, we plan to investigate the anterior chamber characteristics changes after LASIK not only in terms of central anterior chamber structure, but also in terms of peripheral anterior chamber angles. The purpose is to evaluate the effects of LASIK surgery on anterior ocular structures.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee of Zhongshan Ophthalmic Center of Sun Yat-sen University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>54 South Xianlie Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510060</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011KYNL037</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Zhong Xingwu</name>
      <address>54 South Xianlie Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510060</address>
      <phone>+86 13609649279</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zhongxwu@mail.sysu.edu.cn</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Wu Junshu</name>
      <address>54 South Xianlie Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510060</address>
      <phone>+86 020 87330381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wujs78@126.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Wu Junshu</name>
      <address>54 South Xianlie Road, Yuexiu District, Guangzhou
Postcode: 510060</address>
      <phone>+86 020 87330381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wujs78@126.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>