<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369145">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000211460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The role of exhaled nitric oxide in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease undergoing abdominal surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The role of exhaled nitric oxide in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease undergoing abdominal surgery: evaluation of postoperative complications</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-7249</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NOXIOUS (exhaled Nitric OXIde in patients with chronic Obstructive pulmonary disease Undergoing Surgery)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post-operative complications following abdominal surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Preoperative examination for patients scheduled for major abdominal surgeries with diagnosis of COPD for:
- FEV1%pred (the predicted amount as a percentage of the forced expiratory lung volume in one second) using a spirometric test according to the standard procedure
- the 6 minute walking distance test (6 MWD)
- the Modified Medical Research Council Dyspnoea Scale (MMRC).
- the body mass index (BMI)
In additional to all above standard care examinations all patients will be examined for exhaled NO measurement using a portable NO analyzer.
All the examinations will be performed from an experienced anesthetist, within 1 week prior to surgery.
The approximate duration of preoperative examinations is 1 hour.

All patients are administered premedication with diazepam 5mg orally in the evening and in the morning before surgery. 
The induction of anesthesia includes intravenous infusion of midazolam 2,5 mg, 0,1mg fentanyl, propofol 2-2,5 mg/kg and rocuronium 0,6 mg/kg. 
Perioperative monitoring includes ECG, blood pressure measurement, Central Venous Pressure measurement, pulse oximeter and capnograph. 
Postoperatively all complications are recordeded as laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea as well as the need for corticosteroids or bronchodilators administration. 
The values of blood gases 1 and 3 hours postoperatively as well as 3 days after surgery are recorded.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The aim of this study was to evaluate the relationship between exhaled NO in COPD patients undergoing major abdominal surgeries and the risk of presenting postoperative complications
The postoperative complications as laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea will be assessed using clinical examination combined with the recorded use of  corticosteroids and bronchodilators. 
The values of blood gases 1 and 3 hours postoperatively as well 3 days after surgery will be recorded using a blood gas analyzer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Perioperatively and 1-3 days postoperatively</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the diagnostic performance of exhaled NO combined with the classic clinical and laboratory evaluation tests
The evaluation will be achieved after comparing the complication incidence and correlating the results with exhaled NO values, FEV1%pred (the predicted amount as a percentage of the forced expiratory lung volume in one second), the 6MWD test, the MMRC and the BODE Index scores.
The postoperative complications as laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea will be assessed using clinical examination combined with the recorded use of  corticosteroids and bronchodilators. 
The values of blood gases 1 and 3 hours postoperatively as well 3 days after surgery will be recorded using a blood gas analyzer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>- NO values, FEV1%pred, 6MWD test, MMRC, BODE Index scores:1-2 days preoperatively
- Laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea using clinical examination combined with the recorded use of  corticosteroids and bronchodilators, values of blood gases :perioperatively
- FEV1%pred, Laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea using clinical examination combined with the recorded use of  corticosteroids and bronchodilators, values of blood gases: 1-3 days postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the diagnostic performance of exhaled NO for the identification of not well-controlled COPD surgical patients The maximun exhaled NO value for normal patients is defined as 15 while pathological is 16 or more. Patients in one group have well-controlled COPD defined by a NO value of 18 or less while patients from other group have not-well controlled COPD defined by a NO value of 19 or more The evaluation will be achieved after comparing the complication incidence between two groups. The postoperative complications as laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea will be assessed using clinical examination combined with the recorded use of corticosteroids and bronchodilators. The values of blood gases 1 and 3 hours postoperatively as well 3 days after surgery will be recorded using a blood gas analyzer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>- NO values, FEV1%pred, 6MWD test, MMRC, BODE Index scores:1-2 days preoperatively
- Laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea using clinical examination combined with the recorded use of  corticosteroids and bronchodilators, values of blood gases :perioperatively
- FEV1%pred, Laryngospasm, bronchospasm, cough, dyspnea and tachypnea using clinical examination combined with the recorded use of  corticosteroids and bronchodilators, values of blood gases: 1-3 days postoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients scheduled for major abdominal surgeries that were evaluated from an experienced physician were enrolled for the study.
The inclusion criteria are:
- age 18-75 years
- a diagnosis of COPD according to the American Thoracic Society (ATS) criteria in a stable condition and free from exacerbations in the preceding four weeks
- ASA physical status II, III, IV
- Smoking patients</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with:
- other organ failure
- cancer
- inability to cooperate
-  patients with a recent exacerbation (e.g. requiring hospitalization or oral corticosteroids) 
- patients with another or coexisting respiratory disorder (e.g. COPD and bronchiectasis) </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>All statistics will be  using SPSS statistical package for Windows, version 22.0. 
Normally distributed data will be presented as mean +/- SE. 
Comparisons between groups for non parametric data will be performed with Kruskall Wallis test followed by Dunns post-hoc tests. 
Parametric data will be analyzed using ANOVA and the post hoc test with Bonferroni correction used when requested. 
A p value of &lt;0.05 will be considered significant.
In order to specify the number of participants needed to achieve statistical significant measuremets a power analysis was conducted using the results obtained from 10 first patients. According to those results, in order to have a power of 0.8-0.9 in our results the essential number of patients is approximately 100.
The significance level p=0.05 is also used in the sample size calculations.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>26/02/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>70</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faculty of Medicine, University of Thessaly</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Thessaly
Argonafton &amp; Filellinon, 
38221 Volos, 
Magnesia
Greece</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Greece</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Faculty of Medicine, University of Thessaly </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Argonafton &amp; Filellinon,  38221 Volos,  Magnesia Greece</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Greece</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Achillopouleion General Hospital of Volos</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Polymeri 134, 38222, Volos, Magnesia
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Greece</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) has been associated with major perioperative morbidities or mortalities especially in surgical patients receiving general anesthesia. The severity of the COPD and the degree of bronchial hyperreactivity will determine the perioperative anesthetic risk, therefore they have to be assessed by a thorough preoperative evaluation in order to give the rationale on which to decide for the adequate anaesthetic techniques. Increased levels of exhaled nitric oxide (eNO) have been reported in patients with advanced chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).
The present study investigates if the levels of exhaled NO in patients with COPD can predict the risk for complications after surgery under general anesthesia.
Values of exhaled NO are evaluated in patients diagnosed with COPD scheduled for surgery under general anesthesia. COPD is evaluated using BODE Index score based on the Modified MRC Dyspnoea Scale, the BMI and the 6 MWD combined with the forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) parameter. 
All patients are closely observed for presenting respiratory complications postoperatively.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Achillopouleion General Hospital of Volos Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Polymeri 134, 38222, Volos, Magnesia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>222a- 6/2-04-2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Greece</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369145-ethics.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helena Logotheti</name>
      <address>Clinic of Anesthesiology, 
Achillopouleion General Hospital of Volos, 
Polymeri 134, 38222, Volos, Magnesia, 
Greece</address>
      <phone>+306977443244</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>logoeleni@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chryssa Pourzitaki</name>
      <address>Clinic of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care Unit, 
University Hospital AHEPA, 
University Campus, 54124
Faculty of Medicine, School of Health Sciences, 
Aristotle University of Thessaloniki
Greece
</address>
      <phone>+306945492971</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chpour@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chryssa Pourzitaki</name>
      <address>Clinic of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care Unit, 
University Hospital AHEPA, 
University Campus, 54124
Faculty of Medicine, School of Health Sciences, 
Aristotle University of Thessaloniki
Greece</address>
      <phone>+306945492971</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chpour@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>