<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343316">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000904976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the Sensory Outcomes between the iRASP and the Free Thenar Flap in patients with a soft tissue defect on a thumb or finger</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of the Sensory Outcomes between the iRASP and the Free Thenar Flap in patients with a volar soft tissue defect on a thumb or finger</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>coverage of soft tissue defect on a volar side of finger with sensate flap of the iRASP flap</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The iRASP flap is a new modification of the free thenar flap for constant innervation with the PCMN(Palmar Cutaneous branch of the Median Nerve). If there is a soft tissue defect on volar aspect in thumb or fingers, especially a pinching site, the iRASP flap would be applied. The procedure of the iRASP flap takes about 3 hours. The sensory outcomes will be checked by SWM(Semmes-Weinstein Monofilaments), S2PD(Static Two-Point Discrimination) and M2PD(Moving Two-Point Discrimination) tests. The results of sensory outcomes in the iRASp group will be compared with the results in the free thenar flap group. The cases of the free thenar flap which were able to be followed up was selected among the cases that had been performed before the authors designed the iRASP flap. The cases of the free thenar flap would be reviewed by medical record and evaluated by the above methods of sensory evaluation.</interventions>
    <comparator>The results of sensory evaluation in the iRASP group will be compared with the results of the results in the free thenar flap group and results of the uninjured contralateral thumb or finger in a patient. The cases of the free thenar flap which were able to be followed up was selected among the cases that had been performed before the authors designed the iRASP flap. The results of sensory restoration in the free thenar flap group was evaluated during two months (March, 2010 to April, 2010). Statistical analysis with median test would be applied for comparison.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SWM(Semmes-Weinstein Monofilaments) Test that can measures the integrity of afferent fibers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This test will be performed at every month after coverage with the iRASP flap for a total of 12 months. 
In the free thenar flap group, this test was conducted when the patient visited.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>S2PD(Static Two-Point Discrimination) test is a discrimination test. The ability can distinguish the two-point applied on skin as two point. If sensory recovery is not enough, a patient can not distinguish two-point as a one point. It can evaluates the slowly-adapting fiber-receptor system (constant touch).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This test will be performed at every month after coverage with the iRASP flap for a total of 12 months.
In the free thenar flap group, this test was conducted when the patient visited.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>M2PD(Moving Two-Point Discrimination) test can evaluates the innervation density of the quickly-adapting fiber-receptor system which mediates the perception of stimuli moving across the hand.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This test will be performed at every month after coverage with the iRASP flap for a total of 12 months.
In the free thenar flap group, this test was conducted when the patient visited.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>complications(tender scar, limitation of thumb motion or neuroma formation)
Tender scar will be assessed by visual analogue scale that a patient express the amount of discomfort. Limitation of thumb motion on a injured hand ( a same side of the donor site of the iRASP or the free thenar flap) will be assessed by measuring the angle of palmar and radial abduction of thumb. The measured angles will be compared with the results of uninjured (contralateral) hand. The formation of neuroma will be tested by the Tinel's sign. The amount of discomfort will be expressed by the visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In both groups of the iRASP and the free thenar flap, these complications will be evaluated. The iRASP flap group will be checked serially every month for up to 6 months postoperatively. The free thenar flap group will be assessed at the time of follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>In both groups of the iRASP and the free thenar flap, the patients have a volar soft tissue defect on a thumb or finger. A defect is located on pinching area and relatively large not covered easily by small sized flaps like cross finger flap or free partial toe pulp flap.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A patient having a general disease related with nerve recovery or compressive neuropathy should be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/10/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>6</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>JAE-WON YANG</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hand and Microsurgery Center,
Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery,
Kwang-Myung Sung-Ae General Hospital,
389, Chul-San-3-Dong,Gwang-Myeong-Si,
Gyeong-Gi-Do, 423-711</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Korea, Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is intended to compare sensory restoration between the iRASP (sensate flap) and the free thenar flap (nonsensate flap). Because, it was reported that the free thenar flap has satisfactory result of sensory restoration even though the flap do not incorporate a nerve for innervation. It is worthy whether the sensate iRASP flap sacrificing a nerve is necessary. Our data will be useful for a surgeon deciding between a sensate or non-sensate flap for coverage of a volar soft tissue defect on a thumb or finger.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gwang-Myeong Sung-Ae IRB(Institutional Review Board)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>389, Chul-San-3-Dong,
Gwang-Myeong-Si,
Gyeong-Gi-Do, 423-711</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Korea, Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>JAE-WON YANG</name>
      <address>Hand and Microsurgery Center,
Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery,
Kwang-Myung Sung-Ae General Hospital,
389, Chul-San-3-Dong,
Gwang-Myeong-Si,
Gyeong-Gi-Do, 423-711</address>
      <phone>+82-2-2680-7238</phone>
      <fax>+82-2-2615-7218</fax>
      <email>jwonyang@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>JAE-WON YANG</name>
      <address>Hand and Microsurgery Center,
Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery,
Gwang-Myeong Sung-Ae General Hospital,
389, Chul-San-3-Dong,
Gwang-Myeong-Si,
Gyeong-Gi-Do, 423-711</address>
      <phone>+82-2-2680-7238</phone>
      <fax>+82-2-2615-7218</fax>
      <email>jwonyang@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>JAE-WON YANG</name>
      <address>Hand and Microsurgery Center,
Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery,
Kwang-Myung Sung-Ae General Hospital,
389, Chul-San-3-Dong,
Gwang-Myeong-Si,
Gyeong-Gi-Do, 423-711</address>
      <phone>+82-2-2680-7238</phone>
      <fax>+82-2-2615-7218</fax>
      <email>jwonyang@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>