<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336084">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000867099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Acute effect of differents forms of heating on muscle strength</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of aerobic heating and static stretching on muscle strength with 16 female participants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-4665</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>not have a secondary ID</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>muscle fatigue</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We assessed the strength of the 16 women. After the 16 women were divided into three groups. The first group made the passive stretching of the quadriceps muscle. After being targeted, were positioned supine with the legs off the gurney. Initially, the nondominant should remain flexed at the hip and knee, being held by the participant toward the chest (holding member) as the dominant member, with the aid of assessors, was positioned in hip extension and knee flexion (position the Thomas test) to the limit in which the participant reported being endurable maximum stress feeling of extending the knee extensor muscles, but without pain. The stretch was held for 30 seconds. After an interval of 1 minute, the procedure was repeated on the same limb. We conducted four repetitions of each member alternately. The second group held the  aerobic exercise in the bike. The exercise was conducted at a speed between 60 and 70 rounds per minute with 50 W load for 10 minutes. The third group performed static stretching, and after 1 minute warm up in the bike performed aerobics in the same manner as described above. 
After 1 minute of completing the heating was re-evaluated the strength of each participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no control group in the study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Will be evaluated through the Isokinetic dynamometer the performance of muscle strength in knee extension. Three variables will be observed that the equipment provides: concentric peak torque, eccentric peak torque and total work.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 minute after warn up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a) be classified as active or irregularly active through the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) short version b) do not submit musculoskeletal injuries that hindered the completion of the evaluation and implementation of the exercise program.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Males, do submit musculoskeletal injuries that hindered the completion of the evaluation and implementation of the exercise program and do not be classified as active or irregularly active through the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) short version</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Integrated Schools in Brazil</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rua Konrad Adenauer, 442  Taruma (Curitiba/PR)
CEP: 82821-020</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Integrated Schools in Brazil</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rua Konrad Adenauer, 442  Taruma (Curitiba/PR)
CEP: 82821-020</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clinical Knee</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Avenida Presidente Getulio Vargas, 3066  Agua Verde (Curitiba/PR)
CEP: 80240-041</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to evaluate the muscle strength of knee extensors, before and after applying with static stretching (SSG), aerobic exercise (AEG) and the combination of both (SSG + AEG), checking in this way, the effects of different types of warm on muscle strength. For this participated in the study 16 women (age 22.5 +/- 4.7 years, BMI 20.8 +/- 1.83 kg/m2), they were divided into three groups (SSG, AEG and SSG + AEG). The verified variables were: concentric peak torque, eccentric peak torque and total work. Each group, after evaluating of the strength in the isokinetic dynamometer then of minimum 48 hours, performed a warm-up protocol and reviewed the force. The results indicated that there was no significant inter-and / or intra protocols on the observed variables, considering a significance level of p = 0.05. Therefore, we concluded that, acutely, the performance of muscle strength in knee extension did not change significantly after the different protocols used for heating.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Juliana Paula Maschio</name>
      <address>Rua Macapa, 1236, Tingui (Curitiba/PR)
CEP: 82620 110</address>
      <phone>(5541) 9929 3474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maschio.juliana@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cecilia Voloschen de Albuquerque</name>
      <address>Rua Francisco Mota Machado, 879,  Capao da Imbuia (Curitiba/PR)
CEP: 82800 230</address>
      <phone>(5541) 9668 3707</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ceciliavoloschen@pop.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>