<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82509">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/01/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000014358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Young @ Heart: A randomised controlled trial of a multi-disciplinary home based healthcare program for cardiac patients in the private healthcare system</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled study of a multi-disciplinary home based health care program for cardiac patients in the private healthcare sector to reduce the rate of re-hospitalisation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Young@Heart</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Young @ Heart Study</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention involves a nurse coordinated multidisciplinary intervention with home visits involving clinical assessment, medication knowledge and assessment, overall self-care abilities, social status and current use of health care resources. Home visits occur within 2 weeks of discharge from hospital and this will be performed over the initial 6 months with median follow-up for 2.5 years. Each visit will be of 1 to 1.5 hours duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care following hospital discharge which involves General Practitioners (GP) follow-up, out-patients appointment with specialist physician as required.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of all-cause hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mean of 2.5 years follow-up following initial hospital admission.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost per Quality Adjusted Life Years (QALY)- [a commonly used instrument used in health economics] and cardiac-related hospitalisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mean follow-up of 2.5 years following inital hospital admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual quality of life, functional status and overall healthcare satisfaction. The tools used will be the SF-12 for quality of life, the Montreal Cognitive Assessment Tool to examine cognitive function and the EQ-5D and CES-Depression scale to examine mental health status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 3 years follow-up period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All elective and emergency patients admitted to St Andrews or Wesley Hospital, Brisbane and have MBF private health insurance, discharged to home and diagnosed with chronic heart disease:  Coronary artery disease, chronic heart failure and chronic atrial fibrillation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those &lt; 45 years, not in the three diagnostic groups, not being discharged home, have congenital heart condition, a terminal malignancy, live beyond 25 km of the hospital or have surgically repairable heart disease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A blinded, randomisation protocol (using SPSS 14.0) via Preventative Cardiology at the Baker Heart Research Institute, will allocate eligible patients to the study intervention or usual care (on a 1:1 basis) (Central randomisation). Randomisation will only occur after informed consent has been obtained from eligible patients and via a blinded protocol.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on 1:1 randomization and 85% power (two-sided alpha of 0.05), we calculated that 300 patients in each group (600 in total) would be sufficient to detect an absolute 20% difference in the primary outcome. 
Between group (univariate) comparisons were assessed by Students t-tests, Mann Whitney U test (for non-normally distributed continuous data) and Chi-squared test (with calculation of odd ratios [OR] and 95% confidence intervals [CIs]) where appropriate. All-cause mortality and event-free survival data were initially analyzed using Kaplan Meier survival curves. Hospital costs were calculated per patient per day of study follow-up. All costs are expressed in 2011/12 Australian dollars (AU$1.00  US$1.00). Backward, step-wise Cox proportional hazards models (including baseline demographic and clinical profile data) were constructed to examine the independent impact of group allocation on: i) event-free survival from all-cause death or hospitalization,  ii) all-cause mortality and iii) event-free survival from cardiovascular-related hospitalization. Analyses were also performed on a sex-specific basis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/06/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/01/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>602</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>602</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Preventive Cardiology
75 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bupa Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>600 Glenferrie Road
HAWTHORN VIC 3122
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bupa Health Fundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>600 Glenferrie Road
HAWTHORN VIC 3122
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this randomised controlled study is to examine the impact of a nurse-coordinated multidisciplinary intervention on the rate of all-cause hospital stay relative to usual care in privately health insured patients discharged from hospital with chronic heart disease. The mean follow-up will be 2.5 years follow-up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Chan YK, Stewart S, Calderone A, Scuffham P, Goldstein S, Carrington MC. Exploring the potential to remain "Young @ Heart": Initial findings of a multi-centre, randomised study of a nurse-led, home-based intervention in a hybrid health care system. Int J Cardiol 2012;154(1):52-8.
2. Carrington MJ, Chan YK, Calderone A, Scuffham PA, Esterman A, Goldstein S, Stewart S. A multicenter, randomized trial of a nurse-led, home-based intervention for optimal secondary cardiac prevention suggests some benefits for men but not for women: the Young at Heart study. Circulation Cardiovascular quality and outcomes 2013;6:379-389.
3. Byrnes J, Carrington M, Chan YK, Pollicine C, Dubrowin N, Stewart S, Scuffham P. Cost-effectiveness of a home based intervention for secondary prevention of readmission with chronic heart disease. PLoS ONE 2015;10(12):e0144545.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uniting Hospitals Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Uniting Hospitals
Brisbane QLD 4000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/11/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2000773</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Melinda Carrington</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University
Level 5, 215 Spring St, Melbourne, VIC  3000</address>
      <phone>+61399533688</phone>
      <fax>+61396635726</fax>
      <email>melinda.carrington@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Melinda Carrington</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University
Level 5, 215 Spring St, Melbourne, VIC  3000</address>
      <phone>+61399533688</phone>
      <fax>+61396635726</fax>
      <email>melinda.carrington@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yih Kai Chan</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University
Level 5, 215 Spring St, Melbourne, VIC  3000</address>
      <phone>+61392308054</phone>
      <fax>+61396635726</fax>
      <email>yihkai.chan@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Simon Stewart</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University
Level 5, 215 Spring St, Melbourne, VIC  3000</address>
      <phone>+61399533677</phone>
      <fax>+61396635726</fax>
      <email>simon.stewart@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>