<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373218">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001067369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Single patient multiple cross-over trials to determine the efficacy of pilocarpine 5 mg orally dissolving tablets in patients suffering from dry mouth.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Single patient multiple cross-over trials to determine the efficacy of pilocarpine 5 mg orally dissolving tablets in relieving xerostomia 

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-5399 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Xerostomia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single patient trials (n-of-1 or SPTs) of 5 mg pilocarpine orally dissolving tablets (ODTs) vs placebo ODTs,  one tablet orally, 3 times per day for 18 days consisting of 3 cycles. Each cycle contains two periods: 3 days treatment, 3 days placebo. The first day of each period is considered to be the washout and data collected will not be included in analysis. The order of treatment and placebo will be randomly allocated for each cycle. Treatment allocation will be blinded to the participant and the Primary Investigator.

Participants will take one dose of trial medication 60 minutes prior to breakfast, lunch and dinner, each day for the 18 day trial. They will collect saliva samples in pre-labelled tubes 60 minutes after taking the breakfast and dinner doses, just before eating. Participants will complete a daily diary recording symptom scores using validated measures for dry mouth and related symptoms, the presence of any side effects and their estimate of which drug they believe they are taking at the time. The principal investigator will call every participant every 3 days to check their compliance with the medication and completing the daily diary and if there are any adverse effects or serious adverse effects.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment will be be matching placebo orally dissolving tablets, one tablet to be taken three times daily. All orally dissolving tablets are made from: Medi-RDT base, a sucrose-free, finely granulated powder that is compatible with a wide range of active ingredients, Bitterness Reducing Agent (NF01) Natural (Powder), flavour (Powder) and stevia powder (stevioside) as sweetener. All components are pharmaceutical grade.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in each of the three questions of the Subjective Rating of Symptoms questionnaire across the 3 cycles of the trial. This questionnaire is completed by the participant three times a day after each dose taken. Improvement of 2 or more on the 0-10  numerical rating scale (NRS )compared to baseline is classified as a response,</outcome>
      <timepoint>  Baseline and three times daily for 18 days after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in weight of saliva across the 3 cycles of the trial. Saliva will be collected by the participants twice daily (60 minutes after the morning dose and 60 minutes after the evening dose) and mailed to the Principal Investigator at the end of the trial for weighing. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and twice daily for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in the Summated Xerostomia Inventory Dutch-version (SXI-D) scores, a 5-item validated shortened summated rating scale that represents the severity of dysphagia,  measured daily across the 3 cycles of the trial. The significance of the difference between treatment and placebo will be tested at P&lt;0.05   </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and once daily for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in the	Xerostomia-related Quality of Life Scale (XeQOLS) score, a 15-item validated questionnaire,  across the 3 cycles of the trial.. The XeQOLS is completed at the end of each period. The significance of the difference between treatment and placebo will be tested at P&lt;0.05</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and every 3 days for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in the scores for the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) of the EQ-5D, a 5 item questionnaire which assesses the overall health performance,  across the 3 cycles of the trial. The EQ-5D is completed at the end of each period. The significance of the difference between treatment and placebo in VAS will be tested at P&lt;0.05. The scores for the 5 domains, which have a 3-point scale, will be used descriptively </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and every 3 days for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change from baseline in the global score for the Oral Health Impact Profile (OHIP), a 14 item questionnaire that has been validated in a population with xerostomia,  across the 3 cycles of the trial. The OHIP is completed at the end of each period. The significance of the difference between treatment and placebo will be tested at P&lt;0.05 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and every 3 days for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the number of people reporting that they experienced each of the adverse events listed in the symptom checklist included in the daily diary, which are assessed daily, will be made between treatment and placebo. The significance of the difference in number of people experiencing each adverse event between treatment and placebo will be tested at P&lt;0.05. AEs assessed are: Increased sweating, urinary frequency, rhinitis, flushing, nausea/vomiting, dizziness, chills, asthenia, dyspepsia, headache and diarrhoea. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and daily for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of uses of other saliva treatments, self-reported daily in the study diary; Differences between treatment and placebo will be assessed descriptively. Consideration of use is important because it may affect their rating of the Subjective Rating of Symptoms questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and daily for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants guessing of the intervention taken over the past three days, either the drug or the placebo to ensure proper masking of the bitter taste of pilocarpine and hence adequate blinding.</outcome>
      <timepoint>every 3 days for 18 days after the intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males and females aged 18 years or older.
To ensure that xerostomia is significant enough to warrant treatment with pilocarpine, participants must self-report xerostomia of any etiology as a score of 3 or more on a numerical rating scale (NRS) from 0  10 (where 0 = no dry mouth and 10 = worst possible dry mouth) . 
As pilocarpine action requires some residual salivary function, participants must self-report evidence of saliva production in the mouth upon chewing a piece of gum .
Participants are able and willing to give appropriate informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Ocular problems contraindicating the use of parasympathetic agents (e.g. irido-cyclitis, increased intra-ocular pressure);
Other comorbidity where there is a risk of worsening co-existing medical problems during the trial period and/or active treatment is contemplated. For example, severe or uncontrolled asthma or pulmonary disease, uncontrolled hypotension or hypertension, hyperthyroidism, uncontrolled seizures or cardiac arrythmias, (especially bradycardias) and Parkinson's disease. If these diseases are well controlled, they do not constitute exclusion criteria.
An active oral infection i.e. candidiasis, herpetic infections, mucositis, mouth ulcers;
Suspected or confirmed pregnancy;
Intervention (e.g. radiotherapy, chemotherapy, surgery that might alter dry mouth symptoms during the 2 weeks prior to the study period or plans to undergo such therapy during the study period;
Plans to change any medication with the potential to cause dry mouth within the trial period; 
Plans to use any other prescribed medication which is known to increase saliva production and relieve dry mouth during the trial period. Patients already on pilocarpine are eligible, but must stop taking it 1 week before trial commencement;
A poor understanding of written or spoken English that would preclude completion of all trial requirements
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be done via central randomization by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation will be done by simple randomization using a randomization table created by computer software (computerized sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power calculations were based on the primary outcome variable, the NRS score, and a pooled baseline score across groups had mean 3.250 (standard deviation 2.975) from a cross-over study of 70 patients comparing artificial saliva and pilocarpine in the management of xerostomia in patients with advanced cancer. An article on testing the xerostomia inventory was used to estimate patients intra class correlation, ICC. Simulations in Stata programmed to model the repeated measures design, attrition rates and variances revealed that 70 patients are required to detect a 2 cm change in NRS. With this, we would expect 44% to complete all 3 cycles, 6% complete 2 cycles, 10% complete 1 cycle, and 28% will fail to complete any cycles, ie, (31x3)+(4x2)+(7x1)=106 cycles delivered by 42 people. With 20% attrition,  the required number of participants is 51.

Both individual and population treatment differences will be estimated via fitting Bayesian hierachial model with noninformative priors. Where necessary, the appropriateness of the assumed likelihood distributions will be assessed for violations and data transformations undertaken. Markov chain Monte Carlo methods will be used to sample from the posterior distribution of the parameters, and conventional burn-in periods, model convergence, stability diagnostics and goodness-of-fit checks will be employed. The software package WinBUGS will be used for the Bayesian analysis.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>51</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>18/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St. Lucia, QLD, 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Pharmacy, University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Cornwall St, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Xerostomia or dry mouth is a major problem that many people experience, especially those who have received radiotherapy for the treatment of head and neck cancer and it accompanies other diseases such as Sjögren syndrome. Saliva plays many vital roles in our daily life and people with reduced saliva production can experience a variety of health problems.

Pilocarpine is a medication that stimulates the nerves supplying the salivary glands. This stimulates the production of your own saliva. The effect lasts for about three hours, and so it is usually taken three times daily. Pilocarpine is usually taken before a meal to produce more saliva in time for eating.

Pilocarpine is only available as eye drops to treat glaucoma in Australia, but tablets are available for treating dry mouth in many countries around the world. This trial investigates pilocarpine orally dissolving tablets (ODTs), which are little tablets that dissolve rapidly in the mouth and can be compounded in pharmacies.  

This trial will provide information about whether pilocarpine ODTs are effective in treating dry mouth, and this information will help to improve management of dry mouth in Australia.

A series of single patient (N-of-1) trials of 5 mg pilocarpine ODTs (intervention) vs placebo ODTs (control) will be run, in people suffering with xerostomia, with a population estimate of the benefit following the combination of multiple SPTs. Participants will complete 18 days of treatment, consisting of 3 cycles. Each cycle contains two periods: 3 days treatment, 3 days placebo. The first day of each period is considered to be the washout and data collected will not be included in analysis. The order of treatment and placebo will be randomly allocated for each cycle. Treatment allocation will be blinded to the participant and the Primary Investigator. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Queensland
St. Lucia
QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kathryn Steadman</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy, 
The University of Queensland,
20 Cornwall St, 
Woolloongabba, 
QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61733461886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.steadman@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kathryn Steadman</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy, 
The University of Queensland,
20 Cornwall St, 
Woolloongabba, 
QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 1886</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.steadman@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Geoff Mitchell </name>
      <address>Faculty of Medicine
The University of Queensland.
St Lucia, 
QLD 4072 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.mitchell@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Rose Estafanos</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy, 
The University of Queensland,
20 Cornwall St, 
Woolloongabba, 
QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 424 689 544</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.estafanos@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>