<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373125">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000901303p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A 12 week pilot study targeted for adult consumers within a community mental health rehabilitation setting to implement a Personal Safety Tool for self-management and crisis management.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study on the use of a Personal Safety Tool for self-management and crisis management within a clinical mental health rehabilitation setting.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Borderline Personality Disorder </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Personality Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dissociative identity disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive Compulsive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Project Leads to develop a Personal Safety Tool targeted for a community mental health setting. The Personal Safety Tool aims for participants to work collaboratively with Project Leads to identify what the participant is like when they are well, what situations cause them distress and the signals of their distress. The Personal Safety Tool will offer practical suggestions for self-soothing and calming strategies during crisis situations.

 The Personal Safety Tool has been developed as a 3 page paper document which will be provided to participants to utilise at the community mental health rehabilitation program, at their home and in the community.

A range of sensory tools and strategies will be offered to participants to explore when completing their Personal Safety Tool with Project Leads support and supervision. This will include low risk calming/self-soothing and alerting strategies which targets participant senses. Project Leads are trained in implementing sensory modulation, which is the ability to assist the participant to self-regulate by providing an opportunity to participate in activities and behaviours that engage their senses. Project Leads ensure to adhere to SA Health, Northern Mental Health Services Sensory Modulation local procedure guidelines to ensure therapy is offered and facilitated in a safe manner.

Project Leads (Occupational Therapists) with 4 years mental health experience will be delivering the intervention with Project Sponsor/Team Leader support with minimum of 10 years experience in mental health.

The mode of delivery will be face to face in a public community mental health rehabilitation service. Contact will be made individually. Confidentiality requirements will be adhered to through the option to meet in a private meeting room.

The intervention will be delivered over a 12 week period. Weekly face to face contact will be delivered as well as phone calls for 15-30 minutes to support semi-structured debriefing, evaluation and follow up.

The location will be at a public community mental health rehabilitation service. Contact will be made individually.

The Personal Safety Tool will be completed collaboratively with participants and Project Leads to ensure individual needs are considered (e.g. participants early warning signs, triggers and individual sensory based coping strategies to manage in crisis). The Personal Safety Tool can be updated and amended at any time during the pilot study to meet changing needs of participants.

The Personal Safety Tool offers opportunity for consumers to add additional information which is individualised to their preferences and needs e.g. other' sections to make additional comments.

Ensuring the Personal Safety Tool is individualised is important to ensure the document is client centred, meaningful and meets Mental Health and National Safety and Quality Standards (consumer and carer participation standard). It additionally aligns with recovery, sensory modulation and trauma informed care and practice principles. 

The Personal Safety Tool pilot study will commence implementation in July 2017. This initial stage of implementation will be collaboratively completing a Personal Safety Tool with participants and support from Project Leads at the community mental health rehabilitation service. The rest of the implementation phase will be over the following 12 week period.

Project Leads will be determining adherence of the Personal Safety Tool use through weekly debriefing (e.g.  phone calls and face to face meetings). Consent forms will highlight to participants their rights to opt in and opt out of pilot study.

Project Leads have established therapeutic rapport and this will likely support opportunities for open communication around adherence and fidelity and how to mitigate any concerns expressed by participants.

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite Primary Outcome. Self-management assessed by the Sensory Modulation Crisis Management self-rating scale and Questionnaire specifically designed for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergency department presentations assessed by statistics in emergency department contacts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health hospital re-admissions assessed by statistics in inpatient presentations </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of care in mental health inpatient admissions assessed by statistics in inpatient presentations</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phone contacts to mental health crisis services assessed by review of mental health medical records/community based information system database</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult 18-65years
Mental Health Diagnosis including:
 Borderline Personality Disorder
 Anxiety
 Schizophrenia 
 Personality Disorder
 Dissociative identity disorder
 Obsessive Compulsive Disorder
 Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder

Registered consumer with Northern Community Mental Health Services 
Registered Consumer with the Northern Clinical Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Poor judgement / insight
Cognitive impairment impacting on decision making / ability to make informed consent 
Decline mental health symptoms/relapse in mental health 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Nil requirements for sample size to achieve study objectives, desirable sample size 10-20 participants 
Pre and post evaluation measures will be used to evaluate data, in the form of self-rating scales. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth Vale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Michelle Oliver </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Northern Clinical Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program 'Club 84'
84 Yorktown Road, ELIZABETH PARK, S.A., 5113</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Government of South Australia, SA Health, Northern Adelaide Local Health Network, Northern Mental Health Services, Northern Clinical Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program 'Club 84'</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>84 Yorktown Road, ELIZABETH PARK, S.A., 5113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hypothesis: Adult consumers with a mental health diagnosis will have increased skills in self-management and reduce likelihood of crisis presentations through utilising a Personal Safety Tool.

The Personal Safety Tool aims to support adult consumers within a community mental health setting who are distressed and agitated to regain a sense of calm through identifying their triggers, early warning signs and using a range of individualised sensory strategies and tools to self-soothe and self-regulate.

The Personal Safety Tool will adopt a strengths based approach and promote greater self-management in managing their symptoms and health care.

The Personal Safety Tool will work to reduce emergency department presentations, inpatient admissions and length of care in hospital. The Personal Safety Tool adopts recovery and trauma informed care principles. It additionally aligns with the Mental Health act and supports least restrictive approach e.g. reducing need for restraint and seclusion.

The pilot study will work to strengthen partnerships between Occupational Therapists within northern public mental health services and establish greater flow through of information across services. This will in turn, support continuity of communication and consumer care.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethic Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital 
28 Woodville Rd, Woodville South SA 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amily Daw</name>
      <address>Northern Clinical Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program 'Club 84'
84 Yorktown Road, ELIZABETH PARK, S.A., 5113</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7485 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7485 4511</fax>
      <email>amily.daw@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Francis</name>
      <address>Northern Clinical Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program 'Club 84'
84 Yorktown Road, ELIZABETH PARK, S.A., 5113</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7485 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7485 4511</fax>
      <email>anna.francis@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Francis</name>
      <address>Northern Clinical Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program 'Club 84'
84 Yorktown Road, ELIZABETH PARK, S.A., 5113</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7485 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7485 4511</fax>
      <email>anna.francis@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amily Daw</name>
      <address>Northern Clinical Psychosocial Rehabilitation Program 'Club 84'
84 Yorktown Road, ELIZABETH PARK, S.A., 5113</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7485 4500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7485 4511</fax>
      <email>amily.daw@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>