<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372282">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000461392p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nutrition Intervention In Metabolic Syndrome In Young People With Mental Illness (NIMSMI)  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prevention and Early Intervention for the Reduction of Risk Factors for Metabolic Syndrome in Young People with Severe Mental Illness: Health &amp; Nutrition Education Approach

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-4827 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>NIMSMI</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>schizophrenia, </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar Disorder
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Major Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will be delivered by the clinical dietitian who is a higher degree research student with the UNSW.  This dietitian provides services to people with mental illness for the past 18 years. Her dietetics experience is of more than 30 years in clinical dietetics in Australia.
a) For all participants, controls and intervention, there will be an initial individual nutritional assessment with 5 monthly follow ups/reviews (individual reviews). This is a face-to-face consultation.   Initial individual consultation will last an hour and reviews from 45 minutes to an hour according to individual needs.
b) For the randomly allocated participant to the intervention group (50%), in addition, there will be a weekly nutrition and health education session for 6 months.  Each session will last an hour taking into consideration the shortness of concentration of most people with mental illness.
This program will use power point presentations, video forums, cooking demonstrations, eating out and other activities associated with their regular mental health management and activities. 
PROGRAM FOR THE INTERVENTION GROUP
Prevention of Metabolic Syndrome in Young People with Severe Mental Illness:  A Nutrition Education &amp; Health Promotion Approach - WSLHD-MENTAL HEALTH  PEIRS, BEAT &amp; headspace - THE UNSW - SCHOOL OF PSYCHIATRY - 2017  2018
GROUP NUTRITION EDUCATION &amp; HEALTH PROMOTION PROGRAMME INTERVENTION
VENUE: PEIRS &amp; headspace Parramatta [  ]                 BEAT &amp; headspace Mt Druitt [  ]
MONTH 1
Good Eating For Healthy Young People - to reduce major risks for metabolic syndrome.
Applying the Australian Dietary Guidelines for Healthy Eating
Video
1 Recipe development: snacks 
Health Promotion
Art Therapy Evaluation

MONTH 2
Guideline 1  To achieve and maintain a healthy weight
Energy input vs Energy Expenditure
Video
2 Recipe development: meats and fish
Health Promotion
Art Therapy Evaluation

MONTH 3
Guideline 2 Enjoy a wide variety of nutritious foods
Protecting our Heart and Blood Circulation
Video
3 Recipe development: eggs
Health Promotion
Art Therapy Evaluation
MONTH 4
Guideline 3 Limit intake of foods containing saturated fat, added salt, added sugars and alcohol.
Reducing risk of Cancer with good food.
Video
4 Recipe development: fruits and drinks
Health Promotion
Art Therapy Evaluation

MONTH 5
Guideline 4 Encourage, support and promote breastfeeding.
Strong Immune System
Guideline 5 Care for your food; prepare and store it safely
Healthy Bones
Video
5 Recipe development: salads
Health Promotion
Art Therapy Evaluation
MONTH 6
Metabolic Syndrome
Diabetes
Weight  Waist C. 
Video

6 Recipe development: desserts
Health Promotion
Art Therapy Evaluation

All the participants, controls and intervention, will have an hour initial full nutritional assessment including and complemented with the following (baseline to be measured against results at 6 and 12 months from intervention):
Clinical Variable &amp; Method of Assessment	                 
Anthropometry	: At initial consultation the Dietitian will measure anthropometry: weight, height and waist circumference.	
Biochemical markers:	Full Blood Count, Lipid Profile, Fasting Glucose, Insulin Level, and HbA1c when diabetes is present. 
Clinical database maintained at Blacktown-Mental Health, PEIRS and headspace will be used.
These results will be collected on the Dietitians Referral Form.  
Physical activity levels	Simple Physical Activity Questionnaire (SIMPAQ; (Rosenbaum et al., 2011) and to be applied by the dietitian at first consultation (part of the baseline). 	
Dietary habits	Diet history obtained during first clinical consultation. Food Frequency Questionnaire 	developed by Gladys Hitchen 
The University New Castle Food Frequency Questionnaire 
Sleeping patterns-Number of hours of sleep and its pattern, and if food is eaten late at night. Sleep Quality Assessment (PSQI): validated
Nutritional supplementation-If has been prescribed, what was the reason and which supplements are being taken.
	
Why: to establish a baseline for comparison with results at 6 and 12 months from intervention. 
When: to start recruiting in March 2017 (this date needs to be changed as this application is still not approved) as soon as WSLHD-Ethics Committee and the ANZCTR Registry approve my study.
How this will occur:  Liaison with the Principal and Associated Investigators have taken place and all are ready to recruit as soon as Ethics and ANZ Registrys approval is granted. The WSLHD- Referral form for Dietetics in Mental Health will be used for the psychiatrists, nursing and allied health professionals to refer their patients to the study. The computerised randomisation will be the responsibility of the UNSW.
The support of their parents and/or carers have been taken into account, and at the moment of recruitment using a health care professionals referral, this option will be proposed to the parent or guardian, however is not compulsory as some parents work and would not be able to attend. 
The participants are young people with mental illness whose parents and or carers are involved in the clinical care of their children, is part of the patients good clinical care practice. It means that the learning during the individual or group education sessions will have a greater chance of being supported at home. What it is important with this option is the possibility of enhancing the health and lifestyle outcomes for the young person when a close relative or guardian is present.

Both groups will receive the individual assessment and follow up, however the intervention group will be allocated to additional learning program as it was explained before.
The monthly reviews or follow up will have a duration of 45 minutes, however, if there is a need for more time, this will be extended to an hour.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Both, control and intervention participants:
1.  At the first session with the clinical dietitian, all referred participants will have a nutritional assessment followed by a dietetic counselling within an hour consultation. 
2.  All the participants will receive a monthly review session for a period of 5 months. Each review will be for a minimal of 45 minutes and a maximum of 1 hour.
3.  All participants will receive an exercise book in which the dietitian will write the main issues addressed at the session. The book will be a tool to facilitate easy reading-reminders of the main messages about the individual session. Also, it will help the participants to write any concerns such as difficulties for making eating habits changes, new food purchasing, cooking barriers and any consultation that the participant and his/her parent or carer will need, when attending the next session.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1)	Anthropometrical data (weight. height, Body Mass Index (BMI) and waist circumference). To be collected by the Dietitian at initial individual consultation (both controls and intervention).
These measurements mean "anthropometrical outcomes", hence includes BMI (height and weight) and waist circumference. Therefore it becomes a "single" outcome as "anthropometry"
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)	Measurement at baseline. Then at 6 months and finally at 12 months for comparison with baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2)      Physical activity using the brief SIMPAQ questionnaire. The dietitian will verbally gather the information from the participants during the first individual session.  
It will be assessed by using the same questionnaire SIMPAQ.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>2)    To be measured by the dietitian at baseline, and at 6 months and finally at 12 month. The last 2 measurements will be compared to the baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3)    Eating habits. This information will also be gathered during dietitian's first session with all participants.  The questionnaire What Did I Eat Yesterday will be used.
The same questionnaire : The questionnaire "What Did I Eat Yesterday" will be used and it will be applied at baseline, at 6 and 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3)    Measured at baseline, then at 6 months and finally at 12 months. Last 2 measurements to be compared with baseline data.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of sleep pattern. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, then at 6 and 12 months. The last 2 measurement to be compared with baseline as per previous measurements.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of smoking will be collected in an Excel spreadsheet (simple page including smoking status) as part of the baseline data collection from all participants: 
Do you smoke? Yes [  ]  
                              No [  ]
This is part of a lifestyle measurement.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, then at 6 and 12 months. The last 2 measurement to be compared with baseline as per previous measurements recorded in the excel sheet.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of alcohol will be collected in an Excel spreadsheet (simple page including alcohol status) as part of the baseline data collection from all participants. 
Do you drink alcohol? Yes [  ]  
                                         No  [  ]
This is parte of a lifestyle measurement.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, then at 6 and 12 months. The last 2 measurement to be compared with baseline as per previous measurements recorded in the excel sheet.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males and females between 12 and 25 years of age diagnosed with schizophrenia, bipolar disorder and/or major depression will be recruited by referral using the Western Sydney Local Health District-Mental Health (WSLHD-MH) dietetics referral form. This will be stated in the Eligibility Form to be used by the medical, nursing and/or allied health professionals working in the WSLHD-Mental Health and/or headspace Parramatta and Mt Druitt.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants diagnosed with mental health conditions other than schizophrenia, bipolar disorder or major depression.
Young people younger than 12 years of age or older than 25 years of age.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>"Allocation is not concealed" .</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The dietitian will provide dietetic intervention according to their allocation and will hence be aware of the randomisation. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intention to treat analyses with linear regression to examine possible trends in BMI over time. Statistical significance of change over time will be evaluated for all variables included in baseline measurements at 12 months.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>26/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>25/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2150 - Parramatta</postcode>
    <postcode>2148 - Blacktown</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2770 - Mount Druitt</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>BEAT  Blacktown
63 Railway Street  Mount Druitt NSW 2770</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Sydney Local Health District (WSLHD) Mental Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PEIRS,2A Fennell Street
Parramatta NSW 2150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>headspace Parramatta</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>headspace Parramatta
2 Wentworth St, Parramatta NSW 2150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>headspace Mt Druitt  </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>headspace Mt Druitt  
Daniel Thomas Plaza, 12/6-10 Mount St, Mount Druitt NSW 2770

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to contribute to the improvement of the general health of young people affected by schizophrenia, bipolar disease and/or major depression. This model of nutrition and health education is likely to influence the high risk of comorbidities that are known to be related to treatment with the newest  psychotropic medications in severe mental illness. Obesity is the key risk factor predisposing to the development of metabolic syndrome, exacerbated by the lack of physical activity seen with these patients. The prevention of the development of obesity among these young people is paramount in order to enhance their physical and mental well being. Educating in isolation is not sufficient to alter outcomes in these patients who require additional support.  Family or carers, hence, are key players in the education of their young relatives or clients. 

This study aims to establish firm strategies for motivating young people to change their lifestyle by empowering them with knowledge and realistic skills to put into practice for the benefit of  their physical and mental health. It is hoped that this can be achieved via the development of health literacy and nutrition education programs which are not only low cost but highly effective.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None to date.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WSLHD Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Westmead Hospital, Cnr Hawkesbury &amp; Darcy Rds, Westmead NSW 2145 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anthony Harris</name>
      <address>Associate Professor of Psychiatry, Westmead Clinical School
Clinical Director, Brain Dynamics Centre, The Westmead Institute
NSW 2145
</address>
      <phone>+612  9845 6688</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9635 7734</fax>
      <email>anthony.harris@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Ward</name>
      <address>Philip B. Ward, BMedSc, PhD
Associate Professor and Postgraduate Research Coordinator, School of Psychiatry, UNSW
Director, Schizophrenia Research Unit, South Western Sydney Local Health District
Liverpool Mental Health Centre, Liverpool Hospital.
Locked Bag 7103, Liverpool BC 1871 NSW Australia
</address>
      <phone>+612 9616 4308</phone>
      <fax>+612 9602-5917</fax>
      <email>p.ward@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Ward</name>
      <address>Philip B. Ward, BMedSc, PhD
Associate Professor and Postgraduate Research Coordinator, School of Psychiatry, UNSW
Director, Schizophrenia Research Unit, South Western Sydney Local Health District
Liverpool Mental Health Centre, Liverpool Hospital.
Locked Bag 7103, Liverpool BC 1871 NSW Australia
</address>
      <phone>+612 9616-4308 </phone>
      <fax>+612 9602-5917</fax>
      <email>p.ward@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Gladys Hitchen</name>
      <address>Cumberland Hospital
Dietetics Services
1-11 Hainsworth Street  Westmead
NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+612 98403532     Mobile: +612  0421979159</phone>
      <fax>+612  48591582</fax>
      <email>Gladys.Hitchen@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>