<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364295">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000970741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Melatonin and Cognitive-Behaviour Therapy for the treatment of insomnia in individuals with schizophrenia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For individuals with schizophrenia and insomnia, can melatonin and CBT improve sleep, symptoms, functioning and cognitive functions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1143-2948</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SIPS (Sleep Intervention Program for Schizophrenia)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Insomnia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This clinical trial will be conducted to assess the relative or combined efficacy of Melatonin (Circadin), and Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Insomnia in Schizophrenia: CBT-I(S). 

There will be four experimental treatment conditions:
Arm 1: CBT-I(s) and placebo
Arm 2: melatonin
Arm 3: CBT-I(S) and melatonin
Arm 4: placebo

Intervention details:

Arm 1: CBT-I(S) and Placebo: 4 weekly sessions of CBT-I(S), and placebo capsules (corn starch)  daily use for 4 weeks. All CBT-I(S) sessions will be administered to small groups of participants (4-5) by a psychologist. CBT-I(S) merges cognitive and behavioural therapies that address elements specifically found to maintain insomnia, such as poor sleep hygiene, dysfunctional beliefs and attitudes about sleep, rumination, and anxiety. Mainly education and discussion format. Total 4 sessions over 4 weeks (1 session a week for approx 2 hours). 

Arm 2: melatonin: Exogenous slow-release melatonin (Circadin) - total 4 mg of melatonin (in capsule) per person daily for 4 weeks

Arm 3: CBT-I(S) and melatonin: 4 weekly sessions of CBT-I(S), and daily use of exogenous melatonin capsules (Circadin) 4mg for 4 weeks. CBT-I(S) session as described in Arm 1.

Arm 4: placebo: Placebo capsules (corn starch)  daily use for 4 weeks

Treatment instructions for both melatonin and placebo conditions will remain identical. Participants will be told to ingest a daily dose of melatonin, or placebo, after a light meal two hours prior to bedtime for 4 weeks. 

At Week 3, a face-to-face check-up visit will be required for all participants to conduct a pill count and check treatment adherence. At the end of the trial, any unused medication (melatonin or placebo) will be returned to Graylands Hospital Pharmacy, alongside an accountability form, and disposed of in accordance with policies at Graylands Hospital Pharmacy for clinical trials. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: corn starch capsule, made to look/weigh the same as the melatonin capsule to ensure double-blind. To match melatonin condition, participants will be asked to take the capsule daily for 4 weeks.

</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in insomnia symptoms, based on Insomnia Severity Index </outcome>
      <timepoint>After each weekly session, and at the end of the trial  (comparison of pre-treatment baseline data, with post-treatment data collected at week 5)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in sleep - as measured with actigraphy and sleep diaries</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the trial (comparison of pre-treatment baseline data, with post-treatment data collected at week 5)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in clinical symptoms, assessed with Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the trial (comparison of pre-treatment baseline data, with post-treatment data collected at week 5)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in cognitive performance on measures of attention (CPT-IP, Letter Cancellation task),  learning and memory (Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Task), processing speed (Symbol Digit Modality Test, Token Motor Task, Letter Cancellation task), motor performance (Finger Tapping task), and executive functions (Verbal Fluency, Number Generation Task; Trails Making Test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the trial (comparison of pre-treatment baseline data, with post-treatment data collected at week 5)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in functional health measured with the SF-36 Health Survey </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the trial (comparison of pre-treatment baseline data, with post-treatment data collected at week 5)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in sleep hygiene practices and positive thinking, assessed with the Sleep Hygiene Index and Perseverative Thinking Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the trial (comparison of pre-treatment baseline data, with post-treatment data collected at week 5)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged 25 to 50 years.
2. A diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder
3. Length of illness 10-15 years
4. Currently in a clinically stable condition
5. Current insomnia symptoms, characterised by Sleep Onset Latency (SOL) more than 30 minutes, or waking up 3 or more times per night, with an ongoing duration of the sleep problem for at least one month.
6. Stable medication schedule and dosage for the past month
7. English as a first language
8. Using contraceptives (applicable to females only)
9. Confirmation of diagnosis and suitability for the study by the potential participants treating psychiatrist
10. Able to provide informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis or high indication of sleep-related breathing disorder (e.g. obstructive sleep apnoea), narcolepsy, nightmare disorder, periodic limb movement syndrome, or restless legs syndrome.
2. Suicidality.
3. Allergy to melatonin, corn starch, gelatine
4. BMI &gt;35 (clinical obesity). 
5. Co-morbid significant medical conditions (e.g. seizure disorder, traumatic brain injury, dementia, autoimmune disease, liver failure, or kidney failure).
6. Known hereditary problem of galactose intolerance, the LAPP lactase deficiency, or glucose-galactose malabsorption. 
7. Pervasive developmental disorder or mental retardation, as defined by DSM-IV or DSM-V criteria. 
8. Pregnant or breastfeeding (applicable to females only).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>To allocate participants to one of the four treatment conditions, there will be two levels of randomisation. 

Allocation is not concealed for the first level of randomisation.  At the first level of randomisation, each participant will be assigned an ID code by the principal investigator, and a randomised number system using a statistical randomiser will be used to determine whether participants receive CBT-I(S) or no CBT-I(S) treatment.
Because the CBT-I condition cannot be blinded, this randomisation will be conducted by the principal investigator. The ID codes will be used on all study materials to maintain anonymity. 

Allocation is concealed for the second level of randomisation.  Treatment condition will remain undisclosed to both the researchers and participants until cessation of the trial. To achieve double-blinding of melatonin/placebo, the trials pharmacist at Graylands Hospital (who has no knowledge of or contact with participants) will generate trial randomisation codes for the allocation of participants to treatment with melatonin or placebo. </concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation method will be with statistical randomiser in computer software (like SPSS).

</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Participants will include 64 clinically stable individuals with chronic schizophrenia or schizo-affective disorder (aged 25 to 50) (recruitment target will be 80 participants anticipating 25% attrition rate)
Sample size was determined on the ability to detect a large effect between groups from baseline to post-treatment. Calculations were conducted using the G-Power program for repeated-measures ANOVA apriori sample size analysis, at an alpha error probability of 0.05. A sample size of 16 participants in each group (total number of 64) provided 90% power to detect an effect size of 0.50 amongst four groups. While Cortesi and colleagues (2012; the same design in autistic children) reported a very strong effect size between their combination and placebo group (effect size of 0.67), based on actigraphically recorded TST from baseline to 12 week assessment, we chose a more conservative effect size in light of Shamir et al.s (2000) more modestly reported differences in actigraphically recorded TST between placebo and melatonin conditions in schizophrenia. Assuming a 25% dropout rate, our recruitment target will be 80 participants (20 participants per condition).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/01/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Graylands Selby-Lemnos &amp; Special Care Hospital - Mount Claremont</hospital>
    <postcode>6010 - Mount Claremont</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Stirling Highway Crawley WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Australia, Personal Research Funds (Flavie Waters, Vivian Chiu)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Clinical Research Centre, Graylands Hospital, John XXI Avenue, Shenton Park, 6010, WA

Mailing address: Private Mail Bag 1, Claremont 6010, WA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>North Metro Mental Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mailing address: Private Mail Bag 1, Claremont 6010, WA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is to evaluate the effectiveness of (i) Cognitive-behavioural therapy for insomnia in schizophrenia [CBT-I(S)] (ii) melatonin, (iii) a combination of CBT-I(S) and melatonin, and (iv) placebo, on insomnia symptoms, clinical symptoms, cognition, and functional health, in individuals with schizophrenia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Metro Mental Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC, Attention to Professor Mathew Martin Iverson, 
North Metro Mental Health, 
Graylands Hospital, John XXIII, Shenton Park 6010, WA.

Mailing address: Private Mail Bag 1, Mount Claremont 6010, WA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Flavie Waters</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, via Clinical Research Centre, Graylands Hospital, John XXIII Avenue, Shenton Park 6010, WA

Mailing addressing: Clinical Research Centre, Private Mail Bag 1, Claremont 6010, WA</address>
      <phone>+61893476650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>flavie.waters@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Flavie Waters</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, via Clinical Research Centre, Graylands Hospital, John XXIII Avenue, Shenton Park, 6010, WA

Mailing addressing: Clinical Research Centre, Private Mail Bag 1, Claremont 6010, WA</address>
      <phone>+61893476650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>flavie.waters@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Flavie Waters</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, via Clinical Research Centre, Graylands Hospital, John XXIII Avenue, Shenton Park, 6010, WA

Mailing addressing: Clinical Research Centre, Private Mail Bag 1, Claremont 6010, WA</address>
      <phone>+61893476650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>flavie.waters@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Flavie Waters</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, via Clinical Research Centre, Graylands Hospital, John XXIII Avenue, Shenton Park, 6010, WA

Mailing addressing: Clinical Research Centre, Private Mail Bag 1, Claremont 6010, WA</address>
      <phone>+61893476650</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>flavie.waters@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>