<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362056">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000216819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Botulinum Toxin A (BTXA) versus Hydrodistension for Refractory Interstitial Cystitis/Painful Bladder Syndrome (IC/PBS)- a Multicentre, Prospective, Randomized, Double Blind Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Botulinum Toxin A (BTXA) versus Hydrodistension for Refractory Interstitial Cystitis/Painful Bladder Syndrome (IC/PBS)- a Multicentre, Prospective, Randomized, Double Blind Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-9192</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>interstitial cystitis/painful bladder syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Injection of Botulinum A toxin; Dysport 500U diluted in 30 mls of saline  and injected into the bladder wall, submucosally. It occurs once.  Hydrodistension involves stretching the bladder with infusd saline using 120 cm of hydrostatic pressure for 4 minutes .</interventions>
    <comparator>Injection of saline plus hydrodistension
Injection of Saline, 30 mls into the bladder wall, submucosally. It occurs once.  Hydrodistension involves stretching the bladder with infusd saline using 120 cm of hydrostatic pressure for 4 minutes .</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>improvement in Oleary Sant scores problem and symptom. O'leary Sant scoring is a validated , well recognized measure of the impact upon a patient of Interstitial cystitis symptoms and problems that they experience</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>diary data. This data asseses patient  maximum voided volume, patient averaged voided volume. Frequency of voiding during the day, frequency of voiding at night</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient global impression improvement. This is a standardised, validated questionnaire patients will complete</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient global impression severity. This is a standardised, validated questionnaire patients will complete</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>urodynamic data. This is a standardised test that will collect the following information; peak flow rate,voided volume, residual post void volume left in bladder, maximum filling capacity, bladder compliance (pressure rise in cm H20 for a volume of fluid instilled) . Incontinence if it occurs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>urge incontinence impact questionnaire data. This is a standardised, validated questionnaire patients will complete measuring specifically symptoms of urinary urgency</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female, chronic, refractory interstitial cystitis, painful bladder syndrome</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>urinary tract infection
pregnancy
systemic steroid use
cancer
voiding impairment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>enrolment ; existing patients from 3 specialist referral centres invited to participate. Urinary tract infection tested for.
Subjects were randomised to receive, under general anaesthetic, either a 4 minute hydrodistension with injection of 30 mls of normal saline into the bladder wall, or hydrodistension with injection of 500 Units of BTXA  Dysport (registered trademark) diluted in 30 mls of normal saline. Both were injected through a 30 cm Bard 23 gauge needle at 30 sites in 1 ml aliquots, sparing the trigone and avoiding ureters. A bladder biopsy was obtained if not already available. 

Urodynamic studies were repeated upon recruitment if not recently done.  A free urinary flow rate with post void residual was performed at 1 week post treatment. 
Approval for the study was obtained from the Research and Ethics Committees of all 3 hospitals. There was no public trial registry enrolment in 2003. 
Subjects and treating doctors were blinded to treatment allocation, which was prepared in the hospital pharmacy according to a series of computer generated randomization numbers, held confidentially by pharmacy. Unlabelled drug was then delivered to theatre</concealment>
    <sequence>randomization numbers-computer generated by statistician from Dept mathematics local university</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Blinding maintained when all allowed access to active treatment-Botulinum A toxin at 3 months</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2291</postcode>
    <postcode>3189</postcode>
    <postcode>2305</postcode>
    <postcode>3800</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>John Hunter Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Lookout Road 
New Lambton NSW 2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Jane Manning</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 648
The Junction 2291 NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ibsen pharmaceuticals, Bard, and the Principal investigator</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ibsen
suite 6 
40 Montclair Ave 
Glen Waverly
Victoria 3150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bard</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bard Australia
69-71 Waterloo Road
North Ryde NSW, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Jane Manning</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 648
The Junction
2291 NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mercy Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Mercy Hospital for Women
63 Studley Road, Heidelberg  3084
Melbourne,  Victoria</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash Medical Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Road
Clayton  3168

Melbourne,  Victoria</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background
IC/PBS requires effective treatment options. 
Objective
Is BTXA effective for the treatment of IC/PBS?
Design, Setting and Participants:
2003-2009, 55 severe, refractory female subjects from 3 referral centres invited. UTI, malignancy, steroid use  excluded.
Intervention
Double blind design, random allocation to treatment with hydrodistension and bladder wall injection of normal saline, or else hydrodistension with injection of BTXA. 
Outcome measures and statistical Analysis 
OLeary Sant (OLS) problem (PI) and Symptom (SI), UIIQ, compared between BTXA and controls. 
Repeated measures ANOVA tested whether BTXA subjects performed better than control subjects (group effect) for changes from baseline to 3 months (time effect) by assessing significance of group by time interaction. Multivariate modelling analyzed  effect over time of other possible confounders. Measurements  made beyond 3 months, but no further randomized comparisons possible, as majority subjects  then chose  active BTXA injection. Withdrawal; 4  subjects completed questionnaires too poorly,  1 withdrawn pre treatment with bladder cancer, leaving 50.

Results and limitations:
In both groups, the OLS, bladder diary, UIIQ scores showed  improvement over 3 months. But no difference detected during initial analysis between the BTXA and control subjects for any outcome measure except OLS PI, where improvement noted at 3 months (P=0.04).  12 had UTI treated during the study. This significantly confounded, with greater improvement  seen in the control group treated for UTI. Multivariate modelling accounted for effect of UTI showing improvement in the total OLS score (P=0.02), the OLS SI for the BTXA (P=0.008) group, pain (Q4 of OLS PI) (P=0.015) for the BTXA group at 3 months. 24% request continuing periodic BTXA treatment. 
Conclusions
BTXA treatment improves OLS score at 3 months when compared to hydrodistension and saline injection alone, for a minority women. Consideration of the significant confounding effect of UTI, strengthened this improvement.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>IUGA Lake Como 2009</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Area Research Ethics and Governance Unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1
New Lambton
NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/01/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>03/09/10/3.10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Manning</name>
      <address>PO Box 648
The Junction 2291 NSW 
Australia</address>
      <phone>61 02 4940869</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>61 02 49610599</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Manning</name>
      <address>PO Box 648
The Junction 2291 NSW 
Australia</address>
      <phone>61 02 4940869</phone>
      <fax>61 02 49610599</fax>
      <email>jma14246@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Manning</name>
      <address>PO Box 648
The Junction 2291 NSW 
Australia</address>
      <phone>61 02 49408069</phone>
      <fax>61 02 49610599</fax>
      <email>jma14246@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>