<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373320">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001071314p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Actions of kiwifruit and dietary fibre on bowel function in healthy adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Actions of kiwifruit and dietary fibre on bowel function in healthy adults: a randomised cross-over clinical trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-4248 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bowel health and function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a 17-week cross-over study. Participants will consume three treatments; 2 kiwifruit daily, one kiwifruit plus 1.25 tsp of Metamucil® daily or 2.5 tsp of Metamucil® daily. There is two week lead-in period, a three week intervention, a two week wash-out, a second three week intervention, a two week wash-out, a third three week intervention and a two week follow-up period. Venous blood samples (20 ml) will be collected at the beginning and end of the study. Bowel health and dietary intake will be assessed using faecal samples and three-day diet records. A daily bowel habit diary will be completed for 11 weeks of the trial. The trial involves 8 visits to Plant &amp; Food Research. 

At the end of each trial period, participants will return unused kiwifruit or Metamucil® to the trial coordinators as a measure of compliance. Particpants will also be directly asked whether or not they adhered to the protocol. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will complete  three interventions. The three interventions are (1) two green kiwifruit (Actinidia deliciosa var. Hayward) per day; (2) psyllium supplied as a commercially sourced preparation (Metamucil®, 2.5 teaspoons per day) given in two doses per day providing 5.0 g fibre to match the fibre content of two green kiwifruit; and (3) 1 green kiwifruit per day (Actinidia deliciosa var. Hayward) plus psyllium at half the dose ((Metamucil®, 1.25 teaspoons per day). This will allow researchers to compare bowel habits between interventions. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete Spontaneous Bowel Movement (CSBM) Frequency (CSBM/week) as a measure of overall bowel function</outcome>
      <timepoint>CSBM will be measured daily during the lead-in and three intervention periods

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stool consistency as indicated by the Bristol Stool Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured daily during the lead-in and three intervention periods</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of fructan intake as measured using a Fructan Food Frequency Questionnaire

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of lead-in, end of intervention 1, end of washout 1, end of intervention 2, end of washout 2 and end of intervention 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of diet as measured using a three-day Food Diary </outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of lead-in, end of intervention 1, end of washout 1, end of intervention 2, end of washout 2 and end of intervention 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy adults between ages of 18-65 years inclusive with a BMI between 18-35 kg/m2.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential participants will be excluded if they have any alarm features associated with bowel habit (recent changes in bowel habit (&lt;3 months), rectal bleeding, weight loss, occult blood in stools, anaemia), anal fissures, bleeding haemorrhoids, and family history of GI cancer or IBD.

Chronic disease (cardiovascular, cancer, renal failure, previous gastrointestinal surgery (not including appendectomy or cholecystectomy), neurological conditions (e.g. multiple sclerosis, spinal cord injury, stroke).

All participants will be screened at recruitment for fasting blood glucose. Those with results great than or equal to 6.0 mmol/l will not be accepted into the trial as they are at risk of having impaired glucose tolerance, which is an exclusion criteria for the study.

Participants with diagnosed and stable conditions requiring the use of SSRIs (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors), tricyclates, opiates or anti-inflammatories will be permitted into the trial on the condition that the medication has been in use continually and that the condition has been stable for &gt; 3 months. Similarly those with stable and controlled diabetes (&gt; 3 months) will be permitted to participate.

Women who are pregnant, breastfeeding or planning a pregnancy in the 3 months post selection (trial period) will be excluded.

Potential participants with known kiwifruit or latex allergy will be excluded. The reason for excluding latex allergy is because people with this allergy are more likely to have an allergy to food including kiwifruit.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be enrolled by researcher by a face to face interview and will be given a unique identifying number (ID) for labelling all further trial data. The ID number will be provided to an independent biostatistician who will randomise the participants to the treatment schedule. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>n/a</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study is designed to detect an increase of 1.0 or more CSBM per week in healthy individuals. 

An initial calculation has been completed using available data. Based on previous studies (Chan et al. 2007), the standard deviation for the primary outcome (number of CSBM per week) is 1.41. In order to detect an increase in CSBM of 1.0 per week in the study population, with 80% power and 5% significance, 16 participants are required to complete the trial. In order to allow for an expected 25% dropout, 20 subjects will be recruited.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>4/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>5/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Plant and Food Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Batchelar Road
Palmerston North
4474</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Plant and Food Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Batchelar Road
Palmerston North
4474</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed study will be a randomised, controlled, cross-over clinical intervention study. The cross-over design will be completed using the kiwifruit intervention of two green kiwifruit per day, compared to a positive control intervention of psyllium (2.5 teaspoons of Metamucil® per day providing 5.0 g fibre to match that fibre content of two green kiwifruit), and the combination of kiwifruit and psyllium (1 green kiwifruit per day and 1.25 teaspoons of Metamucil per day providing a total of 5.0 g of fibre).

The study duration is a total of 17 weeks; 2-week lead in, 3-week intervention, 2-week washout, 3-week intervention, 2-week washout, 3-week intervention and final 2-week follow-up. All participants will be free living and required to maintain their normal dietary and lifestyle habits for the duration of the trial.

The primary outcome measure will be quantification of CSBM (complete spontaneous bowel movement). Secondary outcome measures will include additional stool frequency measures (spontaneous bowel movements (SBM), complete bowel movements (CBM) bowel movements (BM)), and habitual dietary fibre intake.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
20 Aitken Street
Thorndon
Wellington 
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/07/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christine Butts</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Batchelar Road
Palmerston North
4474
</address>
      <phone>+64 6 3556147</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Chrissie.Butts@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Hannah Dinnan</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Private Bag 11600
Palmerston North
4442</address>
      <phone>+64 6 3530962</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hannah.dinnan@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christine Butts</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Private Bag 11600
Palmerston North
4442</address>
      <phone>+64 6 3556147</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Chrissie.Butts@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Hannah Dinnan</name>
      <address>Plant and Food Research
Private Bag 11600
Palmerston North
4442</address>
      <phone>+64 6 3530962</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hannah.dinnan@plantandfood.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>