<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="925">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/12/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000788673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Role of non-GP Staff in Chronic Disease Management in General Practice.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Trial of Structured Support to Enhance the Role of Non-GP Staff in the Management of Diabetes, Ischaemic Heart Disease and Hypertension in General Practice</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Teamwork</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ischemic Heart Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Study will recruit general practices within participating Divisions of General Practice. Participating practices will be randomly allocated to intervention group (30 practices) which will receive the intervention immediately following randomisation. Study staff collecting data will be blinded. Method: Six-month intervention driven by the practice with assistance from a facilitator (from the research team). The intervention will focus on establishing practice systems and defining roles and procedures for non-GP staff for the management of patients with type II diabetes or ischaemic heart disease, or hypertension to ensure: evidence based care is offered; patients return for follow-up; adequate access to appointments and length of consultations or group sessions is available; regular and comprehensive assessment and monitoring is carried out; multidisciplinary care needs are identified and plans to address them are implemented; access to structured patient education sessions and patient education resources is available; appropriate referral is made; financial stability of teamwork is optimised through use of Chronic Disease Management (CDM) Medicare items. Each practice in the intervention group will receive the core intervention, consisting of education sessions, practice visits and ongoing support, with additional customisation for each practice's specific circumstances. Located in the practice, the intervention will be conducted through and with the support of the division, who will support practices beyond the intervention period to maintain the effect of the intervention. At the completion of the study, the intervention will be offered to the control practices.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group (50 practices) will receive the intervention at 12 months post randomisation.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study will evaluate the impact of the intervention on (i) quality of care</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data Collection:  Measurements will be taken at 3 points in time.  1. Immediately before randomisation and before commencement of the intervention (0 month) to get a baseline measure.  2. At the completion of the training and support (6 months from randomisation) to measure the immediate effect of the intervention.  3. Six months after the completion of the intervention (12 months from randomisation) to measure maintenance of effect.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study will evaluate the impact of the intervention on (ii) patient's perceptions of access, continuity of care, interpersonal care and satisfaction with care </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data Collection:  Measurements will be taken at 3 points in time.  1. Immediately before randomisation and before commencement of the intervention (0 month) to get a baseline measure.  2. At the completion of the training and support (6 months from randomisation) to measure the immediate effect of the intervention.  3. Six months after the completion of the intervention (12 months from randomisation) to measure maintenance of effect.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study will evaluate the impact of the intervention on (iii) health status of patients with diabetes and/or ischaemic heart disease and/or hypertension.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data Collection:  Measurements will be taken at 3 points in time.  1. Immediately before randomisation and before commencement of the intervention (0 month) to get a baseline measure.  2. At the completion of the training and support (6 months from randomisation) to measure the immediate effect of the intervention.  3. Six months after the completion of the intervention (12 months from randomisation) to measure maintenance of effect.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures:  (a) Clinical Care Interview: a GP self-report quality of care interview, which we have developed and validated in our ongoing research program, will be used.  The instrument has good internal consistency and construct validity in relation to record audits.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data Collection:  Measurements will be taken at 3 points in time.  1. Immediately before randomisation and before commencement of the intervention (0 month) to get a baseline measure.  2. At the completion of the training and support (6 months from randomisation) to measure the immediate effect of the intervention.  3. Six months after the completion of the intervention (12 months from randomisation) to measure maintenance of effect.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures: (b) Practice Claims of HIC Payment for long consultations (Levels C &amp; D), care plans, completed cycles of care, investigations (HbAIc, urinary microalbumin) and eye referral for diabetes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data Collection:  Measurements will be taken at 3 points in time.  1. Immediately before randomisation and before commencement of the intervention (0 month) to get a baseline measure.  2. At the completion of the training and support (6 months from randomisation) to measure the immediate effect of the intervention.  3. Six months after the completion of the intervention (12 months from randomisation) to measure maintenance of effect.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The following measures will be taken on each of the 30 patients recruited in each practice:  (c) An Audit of Medical Records to determine the recorded frequency and values of blood pressure, HbAIcm total cholesterol, HDL, LDL levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Audit of Medical Records at baseline and 12 months.  Values of blood pressure, HbAIcm total cholesterol, HDL, LDL levels performed in the last 12 months.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The following measures will be taken on each of the 30 patients recruited in each practice:  (d) 20-item Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care (PACIC) developed and validated in the US that assesses patient's receipt of clinical services and the PACIC consists of 5 scales and an overall summary score.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The following measures will be taken on each of the 30 patients recruited in each practice:  (e) SF-12 (v2), a 7-item questionnaire measureing patients' health status.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The following measures will be taken on each of the 30 patients recruited in each practice:  (f) A 3-item questionnaire surveying whether patients have received i) education or patient education materials by the GP or other general practice staff in the past 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The following measures will be taken on each of the 30 patients recruited in each practice:  (f) A 3-item questionnaire surveying whether patients have received ii) a referral in past 12 months for education, self help or support group, or allied health services (diabetes education, dietetics, podiatrist, cardiac rehabilitation)</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The following measures will be taken on each of the 30 patients recruited in each practice:  (f) A 3-item questionnaire surveying whether patients have received iii) any recall or reminders from the practice.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In addition, data will will be collected on practice and practice staff characteristics including: rurality of local area; number, age, gender, full time/part time status, training of GPs and practice staff; management of practice (e.g. solo, group, corporate).</outcome>
      <timepoint>These data will be collected at the time of recruitment.  They will allow comparison between practices that elect to participate and those who decline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative and quantitative data will also be collected about the roles of the GPs and practice staff in chronic disease management and team functioning at 3 points in time;  Instruments being utilised by the investigators in our current research program will be used, including the 'Team Climate Inventory', the Staff Roles Interview, and a practice profiling survey of practice systems for chronic disease care, including appointment systems, information systems, procedures for recall, patient education materials and education sessions. The data will be used to ascertain which factors are associated with the adoption of a broader role for non-GP staff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the baseline before the commencement of intervention, at the completion of the intervention (6 months from baseline) and 6 months after competition of the intervention (12 months from baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The research will take place in partnership with 10 Divisions of General Practice.  All general practices that use computerised prescribing, have a minimum of 3 people working in the practice, have a practice manager and/or practice nurse role in the practice and the practice manager role is not carried out solely by a GP, are located in the participating Divisions of General Practice will be eligible for inclusion.  Patients in participating practices will be eligible for inclusion in the study if they have type II diabetes and/or ischaemic heart disease and/or hypertension, and have attended the practice in the past 12 months and who have been prescribed medications commonly used to treat the above conditions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>79</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be achieved by Patient selection, patient consent and baseline data collection will occur before randomisation. Using a centralised randomisation scheme where a University of NSW statistician not involved in the study (not linked to practice or patient recruitment, or staff recruitment) and who is blinded to the identity of the participating practices will generate random numbers using computer generated random numbers. The outcome of the random allocation will be kept in sealed envelopes. Project staff who collect data are different from those who deliver the intervention. Data collection officers will be unaware of random practice allocation. The intervention research assistants will not be informed of the practices in the intervention group until they start delivering the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block design will be used to randomise participating practices into intervention and control groups.  Practices within each division of general practice will constitute one block. In each block, practices will be allocated to intervention or control groups using computer generated random numbers.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>3000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for GP Integration Studies, University of New South Wales.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomised clinical trial that tests the efficacy of a general practice based intervention to enhance the role of non-GP staff including practice managers, practice nurses and receptionists in chronice diesease management in general practice in terms of its impact on the quality and outcome of care for patients with diabetes and/or ischaemic heart disease and/or hypertension.  Key primary measures include an audit of medical records, 20-item patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care (PACIC), SF-12 (v2), and practice claims of HIC patment for long consultations (Levels C &amp; D), care plans, completed cycles of care, investigations (HbAIc, urinary micro albumin) and eye referral for diabetes and the quality of clinical care measured by clinical care interview.  Secondary outcome measures include Team Climate Inventory, the Staff Roles Interview, and a practice profiling survey of practice systems for chronic disease care.  These measures will be taken at baseline, 6 and 12 months from baseline.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Human Ethics Committee University of New South Wales</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mark Harris</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity, University of New South Wales, NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93851547</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93851513</fax>
      <email>m.f.harris@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mark Harris</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity, University of New South Wales, NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93851547</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93851513</fax>
      <email>m.f.harris@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mark Harris</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity, University of New South Wales, NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 400987899</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93851513</fax>
      <email>m.f.harris@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>