<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363282">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/12/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001277831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Metformin and dietary advice to improve insulin sensitivity and promote gestational restriction of weight in pregnant women who are overweight or obese: the GroW Randomised trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Metformin and dietary advice compared with dietary advice alone in overweight or obese pregnant women to restrict gestational weight gain and reduce the risk of infants being born above 4.0 kg.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1137-0803</utrn>
    <trialacronym>GRoW</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>High birth weight of infants of obese pregnant women</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Metformin and dietary and exercise advice.
Women will commence at enrollment taking one 500 mg tablet once daily increasing to two tablets twice daily (2000 mg) over the first four weeks and continue until birth.

Initially, there will be a planning session with a research dietitian, in which women will be provided with written dietary and activity information, an individual diet and physical activity plan, recipe book and example menu plans. 

Over the course of pregnancy, each woman will receive 1-2 sessions with the dietitian of up to 45 minutes duration, shortly after trial entry and again at 28 weeks gestation; and telephone calls of up to 20 minutes duration from the research assistant at 24, 32 and 36 weeks gestation.

Dietary advice provided will be consistent with current Australian dietary standards, designed to limit gestational weight gain. The dietary intervention will maintain a balance of carbohydrates, fat and protein, while specifically encouraging women to reduce their intake of energy dense and non-core foods high in refined carbohydrates and saturated fats, while increasing their intake of fibre, and promoting consumption of two serves of fruit and five serves of vegetables each day.

Women will be encouraged to be active every day and will receive written information about exercise in pregnancy consistent with the Guidelines for exercise in pregnancy produce by the British royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo and dietary and exercise advise.

The placebo will be identical in taste and appearance to the metformin tablets.

Women will commence at enrollment taking one placebo tablet once daily increasing to two tablets twice daily over the first four weeks and continue until birth.

Initially, there will be a planning session with a research dietitian, in which women will be provided with written dietary and activity information, an individual diet and physical activity plan, recipe book and example menu plans. 

Over the course of pregnancy, each woman will receive 1-2 sessions with the dietitian of up to 45 minutes duration, shortly after trial entry and again at 28 weeks gestation; and telephone calls of up to 20 minutes duration from the research assistant at 24, 32 and 36 weeks gestation.

Dietary advice provided will be consistent with current Australian dietary standards, designed to limit gestational weight gain. The dietary intervention will maintain a balance of carbohydrates, fat and protein, while specifically encouraging women to reduce their intake of energy dense and non-core foods high in refined carbohydrates and saturated fats, while increasing their intake of fibre, and promoting consumption of two serves of fruit and five serves of vegetables each day.

Women will be encouraged to be active every day and will receive written information about exercise in pregnancy consistent with the Guidelines for exercise in pregnancy produce by the British royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists.

Dietary and exercise advice will be the same as a advice given to women in the intervention group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in risk of infant being born with birth weight above 4.0 kg</outcome>
      <timepoint>At birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Please note this is not a composite and all outcomes will be reported separately, including: preterm birth (birth before 37 weeks gestation); mortality (either a stillbirth (intrauterine fetal death after trial entry and prior to birth), or infant death (death of a live born infant prior to hospital discharge, and excluding lethal congenital anomalies)); infant birth weight less than 2500 grams; infant birth weight &gt;4500 grams; infant birth weight less than the 10th centile for gestational age and infant sex; infant birth weight greater than the 90th centile for gestational age and infant sex; hypoglycaemia requiring intravenous treatment; admission to neonatal intensive care unit, or special care baby unit; hyperbilirubinaemia requiring phototherapy; nerve palsy; fracture; birth trauma; shoulder dystocia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At birth or up until primary hospital discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Please note this is not a composite and all outcomes will be reported separately, including: maternal hypertension and pre-eclampsia (in accordance with recognised Australasian Society for the Study of Hypertension in Pregnancy criteria); maternal gestational diabetes; need for and length of antenatal hospital stay; antepartum haemorrhage requiring hospitalisation; preterm prelabour ruptured membranes; chorioamnionitis; need and reason for induction of labour; any antibiotic use during labour; caesarean section; postpartum haemorrhage (blood loss &gt;600mL); perineal trauma; wound infection; endometritis; length of postnatal hospital stay; thromboembolic disease; maternal death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up until hospital discharge following birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Please note this is not a composite and all outcomes will be reported separately, including:

Maternal quality of life and emotional wellbeing as measured by questionnaires completed by the woman at six months postpartum relating to quality of life (as measured using the SF12 Health Survey Questionnaire), preferences for treatment, satisfaction with care, anxiety (as measured by the Short Form Spielberger State Trait Inventory) and depression (as measured by the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale). Women will be asked a series of questions about their satisfaction with the intervention, using items modified from a previous childbirth questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quality of life measures assessed at trial entry, 28 and 36 weeks gestation and 4-6 months postpartum.

Satisfaction with care and the intervention assessed 4-6 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Please note this is not a composite and all outcomes will be reported separately, including:

Fetal growth and wellbeing at 28 and 36 weeks gestation assessed by ultrasound (fetal biometry, estimated weight, liquor volume, umbilical artery Doppler waveform, and adiposity)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 28 and 36 weeks gestation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This outcome is not a composite and all outcomes will be reported separately. Maternal changes in diet and physical activity as measured by questionnaires completed by the woman at trial entry, 28 and 36 weeks gestation, and 6 months after birth (Harvard Semi-quantitative Food Frequency Questionnaire, and the Short Questionnaire to Assess Health-enhancing physical activity (SQUASH)). Dietary analysis will include an assessment of diet quality using the Healthy Eating Index (HEI) and description of dietary patterns. Physical activity is reported as a metabolic equivalent task (MET) unit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Trial entry, 28 and 36 weeks of gestation and 6 months postpartum.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal weight gain outcomes including total gestational weight gain; gestational weight gain below/within/above IoM recommendations. 
 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up until last recorded maternal weight prior to birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women with a singleton, live gestation between 10 +0 and 20 +0 weeks gestation with a BMI above or equal to 25 kg/m2 at their first antenatal visit.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women with a multiple pregnancy, type 1 or 2 diabetes diagnosed prior to pregnancy, known renal or hepatic failure.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research staff will call a central telephone randomisation service that will verify the participants eligibility and allocate a unique study number and treatment pack number. Repeat treatment pack numbers will be allocated by phoning the randomisation service and entering the participants study id and hospital record number to ensure a treatment pack with the same treatment group allocation is allocated.
All treatment packs will be identical in appearance as will the metformin and placebo tablets.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule will use balanced variable blocks and will be prepared by an investigator not involved with recruitment, clinical care or data collection for the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Initial analysis will examine baseline characteristics of all randomised women as an indication of comparable treatment groups. Primary and secondary outcomes will be analysed on an intention to treat basis according to treatment allocation at randomisation. Relative risks and 95% confidence intervals will be reported for outcomes.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>26/04/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>524</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>524</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Womens and Childrens Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Modbury Hospital - Modbury</hospital>
    <postcode>5006</postcode>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5092 - Modbury</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Discipline of Obstetrics and Gynaecology 
Women's and Children's Hospital 
72 King William St
North Adelaide SA 5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There are a number of complications that women who are obese during pregnancy may develop and can impact on their health an don the health of their baby. There are also longer term risk for infants born including being overweight or obese in childhood and an increased risk of diabetes and heart disease in later life.

Metformin lowers blood glucose by improving  insulin sensitivity and is commonly used to treat diabetes and gestational diabetes. Women who are obese are more likely to be insulin resistant and in pregnancy this increases the risk of developing gestational diabetes. Insulin resistance raises blood glucose levels and provides excess nutrients to the baby increasing the chance that they will be born large for gestational age. Metformin may modify this risk. 

This study is a double blind placebo controlled trial; women will be randomly allocated to receive metformin or an identical placebo. All women in the study will receive dietary and exercise advice from a qualified dietitian throughout their pregnancy to help them adopt a healthy diet and lifestyle.
Information about the womans pregnancy, birth and postnatal admission and the babys postnatal hospital stay will be obtained from case notes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Health Network Human Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William St
North Adelaide SA 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Professor Jodie Dodd</name>
      <address>Discipline of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
72 King William St
North Adelaide SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617619</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617652</fax>
      <email>jodie.dodd@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Andrea Deussen</name>
      <address>Discipline of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
72 King William St
North Adelaide SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617657</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617652</fax>
      <email>andrea.deussen@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Andrea Deussen</name>
      <address>Discipline of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
72 King William St
North Adelaide SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617657</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617652</fax>
      <email>andrea.deussen@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jodie Dodd</name>
      <address>Discipline of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
72 King William St
North Adelaide SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61881617619</phone>
      <fax>+61881617652</fax>
      <email>jodie.dodd@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>