<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366064">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001451392p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A wave randomized trial to determine the efficacy of the Grit Wellbeing program for individuals attending residential rehabilitation for substance use problems.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A wave randomized trial to determine whether the Grit Wellbeing program in combination with standard residential rehabilitation for substance use problems enhances wellbeing, resilience and social engagement, and reduces substance use and mental ill-health, compared to standard residential rehabilitation treatment alone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1203-4258 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Emotional Wellbeing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Social Engagement</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Substance Use</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Grit program + the standard Mirikai residential rehabiliation recovery 28-Day program. Participants in the Grit program will receive 2 program sessions per week, delivered in a group setting, over the course of 4 weeks alongside Mirikai standard treatment. The 8 x 50 minute Grit sessions are detailed below. The program will delivered by a clinical researcher, with a minimum of provisional registration in psychology and training in clinical psychology, and LLW staff who have been trained in the program.

The Grit Wellbeing Program incorporates key elements of strengths-based mindfulness and Rock and Water psychosocial competency training to increase the social, emotional, psychological, and physical wellbeing of young people and decrease their risk of adverse outcomes.
 
Session 1: The program begins by explaining the mind-body connection, and how to breathe, ground and centre. Youtube videos are used to demonstrate breathing techniques, and the participants are invited to practice belly breathing. Grounding is then taught using a series of exercises focusing on balancing and anchoring oneself to the ground. Breathing and grounding techniques are then practiced in combination.  Finally, participants are taught how to centre themselves by activating their core muscles using simple tensing and stretching exercises. These activities are conducted in a circle, individually, and in pairs.
 
Session 2: This session will be directed towards the final component - focusing, through an extended focus on breathing and on being mindful. The session begins revising the previous session, and revisiting belly breathing in particular. Mindfulness is then introduced using a short video to explain the often rapid activity of our mind. Simple mindful activities are then introduced, to increase  participants awareness of how their mind wanders and how to breathe, ground, centre and focus. Focus activities include mindful eating (e.g., popping candy or chocolate), mindful boxing (with boxing gloves and mitts), and/or Chinese boxing (hand exercise). The session concludes with a 10 minute mindful breathing audio track.

Session 3: This session focuses on character strengths. It begins with an exercise to revise teachings on breathing, grounding, centering and focusing. Participants complete a character strengths survey. Participants learn how to identify their own strengths, while also identifying the strengths of others in their group (using exercises to strength spotting and strength feedback). The session concludes with some breathe, ground, centre, focus exercises (tag, boxing, or shooting hoops - boxing gloves and mitts/basketball required).

Session 4: This session focuses on  non-verbal communication. Participants first receive feedback on the results of their strength survey. The session then focuses on body language (charades), building an understanding of the need for flexibility in everyday interactions, through a series of  exercises on physical trust, personal boundaries and tag games, before finishing with some breathe, ground, centre, focus activities  (e.g., tag, boxing, or shooting hoops - boxing gloves and mitts/basketball required).

Session 5: This session focuses on verbal communication. Personal strengths from the previous session are first revised, focusing on how these strengths were used since the past session. The session then focuses on eye contact, and its impact on communication, followed by exercises on mindful listening, small talk and negotiation skills. This session will also focus on friendships and the qualities of a friend.
 
Session 6: This session focuses on social and emotional wellbeing. It begins with a strength spotting exercise, followed by a revision exercise from the previous session on dealing with threats or challenges. The session then focuses how to identify emotions and ways to increase positive emotions using music. The Music eScape app and  posters of the key components of the app, are used to facilitate this process. Practical demonstrations will follow of how music can enhance positive emotions (Music app and speaker)  and how they can be enhanced by breathing, grounding, centering and focusing when listening to music.  
 
Session 7: This session focuses on emotional wellbeing. It begins with a strength spotting and breathing, grounding, centering and focusing exercise. This session focuses on negative emotions, factors that can lead to negative emotions, and strategies that can alleviate negative emotions (e.g., exercise, spending time with friends, music). Practical exercises focused on how different types of music make participants feel, and how they could use music to improve a negative mood. The three minute breathing space mindfulness exercise is also taught.

Session 8: Graduation. This session uses intuition exercises to revise previous session content, as well as a series of exercise on managing challenging situations and conflict. This session concludes with a recap on participants personal strengths and achievements through the program.

Participants receive handouts to remind them of the key exercises from each session.


</interventions>
    <comparator>The standard Mirikai residential rehabilitation recovery 28-Day program. Individuals who enrol in the 28 day recovery program are provided with tailored support which aims to give them the tools to overcome their substance addiction. This standard care aims to provide participants with greater self-awareness, goal setting abilities, greater confidence, interpersonal skills and positive life strategies to help manage later challenges. This program is delivered by Lives Lived Well staff, many of whom are AOD workers, counsellors and social workers.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of Wellbeing  (Mental Health Continuum - Short Form)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1 (primary timepoint), 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of substance use and related problems through a composite score (WHO ASSIST)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1 (primary timepoint), 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of engagement in education, training or employment (Time-use questionnaire measuring time spent engaged in education, training and/or employment - composite score from 2-items from the Australian Outcome Treatment Profile)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1 (primary timepoint), 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health assessed using Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9),</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Engagement and Conflict (social functioning sub-scale of the Brief Treatment Outcome Measure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical health ( 7 day Adolescent Physical Activity Recall Questionnaire (APARQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-Esteem (Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotion Regulation (Difficulties in Emotion Regulation Scale (DERS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: The 8 item EUROHIS-QOL </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client Satisfaction with treatment (Patient Experiences Questionnaire )</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (i.e., one month post-baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resilience ( Brief Resilience Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental illness (Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7 (GAD-7) )</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotion regulation (Coping in Stressful Situations Scale (CISS-SF))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Work and Social Adjustment (Work and Social Adjustment Scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline compared to 1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 month post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will include adults aged between 18 and 35 years, who have an alcohol or other drug dependence and are attending residential treatment at the Mirikai recovery 28-Day program.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Insufficient English to give informed consent (assessed by case manager on referral or by the research team during screening) 
- Severe mental illness or intellectual disability that precludes the ability to consent (determined from case manager knowledge of the participant and based on observation of apparent cognitive capacity during consent call)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>As the 28-day program involves group residential treatment, wave randomization, hence randomization will occur at a cluster, not individual level. A computer generated program, with a 1:1 allocation, will be used to allocate the waves. Assignment for the next wave will not be generated until two weeks prior to the program beginning. LLW intake staff, and all researchers involved in enrolment of participants into the programs will be blind to treatment allocation (both for preceding and upcoming waves). Only the clinicians delivering the treatment, and the staff overseeing the project, will be aware of the upcoming wave allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>The waves will be randomized using a computer generated program, with a 1:1 allocation. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>As the 28-day program involves group residential treatment, wave randomization will be used for the study with at least an eight week hiatus between the session 8 of group one, and session 1 of group two, to avoid contamination due to the shared living environment (this contamination may occur because a 10-week program is co-located with the 28-day program). There will be a minimum of six waves in total (3 x standard 28-day program; 3 x 28-day program + Grit).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample allocation is restricted by the group size. With approx. 15 participants per residential program it as anticipated to have a least 45 participants per condition (with 90 participants in total).  

. Outcome success will be determined by examining the significant difference in scores (p &lt; .05), for key primary outcomes (i.e., wellbeing, resilience, educational/vocational engagement, substance use, depression, anxiety) from baseline to each of the follow-up points, as well as whether the effect size is small (0.2), moderate (0.5) and strong (0.8) depending on the value of cohens d. To determine whether the GRIT program is more efficacious than standard treatment, significant time x group interactions will be for each of the key outcome variables, as well as cohens d effect sizes. 

Treatment condition will be an independent variable with two levels: (i) standard treatment (ii) standard treatment + Grit. Preliminary logistic regressions will be undertaken to check for baseline group differences on demographic, primary and secondary outcomes. A similar analysis will be conducted to detect differences between those with missing data, and those without, on key baseline demographic and outcome variables. Any significant differences will be reported and controlled for wherever possible, to control for sampling bias and completion bias. To determine whether there are group differences in improvements in primary and secondary outcomes of young people at post treatment (4 weeks), 2, 3, 6, and 12 months follow up compared to baseline, a series of mixed effects model repeated measures analyses of variance (MMRM) will be employed. The within groups factor will be time (pre/post treatment, 2, 3, 6, 12 months) and group will be the between subjects factor. This technique can also control for potential confounds (e.g. demographic characteristics, baseline emotion regulation), and for the clustering effects at the wave level. Intent to treat analyses will be performed, with all participants included in analyses, regardless of whether they withdraw from the treatment program, or did not complete all follow-up assessments.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/01/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD 4072
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Government Department of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 9848, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Lives Lived Well</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 1/Boundary Court,
55 Little Edward Street,
Spring Hill, Brisbane.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The efficacy of the Grit wellbeing program, which targets psychological, emotional, and social wellbeing, will be examined in substance using populations, through wave randomized control trials, comparing Grit in combination with the Mirikai Recovery Centre, a residential rehabilitation facility that provides a 28-day program vs 28-day program alone. There will be a minimum of 90 participants, and six wave randomizations (3 x standard program; 3 x standard program + Grit). It is anticipated that those who participate in the Grit Wellbeing Program will have greater reductions in substance use and mental ill-health, show greater increases in wellbeing, resilience and social engagement than those who participate in standard treatment alone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Brian Wilson Chancellery
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leanne Hides</name>
      <address>McElwain Building 
The University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD 4072
</address>
      <phone>+61406185750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.hides@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leanne Hides</name>
      <address>McElwain Building 
The University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61406185750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.hides@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leanne Hides</name>
      <address>McElwain Building 
The University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61406185750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.hides@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Quinn</name>
      <address>McElwain Building 
The University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61431471191</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.quinn@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>