<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343151">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000678998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>NSW Cancer Lifestyle and Evaluation of Risk Study (CLEAR Study)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-centre case-control surveillance study in the NSW population to provide ongoing data on the relative importance of known or emerging exposures and their relationships to leading or emerging cancer types.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CLEAR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Any primary cancer diagnosed in the past 18 months</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Questionnaire (survey) and a blood sample (optional). 

Survey questions relate to lifestyle and risk factors a person may have been exposed to during their lifetime. Data from questionnaires of cancer patients and cancer free controls will be compared.

Blood samples will be analysed in the future in a quest to identify known or new biomarkers for disease. Data from blood analyses fror cancer patients and cancer free controls will be compared.

This is a one-off intervention: completion of one questionnaire and donation of one blood sample. There is no follow up for the participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>Partners of cancer patients are invited to join the study as controls</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Survey questions relate to lifestyle and risk factors a person may have been exposed to during their lifetime.

Data from questionnaires of cancer patients and cancer free controls will be compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data is to be supplied within 18 months of cancer diagnosis, but relates to the person's life.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood samples will be analysed in the future in a quest to identify known or new biomarkers for disease.

Data from blood analyses fror cancer patients and cancer free controls will be compared.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood sample is to be supplied within 18 months of cancer diagnosis, and preferably before treatment commences.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Linkage to routinely collected data (eg NSW Central Cancer Registry, Registry of Births Deaths and Marriages, Admitted Patient Data, ABS, 45 and Up Study, Hereditary Cancer Registry ) will provde further information about the person's health and treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Linkages are likely to be performed annually, for the entire dataset, during the life of the study.  There is no endpoint fixed, at this time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18 years or over; live in NSW; diagnosed with a primary cancer in the past 18 months.
Partners of cancer patients(if there is one) who are cancer free (never had a cancer) are also included in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People who have had a previous cancer are not eligible for the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Case control</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cancer Council NSW</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>153 Dowling Street
Woolloomooloo
NSW 2011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Council NSW</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>153 Dowling Street
Woolloomooloo
NSW 2011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The NSW Cancer, Lifestyle, and the Evaluation of Risk (CLEAR) Study is a multi-centre case-control surveillance study in the NSW population. The objectives of the study are:
1. To provide ongoing data on the relative importance of known or emerging exposures and their relationships to leading or emerging cancer types.
2. To investigate in the short term once sample sizes permit, the effects of migration, ethnicity, physical activity, alcohol consumption, smoking, reproductive history, occupation, screening behaviour and certain dietary patterns on the risk of developing cancer of the colon and rectum, prostate, breast and lung, cutaneous melanoma and non-Hodgkin lymphoma.
3. To investigate in the longer term, once sample sizes permit, the effects of these factors on rarer cancer types, such as hepatoma, thyroid, ovarian and pancreatic cancers.
4. To develop a recruitment infrastructure and biological repository of sufficient size to enable the testing of new hypotheses on gene and environment factors, and in some situations, gene-environment interactions, on the risk of cancers affecting the Australian population.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.clearstudy.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Office
Victoria Street
Darlinghurst
NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H06/081 (changed later, after NEAF, to 07/072)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A Prof Freddy Sitas, Principal Investigator</name>
      <address>Director, Cancer Research Division
Cancer Council NSW
153 Dowling Street
Woolloomooloo
NSW 2011</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9334 1837</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8302 3550</fax>
      <email>freddys@nswcc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Revius, Project Coordinator</name>
      <address>Cancer Council NSW
153 Dowling Street
Woolloomooloo
NSW 2011</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9334 1930</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8302 3550</fax>
      <email>michaelr@nswcc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kate Christian</name>
      <address>Cancer Council NSW
153 Dowling Street
Woolloomooloo
NSW 2011</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9334 1426</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8302 3550</fax>
      <email>katec@nswcc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>