<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372497">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000369325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I Study to evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic profile of single and multiple dose of ANB019 in Healthy Subjects and Psoriasis Patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Single Ascending Dose (SAD) and Multiple Ascending Dose (MAD) Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of ANB019 in Healthy Subjects and Psoriasis Patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Sponsor Study Number: ANB019-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Generalized Pustular Psoriasis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Palmoplantar Pustolosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Plaque Psoriasis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a first-in human study of ANB019. It is a double-blind, randomized, placebo controlled, ascending single (SAD) and multiple-doses (MAD) study in healthy participants and plaque psoriasis patients.
The study is planned to have approximately seven cohorts in the SAD section (six for the healthy participants and one for the plaque psoriasis patients) and approximately three in the MAD section of the study (healthy participants only). Cohorts maybe added or removed upon interim analyses evaluations.
Eight (8) healthy participants will be assigned to all single and multiple dose healthy participants cohorts at predicted doses ranging from 10mg to 750mg. 15 plaque psoriasis patients will be assigned to a single dose cohort. The study drug will be administered by subcutaneous (SC) injection (dose of 100 mg) or intravenous (IV) infusion (doses of 10 mg, 40 mg, 100 mg, 300 mg or 750 mg) for the SAD part. For the MAD part and the plaque psoriasis patients cohort, the doses and administration method (SC or IV) will be determined based on the results from the healthy participants SAD part. The infusion time for the IV infusion cohorts will be 1 hour. Each SC or IV dose cohort of eight healthy participants, for both the SAD and MAD parts, will be distributed on a 3:1 ratio to receive ANB019 (six participants) or placebo (two participants). The plaque psoriasis patients cohort will have a distribution of 2:1 patients that receive ANB019 (ten patients) to patients that receive placebo (5 patients).
Participants in the single dose cohorts will be admitted to the clinical facility on Day -1 and will remain in the clinic for up to 3 days for a total of up to 4 days in-house. Dosing of ANB019 or placebo will occur on Day 1. Safety PK and PD assessments will be performed during the study. Participants will return to the facility on Days 4, 5, 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, 43, 57 and 85 for additional PK, immunogenicity, PD and end of study safety assessments.
Participants in the multiple-dose cohort(s) will be admitted to the clinical facility on the morning of Day-1 and will remain in the clinic for 3 days for a total of 4 days in-house. Following this in-house period, participants will be admitted the evening prior to their next dosing day and discharged the evening of the day of dosing for a total of 3 additional doses of ANB019 and 3 additional days in-for a total of 7 days in-house. Each participant will receive 4 doses of ANB019 or placebo, administered weekly by IV infusion. Following the last dose of study drug on Day 22 of the study, participants will return to the facility on Days 29, 36, 43, 57 and 85 for additional PK, immunogenicity, PD and end of study safety assessments.
In order to monitor participants adherence to the treatment schedule, all the study drug administrations will be performed on-site by the study staff.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo will be sterile normal saline (0.9% NaCl) for injection.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety assessments of ANB019 administration will be based on medical review of adverse event reports and the results of vital sign measurements, ECGs, physical examinations, and clinical laboratory tests. The incidence of observed adverse events will be tabulated and reviewed for potential significance and clinical importance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For SAD part: safety blood sampling will be collected at screening (any time in the 21 days interval before the randomization), at check-in on the day before randomization, on day 1 after the dose administration and on each of the days 3, 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, 43, 57 and 85; vital signs will be measured at screening, at check-in, after dose administration and on each of the days 2, 3, 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, 43, 57 and 85 ;ECG will be performed during screening, on day -1, day 2 and day 85; the Adverse Events will be assessed continuously from the time of the first administration of IMP through discharge from the study at the follow-up visit.

For the MAD part: safety blood sampling will be collected at screening (any time in the 21 days interval before the randomization), at check-in on the day before randomization, on day 1 after the dose administration and on each of the days 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, 43, 57 and 85; vital signs will be measured at screening, at check-in, after dose administration and on each of the days 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, 43, 57 and 85 ;ECG will be performed during screening, on day -1, days 8, 15, 22 and 85; the Adverse Events will be assessed continuously from the time of the first administration of IMP through discharge from the study at the follow-up visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic parameters (Cmax, Tmax, AUC (0-T), AUC(INF), T-HALF, CLT (IV only), CLT/F (SC only), Vz (IV only), Vss (IV only), Vz/F (SC only), and F (SC only)) will be derived from plasma concentration of ANB019 or its metabolite versus time data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the SAD part: for SC administered drug the PK collection timepoints are: Pre-Dose, Post-dose at 30 minutes, 1 hour, 4, 8, 24, 48, 72, 96, 168, 336, 504, 672, 840, 1008, 1344 and 2016 hours; for the IV administered drug the PK collection timepoints are: Pre-Dose, Post-dose at 30 minutes, 1 hour, 2, 4, 24, 48, 168, 336, 504, 672, 840, 1008, 1344 and 2016 hours.
For the MAD cohorts, the PK collection timepoints are: for Day 1, 8 and 15, Pre-Dose, 1 hour and 4 hours post dose, on Day 22 Pre-Dose, 1 hour, 4, 8, 24, 168, 336, 504, 840 and 1512 hours post last dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of anti-drug antibodies measured with an immunoassay method to measure antibodies against ANB019 in human serum.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the SAD part, both SC and IV administration methods, the anti-drug antibodies are collected at the following timepoints: Pre-Dose, 672 and 2016 hours Post-Dose.
For the MAD part, the anti-drug antibodies are collected at the following timepoints: Pre-Dose before the dosing on each of the days 1, 8, 15 and 22 and at 1512 hours since the last dose administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ANB019 "ex vivo" inhibition of cytokine release (IL-8) upon IL-36 stimulation performed using whole blood collected from the participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the SAD part, both SC and IV administration methods, whole blood will be collected for the IL-8 assay at the following time-points: Pre-Dose, 24, 168, 504, 1008, 1344 and 2016 hours Post-Dose.

For the MAD part, whole blood will be collected for the IL-8 assay at the following time-points: Pre-Dose, 168, 504 and 1512 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monitor the modifications of Psoriasis Area Severity Index (PASI) scores in moderate to severe Plaque Psoriasis ANB019 dosed patients compared to placebo treated patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>PASI scores will be measured for plaque psoriasis patients cohort only at the following time point during the study: once during Screening period, on Day -1 and then on Days 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, 43, 57, 71 and 85 (End of Study).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For the healthy participants cohorts - healthy male and female as determined by a lack of clinically significant medical history, physical examination, ECGs, and clinical laboratory determinations.

For the plaques psoriasis cohort - male and female participants as determined by lack of clinically significant medical history other than clinically diagnosed moderate to severe plaque psoriasis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Medical History and Concurrent Diseases:
a) Any significant acute or chronic medical illness.
b) History of bacterial or viral infections that led to hospitalization and IV antibiotic or antiviral treatment within 3 months prior to screening, or any recent infection requiring antibiotic or antiviral treatment within 4 weeks of Day 1.
c) History of recurrent or chronic sinusitis, bronchitis, pneumonia, urinary tract infection (recurrent or chronic infection is 2 episodes within 6 months).
d) History of malaria (excluding falciparum).
e) History or any evidence of active infection or febrile illness within 7 days of dosing (e.g., bronchopulmonary, urinary, or gastrointestinal).
f) Active, or history of, parasitic infections such as, but not exclusively, helminth, protozoa, Trypanosoma cruzi.
g) Subjects with a positive quantiFERON (Registered Trademark) test at screening or within 6 months prior to Day 1 will not be eligible for the study.
h) Known or suspected autoimmune disorder, including but not limited to rheumatoid arthritis, fibromyalgia, systemic lupus erythematosus, polymyalgia rheumatica, giant cell arteritis, Behcets disease, dermatomyositis, multiple sclerosis, moderate to severe asthma, or other severe forms of atopy, any autoimmune vasculitis, autoimmune hepatitis, or any other active autoimmune disease for which a subject requires medical follow-up or medical treatment.
i) Any history of known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency state or condition that would compromise the subjects immune status (e.g., history of splenectomy).
j) Presence of any factors that would predispose the subject to develop infection e.g., rectal fissures, poor dentition, open skin lesions, and presence of preexisting skin conditions that increase risks for injection site complications e.g. Behcets Disease, Psoriasis, pustular dermatoses.
k) Current or recent (within 3 months of study drug administration) gastrointestinal disease.
l) Any major surgery within 4 weeks of study drug administration.
m) Any gastrointestinal surgery that could impact upon the absorption of study drug.
n) Donation of blood to a blood bank or in a clinical study (except a screening visit) within 4 weeks of study drug administration (within 2 weeks for plasma only).
o) Blood transfusion within 4 weeks of study drug administration.
p) Inability to tolerate IV or SC drug administration
q) Inability to be venipunctured and/or tolerate venous access.
r) Previous administration of mAbs
s) Smoking more than 10 cigarettes per day.
t) Recent (within 6 months of study drug administration) drug or alcohol abuse as defined in DSM V, Diagnostic Criteria for Drug and Alcohol Abuse.
u) History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of study defined as: an average weekly intake of &gt;21 units for males or &gt;14 units for females. One unit is equivalent to 8 gram of alcohol: a half-pint (approximately 240 mL) of beer, 1 glass (125 mL) of wine, or 1 (25 mL) measure of spirits.
v) Any other sound medical, psychiatric and/or social reason as determined by the Investigator.

2) Psoriasis Patients
a) Have concomitant dermatologic or medical condition(s) which may interfere with the investigator's ability to evaluate the subject's response to the study drug.
b) Have applied any topical medication (including corticosteroid, calcineurin inhibitor,
topical H1 and H2 antihistamines, topical antimicrobials, other medicated topical agents) or herbal preparation within 21 days prior to Day -1.
c) Have received antibiotic treatment within 1 week prior to study entry.
d) Within 4 weeks prior to study entry, have received systemic treatment for psoriasis (including systemic corticosteroids, non-steroidals, immunosuppressants, or immunomodulating drugs) or treatment with UV light.
e) Have received any investigational drug or been part of any clinical trial within a period of three months or five half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to study entry.
f) Previous treatment with anti-tumour necrosis factor (TNF)/interleukin (IL-12/IL-23) and IL-17 or any other monoclonal antibodies is not allowed within 3 months or 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the product prior to Day -1.
g) Use of any over the counter, or complementary medicines within 7 days prior to the run-in period or during the study.
h) Clinical diagnosis of bacterial infections of the skin, including impetigo or abscesses which meets any of the following criteria: hospital admission within 4 weeks of screening; received intravenous, oral or topical antibiotics within 2 weeks of screening.
i) Receipt of a live attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks of screening.
j) Planned surgery during the study.
k) History of malignancy within 5 years, except non-melanoma skin cancer.

3) Physical and Laboratory Test Findings:
a) Evidence of organ dysfunction or any clinically significant deviation from normal in physical examination, vital signs, ECG or clinical laboratory determinations beyond what is consistent with the target population.
b) Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels greater than 1.5 x ULN, confirmed by one repeat.
c) Total and unconjugated bilirubin greater than 1.5 x ULN, confirmed by one repeat. Subjects with a previously documented diagnosis of Gilberts disease who have serum bilirubin less or equal to 3 x ULN may be enrolled.
d) Evidence of clinically significant abnormality in urinalysis testing as determined by the Investigator.
e) Abnormal chest x-ray.
f) Any of the following on 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) prior to study drug administration, confirmed by repeat.
i) PR greater than or equal to 210 msec
ii) QRS greater than or equal to 120 msec
iii) QT greater than or equal to 500 msec
iv) QTcF greater than or equal to 450 msec
g) Positive urine screen for drugs of abuse.
h) Positive breathalyzer test for recent alcohol consumption.
i) Positive blood screen for hepatitis C antibody, hepatitis B surface antigen, or HIV-1, -2 antibodies or p24 antigen (HIV viral RNA test may be conducted if the Investigator deems necessary).

4) Allergies and Adverse Drug Reaction
a) History of any significant drug allergy or reaction (such as anaphylaxis or hepatotoxicity) and reactivity to polysorbate 20 a component of ANB019 formulation, or the inactive ingredients (excipients).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is an ascending dose study divided into three parts. The healthy participants SAD part, in which, depending on the safety of the drug observed on a cohort, the dose might be increased. If the safety and pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic parameters attain levels acceptable to the sponsor and Safety Review Team (SRT), the study will proceed to the plaque psoriasis patients part and the healthy participants multiple ascending dose (MAD) phase. As well, during the MAD part, the decision to escalated the dose will be taken by the SRT based on the safety parameters observed until that moment. The plaque psoriasis patients will be included in parallel with the healthy participants MAD cohorts.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>87</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>7/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AnaptysBio Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 19, HWT Tower,
40 City Road,
Southbank,
Victoria, 3006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AnaptysBio Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 19, HWT Tower,
40 City Road,
Southbank,
Victoria, 3006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>CPR Pharma Services Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>28 Dalgleish Street, 
Thebarton, Adelaide,
South Australia, 5031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Psoriasis is a chronic, inflammatory skin disease affecting approximately 2-3% of the population globally (Christophers, 2001). The most common form of psoriasis is plaque psoriasis (also known as psoriasis vulgaris) occurring in more than 80% of cases (Lebwohl, 2003). Plaque psoriasis is characterized by recurrent episodes of thickened, erythematous skin plaques covered with silvery scales.
IL-36gamma has been shown to be significantly expressed in psoriasis lesions and only weakly expressed in other skin diseases including eczema and erythrosquamous skin conditions, indicating that IL-36gamma is a specific mediator of psoriasis inflammation.
As such, inhibition of IL-36 by targeting the IL-36 with ANB019 may represent a novel therapy for plaque psoriasis patients.
This study will be conducted in three parts: the first part will investigate the effect of a single dose of ABN019 on healthy participants; the second part will investigate the effect of a single dose of ANB019 on psoriasis patients and the third part will investigate the effect of multiple (weekly) doses of ABN019 for 4 weeks on healthy participants. The single dose study will explore different doses of the study drug given either via a subcutaneous (under the skin) injection (SC) or via an intravenous (into the vein) infusion (IV). The results from this part will be used to determine the dose and route of administration to be used for the patients part and the multiple dose part of the study.
Over the entire study a total of 87 people will be enrolled over 10 dosing groups/ cohorts. In each group of 8 healthy participants, 6 will receive the active drug, ANB019 and the other 2 will receive an equivalent placebo (an injection/ infusion that looks identical to the active drug, but contains no active drug). In the psoriasis patients group, out of the 15 patients, 10 will receive the active drug, ANB019, and the remaining 5 will receive placebo.
This study is a dose escalation study meaning that the first group/ cohort will receive the lowest dose of study drug. Results will be reviewed by a safety monitoring committee after each dose strength has been tested to make sure that it is safe to continue with the next higher dose strength in the next group. The next group will not be enrolled until the safety monitoring committee have confirmed it is safe to do so. The study can be stopped at any time, based on evaluation of the side effects of the study drug.
As this is a first in human study, the primary objective of the study is to assess the safety and tolerability of single and multiple doses of ANB019 administered to healthy humans.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>192 Glen Osmond Road,
Eastwood, Adelaide,
South Australia 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-11-811</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network, The Burnet Tower, 5-th Floor,
89 Commercial Road,
Melbourne,
Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90768960</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90768911</fax>
      <email>J.Lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network, The Burnet Tower, 5-th Floor,
89 Commercial Road,
Melbourne,
Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90768960</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90768911</fax>
      <email>J.Lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.a</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network, The Burnet Tower, 5-th Floor,
89 Commercial Road,
Melbourne,
Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90768960</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90768911</fax>
      <email>J.Lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.a</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Florin Bercu</name>
      <address>28 Dalgleish Street, Thebarton,
Adelaide, 5031,
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81596267</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81596348</fax>
      <email>florin.bercu@cprservices.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>