<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336787">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000618954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Enhancing residential substance abuse treatment with computer interventions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial of a computer-based depression intervention for individuals attending a residential substance abuse program.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol and substance abuse</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Computer delivered motivational interviewing and cognitive behavioural therapy (SHADE therapy: Self-Help for Alcohol and other drug use and Depression). Individuals in this condition will complete 2 x 50 minute sessions of the SHADE program each week, over a period of 5 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>A computer delivered touch typing skills program (Type Master Pro). Individuals in this condition will complete 2 x 50 minute sessions of the Type Master Pro each week, over a period of 5 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks and 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysfunctional Attitudes Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Drug Taking Confidence Questionnaire (DTCQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Drug Risk Response Test (DRRT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 week and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ways of Responding (WOR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PENN Alcohol Cravings Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks and 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants attending The Salvation Army William Booth Program will be asked to participate. All participants will have an alcohol or other substance abuse disorder. Previous surveys of The Salvation Army program indicates that approximately 50% of participants report a previous mental health diagnosis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant acquired brain injury

People who's primary language is other than english

People who are acutely suicidal</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be in the first 3-weeks of the William Booth Program. They will complete a structured interview with a research assistant. At the completion of the interview they will be randomly allocated to one of the conditions (1) Treatment (SHADE) or (2) Active Control (Type Master Pro). .</concealment>
    <sequence>All participants upon entry to the study will be given a unique numerical code. This unique code will have previously been randomly assigned a treatment allocation using a random numbers table. The treatment assignment will be written on a piece of paper, and inserted into a blank envelope with the unique participant code written on the front of the envelope. Upon completion of the
initial assessment, the participant will be asked to open the relevant envelope (the one with their unique code entered on the front) to reveal their treatment allocation. The randomisation procedure will stratify for both gender and whether the person is currently taking antidepressant
medication to ensure the proportion of males &amp; females, and individuals with a history of depression is consistent across the two groups. Randomisation will be blocked so that the distribution of participants across treatment conditions will be maintained regardless of the final sample size.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Wollongong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wollongong Campus
Wollongong, NSW
2522</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 3455
Parramatta, NSW 2124
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of New South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>UNSW KENSINGTON CAMPUS
SYDNEY, NSW
2052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Newcastle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Callaghan Campus
Callaghan, NSW
2308</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is extremely common for individuals with substance abuse disorders to also have co-occurring mental health problems. Approximately 60% of participants at Australian residential rehabilitation services report a previous mental health diagnosis, with depressive disorders being the most common. Individuals with co-occurring mental health problems typically have a poorer treatment response and higher rates of relapse. Integrated treatment approaches are recommended for residential substance abuse programs, where both the persons substance abuse and co-occurring mental health problems are concurrently addressed. However, the majority of residential substance abuse services still primarily target the persons substance abuse problems. 

One approach to improve treatment is to utilise computer-based self-help programs. Benefits of computer-based approaches to residential settings include: a) the low costs associated with delivering the intervention; b) it doesnt require additional staff members or training; and c) participants can continue to access the program should they leave the facility early. There is a growing body of literature supporting the usefulness of computer delivered interventions for mental health problems. Additionally, computer-based interventions have been recommended as a way to improve the use of evidence based approaches within routine care. However, only limited controlled dissemination research has been conducted in this area.

The aim of the present study is to examine the effectiveness of using a computer delivered comorbidity treatment program for individuals attending long-term residential substance abuse programs. The study will be conducted as a real-world randomized trial, where the Treatment Condition will complete the computer-delivered intervention in addition to treatment as usual.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Wollongong Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Wollongong Campus
University of Wollongong
Wollongong, NSW
2522</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE09/091</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter Kelly</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Wollongong Campus
University of Wollongong
NSW, 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 42 39 2382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pkelly@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter Kelly</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Wollongong Campus
University of Wollongong
NSW, 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 42 39 2382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pkelly@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter Kelly</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Wollongong Campus
University of Wollongong
NSW, 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 42 39 2382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pkelly@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>