<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366400">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000581662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>HealthTrack : a healthy lifestyle intervention for overweight adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is a novel lifestyle intervention more effective than usual care in achieving weight loss in overweight/obese adults ?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-2562 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>The HealthTrack Study</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>overweight and obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a 12 month single blinded parallel randomised controlled trial with 3 arms: control (usual care), intervention (multidisciplinary lifestyle support) and intervention (multidisciplinary lifestyle support) + a food supplement. Participants will be randomised into a control or one of the intervention groups testing the effect of a novel versus conventional form of individualised health care targeting diet, exercise and health behaviour. Both control and intervention arms will attend the clinic at baseline, 1,2,3,6,9,12 mo for a face to face session with a health practitioner (nurse/control or dietitian supported by an Exercise Physiologist (EP)/intervention) for 40-60 mins. Participants will be encouraged to set diet and physical activity goals based on either information sheets devised for the control or intervention strategy. A client centred approach will be used, with cognitive behavioural enhancement strategies in the intervention group. A phone call will be made between visits by the nurse/control or a health coach (supervised by psychologists)/intervention. Adherence will be monitored by repeat 4 day food records and pedometers. A subset will be given accelerometers. The food supplement is 30g snack packs of walnuts /day for 12 months. At the end of 12 months all participants will be offered to participate in a further 12 months of follow-up. All consented participants will attend for quarterly visits with a dietitian at 15, 18, 21 and 24 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control: usual care involving client centred support and general advice on diet and physical activity using national guidelines
Comparator: novel approach to lifestyle counselling with diet, physical activity and health coaching.
All groups will be offered follow up with a dietitian 12 months post enrolment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight (kg) will be measured in an upright position in minimal clothing and without shoes using scales with a bio-electrical impedance component to also estimate body fat (%) (Tanita TBF-662).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1mo, 2mo, 3, 6,9,12 months, Longer term follow up at 15,18,21,24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diet intake   will be assessed using diet history interview at clinic visits  and 4 day food records (including one weekend day) completed in the periods prior to attending the clinic (to correspond with the timepoints below). Participants record all foods consumed including amounts and recipes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3mo , 6mo, 9mo, and 12mo. Longer term follow up assessments at 15,18,21,24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP) will be measured using the Omron BP-203RPEIII VP-1000 device (Omron Health Care, Kyoto, Japan). Measurements to be collected at the end of 5 min resting period in supine position.  Arterial stiffness (baPWV) and arterial occlusion (ABI) data also collected from device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 mo, 12mo. Longer term follow up assessments at 15,18,21,24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity will be assesed using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) short form survey questions, along with a set of questions regarding the participants perceptions on how much physical activity is necessary for a healthy lifestyle.  A scientific grade pedometer will be used that is accurate and reliable for counting steps and can be used to explain physical activity levels and sedentary time (cut-points)
In a subsample participants will be assigned an accelerometer and trained in its use (placement on wrist, record keeping). They will be asked to wear the accelerometer on two week days and one weekend (to coincide with the 4 day food record). Total number of counts will be recorded for each day. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 mo, 12mo. Longer term follow up assessments at 15,18,21,24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composite psychological assessment will be conducted at 0,3,12 months using items from validated questionnaires to test for psychological flexibility, diet flexibility, and exercise motivation. This assessment will include include items relating to Physical and mental health Sf-12 (12 questions) , Acceptance and action (11 questions),AAQ-W (22 questions), Positive Emotional Well-being (3 questions), Depression anxiety stress short form (DASS  21; 21 questions), Emotional eating (3 questions), Rigid control of diet (R16; 16 questions), and Motivation for exercise (24 questions) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 mo, 12mo. Longer term follow up 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting blood lipids (cholesterol, LDL, HDL, Trig), 
Blood samples collected at a registered Pathology service (Southern Pathology) 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6, 9, 12mo. Longer term follow up 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary sodium 
Participants will be asked to collect a 24 hour urine sample (at 0, 3 and 12 months) prior to their pathology visit and deliver the sample to nursing staff at Southern Pathology.  A container and instruction sheet will be provided to participants at the same time as they are provided with the pathology forms.   A protocol of contact will be undertaken to remind participants to complete the 24 hour urine collection.   This urine sample will test urinary sodium, potassium and creatinine excretion as the gold standard for sodium intake. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0,3,12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting blood glucose  
Blood samples collected at a registered Pathology service (Southern Pathology)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6, 9 12mo. Longer term follow up 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum HBA1c
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3, 6, 9 12mo. Longer term follow up 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>men and women from the Illawarra community (adults aged 25-54 years, permanent resident, community dwelling), at higher risk of lifestyle related disease (defined by BMI range 25-40kg/m2</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>54</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to communicate in English; severe medical conditions impairing ability to participate in study; other medical conditions thought to limit survival to 1 year; immunodeficiency; reported illegal drug use or regular alcohol intake associated with alcoholism (&gt;50g/day); difficulties or major impediments to participating in the components of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment is via advertising to the general media and completion of a screening questionnaire</concealment>
    <sequence>A researcher independent of the participant interface will undertake the randomisation of subjects into diet groups (stratified by sex and BMI, block randomised STATA (V12 Cary NC)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Several power calculations were conducted using SAS PROC POWER using a range standard deviations from 3.5 to 5. One hundred subjects per group were considered sufficient to detect a minimum between group weight loss difference of 2.7kg as significant with 90% power and a two tailed a of 0.025 and 0.017 (adjusted for planned contrast between control and each treatment group and a between treatments comparison). This assumes up to ~25% post randomization dropout rate and a within group weight loss standard deviation of 3.5-5kg (using available literature and our own experience)
The analysis will be conducted using a linear mixed model. The use of the mixed model allows partial datasets incorporating all available data regardless of whether or not the subject completes the study. The planned contrasts are between the control and the intervention groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>377</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>22/05/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2522 - University Of Wollongong</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Illawarra Health and Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Illawarra Health and Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>California Walnut Commission</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>101 Parkshore Drive, Suite 250
Folsom CA 95630-4726
 USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Wollongong
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Wollongong NSW 2522</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Illawarra Shoalhaven Local Health District</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Wollongong Hospital
Locked Bag 8808
South Coast Mail Centre 
NSW 2521</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a 12 month single blinded parallel randomised controlled trial with 3 arms: control (usual care), intervention (multidisciplinary lifestyle support). A 3rd arm comprises intervention + a food supplement . Participants will be randomised into a control or one of the intervention groups testing the effect of a novel versus conventional form of individualised health care targeting diet, exercise and health behaviour. An additional 12 month long term follow-up will be offered to all participants. Consenting participants will attend quarterly visits with a dietitian</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.ihmri.uow.edu.au/healthtrackstudy</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Tapsell LC, Lonergan M, Martin A, Batterham MJ, Neale EP (2015) Interdisciplinary lifestyle intervention for weight management in a community population (HealthTrack study): Study design and baseline sample characteristics.  Contemporary Clinical Trials 45: 394-403.

Tapsell LC., Thorne R., Batterham M., Russell J., Ciarrochi J., Peoples G., Lonergan M., Martin A. (2015) Feasibility of a community-based interdisciplinary lifestyle intervention trial on weight loss (the HealthTrack study). Nutrition and Dietetics 73 (4); 321-328. DOI: 10.1111/1747-0080.12234.

Martin A., Neale EP., Batterham M., Tapsell LC. (2016) Identifying metabolic syndrome in a clinical cohort: implications for prevention of chronic disease. Preventive Medicine Reports 4C; 502-506.

Houston L., Probst Y., Humphries A. (2015) Measuring data quality through a source data verification audit in a clinical research setting. Studies in Health Technology and Informatics 214; 107-113.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The research is focused on healthy lifestyle which also includes physical activity</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University  of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE13/189</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Linda Tapsell</name>
      <address>Smart Foods Centre
University of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 3152</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4844</fax>
      <email>ltapsell@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rebecca Thorne</name>
      <address>Smart Foods Centre
University of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4844</fax>
      <email>beck@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Linda Tapsell</name>
      <address>Smart Foods Centre
University of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 3152</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4844</fax>
      <email>ltapsell@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Linda Tapsell</name>
      <address>Smart Foods Centre
University of Wollongong
Wollongong NSW 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 3152</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 4844</fax>
      <email>ltapsell@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>