<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336946">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000388819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Neural pathways in problem gambling: Brain function after using Naltrexone for problem gambling.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot for regular Naltrexone (Revia Tablets, 25-150mg per day) dosing of 9 Problem Gamblers for 8-12 weeks assessing their neural changes (pre- and post Naltrexone dosing) using function magnetic resonance imaging.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-5590</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NTXPG</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Problem Gambling</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Regular Naltrexone dosing. Initially, participants will be given seven 25mg oral Naltrexone (ReVia; Bristol-Myers Squib) half tablets at intake (to be taken one a day for seven days). The full dosing regimen will begin if no toxicity issues are observed during the previous week and consists of 7 50mg tablets (one per day for seven days). If gambling urges continue dosages can be stepped up in weekly increments to 21 oral 50mg tablets per week (maximum of three 50mg tablets per day). Therefore, daily dosages can range between 25mg to 150mg. The treatment duration is 8-12 weeks depending on efficacy of medication (12 weeks of treatment is scheduled but can be reduced to 8 if significant improvements have been observed).</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gambling behaviour. This will be measured using the timeline followback questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>intake, weekly, post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neural functioning; impulsivity, inhibition, gambling urges. The level of neural activation to three measures of psychological traits associated with problem gambling will be measured using functional magnetic resonance imaging (blood oxygenation level dependent signal change)  and correlated with task events and behavioural responses. Impulsivity will be measured using a delay discounting task, inhibition will be measured using the STROOP task, and gambling urges will be measured by a gambling stimuli task.</outcome>
      <timepoint>intake, post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol use. Weekly breath sample and Timeline Follow back questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>intake, weekly, post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Liver Toxicity. Blood Liver Tests</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intake, mid-trial, post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18-70 years of age.
Provide written consent.
Evidence of Problem Gambling (PGSI).
Seeking treatment for problem gambling.
Primarily Electronic Gaming Machine (EGM) gamblers.
English speaking.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Evidence of a current significant medical illness, psychiatric or neurological disorder (except for medically unmanaged anxiety, mood, and antisocial personality disorders) as indicated by responses to the MINI or semi-structured life histories questionnaire (e.g. medical, psychiatric, and drug histories).
Positive urine specimen to drugs of abuse.
History of a traumatic brain injury or loss of consciousness (10 minutes or more).
History of evidence of claustrophobia
Failure to follow laboratory or study procedures.
Left handed.
Any condition or circumstance that prohibit imaging sessions such as metal implants.
Contraindications to clinical doses of Naltrexone (e.g. currently using opioid analgesics, are opioid dependent, have acute hepatitis, hypersensitivity to Naltrexone, liver/kidney hypertoxicty, or hepatotoxicity). 
History or evidence of allergic reactions to Naltrexone administration (i.e., rash, itching/swelling, severe dizziness, trouble breathing)/
Concurrent use of additional alcohol dependence medication e.g. disulfiram.
Evidence of current illicit opioid use
Use of medications containing opioids/opiates
Uncorrected visual impairment 
Evidence of brain abnormalities from structural scans
Evidence of heart, liver or kidney failure. We will test for liver function in two ways. First, creatinine levels will be assessed to measure general liver function, where levels outside the normal range (Males: 0.6  1.2 mg/dl, Females: 0.5  1.1 mg/dl) will exclude participation. Second, we will test for aminotransferase liver enzymes in the blood, specifically; aspirate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) in a selective blood metabolic panel. Scores outside the normal range for AST (Males: 15  40 U/L, Females: 13  35 U/L) or ALT (Males; 10  40, Females: 7  35) will exclude participation. The definition of heart failure we will use is the inability of the heart to supply sufficient blood flow to meet the needs of the body (Medterms.com, 2011), as evidenced in a clinical interview and physical examination by our physicians.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment.
Potential treatment participants will be recruited from patients who attend the Addiction Medicines Clinic at St Vincent’s Hospital. Local general practitioners will also be informed of the study and interested patients will be directed to contact the Addiction Clinic. Those patients wishing to join the study will complete a pre-screening questionnaire which the chief investigator will review. Those meeting our initial criteria (i.e., 18 – 70 years, evidence of problem gambling, right handed, no current unmanaged medical or psychological issues, no history of brain injury, no metal implants, no current use of alcohol dependence medication, no current use of opioid analgesics) will be contacted and asked to attend an enrolment session at St Vincent’s Addiction Medicines Clinic.

Enrolment.
We will obtain a range of demographic, contact information (including alternative contact numbers, addresses and people), verification of identity, medical, and cognitive data from participants to assess for eligibility (e.g. MINI, PGSI, etc.). In addition, the MRI safety screening form  will be administered to check for contraindications for scanning, whilst absence from recent substance use (e.g. cocaine, marijuana, methamphetamine, etc.) will be assessed using a urine specimen from each participant and assessed by St Vincent’s Laboratory for evidence of opiates, benzodiazepines, cannabis, and amphetamines. To assess for possible hepatotoxicity medical staff will draw blood and conduct liver function tests (also assessed by St Vincent’s Laboratory). Research staff will ask participants to blow into a breath alcohol analyser (Alcolizer HH1/HH2 personal Breath Tester, manufactured by Drivecheck Australia 2000 Pty Ltd) to test for recent alcohol consumption. Once eligibility has been determined the consent process starts. For those who are ineligible for this study they will be directed to free Gambler’s Help Services.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A. Sequential recruitment methods; no randomised allocation as their is only one group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Design.
The methodology we will use is a pre- and post-test design comparing changes in gambling dependence. Participation will last approximately 10-14 weeks: 8-12 weeks for treatment, and 2 weeks of assessments (one week prior to treatment and one week post treatment). There will be one group; an experimental group consisting of 9 people. The participant schedule is as follows:
1.	Recruitment: Rescreening of potential participants using a short questionnaire completed in the clinic. Approximately 5 minutes
2.	Enrolment: Consent process and forms completed and signed. Initial psychological assessments administered (i.e., MINI), breath sample, blood sample and urine specimen supplied at clinic. Approximately 1 hour.
3.	Intake: Baseline psychometric measures taken at clinic. Approximately 1.5 hours. Brain scan at St Vincents Hospital Melbourne MRI. Approximately 1.5 hours (Enrolment and Intake will occur in the same session).
4.	Treatment: Weekly dispensing of 7- day supply of oral Naltrexone tablets (Initially 7 half tablets per week, one a day; maximum 21 full tablets, three per day). This will take approximately 8-12 weeks (8-12 visits) and last approximately 5 minutes (40 minutes to 1 hour total). Weekly breath sample and Timeline Follow-back questionnaire taking approximately 25 minutes (4 -6 hours in total). Mid-trial: Blood liver function tests. Blood draw during weekly assessments. Delay-Discounting and Process of change administered outside scanner. Approximately 15 minutes
5.	Post-Treatment: Psychological assessments, approximately 1.5 hours. TimeLine Follow-back, blood sample and breath sample at clinic, approximately 30 minutes. Brain scan at St Vincents Hospital Melbourne MRI. Approximately 1.5 hours.

Total Visits: 11 -17 (per participant)
Total Time: 13 hours  15 hours (per participant)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>9</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Problem Gambling Research and Treatment Centre, University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Leicester Street,
Carlton, Victoria 3010
Melbourne</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Melbourne Research Office, University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Alan Gilbert Building,
161 Barry Street (Cnr Grattan Street),
Carlton,Victoria 3053
Melbourne</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Problem Gambling Research and Treatment Centre, University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Leicester Street,
Carlton,
Victoria 3010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Addictions Medicine, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Addictions Medicine,
38 Fitzroy Street,
Fitzroy,
Victoria 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Neurology, St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Neurology,
41 Victoria Parade,
Fitzroy,
Victoria 3065</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We propose to examine the effects of regular Naltrexone dosing as an off-label treatment for problem gamblers. We plan to examine the neural activation when we present gambling stimuli, are asked to make self-controlled or impulsive hypothetical choices and when subjects have to inhibit a learned response. Participants will be tested pre and post treatment and correlate these responses with the urge to gamble and self-reported gambling behaviour. By examining these relationships, specifically the change in neurological functioning, we hope to find the neural correlates to measures of problem gambling. Investigating these issues will assist in the analysis of a putative common neurological basis between gambling and alcoholism and hopefully advance both treatments</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee - D (Drug/Device)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Unit,
Level 5, Mary Aikenhead Building,
27 Victoria Parade,
Fitzroy, 
Victoria 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>077/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Darren R. Christensen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
University of Lethbridge,
4401 University Drive
Lethbridge,
Alberta, T1K3M4
</address>
      <phone>+1 403-329-5124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>darren.christensen@uleth.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Darren R. Christensen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
University of Lethbridge,
4401 University Drive
Lethbridge,
Alberta, T1K3M4</address>
      <phone>+1 403-329-5124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>darren.christensen@uleth.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Darren R. Christensen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
University of Lethbridge,
4401 University Drive
Lethbridge,
Alberta, T1K3M4</address>
      <phone>+1 403-329-5124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>darrenc@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Darren R. Christensen</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
University of Lethbridge,
4401 University Drive,
Lethbridge,
Alberta, T1K3M4
</address>
      <phone>+1 403-329-5124</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>darren.christensen@uleth.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>