<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365974">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000051549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of a new iPhone Mood Management Application </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does the mobile phone app 'Music eScape' promote positive mental health and wellbeing in young people? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-9539</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Emotion Regulation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Positive Mental Health </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Wellbeing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Young people will be invited to use a new music and emotion based mobile phone application 'Music eScape' over a 1 month period. Participants' emotional identification and regulation, wellbeing and involvement in music will be measured before and after using the application. 

The "Music eScape" application automatically tags the user's music library with moods. Users can draw a 'musical journey' through moods by identifying how they are currently feeling and how they would like to feel. Thus the application generates an automated playlist aiming to take the user through the chosen moods by using music.</interventions>
    <comparator>A wait list control will be used whereby 50% of the sample will be provided the mobile phone application one month later than the experimental cohort. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Develop an understanding of emotion regulation and the impact this has on mental health and wellbeing in young people based on participants use of the eScape app and self reports of the success of the app assisting them to reach their target mood as well as on wellbeing and emotion regulation measures including the Difficulties in Emotion Regulation Scale (DERS), K10, Flourishing Scale, Mental Health Continuum Short Form (MHC-SF) and Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS)   </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month post, 2 months post, 3 months post, 6 months post</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Develop an understanding of the use of music and technology to promote positive mental health and wellbeing in young people based on participants use of the eScape app and self reports of their experience of using the mobile application, the success of the app assisting them to reach their target mood as well as on wellbeing and emotion regulation measures including the DERS, K10, Flourishing Scale, MHC-SF, and SWLS   </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 month post, 2 months post, 3 months post, 6 months post</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged 17-25 years
2. Have normal hearing
3. Have access to an iPhone 4 or later model
4. Experiencing mild levels of stress/distress </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have a hearing impairment 
2. Do not have access to an iPhone 4 or later model 
3. Not experiencing mild levels of stress/distress</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Half of the sample will be randomly allocated to a wait list control group. These participants will act as a control for themselves (one month without the intervention vs one month with the intervention) and for the immediate access group (effect of intervention vs no intervention over a one month period).   </designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Earlier, similarly structured research conducted by the same team has used samples of this size to observe outcomes in similar variables. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>23/12/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>190</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>164</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Young and Well Collaborative Research Centre </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit 17, 71 Victoria Crescent
Abbotsford, VIC, 3067</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Young and Well Collaborative Research Centre  </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 17, 71 Victoria Crescent
Abbotsford, VIC, 3067</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Jessica Lewis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology, The University of Queensland
McElwain Building
University of Queensland 
St Lucia, QLD, 4072

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the usability, acceptability and impact of the Music eScape application and its capacity to promote wellbeing in young people. The eScape app is designed for users to identify their current and desired mood states and produce a playlist of mood-tagged music from their own music library that will help them achieve this. 

Prototype testing will be conducted to inform the development of the Music eScape app. Two groups of five participants will each be asked to complete a 30 minute survey, then attend a focus group to explore the mobile application and test its functionality.  

We are then seeking young people who experience at least mild levels of stress/distress to test the music-based mobile phone application. Young people will complete a brief 10-item screen questionnaire to determine their eligibility for participating in the study. 180 participants who report at least mild levels of stress/distress in the past month will be recruited for the outcome evaluation. Participants will be asked to complete an online survey, which will include questionnaires addressing emotion identification and regulation, wellbeing and involvement in music. 

Half of the participants will be asked to download the free eScape app on their mobile devices and trial it for one month (referred to as the immediate access group), while logging in their current and target moods, along with the success rate of the application in assisting them to reach their target mood. During their use of the application, details of app usage (e.g., number of times used, duration of use, features used) will be recorded and automatically downloaded. Participants will be followed up at the end of their one month of app use, and again two, three and six months later to complete online surveys addressing emotion regulation, wellbeing and their experience of using the mobile application. Participants will receive 4 SMSs over their initial first month of app use to remind them to use the app.

The remaining half will comprise a waitlist control, whose access to the application will be delayed by one month. Delayed app access provides a control group for comparison of mood regulation in absence of any intervention. Waitlisted participants will receive up to 4 SMSs to minimise participant attrition. After this month, their involvement will replicate that of the immediate access group, outlined above. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>QUT Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>QUT
IHBI
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1300000803</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Leanne Hides</name>
      <address>QUT 
IHBI
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4069</address>
      <phone>+617 3138 6144</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>leanne.hides@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Leanne Hides </name>
      <address>QUT 
IHBI
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4069</address>
      <phone>+617 3138 6144</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>leanne.hides@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Leanne Hides</name>
      <address>QUT 
IHBI
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4069</address>
      <phone>+617 3138 6144</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>leanne.hides@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jessica Lewis </name>
      <address>School of Psychology, The University of Queensland
McElwain Building
St Lucia, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.lewis3@uq.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>