<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336082">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000904077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of a fully automated online mindfulness-based intervention used by people with problematic alcohol use</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of a fully automated online mindfulness-based intervention used by people with problematic alcohol use</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Efficacy of internet based intervention targeting mental health and wellbeing in a sample of people who drink alcohol to harmful levels</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This project seeks to investigate the efficacy of an internet based fully automated self-help mindfulness program in the promotion of wellbeing and the reduction of symptoms of anxiety and depression amongst people who drink alcohol to harmful levels. 

The Mindfulness Online program will be located on the Swinburne University's eTherapy Unit website. Participants within the target demographic will be invited to participate by email and paper-based flyers. 

The program consists of three sessions designed to make an individual more mindful or aware of moment to moment experiences. The programs duration is 3 weeks. Participants will complete the AUDIT (Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test) to determine eligibility for the study (a score of 8 or higher) and eligible participants will be randomly allocated into either a control waitlist group or an active experimental group. The experimental group will access the mindfulness program immediately and will be advised to complete one session per week. Each session is expected to take 20 minutes and is conducted in participants' own time, within the 3 week period. In addition, participants will be encouraged to practise mindfulness each day for five minutes.

Both the active experimental group and the waitlist control group will be required to log in and complete a series of questionnaires at pre intervention (25 minutes), post intervention, 1 month follow up and 3 month follow up (20 minutes each). The waitlist control group are not required to undertake further activities during the 3 week intervention phase.</interventions>
    <comparator>The study employs a randomised controlled design. Participants will be allocated to either an intervention group who will receive access to the online intervention immediately or to a waitlist control condition. The Waitlist control group will be given access to the intervention after the three month follow up time point for the experimental group (15 weeks after completion of pre-intervention quetionnaires).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention, post intervention, one month and three month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scales (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention, post intervention, one month and three month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal Wellbeing Index (PWI-A5)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention, post intervention, one month and three month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention, post intervention, one month and three month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Severity of Dependence Scale (SDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention, post intervention, one month and three month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mindfulness Attention Awareness Scale (MAAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention, post intervention, one month and three month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Mental Health Continuum-Short Form (MHC-SF)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention, post intervention, one month and three month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Multidimensional Helath Locus of Control Scale (MHLC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Credibility Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be aged 18 years or over and will obtain a score of 8 or higher on the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People under the age of 18 years and those scoring 7 or lower on the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) will be excluded.

This is a open-access health promotion wellbeing program, not designed to 'treat' any condition.  Nor are we targeting people or assessing for alcohol abuse/dependence disorders. Therefore we cannot confirm that participants will be healthy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment to either the waitlist controlled group or the experimental group will be carried out through central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Once participants give their consent and obtain a score of 8 or more on the AUDIT, they will be randomly allocated (based on the date and time of registration, via computer generated random numbers) into one of two groups: a Waitlist Control (WC) group or a Mindfulness Online (MO) group. Once participants finish the pre-intervention surveys they will be informed on the screen about which group they have been allocated to. The WC group will be advised that they will be placed on a waiting list and asked to complete the surveys three more times, and then in 15 weeks they will receive an automated email giving them details of how they can access the MO program. The MO group will be informed of how they can immediately access the MO program. The MO group can then re-enter the MO website at a convenient time and location.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>74</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swinburne eTherapy Unit and National eTherapy Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Swinburne University of Technology
P.O. Box 218
HAWTHORN VIC 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Swinburne's eTherapy Unit will run a research trial to investigate the efficacy of a fully automated self-help online mindfulness intervention, Mindfulness Online, in the promotion of wellbeing amongst people who drink alcohol to harmful levels. Swinburne University of Technology's eTherapy Unit and National eTherapy Centre (NeTC) have developed numerous internet-based prevention and treatment programs that are available to the general public for the treatment of clinical conditions and the promotion of well being. To continue the development of effective online programs, information relating to the appropriateness and efficacy of specific programs for specific user groups is required. The current project seeks to examine the efficacy of the Mindfulness Online program (developed by Dr Jo Mitchell) in its application to adults aged 18 years and over, who scored 8 or higher on the AUDIT. The results of this research will inform future development and recommendation of internet based interventions for specific user groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University Human Research Ethics Committe (SUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Officer
Office of Research and Graduate Studies (H68)
Swinburne University of Technology
P.O. Box 218
HAWTHORN VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SUHREC 2010/170</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Director, eTherapy Unit and the National eTherapy Centre 
Faculty of Life and Social Sciences 
Swinburne University of Technology
PO Box 218 
Hawthorn
VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>61 3 9214 8851</phone>
      <fax>61 3 9214 5260</fax>
      <email>bklein@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Director, eTherapy Unit and the National eTherapy Centre 
Faculty of Life and Social Sciences 
Swinburne University of Technology
PO Box 218 
Hawthorn
VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>61 3 9214 8851</phone>
      <fax>61 3 9214 5260</fax>
      <email>bklein@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Jennifer Hall</name>
      <address>eTherapy Unit and National eTherapy Centre 
Faculty of Life and Social Sciences
Swinburne University 
P.O. Box 218
Hawthorn 
VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>61 405 551 207</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>2749211@student.swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>