<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320868">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000037000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ceramic implants to support dentures for the edentolous patients: a new metal free approach</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ceramic implants to support dentures for the edentolous patients: a new metal free approach</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>This research is designed to evaluate the surgical and peri-implant prosthodontic outcomes of one-piece titanium and ceramic implant designs supporting overdentures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Test group: ceramic implants will be used 

The in-vitro study will utilize numerical modelling and finite element analysis to develop novel designs for ceramic implants and metal-free attachment systems for implant overdentures. 

The in-vivo study will involve surgical and prosthodontic rehabilitation of 40 completely edentulous participants with implant overdentures

The surgical procedure for the placement of ceramic/titanium will be according to a standard protocol by one surgeon. The surgeon will access that portion of the jawbone where the ceramic/titanium implant will be placed. Initially the surgeon will need to access the bone that lies in the region where the tooth implant will be placed. To do so, the surgeon will create a few incisions in the patient's gums that outline two separate flaps of gum tissue. The surgeon will then use a hand instrument to push and peel each flap of gum tissue back, so the bone that lies underneath is revealed. The implant drilling and placement process can then be performed. Each patient will receive three implants in the mandible on the first surgical visit and on the second surgical visit he/she will receive four implants for the upper jaw. Each visit will take two hours. Follow-up visit will be of 15 minutes to remove the sutures.</interventions>
    <comparator>In the control group: the implants will be made from titanium</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surgical outcomes High success rates of cermic/titanium implants will demonstrate high surgical outcomes Outcome measurement: Implant success will be evaluated using a four field table according to Albrektsson and Zarb (1993 &amp; 1998) Marginal bone loss measures by standardized radiographs (Payne et al., 1999). Implant stability: evaluated by resonance frequency analysis (Meredith, 1998; Sennerby and Meredith, 1998). Modified plaque index (Mombelli et al., 1987; Mombelli and Lang, 1994) Modified sulcus bleeding index (Mombelli et al., 1987; Mombelli and Lang, 1994).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, one year and annually thereafter for 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prosthetic design that is number and distribution of implants will be evaluated

This research will be conducted using both an in-vitro and in-vivo study. Firstly, the in-vitro research will evaluate and develop novel designs of ceramic implants to support maxillary and mandibular overdentures and their plastic metal-free attachment systems. Secondly, the in-vivo study will be performed to determine the prosthodontic outcome of novel distribution of ceramic and titanium implants supporting maxillary and mandibular overdentures using plastic attachment systems. 
In addition, a qualitative research will be conducted to evaluate overall patients' general perception on titanium or ceramic implants supporting overdentures. 
In-vitro study:

Numerical modeling and finite element analyses to develop novel designs for ceramic implants and plastic attachment systems for implant overdentures.

Propose an ideal attachment system for ceramic implants in terms of material and design that would require minimal or negligible maintenance possible based on the outcome of these investigations.

Investigate the extent of prosthodontic maintenance and repair as well as the causes of failures of one-piece ceramic implants and their attachment systems for implant overdentures

A semi-structured interview as a qualitative assessment will be conducted to perceive patients' perception on titanium and ceramic implants supporting overdentures. Subsequent to each answer being recorded, the response will be read back to the participant for confirmation and further clarification. This will also enable the assessment of the rationale for the participants' preference for a particular type of an implant material and address their adaptive and maladaptive nature to removable prostheses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, one year and annually thereafter for 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Baseline, one year and annually thereafter for 5 years </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, one year, annually thereafter for 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Baseline, one year and annually thereafter for 5 years </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, one year, annually thereafter for 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Edentulous participants requesting maxillary and mandibular overdentures with adequate bone volume &amp; quality to accommodate implants, good compliance &amp; commitment to attend follow-up review appointments.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient with any systemic disorder that precludes implant placement, bruxism or parafunctional habits, history of irradiation to head &amp; neck, drug and/or alcoholic dependence, systemic or local bone pathology, smokers. Patients on intra venous (IV) forms of bisphosphonates</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Principal investigators will blindly allocate participants to either of the 2 groups by asking them to pick up one of the sequentially numbered, opaque sealed envelopes containing either of the two interventions. 

By this way each participant will have an equal chance of being assigned to one of the two groups.

Randomization process will be based in accordance with items 8-10 of the CONSORT statement 2001-checklist for the randomized controlled clinical trials (Cochrane Collaboration, Manchester, UK).</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using procedures such as coin-tossing and dice-rolling</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Implants (Ltd)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Southern Implants
South Africa 
I PO Box 605</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>South Africa</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Implants (Ltd)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Southern Implants,
South Africa 
I PO Box 605</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>South Africa</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sir JohnWalsk research Institute,
School of Dentistry,
University of Otago
310 Great King Street
Dunedin</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Titanium implants have been used in the last four decades to replace missing teeth. Alternatives to titanium such as zirconia may offer aesthetic advantages and be more acceptable to patients and clinicians concerned about titanium allergy, but must show equivalent biological acceptability to titanium. 
Purpose: The research aimed to investigate soft and hard tissue response to Titanium (Ti) and Zirconia (Zr) implants in edentulous patients. 
Materials and Methods: The research included 24 participants (Ti =12, Zr =12) restored with one-piece ball-abutment implants to support overdentures. Participants received four maxillary implants (two in the premolar alveolus, one off-centre in the alveolar mid-line and one wide-diameter implant in the anterior median palate) and three mandibular implants (one in the mid-line and bilateral posterior implants). 
Results: Success rates for both Ti and Zr implants were low, 67.9% for all alveolar implants and a survival rate of 50.0% for the palatal implants. Only 11 (52.4%) of 21 palatal implants survived the follow up period. Peri-implant health was equivalent for Ti and Zr implants, and showed no statistically significant changes from loading to the one-year follow-up. Statistically significant differences were noted in radiographic bone level between titanium and zirconia implants (p= 0.02), with Zr showing greater bone loss. 
Conclusions:  This study has demonstrated higher failure rates of one-piece titanium and one-piece ceramic implants. The use of the one-piece-ceramic or titanium implants presented in this study cannot be recommended
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Siddiqi, A, Kieser JA, De Silva, RK, McNaughton A, Zafar S, Duncan WJ. (2013) Histomorphometric comparison of trabecular bone micro-architecture in the median palate and maxillary premolar alveolar sites of edentulous elderly cadavers. Accepted for publication in Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgey.
2. Siddiqi, A, Kieser JA, De Silva, Zafar S, Duncan WJ. Bone-implant contact of Zirconium ceramic implants versus Titanium implants in the jaw and femur of a new ovine animal model. (2013) Submitted for publication in Clinical Implant Dentistry and Related Research.
3. Siddiqi, A, Kieser JA, De Silva, Duncan WJ. Bone-implant contact of Ceramic versus Titanium implants: A histomorphometric analysis. J Dent Res 91(Spec Iss A): abstract # 2575, 2013 (www.dentalresearch.org).
4. Siddiqi A, Kieser JA, De Silva RK, McNaughton A, Duncan WJ. (2012) Could the mid-palate accommodate wide-bodied implants in order to support maxillary over-dentures? A radiomorphometric study of human cadavers. Clinical Oral Implants Research. 00, 2012; 19 doi: 10.1111/clr.12050.
5. Osman RB, Ma S, Duncan WJ, De Silva RK, Siddiqi A, Swain MV. (2012) Fractured zirconia implants and related implant designs: scanning electron microscopy analysis. Clinical Oral Implants Research.
6. Siddiqi A, Duncan W, Kieser J, De Sliva RK. (2012) A comparison of trabecular bone micro-architecture in the median palate and maxillary pre-molar alveolar sites of edentulous elderly cadavers: A radiomorphometric study.  Abstract in the New Zealand Dental Journal 108: 149.
7. Siddiqi A, Payne AGT, De Silva R, Duncan WJ. (2011) Titanium allergy: could it affect dental implant integration? Clinical Oral Implants Research 22: 673680. 
8. Siddiqi A, Payne AGT, Duncan W, De Silva RK. (2011) Surgical and peri-implant outcomes of ceramic implants supporting overdentures Abstract in New Zealand Dental Journal 107: 30
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Lower South Ethics Committee.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lower South Ethics Committee. 
Ministry of Health
229 Moray Palace
PO Box 5849
Dunedin</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LRS/09/06/023</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/07/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Warwick Duncan</name>
      <address>Oral Implantology Research Group, School of Dentistry, Sir John Walsh Research Institute, University of Otago, Dunedin.</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4797119</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 4795079</fax>
      <email>warwick.duncan @dent.otago.ac.nz
+64 4 4797110</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Allauddin Siddiqi</name>
      <address>PhD Student, Oral Implantology Research Group, School of Dentistry, Sir John Walsh Research Institute, University of Otago, Dunedin.</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4795664</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 4795079</fax>
      <email>sidal065@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Allauddin Siddiqi</name>
      <address>PhD Student, Oral Implantology Research Group, School of Dentistry, Sir John Walsh Research Institute, University of Otago, Dunedin.</address>
      <phone>+64 3 4795664</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 4795079</fax>
      <email>sidal065@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Allauddin Siddiqi</name>
      <address>PhD Student, Oral Implantology Research Group, School of Dentistry, Sir John Walsh Research Institute, University of Otago, Dunedin.</address>
      <phone>+ 64 34795664</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sidal065@student.otao.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>