<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364579">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000791730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Preventing Progression of Chronic Kidney Disease in Primary Care: A Quality Improvement Pilot Study Using Specialist Renal Nursing in the Primary Care Setting </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adults with type 2 diabetes at high risk of chronic kidney disease progression, does a health service delivery model using a nurse-led clinic result in improved markers of chronic kidney disease progression, decreased risk of cardiovascular events, and improved self-management? A pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1145-5901</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CKD Pilot</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Proteinuria</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Non-adherence</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Risk of cardiovascular events</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention involves a series of sessions in GP practices led by  a nephrology Nurse Practitioner with the assistance of a practice nurse, to deliver medical care based on best practice guidelines through tailored education and the development of individualised care plans, and using self-management and patient-centered theory utilizing the Flinders Chronic Care model. Participants will be seen fortnightly for 30 minutes for 12 weeks by the NP and the practice nurse in an intense induction phase, and then for 30 minutes monthly in a maintenance and monitoring phase to 12 months. A detailed patient education package was developed for the study and included information on diabetes and its complications, blood pressure management, lifestyle modifications, medication adherence, smoking cessation and dietary advice including low salt intake (dietary sodium intake less than 2.3 g/day). All patients were also given a booklet on self-management developed for the study where they could record all clinical results, self-care goals, individualised medication charts and other important information. Adherence to intervention will be monitored through self-reporting using self-management survey instruments, GP attendance records, and clinical and laboratory parameters. Outcomes will all be ascertained as 3 monthly repeated measures.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proteinuria (urinary albumin to creatinine ratio, ACR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure (manual using JNC 7 protocol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c) by serum assay (Abbott)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Estimated glomerular filtration rate ('175' 4-variable MDRD equation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5-year absolute cardiovascular risk (likelihood of a cardiovascular event over 5 years estimated using New Zealand prediction equations (the New Zealand Guidelines Group: New Zealand Cardiovascular Guidelines Handbook: A summary resource for primary care practitioners, 2 edn. Wellington: (New Zealand) Ministry of Health; 2009 ) </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index (BMI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum cholesterol by assay (Abbott)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of active smoking (Partners In Health instrument, self reported)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall medical knowledge (Partners In Health instrument, self reported)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall self management (Partners In Health instrument, self reported)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to medication (Partners In Health instrument, self reported)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prescription of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors or receptor antagonists</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prescription of aspirin</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prescription of lipid lowering medication</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adoption of a health lifestyle (Partners In Health instrument)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age &gt;= 18 years
2. Diagnosis of type 2 diabetes mellitus
3. Diagnosis of hypertension
3. Proteinuria defined as an albumin to creatinine ratio (ACR) &gt; 30
mg/mmol on at least three occasions separated by at least 1 week 
4. At high risk of CKD progression as defined by 
a) at least 12 months of uncontrolled diabetes, defined as HbA1c consistently &gt;8%, AND/OR
b) at least 12 months of uncontrolled hypertension, defined as BP consistently &gt;140/90 mmHg, AND 
c) a history of poor attendance and engagement with their GP (history of unplanned non-attendance of 25% or more of scheduled appointments over the course of 12 months). 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. CKD due to renal parenchymal disease other than diabetic nephropathy
2. Unsuitable for the intervention in the view of their treating GP
3. Unwilling or unable to provide consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be screened and recruited through the clinical records of two primary care (General Practitioner) practices. All eligible patients will be identified, and initially given written information and invitation to participate by their GP or practice nurse. All will be subsequently re-contacted by phone to answer any questions, and offered an initial assessment. Since there is no control group, allocation procedures and concealment in not applicable.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis of study data will use regression models. For continuous data, we will use linear models and for categorical ones we will use logistic models. To account for internal correlation between repeated patient observations, a random effect model will be used for each dependent variable that includes all data from all time periods simultaneously, with observations over time from the same participant sharing the same random effects, assuming different random effects for different participants. To account for non-response bias, regression coefficients will be estimated using the maximum likelihood method. Equivalent analyses after a normalising data transformation will be carried out if non-normality of outcomes is evinced. When a transformation is applied, location estimates and confidence intervals will be transformed back to the original scale, with first-degree bias correction. 

The study is a pilot study, a pilot study, intended to be a small scale preliminary study in order to evaluate feasibility, time, cost, and effect size (statistical variability). As such, no specific calculation for sample size was performed. A minimum sample size of 50 participants was considered a pragmatic target. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/09/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>54</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hawke's Bay</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand Ministry of Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CVD diabetes Long Term Conditions 
Personal Health Service Improvement 
Sector Capability and Implementation 
Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CVD diabetes Long Term Conditions 
Personal Health Service Improvement 
Sector Capability and Implementation 
Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hawke's Bay District Health Board</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Corner Omahu Road and McLeod Street
Private Bag 9014
Hastings 4156
New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic kidney disease (CKD) is an important global health issue, the leading causes being diabetes mellitus and hypertension. Early detection and effective management of risk factors have the potential to delay CKD progression to end stage kidney disease (ESKD), and decrease mortality and morbidity from cardiovascular (CV) disease. We will evaluated a nurse-led intervention utilizing specialist renal nursing in the primary care setting to reduce accepted risk factors for CKD progression and CV disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hawke's Bay DHB Institutional Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hawke's Bay DHB
Corner Omahu Road and McLeod Street
Private Bag 9014
Hastings 4156</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>No approval ID, approved by IRB as "CKD Pilot"</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rachael Claire Walker</name>
      <address>Nurse Practitioner, 
C/- Renal House, 
Hawkes Bay Regional Hospital, 
Hawkes Bay District Health Board,
Private Bag 9014,
Hastings 4120,</address>
      <phone>+64 27 234 9205</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rachael.Walker@hawkesbaydhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nick Raymond Polaschek</name>
      <address>Senior Project Manager, 
CVD diabetes Long Term Conditions,
Personal Health Service Improvement, 
Sector Capability and Implementation, 
Ministry of Health,
PO Box 5013,
Wellington 6145,</address>
      <phone>+64 27 234 9205</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Nick_Polaschek@moh.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Roger Marshall</name>
      <address>Clinical Head, Department of Renal Medicine,
Counties Manukau District Health Board, 
Private Bag 93311,
Otahuhu,
Auckland 1640,</address>
      <phone>+64 21 461766</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mrmarsh@woosh.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Roger Marshall</name>
      <address>Clinical Head, Department of Renal Medicine
Counties Manukau District Health Board 
Private Bag 93311
Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>+64 21 461766</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mrmarsh@woosh.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>