<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371362">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001429448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of a single injection of Articul One in comparison with Synvisc-One Registered Trademark or placebo for the treatment of symptomatic primary knee osteoarthritis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, double-blind using blinded evaluator, placebo and active controlled, pilot study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of intra articular administration of Articul One in patient with symptomatic primary knee osteoarthritis </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-3354 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>MT-GPRT-KOA01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of the knee </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Product: Articul One
Dosage form: pre-filled syringe 
Presentation: Blister containing 3mL syringe enclosed with rubber stoppers and 23G, 1" disposable needle, prefilled with 3mL of formulation as described below.
Route of Administration: Single Intra-articular injection 
Formulation:
Ingredient 1: Sodium hyaluronate (60mg)
Ingredient 2: Sodium dihydrogen phosphate dehydrate (1.2mg)
Ingredient 3: Disodium hydrogen phosphate dehydrate (3.6mg)
Ingredient 4: Sodium Chloride (24.9mg)

Injection will be performed by qualified medical doctors who will be defined as Sub-Investigators in the study. The medical doctors in this study are specialists in pain management.
During the washout period (up to 21 days), participants will be asked to discontinue their anti-inflammatory agents (e.g., NSAIDs) and other analgesics prior to the Baseline Period. 
Only paracetamol (not more than 4 grams per day) will be allowed as rescue medication and this cannot be used within 48 hours of any site visits.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Active comparator arm: Synvisc-One Registered Trademark (6ml) will be given as a single intra-articular injection. 
Placebo: A 3mL intra-articular injection of Phosphate Buffered Saline.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>WOMAC (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index)
To assess the change from baseline in WOMAC A subscore* </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 weeks using Likert Scale in Articul One in patients with Knee Osteoarthritis.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>WOMAC (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index) 
Change from Baseline in WOMAC A1 subscale </outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 4, 12, 20 and 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>WOMAC (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index) 
Change from Baseline in WOMAC A subscale </outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 4, 20 and 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>WOMAC (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index) 
Change from Baseline in WOMAC A subscale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>WOMAC (Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index)
Change from Baseline in WOMAC B subscale **</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 4, 12, 20 and 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from Baseline in WOMAC C subscale ***</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 4, 12, 20 and 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinician Observer Global Assessment (COGA) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 4, 12, 20 and 26 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Global Assessment (PTGA) score </outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 4, 12, 20 and 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumption of paracetamol
*: The WOMAC A subscale is calculated as a mean of 5 WOMAC A (pain) subscale.
**: WOMAC B subscale is calculated as a mean of WOMAC B (stiffness) subscale.
***: WOMAC C subscale is calculated as a mean of WOMAC C (Physical Function) subscale.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Provided written informed consent
Evidence of grade II or III OA (Kellergan-Lawrence scale) on X-ray
Has documented diagnosis of symptomatic primary osteoarthritis of the study knee made at least 3 months prior to Screening.
Has continued study knee osteoarthritis pain despite conservative treatment (e.g., weight reduction, physical therapy, analgesics).
Is ambulatory with an active lifestyle and in good general health. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Had arthroplasty at the study knee at any time or any other previous surgery in the study knee within the 6 months prior to Screening, or  planned surgery throughout the duration of the study.
History of septic arthritis in any joint.
Concomitant inflammatory disease or other condition that affects the joints.
Any known contraindication to paracetamol.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>At week 0, participants with symptomatic primary knee osteoarthritis will be randomized to receive a single intraarticular injection of Articul One or with Synvisc-One Registered Trademark or Placebo.  Total 30 subjects (20 in Articul One, 5 in Synvisc-One Registered Trademark, 5 in Placebo) will be enrolled in the study.
Once a participant qualifies to participate in the study, the site will receive the randomization number for the participant via the interactive web response system (IWRS).</concealment>
    <sequence>A block randomization method will be implemented using SAS ver.9 or higher. The entire randomization-related procedure will be performed and managed by IWRS</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>From previous studies that measured the WOMAC A change after Synvisc-One administration in patients with symptomatic primary knee osteoarthritis, the pre-dose to post-dose Week 12 score change was reported as 0.9+/-0.8 points, respectively(Chevalier). Therefore, this study assumed the expected for pre-dose to post-dose change in the WOMAC A score as 0.9 points, and the standard deviation for the change was assumed as 0.8 of standard deviations in prior studies. 
Based on these assumptions and the significance level for a 2-sided test of 0.05, statistical power of 99%, the minimum sample size is calculated.
Considering drop-out rate of 25%, total 20 subjects were calculated.
In addition, this study is designed to exploratory comparison of the difference between Articul One  vs Synvisc-One and Articul One  vs Placebo. Thus total 10 subjects (5 in Synvisc-One, 5 in Placebo) additionally will be enrolled in the study.  
The planned number of subjects is considered adequate to obtain data for effect size and sample size for subsequent next clinical studies.

For the efficacy assessment, the Full Analysis set is used as the main analysis set, and the Per Protocol set is also analyzed supportively and results are compared.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>8/01/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>16/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>9/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>14/09/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2292 - Broadmeadow</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Network Services (CNS) Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4, 88 Jephson Street
Toowong, Brisbane, QLD 4066
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medytox, Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>78 Gangni 1-gil
Ochang-eup , Cheongwon-gu
Cheongju-si, Chungcheongbuk-do</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Korea, Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Medytox, Inc </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>78 Gangni 1-gil
Ochang-eup , Cheongwon-gu
Cheongju-si, Chungcheongbuk-do</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Korea, Republic Of</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to investigate the effectiveness and safety of a single intraarticular injection of Articul One in comparison with Synvisc-One Registered Trademark or placebo for the treatment of symptomatic primary knee osteoarthritis. 30 subjects will be randomized to receive either Articul one , the experimental arm (20 subjects), Synvisc-One Registered Trademark, the active comparator arm (5 subjects), or Placebo (5 subjects). This will be done by analysing questionnaires to understand the severity of the disease status, pain and rescue medication diary, and side effects. Safety will be monitored during the treatment visits using standard measures, including physical exams, vital signs (including oral temperature), and side effect monitoring. 

Subjects may be eligible to join this study if they are aged over 40 years, have knee pain due to osteoarthritis of the knee and are in otherwise general good health. 

This study will investigate a single dose of Articul One in comparison with Synvisc-One Registered Trademark or placebo (a treatment with no active ingredients which looks like the real thing but it is not). This study is double-blind which means the subject and the assessing doctor, together with the study staff will not know whether the subject is receiving Articul One, Synvisc-One Registered Trademark or placebo. The person who administers the injection will be unblinded (they will know what treatment the subject will receive) however, they will not allow the subject or the assessing team know which treatment  is being received.

The study includes a screening visit (visit 1) to check eligibility and to explain the study.. There will be 1 treatment visit (visit 2) which will occur within 21 days of visit 1. There will also be 4 further visits to assess the safety and effectiveness of the treatment. These visits will occur at weeks 4, 12, 20 and 26.

During the follow up period, four clinic visits are required for: review of diary, medications, AEs;. Participants will record rescue pain medication in a daily diary.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Ltd</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Rd, Eastwood, SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marc Russo</name>
      <address>Genesis Research Services Pty Limited 
220 Denison Street
Broadmeadow NSW 2292

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 1860</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>PI@genesisresearchservices.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Byungyun Han </name>
      <address>Medytox, Inc
78 Gangni 1-gil
Ochang-eup , Cheongwon-gu
Cheongju-si, Chungcheongbuk-do</address>
      <phone>+82.70.8666.6945</phone>
      <fax>+82.2.6941.2241</fax>
      <email>byungyun.han@medy-tox.co.kr</email>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wooshun Lee</name>
      <address>Medytox, Inc
78 Gangni 1-gil
Ochang-eup , Cheongwon-gu
Cheongju-si, Chungcheongbuk-do</address>
      <phone>+82.70.8666.6945</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drlee@medy-tox.co.kr</email>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Deanna Bolto</name>
      <address>Clinical Network Services (CNS) Pty Ltd
Level 4, 88 Jephson St,  TOOWONG   QLD   4066,  Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+61(0)7 3719 6000 </phone>
      <fax>+61(0)7 3719 6011</fax>
      <email>deanna.bolto@clinical.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>