<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320871">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/12/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001034224</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dose Adjustment with Food Insulin Index: the DAFII study, comparing carbohydrate counting versus DAFII algorithm for estimating insulin dosage on measures of glycemic control in adults with type 1 diabetes consuming two different breakfast meals</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To compare carbohydrate counting versus DAFII algorithm for estimating insulin dosage on measures of glycemic control in adults with type 1 diabetes consuming two different breakfast meals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DAFII study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this within-subject crossover study, two methods of adjusting the dose of insulin to match the nutrients in a meal will be compared on measures of postprandial glycemia control in adults with type 1 diabetes. One method, known as carbohydrate counting, uses an algorithm (= formula) that matches the bolus insulin dose to the carbohydrate content of the meal. The other method uses a novel algorithm based on the foods normal insulin response in healthy subjects (DAFII algorithm). Three meal and bolus-dose algorithm combined conditions will be administered in a random order to each participant who is an experienced insulin pump user on three consecutive days. The three test conditions are as follows: 1) meal A (54 g grain bread, 23 ml raspberry jam and 177 g canned peach in syrup), containing 83 g of carbohydrate + bolus algorithm using carbohydrate counting; 2) meal B (59 g croissant, 96 g yogurt and 48 g poached egg), containing 41 g of carbohydrate + bolus algorithm using carbohydrate counting; 3) meal B + bolus  using DAFII algorithm. According to DAFII algorithm, meal A and B have the same bolus insulin dose because of the same insulin demand. Therefore only 3 test conditions will be in randomization. 

The blood glucose levels after meal will be monitored using both a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGMS) and finger-prick blood testings with a blood monitor at regular intervals over the next 3 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Carbohydrate counting, a standard formula to adjust the bolus insulin dose, serves as the control.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial blood glucose profile measured by a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGMS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured after an overnight fast (10 to 12 hours) and over 3 hours after starting eating the breakfast meal</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial blood glucose profile measured by testing finger-prick blood with a blood glucose monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured after an overnight fast (10 to 12 hours) and at regular intervals over 3 hours postprandially ( 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 minutes)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypoglycemia  occurrence measured by a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGMS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured after an overnight fast (10 to 12 hours) and over 3 hours postprandially</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patients with type I diabetes diagnosed for more than 1 year, age 18 - 70 years; use of insulin pump therapy, for more than 3 months; recent glycated haemoglobin (HbA1C) less than 9.0 % and reliably performing self-monitoring of blood glucose at least four times daily.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Eating disorders; individuals using medication that may influence blood glucose profiles.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An outside investigator who is not directly involved with the study will randomize the order of test meal/insulin dose algorithm combination for identification numbers and seal these in labelled opaque envelopes prior to the commencement of the study. After inclusion into the study, participants are given an identification number, which has a previously allocated randomised meal / dose algorithm order.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation digits table from a statistic book will be used to randomise the order of test meal / insulin dose algorithm combination for individual identification numbers.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>35</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4,  Molecular and Microbial Biosciences (MMB) building, G08 The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, Molecular and Microbial Biosciences (MMB) building, G08 The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Gabrielle Howard, Endocrinologist</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 2, 27 Belgrave St, Manly, NSW, 2095</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this within-subject crossover study in individuals with type 1 diabetes, we will compare two methods of adjusting the dose of insulin to match the nutrients in a meal.  One method, known as carbohydrate counting, uses an algorithm (= formula) that matches the dose of insulin to the carbohydrate content of the meal. The second method uses a novel algorithm based on the foods normal insulin response in healthy subjects (the Food Insulin Index or FII). Participants who are experienced users of insulin pumps will consume three breakfast meals and apply different insulin to food algorithms on 3 consecutive test days. Their blood glucose levels will be monitored using a continuous glucose monitoring system (CGMS) and finger-prick blood testings with a blood monitor over the next 3 hours. We hypothesize that using the novel FII to adjust mealtime insulin dose will improve blood glucose readings (ie reduce hyperglycaemia) without increasing the risk of hypoglycaemia, compared with carbohydrate counting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, the University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Jane Foss Russell Building - G02
The University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11-2009/12211</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Jennie Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>Room 472, Human Nutrition Unit, School of Molecular and Microbial Biosciences, G08, University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 3759</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 6022</fax>
      <email>j.brandmiller@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Jennie Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>Room 472, Human Nutrition Unit, School of Molecular and Microbial Biosciences, G08, University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 3759</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 6022</fax>
      <email>j.brandmiller@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Jennie Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>Room 472, Human Nutrition Unit, School of Molecular and Microbial Biosciences, G08, University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 3759</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 6022</fax>
      <email>j.brandmiller@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>