<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370655">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000145303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to investigate the safety of a permanent indwelling catheter for the drainage of malignant ascites in patients experiencing gynecological, gastrointestinal and breast cancers, versus intermittent serial paracentesis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The MORCA study: A study to investigate the safety of a permanent indwelling catheter for the drainage of malignant ascites in patients experiencing gynecological, gastrointestinal and breast cancers, versus intermittent serial paracentesis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-6554</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The MORCA study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malignant ascites</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm A: Temporary placed catheter for recurrent large volume drainage (current best practice) 

Arm B: Permanent placed indwelling catheter (Rocket 'Registered Trademark') for intermittent drainage (treatment group).
Operators / Interventional Radiologists restricted to two very experienced radiolkogists are to wear head, face and shoe coverings. All access to the room will be restricted to the team performing the procedure. Patients are to be nil by mouth for 6 hours before the procedure (water with medication allowed). Patients may receive conscious sedation with IV midazolam (1 mg) and IV fentanyl (50 mcg).  This will be adjusted as required due to patient discomfort, anxiety and body habitus and previous opiate exposure. 

There will be prophylactic pre-procedure antibiotic coverage for skin flora with IV cefazolin 1g will also be administered. An appropriate alternative will be provided for people who have a Cephalosporin allergy.

Radiologic Technique: Sonography will be performed before the surgical scrub to localise of a large pocket of ascites. Lateral location for initial access is preferred to facilitate a medially directed subcutaneous tunnel. This allows the exit site of the catheter to be close to midline, allowing a convenient place for access.

The Rocket Indwelling Abdominal Catheter will be placed as per the product instructions for use. All the equipment needed for placement is included in the Kit.  The site is selected and the patient is prepped. The surgical field will be prepared with providone iodine solution. The operative field will then be draped.

The skin of the insertion site and tunnel will be infiltrated with local anaesthetic. A small incision is then made at the insertion site and the tunnel exit site.  Under ultrasound guidance the 18g needle will be inserted into the peritoneal cavity and aspiration performed to confirm position. The guide-wire will then be inserted through the needle and the needle removed leaving the guide wire in-situ.  The IAC would then be tunnelled (antegrade) using the pre-attached tunnelling device and then drawn through until the cuff is mid-way along the tunnel. 

The 16g tear way sheath will be then inserted over the guide wire into the peritoneal cavity. The catheter detached from its tunneller and inserted through the sheath which is then torn away and removed. The catheter will then be withdrawn until the cuff is one centimetre from the outer end of the tunnel.  The primary insertion site and the tunnel exit are then closed and the site is dressed.  The included drainage bag would then be attached to the catheter and the ascites allowed to drain freely. 

Approximately 90 minutes for the pre and post procedure within interventional radiology, with an additional 6 hours post op follow up within oncology acutes.

The catheter will remain in-situ until death, or removed for an adverse event removal, or at patients request.

Weekly visits to patient  home will be carried out by the Research Nurse. Abdomen will be assessed for ascites, if present will be drained up to a maxim of 2L.

Weekly visits will include an assessment of the insertion site for infection, drainage problems ie occlusion and leakage from the insertion site. All results will be recorded and tabled in the results on frequency of each problem.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm A: Temporary placed catheter for recurrent large volume drainage (current best practice). The patient attends acute oncology and  sent for ultrasonography both to confirm the presence of fluid and to identify where the most successful entry point for the drain would be.  Once a site is chosen an X is marked on the skin using an ink pen.  The patient then returns to Acute Oncology for paracentesis.  The patient is discharged as soon as drainage is completed.

Patients are contacted weekly to assess their level of discomfort and to determine the best time to come in and have a paracentesis. This is very individual and can range from once a week to once every 30 days.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine the difference in quality of life between the two groups as assessed by the EORTC QLQ-C30 (scores of primary interest).  The study will have 80% power and 95% confidence to detect a 20 point difference between the two groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Difference in score between baseline and at 12 week visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of Ovarian Symptoms and Treatment (MOST) questionnaire.

This questionnaire will be used for all patients. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Difference in score between baseline and at 12 week visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Satisfaction with Treatment FACIT-TS-G (Version 1) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Difference in score between baseline and at 12 week visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Paracentesis-free interval / Drainage-free interval</outcome>
      <timepoint>Difference in results between baseline and at 12 week visit. Calculated from Baseline/Random visit to next drainage in days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) will be recorded as per CTC version 3.0. Severity (CTC grade 1-4) its relationship to the study drug/treatment (suspected/not suspected) and its duration (start and end dates or if continuing at final exam) will be recorded.

An example would be an infection from the indwelling catheter, CTC grade on WCC and if oral  or Iv antibiotics are required.

There will be an Independent Monitoring Committee (IMC) for this study. They will be requested to assess the trial safety after 10 patents have been recruited to the study. The study will be terminated if there are three or more SAEs thought to be due to the study treatment OR as directed by the Independent Monitoring Committee at any time
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly from baseline for 12 weeks and/or 28 days from last study visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Karnofsky Score (KS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Difference in score between baseline and at 12 week visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AEs (adverse events) will be recorded as per CTC version 3.0. Severity (CTC grade 1-4) its relationship to the study drug/treatment (suspected/not suspected) and its duration (start and end dates or if continuing at final exam) and whether it constitutes a serious adverse event (SAE)will be recorded.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly from baseline for 12 weeks and/or 28 days from last study visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ECOG PS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Difference in score between baseline and at 12 week visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients greater than or equal to 18 years old
2. Histologically confirmed cancer (Histological or cytological specimens must be collected via surgical biopsy, brushing, washing or core needle aspiration of a defined lesion)
3. Patients should be aware of the diagnosis of cancer and that there are no further systemic anti-cancer treatment options open to them
4. Patients diagnosed with cancer of ovarian (or related), gastrointestinal or breast cancer 
5. Patients able to give written informed consent obtained according to local guidelines
6. Fulfils at least  Grade 2 or 3  International Ascites Club criteria and are symptomatic. (Grade 2: moderate ascites with moderate symmetrical distension of the abdomen and Grade 3: large or gross ascites with marked abdominal distension). Patients should have greater than or equal to grade 2 ascites.
7. Karnofsky Score greater than or equal to 60 OR ECOG Performance Status 0, 1, 2 or 3
8. Requires two therapeutic paracentesis within the last 30 days and been paracentesis-free for the last seven days.
9. Patients with systolic BP greater than or equal to 100 mmHG or diastolic greater than or equal to 60 mm HG

10. Lab values within the range as defined below, on day of randomisation
Absolute neutrophils count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1.5 x  109/L
Platelets greater than or equal to 100 x 109/L
Haemoglobin greater than or equal to  90 g/dL
INR greater than or equal to  1.3
Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN 
Serum bilirubin ULN and both Aspartate transaminase (AST) and Alanine transaminase less than or equal to 5 x ULN 
11. Life expectancy greater than or equal to 3 months
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patient unwilling or unable to comply with the study protocol 
2. Patients with a stoma
3. Patients receiving enteral feeding
4. Concurrent severe and / or uncontrolled medical disease (e.g. uncontrolled diabetes)
5. Infection e.g. peritoneal cavity
6.History of liver disease with chronic cirrhosis
7. Planned intravenous, oral or intraperitoneal chemotherapy or immunotherapy and active treatment in the last 21 days.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enclosed treatment assignments will be serially numbered in opaque, sealed envelopes and opened sequentially after the participant’s name and other details have been written on the appropriate envelope </concealment>
    <sequence>Performed by Ms Joanna Stewart and Ms Ying Huang (Bio-statistician's University of Auckland).

Block randomisation by using SAS 9.4</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To investigate the effect of treatment on the outcomes of interest a general linear mixed model will be used to run a random co-efficient analysis with the EORTC QLQ C30 QOL score as the outcome, time, group and time by group interaction as explanatory variables. The slope over time and intercept for each individual will be included as random effects.  These items of primary interest are those questions that assess symptoms related to ascites and overall quality of life.  They are questions 8-15, 18-19, 29 and 30. That is 12 of the total 30 questions from the EORTC QLQ-C30.

The study will have 80% power and 95% confidence to detect a 20 point difference in the primary items of interest within the EORTC QLQ-C30 between the two groups.  This is a large difference and therefore if the study is negative a smaller but still not insignificant difference may still exist.  There will be a 58% power to detect a 15 point difference.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland City Hospital Cancer and Blood Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gillian Vernon
Research Manager
Cancer and Blood Research
Lower Ground Floor, Building 13, 
Auckland City Hospital, Auckland, 1023
Post Address: Private Bag 92024, Auckland, 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland District Health Board A+ grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ADHB Research Office
Auckland City Hospital
Level 14, Support Building,
Park Road, Grafton,
Private Bag 92024
Auckland 1142, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomised study of a temporary placed catheter for serial intermittent use versus a permanent placed indwelling catheter (Rocket 'Registered Trademark') for continuous drainage of malignant ascites in cancer patients. This study will investigate the acceptability and safety of an indwelling catheter for patients with cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/NTA/185</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Celia Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Palliative Care
Auckland City Hospital
Private Bag 92024
Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 2184 6314	</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CeliaP@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Celia Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Palliative Care
Auckland City Hospital
Private Bag 92024
Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 2184 6314	</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CeliaP@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Celia Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Palliative Care
Auckland City Hospital
Private Bag 92024
Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 2184 6314	</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>CeliaP@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elaine Rogers</name>
      <address>POBOX 110124
Auckland City Hospital
Auckland 1148
</address>
      <phone>+64 211 424 189</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elaine.rogers@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>