<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370416">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000677404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of the effects of general and spinal anaesthesia during cesearean section on breastfeeding
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of the effects of general and spinal anaesthesia during cesearean section on breastfeeding

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>breastfeeding</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast feeding</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patients demographic data were recorded. The patients were divided into two groups based on the type of anaesthesia they received during their caesarean section. Patients were enrolled into the study post-delivery.
Non randomized.
Group G (General anaesthesia): Preoxygenation was achieved with 100% oxygen for 3 minutes. For induction of general anaesthesia, intravenous 2 mg/kg propofol (Propofol (R), Fresenius-kabi; Istanbul, Turkey), intravenous 1.5 mg/kg, lidocaine (Jetmonal(R) 2%, Adeka; Istanbul, Turkey) and intravenous 0.9 mg/kg rocuronium (Esmeron(R), MSD; Istanbul, Turkey) were administered. After the infant was delivered, intravenous 1 mcg/kg fentanyl (Talinat(R), Vem; Istanbul, Turkey) was administered. For maintenance, 50% O2+ 50% air + 1 MAC sevoflurane (Sevorane(R), Abbvie; Istanbul, Turkey) was administered. Tenoxicam (Tilcotil(R), Deva; Istanbul, Turkey) 20 mg was administered intravenously for postoperative pain.  
Group S (Spinal anaesthesia): Spinal anaesthesia was performed by inserting a 25G Quince needle at the L3-4 or L4-5 space. Intratekal 12 mg hyperbaric bupivacaine (Bustesin %0.5 spinal heavy (R), Vem; Istanbul, Turkey) was administered. 
The patients were assessed by another anaesthetist at postoperative 1 and 24 hours and 6 months. </interventions>
    <comparator>Group S (spinal anaesthesia): While the patients were in sitting position, appropriate site cleaning was performed with the 25G Quincke spinal needle through the L3-L4 or L4-L5 disc space. 15mg 0.5% bupivacaine (Bustesin %0.5 spinal heavy(R), Vem; Istanbul, Turkey)  was administered into subarachnoid space.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of breastfeeding in the first 24 hours after surgery assessed through medical records

</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of breastfeeding in the first hour after surgery through medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>First hour post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of breastfeeding in the first 6 months after birth assessed through medical records


</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant subjects at term who were admitted for caesarean section and whom we could contact via phone were included</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-term subjects, those with foetal distress, mentally retarded subjects, those who did not cooperate and those who do not speak Turkish were excluded from the study. The subjects whose infants were admitted to the neonatal intensive care unit after delivery were also excluded. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>6</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>330</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>248</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Bursa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Derya Karasu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Derya Karasu</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Canan Yilmaz</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Turkey</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose: We aim to compare the effects of general anaesthesia and spinal anaesthesia on breastfeeding in caesarean section cases.
Method: Pregnant subjects at term who were admitted for caesarean section and whom we could contact via phone were included. Pre-term subjects, those with foetal distress, mentally retarded subjects, those who did not cooperate and those who do not speak Turkish were excluded from the study. The subjects whose infants were admitted to the neonatal intensive care unit after delivery were also excluded. The subjects demographic data were recorded. The subjects were divided into two groups: those undergoing general anaesthesia (Group G) and those undergoing spinal anaesthesia (Group S). Breastfeeding was assessed by another anaesthetist at post-operative 1 and 24 hours and 6 months. 
Findings: A total of 248 subjects were assessed statistically. No statistically significant difference was found between the two groups in terms of first breastfeeding interval. The rate of breastfeeding within 1 hour of delivery was 15.5% in Group G and 21.8% in Group S. The difference was not statistically significant. No statistically significant difference was found between the groups in terms of the rate of breastfeeding within the first 24 hours, either. The rate of breastfeeding in the 6-month period was statistically significantly higher in Group S than Group G.
Result: We believe that our study contributes to the literature on investigating spinal anaesthesia and general anaesthesia in breastfeeding subjects. We think that in term pregnancies, the type of anaesthesia does not affect the first breastfeeding interval; however, spinal anaesthesia is superior to general anaesthesia in long-term breastfeeding.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>no applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital 
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa
Turkey</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/11-09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Derya Karasu</name>
      <address>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</address>
      <phone>+905057281175</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drderyatopuz@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Canan Yilmaz</name>
      <address>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</address>
      <phone>+90 5059045989</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr_cnnylmz@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Derya Karasu</name>
      <address>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</address>
      <phone>+905057281175</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drderyatopuz@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>