<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363691">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000182796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tonsil Dressing Feasibility Study assessing the use of an Oral Wound Dressing in Adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility Study Assessing 14 days of Postoperative Pain after a single direct application of an Oral Wound Dressing in Post-Tonsillectomy Adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>tonsil hyperplasia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>tonsillitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Tonsil Dressing
This oral wound dressing in powder form is applied immediately post-tonsillectomy as a single intervention on the tonsillectomy wound.  The powder binds to the wound becoming a gel and forms a protective barrier.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control: standard treatment
Participants enrolled and randomized to the standard treatment arm will receive a tonsillectomy with standard post-operative care and no wound dressing.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary purpose of this study is to measure the differences in postoperative pain in subjects undergoing electrodissection monopolar diathermy tonsillectomy who are treated with the Tonsil Dressing (treatment cohort) compared to those undergoing the same procedure who do not receive the Tonsil Dressing (control cohort).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain is measured by the study participant twice daily for 14 days using a visual analogue scale from 0 to 10.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to measure the differences in postoperative recovery time (i.e. return to normal activity and return to normal nutritional intake) in the treatment cohort compared to the control cohort. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative recovery time is measured by the study participant twice daily for 14 days using a questionnaire in a subject notebook.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety data will be collected categorized and evaluated.
Postoperative complications and events will be recorded daily by the participant in a Subject Notebook (diary) and/or reported directly to the clinic. Adverse events will be assessed by the investigator during study procedures (e.g. surgery or discharge) and with an oral cavity examination at the follow-up visit (day 15-25) and upon review of the Subject Notebook.  Adverse events will be recorded on specific case report forms.
Potential Adverse events include the following: 
Allergic reaction, 
Post-operative bleeding, 
Laryngospasm, 
Dehydration, 
Nausea, 
Vomiting,  
Foreign Body Response, 
Referred Ear Pain, 
Oedema, 
Erythema,  
Infection, 
Surgical Pain,  	
Prolonged Surgical Pain, 
Abnormal or Impaired Wound Healing, 
Permanent change in voice, 
Nasal regurgitation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety data will be collected by the study participants daily for 14 days postoperatively and by the investigator at the follow-up visit occurring at day 15 - 25 postoperatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18  50 years of age
Indicated for tonsillectomy due to obstructive breathing tonsil hyperplasia, tonsillitis or other chronic throat-related illness</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior tonsillectomy or tonsillotomy
Concurrent surgical procedures (including adenoidectomy)
Subject has a known shellfish allergy
Body Mass Index (BMI) greater than 35
Known bleeding disorder or prescribed anticoagulants
Cranial facial abnormalities that may interfere with access to the tonsils
Subject is immunocompromised (e.g., taking immunosuppressive medication)
Chronic or frequent use of pain medications
Subject has a serious comorbid condition that may interfere with the conduct or results of the clinical study
Subject is currently participating in another clinical study and has not been approved for concurrent enrolment by the Study Sponsor.
Subject is pregnant or breast-feeding
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be recruited from the practices and clinics of the participating Study Investigators.  The potential subject will be assessed for preliminary eligibility, and subsequently interviewed for their interest in the study and willingness to comply with the study protocol. Potential candidates will be provided the Participant Information Sheet, and will be given ample opportunity to ask questions and receive further information from the study personnel before deciding whether or not they will participate in the study. If the candidate agrees to participate, he/she will be asked to sign the Informed Consent Form.  
Once the Informed Consent Form is signed, the subject will be considered enrolled in the study.

Allocation is concealed through the use of central randomization by a computer system.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will be assigned through a computer database associated with the electronic case report form system.  Once the preliminary participant information has been entered into the system the computer program will select the randomization assignment for that subject.

Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerized sequence generation).
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As this is a feasibility study, and the endpoints do not require a quantified definition of success, no statistical analysis will be undertaken. The data resulting from this study will be summarized and interpreted by the Sponsor using interim assessments; in addition, a final report will be generated after all data are collected.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Cairns Base Hospital - Cairns</hospital>
    <hospital>Mona Vale Hospital - Mona Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Caloundra Private Hospital - Caloundra</hospital>
    <hospital>Noosa Hospital - Noosaville</hospital>
    <hospital>Pittwater Day Surgery - Mona Vale</hospital>
    <postcode>4870 - Cairns City</postcode>
    <postcode>1660 - Mona Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>4551 - Caloundra</postcode>
    <postcode>4566 - Noosaville</postcode>
    <postcode>2103 - Mona Vale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medtronic Australasia Pty Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>97 Waterloo Road
North Ryde, NSW 2113</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medtronic Surgical Technologies</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6743 Southpoint Drive North; Jacksonville, FL USA 32216</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Medtronic Surgical Technologies</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>6743 Southpoint Drive North; Jacksonville, FL 32216</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a prospective, randomized, single-blinded study to observe subject safety and measure efficacy of the Tonsil Dressing in the treatment of subjects post-tonsillectomy.  Up to 36 subjects will be enrolled at up to 6 Australian investigational sites.  Subjects will be randomized 2:1 (test:control).  Tonsillectomy performed using electrodissection monopolar diathermy (10-15W).  Subjects will complete self-assessments of pain (2x/day), activity and nutrition levels for 14 days.  Clinic follow-up visit between days 15-25.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Final Report 31/10/2014
Publications are pending</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Greenslopes Research and Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Greenslopes Private Hosp
Newdegate Street
Greenslopes QLD 4120</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00161</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Gochee, MD</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery 
Cairns Base Hospital
The Esplanade
Cairns 4870 QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 42268085</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 42266519</fax>
      <email>peter.gochee@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Henri Heijnen, PhD.</name>
      <address>8 Benambra Dr. 
Lower Templestowe, VIC 3107</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 435 771 943</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hheijnen@iprimus.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hodge</name>
      <address>6743 Southpoint Drive North
Jacksonville, FL 32216</address>
      <phone>+1 904 2812774</phone>
      <fax>+1 763 3674106</fax>
      <email>david.l.hodge@medtronic.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hodge</name>
      <address>6743 Southpoint Drive North
Jacksonville, FL 32216</address>
      <phone>+1 904 2812774</phone>
      <fax>+1 763 3674106</fax>
      <email>david.l.hodge@medtronic.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>