<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371841">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001638426p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A clinical trial about the effectiveness  of a supported employment linkage intervention for people with schizophrenia  admitted to an  adult mental health unit who want to work.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single blind randomised controlled clinical trial comparing a supported employment linkage intervention to treatment as usual  on work and clinical outcomes  in chronic schizophrenia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SET</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions> There will be two study arms in this clinical trial. Arm 1: Supported Employment Linkage Intervention (SEL) and Treatment As Usual (TAU). Arm 2: Treatment As Usual (TAU).  SEL involves mental health nurse clinicians, with outreach capacity, working on the Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit (SCGH MHU), who will  deliver the intervention. The intervention starts  during the inpatient admission., The patient is linked to an employment agency, called Edge, which is  for people with mental and physical disabilities . Edge has good fidelity to the Individual Placement and Support (IPS) model of supported employment as measured by the IPS fidelity scale. 
The mental health nurse clinician forms a therapeutic relationship with the patient as soon as they complete their comprehensive medical assessment by their treating team on the SCGH MHU and it is deemed during this assessment the patient has schizophrenia and wants to work in competitive employment. The patient is given a blank Treating Doctors Report (TDR) and a Verification of Medical Condition(s)  form (VMC) in an Edge Information Pack (EIP) by the nurse  to be filled out by the patients general practitioner validating capability for at least 8 hours competitive work per week. The TDR and VMC are required to state the patients diagnosis, symptoms and an overview of their current medical conditions. The  nurse  supports and empowers the patient to find and attend a general practitioner to fill out the TDR and VMC while still on the SCGH MHU wherever possible. However this step can occur after discharge. If the patients team are supporting a disability pension application this process and the required forms are completed by the treating Team first.
The nurse  empowers the patient to make and attend an appointment with Edge during the admission or after discharge. The wait list is 1 week at the most. At the initial and subsequent Edge interviews a family member is welcome to attend. During this initial Edge interview the reality of the patients career aspirations is determined and their medical condition disclosed. Regional work in the mining industry is explained as a non-option through Edge. 
The patient plus or minus a family member and Edge worker, request and keep an appointment with Centrelink, the pension agency, for a job capacity assessment (JCA) and an Employment Services Assessment (ESAT) by a job capacity assessor. This appointment could occur whilst an inpatient on the SCGH MHU but may occur after discharge. The patient brings their completed VMC and TDR to this appointment. Based on a 15-30 minute interview and the VMC and TDR the assessor determines the genuineness of the disability and the capacity for at least 8 hours per week work whilst on the disability pension or 15 hours per week  if not on the disability pension.  The patient has to specify that they want Edge for help with job searching and ongoing job support. Centrelink then make a registration appointment with Edge via an on-line diary for the patient plus or minus a family member. Once Edge receives the Centrelink job capacity assessors on-line report and appointment they contact the patient to come in for this registration appointment. This usually takes 1-2 weeks. The patient can go into Edge to see how this is progressing if they are anxious. At the registration appointment with Edge the work capacity is checked as correct.  The work goals and aspirations are again determined as reality based and an employment specialist is allocated. Financial counselling, if required, is offered by a financial counsellor. 
After discharge from the SCGH MHU the designated mental health nurse  contacts the patient weekly by telephone to empower them to be able to work through the steps required to become embedded in the employment agency, Edge, and trust and work with its support. The nurse provides  weekly telephone contact  for up to 6 months from the date of recruitment and the frequency is individually tailored. The ending of this contact is patient determined in collaboration with the nurse . 
Edge will provide support with job search to find an employer who wants to make a place for a sensitive stigmatised individual with schizophrenia in their workplace as well as ongoing job support. Edge requires mandatory 2 weekly appointments with the Edge employment specialist and the patient. Additional support is individually tailored by Edge. The employment specialist helps with resumes, job finding, interviews, and on and off job support. 
For patients who dont attend appointments Edge will provide a telephone call, one letter and a wait of 6 months before deregistering the patient. However, the  SCGH MHU nurse  still has the capacity to make telephone contact with the patient on a weekly basis for up to 6 months following recruitment at the SCGH MHU. These linkage attempts will stop or restart by patient request. If no open competitive employment is found within 2 years the patient is discharged from Edge. The patient can go through the Edge admission process again at any time. The patient can transfer to another employment agency. The nurse  will contact Edge 2 monthly to check on the patients progress and provide help with any issues.  A successful supported employment linkage intervention is achieving at least a 6 month block of registration with Edge in the 2 year period post recruitment. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>TAU  starts  at the time of  recruitment when the patient is at the SCGH MHU . TAU  involves medication plus at least one medical check-up over 12 months with a doctor and a minimum of one other treatment program attendance from the following list: Psychiatrist visit/visits in addition to the one medical check-up over 12 months with a doctor already mentioned; General practitioner visit/visits; Regular pickup of Webster medication packs at pharmacy; Hospital in the Home twice daily nurse visits for 2 weeks; Mental health nurse outreach support; Generic case manager outreach support; Supportive inpatient milieu as required; Inpatient or outpatient occupational therapy program; Community rehabilitation program; Inpatient alcohol and drug program; Inpatient alcohol and drug brief information pack; Community alcohol and drug rehabilitation program; Nicotine addiction treatment; Drop in centre support; Sheltered work; Supported employment; Volunteer work; Education pathway with support; Education pathway without support; Family meetings; Other type of therapy; Non-government organisation outreach support; Non-government organisation social integration via recreational activities; Recreational group/s; Spiritual group; Regular exercise; Supported accommodation-Psychiatric hostel, group home, supported rental alone or shared, family home, aged care facility.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Yes or no to a competitive job. Yes to a competitive job means the participant has worked at least 30 minutes on at least 1 day in a job in an integrated situation in the community where they have done the same tasks as a non- disabled person for the same minimum or higher wage. No means the latter has not been achieved. Yes or No to a competitive job will be self reported using the Job Acquisition Questionnaire. It will be confirmed by also interviewing the employment specialist at Edge Employment agency. Type of job, start time, finish time, hours per week and wages will also be self reported and confirmed by Employment specialist at Edge. </outcome>
      <timepoint>In the last month at baseline and in last 6 months following recruitment at 6, 12,18 and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Digit Span Test (Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale - Revised)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6,12,18 and 24 months post recruitment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trail Making test part A &amp; B</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline , 6,12,18 and 24 months post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brief Psychiatric rating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 6,12,18 and 24 months post recruitment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Addiction Severity Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 6, 12,18 and 24 months post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of Quality of Life Instrument (AQoL-4D Basic)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline,6,12,18 and 24 months post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rosenberg Self Esteem Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6,12,18 and 24 months post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adult Hope Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6,12,18 and 24 months post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>UCLA Loneliness Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activity and Participation Questionnaire (APQ-6)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of schizophrenia defined by DSM-V and want to work; not previously received or currently receiving the supported employment linkage intervention; voluntary resident of SCGH MHU; plans to reside in Australia for the duration of follow-ups; available for follow-up for 2 years; able to comply with requirements of the protocol; able and willing to understand and provide written informed consent; aged between 18 and 65 years of age.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Highly dependent on medical care; significant communication barrier.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The trial design is a randomised single blind clinical trial comparing 2 treatments groups: Supported Employment Linkage Intervention plus Treatment As Usual and Treatment As Usual.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size and power calculations
For a moderate effect size for the primary outcome measure in job acquisition which will be either yes or no to a job over the 2 year period post recruitment and an expected power of 0.8 we will need 36 for each group. There will be an expected dropout rate of 10 to 20 in each group so we will canvas 56 patients for each group.

Data Analysis
A mixed model repeat measures ANOVA (suitable given multiple time points of data collection) will be conducted using SPSSv21 to test the hypotheses that the SEL+TAU group will have significantly higher scores of yes to a job over the 2 year period post recruitment compared to the TAU group at 4 varying time points. In clinical work we use multiple measures of outcome.  No power has been calculated for these other secondary outcome measures. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>112</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>North Metropolitan Health Service -Adult Mental Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 1 PO box Claremont, Western Australia. 6910</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>North Metropolitan Health - Mental Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 1 PO Box Claremont. Western Australia.6009.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Universitiy of Western Australia School of Psychiatry</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital. D Block. Verdun Street. Nedlands. Western Australia. 6009.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim: This is a single blind randomised controlled clinical trial comparing a new therapeutic intervention in addition to Treatment As Usual (TAU) with TAU for patients with schizophrenia at the Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit (SCGH MHU) who want to work.  The new therapeutic intervention is called the Supported Employment Linkage Intervention (SEL).The primary hypothesis tested is the addition of SEL to TAU will improve engagement, by patient choice, with a local employment agency called EDGE and procurement of a competitive job. EDGE has good fidelity to the Individual Placement and Support Approach to Supported Employment. We will also see if psychiatric symptoms, cognition, substance use disorder, hope, loneliness, self-esteem, quality of life and social inclusion will be improved with the addition of SEL to TAU significantly more than with TAU alone.Method: The outcomes measured will be change in: The Engagement with Edge Questionnaire (EEQ), Job Acquisition Questionnaire (JAQ), Trail Making Test A+B, Digit Span Test (Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale  Revised), Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS), Addiction Severity Index (ASI), Assessment of Quality of Life Instrument (AQoL-4D Basic), Rosenberg Self Esteem Scale, Adult Hope Scale, UCLA Loneliness Scale and the Activity and Participation Questionnaire (APQ-6). Measures will be collected at baseline by the research mental health nurse clinicians and 6 monthly for 2 years post recruitment by a blinded research officer unfamiliar with the site.

Expected Outcomes: We expect successful engagement with an employment agency called Edge, as measured by the Engagement with Edge Questionnaire (EEQ), to equal a 6 month block of registration with Edge  during the 2 year period post recruitment  and to be significantly better with SEL + TAU compared to TAU over 2 years post recruitment.  We expect yes to a competitive job, as measured by the Job Acquisition Questionnaire (JAQ), to be significantly greater with SEL + TAU compared to TAU at 4 varying time points over 2 years post recruitment.  Substance use disorder, quality of life, self-esteem, hope, loneliness and social inclusion are anticipated to be significantly improved with SEL + TAU compared to TAU as measured by the Addiction Severity Index (ASI), Assessment of Quality of Life Instrument (AQoL-Basic), Rosenberg Self Esteem Scale, Adult Hope Scale, UCLA Loneliness Scale and the Activity and Participation Questionnaire (APQ-6) respectively at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months post recruitment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Metropolitan Health Service - Mental health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gascoyne House Graylands campus Locked bag No 1 PO Claremont Western Australia 6910</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ann Solar</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental health Unit
Verdun Street Nedlands Western Australia 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63831000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ann.Solar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ann Solar</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Mental Health Unit
Verdun Street Nedlands Western Australia 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 63831000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ann.Solar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ann Solar</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner hospital mental Health Unit
Verdun Street Nedlands Western Australia 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6383 1000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ann.Solar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>