<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335899">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000773033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prescription Procedures for Cochlear Hybrid Devices in Hearing Loss.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prescription Procedures for Cochlear Hybrid Devices to  optimise the acoustic-to electric output requirements for adults who use a Hybrid device.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hearing loss</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Deafness</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Many people with severe to profound, high-frequency  hearing losses obtain limited benefit from hearing aids, but are not candidates for cochlear implants. Fitting an Electric Acoustic Stimulation (EAS) device, also known as a Hybrid device, may be a useful treatment option because these devices combine a hearing aid and a cochlear implant in the same ear. They allow low-frequency information to be delivered via the hearing aid part, and high-frequency information be delivered via the cochlear implant part.  As this technology becomes commercially available and the number of recipients increases, an understanding of how to best apply it is crucial.
Adults who use a Cochlear Hybrid System will be fitted with new hearing aids using standard clinical procedures.  These devices will be optimised according to the individual's needs. The performance of these optimised devices will be compared with proprietary device settings using a range of tests including: speech perception, music perception, localisation and functional performance in real life. The overall duration in which the hearing aids will be worn will be six months. The findings will be used as the basis to develop a prescription for devices that combine electric and acoustic stimulation (EAS).</interventions>
    <comparator>This study will use a repeated-measures, single-subject design. Each subject serves as his/her own control, thereby   accommodating the heterogeneity that characterizes hearing-impaired populations. Such designs are widely used in the study of cochlear implants.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relative acoustic-to-electric output requirements for adults who use a Hybrid device. 
Outcome assessments: Adults' performance with the optimised devices will be compared with their performance with the proprietary device settings using a range of tests including: speech perception, music perception and localisation testing. In addition, adults will be asked to complete questionnaires in regards to how well the devices perform in real life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These evaluations will be made at baseline and at 12 weeks after the fitting and optimisation of the hearing aids.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acoustic-to-electric frequency boundary requirements by adults who use a Hybrid device.
Outcome assessments: Adults' performance with three different frequency boundary programs in their Hybrid sound processor will be evaluated using a range of tests including: speech perception, music perception, localisation testing and functional performance in real life questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These evaluations will be made at baseline and at 4 and 8 weeks after randomisations of frequency boundary allocation programs.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Basis for deriving a theoretical prescription procedure for the fitting of devices that combine electric and acoustic stimulation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of study the acoustic-to-electric frequency boundary allocation and output levels findings will be analysed and used as the basis to develop a prescription for fitting devices that combine electric and acoustic stimulation (EAS).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Will be eighteen years of age or older at the time of evaluation.
 2. Will be users of a Cochlear Hybrid System with a minimum of 12 months experience prior to enrolment.
3. The audiometric criteria for residual hearing in the implanted ear will be within the range of normal to profound. 
4. A  willingness to wear all device conditions (New hearing aids and  Hybrid sound processor) on a daily basis for the duration of the study.
5. A willingness to participate in and to comply with all requirements of the protocol including a willingness to complete all tests and questionnaires.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Children under the age of 18 years of age.
2. People whose primary language is other than English (LOTEs).
3. Additional needs or disability that would prevent participation in evaluations.
4. Unrealistic expectations on the part of the participant, regarding the possible benefits and limitations of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2067</postcode>
    <postcode>3010</postcode>
    <postcode>1675</postcode>
    <postcode>2067</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The HEARing Cooperative Research Centre Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>550 Swanson Street 
Audiology, Hearing and Speech Sciences 
The University of Melbourne VICTORIA  3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The HEARing Cooperative Research Centre Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>550 Swanson Street 
Audiology, Hearing and Speech Sciences 
The University of Melbourne VICTORIA  3010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Acoustic Laboratories</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>126 Greville Street
Chatswood NSW 2067</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people with severe to profound, high-frequency sensorineural (permanent) hearing losses obtain minimal benefit from hearing aids, but do not meet the criteria for standard cochlear implantation.  An Electric Acoustic Stimulation (EAS) device, also known as a Hybrid device,  combines acoustic amplification in the low frequencies where hearing can be effectively aided, with electric stimulation in the high frequencies where hearing loss is profound, all within one implantable system. Fitting an Electric Acoustic Stimulation (EAS) device may be an effective treatment option for people with severe to profound high frequency hearing losses. As this technology becomes commercially available and the number of recipients increases, an understanding of how to best fit and combine the acoustic and electric stimulation to maximise outcomes for recipients is crucial.
Although a significant amount of EAS research has been conducted over the last 10 years, the main focus of reported work has been on the post-operative hearing preservation outcomes and perceptual benefits of this intervention. To date the approach to fitting these devices has been highly variable and no systematic attempts have been made to optimise the fitting for maximising outcomes for recipients.  
The main aims of the proposed study are: 1. To optimise EAS devices as implemented in the Cochlear Hybrid System, which consists of a Nucleus Hybrid L24 cochlear implant and a Hybrid sound processor. 2.To evaluate the effect of systematic variations of acoustic to electrical stimulation on speech perception, music perception, localisation and functional performance in real life. The findings will be used as the basis to develop a prescription for devices that combine electric and acoustic stimulation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Hearing Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00109)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>126 Greville Street
Chatswood NSW 2067</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Approval Number AHHREC2010-4</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paola Incerti</name>
      <address>Senior Research Audiologist
National Acoustic Laboratories 
126 Greville Street 
Chatswood NSW 2067.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9412 6963</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9411 8273</fax>
      <email>Paola.Incerti@nal.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paola Incerti</name>
      <address>Senior Research Audiologist
National Acoustic Laboratories 
126 Greville Street
Chatswood NSW 2067.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9412 6963</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9411 8273</fax>
      <email>Paola.Incerti@nal.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paola Incerti</name>
      <address>Senior Research Audiologist
National Acoustic Laboratories 
126 Greville Street 
Chatswood NSW 2067.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9412 6963</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9411 8273</fax>
      <email>Paola.Incerti@nal.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>