<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335219">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000385044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Deep Brain Stimulation for Cerebral Palsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized, placebo controlled, double blinded trial of pallidal Deep Brain Stimulation for dystonic or dyskinetic Cerebral Palsy to improve Quality of Life</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1114-0874</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DBS for CP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will have deep brain stimulator implanted in the globus pallidus internus, which is part of the basal ganglia network in the brain. The implantation of deep brain stimulators takes approximately 3 to 6 hours. Deep brain stimulators are similar to cardiac pacemakers and the battery is placed - like in pacemakers - under the collar bone. However the electrodes are not in the heart but end in the brain where they stimulate certain areas of the brain - in our study the pallidum or globus pallidus internus. This part of the brain is involved in involuntary movements. We believe that continuous high frequency stimulation of this part of the brain can block involuntary movements and improve dystonia. The treatment group will receive effective continuous stimulation through their implanted deep brain stimulators for three months; The standard setting of the stimulator are pulse width of 90µs, 130 Hz and the highest possible amplitude , that does not cause side effects. The sham group will receive ineffective stimulation through their implanted deep brain stimulators which will mean the stimulator is switched on with the same settings but amplitude of 0 Volt.</interventions>
    <comparator>All patients will have deep brain stimulator implanted in the globus pallidus internus, which is part of the basal ganglia network in the brain. The implantation of deep brain stimulators takes approximately 3 to 6 hours. Deep brain stimulators are similar to cardiac pacemakers and the battery is placed - like in pacemakers - under the collar bone. However the electrodes are not in the heart but end in the brain where they stimulate certain areas of the brain - in our study the pallidum or globus pallidus internus. This part of the brain is involved in involuntary movements. We believe that continuous high frequency stimulation of this part of the brain can block involuntary movements and improve dystonia. The treatment group will receive effective continuous stimulation through their implanted deep brain stimulators for three months; The standard setting of the stimulator are pulse width of 90µs, 130 Hz and the highest possible amplitude , that does not cause side effects. The sham group will receive ineffective stimulation through their implanted deep brain stimulators which will mean the stimulator is switched on with the same settings but amplitude of 0 Volt.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life will be assessed by the Quality of Life Instrument for People with Developmental Disabilities (Rosenbaum, P.L., et al., Quality of life and health-related quality of life of adolescents with cerebral palsy. Dev Med Child Neurol, 2007. 49(7): p. 516-21.) with the domains of Being, Belonging, and Becoming. This scale is validated in Cerebral Palsy (CP).  The health-related quality of life will be assessed with the Short Form General-Health-Survey (SF-36), which evaluates both physical and mental components of functioning (Ware, J.E., Jr. and C.D. Sherbourne, The MOS 36-item short-form health survey (SF-36). I. Conceptual framework and item selection. Med Care, 1992. 30(6): p. 473-83).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome parameter will be measured within 2 months before the intervention. Within 48 hours after implantation of the deep brain stimulator patients will be randomised and either allocated to sham or active treatment. Three months after the randomisation and therefore three months after having had continuous effective deep brain stimulation or sham stimulation the primary endpoint will be assed again. Than all deep brain stimulators will be activated and the third assessment of the primary endpoint will be 6 months after the initial randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Movement and disability will be assessed by the Burke-Fahn-Marsden-Dystonia Rating Scale (BFMDRS) (Burke, R.E., et al., Validity and reliability of a rating scale for the primary torsion dystonias. Neurology, 1985. 35(1): p. 73-7.), which comprises of a disability score ranging from 0 to 30 and motor score ranging from 0 to 120. Further more the motor function will be video taped according to the previous applied video protocol. 
The Gross Motor Function Classification System for children with Cerebral Palsy (GMFCS) [Palisano, R., et al., Development and reliability of a system to classify gross motor function in children with cerebral palsy. Dev Med Child Neurol, 1997. 39(4): p. 214-23.] will be applied as a standard classification tool for children with CP, which rates the severity of the disease in 5 levels with regard to their motor function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary outcome parameter will be measured within 2 months before the intervention. Within 48 hours after implantation of the deep brain stimulator patients will be randomised and either allocated to sham or active treatment. Three months after the randomisation and therefore three months after having had continuous effective deep brain stimulation or sham stimulation the secondary endpoint will be assed again. Than all deep brain stimulators will be activated and the third assessment of the secondary endpoint will be 6 months after the initial randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Dystonic or dyskinetic Cerebral Palsy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Dementia
Predominant Spasticity</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Martin Krause</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Medical School | Nepean 				
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 5, Spurrett Building | Nepean Hospital
Derby Street | Kingswood | NSW | 2747	
PO Box 63 | Penrith | NSW | 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cerebral Palsy (CP) is a neurodevelopmental disorder secondary to injury of the fetal or infant brain causing dystonia, choreoathetosis, and / or spasticity.  Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) improves motor function and quality of life in other forms of dystonia. There are case reports suggesting that DBS improves motor function in dystonic CP as well. This is a proposal to investigate the impact of DBS on motor function and quality of life in adolescents and adults with CP in a randomized, blinded, placebo-controlled design.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Martin Krause</name>
      <address>Sydney Medical School Nepean 				
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 5, Spurrett Building | Nepean Hospital
Derby Street | Kingswood | NSW | 2747	
PO Box 63 | Penrith | NSW | 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 47344280</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mkrause@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Martin Krause</name>
      <address>Sydney Medical School Nepean 				
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 5, Spurrett Building | Nepean Hospital
Derby Street | Kingswood | NSW | 2747	
PO Box 63 | Penrith | NSW | 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 47344280</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mkrause@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>