<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336874">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000470998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Streamlining follow up of intermediate risk chest pain presentations: Does pre-organised early stress testing improve compliance to guidelines and 30-day outcomes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients discharged from the emergency department with intermediate risk acute coronary syndrome, does pre-organised appointments for early stress testing improve compliance with current guidelines and 30 day outcomes compared with patients who were asked to organise their own appointments.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intermediate risk of non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Evaluating the rate of attendance for follow up exercise stress testing in patients who were given pre-organised appointment times.
Evaluating the representation rate with cardiac related chest pain, adverse cardiac events, coronary intervention procedures and mortality over 30 days following their discharge.</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical control group:  this group of patients are patients who have been discharged with the same inclusion criteria as the experimental group but were not given pre-organised appointment times.  Rather they were asked to make their own appointment or contact their general practitioner for a referral for exercise stress testing.  The control group have been selected from patients meeting the inclusion criteria between January 2010 to June 2010 from the same hospital (Armadale Health Services)</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether providing patients with pre-organised appointment times increases their compliance to return for exercise stress testing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up will occur at day 30 post discharge from the emergency department in order to evaluate their compliance with attending exercise stress testing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the 30 day mortality rate of patients discharged with a diagnosis of intermediate risk ACS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 30 post discharge from the emergency department</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the likelihood of major adverse cardiac events in patient who returned for EST compared to those who did not.
Major adverse cardiac events include ST-elevation myocardial infarcts, angioplasty/stent, Coronary Artery Bypass Grafting (CABG), stable and unstable angina.  
This outcome will be assessed by collecting data from health department databases and software and performing telephone interviews with patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 30 post discharge from the emergency department</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine what barriers prevent patients from attending follow up EST.
This outcome will be assessed with telephone interviews and questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 30 post discharge from the emergency department</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the patients' perceived risk of future cardiac events compared to their actual risk determined by the guidelines set out by the National Heart Foundation/Cardiac Society of Australia and New Zealand.
The patient will be asked to perform a questionnaire over the telephone that will address their perceived risk on an alphabetical scale.  (ie A) 1-2%, B) 3-4% etc)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 30 post discharge from the emergency department</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>&gt;18 yo and informed consent obtained, discharged from emergency department with intermediate risk acute coronary syndrome, suitable for exercise threadmill stress testing, able to follow up patient via telephone at 30 days.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, contraindications to stress testing, &lt;18 yo or &gt;75 yo, cognitively impaired, inability to consent, inability to follow up patient (overseas visitor or no telephone access)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof David Playford</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 10, Armadale Hospital Specialist Centre, 
3056 Albany Hwy, Armadale 
Western Australia 6112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nil</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nil</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with chest pain presenting to the emergency department are stratified according to likelihood that the pain is due to a heart attack. Intermediate risk chest pain may be cardiac in origin but is not due to a heart attack, and requires further follow up. According to current Australian guidelines, these patients should be referred for an exercise stress test within 72 hrs to further clarify their risk.

Currently only 30% of patients with intermediate risk chest pain present for their stress test within 72 hours even if stress testing services are readily available on site. We are investigating whether a fixed appointment time given to the patient before they leave the ED results in an improved follow up rate and improved 1 month outcome.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Area Health Services</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Fremantle Hospital 
GPO Box 480
Fremantle, WA 6959</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11/76</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>KEVIN CHUNG</name>
      <address>The University of Notre Dame
School of Medicine, Fremantle
PO Box 1225 
FREMANTLE
WESTERN AUSTRALIA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61(0)401137838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kevin.chung1@my.nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>KEVIN CHUNG</name>
      <address>The University of Notre Dame
School of Medicine, Fremantle
PO Box 1225 
FREMANTLE
WESTERN AUSTRALIA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61(0)401137838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kevin.chung1@my.nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>KEVIN CHUNG</name>
      <address>The University of Notre Dame
School of Medicine, Fremantle
PO Box 1225 
FREMANTLE
WESTERN AUSTRALIA 6959</address>
      <phone>0401137838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kevin.chung1@my.nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>