<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365265">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001246774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Food purchases of New Zealand adults under different conditions in the Virtual Supermarket (pilot)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of a tax increase, information about a tax and a combination of both on purchases in the Virtual Supermarket by New Zealand adults (pilot)
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1149-9729</utrn>
    <trialacronym>n/a</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be asked to conduct a typical weekly shop in the Virtual Supermarket, which is a three-dimensional software application that has been designed in the image of a real New Zealand supermarket. Upon registration, participants will be blindly randomised to one of the following:

- control
- a 20% tax on sugar sweetened beverages and no information about the tax
- a 20% tax on sugar sweetened beverages and information in the form of a newspaper article about the tax prior to the virtual shop
- a 20% tax on sugar-sweetened beverages and information in the form of in-store labels on taxed products
- a 20% tax on sugar-sweetened beverages and information in the form of both in-store labels on taxed products and a newspaper article about the tax prior to the virtual shop
- no tax on sugar sweetened beverages and information in the form of a newspaper article about the tax prior to the virtual shop
- no tax on sugar-sweetened beverages and information in the form of in-store labels on "taxed" products

Participants randomised to an information condition but no tax will be falsely informed that a tax has been put in place (e.g. taxed label on SSB but no price change)</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be exposed to typical supermarket prices for all goods and will receive no information about a tax</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in sugar-sweetened beverage purchases (in litres) between groups in the virtual shop (participants do not actually purchase the products)</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of virtual shopping task</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported response to sugar-sweetened beverage tax and information

The questionnaire used was designed specifically for this study but incorporates questions from previous studies on the determinants of purchasing decisions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-task questionnaire</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in purchases of other product categories in the Virtual Supermarket in the virtual shop

*Beverages (Alcoholic beverages, 100% fruit juices, Milk, Other non-SSBs)
*Baby care
*Bread, bakery, cereal, and cereal products
*Convenience foods, deli and chilled foods
*Dairy and eggs (not milk)
*Edible oils and oil emulsions
*Fruit and vegetables
*Meat, fish and seafood
*Snack foods </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of virtual shopping task</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult (over 18 years)
Key responsible person in the household for grocery shopping
Speaks and reads English
Has access to a computer and internet
Has an email address</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if another member of the household is taking part in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once the participant has been deemed eligible to take part in the trial, the researchers will assign them a unique identifier which they will enter when completing the online virtual shopping task.

The unique identifier contains information about the condition to which the participant has been randomised so that the participant views the Virtual Supermarket task as appropriate to their randomisation condition.

The unique identifier will be generates using simple randomisation by a computer function applied to the case file upon registration by the participant. The condition that the participant is randomised to will not be concealed from the researcher.

</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computer function applied to case file upon registration by participant</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants will be debriefed at the end of the study period as to what condition they were randomised to, and what the other conditions in the study were. This will be done via email at the end of the data collection (i.e. when all participants have completed the task).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This will be a pilot study aiming to explore how an SSB tax, and information about an SSB tax affect purchases. As this is not a full RCT, no formal power calculation is required. However, previous experience with the Virtual Supermarket experiments showed that a sample of around n = 20 participants per condition is sufficient to obtain significant results. Therefore, the study will aim to recruit at least n = 150 participants.

Demographic data and user feedback will be summarised using descriptive statistics. Continuous variables will be reported as numbers of observed and missing values, mean, standard deviation, median, minimum and maximum. Categorical variables will be reported as frequencies and percentages.

Differences between groups will be determined using ANOVA and associated tests where the variables can be approximated to resemble a normal distribution. Non-parametric tests will be used where the underlying distributions do not resemble a normal distribution.

As this is a pilot study, no adjustments will be made to control for multiple comparisons. The results obtained could be used to inform sample size estimates for future large-scale trials in this area.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>All</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>12 Grafton Road
Grafton
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>12 Grafton Road
Grafton
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>n/a</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>n/a</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot randomised controlled study aims to examine the effects of a sugar-sweetened beverage (SSB) tax or SSB tax information or a combination of both on purchases and on consumer perceptions using the recently developed New Zealand Virtual Supermarket. The New Zealand Virtual Supermarket is a three-dimensional software application that has been designed in the image of a real New Zealand supermarket. 

SSB taxes have been proposed as a method to reduce soft drink consumption (and subsequently reduce calorie intake) and could therefore help to tackle the growing obesity epidemic. Evidence on the effectiveness of soft drink taxes is however very limited and has largely been restricted to modelling studies which are not able to explore how information and knowledge about such a tax (referred to as price salience in the economic literature) would mediate changes in consumption. Moreover, such studies give limited insight in cross-price elasticity and substitution effects (e.g., it has been suggested that increased SSB taxes might result in an increased alcohol intake). Before taxes are implemented on a large scale, it is important to gain more insight into these effects and examine the best design of the tax for public health outcomes. Therefore this study aims to:

1.	To examine the differences in SSB purchases between groups of participants exposed to different SSB tax and information scenarios within the Virtual Supermarket.
2.	To obtain participant feedback on perceptions of the SSB tax and their intended response to the tax.

Participants (recruited from the general adult NZ population) will be randomized to one of seven conditions (pricing and/or information conditions or control) and will be asked to conduct a weekly household shop in the Virtual Supermarket. 

The Virtual Supermarket is a 3-dimensional software application designed in the image of a real supermarket. It models a representative product selection of food items that can normally be found in a NZ supermarket, including a wide range of soft drinks. Participants will be provided with a link to this software and can complete this study from their home computer or any computer with internet access.

This pilot trial will be designed to provide an optimal level of information on the potential effectiveness of different tax and information combinations. We anticipate that this trial will inform the design of a larger trial by identifying the interventions with the largest potential for public health. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Integrity Unit
Level 10, Building 620
49 Symonds Street
Auckland 1142</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>010452</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wilma Waterlander</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142

</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 ext. 84743</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>w.waterlander@nihi.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wilma Waterlander</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 ext. 84743</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>w.waterlander@nihi.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wilma Waterlander</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 ext. 84743</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>w.waterlander@nihi.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wilma Waterlander</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 ext. 84743</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>w.waterlander@nihi.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>