<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370249">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000343404p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can early intervention with CO2 laser therapy promote scar maturation following a burn injury?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can early intervention with CO2 laser therapy promote scar maturation following a burn injury?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-2398 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Burn injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Scar</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 10,600nm fractional carbon dioxide laser supplied by Lumenis Ltd is the device to be used in this study. This laser has FDA approval for over 100 applications including the management of scars. It has the ability to deliver precise high energy in short-pulses to thickened scars, and has a good record for safety and outcomes. Participants will receive 3 laser treatments 4- 6 weeks apart. The timing of procedures is dependent on patient availability and availability of surgical capacity (ie space on theatre list).  Each treatment session lasts between 5 and 15 minutes, depending on the size treated. The patient will receive either a general or local anesthetic prior to the procedure. The choice of anesthetic is at the patient's discretion. The treatments are delivered in a laser safe environment - either in the operating theatre or the laser treatment room on the burns unit. The area to be treated is determined by the surgeon and the patient before the procedure. The laser treatment is delivered by the burn surgeon who is trained in the use of laser therapies and holds a current laser licence. Outcome measures will be conducted before laser treatment, after the third (last) treatment of laser and 3 months after the third laser treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients with 2 or more non-contiguous discrete burn areas will be recruited into this study. Each patient will act as their own control. Scar sites will be numbered and each site will be allocated to either LASER (L) or CONTROL (C) treatment regimes. A minimum of two sites are required in each patient. For patients with more than two eligible sites, the most closely matched pair in appearance (based on Vancouver Scar Scale) will be selected. These two scars will then be randomly allocated as the LASER (L) or CONTROL (C) scar. The participant will be unaware of the treated site</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effect of CO2 laser treatment on the clinical outcome of burn scars versus standard scar therapy. This will be assess using scar assessment measures: Vancouver Scar Scale( VSS) and Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale (POSAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post 3rd laser treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time in pressure garments assessed by medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post 3rd laser treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for reconstructive surgery assessed by medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post 3rd laser treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults &gt; 18 years of age
Two or more non-contiguous discrete burn areas
Each burn &gt; 1% TBSA
Scars which would ordinarily be managed by pressure garments
All patients to be at least 3 months from burn injury
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant or lactating females, 
Facial scars
Keloid scars
Inability to give informed consent
Systemic glucocorticoid use
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each patient will act as their own control. Scar sites will be numbered and each site will be allocated to either LASER (L) or CONTROL (C) treatment regimes. A minimum of two sites are required in each patient. For patients with more than two eligible sites, the most closely matched pair in appearance (based on Vancouver Scar Scale) will be selected. These two scars will then be randomly allocated as the LASER (L) or CONTROL (C) scar. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using coin-tossing </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive, univariate statistics will be used to describe the general characteristics of the sample. Each patient serves as their own control, and no assumptions will be made regarding the distribution of the data. Hence, differences between Control and Intervention areas will be examined using the Wilcoxon Signed Rank test, and a p value &lt; 0.05 will be considered to indicate statistical significance. All statistical analysis will be conducted using the statistical package for social sciences (SPSS) program (version 17.0) and STATA. There is no information in the literature on which to base an accurate or meaningful sample size calculation. We are proposing the conventional sample size of 20 patients for a pilot study. This will provide sufficient information to enable an accurate sample size correction for use in a larger trial should a benefit be observed. If no benefit is seen to occur, then we can calculate the probability of having missed a potential benefit in our trial. This data will therefore inform the decision as to whether a future larger trial is warranted, or whether it would be a futile endeavour</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>3/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Suzanne Rea</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>State Adult Burns Unit
Level 4
Fiona Stanley Hospital
102-118 Murdoch Drive
Murdoch, Perth, WA
6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>WA Health Department SHRAC Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>189 Royal St, East Perth WA 6004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fiona Wood Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>State Adult Burns Unit
Level 4,
Fiona Stanley Hospital,
102-118 Murdoch Drive
Murdoch, WA, 
6150</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In high income countries, improvements in first aid and acute specialised care have resulted in reduced mortality from major burn injuries (from approximately 25% to less than 9%). Although specialised care has significantly improved outcomes for these patients, the near universal complication of burn-related scarring persists as a constant reminder of limitations of care. For burn survivors, the development of painful, restrictive and disfiguring scarring, known as hypertrophic scarring (HS), has an incidence ranging from 30-70% in reviewed epidemiological data. The treatment of scarring has, thus far, been unable to keep pace with the advancements in resuscitation and other acute therapies. The consequences of scar formation are many and varied, including joint contractures and stiffness, chronic pain, itching, and anhydrosis. Additionally, the emotional repercussions can be significant, with many patients reporting stigmatization and discrimination due to their burn scars.  As the mortality of acute burn injury continues to diminish, the burden of scarring may continue to rise. Current treatment options for hypertrophic scarring are not yet sufficient to significantly reduce its associated morbidity. Burn clinicians and researchers are focused on understanding scarring in more depth and discovering potential ways to improve patient outcomes. Within this field of innovation, laser resurfacing techniques are gaining greater interest and are currently being utilised in several centres worldwide for the treatment of HS. 

The aim of this study is to investigate if the early use of laser treatment helps minimise scar, decreases the time required in pressure garments, improves range of motion and thus results in fewer episodes of expensive reconstructive surgery.

A 10,600nm fractional carbon dioxide laser supplied by Lumenis Ltd is the device to be used in this study. This laser has FDA approval for over 100 applications including the management of scars. It has the ability to deliver precise high energy in short-pulses to thickened scars, and has a good record for safety and outcomes. The Burns Service of WA has been using this laser for over 18 months for the management of scars, and the health professionals involved have received the appropriate safety training.

Participants will receive 3 laser treatments 4-6 weeks apart. Outcome measures will be conducted before laser treatment, after the last treatment of laser and 3 months post laser treatment.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, Southern Research Facility (Perkins Building) Fiona Stanley Hospital,11 Robin Warren Drive, MURDOCH WA 6150, Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Suzanne Rea</name>
      <address>State Adult Burns Unit
Level 4
Fiona Stanley Hospital
102 -118 Murdoch Drive
Murdoch, Perth, WA
6150</address>
      <phone>+61 413 827 186</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.rea@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Suzanne Rea</name>
      <address>State Adult Burns Unit
Level 4
Fiona Stanley Hospital
102 -118 Murdoch Drive
Murdoch, Perth, WA
6150</address>
      <phone>+61 413 827 186</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.rea@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Suzanne Rea</name>
      <address>State Adult Burns Unit
Level 4
Fiona Stanley Hospital
102 - 118 Murdoch Drive
Murdoch, Perth, WA
6150</address>
      <phone>+61 413 827 186</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.rea@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah McGarry</name>
      <address>State Adult Burns Unit
Level 4
Fiona Stanley Hospital
102 -118 Murdoch Drive
Murdoch, Perth, WA
6150</address>
      <phone>+61 412868508</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.mcgarry@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>