<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81965">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/04/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000218493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to test an oral combination of letrozole and everolimus for patients with advanced lung cancer who have progressed on first line chemotherapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase II Study Evaluating Efficacy and Safety of Everolimus with Letrozole for Management of Advanced (unresectable or metastatic) Non Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) after Failure of Platinum-Based Treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non Small Cell lung cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with metastatic non small cell lung cancer who have previously failed on platinum based chemotherapy will be treated on a daily oral combination of letrozole 2.5 mg and everolimus 10mg. The patients will be assessed on a regular basis with CT-PET scan. The first assessment will be after 4 weeks. Subsequent scans will be at 8 weeks interval. Patients will continue the treatment till they are having benefit.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once at week 4 after starting treatment by RECIST (Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors) criteria.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Progression free survival- time from signing consent to an event (death from any cause or disease progression).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored 4 weekly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Overall survival defined as time between signing consent to death from any cause. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored 4 weekly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Side effects &amp; quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored on 4 weekly basis till 4 weeks after stopping treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Correlation of outcomes with baseline genomic profile. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at week 4 after starting treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Histologically or cytologically proven diagnosis of non-small cell lung cancer of either gender. 2. Age &gt; 18 years for males. Females should be post-menopausal, which is defined as: Prior oopherectomy, or  12 month-history of amenorrhoea, or  FSH (Follicle Stimulating Hormone) and LH (Luteinizing Hormone) in post-menopausal range.  There is no upper age limit. 3. performance status = 2.4. Adequate organ function Hematological- Hb&gt; 90 g/L, Absolute Neutrophil Count = 1.5 x 109/L, platelets = 100 x 109/L. Liver functions- bilirubin = 2 x upper limit normal (ULN), Aspartate Aminotransferase /Alanine Aminotransferase/ Alkaline Phosphatase = 2.5 x ULN or = 5 x ULN in presence of liver metastases, S. albumin = 30 g/L. Renal function- Creatinine = 2 ULN, Creatinine clearance &gt; 30 mL/min. 6. Patients should stop any hormonal medication as hormone replacement therapy or progesterone at least one month prior to enrolment. 7. Patients should have at least one measurable lesion by RECIST criteria.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Untreated brain metastases. 2. Patients on strong inhibitor or inducer of isoenzyme CYP3A. 3. Serious co-morbidities such as severe cardiac failure or severe pulmonary compromise or severe and active infections. 4. Uncontrolled diabetes.5.Patients with grade 3 hypercholesterolemia / hypertriglyceridemia or = grade 2 hypercholesterolemia / hypertriglyceridemia with history of coronary artery disease (despite lipid lowering treatment if given)6. Previous treatment with mTOR inhibitors and/or known hypersensitivity to mTOR inhibitors.7. A known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus or previous seropositivity for the virus.8. Leptomeningeal or uncontrolled brain metastases, including patients who continue to require glucocorticoids or intrathecal chemotherapy for brain or leptomeningeal metastases (documented by lumbar puncture).9. Patients will be excluded if they are on raloxifene or tamoxifen. 10. Patients who have an impairment of gastrointestinal function or who havegastrointestinal disease that may significantly alter the absorption of RAD001 (e.g., ulcerative disease, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, malabsorption syndrome).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dept of Medical Oncology, Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recent work has reflected importance of estrogen in causation of lung cancer. This is especially true for female population and non smokers. Present trial is designed to test the hypothesis that decreasing estrogen along with inhibiting nutrient pathway in cancer cells could lead to disease control. There is preliminary data to suggest that the combination might be useful for other patients as well. The other highlight of the study is the oral treatment in contrast to other treatments which are injectable chemotherapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>060717</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nimit Singhal</name>
      <address>Department of Medical Oncology
Level 7 East Wing
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82224398</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82224358</fax>
      <email>nsinghal@mail.rah.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nimit Singhal</name>
      <address>Department of Medical Oncology
Level 7 East Wing
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82224398</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82224358</fax>
      <email>nsinghal@mail.rah.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>