<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365552">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000038695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of robot-assisted therapy on behavioural and psychological symptoms in community-living older adults with dementia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of robot-assisted therapy using therapeutic robot Paro on behavioural and psychological symptoms in community-living older adults with moderate to severe dementia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects assigned to the intervention group will be invited to participate in the robot-assisted intervention once a week over an 8 week period (max: 30 minutes per session) provided by a trained research assistant/occupational therapist who is familiar with the Paro user manual. The Paro intervention will generally involve six stages/themes (Introduction of Paro, Baby-sitting Paro, Grooming Paro, Feeding Paro, Making over Paro, and Wardrobe Paro), but subjects are also free to interact with Paro whenever they wish.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a single group pre-post intervention study. No control group will be provided.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of the Chinese version of Neuropsychiatric Inventory (CNPI)  apathy score after the intervention when compared with the baseline level (will be assessed with the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI)) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of other neuropsychiatric symptoms (will be assessed with the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of cognitive function (will be assessed using the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of agitation behavior (will be assessed with the Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory (CMAI))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of depression (will be assessed with the Corrnell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of moods (will be assessed with the simplified face scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social interaction and communication (subjects emotion expression towards Paro (Responses) during intervention sessions will be charted on every-one-minute basis with an observation table by reviewing videotaped clips after each intervention session)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intervention sessions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of caregiver burden (will be assessed with the Zarit burden interview (ZBI))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (8 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Community-living older adults aged 60 years and above will be screened using the Mini-Mental State Examination (CMMSE). Those who score between 5 and 15 with a diagnosis of dementia according to the criteria based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-IV) will be screened for eligibility to the study. Severity of dementia will be determined using Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR). Subjects with CDR greater than or equal to 2 will be further assessed for the presence and severity of behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia (BPSD) using Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI). To be clinically significant, those who exhibit any BPSD (have at least one documented behaviours occur at least once per week at a moderate severity level as defined on the NPI) will be invited to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects will be excluded if they have medical conditions severe enough to affect the patients ability to complete the treatment course and/or follow-up.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ruby Yu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine and Therapeutics, 10/F., Clinical Sciences Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, New Territories, Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health and Medical Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research Office
Food and Health Bureau
9/F., Rumsey Street Multi-storey Carpark Building
2 Rumsey Street, Sheung Wan, Hong Kong</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>With the substantial increase of dementia in older adults, robot-assisted intervention using Paro would be a potential alternative intervention for older people with dementia in reducing BPSD, improving moods as well as encouraging social interaction and communication, therefore improving patients quality of life and reducing caregivers, nursing / healthcare worker loads. The information obtained will promote the awareness to health professionals that robot-assisted therapy using Paro is a useful behavior intervention in older people with dementia and could be incorporated as part of BPSD management programs amongst the elderly in both community care and hospital settings in Hong Kong.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruby Yu</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine and Therapeutics, 10/F., Clinical Sciences Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, New Territories, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+852 26322190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rubyyu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruby Yu</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine and Therapeutics, 10/F., Clinical Sciences Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, New Territories, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+852 26322190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rubyyu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruby Yu</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine and Therapeutics, 10/F., Clinical Sciences Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, New Territories, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+852 26322190</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rubyyu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>