<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371483">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001569493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating the feasibility of implementing a pre-operative VLCD weight loss program into the pre-operative model of care for general elective surgery patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating the feasibility of implementing a pre-operative VLCD weight loss program into the pre-operative model of care for general elective surgery patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1185-8940</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is an 8 week Very Low Calorie Diet weight loss program that utlises Optifast meal replacement shakes to 700-800calories/ day intake. This will be achieved through the daily oral consumption of 3-4 Optifast products (shakes) with an additional 2 cups (non-starch) salad, at least 2 litres of calorie free fluids, and 1 teaspoon of oil.
Processes established to measure fidelity / adherence to treatment protocols will be implemented which may include but not limited to urinary ketones. Urinary ketones will be collected by the clinic nurse.</interventions>
    <comparator>As part of standard care, a generic weight loss education pack will be provided to participants randomised to the control group at week 0 by the clinic nurse. The weight loss  information pack includes tips on healthy eating and contact details of where to access Dietitian/ weight loss advice in the community. The pack has been previously developed by Dietitians in the Department and is used in standard practice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluating the feasibility of implementing a pre-operative VLCD weight program in general elective surgery patients at The Prince Charles Hospital.
Feasibility will be determined by evaluating acceptability, demand, practicality and integration.
Areas of Focus
1.	Changes in Health Related Quality of Life scores of participants (Acceptability) 
2.	Recruitment rate of participants (n=50) in the projected time frame (at least 6 participants/ month) (Demand)
3.	Participant attendance rates to clinic appointments (Demand)
4.	Changes in weight and body composition from week 0 to week 8 in participants receiving the intervention, compared to the control group will be measured using bioelectrical impedance (Practicality)
5.	Participant adherence to VLCD program by participants. Urinary ketones will be used as a fidelity measure.(Practicality)
6.	Duration (days) on theatre list, and number of patients with delayed surgeries due to obesity (Practicality). 
7.	Determine Quality Adjusted Life Years (QALYs) using cost utility analysis (Practicality)
8.	Determine perceived fit and sustainability of the program by Key stakeholders. Focus groups with key stakeholders will be undertaken (Integration)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point, post randomisation 1: 8 weeks
Time point 2, post randomisation: 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcome: 'Unfavourable surgical outcomes'
LOS &gt;20% than expected for DRG
Hospital Readmission &lt;30days
Surgical site infection
Delayed wound healing 
Hospital Acquired Pressure Injury Stage 1-4
Unplanned return to theatre
Venous thromboembolism (VTE)
Myocardial Infarction
Conversions from laparoscopic  to open surgery
Unplanned Intensive Care admission
Intraoperative time
Requirement for rehabilitation 

Data to determine outcomes witll be obtained from participants relevant medical records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Elective general surgical patients at The Prince Charles Hospital 
BMI &gt;30kgm2
&gt;18 years old
eGFR &gt;60ml/min/1.73m2
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant, preparing undergoing IVF
Cirrhosis, liver failure, portal hypertension
Acute cardiovascular disease
Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus
Use lithium
long-term use of corticosteroids (&gt; 2 weeks duration)
People with an intellectual or mental impairment
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The use of sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes will ensure allocation concealment as participants and investigators enrolling participants will not foresee assignment.</concealment>
    <sequence>The primary research clinician will randomly allocate eligible consented patients using sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes that contained allocation into the intervention or the control arm. The sequentially numbered envelopes will be produced using computer software and sealed by an independent statistician prior to the activation of the trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size estimation 
The increased risk of surgical complications in obese patients varies throughout the literature with reports of complications between 4-54%. It is hypothesised that the intervention will reduce unfavourable surgical outcomes from 15% to 5%. The sample sizes  required to detect a significant difference between the two groups (alpha 0.05) with 80% power are n=141 in each arm (total n=282). The command power two proportions p1 p2, test (chi2) were used to estimate sample size, where p1 and p2 refer to the expected proportions of patients that experience an unfavourable outcome in the control and intervention groups respectively.Due to the small sample size (n=50) this pilot study will not have the power to determine significance when evaluating surgical outcomes. A successful feasibility study will provide the opportunity for a larger study; stage 2, which will focus on surgical outcomes as a primary outcome.

Statistical methods
Descriptive statistics will be presented for all variables. Univariable associations between the intervention (VLCD) and the main binary outcome (i.e. adverse outcome) will be analysed using Chi square analyses. Associations between other categorical variables of interest and the outcome will be analysed using Chi square analyses and associations between continuous variables and the outcome will be analysed using Students t-tests or non-parametric methods as indicated by the distributions of variables of interest. Logistic regression analyses may be performed as indicated

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>14/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>14/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Surgery and Department of Nutrition and Dietetics, The Prince Charles Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rode Rd 
Chermside QLD 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Prince Charles Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rode Rd 
Chermside QLD 4032</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study will investigate the feasibility of implementing a multidisciplinary pre-operative very low calorie (VLCD) weight loss program in adult obese patients awaiting general elective surgery.
 This study will initially enrol a pilot sample of 50 patients who have a Body mass Index (BMI) equal to or over 30kg/m2 who attend the Pre-admission clinic for elective general surgery at The Prince Charles Hospital. Participants will be randomised into a control group or an intervention group. Participants in the intervention group will follow an 8 week very low calorie diet that incorporates Optifast meal replacement shakes. Participants randomised to the control group will receive standard care that includes a generic weight loss information pack provided by the clinic nurse. 

Measures to assess health related quality of life, body composition and adherence to the program will be collected. Unfavourable surgical outcomes will be measured until 30 days post elective surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital
Building 14
Rode Road, Chermside
QLD 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QPCH/178</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Ethics Unit, The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Lucia, Brisbane 
Queensland 4072
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Greta Hollis</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31394640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Greta.Hollis@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Greta Hollis</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31394640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Greta.Hollis@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Greta Hollis</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31394640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Greta.Hollis@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Greta Hollis </name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>