<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363494">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000170729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Open Label Extension Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability
and Cognitive Effects of VEL015 (Sodium Selenate) in Patients
with Alzheimers Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Open Label Extension Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability
and Cognitive Effects of VEL015 (Sodium Selenate) in Patients
with Alzheimers Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Velacor002-E1</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Sodium selenate (VEL015) 10mg oral capsules three time daily for 24 months</interventions>
    <comparator>This is an open label extension study and will not utilise a comparator or control treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of the study is to assess the longer-term safety and tolerability of a
supranutritional dose of sodium selenate (VEL015) in subjects with probable Alzheimers
Disease (AD). Safety will be monitored by haematology, biochemistry, recording of body weight, the
assessment of adverse events and documentation of concomitant medications. Adverse events may include alopecia, fatigue, nail disorders (fingernails and toenails lifting and falling off), muscle spasms and cramps, decreased appetite, lethargy and fatigue, headache, vomiting, retching and diarrhoea.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments at baseline (week 0), weeks 6, 12 and 24 and months 12, 18 and 24.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objective of the study are to assess the effect of VEL015 on cognitive
performance as measured by ADAS-Cog, MMSE, CogState test battery and components
of the NTB (COWAT and CFT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments at baseline (week 0), weeks 6, 12 and 24 and months 12, 18 and 24.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the magnitude of the treatment (VEL015) effect on cognitive performance (ADAS-Cog, MMSE, CogState test battery) in specific patient subgroups (exploratory; subjects treated/not treated in Velacor 002 study and subjects with MMSE greater than or equal to 20, and less than 20).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments at baseline (week 0), weeks 6, 12 and 24 and months 12, 18 and 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the association between biomarkers and measures of cognitive performance (exploratory). The biomarkers will include Alzheimer's disease biomarkers in the cerebrospinal fluid (A-beta 1-42, total Tau and phospho-Tau), atrophy of brain structures detected via MRI and areas of brain hypo- or hyper-metabolism detected via FDG-PET as part of the Velacor 002 study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments at baseline (week 0), weeks 6, 12 and 24 and months 12, 18 and 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Subject must have been randomised, treated and completed Visit 6 and/or Visit 7
of Protocol Velacor 002 (ACTRN12611001200976).
2. The Baseline (Month 0) visit must be conducted no more than 2 months after the
last scheduled visit (Visit 6 or Visit 7) for Protocol Velacor 002.
3. Females must be of non-child-bearing potential. Male subjects with female
partners of child-bearing potential should use effective contraception for the
duration of the Study and continue it for 12 weeks after cessation of IMP
administration. Women of non-childbearing potential must be either surgically
sterile (hysterectomy and/or oophorectomy) or postmenopausal at least 1 year and
must have a negative urine pregnancy test result at or within 28 days prior to the
Baseline Visit (Visit 1) .
4. Subject must be living in the community and have at least 5 contact hours per
week with a responsible carer. The carer should be capable of ensuring the
subject's compliance with the medication, be prepared to attend with the subject
for assessment and be willing to participate in completing the various assessments
throughout the period of the subjects involvement in the Study
5. Written informed consent must be obtained from the subject or legally authorised
representative (as required by local laws and regulations), and the participants
carer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Subject who has experienced persistent or unresolved side effects thought to be
possibly/probably/very likely/certainly related to Study Drug in the Velacor 002 study
and where the event is classified as either greater than or equal to Grade 3 severity or as a Serious
Adverse Event, or where the event required permanent cessation of Study Drug .
2. Subject has participated in a clinical investigation of a medication (with exception of
Velacor 002 study) or device within the 3 months prior to the Baseline Visit (Visit 1).
3. Subject who is unlikely to comply with trial visit schedule or with trial medication.
4. Subject has a known sensitivity to selenium or sodium selenate or any medicine or
vitamin containing sodium selenate or similar agents.
5. Subject has a primary, secondary or pseudodementia other than probable
Alzheimer's Disease, or has current evidence or history of neurological, psychiatric
and any other illness that could contribute to non-Alzheimer's dementia.
6. Subject has a significant medical disease, with the exception of Alzheimers Disease
that:
* is not adequately controlled by therapy; and/or
* in the opinion of the investigator may interfere with the patients ability to complete
the study or might impact on the patients cognitive performance.
7. Subject has significant impairment of any of the following for the age of the subject,
which may compromise safety of the subject/validity of the data:
* Renal function (i.e. estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &lt; 30)
* Hepatic function (i.e. abnormal liver function tests greater than or equal to 2 x upper limit of normal)
* Haematological function.
8. Subject is currently taking any of the following:
* Dietary supplement containing &gt; 26 micrograms selenium
* Carbamazepine, digoxin, phenobarbitone, phenytoin, warfarin or any other
medication that has a narrow margin between effective dose and toxic dose or
between effective dose and ineffective dose, where the subject would be at risk if
the levels were elevated or fell due to interaction with VEL015.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is an open label extension study to the Velacor 002 study. Patients must have previously participated in the Velacor 002 study to be eligible for this study. All patients enrolled will receive treatment with 10mg sodium selenate (VEL015) three times daily</concealment>
    <sequence>Study is not randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Patients recruited to this extension protocol are self-selecting (including only patients
who satisfactorily complete the main study) and therefore the non-randomised,
uncontrolled nature of the investigation and the potential biasing influences contributing
to any statistical analysis are recognised.
All patients will primarily be included and analysed as a single treated group (VEL015 10
mg tds) according to the treatment received in the extension and not in the main study.
All analyses will involve statistical hypothesis testing or modelling. Emphasis will be
placed on point estimates and 95% confidence intervals of the treatment effect rather
than p values. All analyses are considered exploratory and any conclusions will be
viewed cautiously. However, the study will contribute to knowledge of the disease
modifying potential and safety profile of the compound.
No interim analyses will be performed and the analyses performed at the end of the
study reporting p values will use a 5% (0.05) (two-sided) significance level. No
adjustment for multiple testing will be made.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Caulfield Hospital - Caulfield</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Velacor Therapeutics Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 88 Collins Street
Melbourne, 3000
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Velacor Therapeutics Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 88 Collins Street
Melbourne, 3000
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Open Label Extension Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability
and Cognitive Effects of VEL015 (Sodium Selenate) in Patients
with Alzheimers Disease</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Terence O'Brien</name>
      <address>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville, Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7722</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 8628</fax>
      <email>obrientj@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Darren Germaine</name>
      <address>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville, Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7879</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Darren.Germaine@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Darren Germaine</name>
      <address>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville, Vic 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7879</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Darren.Germaine@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>grant morley</name>
      <address>2 Dalgety Drive
Ascot Vale 3032
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 0407502574</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>velacor@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>