<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83561">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000796280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pain Ease spray vs. Angel cream for drip insertion in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of a vapocoolant spray (Pain Ease) with Amethocaine Gel (AnGel) to reduce the pain associated with intravenous(IV) cannulation in children.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Reduction of pain associated with IV cannulation in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this trial we would be applying a vapocoolant spray (PainEase) on the dorsum of the hands or cubital fossa of the children who would then undergo intravenous cannulation
The maximum number of times that this will be applied is four times and the least number of application would be once.The number of application of the product will be guided be successful intravenous cannulation and as stated the maximum number of application will be limited to four.
The mode of administration is that the prduct will be sprayed onto the skin of the dorsum of hand or the antecubital fossa(Topical).
The dosage will be that the spray will be applied for maximum of 10 seconds at the selected site during one attempt of intravenous cannulation.
The total duration of application at one site is 10 seconds and if cannulation is unsuccessful the next chosen site will be sprayed for maximum of 10 seconds.Overall the maximum total duration at four sites (if needed) will be 40 seconds.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator treatment is Angel cream(4% amethocaine gel).
This product will be applied to four sites(both dorsum of hands and both antecubital fossa) and the site will be covered with transparent Opsite dressing for 45 minutes.
Thus this product will be applied once but to four different sites.
The mode of administration is topical at the four sites previously mentioned.
The dosage would be roughly the size of two dollar Australian coin at one site.
The total duration would be 45 minutes after which the opsite dressing will be removed and the product will be wiped off from the skin prior to cannulation attempt</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aim is to primarily evaluate the effectiveness of PainEase compared to AnGel in reducing the pain associated with IV cannulation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain score 1 min after successful IV cannulation(Child,doctor,nurse and parent).The child's face will be video recorded and two independent doctors will be assigning pain score using the same scale.These doctors will be unaware of the product applied to the child.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the effect of use of AnGel or PainEase on cannulation success rate.
This outcome will be assessed based on the number of attempts needed for achieving suucessful intravenous cannulation when using either products which will be recorded on the study data collection sheet.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of IV cannulation attempts and time required to acheive successful IV cannulation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difficulty in identifying vein after application of either product.
This will be assesed by the treating doctor using a 5 point scale (extremely easy to extremely difficult)</outcome>
      <timepoint>This assessment will be made just prior to cannulation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events secondary to application of either product.
This will be recorded by the treating doctor on the study data collection sheet and reviewed by local adverse event monitoring committee.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assesed immidiately after application of product, before the child is discharged and follow up phone call 2 days after discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children between 6 and 18 yrs of age, presenting to the pediatric emergency department(PED) and requiring IV cannulation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients requiring urgent vascular access 
Patients with impaired consciousness, a history of psychiatric illness or with developmental delay
Use of opioid analgesics or sedating agents within 4 hours of enrollment
Patients with pain score of greater than 6 (Pain Scale 0-10), i.e. requiring urgent analgesia 
In patients with Diabetes Mellitus or patients with Cold hypersensitivity as Pain Ease is specifically contraindicated in these groups.
Sensitivity or previous adverse reactions to halogenated hydrocarbons or amethocaine
Non English speaking families 
Those unable to understand the study protocol or the Visual Analog scale</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All children aged 6-18 years needing IV cannulation will be approached to take part in the study.Randomisation will be done using a computer generated random number table.Allocation will be done by sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated random number table</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The child's face will be video recorded during IV cannulation.This video will be reviewed by two independent person who will each provide a pain score.These pain score will be compared to the scores given by the child, parent,nurse and doctor.This will help improve the validity of the pain score.
Safety/efficacy
Prospective</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>280</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Benjamin D'Souza</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Children youth and women's health service
72 King William Road
Adelaide
SA-5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Benjamin D'Souza</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Children youth and women's health service
72 King William Road
Adelaide
SA-5006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Women's and Childrens Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>72 King William Road
Adelaide
SA-5006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to compare the efficacy of PainEase and Angel for reducing pain associated with intravenous cannulation in children.
The study hypothesis is that application of PainEase will reduce pain associated with drip insertion.We would be comparing PainEase with the current standard treatment of use of Angel for reducing pain associated with drip insertion.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee(HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Children youth and women's health service
72 King William Road
Adelaide
SA-5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2611</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Benjamin D'Souza</name>
      <address>72 King William Road
Adelaide
SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Benjamin.D'Souza@cywhs.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Benjamin D'Souza</name>
      <address>72 King William Road
Adelaide
SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Benjamin.D'Souza@cywhs.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Benjamin D'Souza</name>
      <address>72 King William Road
Adelaide
SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Benjamin.D'Souza@cywhs.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>