<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369465">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000977471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A clinical trial in children presenting to hospital with an asthma attack, to compare the effectiveness of giving the additional treatment of anti-immunoglobulin E antibody or nothing on the time until their next asthma attack. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study evaluating the efficacy of anti-IgE antibody, omalizumab, for the prevention of subsequent asthma exacerbations in children aged 6-12 years (OMALIZ612)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-4795</utrn>
    <trialacronym>OMALIZ612</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CIGE025B2401T</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>asthma exacerbations</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>anti-IgE antibody, omalizumab. 
The dose of omalizumab to be administered to each subject will be calculated using the subjects baseline total serum or plasma IgE levels (IU/ml) plus the subjects weight (kg) in accordance with the dosing table (described in the Xolair (Registered Trademark) (Omalizumab) Product Information Sheet). The Product Information Sheet is listed under Xolair (Registered Trademark) on the the Health Care Professionals page in the following website
https://www.novartis.com.au/products/healthcare-professionals
The dose will be given as a subcutaneous (SC) injection.
A single dose of omalizumab will be given. However, in accordance with the dosing table, each participant with sufficient body weight (kg) and total IgE levels to require a second dose of Omalizumab, will need their second dose of either Omalizumab or placebo to be given two weeks later. 
The treatment drug, omalizumab, (or placebo) will be administered at least 12 hours after the patient presents to hospital, at the enrolment visit.
Treatment will be given in the hospital, so adherence will be monitored by the person administering the treatment</interventions>
    <comparator>Normal saline (0.9% w/v)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time (number of days) to next asthma exacerbation in the subsequent six months
This will be assessed by the review of medical records and diary records completed by the parents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months post recruitment at presentation to hospital with an asthma exacerbation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time  (number of days or hours) to discharge
This will be assessed by the review of medical records.



</outcome>
      <timepoint> Date and time of discharge
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount (number of doses) of short-acting beta2 agonists required in the first 6, 12 and 24 hours after treatment with omalizumab
This will be assessed by the review of medical records.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 12 and 24 hours after treatment with omalizumab</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time (number of days) respiratory symptoms persist after asthma exacerbation
This will be assessed by the review of diary records completed by the parents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of end of respiratory symptoms following recruitment asthma exacerbation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount (number) of asthma exacerbations in subsequent 6 months
This will be assessed by the review of medical records and diary records completed by the parents.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months following recruitment asthma exacerbation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount (number) of asthma exacerbations in subsequent 12 months
This will be assessed by the review of medical records and diary records completed by the parents as well as telephone interview at 12 months post recruitment.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Twelve months post recruitment at presentation to hospital with an asthma exacerbation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Male or female children 6-12 years of age presenting to PMH ED with a diagnosis of either acute asthma or asthma exacerbation by the treating physician. 
2.	An acute asthma severity score of moderate or severe as defined by Qureshi, F. et al. NEJM (1998) 339:1030-5.
3.	Admission to hospital with acute wheeze or asthma at least once in the previous year.
4.	Parent(s) or legal guardian(s) of the child is able to understand the study requirements and willing to provide informed consent

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A child who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study: 
1.	Known (or evidence of) chronic underlying condition (other than asthma) 
2.	Known hypersensitivity to omalizumab or other anti-IgE drugs
3.	History of a previous doctor diagnosis of anaphylaxis
4.	At high risk of chronic helminth infection
5.	History of malignancy
6.	History of a prior diagnosis with cardiovascular disease or an arterial thromboembolic event
7.	Treatment with immunosuppressant drugs including methotrexate, cyclosporine or azathioprine within 30 days prior to enrolment in this study
8.	Treatment with omalizumab within 6 months prior to enrolment in this study
9.	Participation in another randomized control trial within the 3 months preceding enrolment in this study
10.	Any clinically relevant abnormal findings in physical examination and/or vital signs at Visit 1, which, in the opinion of the investigator, may deem the child unsuitable for the study. 
11.	Pregnancy, breast-feeding or planned pregnancy during the study.  Female participants who are fertile (i.e. have reached menarche) will undergo a pregnancy test by urine dipstick.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>We use an electronic tool from a website called Randomisation.com to generate the sequence. 
Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is independent of the recruitment team and will prepare the treatment or placebo.</concealment>
    <sequence>(link: http://www.randomization.com/ 
Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We will analyse the data using an intention-to-treat analysis strategy to compare the difference in asthma severity scores, treatment response outcomes, length of stay in hospital, time to resolution of symptoms and subsequent exacerbation rates between the intervention and placebo groups.  Analysis of variance or independent sample T tests, where appropriate will be employed for the comparison of the outcome variables with a normal or transformed normal distribution.  For the data with a non-normal distribution, corresponding non-parametric tests will be used.  As we will follow up the clinical trial cohort up to 12 months, we will employ survival and Poisson analysis methods to investigate the effects of the intervention on the outcome variables: time to event and number of recurrent infections, respectively. 
We assume 80% will complete the follow-up as this is expected based on our experience in other clinical research trials and research studies.  Thus, we need to recruit at least 128 subjects. We have now also calculated the power with the primary objectives of time to recurrence of asthma symptoms (exacerbation). A two-sided logrank test with an overall final sample size of 100 subjects (50 in the control group and 50 in the treatment group) achieves 79.3% power at a 0.050 significance level to detect a hazard ratio of 0.5 when the control group hazard rate is a hazard ratio of 1.00. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/10/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Stirling Highway
Perth WA 6009
Australia </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601

Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>54 Waterloo Rd, 
Macquarie Park, 
NSW, 2113
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, clinical trial with the primary objective to determine the efficacy of omalizumab given to children aged 6-12 years during an acute asthma exacerbation to prevent asthma exacerbations in the subsequent six months.  
Subjects include male and female children aged 6-12 years presenting to Princess Margaret Hospital for Children (PMH) Emergency Department with moderate to severe acute asthma.  The treatment group (n=64) will receive one dose of omalizumab at the enrolment visit (Visit 1). The placebo group (n=64) will receive one dose of a placebo at the enrolment visit (Visit 1). However, in accordance with the dosing table (described in the Xolair (Registered Trademark) (Omalizumab) Product Information Sheet), each participant with sufficient body weight (kg) and total IgE levels to require a second dose of Omalizumab, will need to have a second dose of either Omalizumab or placebo two weeks later.  The treatment drug, omalizumab, (or placebo) will be administered at least 12 hours after the patient presents to hospital, at the enrolment visit  and following treatment, the patient will be monitored for a minimum of two hours by an experienced paediatrician. All children will also receive standard asthma therapy according to the PMH Clinical Practice Guidelines.  This study consists of 3-4 visits over six months (including the first enrolment and treatment visit) and 1 follow-up telephone interview at 12 months. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This is a proof of concept clinical trial</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 1, Children's Clinical Research Facility
Princess Margaret Hospital
Roberts Road, Subiaco WA 6008
GPO Box D184
Perth WA 6840</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015182</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Le Souef</name>
      <address>Professor of Paediatrics
Consultant Respiratory Physician
School of Paediatrics and Child Health, The University of Western Australia and Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
GPO Box D184, Perth, WA, AUSTRALIA 6840
</address>
      <phone>+61893408173</phone>
      <fax>+61893882097</fax>
      <email>peter.lesouef@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ingrid Laing</name>
      <address>Senior Research Fellow
UWA SPACH Children's Respiratory Research Group
Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855 West Perth WA 6872</address>
      <phone>+61894897706</phone>
      <fax>+61894897700</fax>
      <email>ingrid.laing@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ingrid Laing</name>
      <address>Senior Research Fellow
UWA SPACH Respiratory Research Group
Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855 West Perth WA 6872</address>
      <phone>+61894897706</phone>
      <fax>+61894897700</fax>
      <email>ingrid.laing@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ingrid Laing</name>
      <address>Senior Research Fellow
UWA SPACH Respiratory Research Group
Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855 West Perth WA 6872</address>
      <phone>+61894897706</phone>
      <fax>+61894897700</fax>
      <email>ingrid.laing@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>