<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373171">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000997358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Objective and subjective assessment of readiness to Return to Sport post Anterior Cruciate Ligament (ACL) reconstruction.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Subjective assessment of knee function and readiness to Return to Sport, versus objective muscle strength asymmetry 6 and 10 months post Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-1867 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction (ACLR)

The ACLR will be performed using a medial portal femoral tunnel approach. 
A hamstring autograft will be harvested from either ipsilateral or contralateral side and fixed in the femoral tunnel using an endobutton, and within the tibial tunnel using an intracortical tibial screw, plus/minus a staple, as necessary. Patients will be recruited for study participation 3 months post ACLR, and as such the ACLR is not conducted as part of this study.

The aim of this study is to investigate the correlation between an objective measure of quadriceps and hamstring isometric muscle strength (LSI) and subjective assessment of knee joint function and perceived readiness to Return to Sport (RTS) at 6 months and 10 months post ACLR.

</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Isometric muscle strength of both the quadriceps and hamstring, measured by Limb Symmetry Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months and 10 months post ACLR</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported knee function measured by the International Knee Documentation Committee (IKDC) 2000 Subjective Knee Form </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months and 10 months post ACLR. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological readiness to Return to Sport assessed using the ACL  Return to Sport after Injury (ACL  RSI) Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 10 months post ACLR.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in isometric muscle strength of both the quadriceps and hamstring, measured using an isokinetic dynamometre</outcome>
      <timepoint>change in time from 6 to 10 months post ACLR. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patient has provided written, informed consent and is willing to participant;
2. Patient is prior to 6 months post ACLR following isolated rupture of the ACL;
3. Patient regularly participates in a Level 1 or Level 2 Activity level sports*;
4. Male and/or female patients of 14 years of age or greater.

*Activity Levels are defined by those outlined by Hefti et al. 1993. Levels 1 and 2 will be sub-classified to whether the athlete competed at elite (professional) level, or non-elite level sport.
-	Level 1: Jumping, pivoting, hard cutting, football, soccer;
o	Level 1A: Competing at an elite, professional sporting level
o	Level 1B: Not competing in an elite, professional sporting level
-	Level 2: Heavy manual work, skiing, tennis;
o	Level 1A: Competing at an elite, professional sporting level
o	Level 1B: Not competing in an elite, professional sporting level
-	Level 3: Light manual work, jogging, running;
-	Level 4: Sedentary work (ADL)


Reference: Hefti F, Muller W, Jakob RP, Staubli HU. Evaluation of knee ligament injuries with the IKDC form. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc. 1993;1(3-4):226-34.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patient having undergone Revision ACLR.
2. Patients with a multi-ligament knee injury.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size:

Consecutive recruitment will occur over a 6 month period. All patients of whom have undergone an ACLR performed by a single surgeon will be invited to participant in the study. A sample size of 40 patients is estimated, which is an equivalent sample size used by Muller U, et al. 2015 to address similar objectives. 

The sample size has been estimated within the limitations of cost and time availability. A post hoc power analysis will be conducted, and effect sizes reported.

Data Analysis:

Primary Objectives:
1.	To determine whether quadriceps and hamstring isometric muscle strength measured by Limb Symmetry Index correlates with self-reported function and psychological readiness to RTS measured by the IKDC and ACL-RSI, at 6 months and 10 months post ACLR. 
2.	To determine how the association between muscle strength and self-reported function and psychological readiness to RTS changed time (6 to 10 months).

To address Objectives 1 and 2, a Pearsons correlation coefficient will be calculated, conditional on distributions of both objective (LSI) and subjective (IKDC and ACL-RSI) measures.

3.	To determine whether self-reported function and psychological readiness to RTS change, following knowledge of a good muscle strength outcome (LSI of = 90.0%), and awareness of personal muscle strength results at 6 and 10 months post ACLR.

A Mixed ANOVA with two within factors including time (2 levels: Time 1 (6 months) and Time 2 (10 months)) and Pre-Post knowledge of muscle strength (2 levels), in addition to a between factor of nature of clinical outcome (3 levels). The established threshold is greater than or equal to 90% LSI, and the 3 levels include the following:
1.	Positive LSI results exceeding threshold on both Time 1 and Time 2;
2.	Negative LSI results below the threshold on Time 1 and Time 2;
3.	Negative LSI results below the threshold for Time 1 but positive LSI results exceeding threshold for Time 2.

Secondary Objectives:
1.	To determine if there is an improvement in muscle strength over time, from 6 to 10 months post ACLR. 
2.	To determine whether patients that require a 4-strand double hamstring autograft experience poorer muscle strength at 6 and 10 months post ACLR, compared with patients whom received a 4-strand single hamstring autograft.

Outcomes of LSI between patients that received a double versus single hamstring autograft will be assessed using a Mixed ANOVA with the within factor of time (6 Months and 10 months) and between factor of graft type.

In the event that study data produced results in a violation of the proposed test assumptions, alternative non-parametric equivalence will be utilised. 

Reference: 
Muller U, Kruger-Franke M, Schmidt M, Rosemeyer B. Predictive parameters for return to pre-injury level of sport 6 months following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction surgery. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc. 2015;23(12):3623-31.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>5/07/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>5/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Matthew Liptak</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flinders Private Hospital, Ground Floor, 
1 Flinders Drive, 
Bedford Park SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Incorporated</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Incorporated
13 Laffers Rd, 
Belair, SA 5052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Conflicting evidence and inconsistent criteria regarding Return to Sport (RTS) following Anterior Cruciate Ligament (ACL)  highlights the necessity for further investigation into ACL Reconstruction (ACLR), and factors that influence RTS.

The aim of this study is to investigate the correlation between an objective measure of quadriceps and hamstring isometric muscle strength and subjective assessment of knee joint function and perceived readiness to RTS at 6 months and 10 months after ACLR.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
Ward 6C, Room 6A219
Flinders Drive, Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Liptak</name>
      <address>Flinders Private Hospital, Ground Floor, 
1 Flinders Drive, 
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+618 8267 8237  </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>liptakadmin@orthosa.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Annika Theodoulou</name>
      <address>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc.
13 Laffers Road,
Belair, SA 5052,</address>
      <phone>+618 7231 8452</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Annika.Theodoulou@imri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Annika Theodoulou</name>
      <address>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc.
13 Laffers Road,
Belair, SA 5052,</address>
      <phone>+618 7231 8452</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Annika.Theodoulou@imri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Annika Theodoulou</name>
      <address>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc.
13 Laffers Road,
Belair, SA 5052,</address>
      <phone>+618 7231 8452</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Annika.Theodoulou@imri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>