<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373161">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000946314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Connecting Kin Research Project: A trial of a trauma- and attachment-based intervention in kinship care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the feasibility and effectiveness of a trauma- and attachment-based parenting intervention in kinship care </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CK Project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Child behavioural and socioemotional functioning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Complex trauma </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Trauma-informed caregiving </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study aims to evaluate the implementation and preliminary effectiveness of a modified version of the Connect parenting program (see Moretti, Pasalich, &amp; ODonnell [in press], Handbook of Attachment-Based Interventions, for a review) for children in kinship care. The version of the Connect program trialled in this study has been tailored to the specific needs of alternative/kin carers and children in out-of-home-care (OOHC). The intervention is trauma-informed and incorporates key principles from attachment theory. These intervention features are critical to promoting the wellbeing and resilience of children in OOHC who have histories of trauma and disrupted attachment relationships. 

The Connect parenting program will be implemented by practitioners (including psychologists, counsellors and social workers) in a child protection agency, who will be trained in the manualised intervention and provided with ongoing consultation and feedback. Two practitioners will co-facilitate each parenting group of 8-10 kinship carers. Groups will meet weekly for 1.5 hours over 8 weeks at a local community centre.  Each Connect session introduces an attachment principle that relates to child development, trauma and kinship care, and captures a key aspect of the caregiver-child relationship and common parenting challenges (e.g., empathy, conflict, growth and change). Experiential activities, including role-plays and reflection exercises, are used to illustrate each principle and build parenting knowledge and skills to promote secure attachment.

Practitioners adherence to the intervention protocol will be assessed via practitioners self reports using a fidelity checklist and direct observations of the leaders delivering the program using a sample of video recordings. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Families in the delayed intervention control group will receive care as usual (CAU). CAU includes support and intervention services provided by the child protection agency and/or by mental health and other health specialists (based on referrals made by agency staff). Data will be collected regarding the type and frequency of CAU services received by families in both the experimental and control conditions. Kinship carers in the control group will be offered the Connect program six months after completing the baseline assessment. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in children's dysregulated behaviour and emotions as measured by the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire and Affect Regulation Checklist. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline)  and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the quality of the caregiver-child relationship as measured by the Comprehensive Child-Parent Attachment Inventory and Revised Conflict Tactics Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in caregivers' parental satisfaction as measured by the Parenting Sense of Competence Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in carers' caregiving strain as measured by the Caregiver Strain Questionnaire - Short Form.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in caregivers' reflective functioning as measured by the Five-Minute Speech Sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in caregivers' mindful parenting as measured by the Interpersonal Mindfulness in Parenting Scale.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in children's prosocial emotions as measured by the Inventory of Callous-Unemotional Traits. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in children's traumatic stress as measured by the Child PTSD Symptom Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children's placement stability as measured by children's placement records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately post-intervention (10 weeks after baseline) and 6-month, 12-month and 24-month follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children will be eligible to participate in the study if they are aged 8-16 years, have resided in their current kinship care placement for at least four weeks, and demonstrate elevated behavioural and/or emotional problems as defined by a score equal to or exceeding the 85th percentile cutoff score. 

Caregivers will be eligible to participate if they are currently supporting a child in a kinship care placement. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Families will be excluded from participating in the study based on child and/or kinship carer characteristics. Exclusion criteria concerning children includes: currently in a crisis/emergency situation, severe mental illness (e.g., schizophrenia, bipolar disorder), significant physical health care needs, severe developmental disability, and/or severe intellectual disability. Families will also be excluded if kinship carers have a severe mental illness or substance use problem, and are unable to speak sufficiently fluent English and/or have limited comprehension of English.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participant recruitment and allocation will occur in cohorts at several different times across the duration of the study. Families will be identified and then individually screened for eligibility. After obtaining participant consent or assent (for children aged 11 years or younger), carers and children in each family will complete the baseline assessment. Families will then be randomly allocated to either the intervention or control condition. To ensure concealment of the allocation sequence, a researcher who is not directly involved in the study will (only) be given the study IDs of the enrolled participants and will use a computer generated randomisation list to randomly assign participants to a condition. </concealment>
    <sequence>To ensure that the conditions are balanced with respect to the number of pre-teens and teens, and boys and girls, randomisation will be stratified by child age (8-11 years, 12-16 years) and sex. Randomisation will be based on a computer generated randomisation list. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intent to treat ANCOVA models will be used to examine group differences (Connect vs. control) on child and caregiver outcomes at post-intervention and follow-up time points. Missing data (attrition estimated at 15%) will be handled using multiple imputation. Structural equation modeling (SEM) will be used to replicate and expand on mediation models found in prior evaluations of the Connect intervention model. SEM will also be used to examine the moderation of child and caregiver variables at baseline on program effects on dependent variables. Missing data in the mediation and moderation models will be handled using full information maximum likelihood.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/12/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/08/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Australian National University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Acton ACT 2601
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2702 
Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Australian National University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Acton ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ACT Community Services Directorate </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 158
Canberra City ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>ACT Child and Youth Protection Services </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>GPO Box 158
Canberra City ACT 2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The goals of this research project are to evaluate the feasibility and effectiveness of an attachment-based and trauma-informed parenting program for kinship carers and children in their care. The program aims to promote carers' understanding of and sensitive responding to their child's behaviour and emotions, and, in turn, strengthen the carer-child relationship and reduce children's behavioural and emotional problems. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Australian National University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Australian National University Human Research Ethics Committee
Acton ACT 2601


</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dave Pasalich</name>
      <address>Research School of Psychology
ANU College of Medicine, Biology and Environment 
Building 39 Science Rd
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2067 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0499</fax>
      <email>dave.pasalich@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dave Pasalich </name>
      <address>Research School of Psychology
ANU College of Medicine, Biology and Environment 
Building 39 Science Rd
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2067 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0499</fax>
      <email>dave.pasalich@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dave Pasalich </name>
      <address>Research School of Psychology
ANU College of Medicine, Biology and Environment 
Building 39 Science Rd
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2067 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0499</fax>
      <email>dave.pasalich@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dave Pasalich </name>
      <address>Research School of Psychology
ANU College of Medicine, Biology and Environment 
Building 39 Science Rd
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2067 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6125 0499</fax>
      <email>dave.pasalich@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>