<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371222">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001095459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating response to exercise programs in monozygotic and dizygotic twins to determine whether exercise response is generic, genetic or modality dependent.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Towards Exercise as Personalised Medicine: Is Non-Response to Exercise Generic, Genetic or Modality Dependent?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular health responses to exercise modalities in apparently healthy subjects</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Twin pairs will be randomised to simultaneously undertake 36 sessions of 3 sessions per week of either resistance or endurance training. This will be followed by a 12 week washout period. Each twin pair will then cross-over to start a similar period of training with the alternate intervention.

Each exercise session will last for 1 hr and be group, centre-based and supervised by and exercise scientist at the UWA Sport Science research gym. Adherance will be monitored by registering attendance at each session. The resistance training will consist of weighted exercises at an intensity according to RPE (&gt;14/20) and endurance training will consist of running and cycle ergometer at intensity according to HR max (60%+). </interventions>
    <comparator>Two exercise programs (endurance and resistance) exercise will be randomised and compared. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Conduit artery function: Brachial and femoral artery flow mediated dilation (FMD) will be assessed according to best practice guidelines. A cuff is inflated (220mmHg) around the forearm and upper thigh for 5min to induce ischaemic conditions whilst high resolution ultrasound of the brachial and femoral artery are obtained pre-post- artery occlusion. The FMD% increase in artery dilation is an indicator of artery function and independently predicts CV events. Endothelium independent dilation is examined using a single, subligual administration of glyceryl trinitrate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 
0 (pre-training intervention 1), 
12 (post-training intervention 1), 
24 (post-washout period and pre-training intervention 1), and 
36 (post-training intervention 2).

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intracranial blood velocity: Cerebral blood flow velocity (CBFv) is assessed by combining bilateral measures of middle (MCA) and posterior cerebral artery (PCA) flow velocities using transcranial Doppler (TCD) techniques.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 
0 (pre-training intervention 1), 
12 (post-training intervention 1), 
24 (post-washout period and pre-training intervention 1), and 
36 (post-training intervention 2).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac outcome measures:  Echocardiographic images will be acquired using a 1.5-4MHz transducer (Vivid I, GE). Left ventricular stress, strain and mechanics will be assessed using echopac. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 
0 (pre-training intervention 1), 
12 (post-training intervention 1), 
24 (post-washout period and pre-training intervention 1), and 
36 (post-training intervention 2).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fitness will be assessed via common practice of a maximal graded treadmill running test that will determine VO2peak. This will be accompanied by common practice blood lactates, heart rate (via chest-worn HR monitor) and rate of perceived exertion (via Borgs scale; composite outcomes) during every stage of the test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 
0 (pre-training intervention 1), 
12 (post-training intervention 1), 
24 (post-washout period and pre-training intervention 1), and 
36 (post-training intervention 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fitness will also be assessed via common practice of strength (1RM) testing, of the maximum load that can be moved by the participant in one muscular contraction of the squat and bench press machine exercises. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 
0 (pre-training intervention 1), 
12 (post-training intervention 1), 
24 (post-washout period and pre-training intervention 1), and 
36 (post-training intervention 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure will be assessed continuously via ambulatory 24hr measures (Welch Allyn ambulatory blood pressure machine)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 
0 (pre-training intervention 1), 
12 (post-training intervention 1), 
24 (post-washout period and pre-training intervention 1), and 
36 (post-training intervention 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Body composition will be assessed by girths of common sites (hips, wait, arm), BMI and DEXA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks: 
0 (pre-training intervention 1), 
12 (post-training intervention 1), 
24 (post-washout period and pre-training intervention 1), and 
36 (post-training intervention 2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy twin pairs aged 15-30yrs will be recruited. We will recruit twin pairs via advertisement in the Perth metropolitan area via flyers. Additionally, we have approval from the Australian Twin Registry (ATR) to use their database.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>&gt;4 units alcohol/day, medical conditions that compromise survival (i.e. cancer) or render subjects unable to exercise, BMI&gt;35, history of myocardial infarction, coronary artery disease, stroke, chronic heart failure, diabetes. Cardiovascular medications or supplements that affect cardiovascular function will also constitute exclusions. Twins completing &gt;150mins/wk of exercise will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Twin study design of MZ and DZ (sex matched) twin pairs</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Winthrop Professor Daniel Green</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Western Ausralia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There has never been a more sedentary population than the 21st century western society, with physical inactivity accounting for a similar number of deaths per annum as tobacco. Physical inactivity is a modifiable risk factor for chronic disease, especially cardiovascular diseases, and no other intervention possesses the broad spectrum of health impacts that can be attributed to exercise. However, the cardiovascular response of an individual to exercise is idiosyncratic and, whilst most individuals incur favourable effects, a sizeable proportion (~30%) of individuals either do not respond or respond adversely to exercise. The current research study aims to answer two fundamental questions. Firstly, is non-response to one exercise modality universal across all modalities? Secondly, to what extent is non-response to exercise environmentally versus genetically determined? </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Western Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/7031</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Daniel J Green</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 64882361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>danny.green@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Channa Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 64882361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>channa.marsh@research.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Daniel Green</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone> +61 8 6488 5609</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>danny.green@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Channa Marsh</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 64882361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>channa.marsh@research.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>