<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368024">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001680459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of Artemether - Lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in in sentinel sites in Mozambique.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of Artemether - Lumefantrine for the treatment of children with uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in in sentinel sites in Mozambique.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To assess the efficacy and safety of artemether/lumefantrine (20mg/120mg: 3 day regimen of twice daily dose of 1 tablet for 5-14 kg; 2 tablets for 15-24 Kg) for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum infection. The treatment will be taken orally under direct supervision by the health worker. Eligibile subjects will be treated for three days and followed up for 28 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A
This is a surveillance prospective study of one-arm.
</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of treatment failures (early treatment failure + late clinical failure + late parasitological failure). This is composite primary outcome. 

Enrolled patients will be assessed for parasitological (using microscopy), clinical responses during the 28 days follow-up and treatment outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 28 following initiation of artemether+lumefantrine treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of adverse event will be documented. The known adverse events of artemether/lumefantrine are abdominal discomfort, nausea, headache and dizziness. 

Parents or guardians of all enrolled patients will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be evaluated and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 28 following initiation of treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of artemisinin resistance molecular markers (K13).

Parasite DNA extracted from the dried blood spots will be analyzed by PCR and sequencing for the presence of K13 (molecular marker for artemisinin resistance).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 0 (prior initiation of treatment) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. age from 6 to 59 months; 
2. mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy;
3. parasitaemia of 2000  200000 asesual/microliter asexual forms;
4. presence of axillary temperature greater than or equal to 37.5 degree centigrade or history of fever during the past 24 h;
5. ability to swallow oral medication;
6. ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule; 
7. informed consent from parent or guardian
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the latest definitions of WHO;
2. weight under 5 kg;
3. mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
4. presence of severe malnutrition defined as a child aged 6-60 months who has a mid-upper arm circumference &lt; 115 mm);
5. presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS);
6. regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics, (see appendix 2 for detailed list of prohibited medication during the study
7. history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s);
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients aged 6 to 59 months with uncomplicated malaria who met the study inclusion criteria were enrolled, treated on site with artemether/lumefantrine and monitored for
28 days. The follow-up will consist of a fixed schedule of check-up visits and corresponding clinical and laboratory examinations. </concealment>
    <sequence>N/A
This surveillance study was one-arm prospective evaluation of clinical and parasitological responses to directly observed treatment for uncomplicated malaria with  
artemether/lumefantrine. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Currently the treatment failure rate to artemether+lumefantrine in the study area is less than 5%. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 5%, a minimum of 73 patients must be included per drug test. With a 20% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the 28-day follow-up period, 88 patients should be included in the study per treatment arm per site. 

Excel WHO tailored database will be used for data management and analysis. Data will be analysed by two methods: the Kaplan-Meier method and per-protocol analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>352</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>353</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>27/05/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <state>Northern Region, Central Region, Southern Region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Central District, 1008 Avenue Eduardo Mondlane, Maputo, 1100</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Mozambique</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health of Mozambique</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Central District, 1008 Avenue Eduardo Mondlane, Maputo, 1100</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Mozambique</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of Artemether - Lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in in sentinel sites in Mozambique.

Purpose: To assess the efficacy and safety of the current first line treatment policy; 

Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety of Artemether  - Lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria infections.

Study Sites: Cabo-Delgado in the northern region; Tete and Sofala in the Central region and Gaza in the Southern region of Mozambique.

Study Period: The study will be conducted from March to August 2015.

Study Design: One arm prospective study. 

Patient population: Febrile patients aged 6 to 59 months, with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum infection. 

Sample Size: 88 patients will be enrolled in each site.
Treatment(s) and follow-up: Artemether - Lumefantrine twice daily dose for three days. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 28-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy.

Primary endpoints: The proportion of patients with early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response as indicators of efficacy.  Recrudescence will be distinguished from re-infection by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis.
Secondary endpoints: The frequency and nature of adverse events.

Optional exploratory endpoints: 
to determine the polymorphism of molecular markers for name of artemisinin resistance; 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite Nacional de Bioethica para a Saude</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Central District, 1008 Avenue Eduardo Mondlane, Maputo, 1100</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>IRB00002657</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Mozambique</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sonia Enosse</name>
      <address>Instituto Nacional de Saude, Ministerio da Saude, Mocambique
Central District, 1008 Avenue Eduardo Mondlane, Maputo, 1100</address>
      <phone>+258829690090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enossesonia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sonia Enosse</name>
      <address>Instituto Nacional de Saude, Ministerio da Saude, Mocambique
Central District, 1008 Avenue Eduardo Mondlane, Maputo, 1100</address>
      <phone>+258829690090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enossesonia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sonia Enosse</name>
      <address>Instituto Nacional de Saude, Ministerio da Saude, Mocambique
Central District, 1008 Avenue Eduardo Mondlane, Maputo, 1100</address>
      <phone>+258829690090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enossesonia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sonia Enosse</name>
      <address>Instituto Nacional de Saude, Ministerio da Saude, Mocambique
Central District, 1008 Avenue Eduardo Mondlane, Maputo, 1100</address>
      <phone>+258829690090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enossesonia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Mozambique</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>