<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363356">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000186651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A trial investigating the convenience and practicality of utilising a floor-based dome device by healthy 18 to 75 year old subjects whilst in their usual working environment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Open label trial investigating the convenience and practicality of utilising a floor-based dome device by healthy 18 to 75 year old subjects whilst undertaking a sedentary job in their usual working environment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-3011 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Venous Thromboembolism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Clotting disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Floor-based footrest.
This is a small device, approximately 300mm in length, with two raised domes. Viewed from the front it looks like a letter m. Users will flex and extend the soles of their feet over the humps. This is expected to improve blood flow from the legs back to the heart even while the users are seated. 

After informed consent, the volunteers will each be given a floor-based dome device and shown how to use it throughout the working week. Participants in this study will be asked to utilise the device for a minimum of 30 to 60 seconds every hour regardless of how long they may have been sitting down or how much they may have been walking in the office throughout the day. 

Participants will be given a diary in which to document their device usage (time of day it was used, duration of use and whether they had shoes on or off) each day. At the end of the week they will also be asked to rate how convenient they found the device, how easy and comfortable it was to use and how likely they would be to use it regularly throughout their working days in the future. These rating will be measured on a scale of 1 (very convenient / easy / comfortable / likely to use it again) to 4 (very inconvenient / very hard / very comfortable / definitely not likely to use it again).  They will be asked to note down any adverse events associated with the device in the workplace. A free text space will be provided to note down any other thoughts or concerns about the device.   
</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no comparator / control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean number of times the device is used in a working day.   

Mean calculated by taking documented diary notes as made by the participants during the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative feedback on the acceptability of the device and likelihood of its continued use in a sedentary workplace environment.
This will be established by reveiwing the questionnaire filled in at the end of the study by the participants 
These ratings will be measured on a scale of 1 (very convenient / easy / comfortable / likely to use it again) to 4 (very inconvenient / very hard / very comfortable / definitely not likely to use it again).  A free text space will be provided to note down any other thoughts or concerns about the device.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 5 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged between 18 to 75 years
Able to provide informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to give informed consent
Inability to abide by the requirements of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Non randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The proportion of participants who use the device at least 4 times per day (50% adherence) will be estimated by the exact binomial method with 95% confidence intervals.

Mean times usage per day and maximum and minimum times used per day will be calculated to allow comparison between each day of intervention.  

Ordinal scale variables will be dichotomised into positive (e.g. very comfortable + comfortable) versus negative (e.g. uncomfortable and very uncomfortable). McNemars test for paired proportions will be applied, and appropriate estimates and confidence intervals will be developed for the discordant proportions.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Victoria University of Wellington</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Biological Sciences
Victoria University of Wellington
PO Box 600
Wellington 6140
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7, CSB Building
Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We want to see whether it is convenient and practical for office-based workers to use the dome device regularly throughout the working day to improve blood flow through their legs while they are sitting down. We know that people sitting down for long periods of time (like when they are flying long distances, or in desk-bound role), may be at increased risk of developing blood clots called deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in their legs.  This risk might be partly due to pooling of blood in the leg during long periods of sitting. Using the dome device every so often may help reduce pooling by improving the return of blood from the legs when used.

To see if its practical to use the dome device in the workplace we would like to run a trial of approximately 200 office and call centre-based people using the device over the course of their working week.  

If we can show that the dome device is convenient, safe and practical, we may be able to introduce it as a simple office tool for people to help reduce the risk of developing blood clots when they are sitting down for long periods of time. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>New Zealand Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/STH/6</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research institute of New Zealand, 
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research institute of New Zealand, 
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research institute of New Zealand, 
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research institute of New Zealand, 
Private Bag 7902, 
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>