<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365857">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000327684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimum Thiamine Intervention for Treatment and Prevention of Wernicke-Korsakoff Syndrome (WKS): A Randomised Controlled Trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Optimum Thiamine Intervention for Treatment and Prevention of Wernicke-Korsakoff Syndrome (WKS): A Randomised Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-7696</utrn>
    <trialacronym>OpT In</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wernicke-Korsakoff Syndrome (WKS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Thiamine Hydrochloride

On the first day of the trial, following baseline assessment, participants will be randomised to one of three parenteral thiamine dose conditions.

Acute Symptomatic WKS Group:
i.	300mg daily (i.e. 100mg 3 times/day) for 5 days 
ii.	900mg daily (i.e. 300mg 3 times/day) for 5 days or
iii.	1500mg daily (i.e. 500mg 3 times/day) for 5 days.

High-risk of subclinical WKS-related brain damage:
i.	100mg once daily for 3 days, 
ii.	300mg (i.e. 100mg 3 times/day) for 3 days or 
iii.	900mg (i.e. 300mg 3 times/day) for 3 days.

Thiamine Hydrochloride will be prescribed by the Addiction Medicine physician (also a trial Investigator) using standard hospital prescribing. The thiamine will be provided by the hospital pharmacy and administered by the registered nurse caring for the patient. Administration will be intravenously in a 100ml bag of normal saline (0.9%) infused over 30 minutes. Adherence will be recorded by reviewing medication chart.</interventions>
    <comparator>Thiamine Hydrochloride

Active - Standard treatment

Acute Symptomatic WKS Group:
300mg thiamine hydrochloride daily (i.e. 100mg 3 times/day) for 5 days administered intravenously in 100ml bag of normal saline (0.9%) infused over 30 minutes 

High-risk of subclinical WKS-related brain damage:
100mg thiamine hydrochloride once daily for 3 days, 
administered intravenously in 100ml bag of normal saline (0.9%) infused over 30 minutes</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate differences in cognitive outcomes among acute symptomatic WKS patients under three parenteral thiamine treatment conditions (300mg/day for 5 days, versus 900mg/day for 5 days, versus 1500mg/day for 5 days);and among patients at high- risk of subclinical WKS-related brain damage under three parenteral thiamine treatment conditions (100mg/day for 3 days, versus 300mg/day for 3 days, versus 900mg/day for 3 days);
Standardised cognitive assessments (RUDAS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1 and 5 for acute symptomatic patients; Days 1 and 3 for at risk patients</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate differences in neurological outcomes among acute symptomatic WKS patients under three parenteral thiamine treatment conditions (300mg/day for 5 days, versus 900mg/day for 5 days, versus 1500mg/day for 5 days); and among patients at high-risk of subclinical WKS-related brain damage under three parenteral thiamine treatment conditions (100mg/day for 3 days, versus 300mg/day for 3 days, versus 900mg/day for 3 days);
Standardised neurological examination</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1 and 5 for acute symptomatic patients; Days 1 and 3 for at risk patients</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlate changes in red cell thiamine test results (blood test) with cognitive (RUDAS scores) and neurological functioning (Standardised Neurological examiniation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1 and 5 for acute symptomatic patients; Days 1 and 3 for at risk patients</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine the impact of  magnesium deficiency (magnesium blood test) on thiamine treatment response  (cognition as measured by RUDAS and thiamine pyrophosphate levels as measured by blood test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1 and 5 for acute symptomatic patients; Days 1 and 3 for at risk patients</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess independent predictors of WKS including nutritional factors, substance use history and demographic factors
assessed by questionaire items including Nutritional Risk Assessment and AUDIT-C.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine the impact of patient re-admission on red cell thiamine pyrophosphate levels (blood test) and cognitive (RUDAS) and neurological functioning (standardised neurological exam)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged between 18-65
History of heavy alcohol use AUDIT-C score &gt;4 or consumption &gt;60mg/day or &gt;80mg/binge</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant women.
Under the age of 18 or over 65 years old
Known pre-existing neurological or cognitive impairment unrelated to thiamine deficiency or WKS.
Intubated
on vasopressor therapy for hypotension
on Renal dialysis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The Clinical Investigator or medical registrar will be provided with opaque sealed envelopes (for Symtomatic and At-Risk groups separately) following recruitment and completion of informed consent documentation. The envelopes will be provided in consecutive order of participant recruitment and indicate the thiamine dose condition allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The Menzies biostatistics group (independent statistician) will draw up the randomisation schedule using a computerised random number generator, with restricted randomisation (blocks of varying sizes) to ensure that equal numbers of participants are allocated to each treatment condition. The study medicines will be administered according to the randomisation code. The independent statistician will keep the randomisation code on file, kept securely at Menzies School of Health Research.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>450 participants (total N=225 participants to each patient group)

We wish to detect the smallest experimental effect that will lead to a clinically useful outcome, even if this effect is modest (ie Cohen's d of 0.5) Sample size calculations using Stata version 12.1 for ANCOVA dictate that to detect the above difference with 90% power, an alpha of 0.05 and three dosage conditions, we will require a sample size of 51 per dosage condition (assuming baseline data are correlated r=0.7 to final day of treatment data).  Allowing for approximately 30% attrition, we will recruit 75 participants to each dosage condition.  Therefore we aim to recruit total N= 225 participants to each patient group.

Continuous outcome measures on the final day of treatment will be compared between the dosage conditions, adjusted for the outcome measure at baseline level using an ANCOVA approach

Binary neuological data will be analysed using logisitc regression adjusting for the outcome measure at baseline</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>18/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>450</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Alice Springs Hospital - Alice Springs</hospital>
    <postcode>0870 - Alice Springs</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kylie Dingwall</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Menzies School of Health Research
c/o Centre for Remote Health
Cnr Simpson and Skinner Street
Alice Springs NT 0870</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Menzies School of Health Research
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Darwin Hospital Campus
John Mathews Building
Building 58, Royal Darwin Hospital Campus
Rocklands Drive
TIWI NT 0810</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome (WKS), once thought to be a rare condition, is now known to be common in people with nutritional deficiencies or alcohol dependence. The primary cause of WKS is thiamine deficiency, and more than 90% of cases are reported in alcohol dependent patients because alcohol dependence predisposes to severe nutritional deficiency. WKS may lead to significant, long-term brain dysfunction with severe effects on work, personal and social function. Whilst effective treatment may greatly reduce severe disability and the human and social costs of this illness, almost no evidence exists on optimal dosing regimens. This project proposes to develop quality evidence for effective treatment of WKS in an Aboriginal setting.  

The need for evidence-based thiamine treatment protocols is of great clinical importance for two related reasons. First, in relation to acute symptomatic WKS, a failure to treat immediately or adequately may result in profound and often permanent cognitive and neurological disability. Secondly, the need for evidence-based treatment guidelines is greatly magnified when it is recognised that milder, subclinical WKS may be preventable with adequate thiamine treatment. 

The aims of this study are to determine the optimal thiamine dose required for:
A.	Treatment of acute symptomatic Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome (WKS) among Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal alcohol-dependent patients.
B.	Reducing or preventing subclinical WKS-related brain damage in at-risk Aboriginal and non-Aboriginal alcohol-dependent patients. 

Primary Hypotheses
1.	Among alcohol-dependent patients with acute symptomatic WKS, higher doses of parenteral thiamine (1500mg) will lead to greater improvements in specific cognition and neurological functions than lower doses (900mg or 300mg).
2.	Among alcohol-dependent patients that are at high risk for subclinical WKS-related brain damage, higher doses of parenteral thiamine (900mg) will lead to greater improvements in specific cognition and neurological functions compared to lower doses (300mg or 100mg). 

Secondary Hypotheses
1.	Thiamine deficient patients will show poorer performance on cognitive and neurological measures
2.	Patients with concurrent magnesium deficiency will show greater impairment at baseline
3.	Nutritional risk and alcohol frequency will correlate with thiamine pyrophosphate levels.
4.	Number of previous admissions with thiamine supplementation in the past 3 months will correlate with thiamine pyrophosphate levels.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the Northern Territory Department of Health and Menzies School of Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 41096
Casuarina NT 0811</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-2014-2151</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Australian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 4066
Alice Springs, NT 0871</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14-226</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Dingwall</name>
      <address>c/o Centre for Remote Health
Cnr Simpson and Skinner Street
Alice Springs NT 0870</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89514753 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89514777</fax>
      <email>Kylie.Dingwall@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Dingwall</name>
      <address>c/o Centre for Remote Health
Cnr Simpson and Skinner Street
Alice Springs NT 0870</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89514753 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89514777</fax>
      <email>Kylie.Dingwall@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Dingwall</name>
      <address>c/o Centre for Remote Health
Cnr Simpson and Skinner Street
Alice Springs NT 0870</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89514753 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89514777</fax>
      <email>Kylie.Dingwall@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>