<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="307980">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000447257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes in ocular mucin expression due to contact lens wear</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective study investigating the change of ocular mucin expression on the ocular surface and in tear fluid due to contact lens wear and its correlation with contact lens clinical performance in neophytes and regular wearers with minimal lens wear in the previous one month.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>New secondary ID. Please modify.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contact lens wear affects mucin expression on the ocular surface and in tear fluid. The mucin change correlates with clinical variables and lens performance.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A prospective, randomised, contralateral lens wear, open label, single group design clinical trial. with participants wearing comercially available lenses (AIR OPTIX AQUA and PUREVISION) and lens care solution (AOSEPT PLUS). Lenses will be worn for one month and a minimum of 6 hours per day, 5 days per week, on a daily wear basis (i.e. removed prior to sleep).  Lenses will be disinfected overnight (minimum of 6 hours) in the lens care solution.</interventions>
    <comparator>Changes in mucin expression after 1 month contralateral wear of two lens types will be compared to the initial visit (i.e. baseline visit) where no lenses are worn.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate mucin changes due to contact lens wear using impression cytology to permit collection and morphological examination of the superficial layers of the superior tarsal conjunctival epithelium. Samples will be taken prior to lens wear (i.e. baseline visit) and following 1 month of lens wear.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 30 days after baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether there is a correlation between mucin changes and clinical performance or comfort of commercially available contact lenses. Qestionnaires will be used to asess subjective performance. Objective assessment of the eyes wiill be conducted with a slit-lamp biomicroscope (including corneal and conjunctival staining fluorecein).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline then 1, 2 and 30 days after baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses;
Has vision correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Regular contact lens wearers;
Pre-existing ocular irritation that would preclude contact lens fitting;
Any ocular condition that may preclude safe wearing of contact lenses e.g. active corneal infection, severe dry eye, reduced corneal sensitivity, exophthalmos/lagophthalmos, facial nerve palsy;
Active corneal infection (bacterial, viral, fungal or protozoan) or any active ocular disease such as iritis, corneal edema or corneal dystrophies, including anterior membrane dystrophy that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
Use of any of the following medications (including steroids) up to 12 weeks prior to start of the clinical trial, or during the course of the trial:
Ocular medication, category S3 and above;
Any systemic or topical medications that will affect ocular physiology or the performance of the lenses e.g. anti-acne medications such as Roaccutane and corticosteroid or immunosuppressant medications such as Hydrocortisone, Prednisolone;
Any systemic disease that may affect ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankolysing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjogrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosis;
Conditions such as systemic hypertension do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
Previous corneal refractive surgery;
Any ocular injury or condition (including keratoconus and herpes keratitis) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would affect the wearing of contact lenses;
Contraindications to hydrogel contact lens wear;
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial;.
Be pregnant or breast feeding;*.
Allergy or intolerance to topical anaesthetics.
*verbal report of pregnancy by the participant is sufficient, formal testing not required</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two different lens types. Allocation will be concealed and done by central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation plan will be generated by computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute for Eye Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street,
University of New South Wales, SYDNEY   NSW   2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Eye Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street,
University of New South Wales, SYDNEY   NSW   2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Contact lens wear affects mucin expression on the ocular surface and in the tear fluid. The mucin change correlates with clinical variables and lens performance.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rupert Myers Building, c/o Research Office / Ethics, Gate 14, Barker St, Kensington, 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/01/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07310</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mark Willcox</name>
      <address>Level 4, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street,
University of New South Wales, SYDNEY   NSW   2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>m.willcox@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street,
University of New South Wales, SYDNEY   NSW   2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street,
University of New South Wales, SYDNEY   NSW   2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>