<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82911">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/06/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000309381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Do dynamic splints reduce wrist stiffness following fracture?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For wrist stiffness following fracture, will the addition of a dynamic splint to exercises and advice improve range of motion and function?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wrist fracture</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stiffness</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The dynamic splint is custom-made for the subject with thermoplastic. There is an axis about the wrist joint, and a force is applied into wrist extension with rubber band traction. The fingers and thumb will be free to move, and the subjects will be encouraged to use their hands for activities of daily living with the splint on wherever possible. Subjects will be instructed to wear the splint for more than 6 hours per day, (with total time of wear recorded) for 8 weeks. The subjects in the intervention group will also receive exercise and advice, as per the control group.
The exercises will involve active range of motion and stretches into wrist extension, flexion, radial deviation, and ulnar deviation, as well as forearm pronation and supination. Subjects will be asked to perform the exercises three times per day, with ten repetitions per type of exercise for 8 weeks.
The advice will be verbally given. Guidelines for advice to the patient will include using the involved upper limb for activities of daily living as much as possible, together with advice and reassurance relating to situations which may involve discomfort resulting from the exercises or activities of daily living. The type of advice and manner of delivery best reflects current clinical practice.
In this way, the effectiveness of a dynamic splint over and above exercise and advice can be determined.</interventions>
    <comparator>Exercise and advice will be used as the control treatment. The exercises will involve active range of motion and stretches into wrist extension, flexion, radial deviation, and ulnar deviation, as well as forearm pronation and supination. Subjects will be asked to perform the exercises three times per day, with ten repetitions per type of exercise for 8 weeks.
The advice will be verbally given. Guidelines for advice to the patient will include using the involved upper limb for activities of daily living as much as possible, together with advice and reassurance relating to situations which may involve discomfort from exercises or activities of daily living. The type of advice and manner of delivery best reflects current clinical practice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion with standardised torque</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures taken at recruitment, two months of intervention, and one month post cessation of all interventions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient rated hand and wrist evaluation. Validated questionnaire for patient restrcition.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaire taken at recruitment, two months, and one month post cessation of all interventions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active range of extension, flexion, radial deviation, and ulnar deviation of the wrist using a goniometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures taken at recruitment, two months of intervention, and one month post cessation of all interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Canadian Outcome Performance Measure. Client centred interview of self-perceived peformance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Interview given at recruitment, two months, and one month post cessation of all interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Have sustained a fracture to the wrist at least ten weeks prior to inclusion. The fracture must be healed (united) at the time of recruitment.
- Have been referred to physiotherapy by a consultant hand surgeon.
- Have a unilateral injury.
- Have wrist stiffness evident by loss of passive range of motion compared to the contralateral wrist.
- Be living in the Sydney Metropolitan Area.
- Be willing/likely to cooperate with the intervention.
- Be over the age of 18.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects will be excluded from the study if they are unable to tolerate wearing a splint.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal North Shore Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pacific Highway
St Leonards
NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rehabilitation Studies Unit, PO Box 6, Ryde NSW 1680</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study is to determine the effectiveness of dynamic splints applied for two months on wrist stiffness and patient restrictions following wrist fractures.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Health Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00333)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0803-027M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Lisa Harvey</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Studies Unit
Royal Rehabilitation Centre Sydney
PO Box 6
Ryde NSW 1680</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9808 9236</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.harvey@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Ray Jongs</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 7556</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rjongs@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Ray Jongs</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 7556</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rjongs@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>