<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370917">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000864426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Stability, functional and clinical outcomes following Reverse Total Shoulder Arthroplasty (RSA); Repair versus Non-Repair of the Subscapularis </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Stability, functional and clinical outcomes following Reverse Total Shoulder Arthroplasty (RSA); Repair versus Non-Repair of the Subscapularis </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-3618 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Management of the subscapularis following reverse total shoulder arthroplasty </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients undergoing Reverse Shoulder Arthroplasty (RSA)  using the deltopectoral approach require the release of the subscapularis either via tenotomy or lesser tuberosity osteotomy. The importance of the subscapularis in patients with a RSA prosthesis and consequently, the need of repair following implantation, remains controversial.

The exposure of interest is Subscapularis repair compared to non-repair following RSA.

The duration of follow-up period is designed for a single assessment session in which the clinical, functional and radiographic assessments will be conducted. Assessments will require approximately two hours to complete, occurring at any point between surgery and 5 years post surgery. The two hours may be spread of over multiple visits depending on the participant's and health professionals availability. </interventions>
    <comparator>This study will compare stability, functional and clinical outcomes of a repaired versus non-repaired/irreparable Subscapularis following reverse shoulder arthroplasty.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the difference in the function, as measured by the self-reported ASES score, between two RSA treatment groups up to 5 years post-surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare outcomes of patients implanted with a medialised versus lateralised Reverse Total Shoulder prosthesis between the two treatment groups. 

A CT-scan will be conducted to measure the extent of lateralisation, achieved by the use of a lateralised prosthesis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To consider the influence of scar tissue development on functional and clinical outcomes between the two treatment groups. 

Scar tissue development will be assessed using Ultrasonography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the patient-reported shoulder function following RSA without repair of the subscapularis compared to RSA with repair of the subscapularis.

This will be measured using American Shoulder and Elbow Surgeons Questionnaire patient-reported outcome measure.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the patient-reported quality of life  following RSA without repair of the subscapularis compared to RSA with repair of the subscapularis.

This will be measured using the Euroqol 5 Dimensional Health Survey (EQ-5D-5L) patient reported outcome measure.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess patient-reported shoulder instability following RSA without repair of the subscapularis compared to RSA with repair of the subscapularis.

This will be measured using the Western Ontario Shoulder Instability Index (WOSI) patient reported outcome measure.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the patient-reported symptoms and function following RSA without repair of the subscapularis compared to RSA with repair of the subscapularis.

This will be measured using the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand Questionnaire (DASH) outcome measures.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the patient's perception of recovery following RSA without repair of the subscapularis compared to RSA with repair of the subscapularis.

This will be measured using the Patient perceived rate of recovery patient-reported outcome measure.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the intra- and inter-rater reliability of range of motion (ROM), manual muscle testing (MMT) and hand held dynamometry (HHD) strength testing for assessment of Reverse Total Shoulder Arthroplasty patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the extent of internal impingement, fatty infiltration of the rotator cuff and presence of an acromial fracture (composite). Such factors will be measured using a CT-scan and compared between the 2 study groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single time-point between 0 and 5 years post reverse total shoulder replacement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patient has provided written, informed consent and is willing to participant.
Participant is a male or non-pregnant female, at least 40 years old, and preferably at least 50 years of age. 
Patient has received a Reverse Total Shoulder Replacement implanted within the previous 5 years.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient has undergone Revision reverse shoulder arthroplasty (i.e. previous resurfacing, hemi, total or reverse).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A total sample of 56 participants achieves 80% power to detect a difference of at least 9.70 using a two independent samples t-test at a 0.0500 significance level. The common standard deviation within a group is assumed to be 12.7.

Repeated strength and range of motion measures will be performed on a convenience sub-sample of 20 RSA subjects in order to consider intra- and inter-rater reliability of MMT, HHD and ROM in the functional assessment of RSA subjects.

Statistical analyses that will be undertaken to assess study objectives will be a two independent samples t-test, conditional on fulfilling test assumptions. If study data produced results in violation of test assumptions of the two independent samples t-test, alternative testing may include non-parametric equivalence of this t-test.

The two independent samples t-test can be controlled for some of the variants that may confound study results. Such variants may include a difference in prostheses implanted or in the mean follow-up between receiving the surgical procedure and post-operative time of recall. An analysis technique may be required to assess the group means while controlling for such aforementioned confounding variables.    
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>56</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Southern Adelaide Health Institute - Belair</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Jeganath Krishnan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Professor Jegan Krishnan
13 Laffers Rd,
Belair, SA 5052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc.
13 Laffers Rd, 
Belair, SA 5052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>13 Laffers Rd, 
Belair, SA 5052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The importance of the subscapularis in patients with a Reverse Shoulder Arthroplasty prosthesis and consequently, the need of repair following implantation, remains controversial.  The aim of the study is to determine the stability, functional and clinical outcomes of a repaired versus non-repaired/irreparable subscapularis following Reverse Total Shoulder Arthroplasty. 

The primary objective of this study is to assess the difference in the function, as measured by the self-reported ASES score, between two RSA treatment groups up to 5 years post-surgery. 

Secondary objectives are to: 

Compare outcomes of patients implanted with a medialised versus lateralised Reverse Total Shoulder prosthesis between the two treatment groups. 

Consider the influence of scar tissue development on functional and clinical outcomes between the two treatment groups. 

A physiotherapy focused substudy will evaluate the intra- and inter-rater reliability of range of motion (ROM), manual muscle testing (MMT) and hand held dynamometry (HHD) strength testing for assessment of Reverse Total Shoulder Arthroplasty patients.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre/The Flats F6/F8
Flinders Drive, Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>460.15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jeganath Krishnan</name>
      <address>Professor Jegan Krishnan
13 Laffers Road,
Belair, SA 5052</address>
      <phone>+618 8267 8233 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krishnanadmin@sahi.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Annika Theodoulou</name>
      <address>The International Musculoskeletal Research Institute Inc.
13 Laffers Road,
Belair, SA 5052, </address>
      <phone>+61 8 7231 8452</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Annika.Theodoulou@imri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jeganath Krishnan</name>
      <address>Professor Jegan Krishnan
13 Laffers Road,
Belair, SA 5052</address>
      <phone>+618 8267 8233 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krishnanadmin@sahi.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Annika Theodoulou</name>
      <address>13 Laffers Road, 
Belair, SA 5052</address>
      <phone>+618 7231 8452</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Annika.Theodoulou@imri.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>