<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370183">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000344493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The LIFTMOR for Men trial: Is heavy resistance training or a machine-based isometric exercise program more effective at reducing risk of fracture in older men with reduced bone mass?
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to determine the effectiveness of heavy progressive resistance training versus high load machine-based isometric resistance training to reduce the risk of osteoporotic fracture in older men with low bone mass
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym>LIFTMOR (for Men): Lifting Intervention For Training Muscle and Osteoporosis Rehabilitation</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteopenia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Osteoporosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vertebral fracture</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Kyphosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoporosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is a three-arm, semi-randomised controlled exercise intervention trial.  Eligible volunteers will be randomly allocated to one of two eight month, twice-weekly, 30-minute exercise programs; either supervised heavy progressive resistance training and impact loading, or machined-based isometric resistance training using the bioDensity system.  
Arm 1  supervised heavy progressive resistance training and weight-bearing impact loading.
Three compound movement exercises (deadlift, overhead press, and squat) using olympic weights will be completed. For each exercise, 5 sets of 5 repetitions, corresponding to an intensity of 80-85 % of 1 repetition maximum will be performed. 5 sets of 5 repetitions of weight-bearing impact loading exercises (i.e. drop jumps) will also be performed, with height of the jump progressively increasing across the intervention period.
Arm 2  supervised high-load isometric exercise using the bioDensity system.
A single set of four isometric exercises (chest press, leg press, core and arm pull, and vertical lift) will be performed according to bioDensity device specifications.  For each exercise, one repetition of a self-initiated 75%-maximum contraction will be held for 5 seconds.
Sessions are supervised by a single qualified trainer (Bachelor of Exercise Science with Honours, Level 1 Sports Trainer, Certificate III in Fitness), a PhD candidate in the School of Allied Health Sciences.
Training diaries will be used to record participant attendance at exercise sessions, and the completion of each element of the training session. Compliance will be determined as the number of sessions attended as a percentage of total possible sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 3  the comparator will be a non-randomised sample of men, recruited independently but sex- and age-matched to the exercise arms.  They will simply continue with their usual activities for 8 months, but will undergo the identical testing protocol at baseline and follow-up as the two randomised arms.  Weekly email contact will be maintained to approximate investigator exposure and track alterations to habitual diet or physical activity levels over the 8 month period. 

Diaries will be provided and all participants will be encouraged to record any changes to medication, medical conditions and general health.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whole body bone mineral density determined by Dual-energy X-ray Absorptiometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bilateral proximal femur (femoral neck, trochanter and total hip regions of interest) bone mineral density determined by Dual-energy X-ray Absorptiometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lumbar spine (L2-L4) bone mineral density determined by Dual-energy X-ray Absorptiometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Indices of bone strength of the skeletally non-dominant forearm determined from peripheral Quantitative Computed Tomography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heel bone quality determined by Quantitative Ultrasonometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition (lean mass, fat mass, appendicular lean mass and percentage body fat) from whole body Dual-energy X-ray Absorptiometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength will be measured via handheld dynamometry using previously validated techniques (maximal isometric leg and thoracic extension muscle strength).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thoracic kyphosis will be determined using an inclinometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily average calcium intake using the validated AusCal questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety (adverse events and injuries) from training diaries across the whole exercise intervention period.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Across the intervention period (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using the validated World Health Organisation 'Quality of Life' questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bone-specific physical activity level using the validated 'Bone-specific Physical Activity' (BPAQ) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Indices of bone strength of the skeletally non-dominant leg determined from peripheral Quantitative Computed Tomography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle density of the skeletally non-dominant forearm determined from peripheral Quantitative Computed Tomography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle density of the skeletally non-dominant leg determined from peripheral Quantitative Computed Tomography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance from training diaries across the whole exercise intervention period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Across the intervention period (8 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function will be determined using previously validated techniques, forming a composite measure (timed up-and-go and five-times sit-to-stand).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All participants, pre (baseline) and post-intervention (8 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men
Apparently healthy
With low bone mineral density (hip or spine BMD T-score less than or equal to -1.0)
Not currently or recently participating in regular resistance training or impact-type exercise</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current participation in resistance training or exercise with an impact-loading component
Uncontrolled cardiovascular disease/respiratory conditions
Neurological conditions which might limit an individuals ability to perform resistance training
Malignancy
Hernia
Medications know to adversely affect musculoskeletal health such as corticosteroids, anti-convulsants
Medical conditions known to effect musculoskeletal health such as hyperparathyroidism, Pagets disease, diabetes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Block randomisation to exercise will occur after participants are stratified by the presence or absence of medications for osteoporosis.  The allocation sequence will be generated by a person independent of the trial and filed in sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random order generated by computer program</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Intervention assignment parallel</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Allied Health Sciences, Griffith University, Gold Coast campus
Parklands Drive, Southport, Gold Coast 4222, Queensland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Osteoporosis Australia Equipment award (bioDensity device supplied and installed by Performance Health Systems)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Osteoporosis Australia National Office
Postal: PO Box 550, Broadway, NSW 2007
Street: Level 2, 255 Broadway Glebe NSW 2037
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Performance Health Systems</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>International head office:
401 Huehl Road, Suite 2A
Northbrook, Illinois
60062</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sports Medicine Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Office:
Sports House, 375 Albert Road, Albert Park, VIC 3206</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recent work undertaken at Griffith University (the LIFTMOR trial) has revealed that brief exposure to a bone-targeted heavy progressive resistance training program is both safe, and effective for enhancing musculoskeletal health and function, in postmenopausal women with low to very low bone mass. Similar claims have been made by the developers of the bioDensity system, designed around the premise that low volume machine-based isometric resistance training produces beneficial effects on balance, physical function, muscle strength and bone mass. Whether dynamic or isometric resistance training will be more effective in men over the age of 50 with reduced bone mass at the hip and spine remains to be seen. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.liftmor.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Registration for the study can be made on the trial website</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>170 Kessels Road Nathan, QLD 4111 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>AHS/07/14/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Belinda Beck</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Gold Coast campus
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport, Gold Coast,
Queensland, 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 8793</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5552 8674</fax>
      <email>b.beck@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Belinda Beck</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Gold Coast campus
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport, Gold Coast,
Queensland, 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 8793</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5552 8674</fax>
      <email>b.beck@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Belinda Beck</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Gold Coast campus
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport, Gold Coast,
Queensland, 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 8793</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5552 8674</fax>
      <email>b.beck@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Amy Harding</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Gold Coast campus
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport, Gold Coast,
Queensland, 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552 8793</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5552 8674</fax>
      <email>amy.harding@griffithuni.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>