<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362875">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000985886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>SOMNA: Sleep Or Mood Novel Adjunctive therapy. The effectiveness of an adjunctive internet Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT)  intervention for insomnia in older men with depression.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate whether a proven internet-delivered Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) treatment program for insomnia can improve the outcomes of standard treatment of depression in men.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-7321</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SOMNA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Insomnia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention of interest for this study is the adjunctive internet based insomnia treatment program - Sleep Healthy Using the Internet (SHUTi). SHUTi is an efficacious e-health Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for Insomnia (CBTi), which consists of six modules delivered over nine weeks. These address sleep behaviours, sleep beliefs and sleep hygiene in a structured interactive format. Completion of the six modules involves up to an hour per week over nine weeks.
  
All trial participants will also have their depression managed over the three months of the trial by the psychiatric team using standard guideline based depression treatments.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants assigned to the adjunctive control treatment will interact with the specially designed internet-based attention-control program comprising credible, but ineffective, sleep health information. Participants in this treatment arm will be free to use the program at their discretion over the nine week period.

All trial participants will also have their depression managed over the three months of the trial by the psychiatric team using standard guideline based depression treatments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in the severity of self reported depressive symptoms, as measured using the Centre for Epidemiological Studies Depression scale (CES-D) between baseline and week 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints where assessments will be made will be at baseline, weeks 4, 8 and 12.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in the severity of clinician rated depressive symtpoms as measured using the Hamilton Rating Depression Scale (HAM-D) between baseline and week 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints where assessment will be made will be at baseline and week 12.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in the severity of anxiety symptoms, as measured using the anxiety scale of the State Trait Personallity Inventory between baseline and week 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints where assessment will be made will be at baseline, week 12.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A change in the severity of insomnia symptoms, as measured using the Insomnia Severity Index rating scale between baseline and week 12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints where assessment will be made will be at baseline, weeks 4, 8 and 12.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants must meet the following inclusion criteria: (a) currently meet the criteria for at least minor depression (defined as screening positive (8+) on the Quick Inventory of Depression Symptomology (QIDS) and at clinical interview by having one of the two cardinal symptoms of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and at least two other symptoms of depression for two weeks or more (four symptoms minimum in total)); and (b) self report insomnia symptoms above the threshold (8+) Insomnia Severity Index (ISI).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We will exclude participants if: (a) they have a history of psychosis, or hypo/manic episodes; (b) have a current substance dependence; (c) have a score of &lt;24 on the Mini Mental State Examination; all as determined by the psychiatrist clinical interview; (d) are a rotating shift worker with overnight shifts or transmeridian travel &gt;2 hours in the past month with inadequate time to readjust prior to trial commencement; (e) have all the criteria for Restless Legs Syndrome as defined using the RLS-12 at screening; (f) are at high risk for obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) as defined by the Berlin Questionnaire or have been treated for OSA. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The trial will recruit men aged 50+ with current clinically significant depressive and insomnia symptoms from the BMRI Clinical Centre, local secondary and primary care providers, and potentially high yield community advertising (for example, Centrelink) and local newspapers. Participants will be automatically randomised upon completion of the online consent, eligibility screening, and baseline assessment phase. Allocation concealment will be achieved using a customised randomisation schedule. The fully itemised procedure allows for full replication and can accommodate stratification and specification of block sizes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised at the time of baseline assessment using a randomly generated number sequence allocated by a blinded researcher not involved in trial data gathering, assessments or treatment. Randomisation will be undertaken using permuted blocks and stratified by depressive symptom severity with strata defined by HAM-D scores of &lt; 17 or &gt;= 17. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The intervention is internet based.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/12/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>87</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brain and Mind Research Institute
100 Mallet St
Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue: the national depression and anxiety initiative</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Movember Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 60
East Melbourne VIC 8002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study investigates the efficacy of an internet-based insomnia treatment program (SHUTi), compared to an internet delivered control program, as an adjunctive treatment to beyondblue guideline based treatment for reducing depressive symptom severity amongst men aged 50 and over with co-morbid depression and insomnia symptoms. 

Secondary aims are to determine whether adjunctive SHUTi improves insomnia and anxiety symptoms.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.somna.com.au for trial entry and
www.sydney.edu.au/bmri for trial description</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building G02
The University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06-2012/14938</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Nicholas Glozier  </name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute
100 Mallett St
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0536</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.glozier@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amelia English</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute
100 Mallett St
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61291144213</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amelia.english@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amelia English</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute
100 Mallett St
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61391144213</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amelia.english@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Glozier</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Research Institute 100 Mallett St Camperdown NSW 2050  </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0536</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.glozier@sydney.edu.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>