<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320820">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000173099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does gabapentin reduce itch in children with acute severe burns? A prospective randomised double blinded controlled study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of two gabapentin doses with placebo for the management of itch in children with acute burns.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pruritus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acute burns in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Gabapentin oral, two dose regimens:
Group 1: oral gabapentin syrup 5mg/kg three times a day for 28 days.
Group 2: oral gabapentin syrup 10mg/kg three times a day for 28days.
Both groups and the control group will have access to rescue medication for peristent itch. The rescue medication reflects current clinical practice i.e. trimeprazine 0.5mg/kg oral up to every 8hours.
N.b. the study intervention tests a 'preventative action' on itch. Itch that occurs despite the study drug intervention will be managed according to a standard protocol i.e. a 'rescue protocol- given below.

Standardised management of itch in children with burns.

The management of itch will be standardised and include both non-pharmacological and pharmacological interventions. Non-pharmacological interventions include the use of pressure garments where appropriate, skin and scar lubrication if appropriate (healed burns or donor sites), soft tissue mobilisation or massage and play and distraction therapies. Pharmacological intervention will be standardised into three sequential tiers of rescue interventions reflecting current clinical practice. 


	
I) Itch score &gt; 2: Trimeprazine 0.5 mg/kg  orally tds for 48 hours.
II) Itch unresponsive to anti-histamine :Ondansetron 0.1 mg/kg orally or IV tds for 24 hours.
III) Persistent itch. Itch causing distress more than 72 hours after commencing anti-histamine: 	IV naloxone infusion. 0.5/micrograms/kg/hour for 12 hours.

Study drug treatment will continue for 28 days unless a side-effect or adverse event suspected to be related to the study drug is detected.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo:
oral syrup (identical flavouring and natural colour so as to be identical to intervention) administered three times a day for 28 days.
Both study groups and the control group will have access to rescue medication for peristent itch. The rescue medication reflects current clinical practice i.e. trimeprazine 0.5mg/kg oral up to every 8hours.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of itch during the last week of a four week treatment period.
Itch is present if 4 or more  itch scores (of the seven recorded scores)are greater than 3 in the last week of observation.
Itch will be measured using a 10 point visual analogue scale (0= 'no itch', and 10 = worst possible itch').</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once per day during the last week of a four week treatment period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average itch score over the entire four week treatment period.  Itch scores (either self-reported or reported by carers) will be documented in a diary supplied to all study recruits. Diary entries will be checked at weekly intervals through a phone interview and diaries will be collected for analysis at the end of the study period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Itch is assessed daily during the four week treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of conventional rescue anti-pruritic medication. (Total number of doses of trimeperazine oral syrup given during the 28 day study period.)
Rescue medication will be available as per current clinical practice for persistent itch with scores &gt;2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Total over 28 day study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental satisfaction- assessed through a 5 point scale (0= completely dissatisfied, 4= completely satisfied)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of 28 day study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reported itch severity at 3 months after discharge. Assessed on a 10 point visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 months after discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients admitted to a burns ward.
Admission within 14 days of an acute burn injury.
Parenteral opioids required for analgesia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Haemodynamic instability.
Previous or current treatment with gabapentin.
Receiveing Anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs).
Intubated and ventilated in a paediatric intensive care (PICU).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be identified by the primary investigators. Eligibility will be confirmed.
Following informed consent , a sealed opaque envelope containing an allocation code will be used. The hospital clinical trial pharmacist will hold the allocation schedule and will then dispense the study drug and maintain the blinding.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be by computerised sequence generation and will be stratified by age.
Randomisation will be completed in blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2145</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Children's Hospital at Westmead</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hawkesbury Road
Westmead 2145
NSW
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Hospital at Westmead</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hawkesbury Road
Westmead 2145
NSW
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Society of Paediatric Anaesthetists of New Zealand and Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>SPANZA secretariat
PO Box 180
Morisset
New South Wales   2264
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomised, placebo-controlled and blinded study aims to quantify the effect of regular oral gabapentin (28 day course) on the incidence and severity of pruritus in children with acute severe burns. Itch will be assessed using standardised age appropriate itch scales. The primary outcome measure will be the proportion of children who are itch free in the final week of a four week study period. Secondary outcomes will include the average severity of itch during the four week study period and the use of conventional rescue anti-pruritic medication. Other secondary outcomes include parental satisfaction and reported pruritus severity at 3months after discharge (obtained through a follow-up phone interview). 
Although not the primary focus of this study, the effect of gabapentin on pain scores and opioid requirements in these patients will be explored. 
The is a single-centre, investigator-driven study that will be conducted within the Burns Unit at the Childrens Hospital at Westmead, which is the referral centre for all children with burns in New South Wales. Modest financial support for this study has been obtained from the Society of Paediatric Anaesthetists of New Zealand and Australia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Road
Westmead  2145
NSW
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/01/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/CHW/152</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Andrew Weatherall</name>
      <address>c/o Dept of Anaesthesia
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Road
Westmead
NSW 2145
Australia</address>
      <phone>61 2 9845 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andreww9@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Andrew Weatherall</name>
      <address>c/o Dept of Anaesthesia
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Road
Westmead
NSW 2145
Australia</address>
      <phone>61 2 9845 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andreww9@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jonathan de Lima</name>
      <address>c/o Dept of Anaesthesia
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Road
Westmead
NSW 2145
Australia</address>
      <phone>61 2 9845 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jonathad@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>