<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369468">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001131549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Gastrointestinal Hypomotility Study: Studying how Intestinal Transit is affected by Clozapine
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An observational study: How does clozapine affect gastrointestinal transit (including gastric  emptying and small and large bowel transit) as measured by wireless motility capsule in clozapine-treated inpatients in a rehabilitation service compared with normative transit times.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-4923 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>clozapine-induced gastrointestinal hypomotility</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The exposure is clozapine treatment. The condition observed is gastrointestinal transit times (gastric emptying, small bowel transit, colon transit) as measured by wireless motility capsule (WMC). After fasting overnight, the participant consumes a small standardised meal (Smartbar) then  ingests a wireless motility capsule (Smartpill) which is equipped with temperature, pH, and pressure monitoring devices.  The participant wears a recording device. They do not eat over the next 6 hours to capture gastric emptying times. They then eat and drink as normally. Bowel motions are noted by the participant pressing an event button on the data recorder. The WMC will transit through the gastrointestinal tract relaying data telemetrically to the recorder. The WMC ends up being expelled in the faeces and is single use only. The data receiver will be worn for 96 hours post capsule ingestion. At t=96 we will check the data output to confirm whether the WMC has been expelled. If it is still recording, the participant will wear it for a further three days. The study will be terminated at t=168 hours</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group - transit times from the clozapine treated group will be compared with standardised population normative gastric emptying and small and large bowel transit times</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastric emptying time of clozapine-treated patients as determined by WMC  (compared with population normative values). Results will be considered statistically significant at p&lt;0.05</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time of WMC ingestion to the time the WMC enters the small intestine.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Small bowel transit time of clozapine-treated patients as determined by WMC (compared with population normative values). Results will be considered statistically significant at p&lt;0.05</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time the WMC enters the small intestine until the WMC enters the large intestine.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Large bowel transit times of clozapine-treated patients as determined by WMC (compared with population normative values). Results will be considered statistically significant at p&lt;0.05</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the time the WMC enters the large intestine until the time it is expelled.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective symptoms of constipation as assessed by Modified ROME III constipation criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5 of Wireless Motility capsule test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Competent and consenting adult (&gt;18) patients prescribed clozapine (any dose) residing in a specific New Zealand low-secure mixed rehabilitation facility</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not competent to consent 
Participant takes laxatives  and prefers to continue taking them during study period or their treating team has concerns about them having a laxative holiday (laxatives would cause spurious transit times)
Insulin dependent diabetics
History of:
(a) GI surgery in the last 3 months
(b) Crohns disease or diverticulitis 
(c) implanted electromechanical device (i.e a cardiac pacing device or cochlear implant) 
(d) gastric bezoar 
(e) swallowing disorder
(f) suspected or known stricture or fistula 
(g) physiological/ mechanical GI obstruction
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Downloaded data will be analysed using the display software (MotiliGI, SmartPill Corporation). 
The WMC software generates an automated report including regional transit, and the data will be manually read and interpreted by senior gastroenterologist. When there is disagreement between automated and manual reporting a third opinion will be sought from an independent expert.
Capsule ingestion will be identified from a sudden rise in temperature profile. 
Gastric emptying time (GET) will be identified as the time from ingestion of the WMC to the abrupt pH rise when the WMC leaves the acidic environment of the stomach for the alkaline duodenum. This rise will normally be &gt;3 pH units, but will be less marked for participants on proton pump inhibitors or H2 antagonists (approx 1 pH unit).
Small bowel transit time (SBTT) is defined as the time from capsule ingestion until the abrupt pH drop (&gt;1 pH unit), observed at least 30 min after GET and persisting for a minimum of 10 min, signifying entry into the caecum. 
Body exit time is identified as an acute temperature drop when the ambient temperature, rather than body temperature, is sensed. 
Colonic transit time (CTT) is defined as the time from the pH-defined entry of the WMC to the caecum until the temperature-defined body exit time.

The primary outcome variables are the various gastrointestinal transit times. Descriptive statistics (means with SDs, and plotted distributions of transit times) will provide data summaries for transit times. The estimated mean transit time will be compared with normative population data (using confidence intervals for the mean transit time). Comparison of subjective measures of constipation (using the purpose designed screening tool adapted from the Rome III criteria) will be compared between using the chi-squared test or Fisher's exact test (for comparison of categorical outcomes.) Linear regression will be used to examine the relationship between the outcome variable and other covariates such as age, gender, ethnicity and medication dose.

For colonic transit times, a-priori power analysis were conducted using data from a previous study measuring colonic transit times in clozapine-treated participants. In this previous research, clozapine treated participants had transit times four times longer that that of controls (Every-Palmer et al 2015, in progress). Mean colonic transit times in controls were 24.06 hours (CI 16.8-31.3) and in clozapine-treated participants were 100.6 hours (CI 82.1-119). At alpha=0.05 and beta =0.8, fewer than 6 participants are required to adequately power the study to detect this degree of difference in colonic transit times.

No previous research has looked at gastric or small bowel emptying in clozapine treated participants. However, if transit times were increased by a factor of 0.5, (e.g with normal GETs around 3.4 hours , +/- 1.5 hours (SD) increasing to 5.1hours in clozapine-treated participants) then at least 14 participants would be required to detect this degree of difference at alpha 0.05 and beta 0.8.

The target sample size is 20, to account for up to a 30% drop out rate.
 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>10/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Susanna Every-Palmer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington 6242
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Maurice and Phyllis Paykel Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 37 760 Parnell
Auckland 1151, New Zealand </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wellington Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 51 211
Wellington 
New Zealand
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Peter Ellis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington 6242
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Stephen Inns</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Medicine University of Otago, Wellington PO Box 7343
Newtown, Wellington
6242</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gastrointestinal hypomotility ("slow gut") caused by clozapine is common, important and poorly understood. It causes distress and even sudden death. It may affect more than half of clozapine treated patients, but there are no clinically reliable signs and symptoms to identify it. One in 500 clozapine treated patients die from drug足induced bowel obstruction.
Segmental gastrointestinal transit times (e.g. gastric and small bowel emptying) of clozapine treated patients have never been quantified.
This is an extension of  a previous study which used radiopaque markers to explore gastrointestinal transit time in clozapine treated patients. These results showed very abnormal bowel function, but data were crude and limited to the colon. This study involves similar methodology, but a more sensitive measurement technique 足-a wireless motility capsule足 -which will provide more data and add to the understanding of this problem.
Wireless motility capsules ('smartpills') are vitamin-足pill sized capsules. When swallowed they offer an ambulatory, safe, minimally invasive and validated assessment of intraluminal pH, temperature, and pressure during their transit through the gastrointestinal (GI) tract. There is no radiation exposure to the patient. This technology allows for accurate measurement of transit times in multiple regions of the upper and lower GI tract.  benefit them individually, as well as informing the evidence base.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/CEN/114</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susanna Every-Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6421767675</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susanna.every-palmer@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susanna Every-Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6421767675</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susanna.every-palmer@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susanna Every-Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6421767675</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susanna.every-palmer@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susanna Every-Palmer</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6421767675</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susanna.every-palmer@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>