<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343174">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000751976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective randomised controlled trial comparing the efficacy of laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass versus laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy for the management of type 2 diabetes mellitus in obese patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Type 2 diabetes remission in obese patients: A randomised controlled study of laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass versus laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Laparoscopic sleeve gastrectomy - resection of the greater curvature of the stomach from the distal antrum (3 cm proximal to pylorus) to the angle of His, using a laparoscopic stapling device over a 36Fr bougie, will be performed to create a lesser curve gastric sleeve. Approximate duration of procedure: 60-120 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2: Laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass - An isolated lesser curve-based gastric pouch will be created, with an antecolic antegastric Roux limb fashioned measuring 100 cm in length. The biliopancreatic limb will measure 50cm for all patients. A 6.5cm silastic ring will be placed above the gastrojejunostomy to prevent long term stomal dilatation. Approximate duration of procedure: 90-120 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Remission of Type 2 diabetes mellitus as follows:-

Complete remission = Fasting plasma glucose less than 5.6 mmol/L and glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) less than 6.0% in the absence of active pharmacologic therapy

Partial remission = Fasting plasma glucose between 5.6 and 6.9 mmol/L and glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) between 6.0 and 6.5% in the absence of active pharmacologic therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>At one year and five years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight change (excess weight loss and total body weight loss) including change in Body Mass Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year and five years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comorbidity resolution (measurement of changes in blood pressure, blood lipid profile, obstructive sleep apnoea symptoms and CPAP usage, urinary incontinence frequency, angina severity, reflux symptoms using Visick scale, medication changes)</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year and five years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peri and post-operative complications (e.g. haemorrhage, thromboembolic events, cardiorespiratory events, marginal ulceration, anastomotic / staple line leak, internal herniation, nutritional deficiencies) and mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>30-days after surgery

In-hospital - i.e. events occurring in hospital during 
the primary admission for surgery

One year and five years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in body composition, resting energy expenditure and bone density (using dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) scanning and bioimpedance measurement techniques).</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year and five years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (using Short from 36 and Hospital and Anxiety depression scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At three monthly time points during first year after surgery, six monthly during the second year, then yearly until five years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus for at least 6 months
-Previous failed attempts at weight loss through dieting and exercise
-BMI 35 - 65 kg/m2 for at least 5 years 
-Suitable for either of the two surgical procedures
-Able to give informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Type 1 diabetes mellitus
-Previous bariatric or oesophagogastric surgery
-Poorly controlled psychiatric disorder
-Myocardial infarction, heart bypass surgery or stroke within 6 months
-Malignancy in last 5 years
-Not suitable for general anaesthesia</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Surgeon assesses patient in the outpatient clinic to determine if a suitable candidate for either type of bariatric surgical procedure.

Allocation will be concealed using sealed opaque envelopes. The envelope will be opened in theatre once the patient is anaesthetised and the procedure will then be disclosed to the operating surgeon.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation with minimisation based on age (grouped as 20-30, 30-40, 40-50); time since diagnosis of T2DM (grouped as &lt;5yrs, 5-10yrs, &gt;10yrs) and ethnicity (grouped as Maori, Pacific, European or other). Randomisation will be computer generated with allocation concealment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>3/09/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>106</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Waitemata District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Shore Hospital
Shakespeare Road
Takapuna
Private Bag 93 503
Auckland 0740</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Waitemata District Health Board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Shore Hospital
Shakespeare Road
Takapuna
Private Bag 93 503
Auckland 0740</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 2 diabetes (T2DM) and obesity are becoming increasingly common in New Zealand (NZ) and worldwide. Both are associated with a risk of early mortality (death). Whilst weight loss surgery is known to be effective for weight loss, current research suggests that it may also be effective in resolving T2DM in around 60-80% of patients, with some no longer requiring their medication. The mechanism for this remains unclear.

Two main types of weight loss surgery are performed in NZ public hospitals, which include gastric bypass and sleeve gastrectomy. The gastric bypass is a more complex procedure compared to the sleeve gastrectomy. Whilst both appear to be effective for weight loss (with most patients losing more than 60% of their excess weight), it is still not known which one is better for treating T2DM.

This study will therefore compare which of these two surgical procedures is most effective at treating T2DM in obese patients, as well as comparing whether there are any differences in the amount of weight lost, side effects and quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Nil yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/O Ministry of Health, PO Box 1031, Hamilton 3240</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>NTY/11/07/082</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/07/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mr Michael Booth</name>
      <address>Consultant Laparoscopic Upper GI &amp; Bariatric Surgeon
Department of General Surgery
North Shore Hospital
Shakespeare Road, Private Bag 93 503
Takapuna
Auckland 0740</address>
      <phone>+64 9 486 8900 Ext 2459</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.booth@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mr Michael Booth</name>
      <address>Consultant Laparoscopic Upper GI &amp; Bariatric Surgeon
Department of General Surgery
North Shore Hospital
Shakespeare Road, Private Bag 93 503
Takapuna
Auckland 0740</address>
      <phone>+64 9 486 8900 Ext 2459</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.booth@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Michael Booth</name>
      <address>Consultant Laparoscopic Upper GI &amp; Bariatric Surgeon Department of General Surgery North Shore Hospital Shakespeare Road, Private Bag 93 503 Takapuna Auckland 0740 </address>
      <phone>+64 9 486 8900 Ext 2459   </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.booth@waitematadhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>