<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370990">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000897460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial to Examine the Effectiveness of Oxytocin to Improve Treatment for Anorexia Nervosa</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial to Examine the Effectiveness of Oxytocin to Improve Treatment for Anorexia Nervosa</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anorexia nervosa</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Daily dosing (28 days) of intra-nasal oxytocin (36 IU/day). Each dose session (one spray in each nostril, morning and night) will be monitored by a nurse using a dose diary and at the end of the trial the used vials will be collected and stored for future use to analyze unused contents (if necessary).</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo control, nasal spray without any active ingredients. Placebo contain the same contents as active sprays (distilled water, glycerol and sorbitol) without oxytocin.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of repeated dosing with IN-OT versus placebo in treating core eating disorder psychopathology change after 28 days of inpatient treatment. The Eating Disorders Examination, eating concern sub-scale will be used for this purpose (baseline vs day 28)</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of dosing, 28 days (4 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of the first (Day 1) and final daily dose of IN-OT (day 28, 4 weeks) in reducing food-related anxiety in response to a high-energy fun food snack via saliva tests of cortisol and State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (short-form) given before and after the fun food snack.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after the first dose of IN-OT (day 1) and end of treatment (day 28)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure body mass index (BMI) for weight gain over the treatment trial and follow-up period</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, day 28, one and six months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cognitive rigidity after the treatment period using the Wisconsin Card Sort task </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28 (end of daily oxytocin or placebo treatment) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cognitive rigidity using the Yale-Brown-Cornell Eating Disorder Scale (YBC-EDS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in core eating disorder psychopathology using the Eating Disorders Examination (EDE, version 17) which has sub-scales for weight concern, shape concern and eating restraint</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment (28 days, 4 weeks) and follow-up (6 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment utilization will be collected using a self-report questionnaire to assess GP visits, medical services and days spent in hospital before and after the intervention </outcome>
      <timepoint>prior 6 months and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Anorexia nervosa requiring treatment in hospital for re-feeding</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current mania, psychosis, acute suicidality or drug dependence,
severe medical comorbidity or major septal deviation to interfer with nasal delivery,
currently pregnant, or
Treated under the Mental health Act or Compulsory Treatment Orders (CTO)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Yes, sequence generated by independent researcher in sealed (opaque) envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods> Initially, chi-square tests for categorical variables and Students t-tests for continuous variables will be conducted at each time point to assess significant group differences. Mixed effects models are often preferred over more traditional approaches such as repeated measures ANOVA because of their ability to deal with missing values. All randomised patients will be analysed according to the intention-to-treat principle. Continuous outcome measures will be analysed using multivariate analysis of variance (ANOVA) mixed models with repeated measurements. This will include interaction analyses of time (T1, T2, and T3) and type of treatment (OT vs. placebo) in order to evaluate effects over time. 
From our pilot data we calculated Cohen's effect sizes for change in EDE global from baseline to week 6 to be 0.897. Using the standard power calculations of 80% power and alpha set at 0.05; the number required for a two-tailed test is 42 subjects (21 in each arm). Assuming 20% drop out, 50 subjects are required (25 in each arm) for the primary outcome variable. For the secondary outcomes we used the scores from the anorexia stages of change questionnaire to calculate effect sizes of 0.623; 84 subjects are needed (42 per group) or ~100 (50 in each arm) to accommodate for possible drop outs. Thus, the current study will plan to recruit a total of 120 subjects to ensure it is sufficiently powered for the planned analysis, we we are unsure how many will drop out at the 6 month follow-up.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/01/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>25</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Northside Clinic Private Hospital - Greenwich</hospital>
    <hospital>Wesley Hospital Ashfield - Ashfield</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - Greenwich</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>2131 - Ashfield</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Medical School, Charles Perkins Centre
John Hopkins Drive
Camperdown, NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke St
GPO BOX 1421, 
Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of this study is to investigate the efficacy of intra-nasal oxytocin (IN-OT) as a single dose and in repeated dosage as an adjunct to nutritional rehabilitation in anorexia nervosa. We specifically want to determine the effects of IN-OT on weight gain, food-related anxiety, eating behaviour, core psychopathology eating concern, weight concern, shape concern and eating restraint) and cognitive rigidity additional to the effect of weight gain over 28 days then to assess these effects at six months follow up along with changes in body mass index (BMI) and health service utilisation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This study was previously registered in 2015 (ISRCTN11108405). The trial in the United Kingdom was stopped before ethical approval was sought due to funding and governance problems between the UK and Australia. The study will now only recruit participants in Australia. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee (Royal Prince Alfred Hospital  Zone)(EC00113)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Research Ethics and Governance Office
Missenden Road
Camperdown, NSW, 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/RPAH/15, protocol number X15-0007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northside Group Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Northside Clinic
2 Greenwich Road
Greenwich, NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X-0007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Janice Russell</name>
      <address>Eating Disorders Unit
Northside Clinic
2 Greenwich Road
Greenwich, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+612 9433 3555</phone>
      <fax>+612 9433 3599</fax>
      <email>janice.russell@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Maguire</name>
      <address>Boden Institute, Charles Perkins Building
University of Sydney
Camperdown, 2006, NSW</address>
      <phone>+612 9515-1523</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.maguire@email.cs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Hunt</name>
      <address>Discipline of Psychiatry
University of Sydney and 
Concord Centre for Mental Health
Concord Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+612 9767-8978</phone>
      <fax>+612 9767-8989</fax>
      <email>glenn.hunt@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Hunt</name>
      <address>Discipline of Psychiatry
University of Sydney and 
Concord Centre for Mental Health
Concord Hospital
Hospital Rd, Concord, NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+612 9767-8978</phone>
      <fax>+612 9767-8989</fax>
      <email>glenn.hunt@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>