<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363839">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000295741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Healthy Body Vitamin Pack: A Randomised Controlled Trial assessing mood and behaviour in adults reporting feeling stressed in the workplace.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of Healthy Body Pack supplementation, relative to placebo, on mood and behaviour in adults reporting feeling stressed in the workplace.  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Workplace stress
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants are randomly allocated to receive one of two treatments to be consumed once daily with a meal for a period of 12 weeks:

A. Healthy Body Vitamin Pack (containing 2 x 600mg fish oil softgels and 1 x Basic One Iron free multivitamin and mineral oral tablet)

OR 

B. Placebo tablets (2 x softgels and 1 x oral tablet) matched for appearance and flavor.

Please note:

The daily dosage of 1 Basic One Iron free multivitamin and mineral oral tablet contains: 
Vitamin A (as natural beta carotene)	2,000IU
Vitamin C (ascorbic acid)	150mg
Vitamin D (cholecalciferol)	2,000IU
Vitamin E (as d-alpha tocopherol succinate)	200IU
Thiamine (Vitamin B1 as HCI)	1.5mg
Riboflavin (Vitamin B2)	2mg
Niacinamide (niacinamide/Vitamin B3)	20mg
Vitamin B6 (pyridoxine hydrochloride)	10mg
Folic Acid (Folate/Vitamin B9)	400mcg
Vitamin B12 (Cyanocobalamin)	400mcg
Pantothenic Acid (as calcium pantothenate)	10mg
Magnesium (as magnesium oxide)	200mg
Zinc (zinc oxide) 	15mg
Selenium (as selenium chelate)	100mcg
Chromium (as chromium amino acid chelate)	100mcg
Lycopene 	5mg

</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo tablets matched for appearance and taste, but does not contain any active ingredient.  </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Workplace stress (Occupational Stress Inventory Revised)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4, 8 and 12.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other Stress: Perceived Stress Scale

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood: Profile of Moods Questionnaire; Beck Depression Inventory
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health: General Health Questionnaire
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular parameters: Blood analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants who meet the following eligibility criteria will be recruited in the trial:
1. Healthy non-smoking males and females aged between 30 and 55 years.
2. Currently in full-time employment.
3. Are not heavy drinkers of alcohol (defined as greater than 14 standard drinks per week for women and 28
standard drinks per week for men).
4. No history of anxiety, depression, psychiatric disorders or epilepsy
5. No history of / do not currently suffer from heart disease or high blood pressure or diabetes.
6. Not taking any medication, herbal extracts, vitamin supplements or illicit drugs which might reasonably be
expected to interfere with cognition or mood for 4 weeks prior to (and duration of) study (such as
multivitamins, B vitamins, ginkgo biloba, antioxidants or other supplements).
7. Not taking any form of medication within 5 days of admission (except for prophylactic antibiotics, or other
routine medications to treat benign conditions, such as antibiotics to treat acne) and agree not to take any
medication throughout the study
8. No health conditions that would affect food metabolism including the following: food allergies, kidney
disease, liver disease and/or gastrointestinal diseases (e.g. Irritable bowel syndrome, coeliac disease, peptic
ulcers)
9. Not pregnant or breast feeding
10. Not allergic to gluten/wheat
11. Are willing and able to participate in all study requirements, treatment plan, have access to
completeonline measures, and other trial procedures according to the protocol.
12. Are willing to provide blood samples on the two prescribed visits in the testing phase.
13. Provide a personally signed and dated informed consent indicating that the participant has been
informed of all pertinent aspects of the trial.
14. Fluent in written and spoken English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants presenting with any of the following will not be included in the trial:
1. Cigarette smoker
2. Current heavy regular use of alcohol exceeding 14 standard drinks per week for women and 28 standard
drinks per week for men).
3. Diagnosis of Type 1 or Type 2 diabetes.
4. History of anxiety, depression, psychiatric disorders or epilepsy
5. History of / currently suffers from heart disease or high blood pressure.
6. Evidence or history of any clinically significant (in the judgment of the investigator) renal, endocrine,
pulmonary, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, psychiatric, neurological, within the last 5 years
7. Use of any over-the-counter herbal extracts, vitamin supplements and/or other dietary supplements which
might influence cognition or mood for four weeks prior to the practice day (such as multivitamins, B vitamins,
ginkgo biloba, antioxidants or other supplements).
8. Currently taking any illicit drugs and/or a history of substance abuse.
9. Health conditions that would affect food metabolism including the following: food allergies, kidney disease,
liver disease and/or gastrointestinal diseases (e.g. have Irritable bowel syndrome, coeliac disease, peptic
ulcers)
10. Pregnant or breast feeding
11. Not fluent in written or spoken English
12. Allergy to gluten/wheat
13. Are not willing to provide blood samples throughout the testing phases
14. Current participation in any other trials involving investigational or marketed products within 30 days prior
to the practice day.
15. History of head injury/stroke
16. Any clinically relevant abnormalities in a volunteers medical history, physical examination, or results of
laboratory tests.
17. Currently taking Warfarin
18. Are unable to participate in the treatment plan and other trial procedures according to the protocol</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through advertising in local newspapers and community bulletin boards. Participants will contact researchers where they will be screened for eligibility over the phone to ensure they are eligible to participate in the study. Participants will be randomly allocated to treatment A or B once allocated a trial participants number.

Randomisation of participants to treatment groups will be determined by random allocation. All participants will be assigned to treatment group A or B using a computer generated random number generator by a disinterested third party. Eligible, recruited participants will be assigned a participant number. The treatment number that has been placed next to the participant’s number will be the allocated treatment for that individual. Randomisation codes will be kept in a password protected computer file. 

Blinding will be achieved by enlisting a person outside of the project to code the treatments, conceal them in sealed opaque containers for dispensing and maintain the key to this code until data collection is completed. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be achieved through the use of computerised random number generator software.   </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swinburne University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>John Street, Hawthorn, Victoria, 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cooper Concepts</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>12200 Preston Road
Dallas, TX, 75230, USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Given the range of observed (randomised controlled trials) and purported (anecdotal and epidemiological evidence) effects of both multivitamin and Omega-3 supplementation has upon mood and behaviour the general aim of the study is to investigate the combined effects of Omega-3 and multivitamin supplementation. The study will focus on the effects on mood, workplace stress and cardiovascular health in a workplace sample. 

More specifically, a three month supplementation with Healthy Body Vitamin Pack is expected to improve the experience of workplace stress, workplace variables, cardiovascular risk parameters and mood in conjunction with an improvement in biological measures such as antioxidant status and triglycerides. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>John Street, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Con Stough</name>
      <address>PO Box 218 
Mail H24
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+613 9214 8167</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cstough@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Antionette Goh</name>
      <address>PO Box 218 
Mail H24
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+613 9214 5094</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>agoh@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luke Downey</name>
      <address>PO Box 218 
Mail H24
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+613 9214 5781</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ldowney@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Justine Lomas</name>
      <address>PO Box 218 
Mail H99
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+613 9214 4923</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jlomas@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>