<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372164">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000091303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validation of the 2-minute step test in healthy middle-aged adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Sub-maximal assessment of aerobic capacity using the  2-minute step test in healthy middle-aged adults: a validation study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1191-6225</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Aerobic capacity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Design
This is a criterion validity study to be conducted at the University of Canberra. Following recruitment of eligible healthy middle-aged adults during January  April 2017, the participants will be required to take part in a submaximal fitness test (2 minute step test (2-MST)) and a peak incremental cycle fitness test to assess peak oxygen consumption (VO2peak; criterion measure) in May 2017. Participants will be required to complete the fitness tests on one day, with an adequate rest (heart rate returned to resting level) in between tests to minimise fatigue. The 2-MST will be completed first, followed by the peak incremental cycle test on the same day.

2 minute step test
The 2-MST requires little space and equipment, with large studies finding it both reliable and valid in older adults. The 2-MST protocol involves determining the number of times in 2 minutes that a person can step in place raising the knees to a height halfway between the patella (kneecap) and iliac crest (front hip bone), a continuous measurement. Two trials will be administered (practice test followed by the official test) by a physiotherapist, allowing an adequate rest (heart rate returned to resting level) between tests to minimise fatigue. Outcome measure is the number of steps completed by the right leg in 2 minutes. Manual heart rate taken for 15 seconds will also be taken at the end of the 2-MST to calculate heart rate in beats per minute. To improve the validity of taking manual heart rate following the 2MST, a heart rate monitor will also be used, and these two measures will be compared to determine the accuracy of the manual heart rate.

Peak cycle fitness test (GXT)
Direct measurement of aerobic fitness (VO2peak) will be measured on a stationary bicycle by an exercise physiologist. An incremental test will be carried out where participants will begin cycling at an easy level and additional resistance will be applied each minute. The participants will be fitted with a facemask (V2 Mask, Hans-Rudolph, Inc., United States of America) to enable the analysis of expired gases. Participants will also have an ECG attached so their heart rate can be monitored throughout the test. This test will take approximately 5-10 minutes.

Other outcome measures are:
* a questionnaire describing their physical activity over the last 7 days (Active Australia Survey),
* blood pressure measured via a sphygmomanometer,
* waist and hip measurements using a tape measure,
* height and weight measures, using a stadiometer and weight scales.</interventions>
    <comparator>Peak cycle fitness test.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2-minute step test number of steps.</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2017. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak oxygen consumption from the incremental peak cycle fitness test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2017.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity using the Active Australia Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2017.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure using a mercury sphygmomanometer,</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2017.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist and hip measurements using a tape measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2017.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Height and weight measures, using a stadiometer and weight scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2017.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate at rest and at the end (first 15 seconds following completion of the 2-minute step test) of the 2-minute step test taken manually and using a heart rate monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2017.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:
1. Between 40 and 60 years old. 
2. They will have no serious medical conditions that could limit participation in either fitness test, such as unstable angina, uncontrolled hypertension, diagnosed or hospitalized with chest pain, heart attack or heart surgery in the past 6 months and no severe functional impairments due to multiple medical or psychiatric diseases. 
3. Participants will have adequate English skills and have appropriate cognitive skills to provide informed consent and follow instructions for the fitness tests.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria
Medical clearance screening will be undertaken using the Sports Medicine Australia (SMA) Pre-Exercise Screening System. If the participant answers yes to any of the SMA screening questions, they will be asked to attend their local medical officer to receive medical clearance before they can be included in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis
The number of steps completed by the right leg in the 2MST will be compared to the directly measured VO2peak (peak cycle test) to determine its validity.
The strength of the relationship between the tests will be assessed using the Pearson correlation coefficient. A Bland-Altman plot will be used to assess the agreement between the tests.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Nicole Freene</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
 Bruce ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Kellie Toohey</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Exercise and Sports Science
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Evidence suggests that poor cardiorespiratory (CR) fitness is associated with increased risk of morbidity and mortality, and is therefore used as a measure of health. Submaximal exercise testing is commonly used in practice to assess CR fitness due to time constraints, lack of equipment and safety. Submaximal step tests have been shown to be valid method of assessing CR fitness (Bennett et al 2016), although the majority of these tests require a step and are externally paced. The 2-minute step test (2MST) requires minimal equipment (no step) and is self-paced. It has been shown to be reliable and valid in an older population (60+ years old) (Rikli and Jones 1999). If the 2MST is found to be valid in a wider age range, it may be a simpler method of assessing CR fitness that can be used in a variety of settings, potentially preventing a decline in health and physical fitness in the population. Here we will compare the number of steps completed in the 2MST in middle-aged adults to a direct measure of peak oxygen consumption (cardiorespiratory fitness) using an incremental cycle test. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Canberra's Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services Office
Building 1 Level D Room 88
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 16-212</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicole Freene</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health
University of Canberra
Bruce ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6201 5550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.freene@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>