<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364943">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001015730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Voice disorders in very preterm children: incidence, presentation and influencing factors.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Voice disorders in very preterm children: an observational study of voice quality at school age, analysis of associated factors from retrospective chart review and investigation into laryngeal pathology of children with moderate to severe voice difficulties.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysphonia.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Laryngeal abnormalities.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intubation injury.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hyperfunctional voice use.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Very preterm birth.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase I Clinical Voice Assessment: the voice quality of 200 very preterm children with dysphonia will be clinically assessed at a single timepoint at school age. Clinical assessment will consist of an acoustic analysis of voice quality, perceptual ratings of voice quality, a quality-of-life questionnaire to be completed by a caregiver and a self-report questionnaire to be completed by the child. This assessment will take between 30 and 45 minutes, depending on the clinical presentation and discussion.

A number of medical variables will be determined via retrospective chart review. These include: birthweight, gestational age, frequency of intubation, duration of intubation and tube size to body weight ratio.

Phase II Fibreoptic Endoscopic Evaluation of Laryngeal Function: participants presenting with moderate to severe dysphonia will be offered a fibreoptic endoscopic evaluation of laryngeal function at a single time point. This evaluation will take approximately 30 minutes in total.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Voice quality, as measured by the severity score on the Consensus Auditory Perceptual Evaluation of Voice scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On clinical voice assessment in Phase I, immediately after recruitment to the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The presence of voice disturbance, defined as a score of 3.46 or above on the Acoustic Voice Quality Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On clinical voice assessment in Phase I, immediately after recruitment to the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence and severity of laryngeal pathology, as measured using the Stroboscopy Evaluation Rating Form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of clinical voice assessment in Phase I - Clinical Voice Assessment, on recruitment into Phase II - Fibreoptic Endoscopic Evaluation of Laryngeal Function.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Voice-related quality of life restriction, as measured by the Pediatric Voice Handicap Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On clinical voice assessment in Phase I, immediately after recruitment to the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between medical variables with the presence and severity of dysphonia: birthweight, gestational age, number of intubations, frequency of intubation, duration of intubation and tube size to body weight ratio.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After clinical voice assessment, prior to recruitment to Phase II (if applicable).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Birth at less than 32 weeks gestation and admitted to the NICU at a single tertiary centre at birth.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known disability likely to preclude compliance with assessment tasks.
Residence &gt;200km from the study centre.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/11/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>198</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women and Infant's Research Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/O Carson House
Bagot Road
SUBIACO  WA  6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telethon Trust, administered by the Women and Infant's Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>C/O Carson House
Bagot Road
SUBIACO  WA  6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Greater numbers of children now survive preterm birth. Dysphonia is a newly-recognised long-term complication of extremely preterm birth, yet remains a relatively little-researched entity. Voice outcomes have been associated with gestational age, birthweight and cardiac surgery. However, the strongest association found has been with intubation in the neonatal period. Thus, there is a need to investigate voice quality of all who may be intubated.

Laryngeal pathology of very preterm children has not been systematically documented in the literature. Yet knowledge of laryngeal pathology is essential for intervention planning. Laryngeal pathology is investigated jointly by the Ear, Nose and Throat medical speciality and the Speech Pathology Voice allied health speciality. 

Further, there has been no investigation of treatment effects in preterm voice disorders. Having identified that dysphonia is a long-term voice outcome for some preterm children, treatment options should be investigated.

Finally, many preterm children participate in paediatrician follow-up programmes to maximise medical and developmental outcomes. As dysphonia can now be considered a possible long-term complication for some preterm children, a screening tool for voice difficulties could be incorporated into existing follow-up programmes. The ideal measure would have: i) diagnostic accuracy to correctly identify the presence of dysphonia; ii) sensitivity to change in voice quality due to therapy; and iii) be quick and simple to administer to minimise cost.

This study consists of three phases: an observational study of voice quality and its impact on quality of life in 200 children born at less than 32 weeks gestation; assessment of the nature and extent of laryngeal pathology visualised in those children with moderate to severe dysphonia; and a quasi-randomised, non-blinded, controlled trial of behavioural voice therapy in the children with moderate to severe dysphonia.  Additionally, the sensitivity to therapeutic change of an objective voice assessment, the Acoustic Voice Quality Index, validated by our laboratory as a measure of dysphonia severity in children, is being measured. 

This registration pertains to phases I and II of the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road
SUBIACO WA  6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1995EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Australia Human Research Ethics Office</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Western Australia
Hackett Drive
CRAWLEY  WA  6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/5633</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Noel French</name>
      <address>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Rd
SUBIACO WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 1260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>noel.french@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Victoria Reynolds</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Paediatrics and Child Health
M561
Hackett Drive
Crawley WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 438 749 005</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>victoria.reynolds@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Victoria Reynolds</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Paediatrics and Child Health
M561
Hackett Drive
Crawley WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 438 749 005</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>victoria.reynolds@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>