<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369093">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000878572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy of the application of Self-Determination Theory to an online cognitive rehabilitation intervention in remediating cognitive dysfunction associated with cancer and its treatment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized controlled trial comparing a web-based version of the Responding to Cognitive Concerns (ReCog) cognitive-behavioural intervention to waitlist for subjective and objective cognitive functioning in cancer survivors.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-0618</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Online ReCog RCT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive dysfunction associated with cancer and treatment.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The online version of "ReCog" was adapted from the face-to-face manualized intervention that is based on principles of cognitive behavioral therapy and cognitive rehabilitation. The online intervention is comprised of 4 modules that offer education, skills training and skills practice on topics such as memory, attention, fatigue, and emotions, as well as between-session homework. The intervention is designed to be completed on a laptop or desktop computer remotely (e.g., at home) via the internet. Each module takes approximately 60 minutes to complete, and should be completed in one sitting. Participants are expected to complete one module per week, and thus are given 4 weeks access to complete all 4 modules. Each module involves education and skills training (e.g. goal-setting, problem solving, relaxation training). Participants are then expected to practice these skills for homework each week by keeping record of their practice habits and their implementation of their learnt skills. This should take approximately 30-60 minutes per week. Treatment adherence is monitored through response submissions during completion of the online modules, and participant feedback about homework completion. </interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control. Participants who are randomly assigned to the waitlist group are offered intervention after all assessments are completed (4.5 months after initial assessment). Waitlist participants are able to access standard medical and health treatments, with no specific restrictions other than not participating in the online ReCog intervention until after assessments are completed.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective cognitive function assessed by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy Cognitive Function 3 (FACT-Cog-3), and the Brief Assessment of Prospective Memory (BAPM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline) and follow-up (3 months after intervention completion).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective cognitive function assessed by a series of 13 neuropsychological tests using the WebNeuro online program. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (3 months after intervention).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distress assessed by the Kessler Psychological Distress scale (K10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (3 months after intervention completion).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, as measured by the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire version 3 (EORTC-QLQ-C30).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (3 months after intervention completion).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Illness perceptions, as assessed by the Brief Illness Perceptions Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (3 months after intervention completion).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of Autonomy, as measured by the Basic Psychological Needs Scale (BPNS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 weeks after baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (3 months after intervention completion).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of Competence, as measured by the Basic Psychological Needs Scale (BPNS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 weeks after baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (3 months after intervention completion).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of Relatedness, as measured by the Basic Psychological Needs Scale (BPNS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 weeks after baseline, post-intervention (6 weeks after baseline), and follow-up (3 months after intervention completion).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults aged 18 or more; experienced adult-onset cancer (excluding cancer known to have affected the central nervous system); completed all major treatments for cancer (e.g., surgery, chemotherapy, and radiotherapy) at least 6 months prior to data collection (but ongoing hormone treatments are acceptable);subjective complaints of cognitive impairment; access to a laptop/desktop computer with a mouse and reliable internet services.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Cancer involving the central nervous system (primary or secondary tumors); previous treatment with cranial radiotherapy or intrathecal chemotherapy; current cancer diagnosis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants volunteer by contacting the research team. Sealed opaque envelopes will be prepared by a researcher who is not connected to the research project.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization using a randomization table from a statistics book.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Random allocation of cancer survivors to either immediate Intervention or Waitlist (delayed access to intervention).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of a minimum 20 participants per group (40 total) is planned based on previous data showing effect sizes in the approximate range Cohen's d=0.5 to d=1.0. This would provide power of more than 80% at alpha level = .05, for detecting a Group x Time interaction. Analysis plan: Group x Time repeated measures ANOVAs. The target sample size of 40 participants per group (80 total) was decided to account for anticipated drop out rates.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gold Coast Campus, Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport, Qld 4222</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Griffith University
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gold Coast Campus, Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport, Qld 4222
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Council Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 201
Spring Hill, Qld 4004

553 Gregory Terrace 
Fortitude Valley, Qld 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cancer Council Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 201 
Spring Hill, Qld 4004

553 Gregory Terrace 
Fortitude Valley, Qld 4006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to determine whether a web-based version of the ReCog program has a greater impact on cognitive function and other wellness measures than standard care in cancer survivors. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 or over, have experienced adult-onset cancer of any type other than a cancer affecting the central nervous system, have completed treatment at least 6 months ago (and not more than 5 years ago) and have complaints of cognitive function. 

Study details:
On enrolling in this study, participants will be allocated to one of two groups. The first group will receive access to the ReCog online program. You will be required to complete 4 modules, each lasting approximately 60 minutes, plus weekly homework activities taking approximately 30-60 minutes each. Activities will include relaxation training, goal-setting, problem-solving and the learning of new strategies to improve areas of cognitive function, such as memory, fatigue, attention and emotions. Participants will have 4 weeks to complete the modules, and are expected to complete one module per week. The second group will have access to the ReCog program 4.5 months after group 1. All participants will be asked to fill out a series of questionnaires at four timepoints up to 3 months after the end of the intervention period. 

It is hoped that the findings of this trial will establish the efficacy of the web-based ReCog program to aid cognitive function in cancer survivors.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.recogintervention.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus
Parklands Drive
Southport, Qld 4222</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PSY/F4/14/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mary Mihuta</name>
      <address>Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus
School of Applied Psychology
Parklands Drive
Southport, Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 435 040 507</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mary.mihuta@griffithuni.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heather Green</name>
      <address>Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus
School of Applied Psychology
Parklands Drive
Southport, Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 5678 9086</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.green@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heather Green</name>
      <address>Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus
School of Applied Psychology
Parklands Drive
Southport, Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 5678 9086</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.green@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mary Mihuta</name>
      <address>Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus
School of Applied Psychology
Parklands Drive
Southport, Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 435 040 507</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mary.mihuta@griffithuni.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>