<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372476">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000610336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Baby-Directed Umbilical Cord Clamping Feasibility Study: The Baby-DUCC Feasibility Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Baby-Directed Umbilical Cord Clamping Feasibility Study: The Baby-DUCC Feasibility Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Baby-DUCC Feasibility Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neonatal resuscitation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Umbilical cord management</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The purpose of this non-randomized feasibility study is to gain experience providing baby-directed umbilical cord clamping (BABY-DUCC) in newborn infants, born at 28 weeks or later, immediately after birth. BABY-DUCC is delaying umbilical cord clamping after birth to maintain placental circulation and gas exchange and provide respiratory support (if indicated) until lung aeration and pulmonary gas exchange has begun indicating successful neonatal adaption after delivery.

This will be a single centre non-randomized feasibility study in babies born at a gestational age 28 weeks or greater at the Royal Womens Hospital. We plan to provide respiratory support to the newborn infant with the umbilical cord intact. The umbilical cord will then be clamped after physiologic changes indicating a successful neonatal adaption has begun, based on end tidal carbon dioxide monitoring. Specifically, umbilical cord clamping will be delayed for 60 seconds after the newborns end-tidal carbon dioxide is measured at &gt;15 mmHg. If the infant requires no respiratory support and is breathing/crying well, cord clamping will occur as early as 2 minutes. The maximum time of delayed umbilical cord clamping will be 5 minutes after birth. 

The clinical team in charge of the care for the baby will use a portable BABY-DUCC warming mattress allowing the evaluation and initiation of respiratory support to occur next to the mother. Specifically, the portable BABY-DUCC warming mattress will be equipped to provide heat to the newborn (chemical heating packs or electric warming mattress) and we will have a dedicated study respiratory support pole with the ability to provide blended oxygen, CPAP, positive pressure ventilation, heated and humidified gas, and suction. We will monitor and record end tidal carbon dioxide, tidal volume, pulse, and saturation of peripheral oxygenation using the NM3 Respiratory Profile Monitor (Phillips Healthcare, Massachusetts, USA), heart rate via electrocardiographic electrodes or portable ultrasound machine (GE Venue 50, Illinois, USA), and a high definition audio/video recording of the events (GoPro Hero3, California, USA). All physiologic information will be converted from analog to digital signal and recorded at 100 Hz using a custom built software program called the BABY-DUCC Data Acquisition System by the Royal Womens Biomedical Engineering department which presents the data in graphical and table form for analysis.

In addition to the standard medical staff attending the deliveries, two dedicated members of the research team will be present at each delivery to review the study protocol with all the clinical staff in the delivery room (including staff looking after the mother), confirm with the clinical teams that there are no increased risks to the mothers or babys health that would preclude attempting the BABY-DUCC protocol, set up the study materials, and carry out the study protocol. Apart from initiating respiratory support, if needed, prior to umbilical cord clamping, babies will be supported according to the Australian/RWH Neonatal Resuscitation guidelines. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>None, feasibility trial.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if it is feasible to perform baby-directed umbilical cord clamping (BABY-DUCC) or providing respiratory support with an intact placental circulation and clamping the umbilical cord after successful neonatal adaption has begun in babies born at 28 weeks or greater gestational age. 

Feasibility will be assessed by compliance with protocol and assessment of physiologic measurements made during the study period (HR, SpO2, respiratory status, APGAR scores, maternal bleeding including quantification of post partum blood loss and the need for treatment for PPH), and maternal complications, such as infection. We will also debrief with the maternal and neonatal treatment teams to assess for any additional issues. Physiologic measurements will be made by pulse oximetry, ECG electrodes, bedside ultrasound machine, written records by the clinical and research teams (including medical records prior to discharge), and video review where available. </outcome>
      <timepoint>In the first 5 minutes after delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) To study the safety of baby-directed umbilical cord clamping on infants born at 28 weeks or greater gestational age. specifically reviewing available medical records for evidence of neonatal infection, maternal infection, temperature on admission to the NICU, haematocrit levels, number of transfusions, bilirubin levels, treatment for jaundice and polycythaemia, feeding issues, necrotising enterocolitis, intraventricular haemorrhage, echocardiography results, need for inotropic support, intubations, days of mechanical ventilation, or other relevant morbidities. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to discharge from the hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) To study the feasibility of the BABY-DUCC protocol (including video review when available).

Feasibility will be assessed by compliance with protocol and assessment of physiologic measurements made during the study period (HR, SpO2, respiratory status, APGAR scores, maternal bleeding including quantification of post partum blood loss and the need for treatment for PPH), and maternal complications, such as infection. We will also debrief with the maternal and neonatal treatment teams to assess for any additional issues. Physiologic measurements will be made by respiratory function monitor, pulse oximetry, ECG electrodes, bedside ultrasound machine, written records by the clinical and research teams (including medical records prior to discharge), and video review where available. </outcome>
      <timepoint>In the first minutes after birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3) To determine if it is feasible to measure and record an accurate HR (via ECG electrodes or portable ultrasound) in babies receiving BABY-DUCC prior to umbilical cord clamping. 

Feasibility will be assessed by compliance with protocol and assessment of physiologic measurements made during the study period (EtCO2, tidal volume, HR, SpO2, respiratory status, APGAR scores, maternal bleeding including quantification of post partum blood loss and the need for treatment for PPH), and maternal complications, such as infection. We will also debrief with the maternal and neonatal treatment teams to assess for any additional issues. Physiologic measurements will be made by respiratory function monitor, pulse oximetry, ECG electrodes, bedside ultrasound machine, written records by the clinical and research teams (including medical records prior to discharge), and video review where available. </outcome>
      <timepoint>In the delivery room</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4) To observe the HR of apnoeic newborns with intact placental circulation. HR monitored via pulse oximetry, ECG, or portable ultrasound. Respiratory status monitored with video recording and respiratory function monitor as available.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous monitoring in the delivery room for at least 5 minutes after birth if no respiratory support is needed after birth and at least 10 minutes after birth if any respiratory support is needed after birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5) To measure saturation of peripheral oxygen in babies receiving respiratory support with an intact umbilical cord assessed via pulse oximeter. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous monitoring in the delivery room for at least 5 minutes after birth if no respiratory support is needed after birth and at least 10 minutes after birth if any respiratory support is needed after birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6) To describe umbilical cord arterial and venous blood gas results in babies receiving BABY-DUCC. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Umbilical arterial and venous blood gases will be obtained within 15 minutes of delivering the placenta after birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inborn babies born at greater or equal to 28 weeks gestation are eligible for this study. The research team will obtain permission to approach the expecting family from the treating maternal clinicians (e.g. midwife, obstetrician, and anaesthesiologist) responsible for the care of the expecting mother. Antenatal consent will then be sought and obtained from the parents prior to enrolment. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Hours</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants will be excluded from analysis if they have a known congenital abnormality compromising cardiorespiratory function including congenital diaphragmatic hernia, hydrops fetalis, cyanotic congenital heart disease, and airway anomalies compromising mask ventilation. Infants who are not medicare eligible will be excluded. 

If the maternal treatment team feels that the mother is at high risk for obstetric complications that may be exacerbated by the study intervention prior to delivery or during the study intervention, the study intervention will be immediately discontinued, the umbilical cord will be clamped and the baby will be moved to the standard radiant warmer bed. Neonatal support will be continued according to the Australian/RWH Neonatal Resuscitation guidelines. Potential maternal obstetric complications that may be criteria for exclusion from the study at the discretion of the maternal care team include abnormal placentation, suspected placental abruption, suspected uterine rupture, significant antenatal blood loss, coagulopathy, and previous history of significant blood loss. 

In the event of dichorionic diamnionic twins the research team may enrol the presenting twin at the discretion of the maternal care team. The second twin will not be enrolled because of the increased risk of post-partum haemorrhage. Monochorionic twins will be excluded. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>None</concealment>
    <sequence>None</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Infants will be recruited over a period of 12 months. Approximately another 3 months will be required to collect hospital data on all infants enrolled. Medical data on each infant will be collected on Case Report Forms (Patient Data Form, Baby-Directed Umbilical Cord Clamping Feasibility Study). Non-identifiable study numbers will be assigned to each patient. De-identified information will be collected via the BABY-DUCC Data Acquisition System and audio, video recordings. Non-identifiable information will then be entered into an excel database for analysis. Non-identifiable patient information will be maintained in a password protected computer, which will be stored in a locked office in accordance with RWH R&amp;E standards. 

The primary objective for this study to determine if baby-directed umbilical cord clamping (clamping the umbilical cord after successful neonatal adaption has begun) is feasible and safe. The study is descriptive in nature. We plan on describing the neonatal transition of the infants in this study based on our physiologic monitoring, including measuring heart rate, saturation of peripheral oxygen, end-tidal carbon dioxide, tidal volume in the first minutes of life. We plan to record the respiratory effort of the infant, when the end-tidal CO2 goal is reached, when the umbilical cord is clamped, and describe the changes in the HR, SpO2, ECO2, and tidal volume after umbilical cord clamping. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Douglas Blank</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health And Medical Research Council Program Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Women's Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Peter Davis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Omar Kamlin</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Jennifer Dawson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sue Jacobs</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Marta Thio</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Kevyn Nyland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Stefan Kane</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alicia Dennis</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Graeme Polglase</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Ritchie Centre, The Hudson Institute
Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash University
27-31 Wright Street
Clayton, VIC 3168
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Stuart Hooper</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Ritchie Centre, The Hudson Institute
Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash University
27-31 Wright Street
Clayton, VIC 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Using the PICO format (participants, intervention, comparison, outcome):

P: In babies greater than or equal to 28 weeks gestational age at birth
I: can umbilical cord clamping be delayed for 60 seconds after newborn end-tidal carbon dioxide levels exceed &gt;15 mmHg (baby-directed umbilical cord clamping)?
C: no comparator
O: The primary outcome is adherence to study protocol and evaluation of protocol safety.

The purpose of this non-randomized feasibility study is to gain experience providing baby-directed umbilical cord clamping (BABY-DUCC) in newborn infants born at 28 weeks or later immediately after birth. BABY-DUCC is delaying umbilical cord clamping after birth to maintain placental circulation and gas exchange and provide respiratory support (if indicated) until lung aeration and pulmonary gas exchange has begun indicating successful neonatal adaption after delivery.

This will be a single centre non-randomized feasibility study in babies born at a gestational age of 28 weeks or later at the Royal Womens Hospital. We plan to provide respiratory support to the newborn infant with the umbilical cord intact. The umbilical cord will then be clamped after physiologic changes indicating a successful neonatal adaption has begun, based on end tidal carbon dioxide monitoring. Specifically, umbilical cord clamping will be delayed for 60 seconds after the newborns end-tidal carbon dioxide is measured at &gt;15 mmHg. 

The clinical team in charge of the care for the baby will use a portable BABY-DUCC warming mattress allowing the evaluation and initiation of respiratory support to occur next to the mother. Specifically, the portable BABY-DUCC warming mattress will be equipped to provide heat to the newborn (chemical heating packs or electric warming mattress) and a dedicated study respiratory support pole with the ability to provide blended oxygen, CPAP, positive pressure ventilation, heated and humidified gas, and suction. We will monitor and record end tidal carbon dioxide, tidal volume, pulse, and saturation of peripheral oxygenation using the NM3 Respiratory Monitor, heart rate via electrocardiographic electrodes or portable ultrasound machine, and a high definition audio/video recording of the events. All physiologic information will be converted from analog to digital signal and recorded at 100 Hz using a custom built software program called the BABY-DUCC Data Acquisition System which presents the data in graphical and table form for analysis.

In addition to the standard medical staff attending the deliveries, two dedicated members of the research team will be present at each delivery to review the study protocol with all the clinical staff in the delivery room (including staff looking after the mother), confirm with the clinical teams that there are no increased risks to the mothers or babys health that would preclude attempting the BABY-DUCC protocol, set up the study materials, and carry out the study protocol. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Women's Hospital Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Women's Hospital
Newborn Research
Locked Bag 300
Cnr of Grattan Street and Flemington Road 
Parkville, VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/34</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Blank</name>
      <address>The Royal Women's Hospital
Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road
Locked Bag 300
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61422305487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>douglas.blank@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>