<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372411">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000396325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Personalised Health Care Proof of Concept Pilot to test the intervention of home health monitoring in supporting the self management needs of participants with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) and Diabetes </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Personalised Health Care- efficacy of home health monitoring intervention in supporting the self management needs of participants with COPD and Diabetes: proof of concept study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PHCPCPS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Airways Disease </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is an additional monitoring service on top of patients "usual care".
There are three core aspects to the intervention
*patients submitting data on a daily basis
* Clinical staff to provide support for patients to self-manage  accessible seven days a week twenty four hours a day
* Individualised care plans
 Participants are requested to enter their bio metric data on a daily basis for the duration of the trial. Participants are also requested to answer a series of questions specifically designed to support the development of their health literacy about their condition (COPD and or Diabetes).  
Daily nurse monitored tele-health is facilitated by a fit for purpose IT system was purchased to facilitate the pilot. The name of the IT system is Remote Patient Monitoring (RPM) from a Canadian telco Telus. The IT platform allows for the data that is submitted by patients to be sorted by the system and only data that is outside of usual for that particular patient is flagged for follow up by the nurses. The communication between the patient and nurse is then facilitated by video conferencing using the systems supplied to participants. The nurse or patient can instigate a phone call. The communication supports the immediate needs of the patient, for example the need to address a low blood sugar. The less immediate needs are also supported in planning for better management of chronic disease eg. early presentation to General practitioners based on early symptom identification. These phone/Video Conferencing sessions can take anywhere from 2minutes to 20 minutes depending on the need of the patient.
Personalized care plans are developed. The care plans are designed in collaboration with the patient by the nurse on admission and altered as required during the intervention with the patient depending on their personal (SMART) goals. The individualised plans are achieved in three ways
*	By selecting protocols which are designed by Barwon Health and instigate the questions asked of and the information delivered to patients within the IT system. The question sets are designed to enhance health literacy and provide support for early identification of symptoms and in some cases simplified management of these symptoms. For example a foot care protocol for diabetics is available but not necessary for those patients with only COPD. There are approximately 20 protocols to select from. Some of the protocols include hemodynamic measurements, BP, pulse, blood oxygen, Blood sugar levels, temperature, COPD symptom protocols, quit smoking protocols, Keytone protocols, anxiety and depression screening protocols, Medication protocols, pedometer protocols. 
*	Parameters for the data entered can be altered for patients depending on what is normal for them. For example a patient with COPD might have a usual oxycimitery measurement of 88% and this can be modified from the usual measure in the system of 94%. The other variables that can be altered are Blood Pressure, pulse, weight, blood sugar readings, temperature. All modifications to hemodynamic parameters are agreed to and signed off by senior consultants supporting the program, an Endocrinologist and Respiratory specialist. 
*	On a fortnightly basis the patients are requested to schedule a meeting time with the nurse to undertake a Health Coaching session. These sessions are individualised to what the patient goals are and what is the broader picture for the patient during the preceding two weeks and following two weeks. Issues such as moderately high blood pressure results on a number of occasions would be discussed and if the patient might consider review with their GP. Other issues discussed might be medication changes or health appointments they have or are going to attend. Anxiety and Depression screening also takes place at this session. The sessions can take typically 20-30 minutes depending on the need of the patient and are the main point of review of the care plan.

Patients have access to personalised advice from nurse team 24 hours a day which was provided by a team of nurses with access to specialist if required. Patients have the ability to  contact the nurse at any time via phone and via video conferencing 7 days a week 0830 hrs  to 1700hrs . If a patient entered their data afterhours and it is outside of their usual parameters an sms message is sent to the on call phone and the nurse is able to review the data and respond to the patient if this is required.  Patients are advised and reminded throughout the pilot study period that at any time they feel they require emergency care they should follow their usual practice (eg. call 000).
Research suggests that these aspects individually can improve the consumer's understanding and ability to manage their own health conditions. This proof of concept pilot aims to demonstrate that a combination of these core aspects leads to decreased hospital utilization as well as increases in health literacy and improved ability to self-manage their health conditions. Patients will be enrolled in the pilot for a period of 12 months unless they chose to withdraw and each intervention will be delivered concurrently. The fidelity of the intervention will not be assessed due to the difficult nature of data extraction from the IT system utilised. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group consists of consecutively randomized participants who will not received the intervention. The control group will receive usual care inclusive of access to all Community Health and Rehabilitation  based programs, All inpatient facilities including emergency acute and sub acute care.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean number of Hospital admissions during the patients 12 month enrollment </outcome>
      <timepoint>for the 12 months of the participants enrollment utilising self-reported admissions to private hospital setting and Victorian Admitted Data from Barwon Health data submitted to the Department of Health </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean length of stay for patients for that might be admitted during their 12 month enrollment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>for the 12 months of the participants enrollment utilising self-reported admissions to private hospital setting and Victorian Admitted Data from Barwon Health data submitted to the Department of Health </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with changes to their Quality of Life survey using the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL-8D) instrument</outcome>
      <timepoint>Base line and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with changes to their Health literacy scores using the Health Education Impact Questionnaire (heiQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Base line and at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of the participants that have a change to the measurement of their 6 min walk test (COPD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>base line and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with a reduction in resting blood pressure, assessed using a digital sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>base line and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of participants with changes in their HbA1C (diabetes) </outcome>
      <timepoint>base line and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of participants with reduction in serum lipids</outcome>
      <timepoint>base line and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with changes to the measurements of  depression PHQ 9 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Base line and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic evaluation , comparison of cost for service delivery based on admitted data and hospital level costings and self reported data of private hospital admissions and standardized costing for hospital coding. The mean total cost per patient for the intervention group was compared to the mean total cost of the control group. The evaluation included actual nursing resource costing including on call amounts. Purchase of equipment and travel requirements for nursing staff and patients. The Quality of Life  using the AQoL-8D ICER is also calculated and contrbutes to the overall evaluation in $ terms</outcome>
      <timepoint>for the 12 months of the participants enrollment utilising self-reported admissions to private hospital setting and Victorian Admitted Data from Barwon Health data submitted to the Department of Health and the AQoL- 8D at base line and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of participants who present and frequency of their attendance to the Emergency Department during their 12 month enrollment. this was measured using internal the Barwon Health reporting . No private hospital emergency data was provided as there were no private hospital with Emergency Departments at the time of the trial. A report was run daily and at the end of the pilot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>for the 12 months of the participants enrollment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with changes to the measurements of anxiety GAD 7</outcome>
      <timepoint>base line and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Barwon Health has formed a partnership with Deakin University's Centre for Pattern Recognition and Data Analytic s (PRaDA) PRaDA Using computer modelling aims to explore latent patterns in health data and medical records and assign individual to their patterns. The method uses characteristics of individual s such as diagnosis , co morbidity , age , gender , admission and length of stay history, diagnosis procedures past HbA1c measures , past operations and past medication to predict the likelihood of numbers of admission between 0 and 1. The patient cohort selected for this trial will have a likelihood of readmission between 0.5 and 0.8 according to PRaDA. and have COPD , Diabetes or both COPD and Diabetes.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those living in supported accommodation
Those who do not have a diagnosis of COPD or Diabetes
Those who do not have a PRaDA score of between 0.5 adn 0.8
Those who do not have the ability/dexterity to enter and submit own data via a computer
Those who do not have functional grasp of English
Pregnancy
Vision Impairment or hearing impairment which impacts on ability to use the telehealth device
Poor 12 month prognosis
Severe cognitive impairment as determined by clinical assessment
Sub optimal management of mental illness as per clinical assessment
Current enrollment in Hospital Admission Risk Program (HARP)
Active palliative care patient
Drug or alcohol dependency 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Individuals agreeing to be involved in the study and were assigned by Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software for three groups
Diabetes
COPD
Both Diabetes and COPD</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Economic Evaluation was undertaken 
Due to the pilot nature of the study, analysis of study data will not follow a hypothesis testing framework. Confidence intervals for efficacy outcomes will be calculated within each group at the 95% confidence level, however no formal significance tests will be made. Hospital admissions will be treated as a binary variable, ED presentations as counts, and LoS as ordinal. Total LoS (summed over all admissions) will be presented.
Allowances for stratification of the sample will be made via the CochranMantelHaenszel (CMH) test for unadjusted analyses, and adjustment for covariates will further be investigated via logistic regression for binary variables; adjustment for covariates will use Poisson regression for count variables. Analysis of the readmission rates will further be summarised under a time-to-event framework.
Baseline measures will be summarised by group, as will any differences post-intervention. Trial procedures (such as recruitment and retention rates, compliance and monitoring loads) will be monitored and summarised by confidence intervals where appropriate.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/12/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/07/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>171</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>7/07/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong Hospital campus - Geelong</hospital>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - Rippleside</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - Bell Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - Drumcondra</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - Hamlyn Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - Geelong North</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - Bell Post Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - North Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Belmont</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Freshwater Creek</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Grovedale</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Grovedale East</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Highton</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Marshall</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Mount Duneed</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Wandana Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Waurn Ponds</postcode>
    <postcode>3218 - Fyansford</postcode>
    <postcode>3218 - Geelong West</postcode>
    <postcode>3218 - Herne Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3218 - Manifold Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>3218 - Murgheboluc</postcode>
    <postcode>3219 - Breakwater</postcode>
    <postcode>3219 - East Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3219 - Newcomb</postcode>
    <postcode>3219 - St Albans Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3219 - Thomson</postcode>
    <postcode>3219 - Whittington</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Bareena</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Newtown</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - South Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3222 - Clifton Springs</postcode>
    <postcode>3222 - Curlewis</postcode>
    <postcode>3222 - Drysdale</postcode>
    <postcode>3222 - Mannerim</postcode>
    <postcode>3222 - Marcus Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>3222 - Wallington</postcode>
    <postcode>3223 - Bellarine</postcode>
    <postcode>3223 - Indented Head</postcode>
    <postcode>3223 - Portarlington</postcode>
    <postcode>3223 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>3224 - Leopold</postcode>
    <postcode>3224 - Moolap</postcode>
    <postcode>3225 - Point Lonsdale</postcode>
    <postcode>3225 - Queenscliff</postcode>
    <postcode>3225 - Swan Bay</postcode>
    <postcode>3225 - Swan Island</postcode>
    <postcode>3226 - Ocean Grove</postcode>
    <postcode>3227 - Barwon Heads</postcode>
    <postcode>3227 - Breamlea</postcode>
    <postcode>3227 - Connewarre</postcode>
    <postcode>3228 - Bellbrae</postcode>
    <postcode>3228 - Torquay</postcode>
    <postcode>3330 - Rokewood</postcode>
    <postcode>3321 - Hesse</postcode>
    <postcode>3328 - Teesdale</postcode>
    <postcode>3331 - Bannockburn</postcode>
    <postcode>3331 - Gheringhap</postcode>
    <postcode>3331 - Maude</postcode>
    <postcode>3331 - Steiglitz</postcode>
    <postcode>3332 - Lethbridge</postcode>
    <postcode>3333 - Meredith</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Barwon Health </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>156 Bellerine St
Geelong
Victoria
3220
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Londsdale St 
Melbourne
Victoria
3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Barwon Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>156 Bellerine St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Health Victoria </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>50 Londsdale St
Melbourne
Victoria
3000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deakin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>221 Burwood Highway, 
Burwood, 
Victoria 
3125</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proof of concept pilot explores the effectiveness of  Remote Patient Monitoring (RPM) to support patients with COPD and Diabetes. The IT system used in this pilot project is a web based platform that can be accessed from any internet connected device.  The patient, when accessing the platform, will be directed to their personalised care plan that has a questionnaire designed to educate and guide the client to monitor and support their own health. The peripheral devices that link to the system, enable the monitoring of clinical signs and symptoms such as SaO2, blood pressure and blood glucose measures. 
For the health service clinicians accessing the platform, the RPM system identifies in real time which clients have recorded results at that point in time and which have not, it provides an indication of which results are at variance to the result parameters set for each individual;, thus enabling a rapid and timely response.
The RPM system generates individualized reporting that allows the clinicians to monitor trends within a clients health care over time, enabling treatment to be appropriately adapted as and if required.
The pilot was supported by a Data Safety Monitoring Board and is aim at evaluating the effectiveness of the tele-health intervention 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Successes and Failures in Tele-health/HiNZ conference
Auckland 
2016 November 
Presenter Josephine Stevens
Title of Presentation : Barwon Healths Personalised Health Care a Randomised Controlled Pilot for the delivery of Chronic Disease care for patients with COPD and Diabetes using a home monitoring tele-health solution.
Publications pending</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee Barwon Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research 
Kitchener House 
PO Box 281
Geelong
3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372411-13 14 HREC approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372411-HREC PHC origninal.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372411-Merge letter with CHARS letterhead 1 12 13 final.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Robyn Hayles</name>
      <address>c/- Barwon Health Corporate Offices
156 Bellerine St 
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 42151057</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.hayles@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Josephine Stevens</name>
      <address>Barwon Health 
120 Settlement Rd
Belmont
Victoria
3216</address>
      <phone>+61 448688082</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>josephis@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Josephine Stevens</name>
      <address>Barwon Health
120 Settlement Rd
Belmont
Victoria
3216</address>
      <phone>+61 448688082</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>josephis@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Josephine Stevens</name>
      <address>Barwon Health 
120 Settlement Rd
Belmont
Victoria
3216</address>
      <phone>+61 448688082</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>josephis@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>