<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343166">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000703909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Kinematic analysis of reaching movement after segmental muscle vibration therapy in patients with chronic stroke: a randomized controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with hemiparesis following a stroke, is the addition of segmental muscle vibration therapy to exercise more effective than exercise alone in modifying reaching movement?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Segmental muscle vibration (SMV) is a technique that applies a vibratory stimulus to a specific muscle using a mechanical device. When applied to a muscletendon unit, SMV induces the generation of Ia inputs as a consequence of activation of muscle spindle primary endings. The Ia inputs activated by SMV can alter the excitability of the corticospinal pathway by modulation of intracortical inhibiting and facilitating inputs to the primary motor cortex. Indeed, recent transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS)
studies have shown increased excitability in the primary
motor cortex representation of the vibrated muscle following
the application of low-amplitude SMV to the flexor carpi radialis muscle and intrinsic hand muscles in healthy
subjects. Moreover, SMV applied to healthy subjects effectively compensates for repetitive TMS-induced inhibition
of the prefrontal cortex. It has been demonstrated that SMV
added to general physical therapy may improve gait performance in patients with foot drop secondary to chronic stroke. SMV is chracterized by amplitude of displacement (mm), frequency (Hz) and duration of application. Particularly suited for application in neurological condition are low amplitude (0.01 mm), high frequency (120 Hz) stimuli, applied for 30 minutes/day, 5 days/week over a total of 2 weeks.
Patients will also receive exercise therapy consisting in stretching, strengthening, proprioceptive training and reaching training. Exercise will be performed under the guidance of a physical therapist with experience in the field of stroke rehabilitation, 60 minutes/day, 5 days/week over a total of 2 weeks. Exercise therapy will be delivered at the end of each SMV session.</interventions>
    <comparator>Exercise therapy consists in stretching, strengthening, proprioceptive training and reaching training. Exercise will be performed under the guidance of a physical therapist with experience in the field of stroke rehabilitation, 60 minutes/day, 5 days/week over a total of 2 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement of mean linear speed (m/s) during reaching movement, as measured by instrumental kinematic analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks and four weeks after treatment starts.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in the smoothness of movement, as measured by normalized jerk, i.e. the third derivative of displacement, through instrumental kinematic analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks and four weeks after treatment starts.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in upper limb kinematics at the end of reaching movement, as measured by quantifying elbow extension and shoulder flexion angles.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks and four weeks after treatment starts.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Right or left hemiplegia of at least 6 months duration, secondary to magnetic resonance imagingdocumented chronic ischemic stroke.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Bilateral brain lesions, ischemic involvement of the cerebellum or basal ganglia, aphasia, psychiatric disease, cognitive impairment (Mini-Mental State Exam evaluation &lt;23), and previous history of neurological diseases, diabetes, or rheumatic and orthopedic conditions that may interfere with upper limb movement. Patients are
also excluded if they are involved in other clinical trials or if
they are under antispasticity therapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly assigned to either an experimental group or a control group by an independent person who will select a sealed envelope 30 minutes before the intervention is due to start.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table from a statistic book</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sapienza University of Rome</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>piazzale Aldo Moro, 5
00185, Rome</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sapienza University of Rome</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>piazzale Aldo Moro, 5
00185, Rome</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Azienda Policlinico Umberto I, Rome</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>piazzale Aldo Moro, 5
00185, Rome</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Italy</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the present study is to ascertain whether the application of low-amplitude/high-frequency segmental muscle vibration on spastic muscles of the arm of patients with hemiparesis secondary to chronic focal ischemic brain injury, improves kinematic characteristics of reaching movement.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marco Paoloni</name>
      <address>Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation unit
Azienda Policlinico Umberto I
piazzale Aldo Moro, 5
00185 Rome</address>
      <phone>+396491672</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paolonim@tin.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marco Paoloni</name>
      <address>Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation unit
Azienda Policlinico Umberto I
piazzale Aldo Moro, 5
00185 Rome</address>
      <phone>+396491672</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paolonim@tin.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marco Paoloni</name>
      <address>Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation unit
Azienda Policlinico Umberto I
piazzale Aldo Moro, 5
00185 Rome</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>paolonim@tin.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>