<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335399">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000346077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>General practitioner and exercise physiologist interventions for decreasing primary cardiovascular risk in the overweight/obese general practice population - a pilot randomised control study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 24-week pilot feasibility study comparing the effects of usual general practitioner care (control) with additional general practitioner or exercise physiologist consultations focused on weight and cardiovascular risk reduction, on measures of cardiovascular risk in overweight/obese adults in general practice.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1114-7596</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Usual general practitioner (GP) care plus five specific GP consultations at 5-weekly intervals over 24 weeks; consultations to focus on the management of weight and cardiovascular risk factors (e.g. diet, exercise).
2. Usual GP care plus five specific exercise physiologist (EP) appointments at 5-weekly intervals over 24 weeks; consultations to focus on the management of weight and cardiovascular risk factors (e.g. diet, exercise).
GPs and EPs were asked to focus the scheduled sessions on the management of weight and cardiovascular risk factors, in the way that they would normally do this.  For GPs this was likely to be via advice, education, motivation, and referral to other health professionals.  For EPs, this was likely advice, educations, motivation and the provision and supervision of practical exercises and training.  GP sessions were estimated to be of 10 - 30 minutes duration, whilst EP sessions were estimated to be of 30 - 60 minutes duration.  Participants underwent only 1 arm of the trial.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual general practitioner care.  This refers to patients seeing their GP as needed or as recommended by their GP regarding any symptom(s)/complaint(s), just as they would if they were not involved in the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular risk factor reduction measured by: weight (kg), body mass index (BMI), waist-to-hip ratios , mean blood pressure (mm Hg), fasting blood lipids (total cholesterol, high density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, low density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol, triglycerides)(mg/dL), and fasting blood glucose (mmol/L)

Body mass / weight, with clothing, was measured to 0.1 kg accuracy using a Tanita Digital Lithium Scale (Model: HD-327).  For participants exceeding the 150kg weight capacity for the Tanita Scale, weight was measured using a Seca Compact Electronic Scale (Model: 770), with a weight capacity of 200kg and graduation of 0.1kg. 
Height was measured to 0.1cm accuracy using the stretch stature technique1 with a wall-mounted 200cm Stature Meter.   
Body Mass Index (or Quetelet Index) was calculated using the universal formula: BMI = mass ((kg) / height (m))2 for each participant. 
Waist and hip circumferences were measured to 0.1 cm accuracy with a Futaba (spring-loaded) Rotary 2m cloth measuring tape (Model: R-280) using protocols from the anthropometric standardisation reference manual2 by Lohman et al (1988).  
Waist-hip ratio (waist circumference (cm)/hip circumference (cm)) was calculated for each participant.  
Mean Blood Pressure (mm Hg) was measured using an Omron Digital Blood Pressure Monitor (Model: HEM-907).  One participant required measurement using a medium-sized Omron Cuff (HEM-CR19) over the radial artery and above the ulna styloid process, with the cuff placed at heart level.  For this participant, the Omron Automatic Wrist Blood Pressure Monitor (Model: IW2) was not used due to its smaller cuff size.
Fasting blood lipids (total cholesterol, HDL) cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, triglycerides)(mg/dL), and fasting blood glucose (mmol/L) were measured on a sample of blood collected from each patient via venesection, analysed at pathology laboratory  using the Advia 2400 chemical system by Siemens, and their associated reagents.

[1.      Lohman, T.G., Roche, A.F., &amp; Martorell, R. (1988).  Anthropometric Standardisation Reference Manual. Champaign, Illinois: Human Kinetics Books.
2.      Kaminsky, L.A. (ed.) (2006). ACSM?s resource manual for Guidelines for exercise testing and prescription. Baltimore: Lippincott Williams and Wilkins.]</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant self-reported cardiovascular lifestyle risk factors:  cigarette smoking, alcohol consumption, fruit and vegetable consumption, exercise.
Information collected via paper-based survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 24 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of the study, determined by measures including general practitioner and exercise physiologist recruitment, and participant recruitment and retention rates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of 24 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The use of guidelines and intervention strategies employed by GPs and EPs for management of weight loss and cardiovascular risk, as reported by GPs and EPs in a paper-based survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant self-reported effectiveness of the interventions and satisfaction with weight reduction.
Information collected via paper-based survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart rate (beats / min) (measured using an Omron Digital Blood Pressure Monitor (Model: HEM-907)) and  recovery rate (beats/min) using the "YMCA" 3-Minute Step Test protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Aged 18 years or older; 
- Being overweight and having a body mass index (BMI) 27 or more;
- Able to speak and understand the English language; 
- Able to understand the nature and requirements of the research project; AND
- Being considered medically fit to undertake all three arms of the trial by his / her GP.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Pregnant;                                              
- Having known cardiovascular disease including acute coronary syndrome (ACS), previous ST elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI), angina, heart failure, clinically significant arrhythmia, or previous cardiac surgery</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolling study subjects:  GPs enrolled subjects by approaching consecutive patients who satisfied the inclusion criteria, providing them with a Patient Information Sheet and the opportunity to discuss the project and their potential involvement, and then seeking their consent to participate in the study.

Allocation concealment was used and consisted of sealed, opaque envelopes, which were indistinguishable externally and marked with a unique identifying code.  Allocation was performed by the study’s exercise physiologist, after the enrolled participants completed all baseline assessments.  The exercise physiologist did not have any involvement in the subject enrolment process.</concealment>
    <sequence>A simple randomisation procedure was used.  

Depending on the number of patients recruited at each practice, practices were given one or more batches of nine sealed, indistinguishable opaque envelopes.  (For example, a practice recruiting 28 patients would be given four batches of nine envelopes; a practice recruiting 7 patients would be given one batch of nine envelopes).  The shuffled envelope batches contained three allocations to each of the Control, GP and EP arms of the study. Each patient received one envelope, containing his / her group allocation. Participants’ allocations were recorded against their unique identifying numbers on a data collection spreadsheet.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/05/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4077</postcode>
    <postcode>4151</postcode>
    <postcode>4305</postcode>
    <postcode>4067</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Marie-Louise Dick</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Discipline of General Practice
School of Medicine
University of Queensland
Level 8, Health Sciences Building
Building 16/ 910 
Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital
Herston  QLD  4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Australian College of General Practitioners (RACGP)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>RACGP College House, 1 Palmerston Crescent, South Melbourne, Victoria. 3205</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pfizer Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>38-42 Wharf Road, West Ryde NSW 2114; PO Box 57, West Ryde NSW 2114</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane QLD 4072 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To investigate the feasibility of a community-based randomised control trial exploring the practices employed by general practitioners and exercise physiologists in the management of overweight/obese patients, and their effect on weight reduction and cardiovascular risk factors.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Conference presentation:
Dick, Marie-Louise, Harris, Lisa, Janamian, Tina, Schubert, Rebecca, Doust, Jenny. (2009). A pilot randomised control trial of general practitioner and exercise physiologist interventions to reduce primary cardiovascular risk in overweight patients. 2009 General Practice and Primary Health Care Research Conference, Melbourne 15-17 July, 2009.   In:  2009 General Practice and Primary Health Care Research Conference: Program &amp; Abstracts. Primary Health Care Research and Information Service, Australia.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland's Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cumbrae-Stewart Building
Research Road
St Lucia
Brisbane Qld 4072 Australia
Telephone +61 7 3365 3559
Facsimile +61 7 3365 8383</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007001085</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marie-Louise Dick</name>
      <address>Discipline of General Practice
School of Medicine, University of Queensland, Level 8, Health Sciences Building, Building 16/ 910, Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital, Herston  QLD  4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5380</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33465178</fax>
      <email>m.dick@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marie-Louise Dick</name>
      <address>Discipline of General Practice
School of Medicine, University of Queensland, Level 8, Health Sciences Building, Building 16/ 910, Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital, Herston  QLD  4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5380</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33465178</fax>
      <email>m.dick@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marie-Louise Dick</name>
      <address>Discipline of General Practice
School of Medicine, University of Queensland, Level 8, Health Sciences Building, Building 16/ 910, Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital, Herston  QLD  4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5380</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33465178</fax>
      <email>m.dick@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>