<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371415">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001320448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Healthy Brain Ageing E-Health Platform: Validating Online Strategies to Recruit and Assess Older Adults at Risk of Cognitive Decline</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Healthy Brain Ageing E-health Platform: Validating Recruitment Strategies and Online Assessment Tools for Older Adults at Risk of Cognitive Decline</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-0626 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular risk</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sleep disturbance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Online screening for at risk profiles: Cognitive and modifiable risk data:

Modifiable risk factors: All participants (n=1500) will be asked to complete the HBA E-health Questionnaire (duration: up to 1 hour) to provide details about their demographics, medical history, mental health history (e.g., Generalized Anxiety Disorder Assessment (GAD-7), Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K-10), cognition and functional status (e.g., HBA Functional Assessment Tool, WHO Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0), sleep (e.g., Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI), physical activity (e.g., Active Australia Survey), nutrition and dietary habits (e.g., HBA Food Frequency Screening Questionnaire), alcohol and substance use history (e.g., Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT-C), Alcohol, Smoking and Substance Involvement Screening Tests (ASSIST)), medications, and quality of life (e.g., WHO Quality of Life Scale). All data necessary for enabling comparisons with Australian-based dementia prediction algorithms for older individuals and the European-based personalised lifestyle for brain health (LIBRA) global score for middle-aged individuals will be collected. Modifiable risk factors for cognitive decline include the following: depressive symptoms (K-10&gt;20); hypertension; hypercholesterolaemia; heart disease; high risk of Type 2 diabetes (AUSDRISK score=12) or diagnosed Type 1 or Type 2 diabetes; smoker, low education (less than year 9); low exercise (Active Australia guidelines for sufficient physical activity); obesity (BMI&gt;30). Although not formally identified in the recent reviews of established risks, we will also define as risk a person with poor sleep quality (PSQI&gt;5), or excess alcohol consumption (AUDIT-C&gt;4).

Cognitive decline: All participants will also complete an online cognitive assessment using CogState (duration: 15 minutes).  Age-related cognitive decline will be defined as at least 1SD decline on CogState relative to age and education matched normative data.

Face-to face clinical assessments:
A subsample (n=180) participants will be drawn from the broader group and invited to attend their nearest study site (i) The Healthy Brain Ageing Clinic, Brain and Mind Centre, Camperdown; ii) Alzheimers Australia NSW Community Centre, Newcastle; iii) Alzheimers Australia NSW Community Centre, Port Macquarie) for detailed (face-to-face) neuropsychological, medical and psychological assessment (described in more detail below) within one month of when they completed the online assessments.. 
i)	Medical assessment (duration: up to 1 hour): A medical professional will review the patients medical history with an emphasis on vascular risk factors and diabetes as well as details regarding family medical history. Biomedical measurements include height, weight, waist circumference, and blood pressure. Finally, in order to obtain objective markers of key health outcomes, a nurse or staff member trained in blood collection procedures will take a blood sample that will be tested for cardiovascular markers (e.g., HDL/LDL cholesterol).

ii)	Neuropsychological assessment (duration: 1 hour): The clinical neuropsychologist will conduct a brief clinical interview to collect details about the participants background, education and occupation, cognition and functional status. Participants will also complete approximately one hour of neuropsychological tests including Digit Span from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale, Third Edition (WAIS-III), Logical Memory subtests from the Wechsler Memory Scale, Third Edition (WMS-III), Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT), Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure Test, Controlled Oral Word Association Test, Semantic Fluency, Trail Making Test A and B, Boston Naming Test, Clock Drawing Test, and the Delis-Kaplan Executive Functioning System (D-KEFS) Color-Word Interference subtest (D-KEFS).

iii)	Mood assessment (duration: up to 1 hour): To assess each participants mood and psychiatric history, the clinical neuropsychologist will ask semi-structured interview questions including the Structured Clinical Interview for the Hamilton Depression Scale and modules A (Major Depressive Episode), N (Generalized Anxiety Disorders), and O (Rule-Out Medical, Organic or Drug Causes for All Disorders) of the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview, Version 6.0. 

Both the online assessments and the face-to-face assessments will only occur one time. </interventions>
    <comparator>Validation will comprise of assessment of the capability of two components of Cogstate (the overall CBB and memory sub-test, conducted on the e-health platform) against the ability to detect memory impairment on gold-standard neuropsychological tests (i.e., Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test and Logical Memory) collected in clinic. In addition, we will determine the validity of other risk factors assessed via the platform to detect cases of interest. In particular, participants who attend the HBA clinic for face-to-face assessment will undergo the following assessments:
i)	Medical assessment: Review of the patients medical history with an emphasis on vascular risk factors and diabetes as well as details regarding family medical history. Biomedical measurements include height, weight, waist circumference, and blood pressure. Finally, in order to obtain objective markers of key health outcomes, a nurse or staff member trained in blood collection procedures will take a blood sample that will be tested for cardiovascular markers.

ii)	Neuropsychological assessment: The clinical neuropsychologist will conduct a brief clinical interview to collect details about the participants background, education and occupation, cognition and functional status. Participants will also complete approximately one hour of neuropsychological tests including Digit Span from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale, Third Edition (WAIS-III), Logical Memory subtests from the Wechsler Memory Scale, Third Edition (WMS-III), Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT), Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure Test, Controlled Oral Word Association Test, Semantic Fluency, Trail Making Test A and B, Boston Naming Test, Clock Drawing Test, and the Delis-Kaplan Executive Functioning System (D-KEFS) Color-Word Interference subtest (D-KEFS).

iii)	Mood assessment: To assess each participants mood and psychiatric history, semi-structured interview questions will be used including the Structured Clinical Interview for the Hamilton Depression Scale and modules A (Major Depressive Episode), N (Generalized Anxiety Disorders), and O (Rule-Out Medical, Organic or Drug Causes for All Disorders) of the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview, Version 6.0. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of recruitment will primarily be assessed based on our ability to meet recruitment targets in specified project timelines. </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year post commencement of recruitment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will assess the capacity of the overall Cognitive Brief Battery conducted on the e-health platform against the ability to detect memory impairment on gold-standard neuropsychological tests (RAVLT and Logical Memory), collected in face-to-face clinic settings.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cogstate completed at baseline and face-to-face clinic assessment conducted within 1 month of completion of the online screening measures. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will assess the capacity of the memory sub-test from Cogstate Brief Battery conducted on the e-health platform against the ability to detect memory impairment on gold-standard neuropsychological tests (RAVLT and Logical Memory), collected in face-to-face clinic settings.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cogstate completed at baseline and face-to-face clinic assessment conducted within 1 month of completion of the online screening measures. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will assess and compare response rates across the various methods of recruitment and advertising (i.e., physician referral, print advertising, social media, etc.).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post commencement of recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative and quantitative techniques will be used to evaluate the online assessment measures offered through the HBA e-health platform with the aim of further refining the system for future users.  

Evaluation survey questions will include:
1. How long did it take you to complete the HBA E-health questionnaire?
2, How many sessions did it take you to complete the survey?
3. How easy was the survey to use? (5 point Likert scale)
4. How easy were the questions to understand? (5 point Likert scale)
5. If you did not complete the survey, why did you discontinue?
*The questions did not apply to me.
*I did not have enough time to finish the survey.
*The survey was too long.
*I had computer and/or internet problems when trying to complete the survey.
*The survey was boring.
*The survey was hard to read and understand (e.g., words too small, too many words, scrolling through the pages was problematic).
*I did not feel comfortable answering all of the mandatory questions.
*Other
6. How worried about your privacy were you when responding to the survey? (5 point Likert scale)
7. How long did it take you to complete the thinking and memory tests?
8. What changes to the online assessments would you recommend? (text box) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post commencement of recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults between the ages of 50 and 70 who speak fluent English and who have concerns about their cognition (but not a formal diagnosis of dementia) or mood are eligible to participate in this study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals will be excluded from the study if they are aged &lt;50 years or &gt;70 years, do not speak fluent English, have been diagnosed with dementia, or do not have concerns about their cognition or mood.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>We aim to recruit 1500 participants to complete the HBA E-health Questionnaire and CogState. A subsample of 180 participants will be drawn from this broader group and invited to attend their nearest study site (i) The Healthy Brain Ageing Clinic, Brain and Mind Centre, Camperdown; ii) Alzheimers Australia NSW Community Centre, Newcastle; iii) Alzheimers Australia NSW Community Centre, Port Macquarie) for detailed (face-to-face) neuropsychological, medical and psychological assessment (this component is optional).

Through a newly developed partnership with Alzheimers Australia, we have the opportunity to recruit large numbers of participants from across NSW, ensuring that we are recruiting a representative sample of the total population. Alzheimer's Australia is extremely supportive of this project and plan to active promote the study. The sample size of 1500 participants was determined in collaboration with Alzheimer's Australia based on the response rates they have had to other online surveys. 

Once we have successfully reached our target sample size in each site (total n =180), an additional 1320 participants will still be able to complete the online assessment so as to allow for engagement of those interested as well as to provide relevant data as per study aims regarding feasibility of recruitment. 

Feasibility of recruitment will primarily be assessed based on our ability to meet recruitment targets in specified project timelines. Additionally, we will assess and compare response rates across the various methods of recruitment and advertising (i.e., physician referral, print advertising, social media, etc.). 

In terms of validity, we will assess the capacity of two components of Cogstate (the overall CBB and memory sub-test, conducted on the e-health platform) against the ability to detect memory impairment on gold-standard neuropsychological tests (RAVLT and Logical Memory), collected in clinic. We will fit receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves to verify (or modify) the validity of the Cogstate cut-scores for future selected prevention trials. We note that while Cogstate has been validated in prior community samples, establishing the validity of screening tools for the e-health population of interest is a fundamental requirement for new populations. In addition, we will determine the validity of other risk factors assessed via the platform to detect cases of interest. This component of the validation is required for indicated and selective trials, which we also plan to do using the e-health platform (e.g. use a depression intervention to target depressive symptoms coupled with cognitive decline), as well as comparison with other validated dementia risk algorithms (e.g. CAIDE, LIBRA).

At the conclusion of their involvement in the study, qualitative and quantitative techniques will be used to evaluate the online assessment measures offered through the HBA e-health platform with the aim of further refining the system for future users.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>31</followup>
    <followuptype>Days</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>114</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brain and Mind Centre, Healthy Brain Ageing Program, 94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Healthy Brain Ageing Program, Brain and Mind Centre, 94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>As there are no effective cures for dementia, it is essential that efforts focus on screening for potentially modifiable risk factors of cognitive decline as it has been estimated that reductions in these treatable conditions could result in 1.1 million fewer cases of Alzheimers disease worldwide. These modifiable risk factors include depression, diabetes, having high blood pressure, being overweight, being a smoker, being physically inactive, and having low education which in turn relates to not keeping the brain active enough.

The internet is a powerful means by which to prevent health-related problems and to promote general health and wellbeing on a large-scale, referred to as e-health. E-health can be used to screen at risk individuals, offer self-help through online interventions or deliver proactive and guided interventions facilitated by expert clinicians. The major advantage of e-health over standard models of care is the ability to recruit and deliver interventions on a large-scale, thereby being able to more effectively address major public health issues. 

Our team has developed a large scale Healthy Brain Ageing (HBA) e-health platform designed specifically for older adults who are at risk of cognitive decline and dementia. Our goal is to establish a register of at risk individuals with ongoing monitoring of cognition as well as potentially modifiable risk factors for cognitive decline, with a view to providing targeted interventions as appropriate. 

Prior to implementing this system, we seek to confirm that we can successfully recruit older adults at risk of dementia via the HBA e-health platform. Additionally, we aim to establish that the assessment tools used in the e-health platform accurately screen for age-related cognitive impairment and correctly identify an individuals dementia risk factors relative to gold-standard clinical assessment tools conducted in a face-to-face clinic setting. 

We will invite 1500 people from across NSW aged 50-70 years to complete an online screening questionnaire as well as a brief battery of online neuropsychological tests (Cogstate). Subsequently, a subsample of 180 participants with varying levels of cognitive impairment and/or modifiable risk factors will be invited to attend one of three assessment sites for detailed neuropsychological, medical, and psychological assessment. We will compare the results of these two evaluations to ensure that the online assessment tools are sensitive to dementia risk factors and cognitive decline (i.e., equivalent to standardised assessment tools used in clinical practice). Additionally, feasibility of recruitment will be assessed based on our ability to meet recruitment targets in specified project timelines. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office
Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/389</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sharon Naismith</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre, 94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 0781</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9351 0551</fax>
      <email>sharon.naismith@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Haley LaMonica</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre, 94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 0785</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9351 0551</fax>
      <email>haley.lamonica@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Haley LaMonica</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre, 94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 0785</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9351 0551</fax>
      <email>haley.lamonica@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Haley LaMonica</name>
      <address>Brain and Mind Centre, 94 Mallet Street, Camperdown, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 0785</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9351 0551</fax>
      <email>haley.lamonica@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>