<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370966">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000915459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison between Ultrasound Guided Abdominal Wall Catheter (by Anaesthetist) and Wound Catheter (by Surgeon) for the Treatment of Postoperative Pain after Abdominal Surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Transmuscular Quadratus Lumborum versus Pre-Peritoneal Catheters for Postoperative Analgesia in Abdominal Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NilKnown</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postoperative Analgesia in Abdominal Surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The two groups are Pre peritoneal(PP) and Trans-muscular Quadratus lumborum(TQL) group. Both groups will have standard General anesthesia. Both groups will have standard monitoring: involving ECG, pulse oximetr, capnography, noninvasive BP and noninvasive clear sight to facilitate fluid replacement.,At the end of the surgery patients in the PP group, the surgeon will inject 20ml of 0.375% ropivacaine at subcutaneous, sub-fascial and pre-peritoneal level followed by catheter insertion under direct vision  and connected to an elastomeric pump. In the TQL group anaesthetist performs the TQL block post-surgery in lateral position, Under aseptic precautions, ultrasound guidance, an 18 gauge Tuohy needle will be used to reach the QL muscle posterior aspect. This is confirmed by injecting saline and followed by a bolus dose of 20 ml of0.375% ropivacaine . Subsequently a catheter is inserted. The same technique is repeated on the other side. Both groups will receive multimodal analgesia which is part of Acute pain service(APS) hospital protocol. Which involves Paracetamol 1 gram 6hourly (IV/oral) and fentanyl PCA.  Paracetamol will be administered IV if patient not tolerating orally at the discretion of treating physician. Fentanyl PCA device (bolus 10 to 40 mcg based on pain scores with lockout time 5 min) is  managed at the discretion of APS staff. Both groups will be infused with 0.2% ropivacaine 5ml/hr on each side during 48 hours. Intervention will be adhered to the protocol in the single center at the hospital, which also include staff from the the pain service in the post operative period. APS personnel will independently assess the postoperative pain scores and analgesia used in recovery and on day one and two. Duration of introduction of catheter insertions and complications related to tit will be noted. Patient satisfaction will be assessed on day 2 and during a follow-up telephone call at one month. First flatus or bowels opening time and discharge time will also be tracked. Personnel and material costs will be used for a cost analysis</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator is Pre peritoneal catheter group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain scores  at rest and on cough in the post anaesthesia care unit </outcome>
      <timepoint>On arrival and 1 hour stay in the post anaesthesia care unit.Data obtained from the review of medical records.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain scores  at rest and on cough on day one and two</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post operative period on day one and two.
Data obtained from the review of medical records.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analgesia use in the recovery room and 48 hours stay from the patient controlled analgesia device, assessed by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Analgesia used the day of the procedure and on day one and day two in the post-operative period including cumulative analgesia used in 48 hours, Data obtained from the review of medical records. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>satisfaction scores ,
Likert score is used to assess patient satisfaction with the analgesic technique on the scale of 1-4.</outcome>
      <timepoint>on Day 2 and day 30 post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The cost of the all consumables and time consumed by the staff .</outcome>
      <timepoint>First post operative week., data collected from patient medical records</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first passing of flatus or bowel movement. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of first passing of flatus or bowel movement. Data collected from the post operative visit on review of the medical records</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>discharge time</outcome>
      <timepoint> At time of hospital discharge. Data collected from the post operative visit on review of the medical records.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>duration of introduction of catheter insertions, </outcome>
      <timepoint>outcome is assessed at the end of the surgical procedure on the operative day. This time is obtained from the observation sheet or review of medical records</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Catheter related complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of 48 hours in the post-operative period from the pain or medical records</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dermatomes levels assessed by ice pack tested  for cold sensation and test results. by review of medical records, </outcome>
      <timepoint>Recovery room on the operative day and day one</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Elective abdominal surgery
2.Between 18 and 85 years of age
3.ASA less then 4
4.Adequate English language skills</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Emergency surgery
2.Allergy to local anaesthetic
3.Pregnancy
4.On regular opioid medication prior to surgery(&gt;30mg/day)
5.Mental handicap or psychiatric condition precluding adequate communication</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization will occur by random group allocations through a computer program (computerised sequence generation). This will provide group allocation concealed in sealed numbered opaque envelopes. Preoperatively the patients will not know which group they are allocated to. The medical staff involved in the treatment of the patient will not be blinded. We have decided not to use sham treatments due to additional time investment required, treatment related risks, and ethical considerations. As the employed techniques are essentially different, the assessors and APS staff will not be blinded either.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will occur by random group allocations through a computer program (computerised sequence generation). This will provide group allocation concealed in sealed numbered opaque envelopes. Preoperatively the patients will not know which group they are allocated to. The medical staff involved in the treatment of the patient will not be blinded. We have decided not to use sham treatments due to additional time investment required, treatment related risks, and ethical considerations. As the employed techniques are essentially different, the assessors and APS staff will not be blinded either</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Its a prospective study single blinded. The study is designed to recruit 80 patients; 40 in each arm of the study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the statistical analysis of the data we will be using the following methods: Differences between the continuous variables by the t-test; categorical variables by Fisher's exact test; and the pain scores between groups (TQL vs PP) will be analysed by rank non-parametric methods (Man Whitney U test).
Sample size: No formal calculations was performed for this study as there are no parallel trial available.Target sample size of 80 participants were considered appropriate with 40 in each arm.
A blinded interim analysis will be performed during the initial stage of progress of the study.. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Queen Elizabeth hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Queen Elizabeth hospital, 28 Woodville road, Woodville south.SA.5011.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Anaesthesia department, The Queen Elizabeth hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Queen Elizabeth hospital
28 Woodville road
Woodville south. SA.5011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>not known</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Not known</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The investigators are proposing a prospective, randomized study of 2x40 patients undergoing major abdominal surgery to compare ultrasound-guided TQL block catheters versus surgically placed PP catheters as an active control-group. We have been conservative in estimating the number of patients required, as there are no parallel active trials in the literature to draw from. However a single study using single shot TQl block in the lower abdominal surgery found 25 patients sufficient to get power of 0.8.The study will be conducted with the 2 measurable endpoints (Analgesic use as primary endpoint (cumulative and daily -PACU, day 1, day 2- Fentanyl use) and pain score differences over time as secondary endpoint -PAC, day 1, day 2 at rest/dynamic-. The investigators hypothesize that ultrasound-guided TQL block is superior to surgically guided Pre-Peritoneal block with respect to both end-points and either technique may be superior in discharge times or cost-efficacy.
The primary objective of the study is to compare analgesia used and the pain scores with the ultrasound guided TQL vs. surgically placed PP catheter infusion techniques in abdominal surgery. Secondary aim is to assess the subjective quality of pain management (satisfaction score), discharge times and cost analysis of the two methods of delivery. Patients in the PP group will have PP catheters placed under direct vision by the surgeon at the end of the surgery. Initially the surgeon injects 20 ml ropivacaine 0.375% at each site; subcutaneous, sub-fascia and pre-peritoneal levels followed by catheter insertion. This catheter are connected to an elastomeric pump. In the TQL group post-surgery, with the patient in lateral position, under ultrasound guidance, an 18 gauge Tuohy needle will be used to reach the QL muscle posterior aspect. This is confirmed by injecting saline and followed by a bolus dose of 20 ml of ropivacaine 0.375%. Subsequently a catheter is inserted. The same technique is repeated on the other side. Both groups will receive multimodal analgesia with Paracetamol 1 gram QID (orally or IV) and a Fentanyl PCA device (bolus 10 to 40 mcg; lockout time 5 min). Both groups will be infused with 0.2% ropivacaine 5ml/hr on each side during 48 hours via elastomeric pump. Acute Pain Service (APS) personnel will independently assess the postoperative pain scores and analgesia used in recovery and on day one and two. Procedure related technical issues; duration of introduction of catheter insertions and complications related to it will be noted. Patient satisfaction will be assessed on day 2 and during a follow-up telephone call at one month. First flatus or bowels opening time and discharge time will also be tracked. Personnel and material costs will be used for a cost analysis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE (TQEH/LMH/MH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>BHI
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South SA 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vasanth Rao Kadam</name>
      <address>Anaesthesia department.The Queen Elizabeth hospital, 28 Woodville road. Woodville south. SA.5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82226000</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82227065</fax>
      <email>vasanth.rao@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Van Wyjk Roelof</name>
      <address>Head of Anaesthesia, Anaesthesia department. The Queen Elizabeth hospital, 28 Woodville road. Woodville south. SA.5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82226000</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82227065</fax>
      <email>Roelof.VanWijk@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vasanth Rao Kadam</name>
      <address>Anaesthesia department. The Queen Elizabeth hospital, 28 Woodville road. Woodville south. SA.5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82226000</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82227065</fax>
      <email>vasanth.rao@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vasanth Rao Kadam</name>
      <address>Anaesthesia department. The Queen Elizabeth hospital, 28 Woodville road. Woodville south. SA.5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82226000</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82227065</fax>
      <email>vasanth.rao@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>