<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82174">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000447459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 1/2 Single Center, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Left-Right Comparison Study to Evaluate the Safety and Preliminary Efficacy of a Topical Antimicrobial (NEO101) in Older Adolescents and Adults with at least Moderate Atopic Dermatitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1/2 Single Center, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Left-Right Comparison Study to Evaluate the Safety and Preliminary Efficacy of a Topical Antimicrobial (NEO101) in Older Adolescents and Adults with at least Moderate Atopic Dermatitis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NEO101-CLIN-AD001</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Antimicrobial treatment of atopic dermatitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible subjects will be randomized to receive both NEO101 0.95% gel and vehicle-containing placebo gel twice daily for 14 days.  Treatment (blinded to treatment assignment) will be administered to the left and right side target skin surface areas for 14 days.  A 14-day safety and efficacy assessment period will follow the treatment period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo Gel</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the safety and local tolerability of twice-daily topical application of NEO101 gel for 14 days in subjects with a clinical diagnosis of at least moderate atopic dermatitis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and local tolerability will be assessed during the 14-day treatment period and through the 14-day follow-up period.  Physical examinations will be performed at Screening, and on Days 1, 15 and 29.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) To make a preliminary evaluation of the efficacy of bid topical application of NEO101 in the reduction or eradication of  Staphylococcus aureus.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cultures will be performed on Days 1, 2, 4, 8, 15 and 22</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) To make a preliminary evaluation of the efficacy of bid topical application of NEO101 in the reduction or eradication of other microorganisms including Streptococci and gram-negative bacteria such as Proteus or Pseudomonas.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cultures will be performed on Days 1, 8 and 15.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosed with atopic dermatitis as defined by pruritus, eczmetatous dermatitis, personal or family history of atopy; have a Physician's Global Assessment score equivalent to mild-to-moderate atopic dermatitis at Screening and Day 1; have a target treatment area of 50-150 cm squared on both a left and a right side of the body; have a positive culture for Staphylococcus aureus on both target treatment areas; compliant with defined birth control.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have concomitant dermatologic or medical condition(s) which may interfere with the investigator's ability to evaluate subject response; have immunocompromised status; have any clinically significant abnormal clinical laboratory test results at screening; have a history of malignancy not in remission for at least 5 years excluding basal cell carcinoma and nonperiorificial squamous cell carcinoma of the skin; have an active intercurrent infection; have used any topical antibiotic or antibacterial soap or bleach baths within 72 hours prior to Day 1; have used any systemic antibiotic within 1 week prior to Day 1; have a history of hypersensitivity or allergic reactions to parabens, sodium sulfite or other ingredient in the vehicle formulation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once a subject is identified as eligible to be randomized into the study, he/she will be assigned a unique subject number, which will correspond to the randomization code indicating which side (left or right) is to be treated with NEO101, while the other side is to be treated with vehicle.  The study site will be supplied with blinded numbered study drug kits and a drug dispensation list.  Subjects will be randomized to treatment side using the order established on the drug dispensation list.  Blinding of treatment assignment is achieved using vials distinguished by a yellow (lemon)-colored label (to be used ONLY for left side application) and a white label (to be used ONLY for right side application).</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be assigned a unique subject number, which will correspond to the randomization code indicating which side (left or right) is to be treated with NEO101, while the other side is to be treated with vehicle.  The study site will be supplied with blinded numbered study drug kits and a drug dispensation list.  Subjects will be randomized to treatment side using the order established on the drug dispensation list.  The randomization schedule was developed using a blocked randomization scheme.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a left-right treatment site comparison study.  The investigator, study staff and subjects will be blinded.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/09/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4217</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neosil Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5980 Horton Street, Suite 525
Emeryville, California 94608</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neosil Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5980 Horton Street, Suite 525
Emeryville, California 94608</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Skin Centre
Suite 5
AHC House
14 Carrara Street
Benowa, Queensland 4217

Therapeutic Goods Administration
CTN Number 2007/490</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>First Floor
71 Anzac Highway
Ashford, South Australia 5035</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/07/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>57/07</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andria Langenberg, MD</name>
      <address>Neosil Inc.
Suite 525
5980 Horton Street
Emeryville California 94608</address>
      <phone>+1 510 547 3610, ext. 180</phone>
      <fax>+1 510 547 3604</fax>
      <email>andria.langenberg@neosil.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolyn Nicholls</name>
      <address>The Skin Centre
Suite 5
AHC House
14 Carrara Street
Benowa QLD 4217</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5597 7170</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5597 7370</fax>
      <email>carolynnicholls@ozemail.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael McKown</name>
      <address>Neosil, Inc.
5980 Horton Street, Suite 525
Emeryville, California 94608</address>
      <phone>+1 510 547 3610, ext. 140</phone>
      <fax>+1 510 547 3604</fax>
      <email>michael.mckown@neosil.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>