<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371457">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001286437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the impact of hygiene and water interventions on diarrhoeal disease in India</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cluster randomised stepped-wedge trial assessing the impact of a community-level hygiene intervention and a water intervention using riverbank filtration technology on diarrhoeal prevalence in India</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-3423</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NHMRC1083408 (Grant number from National Health and Medical Research Council Australia)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diarrhoea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory infections</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Skin infections</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will be conducted over an 18-month period. As per the stepped wedge trial design, each of the four villages recruited for the trial will spend time in the control arm and the intervention arm of the study. Prior to the start of the control arm, a baseline survey will be conducted to collect baseline demographics and health data.

The control arm will involve delivery of a community-level hygiene education program and improved access to water at a community level (improved water quantity). The intervention arm will involve delivery of a community-level hygiene education program and access to water treated using riverbank filtration technology (RBF) at a community level (improved water quality). The intervention will be implemented by the non-governmental organisation The Energy and Resources Institute (TERI) in India. 

Hygiene education including posters relating to hand hygiene and safe water storage will be delivered to individual households and public places and trained field workers will provide house-by-house education on hygiene practices.  House-to-house education will consist of a verbal discussion of hygiene practices with the householder using educational posters. This will take approximately 10 minutes per household and will be delivered along with the baseline survey. Hygiene education messages will be reinforced by a trained field worker at each subsequent survey. 

RBF-treated water will be delivered via newly built water delivery systems. RBF is an inexpensive  water treatment technique that uses auto-regenerative, natural treatment processes to improve water quality. Contractors working with TERI will install new pipes, covered storage tanks and taps throughout each of the study villages. RBF wells will also be installed in each village. 

All villages will start in the control arm and will receive piped unfiltered river water via new water delivery systems. Villages will then be randomised to receive the RBF intervention at three monthly intervals (3, 6, 9 and 12 months after the start of the control arm). Once a village is randomised to receive the intervention, piped RBF-treated water will be delivered to that village for the remainder of the study period.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control arm will involve delivery of a community-level hygiene education program and access to improved water quantity at a community level. New water delivery systems (pipes, tanks and taps), will be used to deliver piped untreated river water to improve spatial access to water for hygiene and drinking purposes. Piped untreated river water will continue to be delivered until the village is randomised to receive RBF-treated water.

Hygiene education including posters relating to hand hygiene and safe water storage will be delivered to individual households and public places and trained field workers will provide house-by-house education on hygiene practices.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported diarrhoea (7 day period prevalence)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and every three months for 18 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported respiratory infections (7 day period prevalence)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and and every three months for 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported skin infections (7 day period prevalence)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and and every three months for 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported hygiene practices</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and and every three months for 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported preferred/adopted domestic water supply and household water consumption</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and and every three months for 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative detection of E. coli in water samples assessed as most probable number using Colilert (Registered Trademark) </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and weekly for 18 months. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness of RBF system installation in India measured and reported as cost per event prevented and cost per disability-adjusted life year (DALY) averted</outcome>
      <timepoint>At conclusion of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for village selection: 
- Villages in rural India currently using untreated river water as a primary source of drinking water
- Hydrogeologic conditions allowing construction of RBF systems 
- Availability of suitable land for RBF system installation
- Community receptiveness to installation of RBF systems and commitment to ongoing operation and maintenance </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Villages with less than 500 households
- Villages where untreated river water was not a primary source of drinking water for most households
- Villages where hydrogeologic conditions were unsuitable or land was not available for RBF system installation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Stepped wedge cluster randomised design involving random and sequential crossover of clusters (villages) from the control to the intervention arm so that every cluster eventually receives the intervention. This pragmatic study design allows for analysis of seasonal effects and inter-village variation, and allows all villages within the study to eventually receive the intervention, thus improving equity and acceptability. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size estimates were based on detecting an absolute difference in the 7-day period prevalence of diarrhoea (primary outcome) with 80% power and an alpha value of 0.05.   Estimates were obtained from pilot work conducted in Karnataka, India. Using these parameters, we estimated that 430 households (average household size of 5 persons) will need to be recruited from each village to detect a 30% reduction from a baseline diarrhoeal prevalence of 3%. To allow for attrition across repeat surveys, we plan to approach and recruit up to 750 households per village at baseline to ensure that adequate power will be retained for analysis of the primary outcome.

The data will be summarised using simple prevalences of diarrhoea for each cell in the stepped wedge design. Analyses will be conducted using a linear mixed model approach to estimate absolute reduction (with 95% confidence intervals) in overall prevalence of diarrhoea in the intervention periods (RBF-treated water) compared to control periods (piped unfiltered river water), taking into account trends over time common to all villages and clustering of individuals within villages.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>25/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>8600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>India</country>
      <state>Karnataka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Karin Leder</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine,
School of Public Heath and Preventive Medicine,
Monash University
Level 6 The Alfred Centre,
99 Commercial Road, 
Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Tom Boving</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Geosciences &amp; Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering
University of Rhode Island
Woodward Hall Rm. 314
Kingston, Rhode Island 02881</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Energy and Resources Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>6C Darbari Seth Block
India Habitat Centre
Lodhi Road
New Delhi 110003</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>India</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Access to a safe, reliable, and continuous supply of water for drinking, sanitation and hygiene is an essential requirement for good health. Diarrhoea is a leading cause of death and disease globally, and almost 90% of diarrhoea-related deaths occur as a result of unsafe drinking water and sanitation. India has the highest burden of childhood death and disease related to diarrhoea in Asia. Many people in rural India still cannot access improved water sources and gross disparities in coverage exist across the country. Affordable water treatment solutions that have beneficial human health effects and that can be maintained and sustained using local resources are needed. 

Riverbank filtration technology (RBF) is an inexpensive community-level water treatment technique that can improve water quality. RBF systems use auto-regenerative, natural treatment processes, so properly engineered systems can remain effective indefinitely. 

This study aims to investigate whether a community-based hygiene education program and water quality intervention using RBF technology reduces diarrhoeal prevalence in India over and above hygiene education plus improved access to water. We also aim to evaluate the feasability and acceptability of RBF technology in this setting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee (MUHREC) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>First Floor, Room 111
Chancellery Building E 
24 Sports Walk
Clayton Campus
Monash University VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF15/522-2015000248</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>TERI Institutional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Darbari Seth Block
IHC Complex
Lodhi Road
New Delhi 113 003
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF/15/522-2015000248</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>India</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Karin Leder</name>
      <address>Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine,
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine,
Monash University
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road, 
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0577</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karin.leder@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah McGuinness</name>
      <address>Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine,
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine,
Monash University
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road, 
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.mcguinness@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah McGuinness</name>
      <address>Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine,
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine,
Monash University
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road, 
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0118</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.mcguinness@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah McGuinness</name>
      <address>Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine,
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine,
Monash University
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road, 
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>