<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369877">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000339459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of a workplace-based hand therapy intervention on the return to work and clinical outcomes of injured workers with Lateral Epicondylalgia. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of a workplace-based hand therapy intervention on the return to work and clinical outcomes of injured workers with Lateral Epicondylalgia. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-2539</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lateral Epicondylalgia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention exposure is an additional workplace visit (to the usual clinic based treatment) by the treating hand therapists within the first four weeks of the initial appointment to identify risk factors associated with LE and provide specific education on pathology, activity modification, postures to avoid and recommendations tailored specifically to the patient in their workplace. The duration of this work site visit will be one hour. There is a work site visit form that will be used by all hand therapists when completing this work site visit. There are four common steps for all hand therapists to follow: (1) Identify the activities that the patient has difficulty at work (2) Assess the risk factors for LE in the workplace (3) Provide and demonstrate specific work recommendations to reduce the risk factors (4) Educate and inform the appropriate key parties. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group are those patients that receive normal hand therapy clinic-based treatment only. These treatments for LE are completed in the workplace and include prescription of orthoses, eccentric exercises, heat, soft tissue therapy and in clinic education on pathology and positions to avoid. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Durable Return to Work</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be measured from the day the patient receives a workers compensation claim (first medical certificate) to the day the claim is closed (final certificate from the medical practitioner). This outcome measure will be assessed by data linkage to workers compensation records. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Claims Cost</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be measured from the day the patient receives a workers compensation claim (first medical certificate) to the day the claim is closed (final certificate from the medical practitioner). This outcome measure will be assessed by data linkage to workers compensation records. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Claim Duration</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be measured from the day the patient receives a workers compensation claim (first medical certificate) to the day the claim is closed (final certificate from the medical practitioner). This outcome measure will be assessed by data linkage to workers compensation records. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain will be measured at the initial appointment, 6 weeks, 12 weeks and a follow up 1 year mark after the initial appointment using the Visual Analogue Scale. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain-free Grip Strength</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed at the initial, 6 week and 12 week and a follow up 1 year mark after the initial appointment using a calibrated Jamar Dynamometer. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Function will be assessed using the Patient Related Tennis Elbow Evaluation Assessment at the initial, 6 week and 12 week and 1 year mark after the initial appointment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:
*Male or female 
*Aged 18 to 65 years of age
*Clinically diagnosed with LE characterised by pain reproduced on at least 2/5 of these clinical tests: (1) resisted middle finger test (2) resisted wrist extension (3) resisted supination (4) palpation over LE (5) palpation over CETO
*Submitted a claim for workers compensation related to LE
*Unilateral only 
*Can be acute or chronic patients (Acute= &lt;3 months of symptoms, Chronic= &gt;3 months) 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if they have had any of the following in the past 6 months:
*Corticosteroid injection
*Blood injections (ABI, PRP) 
*Previous surgeries for the management of LE 
*Workers compensation claim is declined 
*Has other upper limb injuries
*If the patient works FIFO or in rural setting (whereby a worksite visit would not be possible) 
*Does not speak or understand English 
*Are unable to return to work duties due to intense LE symptoms
*Are unable to return to work on alternative work duties 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>There will be 180 pre-prepared opaque envelopes with n=90 that have a "Group A" and n=90 that have a "Group B" token in it. Group A= control group and Group B= Intervention group.  These envelopes are held by the admin staff member.  The allocation envelopes will be kept secret from the clinical staff who are directly involved in the trial so they are blinded to the allocation.  </concealment>
    <sequence>To get around the issue of the simple random allocation ending up with an imbalance of numbers on each side of the fence, Block randomisation will be used. The admin staff will start off with 30 mixed up opaque envelopes (15 Group A and 15 Group B). Once the treating hand therapist gain consent from the patient to be in the study, they will inform the admin staff member. The admin staff member will randomly pick out 1 of the 30 envelopes to allocate that patient into Group A or B. Once all 30 envelopes are distributed, then the next block of 30 will be used. This will continue until the desired 180 envelopes are distributed.  </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS, v. 22) will be used to perform data analysis. The level of statistical significance (P value) will be set at 0.05 for all statistical tests, allowing for a 5% risk of a Type-I error. Week 0 baseline demographics between the control and intervention groups will be compared to determine any differences. 

The differences in claims costs and claims duration between the comparison and experiment groups will be analysed using relevant parametric/non-parametric inferential statistics (e.g. independent t-tests, Mann-Whitney U tests, regression analyses to control for confounding factors). 

The differences in pain levels, grip strength and between the comparison and experiment group will be analysed by:
*Having continuous data compared;
*The best, worst and average visual analogue pain, grip strength and PRTEE scores and measurements will be calculated;
*Repeated measures two-way ANOVA will be used to test for any significant differences (p&lt;0.05) which will result within and between the comparison and experimental groups for all outcome measures; and
*The researcher performing the analysis will be blinded to whether data are from group A or B until after the data are analysed. 

Intention-to-treat analysis will be used to deal with data from any participants who drop out of the study or do not comply with the interventions to which they are allocated.

The study aims to include 180 participants (90 in each group), which is based on an a-level of 0.05 and a 1-beta of 0.8, as this will make it possible to detect a standardised difference of 0.4 between the two groups.  
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of OT and Social Work 
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NONE</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NONE</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Lateral Epicondylalgia (LE), also known as tennis elbow, is one of the most prevalent musculoskeletal disorders among the working population. Despite the numerous treatment methods available to manage the symptoms of this common condition, no sound clinical evidence is available to suggest long term relief and functional restoration for injured workers with LE. Workplace-based rehabilitation has been recognised in recent years to provide many benefits in the return to work process for injured workers for other health conditions. However, no studies have investigated this type of intervention for the management of LE. Consideration of the injured workers workplace as part of the rehabilitation program may not only possibly improve long term outcomes for workers with LE, but may also provide further information on preventative strategies to avoid the occurrence of LE. 
Purpose:  The primary purpose of this study is to investigate the impact of adding a workplace-based hand therapy intervention to the usual clinic-based approach on the return to work outcomes of injured workers with LE, compared to the usual clinic-based hand therapy intervention only. 
Method:  Mixed methodologies will be used in this study. A scoping review will be conducted to identify the effectiveness of current common conservative treatment methods for the management of LE and determine the impact of workplace-based interventions for the general management of injured workers in the return to work process.  Surveys will be distributed to identify the current practice trends of medical practitioners and hand therapists in the management LE. A randomised controlled trial (RCT) will be conducted to identify (i) any differences in primary outcomes of claims costs and claims duration on the return to work status of injured workers who receive usual care vs. usual care + workplace-based intervention and (ii) any differences in secondary outcomes of pain, grip strength and function of injured workers who receive usual care vs. usual care + workplace based intervention. Finally, focus groups will be used to identify the lived experience of these injured workers with LE within the workers compensation system. 
Expected Results:  The results from this study will inform the key stakeholders in the workers compensation system (employers, medical practitioners, insurance case managers, vocational rehabilitation providers, and hand therapists), to establish an evidence-based approach for the management of injured workers with LE. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16th March 2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Torbjorn Falkmer </name>
      <address>Curtin University
School of OT and Social Work
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 9051</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.falkmer@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Thuy Tran</name>
      <address>Hand Works Occupational Therapy
PO Box 362, Bull Creek WA   6149</address>
      <phone>+61 431653315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thuy.tran23@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Marina Ciccarelli</name>
      <address>Curtin University
School of OT and Social Work
Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3692</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>M.Ciccarelli@exchange.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Thuy Tran</name>
      <address>Tuart Hill WA 6060</address>
      <phone>+61 431653315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thuy.tran23@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>