<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369127">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000800325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical evaluation of a novel suture anchor for rotator cuff repairs  ATOK Anchor</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a novel suture anchor compared to a historical controls on repair integity and function in patients with rotator cuff tear.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-2414</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients over the age of 60, with a less than 3cm rotator cuff tear involving the supraspinatus and at least part of the infraspinatus tendons. Patients will have failed non-operative management.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Repair of rotator cuff tear using an arthroscopic technique, utilizing a new anchor to secure the transosseous sutures to the lateral humeral cortex.
The repair will idealy performed using an arthroscopic however a mini-open approach may be utilised if there is inadequate visualisation, or concerns about seating of the implant. 
 The novel anchor to be used is the Arthroscopic Trans-Osseous Knotless (ATOK) anchor.  Generally 2 anchors are used.  The procedure will be performed under a general anaesthetic and by an orthopaedic surgeon, who is the principal investigator.
The procedure is anticipate to take between 30 and 60 minutes and will where appropriate be combined with an acromioplasty, or lateral clavicle excision.
The anchor is inserted percutaneously through the lateral arm muscle and into the humeral cortex.  The suture are passed and secured using the locking plug.
There are no exactly similar studies on such a challenging group of patients, however, changes in outcome scores and displacement of anchors based on MRI review are the critical review end points. 
The patients will undergo the surgery between July 2015 and July 2016, with assessment of anchor position at 1 and 6 months, tendon healing at 6 months, and functional outcomes progressively from 3 months out to 2 years. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison controls will be with previously publlished series and relates to rupture and re-tear rate as well as functional outcomes.
The most relevent comparator published study is:
 Boileau P, Brassart N, Watkinson DJ, Carles M, Hatzidakis AM, Krishnan SG. Arthroscopic repair of full-thickness tears of the supraspinatus: does the tendon really heal? J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2005;87:12291240.

The initial study aim is to assess safety and general efficacy, but without the precision to compare to an alternate technique. 
The comparator is a benchmark study using arthroscopic repairs using standard techniques and a variety of anchors.  The outcomes are generally favourable using existing anchors, however, the new anchor aims to address difficult patients where the proximal humeral bone is quite osteoporotic and prone to lead to pull out of currently used anchors.
There are no exactly similar studies on such a challenging group of patients, however, changes in outcome scores and displacement of anchors based on MRI review are the critical review end points. 

Historical controls will those gleaned from published data which most closely matches the patient group.  There are not truly comparative cohort.  
</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Repair of rotator cuff tear, assessed by MRI; timepoint- 6 months post surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shoulder function, assessed on Constant, Oxford Shoulder Score </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-displacement of ATOK anchors as identified on MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>one month and 6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional outcome based on Constant and Oxford Sholder score</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with rotator cuff tears, less than 3cm, and over 60 years of age.
Failed 3 months of of targeted conservative therapy.
These patients are likely to have osteoporosis of the proximal humerus, but such bone changes will not be quantified.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Arthritis of the shoulder
Unable to understand the trial due to language or comprehension
Significant loss of motion</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The number of participants was determined on the number of potential patients likely to be recruited over a 12 month period.
This is a pilot study to assess anchor integrity and potential for displacement as well as ability to achieve rotator cuff healing at a rate, at least as good as existing published results.
Sample size calculation was not formally performed.  Once 20 patients have been recruited and followed for 12 months, a formal comparative trial will be considered.
At any stage if there is displacement of the anchors, the trial is likely to be terminated, unless there are reasons for the failure can be reasonable explained, such as technical error, or additional trauma.
Pre and 6, 12 and 24 month functional outcomes will be statistically compared.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Calvary Wakefield Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Parkwynd Private Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>St Andrew's Hospital Inc - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assoc Prof Michael Sandow</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wakefield Orthopaedic Clinic
270 Wakefield Street,
Adelaide
SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wright Medical</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>3/17 Rodborough Rd, Frenchs Forest 
NSW 2086

 PO Box 6052, 
Frenchs Forest NSW 1640, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Macropace Products Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>14 Hauteville Terrace
Eastwood SA 5063</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose of study to investigate the safety and efficacy of a novel attempt to achieve trans osseous repair of disrupted or torn rotator cuff using the knotless technique.

This is essentially a safety and efficacy trial to confirm the biomechanical advantages in a clinical setting of the recently designed arthroscopic trans-osseous knotless technique using an ATOK implant.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, Royal Adelaide Hospital  </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital :-
Level 4, Womens Health Centre, Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace, Adelaide  SA  5000
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/RAH/40 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369127-ANZORS Abstract_CFJ_21June2014.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Sandow FRACS</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic Clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide
Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8236 4166</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msandow@woc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Sandow FRACS</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic Clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide
Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8236 4166</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msandow@woc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Sandow FRACS</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic Clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8236 4166</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msandow@woc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Sandow FRACS</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic Clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide</address>
      <phone>+61 82364166</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msandow@woc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>