<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="950">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/12/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000794606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled crossover study on the effects of 100mg, three times daily, Z-338 on the symptomatic response to a nutrient challenge and gasteric nutrient distribution and emptying in subjects with and without functional dyspepsia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled crossover study on the effects of 100mg, three times daily, Z-338 on the symptomatic response to a nutrient challenge and gasteric nutrient distribution and emptying in subjects with and without functional dyspepsia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Functional dyspepsia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Recent studies have demonstrated that various pharmacologic treatments including proton pump inhibitors (PPI) and prokinetics and psychological treatments improve the symptoms in subjects with functional dyspepsia. The mode of action of gastroprokinetic drugs is via various receptor mechanisms, which include action at motlin receptors, serotonin receptors, dopamine receptors and/or acetylcholinesterase.The effects of treatment with the study drug Z-338 yielded significant improvement of symptoms in functional dyspepsia in a well controlled study in Japan. The aim of this study, therefore, is to assess in healthy controls and subjects with functional dyspepsia the effects of the study drug Z-338 on the type and severity of symptoms during standardized nutrient challenge, the gastric nutrient distribution and gastric emptying of a standardized nutrient challenge and the association of the prior mentioned points with manifestations of symptoms and symptom pattern.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo will be provided to participants instead of the study drug Z-338.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the improvement of meal related symptoms in healthy controls and subjects with functional dyspepsia during treatment with Z-338.</outcome>
      <timepoint>subject completes assessments 60 days after commencing treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The influence of the treatment on the regional nutrient distribution (%) of ingested test meal in the proximal and distal stomach.</outcome>
      <timepoint>subject completes assessments 60 days after commencing treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes of gastric emptying and the link of regional gastric nutrient distribution/gastric emptying and improvement of meal related symptoms referred to the upper stomach occurs (i.e. pain, nausea, fullness and discomfort) will be analyzed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>subject completes assessments 60 days after commencing treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(Subjects with no history of functional dyspepsia):1) Clinical assessment, physical examination and laboratory testing without evidence for relevant abnormality (e.g. no need for further clinical testing)Inclusion criteria (Subjects with functional dyspepsia):1) Diagnosis of functional dyspepsia according to Rome II criteria and three or more moderate symptoms of Gastrointestinal Symptom Score.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(All subjects):1) previous abdominal or gynaecological surgery (except appendectomies, vaginal hysterectomy, diagnostic laparscope and other as determined by Investigator).2) previous gastrointestinal cancer, previous malignancy, except non-metastatic basak or squamous cell carcinoma cancer within the last five years.3) known current peptic ulcer disease4) predominant gastro-esophageal reflux symptoms or Irritable Bowel Syndrome.5) pregnancy or breast feeding6) Treatment with antibiotics 8 weeks prior7) Taking acid suppressing medications (proton pump inhibitors, histamine 2 receptor antagonist, antacids), prokinetics (e.g. Cisapride, Maroon) for 2 weeks.8) Diabetes on continuous medical therapy9) clinically relevant cardiovascular disease (as assessed by the Investigator)10) Any clinically relevant uncontrolled medical condition (as assessed by the investigator)11) No other clinical trials within the last 30 days12) Subject has not been a volunteer in any other research projects which have involved radioactivity exposure in the last twelve months.13) Subject testing positive for Helicobacter pylori.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study is a randomised crossover design in which both groups take placebo and active drug at different intervals of the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Healthy volunteers will be assigned to a unique sequence of numbers, diagnosed functional dyspepsia patients will be assigned a seperate unique number sequencing system.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zeria Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>10-11 Nihonbashi Kobuna-Cho, Chuo-Ku 103-8351, Tokyo</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Japan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Zeria Pharmaceutial Co., Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10-11 Nihonbashi Kobuna-Cho, Chuo-Ku 103-8351, Tokyo</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Japan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Kendle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>1200 Carew Tower, 441 Vine Street, Cincinnati, Ohio 45202</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Zeria Pharmaceutical Co. Ltd is studying an investigational drug called Z-338.  This drug is not available for sale in the United States or Australia.  Z-338 is being studied as a possible treatment for functional dyspepsia (FD).  FD is a disease that causes various abdominal symptoms such as fullness, stomach pain, nausea, early satiety and bloating.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Gerald Holtman</name>
      <address>Gasteroenterology, Hepatology and General Medicine Department
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace 
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82225207</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gholtman@mail.rah.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lee-Anne Faraguna (study co-ordinator)</name>
      <address>Gasteroenterology, Hepatology and General Medicine Department
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace 
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82225827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>LFaragun@mail.rah.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>