<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371612">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001586404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of a pulmonary rehabilitation program of 8 weeks duration compared to 12 weeks on exercise capacity in people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (PuRe Duration): A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a pulmonary rehabilitation program of 8 weeks duration compared to 12 weeks on exercise capacity in people with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (PuRe Duration): A randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-4919</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PuRe Duration</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Exercise training in a pulmonary rehabilitation program twice per week for 12 weeks. Programs are completed in an outpatient hospital setting and run by physiotherapists. Each training session will run for between 1 - 1.5 hours.

Exercise training will consist of overground or treadmill walking, lower limb cycling, lower limb strengthening exercises (including body weight exercises; squats, sit to stands and step-ups and fixed weight exercises; leg press and leg extension) and upper limb exercises (including arm ergometry, lat pull-downs, chest press/fly and arm exercises with free weights).

Initial exercise intensities will be standardised for each modality. Walking (overground or treadmill) will begin at 80% of peak walk speed determined by the six-minute walk test (6MWT) and progressed based on symptoms of dyspnoea and fatigue, with the aim of participants scoring a dyspnoea or fatigue score of at least 3-4 ('moderate' to 'somewhat severe') on the modified Borg dyspnoea 0-10 scale. Initial walking duration will be 10-15 minutes and progressed to 20-30 minutes between weeks 2-4.
Lower limb cycling intensity will commence at 60% peak work rate using an equation based on the results of the 6MWT and progressed to 70% peak work rate based on symptoms of dyspnoea and fatigue, with the aim of participants scoring a dyspnoea or fatigue score of at least 3-4 on the modified Borg dyspnoea 0-10 scale.
Arm ergometry will be performed for 10 minutes at a Borg score of 3-4 on the modified Borg dyspnoea 0-10 scale.

Body weight lower limb strengthening exercises (squats, sit to stands and step ups) and arm free weight exercises will commence in week 2 at a load that can be achieved for 8 -10 repetitions before local muscle exhaustion. Fixed weight strengthening exercises for the lower limbs and upper limbs (leg extension, leg press, lat pull downs and chest press/fly) will commence in week 3 at a load that can be achieved for 8 -10 repetitions before local muscle exhaustion. By week 4, all strengthening exercise (body weight, free weight and fixed weight exercises) will be completed 3 times (i.e 3 sets). Resistances will be increased once participants can achieve 3 sets of 10 repetitions in two or more consecutive training sessions.

Attendance will be monitored by the physiotherapists and participants will be encouraged to attend each allocated session. </interventions>
    <comparator>Exercise training in a pulmonary rehabilitation program twice per week for eight weeks. Programs are completed in an outpatient hospital setting and run by physiotherapists. Each training session will run for between 1 - 1.5 hours.

The exercise training component will be the same as the intervention group.

Attendence will be monitored by the physiotherpists and participants will be encouraged to attend each allocated session. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endurance Shuttle Walk Test (ESWT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks, eight weeks, 12 weeks, six months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>St George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks, eight weeks, 12 weeks, six months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>COPD Assessment Test (CAT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks, eight weeks, 12 weeks, six months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale (HADS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks, eight weeks, 12 weeks, six months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity via Actigraph and ActivPAL</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, seven weeks, completion of pulmonary rehabilitation program (eight or 12 weeks respectively), six months and 12 months.
Physical activity monitors will be worn for 1 week at each timepoint.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a) have a medical diagnosis of COPD [forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1)/ forced vital capacity (FVC) &lt;0.7 and an FEV1 between 20% and 80% predicted normal].

b) Referred to pulmonary rehabilitation.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a) morbidly obese (BMI &gt; 35  [kg/m2]).

b) receiving long term oxygen therapy (LTOT).

c) co-morbidities; either musculoskeletal, cardiovascular or neurological which would adversely affect exercise performance.

d) have participated in a supervised exercise program within the last 12 months.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly allocated, following informed consent, into one of two groups: an eight week or 12 week pulmonary rehabilitation program. Computerised, stratification randomisation will be completed for each consenting participant by a person independent of the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation will be determined using a computer-generated randomisation program with a minimisation algorithm, stratifying for centre, gender, FEV1% &lt;50% predicted, six minute walk distance (6MWD) &lt;350m, oxygen desaturation during 6MWT &lt;90%, and recent exacerbation of COPD (&lt;4 weeks).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation was based for a significance level of 0.05 and a power of 0.8 with a standard deviation of the ESWT of 239 seconds (1). 58 participants are required to be 80% sure that the two-sided confidence interval will exclude a difference of the mean by 186 seconds (2,3). To allow for 15% dropout 68 participants will be recruited.

Data will be analysed using SPSS, and expressed as means and standard deviations. Repeated measures ANOVA will analyse differences between the groups for all outcomes. Independent sample t-tests will assess the differences between groups at specific time points. Data will be analysed on an intention-to-treat (ITT) basis.

1.	Leung RW, McKeough ZJ, Peters MJ, Alison JA. Short-form Sun-style t'ai chi as an exercise training modality in people with COPD. EurRespir J. 2013;41(5):1051-7.
2.	Pepin V, Laviolette L, Brouillard C, Sewell L, Singh SJ, Revill SM, et al. Significance of changes in endurance shuttle walking performance. Thorax. 2011;66(2):115-20.
3.	Holland AE, Spruit MA, Troosters T, et al. An official European Respiratory Society/American Thoracic Society Technical Standard: field walking tests in chronic respiratory disease. EurRespir J. 2014; 44: 1428-46.6. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>68</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Joshua Bishop</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Balmain Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
29 Booth Street 
BALMAIN, NSW, 2041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Local Health District</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 11, KGV Building
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN, NSW, 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pulmonary rehabilitation (PR) guidelines and reviews of current research repeatedly state that PR programs should be between six and 12 weeks, with a recommended duration of eight weeks, but have been unable to draw significant conclusions regarding an optimal duration of PR programs to achieve improvements in exercise capacity and health-related quality of life.  

Aim : To evaluate the effect of an eight week pulmonary rehabilitation program compared to a 12 week program on exercise capacity and quality of life in people with COPD. 

Hypothesis: An eight week PR program is equivalent to a 12 week PR program at improving exercise capacity in people with COPD. 

Design: This is a multi-centre study where 68 participants will be recruited from pulmonary rehabilitation sites across the Sydney Local Health District. A randomised controlled trial design will be used with participants randomally allocated to one of two groups:
1. an eight week PR program or
2. a 12 week PR program.
Participants will be asked to complete exercise tests and questionnaires at baseline, four weeks, eight weeks, 12 weeks, six months and 12 months follow-up. 
Participants will also be asked to wear physical activity monitors at baseline, seven weeks, at completion of their respective exercise programs (eight weeks or 12 weeks), six months and 12 months  follow-up.
This research will determine if an eight week PR program is equivalent to a 12 week PR program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Research Ethics Committee (RPAH zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN, NSW, 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joshua Bishop</name>
      <address>Balmain Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
29 Booth Street,
BALMAIN, NSW, 2041</address>
      <phone>+61293952093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joshua.bishop@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joshua Bishop</name>
      <address>Balmain Hospital
Physiotherapy Department
29 Booth Street,
BALMAIN, NSW, 2041</address>
      <phone>+61293952093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joshua.bishop@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joshua Bishop</name>
      <address>Balmain Hospital 
Physiotherapy Department
29 Booth Street,
BALMAIN, NSW, 2041</address>
      <phone>+61293952093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joshua.bishop@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>