<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335811">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000717055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ReCaPTure LiFe: A phase II cluster-randomised controlled trial of a psychological intervention to support young people with cancer and their families to make a positive transition from cancer patient to survivor.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>ReCaPTure LiFe: A phase II cluster-randomised controlled trial of a psychological intervention to support young people with cancer and their families to make a positive transition from cancer patient to survivor.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ReCaPTure LiFe: Resilience and Coping skills for young People and To Live well Following cancer treatment</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Distress, psychological adjustment and coping after cancer treatment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are 2 arms to this trial. Arm 1: 'ReCaPTure LiFe', a cognitive-behavioural intervention. Arm 2: Supportive Counselling. A third group will be randomised to a 12-week waitlist until the post-intervention assessments of the other groups are complete, at which point they will be randomly allocated to one of the other two arms. 'ReCaPTure LiFe' will be delivered in 6 x 90-minute group sessions, delivered weekly over the internet using web-conferencing technology and by a clinical psychologist. These sessions will focus on the acquisition and application of cognitive-behavioural skills, such as cognitive restructuring and problem-solving, to the experience of returning to normality post cancer treatment. There is also a one-off 'booster' session 6-weeks following the completion of the main 6-session group program. The intervention will be offered to adolescents and young adults (AYAs) aged 15-25 years who are 1-12 months post active treatment. Participants will complete a 1-week, 3-month and 12-month follow-up, after which their study participation will conclude. </interventions>
    <comparator>The Supportive Counselling condition uses the same group format, delivered over the internet by a clinical psychologist for six, weekly, 90 minute sessions. This therapy includes nondirective counselling that does not include any Cognitive Behaviour Therapy components, but will instead simply give young cancer survivors an open forum to discuss their experience. There is also a one-off 'booster' session 6-weeks following the completion of the main 6-session group program. The intervention will be offered to adolescents and young adults (AYAs) aged 15-25 years who are 1-12 months post active treatment. Participants will complete a 1-week, 3-month, and 12-month follow-up, after which their study participation will conclude. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, anxiety and stress symptoms as measured by the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale - Short Form (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment, 1 week Follow-Up, 12-Month Follow-Up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of Cancer Scale (IOCS) to measure cancer-specific changes in quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment, 1 week Follow-Up, 3-month follow-up, 12-Month Follow-Up  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>KIDCOPE-Older Version will be used to assess adaptive coping strategies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment, 1 week Follow-Up, 3-month follow-up, 12-Month Follow-Up  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family interactions and communication will be measured using three subscales from the McMaster Family Assessment Device  (FAD; Epstein, Baldwin L.M., &amp; Bishop, 1983), including Problem Solving (5 items), Communication (6 items), and General Functioning (12 items) subscales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment, 3-Month Follow-Up, 12-Month Follow-Up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Centrality of Event Scale-Short Form, to measure the ongoing impact of the cancer in terms of young people's perceptions of their identity and life goals. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment, 3-Month Follow-Up, 12-Month Follow-Up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*  Eligible participants will be (1) Young cancer survivors who have finished treatment and are aged 15-25; (2) Able to give informed consent; (3) Fluent in English; (4) able to provide the name and contact details of a trusted health professional (e.g., local general practitioner, family doctor or hospital social worker); and 5) be able to access the Internet in a private location Young people who have previously relapsed (and are finished relapse treatment) will be encouraged to participate. Internet access and a suitable computer set-up is a requirement to participate in Recapture Life-AYA. This includes access to a computer/laptop which has a microphone and web-camera, and is located such that the participant will be able to participate in the sessions comfortably and in a private and uninterrupted capacity once per week for six weeks. AYAs without access to these resources will be able to borrow a laptop, web-camera, microphone and/or wireless internet connection device for the duration of the study (the costs ofwhich are covered by a project grant). The equipment and internet needs of all AYA participants will be assessed at the initial telephone intake interview,and access issues managed on a case-by-case basis.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals may not participate if they 
(1)  cannot speak English;
(2)  exhibit suicidal intent, psychotic features, or substance dependence;
(3)  are receiving active treatment, or palliative care. This includes if a patient has recently relapsed and is still in active treatment; they and their family will be excluded, as their needs will be difficult to manage within the protocol, and their inclusion might also negatively affect others in their group.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited 0-12 months after treatment completion, from one of several interstate hospital sites. Each potential participant will be sent a personalised invitation letter from their oncologist, a consent form and an opt-in card. Participants who opt-in will be placed on a waiting list for the next intervention. Group allocation will occur by personnel holding the allocation schedule located at another, separate off-site location, thus ensuring allocation concealment during the process of determining participant eligibility. Participants will be blinded to their intervention assignment, as both arms of the trial will be referred to as a 'peer support and education group for young cancer survivors off-treatment'.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised using an electronic randomiser (using a random number system) implemented by independent personnel located at a distant site from the primary researchers.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This trial will employ Intention to treat and as treated analyses. Analyses will be based on mixed random-intercept models which will assess differences between the groups in terms of change in QoL from T1 to T2, and from T1 to T3. Random intercept models, which utilise maximum-likelihood estimation, provide more efficient estimates of effects with unbalanced data than the traditional repeated measures approach (Myung, 2003). Analyses will follow recent commentaries on the best way to manage missing data by employing multiple imputation techniques. Multiple regression analyses will also be conducted using T1 data to identify demographic and other factors that contribute to treatment outcome. Multiple comparisons will be used to test a priori and post-hoc hypotheses, appropriately adjusted to maintain the nominated Type I error rate.
A sample size of 90 (assuming equal numbers in each group, and a correlation between T1 and T2 of .6) will allow differences of d=0.65 (calculated as the difference in change from T1 to T2 for any pair of groups, standardised on the pooled within-group standard deviation)- a medium-large effect- on the primary outcome variable (QoL) to be detected with a power of 80% at a significance level of 0.05 (two-tailed). This effect size is clinically significant55 and is based on other RCTs of similar interventions for AYAs with chronic illness (eg., Channon et al., 2007; Hampel et al., 2003). It is anticipated that approximately 220 patients will need to be approached to achieve a final sample of 90 participants (assuming a response rate of 50% and attrition rate of 20%, based on our previous research. This is feasible, based on estimates the potentially eligible AYAs treated annually at our recruiting sites, which include: NSW AYA Service (~140 patients), the Victorian AYA Service (~100 eligible patients), SCH (~15 patients), Childrens Hospital at Westmead (~20 patients), Sir Charles Gardner Hospital, Perth (~30 patients) and the AYA Cancer Service, Womens and Childrens Hospital, Adelaide (~20 patients). These sites will yield a possible pool of 325 patients eligible for the study during the recruitment phase.

REFERENCES
Channon et al. A multicenter randomized controlled trial of motivational interviewing in teenagers with diabetes. Diabetes Care 2007;30:1390-5.
Hampel et al. Multimodal patient education program with stress management for childhood and adolescent asthma. Patient Educ Couns 2003;49:59-66.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology,
University of New South Wales,
Anzac Parade,
Kensington, Sydney, 2052,
NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Children's Cancer &amp; Blood Disorders</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, South Wing,
Sydney Children's Hospital,
High Street,
Randwick, Sydney, 2031,
NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia (co-funded grant in 2012 with Beyond Blue)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 3, STRAWBERRY HILLS NSW 2012

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Beyond Blue (co-funded grant in 2012 with Cancer Australia)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100 Hawthorn West
Victoria, Australia 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sydney Children's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Kids Cancer Centre, Level 1, South Wing, Sydney Children's Hospital, High Street, Randwick, Sydney, 2031, NSW </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at the effectiveness of a psychological therapy designed to support young people with cancer and their families to make a positive transition from cancer patient to survivor. Who is it for? You can join this study if you are a young cancer survivor aged 15-25 who has finished treatment for either a primary or secondary cancer in the past 12 months. Trial details: Participants will be divided into two groups. One group will take part in 'ReCaPTure LiFe', a cognitive-behavioural program designed to help people build skills to return to normality after cancer treatment. This will take place in six 90-minute group sessions, delivered weekly over the internet. Participants will complete a 1-week, 3-month and 12-month follow-up. The second group will take part in an open discussion forum with the same schedule. The study aims to monitor the distress, psychological adjustment and coping after cancer treatment. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Sansom-Daly, U.M., Wakefield, C.E., Bryant, R.A., Butow, P., Sawyer, S., Patterson, P., Anazodo, A., Thompson, K., Cohn, R.J. (2012). Online group-based cognitive-behavioural therapy for adolescents and young adults after cancer treatment: A multicenter randomised controlled trial of Recapture Life-AYA. BMC Cancer, 12: 339. URL: http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2407/12/339/abstract. DOI: 10.1186/1471-2407-12-339.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District- Northern Section Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office G71, East Wing Edmund Blacket Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Wakefield</name>
      <address>Kids Cancer Centre, Level 1 South Wing Sydney Children's Hospital High Street Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>(+612) 9382 3113</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.wakefield@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Wakefield</name>
      <address>Kids Cancer Centre, Level 1 South Wing Sydney Children's Hospital High Street Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>(+612) 9382 3113</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.wakefield@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Ursula Sansom-Daly</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Matthews Building
The University of New South Wales
Anzac Parade
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>ursula@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Wakefield</name>
      <address>Kids Cancer Centre, Level 1 South, Sydney Children's Hospital, Randwick NSW 2031.</address>
      <phone>(+612) 9382-3113</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.wakefield@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>