<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364942">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001021763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treatment of disordered blood pressure in spinal cord injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blind, placebo controlled, crossover study of a nocturnal dose of captopril to determine its effect on diurnal blood pressure and orthostatic symptoms in people with spinal cord injury</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1147-8242 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Orthostatic intolerance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypotension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diurnal blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nocturnal polyuria</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Spinal cord injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Captopril, orally, nightly, starting at 25mg and uptitrating by 25mg a week to a maximum of 100mg over a 4 week titration phase, followed by maintenance phase for 4 weeks at the highest dose reached. Unused capsules to be returned at the end of each treatment arm. Washout period of 2 weeks between treatment arms.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - microcellulose capsule 
Placebo and captopril capsules are packaged to look identical</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean daytime blood pressure - measured by ambulatory blood pressure monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after each treatment arm</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of nocturnal dipping - ratio of mean night:day systolic blood pressure as measured by ambulatory blood pressure monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after each treatment arm</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Orthostatic hypotension questionnaire symptom scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after each treatment arm</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nocturnal urine production - volume of urine produced overnight expressed as a percentage of the entire day's urine volume; calculated from a diary kept over 3 consecutive days</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after each treatment arm</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Traumatic spinal cord injury
Age 18 years or greater
Able to provide informed consent
Symptoms of orthostatic intolerance</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known hypersensitivity to captopril or any other ACE inhibitor
Significant renal impairment
Persistent hyperkalaemia
Recent changes or titration of antihypertensive agents or intention to do so within duration of study
Presence of any other significant medical conditions likely to influence ability to co-operate or prevent adherence to protocol, or where treatment with captopril would put the participant at increased risk of adverse events or drug interactions
Pregnancy or breastfeeding</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolled participants are allocated sequential randomisation numbers, where the randomisation schedule is held by the Department of Pharmacy, hence the investigators, assessors and participants remain blinded to treatment allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample demographics, blood pressure and symptom scores will be described using descriptive and summary statistics. Comparisons of symptoms, blood pressure, autonomic function and urine measures between the treatment and placebo groups will be made using parametric (e.g. paired t-tests) or repeated measures analysis of variance as appropriate. Blood pressure will also be plotted across assessment points. Blood pressure, autonomic functioning and urine measures will be correlated with symptoms. 

Assuming a total of 25 patients enter this two-treatment crossover study, the probability is 80 percent that the study will detect a treatment difference at a two-sided 0.05 significance level, if the true difference between treatments is 10 mmHg. This is based on the assumption that the within-patient standard deviation of the systolic blood pressure is 12 mmHg.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Austin Hospital 
145 Studley Road 
Heidelberg Vic 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Transport Accident Commission</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6, 60 Brougham Street
Geelong, VIC 3220
Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Spinal cord injury (SCI) results in permanent paralysis and significant disability. In addition, some spinal cord injured people experience postural hypotension, a large drop in blood pressure when assuming the upright position, associated with dizziness and fainting. For someone with SCI who is wheelchair dependent, fainting can have significant consequences such as further injury from falling out of the chair, reduced independence and limited vocational outcomes, thus poorer overall physical and psychological well-being.
In SCI, interruption of nervous communications, along with the loss of muscle pump in the legs, results in the impaired ability to maintain blood pressure on getting upright. Such persons have an abnormal pattern of blood pressure, whereby the blood pressure does not drop overnight, unlike the usual pattern. In some cases, there is even a higher blood pressure during the night than during the day  opposite to the normal pattern.
Higher night time blood pressure leads to increased night time urine production, leaving the body with relatively less circulating blood volume in the morning, at the time that one is about to get out of bed, further contributing to postural hypotension.
This study aims to examine the effects of treatment with captopril, a blood pressure lowering medication, at night, in a person with SCI who experiences symptoms of postural hypotension; we hypothesise that lowering night time blood pressure will reduce night time urine production, therefore increase blood pressure during the day, and reduce symptoms of postural hypotension, allowing the ability to stay upright during the day to carry out activities.
In this placebo controlled crossover study, participants will receive either the drug treatment or a placebo (dummy pill) for 8 weeks, and then switch to the other pill to determine if there is a difference in effects between the two. Each treatment period will be separated by two weeks where the participant is not on
either pill. Before and after each treatment, assessments include: measurements of blood pressure profile over 24 hours using an automatic portable monitor, recording urine volumes for 4 days, analysis of urine and blood samples.
Current treatment for such blood pressure disturbances and symptoms of low blood pressure are inadequate, and this study will help to determine whether this novel treatment is effective.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.sciautonomic.com/index.html</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research,
Austin LifeSciences
Austin Health
PO Box 5555
Heidelberg
Victoria
Australia, 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2013 / 04981</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher O'Callaghan</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology
Harold Stokes Building Level 5
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
PO Box 5555
Heidelberg Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>61 3 9496 5029</phone>
      <fax>61 3 9496 3221</fax>
      <email>christopher.o'callaghan@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Melinda Millard</name>
      <address>Victorian Spinal Cord Service
Harold Stokes Building Level 8
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
PO Box 5555
Heidelberg Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>61 3 9496 5906</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melinda.millard@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Min Yin Goh</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology
Harold Stokes Building Level 5
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
PO Box 5555
Heidelberg Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>61 3 9496 5029</phone>
      <fax>61 3 9496 3221</fax>
      <email>min.goh@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>