<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372714">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000657325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lisdexamfetamine for the treatment of methamphetamine addiction</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised double blind placebo controlled study of lisdexamfetamine for the treatment of methamphetamine dependence</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1195-2142</utrn>
    <trialacronym>LiMA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Addiction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Methamphetamine dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Week 1 (Induction): 150mg lisdexamfetamine capsules taken orally, daily 
Weeks 2-13 (Maintenance phase): 250mg lisdexamfetamine capsules taken orally, daily 
Weeks 14-15 (Reduction): 150mg lisdexamfetamine capsules taken orally, daily for 1 week, then 50mg lisdexamfetamine capsules daily taken orally,daily for a further week 

A contracted Good Manufacturing Practicing (GMP) facility will over encapsulate active (lisdexamfetamine size 3 capsule into a size zero capsule with microcrystalline cellulose to prevent any movement. 
The GMP facility shall package and label the study medication in daily blister packs. . These blister packs shall be further packaged into boxes (kits) and shipped to the relevant pharmacy departments. 
Each individual blister pack and each kit shall include the name and strength of the drug along with all other warnings and instructions necessary to fulfil the requirements of the Poisons and Therapeutic Goods Act 1966 and the Poisons and Therapeutic Goods Regulation 2008
Each kit shall be dispended by a pharmacist and provided to an appropriately qualified nurse, who will supervise the administration of the medication (from a daily blister pack) to the participant.  The participant will take home the kit containing the remainder of the labelled daily blister packs.
At initial research interview, participants will be counselled on strategies to promote medication adherence using a modified version of the COMBINE to draw up an initial medication adherence plan check which will be conducted at subsequent research assessments. Adherence will be assessed through self-report and pill counts and conduct counselling to promote adherence using the brief medication adherence check session worksheet. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Daily placebo for the 15 week duration of the trial treatment. Size zero placebo capsules containing microcrystalline cellulose (to mimic that of the active capsule) will be used

The routine 4-session manualised Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT) program developed by Baker et al will be provided by trained therapists to all participants in the trial. 
For the purpose of this study, therapists are defined as staff with graduate qualifications in a relevant health discipline (such as counselling, nursing, social work, psychology, psychiatry), including trainees with adequate skills, that have undergone training on the use of the manual.
For patients that meet the eligibility criteria of the study, a copy of the trial documentation completed at screening will be provided to the therapist for the purpose of an initial assessment.  
Therapists will co-ordinate four 1 hour sessions to occur at least one week apart, between weeks 2 and 13 (i.e.  during the maintenance dose treatment period) 


</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine the efficacy of oral lisdexamfetamine in reducing methamphetamine use compared to placebo in people who are dependent on methamphetamine. 
This outcome will be assessed using the Timeline Follow back Questionnaire (patient reported drug use) self reports. In addition, urine samples will be collected and analysed for methamphetamine. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine the safety of oral lisdexamfetamine  in people who are dependent on methamphetamine.
Safety will be assessed using a number of measures as follows:
Vitals signs (Blood pressure, pulse, temperature, respiratory rate)
Electrocardiogram
Physical assessments
Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (Psychosis &amp; hostility items)
21-item Depression and Anxiety Scale
Adverse Events: Any spontaneously reported adverse events will be recorded after the subject signs the informed consent form. In addition, adverse events will be elicited using
a non-leading question each time the subject visits the clinic.
Many of the side effects that have been associated with lisdexamfetamine are also seen in methamphetamine use and include: 
* loss of appetite (25 out of 100 people)
* dry mouth (23 out of 100 people) 
* headache (20 out of 100 people)
* trouble sleeping (16 out of100 people)
* diarrhoea (6 out of 100 people)
* agitation, anxiety, aggression, irritability, feeling jittery, feeling tired, feeling sleepy, dizziness, and restlessness (5 out of 100 people)
* nausea (5 out of 100 people) 
* weight loss (4 out of 100 people)
* upper stomach area pain (1 out of 100 people)
* vomiting (less than 1 out of 100 people)
Medications in this drug class can also cause:
* rash and fever
* shortness of breath, excessive sweating, and excessive widening of the pupil
* decreased sex drive and erectile dysfunction
* excessive motor activity with or without feelings of restlessness
* tic, tremor
* rapid heartbeat (tachycardia), palpitations, increased blood pressure
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine the abuse liability profile of oral lisdexamfetamine in people who are dependent on methamphetamine.
This outcome will be assessed using the Abuse Liability modified DEQ-5 questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine changes in physical health, mental health and wellbeing in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo. 
This is a composite endpoint and will be assessed using the Patient Health Questionnaire  15 (PHQ-15) and the Short Form-12 Health Survey (SF-12) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine differences in retention rates in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo.
Retention rates of participants between arms will be examined by the number of patients that completed treatment (i.e. number of patients that completed week 13)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 13</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine differences in amphetamine cravings in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo
This outcome will be assessed using a Visual Analogue Scale for cravings</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine differences in use of other drugs of abuse (alcohol, cocaine, opioids, cannabis and benzodiazepines) in the study populations between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo.
This is a composite secondary outcomes and will be assessed using the Timeline Follow back Questionnaire (patient reported drug use) self reports and urine drug screens.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine differences in blood borne virus transmission risk behaviour in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo
This outcome will be assessed using the Opioid Treatment Index  Injecting (OTI-I) Section III: HIV Risk-Taking Behaviour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine difference in criminality in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo.
This outcome will be assessed using the Treatment Index Crime (OTI-C) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the cost effectiveness of lisdexamfetamine relative to the placebo control.
This outcome will be assessed using a number of methods as follows:
Additional questions will be included on the OTI-C to determine related costs of any criminal offense committed during the timeframe of the study, and any relevant criminal justice costs.
The EQ-5D-5L will contribute to the estimation of quality-adjusted life years 
A Health Services Utilisation questionnaire will be used to assess work time lost to attend treatment and any changes /differences in productivity due to having undertaken treatment.  
Travel time and costs for participants will be collected at a single time point (week 5) and  averaged across their number of attendances
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine differences in amphetamine withdrawal in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo
This outcome will be assessed using the Amphetamine Withdrawal Questionnaire (AWQ) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine differences in amphetamine severity of dependence in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo
This outcome will be assessed using the Severity of Dependence Scale (SDS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 5, 9, 13, and 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine changes in cognitive and psychosocial functioning in the study population between those taking oral lisdexamfetamine compared to placebo. 
This outcome will be measured by the following battery of neurocognitive tests and validated patient surveys:
Wechsler test of adult reading (WTAR)
Montreal Cognitive Assessment  (MOCA) 
Trail-making test 
Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Task (RAVLT) 
Flankers task
Rapid Visual Information  Processing (RVIP) 
Digit-Symbol 
N-Back 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 1, 5, 9, 13 and 19 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Seeking treatment for methamphetamine use.
Meet ICD-10 criteria for methamphetamine dependence for at least 12 months.
Self-reported methamphetamine use at least 14 days out of the previous 28.
One urine drug screen positive for methamphetamine within 7 days prior to enrolment. 
Have previously attempted but not responded to treatment for methamphetamine use (relapse to dependent use within 1 month of completing treatment).
Participants must have the ability to store study medication securely
Willing and able to comply with requirements of the study.
Willing and able to provide written, informed consent to participate in the study
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current active counselling based treatment for methamphetamine dependence 
Use of prescribed dexamphetamine in the previous four weeks.
Dependent use of alcohol or non-prescribed substances other than amphetamines (including gamma-hydroxybutyrate, cocaine, benzodiazepines and opioids) diagnosed by specialist clinical assessment against ICD-10 criteria.
Lactating, pregnant or childbearing potential not willing to avoid becoming pregnant during the study.
Sensitivity or previous adverse reaction to lisdexamfetamine. 
Severe and active medical disorder (e.g. cardiovascular disease, uncontrolled hypertension, peripheral vascular disease, assessed by study medical officer
Severe psychiatric disorder (e.g. acute psychosis, severe anxiety and/or mood disorder, intent to harm self or others assessed by study medical officer and/or psychiatrist).
History of glaucoma, hyperthyroidism, phaeochromocytoma, motor and phonic tics and Tourettes syndrome;
Current use of medications that could interact with study medication: venlafaxine, desvenlafaxine, or monoamine oxidase inhibitor use in previous 14 days.
Not available for follow-up (e.g. likely travel or imprisonment).
Exposure to any investigational drug within the 4 weeks prior to screening
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be performed by an independent statistician </concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated randomisation schedule has been developed and participants will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio between groups using variable block randomisation to help maintain blinding, stratified by site. The next treatment schedule will only be known by the independent statistician. Once a patient is randomised to the trial this randomisation will not be cancelled. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Mixed Models for Repeated Measures will compare groups on changes in outcome variables (days of  methamphetamine use derived from self report interview data) in the maintenance medication phase (weeks 2 - 13).  All analyses will use intention-to-treat analyses.  Missing data will be imputed using multiple imputation procedures.  These primary analyses will also be controlled for any significant between-groups differences in baseline demographic and methamphetamine use between groups. Bivariate comparisons at each time point (weeks 5, 9, 13, 19) will be conducted controlling for familywise Type I error rates. 
Analysis of urine drug screen results (UDS) will follow established techniques for similar drug trials, whereby missing UDS results assigned as positive, such that each participant will have a proportion (%) of methamphetamine positive UDS between 0-12 out of 12 possible weekly UDS
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Cumberland Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2302 - Newcastle West</postcode>
    <postcode>5069 - Stepney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Associate Professor Nadine Ezard</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney
390 Victoria Street 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GOP Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curran Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, de Lacy Building
390 Victoria Street 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Australia has one of the highest rates of methamphetamine dependence in the world. While counselling is effective for many people with less severe dependence, there is no proven medication treatment for severe dependence. 

Lisdexamfetamine is a stimulant of the brain and is approved in Australia for the treatment of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD).  It is a once-daily oral medication converted to dexamphetamine in the blood.  

The aim of the LiMA study is to test if lisdexamfetamine is effective in reducing methamphetamine use, cravings and withdrawal symptoms in people who are dependent on methamphetamine. 

This will be a randomised double-blind placebo-controlled study which means that one group will receive lisdexamfetamine and another will receive a placebo (a medication with no active ingredients), in addition to counselling. Participants, clinicians and researchers involved in the study will not know to which group they have been allocated. The two groups will be compared and the findings will contribute to evidence for the future use of lisdexamfetamine in the treatment of methamphetamine dependence.

180 people will be recruited to the LiMA study which will be conducted in specialist treatment centres in Sydney, Newcastle and Adelaide. It is anticipated that recruitment will start in early 2017. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincents Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/ SVH/222</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nadine Ezard</name>
      <address>Alcohol &amp; Drug Service, St. Vincents Hospital
Level 4 OBrien Centre, 
Victoria &amp; Burton Streets, 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010 
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8382 1036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nadine.ezard@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Michelle Hall</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Health
Drug &amp; Alcohol Clinical Services
670 Hunter Street, 
Newcastle, NSW, 2300</address>
      <phone>61 2 4016 4781</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.hall@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nadine Ezard</name>
      <address>Alcohol &amp; Drug Service, St. Vincents Hospital
Level 4 OBrien Centre, 
Victoria &amp; Burton Streets, 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010 </address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 8382 1036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nadine.ezard@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Michelle Hall</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Health
Drug &amp; Alcohol Clinical Services
670 Hunter Street, 
Newcastle, NSW, 2300</address>
      <phone>61 2 4016 4781</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.hall@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>