<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336936">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000522910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised controlled trial comparing ligation of the intersphicteric fistula tract vs advancement flap for complex anorectal fistulas requiring intial seton drainage</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does ligation of the intersphicteric fistula tract provide at least a  40% improvement in recurrence rate compared with anorectal advancement flap:  A randomised controlled trial comparing ligation of the intersphicteric fistula tract with advancement flap for complex anorectal fistulas requiring intial seton drainage</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Complex anorectal fistulas where setons were previously inserted because fistulotomy was deemed to risk significant incontinence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A probe was inserted into the tract an incision then made in the intersphincteric groove and the fistula tract identified in this space. Once the tract is dissected free it is encircled and the probe removed. The fistula tract is then divided and transfixed both sides with 3/0 PDS. The external opening is left open the internal opening is curetted and closed with a vicryl suture. This is a single intervention. Operation duration is approximately 10 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>A full thickness flap consisting of mucosa and submucosa and the internal anal sphincter was mobilised from the level of the dentate line cephalad. The base of the flap was at least twice as wide as its apex to ensure adequate blood supply to the distal end. The fistula tract was curetted and the mucosa of the internal sphincter opening excised. The edge of the flap was advanced onto the dentate line and sutured without tension over the internal opening using vicryl. This is a single intervention. Operation duration is approximately 40 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if ligation of the intersphicteric fistula tract  provides at least a 40% improvement in recurrence rate over anorectal advancement flap for complex anorectal fistulas after initial seton drainage. This outcome will be assessed by clinical examination, history and if required MRI and ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients were reviewed in clinics at weeks 2, 4 and 16 then annually thereafter.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>At each clinical and history interview: at weeks 2, 4 and 16 then annually thereafter</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month post operatively by an independent research nurse using a visual analogue scale (1-10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month post operatively by an independent research nurse using visual analogue scale (1-10)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bowel function: return to normal healthy bowel function</outcome>
      <timepoint>At two weeks postoperatively by interview</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time taken to resume normal activities</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month postoperatively by interview</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incontinence</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and one month post operatively by an independent research nurse using using the Cleveland Clinic Florida Fecal Incontinence Score(0-20, 0=continent)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with transsphincteric or complex fistulas were entered into the study. Fistulas were classified as complex if any of the following were present: tract crossing more than 30% to 50% of the external sphincter, anterior fistula in a woman, multiple tracts, recurrent fistula, pre-existing incontinence or Crohns disease.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with Crohns disease were excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study arm was placed in a sealed opaque envelope with the participant identification number on the front and given to the surgeon prior to surgery.</concealment>
    <sequence>Independent unrestricted parallel randomization was performed prior to study commencement using a computer-generated sequence.</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Only participants were blinded as to study group.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/12/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Yik Hong Ho</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Professor of Surgery and Head of Surgery 
Department of Surgery School of Medicine, Townsville and the Australian Institute of Tropical Medicine, within the North Queensland Centre for Cancer Research, James Cook University, Townsville, QLD 4811, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>James Cook University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Medicine 
The Townsville Hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive 
Townsville
Queensland 4811</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>James Cook University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Surgery School of Medicine, Townsville and the Australian Institute of Tropical Medicine, within the North Queensland Centre for Cancer Research, James Cook University, Townsville, QLD 4811, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Bettina Schultze</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Surgery School of Medicine, Townsville and the Australian Institute of Tropical Medicine, within the North Queensland Centre for Cancer Research, James Cook University, Townsville, QLD 4811, Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Chris Mushaya</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Surgery School of Medicine, Townsville and the Australian Institute of Tropical Medicine, within the North Queensland Centre for Cancer Research, James Cook University, Townsville, QLD 4811, Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A new method of treating difficult anorectal fistulae was compared with the traditionally accepted approach.  Management of this condition is known to have a relatively high recurrence rate.  Treatment also carries a risk of faecal incontinence.  Our results show after seton drainage of infection the new method ligation of the intersphicteric fistula tract (LIFT) is at least as good as traditional anorectal advancement flap method with regard to recurrences.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Randomized, Controlled Trial Comparing Lift vs. Advancement Flap for Complex Anorectal Fistulas Requiring Initial Seton Drainage Presnted by C. Mushaya, at The American Society of Colon and Rectal Surgeons Annual Meeting May 14- 18, 2011, Vancouver Convention Centre, Vancouver, Canada</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee The Mater Miscordiae Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Mater Hospital
Fulham Road 
Pimlico
Townsville
4810
Queensland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>The Mater Miscordiae Hospital Ethics Committee Townsville does not provide HREC numbers.  We are happy to email a scanned copy of the ethics approval letter. An original collaborator of the study received verbal ethics approval prior to commencement of this study.  The sponsor was of the understanding that this process was complete. The current collaborators could not find the approval documentation when when conducting data verification, so re-applied.  Some delays in this 2nd process occured due to postponement of HREC meetings due to cyclonic conditions etc.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yik Hong Ho</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery School of Medicine, Townsville and the Australian Institute of Tropical Medicine, within the North Queensland Centre for Cancer Research, James Cook University, Townsville, QLD 4811, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4796 1417</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4796 1401</fax>
      <email>yikhong.ho@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lynne Bartlett</name>
      <address>School of Public Health, Tropical Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation Science within the North Queensland Centre for Cancer Research, James Cook University, Townsville QLD 4811, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4796 1721</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4796 1767</fax>
      <email>lynne.bartlett@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lynne Bartlett</name>
      <address>School of Public Health, Tropical Medicine &amp; Rehabilitation Science within the North Queensland Centre for Cancer Research, James Cook University, Townsville QLD 4811, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4796 1721</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4796 1767</fax>
      <email>lynne.bartlett@my.jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>