<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335950">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000046909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Microencapsulation for Enhanced Bioavailability of Fish Oil - Long Term Ingestion Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Microencapsulation for Enhanced Bioavailability of Fish Oil in Healthy Adult Volunteers - Long Term Ingestion Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bioavailabilty of microencapsulated omega-3 oil as a dietary supplement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will compare the bioavailability of 3 delivery systems containing omega-3 oils (gel capsules versus two different MicroMAX powders  one formulated with milk protein-sugar and other milk protein-sugar-resistant starch) together with a flavoured milk in individuals. Bioavailability will be assessed by measurement of EPA &amp; DHA in blood/plasma.

This is a non-blinded, parallel design study in which participants will be randomised to receive one of the three treatments to be consumed over a 4 week period immediately following a 4 week washout period.

Participants will be asked to abstain from consuming high omega-3 foods throughout the 8 weeks (includes 4 week washout and 4 week intervention).


The bioavailability of a daily dose of omega-3 oils delivered via the three above mentioned formats over 4 weeks is to be investigated. The two different MicroMAX powders (one formulated with milk protein-sugar and other milk protein-sugar-resistant starch) will each be provided in a daily dose of 8g containing 500mg/g omega-3 oil. The gel capsules will be given as a daily dose of 4 capsules (each capsule will contain 1000mg of omega-3 oil).</interventions>
    <comparator>Being a bioavailabilty study the comparison to commonly available gel capsules will be considered the bench mark or comparator treatment to the 2 microencapsulated products.  The subjects for this study have been recruited from existing database of past study volunteers.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>As a parallel design, this study will focus on cumulative response of long term ingestion (28 days) as measured by incorporation into red blood cell membranes.  

Red blood cell membrane fatty acids and lipids (cholesterol, TAG, HDL, LDL) will be measured at each appropriate time point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A baseline measurement will be taken at the end of the 4 week washout period, and then at the end of weeks 2 and 4 of the 28 day treatment phase.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A selected panel of inflammatory markers (eg. CRP/TNF/VCAM etc.) and plasma total fatty acids.</outcome>
      <timepoint>As a parallel design this study will focus on cumulative response of long term ingestion (28 days) secondary outcomes listed above.

Baseline measurements will be taken at the end of the 4 week washout period, and then at the end of weeks 2 and 4 of the 28 day treatment phase.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Male and Females aged between 18-70 years 
(2) Normal dietary habits (no medically prescribed diet, no slimming diet, and no vegan or macrobiotic diet). 
(3) Body Mass Index &gt;18 kg/m^2 &lt; 35kg/m^2 (calculation: Body Mass Index = weight in kg / height^2 in m^2).
(4) Apparently healthy: no reported current or previous metabolic diseases, gastrointestinal disorders, renal or cardiovascular disease.  
(5) Person having given their specific consent in writing.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Regular use of supplements containing omega-3 essential fatty acids must have ceased 2 months prior to the start of the study. 
(2) Current relevant medical treatment (subject to judgement of the investigator).
(3) High alcohol consumption (&gt;21 standard drinks/week)
(4) Reported participation in another biomedical trial 3 months before the start of the study or during the study.
(5) Food allergies or intolerances (dairy, lactose, peanuts, shellfish, etc).
(6) Recent history (within 12 months) of substance abuse including alcohol abuse.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects to be recruited from an existing database of past study  volunteers based on inclusion and exclusion criteria set for this particular study.  Random allocation to treatment groups will be done using the computer software programme Clinstat.  At the time of recruitment, the person responsible for determining eligibilty will be unaware of which treatment group subjects will be allocated to.</concealment>
    <sequence>Volunteers will be randomised to a treatment using Clinstat randomisation programme.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CSIRO Preventative Health Flagship</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences, PO box 10041 Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CSIRO Preventative Health Flagship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences, PO box 10041 Adelaide SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will compare the short term bioavailability of 3 delivery systems containing Omega-3 oils (gel capsules versus two different MicroMAX powders - one formulated with milk protein-sugar and other with milk protein-sugar-resistant starch) together with a flavoured milk in individuals.  Bioavailablilty will be assessed by measurement of EPA and DHA in blood/plasma.

To investigate the bioavailability of EPS and DHA delivered in 3 formats after a 4 week intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
ADELAIDE
South Australia  5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/20</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mahinda Abeywardena</name>
      <address>C/- CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
PO box 10041
Adelaide BC
South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mahinda.abeywardena@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter Royle</name>
      <address>C/- CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences
PO box 10041
Adelaide BC
South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8947</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.royle@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vanessa Courage</name>
      <address>CSIRO
Kintore Avenue
ADELAIDE  SA  5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8863</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8303 8899</fax>
      <email>Vanessa.Courage@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>