<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362783">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000945820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Continuous infusion antipseudomonal
beta-lactams for acute infective exacerbations in cystic fibrosis: a prospective randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Continuous infusion antipseudomonal
betalactams versus standard short infusions in the treatment of acute infective exacerbations in patients with cystic fibrosis - impact on clinical and microbiological outcomes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-8291</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CISTIC (Continuous Infusion Strategy To Improve Clinical outcomes)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Clinicaltrials.gov identifier NCT01667094</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute pulmonary exacerbation of cystic fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Continuous infusion antipseudomonal beta-lactam. The antipseudomonal beta-lactam will be chosen by the treating physician and the method of administration will be subject to randomisation. Participants will receive ONE of the following intravenous antibiotics, as decided by their treating physician. Ceftazidime: Loading dose 500mg on day 1 then 3g infused over 24 hours continuously or Ticarcillin-clavulanate: Loading dose 1.5g ticarcillin/0.05g clavulanate on day 1 then 12g ticarcillin/0.4g clavulanate infused over 24 hours continuously or Meropenem: Loading dose 500mg on day 1 then 3g infused over 24 hours continuously or Cefepime: Loading dose 500mg on day 1 then 3g infused over 24 hours continuously or Piperacillin-tazobactam: Loading dose 2g piperacillin/0.25g tazobactam on day 1 then 16g piperacillin/2g tazobactam infused over 24 hours continously 24 hour infusions are repeated daily over the 14 day treatment period, i.e. continuous infusion for 14 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intermittent, short (30 minute) infusion antipseudomonal beta-lactam Participants will receive ONE of the following intravenous antibiotics as decided by their treating physician: Ceftazidime: 2g every 8 hours or Ticarcillin-clavulanate: 3g ticarcillin/0.1g clavulanate every 6 hours or Meropenem: 1g every 8 hours or Cefepime: 1g every 8 hours or Piperacillin-tazobactam: 4g piperacillin/ 0.5g tazobactam every 6 hours Each infusion will be over 30 minutes. Total duration of treatment 14 days.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R) respiratory symptom score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 to Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in lung function testing; Forced volume expired in one second (FEV1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 to Day 7, Day 0 to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in C-reactive peptide (CRP) measured by blood analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 to Day 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to next infective exacerbation; measured from medical records data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R) respiratory symptom score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 to Day 7, Day 0 to Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative bacterial load in sputum and virulence gene expression.
Quantitative PCR and RNA analysis on sputum samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0 to Day 3, Day 0 to Day 7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time above minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC).
Substudy; if Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated from participant's sputum, the MIC will be determined for the selected antibiotic.  Blood samples will be taken to measure the antibiotic levels and a calculation of the time above minimum inhibitory concentration will be made from these measurements.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antibiotic stability data.  
Samples will be taken from the infusion bag and the amount of antibiotic will be measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Patients greater than or equal to 18 years of age, 
2) Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated in sputum within the last 12 months, 
3) has an acute infective exacerbation, defined by international standards 2 or more of the following in the last 2 weeks: 
change sputum volume or colour, 
increased cough, 
increased dyspnoea, 
increased malaise, fatigue or lethargy, 
anorexia or weight loss, 
decrease in pulmonary function by 10% or more, or 
new radiographic changes</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) patients &lt; 18 yrs of age, 
2) patients that do not meet the criteria for an acute infective exacerbation, 
3) previous enrolment in the study, 
4) concurrent pulmonary embolism, significant haemoptysis, pneumothorax, or respiratory failure, 
5) impaired renal function with an estimated creatinine clearance &lt; 60 mls/min, 
6) patients allergic to beta-lactam antibiotics, 
7) aminoglycoside contra-indicated, 
8) intravenous antibiotics in the last 2 weeks, prior to this admission, 
9) received more than 24 hours of intravenous antibiotics in this admission, 
10) previous lung transplantation, 
11) pregnancy or lactation, or 
12) inability to consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Those patients who meet the inclusion criteria definition for a pulmonary exacerbation and admitted for intravenous antibiotics will be identified and consent sought.
The antipseudomonal beta-lactam will be chosen by the treating physician and the method of administration will be subject to randomisation.
Treatment allocation encoded by random numbers will be enclosed in numbered, sealed opaque envelopes which will be opened at the time of the subject commencing the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random numbers sequences will be generated by a computer program (STATA-11) in a block design by a study investigator not involved with recruitment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Anton Peleg</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Infectious Diseases
Level 2 Burnett Institute
The Alfred Hospital
PO Box 315
Praharn
VIC  3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sylvia &amp; Charles Viertel Charitable Foundation Clinical Investigatorship Award</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/- ANZ Trustees
GPO Box 389D
Melbourne 
VIC 3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cystic fibrosis (CF) is an inherited disorder which results in increased thickness of secretions, especially in the lungs. By adulthood, the majority of patients with CF will have a bacteria living in their lungs, called Pseudomonas aeruginosa which can cause lung infections. This usually results in worsening respiratory symptoms and often an acute deterioration in their lung function. They are usually treated with antibiotics that target the Pseudomonas aeruginosa. These antibiotics are typically given as short intravenous infusions several times a day. This study aims to compare the standard method of giving these antibiotics with a different strategy of giving these antibiotics to see
if this can improve the outcomes of treatment of these infections and reduce the amount of Pseudomonas aeruginosa in the lungs of these patients. This strategy consists of giving the same antibiotics continuously, to ensure there is always enough antibiotic in the bloodstream and the lung to be able to kill the bacteria.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Praharn
VIC 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/12/0249</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Anton Peleg</name>
      <address>Department of Infectious Diseases, The Alfred Hospital
Level 2 Burnett Institute
PO Box 3181
Praharn
VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>613 9076 5436</phone>
      <fax>613 9076 6557</fax>
      <email>Anton.Peleg@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Katherine Langan</name>
      <address>Department of Infectious Diseases, The Alfred Hospital
Level 2 Burnett Institute
PO Box 3181
Praharn
VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>613 9076 5436</phone>
      <fax>613 9076 6557</fax>
      <email>Katherine.Langan@monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Katherine Langan</name>
      <address>Department of Infectious Diseases, The Alfred Hospital
Level 2 Burnett Institute
PO Box 3181
Praharn
VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>613 9076 5436</phone>
      <fax>613 9076 6557</fax>
      <email>Katherine.Langan@monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anton Peleg</name>
      <address>Department of Infectious Diseases, The Alfred Hospital Level 2 Burnett Institute PO Box 3181 Praharn VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>613 9076 5436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Anton.Peleg@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>