<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365327">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000042640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>PROTECT-ICD Trial: Programmed Ventricular Stimulation to Risk Stratify for Early Cardioverter-Defibrillator (ICD) Implantation to Prevent Tachyarrhythmias following Acute Myocardial Infarction</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>PROTECT-ICD Trial: A study targeting prevention of sudden cardiac death in patients who have reduced cardiac function following a myocardial infarct by assessing whether electrophysiologic study to guide prophylactic implantation of an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD) early following myocardial infarction (first 40 days) will lead to a significant reduction in sudden cardiac death. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1150-3865 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sudden cardiac death</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group all undergo electrophysiologic study early after myocardial infarction (within 40 days of MI). The electrophysiology study is done in a hospital laboratory by a specialist cardiologist under local anaesthetic and sedation given through a cannula. A sheath will be placed into the vein in the groin. The Cardiologist will then place 2 electrode catheters into the heart with the use of x-ray images to carefully guide the catheters into the proper areas. The electrode catheters will be used to stimulate the heart and record the electrical activity. This test will take approximately one hour. The patient will generally stay overnight in hospital and go home the next day.
If the study is positive (inducible monomorphic ventricular tachycardia of cycle length less than or equal to 200ms) participants have an ICD implanted. Participants with a negative study (no inducible arrhythmia or induced ventricular fibrillation/ ventricular flutter cycle length &lt;200ms) are discharged without an ICD. 
Implantation of an ICD device involves positioning leads in the heart and placing a box device under the skin, usually in the shoulder area. The procedure is done in a hospital laboratory by a specialist cardiologist under local anaesthetic and with sedation through an intravenous cannula. The leads are inserted through a small incision, usually near the collarbone. X-ray images are used to guide the lead/s into the heart. These leads are attached to the device box which is then placed just beneath the skin and the incision closed with stitches. The patient will often stay overnight in hospital and go home the next day. The device remains in situ for the remainder of the patient's life, barring any complications that would require it's removal.

At select centres a proportion of trial patients at &gt;48 hours following revascularisation for myocardial infarction will also undergo cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR). This is a non-invasive painless test which does not involve any radiation. A series of images will be taken of the heart while positioned on a moveable examination table. The test will take 30-45 minutes and in most cases will involve injection of a contrast material into an intravenous line. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group receive ongoing standard care according to the practise of their institution. This includes discharge from hospital as per their treating physician and follow up as usual in the community. Participants in this group would be eligible to receive an ICD according to the standard practise of their cardiologist (guideline recommendations are after 40 days following myocardial infarction or 90 days following revascularisation only in patients with left ventricular ejection fraction less than or equal to 30% or less than or equal to 35% in the presence of heart failure). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be a combined endpoint of non-fatal arrhythmia and sudden cardiac death. Non-fatal arrhythmia includes resuscitated cardiac arrest, sustained ventricular tachycardia and ventricular fibrillation in participants without an ICD. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause mortality. Assessed by patient follow up and review of clinical files and data. Adjudicated by an independent core lab/committee. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-sudden cardiovascular death. Assessed by patient follow up and review of clinical files and data. Adjudicated by an independent core lab/committee. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-fatal repeat MI. Assessed by patient follow up and review of clinical files and data. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart failure. Assessed by patient follow up and review of clinical files and data. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In patients with an ICD, secondary outcomes will include appropriate and inappropriate ICD activations. Assessed by patient follow up and review of clinical files and data. Adjudicated by an independent core lab/committee. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In patients with an ICD, secondary outcomes will include complications or re-hospitalisation associated with ICD implantation. Complications may include death related to implantation, pneumothorax following procedure, significant bleeding or hematoma related to procedure, lead or box infection, wound infection, lead revision or failure. Assessed by patient follow up and review of clinical files and data. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CMR images will be reviewed and the infarct zone will be quantified for each patient and correlated with: 
* Presence or absence of inducible ventricular tachycardia at electrophysiology study 
* Combined endpoint of appropriate ICD activation or sudden cardiac death and non-fatal arrhythmia at follow up.
Assessed by patient follow up and review of clinical files and data. Adjudicated by an independent core lab/committee. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be 2-40 days (inclusive) following a myocardial infarct, with impaired left ventricular systolic function (Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction &lt;=40% or at least moderately impaired). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Pregnancy; 
* Nursing home resident dependent on one or more activities of daily living; 
* Significant non-cardiac co-morbidity with high likelihood of death within 1 year; 
* Significant psychiatric illnesses that may be aggravated by device implantation or that may preclude regular follow up;
* Intravenous drug abuse (ongoing);
* Unresolved infection associated with risk for hematogenous seeding;
* Pre-existing implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD);
* Secondary prevention indication for an ICD (i.e. sustained ventricular arrhythmias occurring more than 48 hours after qualifying myocardial infarction); 
* On the heart transplant list;
* Recurrent unstable angina despite revascularisation (defined as ongoing chest pain or ischemic symptoms at rest or with minimal exertion despite adequate treatment with anti-anginal medications);
* Congestive heart failure New York Heart Association class IV, defined as shortness of breath at rest, which is refractory to medical treatment (not responding to treatment)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed at the time of enrolling a subject. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by the electronic data capture database</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In the study cohort it is anticipated that early (first 40 days) sudden cardiac death / non-fatal arrhythmia occurs in 5.4% and late (40 days to 2 years) sudden deaths / non-fatal arrhythmia occur in 1.3% of surviving patients. It is also assumed that a proportion of events will not be prevented in the intervention arm due to 30% of sudden deaths being due to non-arrhythmic causes, and 13% occurring in EPS negative patients. It is anticipated that a 2 year primary event rate of 6.7% in the control arm will be reduced to 2.8% in the intervention arm. A two group chi-squared test with a 0.05 two-sided significance level will have 80% power to detect the difference between a Group 1 proportion of 0.028 experiencing the primary endpoint and a Group 2 proportion of 0.067 experiencing the primary endpoint when the sample size in each group is 470. Allowing 2% crossover and 10% loss to follow up the required sample size is 1,058 (529 patients per arm).
 
The primary endpoint will be analysed using the Kaplan-Meier estimator with log-rank tests used to compare the occurrence of the primary outcome between the intervention and control groups. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1058</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital Royal Newcastle Centre - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Gosford Hospital - Gosford</hospital>
    <hospital>Eastern Heart Clinic - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <hospital>Blacktown Hospital - Blacktown</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>John Flynn - Gold Coast Private Hospital - Tugun</hospital>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service - Fremantle</hospital>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Western Sydney Local Health District
Cnr Darcy and Hawkesbury Rd
Westmead NSW 2145 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BIOTRONIK Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 2, Level 4, Building 2
20 Bridge Street, 
Pymble NSW 2073</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The PROTECT-ICD study is a multi-centre randomised controlled trial targeting prevention of sudden cardiac death in patients who have reduced cardiac function following a myocardial infarct. The primary objective of the trial is to assess whether electrophysiologic study to guide prophylactic implantation of an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator early following MI (first 40 days) will lead to a significant reduction in sudden cardiac death. The secondary objective is to assess the utility of cardiac magnetic resonance imaging in assessing early myocardial viability, and its predictive value for both inducible and spontaneous ventricular tachyarrhythmias post-myocardial infarction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office 
Room 1072, Level 1, Education Block
Westmead Hospital, Hawkesbury and Darcy Roads
Westmead NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC2012/8/4.5(3572) AU RED HREC/12/WMEAD/277</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Pramesh Kovoor</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Level 2, Westmead Hospital
Cnr Darcy and Hawkesbury Rd
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pramesh.kovoor@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jackie Hoynes</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Level 2, Westmead Hospital
Cnr Darcy and Hawkesbury Rd
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 8509</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhoynes@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Pramesh Kovoor</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Level 2, Westmead Hospital
Cnr Darcy and Hawkesbury Rd
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pramesh.kovoor@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>