<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369511">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001330538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of mobilisation with movement in participants with distal radius fracture: A randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of mobilisation with movement plus range of motion (ROM) exercises compared to ROM exercises alone on range of motion and function following a distal radius fracture: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Distal radius fracture</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will receive four standard physiotherapy consultations (approximately 20-30 minutes each) over four weeks. These sessions will commence within one week of removal of the plaster. A participant will receive two intervention sessions within the first week, session 3 will occur one week after session 2, session 4 will occur two weeks after session 3. 
The treatment will be Mulligan mobilisation with movement (MWM) into the direction used to increase supination of the forearm and extension of the wrist. In addition to the therapist intervention, the participant will be taught at the first session to  to do self-MWMs x 6 for forearm supination and wrist extension at home, twice a day (duration 6 minutes). They will also receive instructions  by the physiotherapist to perform range of motion (ROM) exercises for the wrist (flexion, extension, pronation/supination arc), elbow (flexion/extension arc) and shoulder flexion x 5 for each exercise. The participant will be asked to do these ROM exercises twice a day (duration 4 minutes). Each home exercise session should last approximately 10 minutes; 6 minutes for the self-MWMs and 4 minutes for the ROM exercises. The home MWM and ROM sessions will continue for a duration of 4 weeks post first treatment session.
Participants will be encouraged to resume graded activities using the upper limb during activities of daily living. They will all be given a booklet with advice on fracture protection, swelling control, skin care. 
Participants will have their attendance at the 4 Physiotherapy sessions logged in the Physiotherapist Notes - which will be supplied to the researchers after their 4th treatment session. The participants will keep a diary to log their adherence to the Self-MWMs and ROM exercises. 
</interventions>
    <comparator> The control group will receive four standard physiotherapy consultations (approximately 20-30 minutes each) over four weeks. These sessions will commence within one week of removal of the plaster. A participant will receive two intervention sessions within the first week, session 3 will occur one week after session 2, session 4 will occur two weeks after session 3. 
The control group will receive: 
Session 1: instructions by a physiotherapist on how to perform ROM exercises for the wrist flexion, wrist extension, forearm pronation/supination, elbow flexion/extension, and shoulder flexion  x 5 for each exercise. The participant will be asked to do these exercises twice a day. Each home ROM session should last approximately 4 minutes. The home ROM sessions will continue for a duration of 4 weeks post first treatment session.
Session 2: range of motion will be re-measured. The exercises will be checked. 
Session 3: range of motion will be re-measured. The exercises will be checked.
Session 4: range of motion will be re-measured. The exercises will be checked
 Participants will be encouraged to resume graded activities using the upper limb during activities of daily living. They will all be given a booklet with advice on fracture protection, swelling control, skin care. 
Participants will have their attendance at the 4 Physiotherapy sessions logged in the Physiotherapist Notes - which will be supplied to the researchers after their 4th treatment session. The participants will keep a diary to log their adherence to the home ROM exercises. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean forearm active supination range of motion measured with a goniometer and following the standard administering procedures as outlined by the American Society of Hand Therapists and also using the Dr Goniometer smartphone app.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary time point for supination will be 4 weeks from baseline (straight after the interventions). The other time points for supination are base line and 12 week follow-up. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean forearm active pronation range of motion measured with a goniometer and following the standard administering procedures as outlined by the American Society of Hand Therapists and also using the Dr Goniometer app.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean isometric grip strength scores, measured in kilograms using a calibrated Jamar goniometer on setting 2 to ensure maximum grip strength with the participant seated and the elbow flexed to 90 degrees.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional test: ability to pour a cup of water into another cup using pronation and backwards into a cup using supination. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain and function as assessed on the Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation questionnaire

The Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation questionnaire is a composite secondary outcome. The questionnaire includes a numerical rating scale (0-10) for pain and rating scales (0-10) for functional activities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Two weeks 
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up)
6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global rating of change </outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks 
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up)
6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean score on the Quality of Life SF8 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Two weeks 
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up)
6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean score on the Quick-DASH questionnaire will be used to measure disability of the affected upper limb. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Two weeks 
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up)
6 months
12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to home exercise program will be assessed using the home exercise diaries. Participants will have to tick if they completed the exercise session. To determine adherence rates the number of sessions they completed will be compared to number of sessions prescribed. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Diary will be kept by all participants for four weeks from Session 1 to record adherence to home exercise program.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean wrist active extension range of motion measured with a goniometer and following the standard administering procedures as outlined by the American Society of Hand Therapists and also using the Dr Goniometer app.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean wrist active flexion range of motion measured with a goniometer and following the standard administering procedures as outlined by the American Society of Hand Therapists and also using the Dr Goniometer app.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline= 0 weeks (time of recruitment = about 6 weeks from time of injury)
Four weeks (immediately following intervention)
12 weeks (follow-up). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be people who have suffered a fracture to the distal radius that has been treated non-surgically with a plaster cast. 
They will be required to be aged over 18 years of age.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Surgical management of the distal radius fracture such as external fixation or open reduction with internal fixation 
Previous wrist fracture on the affected side within last 20 years
Concurrent ipsilateral upper limb fracture 
A condition such as pre-existing inflammatory joint condition that might raise the risk of injury with manual therapy treatment.
Signs and symptoms of complex regional pain syndrome
Inability to understand written or spoken English, </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be referred by medical practitioners, outpatient clinics, hand surgeons, Orthopaedic surgeons, hand units, and physiotherapists. They may also be recruited via a press release or advertisement such as on Facebook or Twitter. After a potential participant is referred to the study or makes contact to say they would like some information about the study, a researcher will explain the details of the study and determine if they meet the inclusion criteria. They will be given a participant information statement and taken through the consenting process.
A statistician (not aware of participant details or involved in participant recruitment, assessment or treatment) will use a computer generated mixed random allocation sequence to provide a randomisation table to advise of participant allocation to either the intervention or control group. This will be placed in sealed opaque envelopes to be used by the researchers. </concealment>
    <sequence>The sealed opaque envelope will have a computer generated random number inside. The simple randomisation will be performed using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation). Participants will be stratified for type of fracture: if it is intra-articular or extra-articular.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size
Calculations to estimate the sample size were based on a difference between groups that would be clinically significant for the main outcome measure, supination ROM, supported by the results of previous research. This was estimated by a biostatisticians from the Australian Catholic University using other studies that used supination ROM as an outcome measure (Challis et al 2007; Kay et al. 2008). Thirty-three participants in each group are required based on a change of 14 degrees in supination and a standard deviation of 20 with a power of 80% and a 5% confidence interval. For a moderate effect size of 0.7 we need to have 33 in each group. A linear mixed model will be used.

Statistical methods
Statistical analyses will be conducted using the SPSS (SPSS Inc., Chicargo, IL, USA) statistical package. It is proposed that as the response variables should have a normal distribution, parametric statistics including repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be used. Nominal and interval data will be analysed using chi-square test and independent samples t-test. Biostatisticians from the Australian Catholic University will help with the statistical analyses. An intention-to-treat analysis will be performed. An alpha level of p&lt;0.05 will be regarded as statistically significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>58</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Catholic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>40 Edward St
North Sydney
NSW 2060
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mulligan Concept Teachers Association</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>.Funding source Mulligan Concept Teachers Association LLC
7051 Navajo Trail
Solon OH 44139 USA
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Lucia 
Brisbane
QLD 4072
Australia </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to see if adult patients who have suffered a fracture to the distal radius, which has been treated non-sugically, benefit from receiving Mulligan mobilisation with movement (MWM) plus self-MWMs.
In this study the hypothesis to be tested is that adult patients who have suffered a fracture to the distal radius who receive four treatments of MWMs plus self-MWMS as well as simple ROM exercises, will demonstrate a significant difference in ROM, pain and function to patients who are treated with simple ROM exercises alone.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services
ACU Melbourne Campus
Locked Bag 4115
Fitzroy. Victoria 3065
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-314H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sue Reid</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy 
Faculty of Health Sciences                  
AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY
Level 9, 33 Berry Street
North Sydney.
NSW. 2060
Australia 
           

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9739 2267</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9739 2132 </fax>
      <email>Sue.reid@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sue Reid</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy 
Faculty of Health Sciences                  
AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY
Level 9, 33 Berry Street
North Sydney.
NSW. 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9739 2267</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9739 2132 </fax>
      <email>Sue.reid@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sue Reid</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy 
Faculty of Health Sciences                  
AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY
Level 9, 33 Berry Street
North Sydney.
NSW. 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9739 2267</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9739 2132 </fax>
      <email>Sue.reid@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sue Reid</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy 
Faculty of Health Sciences                  
AUSTRALIAN CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY
Level 9, 33 Berry Street
North Sydney.
NSW. 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9739 2267</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9739 2132 </fax>
      <email>Sue.reid@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>