<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347685">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001187932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Among overweight adolescents, does a community based  program (Curtin Activity, Food and Attitudes Program) lead to improved activity and food behaviours?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Among overweight adolescents, does a community based family centred multidisciplinary program (Curtin Activity, Food and Attitudes Program) lead to improved activity and food behaviours?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CAFAP2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intensive 8 week period involving twice weekly sessions of 2 hours duration followed by 12 weeks of maintenance contact. 

On entry into the study participants will be assessed and be placed on a waitlist for 8-12weeks before being assessed again prior to starting the intensive 8 week program. This waitlist period will provide a within-subject control period. Participants will be assessed at the end of the 8 week intensive program and again after 3, 6 and 12 months. Cohorts of 10-15 adolescents (along with a parent for each) will be recruited in 2-3 geographical regions with multiple cohorts in each region. The staggered start to the multiple cohorts in each region provides a control over major external events.

The intensive program involves 1 hour of exercise and 1 hour education and support twice weekly for adolescents. Exercises include aerobic, strength, power and endurance stations and are performed in a group setting administered by a physiotherapist. Education and support covers activity, food and attitudes. Activity intervention includes education to improve moderate/vigorous physical activity, light activity and sedentary behaviours. Food intervention includes education to improve healthy eating behaviours. Attitude intervention includes goal setting, problem solving, affect regulation. Education sessions are administered in a group setting by one of the physiotherapy, nutrition, social work or psychology facilitators.

The intensive program includes 2 hours of education and support for parents of the adolescents. Some sessions are combined with adolescents. Other sessions include 'walk and talk' informal support, supermarket buying skills, snack and meal preparation skills, providing autonomy support for adolescents.

The 2 hour twice weekly adolescent and parent sessions during the intensive phase occur concurrently, with some joint education sessions.

The 3 month maintenance program includes several reminders and review of goal setting each week using information technologies (phone, SMS, email, web) and occaisonal group meetings.</interventions>
    <comparator>Within subjects study, with waitlist period as the active comparator and staggered start of 3 cohorts followed to 12 months post-intevention</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity assessed by accelerometer (time in sedentary, light and moderate/vigorous activity)</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutrition behaviour assessed by 3 day food diary (daily serves of fruit, vegetables, 'extras')</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behaviours assessed by questionaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutrition behaviours assessed by questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical status assessed by examination (BMI, waist and hip girth, cardiovascular fitness (modified shuttle walk test), muscle strength (quadriceps, biceps, deltoid manual break test), muscle power (vertical jump), muscle endurance (abdominal curls)</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health assessed by Moods and Feelings questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life assessed by Paediatric Quality of Life - Teen Report</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Autonomy support, structure and involvement (Perceived Autonomy Support Scales for Exercise Settings and Perceived Environmental Supportiveness Scale) and autonomous motivation (Revised Behavioural Regulations and Exercise Scale, Integrated Regulation Scale for Exercise Behaviour, and Percieved Locus of Causality for Dieting) for physical activity and healthy eating</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental mental health assessed by Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family functioning assessed by McMaster Family Assessment Device general functioning subscale</outcome>
      <timepoint>study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Goal attainment and conflict assess by questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>goal conflict will be assessed at study entry (pre waitlist), pre program (post waitlist), immediately post program, 3, 6 and 12 months post program
goal attainment will be collected each week during the intervention period (starting from middle of the intensive intervention period when goal setting is introduced) and at followups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Program evaluation using interviews with participants and facilitators</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately post program and 12 months post program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>body mass index &gt; 85th percentile</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>11</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>obesity due to identified genetic, metabolic, endocrine disease; psychiatric disorder; medic assessed as unsuitable to participate</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>multiple cohort, staggered start, waitlist controlled, within subject design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/01/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>96</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>69</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Australian Health Promotion Foundation (Healthway)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1284
West Perth WA 6872</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to help overweight adolescents develop healthy activity, food and attitude habits. Adolescents and their parents participate in an intensive 8 week program (involving twice weekly 2 hour sessions) followed by regular contact for 3 months to assist with goal achievement. The study hypothesis is that adolescent activity and food behaviours will be improved after the intensive program and be maintained at 12 months post program</summary>
    <trialwebsite>cafap.curtin.edu.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Straker, L., Smith, K., Fenner, A., Kerr, D., McManus, A., Davis, M. Fielding, A., Olds, T., Hagger, M., Smith, A. &amp;. Abbott, R. (2012). Rationale, design and methods for a staggered-entry, waitlist controlled clinical trial of the impact of a community-based, family-centred, multidisciplinary program focused on activity, food and attitude habits (Curtin University's Activity, Food and Attitudes Program-CAFAP) among overweight adolescents. BMC Public Health, 12, 471.

Fenner, A., Hagger, M., &amp; Straker, L. (2013). Theoretical underpinnings of a need-supportive intervention to address sustained healthy lifestyle changes in overweight and obese adolescents. Psychology of Sport and Exercise, 14, 819-829.

Straker, L., E. Howie, K. Smith, A. Fenner, D. Kerr, T. Olds, R. Abbott and A. Smith (2014). "Curtin University's Activity, Food and Attitudes Program improves physical activity, sedentary time and healthy eating among overweight and obese adolescents: A waitlist controlled trial." PlosOne 9(11): e111954.

Smith, K., Kerr, D., Howie, E., &amp; Straker, L. (2015). Do overweight adolescents adhere to dietary intervention messages? Twelve month detailed dietary outcomes from Curtin University's Activity, Food and Attitudes Program. Nutrients, 7, 4363-4382.

Smith, K., L. Straker, D. Kerr &amp; A. Smith (2015). Obese adolescents eat what? And when? Detailed consumption patterns provide targets for intervention goal setting. Journal of Human Nutrition and Dietetics 28(s2): 80-93.

Howie, E., McVeigh, J., Abbott, R., Olds, T., &amp; Straker, L. (in press (accepted 18th Nov 2015)). Multiple components of fitness improved among overweight and obese adolescents up to one year following a community-based lifestyle intervention. Journal of Sports Science. 

Howie, E., Olds, T., McVeigh, J., Abbott, R., &amp; Straker, L. (in press (accepted 11 Jan 2015)). It's a-bout time: Detailed patterns of physical activity in obese adolescents participating in a lifestyle intervention. Journal of Physical Activity and Health. 

Smith, K., Kerr, D., Howie, E., &amp; Straker, L. (2015). Do overweight adolescents adhere to dietary intervention messages? Twelve month detailed dietary outcomes from Curtin University's Activity, Food and Attitudes Program. Nutrients, 7, 4363-4382.

Fenner, A., Howie, E., Hagger, M., &amp; Straker, L. (in press (accepted 6th Dec 2015)). Exploration of the mechanisms of change in constructs from Self-Determination Theory and quality of life during a multi-disiplinary family-based intervention for overweight adolescents. Journal of Sport and Exercise Psychology. 

Smith, K., L. Straker, A. McManus and A. Fenner (2014). Barriers and enablers for participation in healthy lifestyle programs by adolescents who are overweight: A qualitative study of the opinions of adolescents, their parents and community stakeholders. BMC Paediatrics 14: 53.

Smith, K., D. Kerr, A. Fenner and L. Straker (2014). Adolescents just don't know what they want: a qualitative study to describe obese adolescents' experiences of text messaging to support behaviour change maintenance post intervention. Journal of Medical Internet Research 16(4): e103.

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR105/2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3699</fax>
      <email>cafap@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3699</fax>
      <email>cafap@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 3699</fax>
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Leon Straker</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3634</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>L.Straker@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>