<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367475">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001283662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of Arnotts Vita-Weat supplementation on weight loss in overweight and obese participants. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to determine the efficacy of Vita-Weat food supplementation on weight loss in overweight and obese participants.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Protocol no X14-0300 </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>During the six week intervention period, the intervention group will replace their breakfast and lunch each day with either 2 Arnott's Lunch Slices or up to 6 Vita-Weat crispbreads based on personal preference, with a choice of prescribed toppings consisting of a protein, vegetable and condiment component. An Accredited Practising Dietitian will administer the intervention during a one on one, face to face consultation of approximately 30 minutes duration. 

To aid with dietary compliance, participants will be required to complete and return a 3 day diet diary (2 working days and 1 weekend day) at the first (Baseline) and final (Week 6) visits. Participants will receive enough product for the duration of the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>During the six week intervention period, participants in the Control group will be given advice on the Australian Guide to Healthy Eating. The study dietitian will provide a guide as to the types of foods that can be bought and consumed. An Accredited Practising Dietitian will administer the intervention during a one on one, face to face consultation of approximately 30 minutes duration. 

To aid with dietary compliance, participants will be required to complete and return a 3 day diet diary (2 working days and 1 weekend day) at the first (Baseline) and final (Week 6) visits . Participants will receive a grocery voucher to buy food for their diet ($20 per week). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the efficacy of Vita-Weat food supplementation on weight loss in an overweight and obese group.

Weight loss will be assessed by comparing pre and post intervention weights obtained using calibrated scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the difference in subjective appetite between the two diet groups.

Subjective appetite will be assessed using a 100 mm Visual Analogue Scale scores. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six weeks after randomisation.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the food acceptability of the two diet groups.

Food acceptability will be assessed using a Food Acceptability Questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine changes in body composition by waist circumference, fat mass and fat free mass between groups.

Waist circumference measurement is obtained by placing a tape measure at the midline of highest point of the iliac crest and lowest part of the costal margin in the mid-axillary line in expiration.

Fat mass and fat free mass will be assessed using a DEXA scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine changes in type 2 diabetes and cardiovascular risk factors between groups.

This is a composite secondary outcome.

Changes in type 2 diabetes and cardiovascular risk factors will be assessed using pathological parameters including fasting plasma glucose, insulin, glycated haemoglobin, and full lipid profile. Anthropometric measures such as waist circumference and blood pressure will also contribute to the assessment of this outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six weeks after randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Aged 25-55 years
*Pre-menopausal
*BMI greater than or equal to 25 to less than or equal to 35 kg /m^2
*Regular eating habits; familiar with Vita-Weat
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Type 1 diabetes
*Type 2 diabetes treated with insulin 
*Coeliac disease and gluten intolerance 
*Previous bariatric surgery
*Untreated thyroid disease
*Greater than 10% change in body weight over the past 3 months
*Alcohol or illicit drug abuse
*Pregnant or breastfeeding women, and women who might be planning pregnancy during the duration of the study
*Use of weight loss medications and other drugs that may affect body weight e.g. anti-psychotics, anti-depressants, or corticosteroids
*A history or presence of malignancy [completely resected basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin if treatment completed &gt; 6 months prior to enrolment and participants in remission for &gt; 5 years prior to screening remain eligible]
*Inability to read and write English
*A history of frequently changing smoking habits, in addition to smoking cessation within 6 months prior to screening. Those who wish to take on the advice of a 'Quit' smoking programme at the time of screening will be eligible to start the trial after 6 months
*Participants may also be excluded, if in the opinion of the study investigators, they have some other condition or disorder that may adversely affect the outcome of the study or the safety of the participant
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by a computer generated randomisation programme.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Assuming a mean reduction in percentage weight loss from baseline of 5% and 2% in the intervention and control treatments respectively (to Week 6), with a standard deviation (SD) of 4.5% and an estimated drop-out rate of 5%, a total of 76 participants would be required to achieve 80% power to detect a difference between the two groups (at a 2-sided significance level of 5%).
Based on these calculations, 76 participants (38 in each group) will be recruited and randomised to one of two treatment groups.
Data will be analysed for normality using the Shapiro-Wilk test. For analysis of differences between treatments, an independent sample t test, or the non-parametric equivalent Mann-Whitney U test, will be used. For within group changes, repeated measures ANOVA will be used. As well as an analysis of completers (those that attend the final visit), an intention to treat (ITT) analysis will also be included. For the ITT analysis, dropouts will be treated using a variety of sensitivity analyses.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>76</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Boden Institute
Charles Perkins Centre D17
John Hopkins Drive
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Research donation from Campbell Arnott’s </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, Building B, 24 George Street
North Strathfield NSW 2137</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>An area of research that receives a lot of attention currently relates to the physiological mechanisms that are involved in maintaining the feeling of fullness after people have eaten (referred to as satiety). Previous studies have shown that the most satisfying foods were found to be high in carbohydrate or protein, and most were also high in water and fibre. 

Considering the high carbohydrate (&gt; 60 grams per 100 grams) and high protein (&gt;10 grams per 100 grams) content of Campbell Arnotts Vita-Weat range, these products may produce greater satiety and hence help produce weight loss for those needing to lose weight.

The current randomised controlled trial is designed to investigate the beneficial effect of this food product in an overweight and obese population group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://sydney.edu.au/medicine/research/units/boden/clinical-trials.php</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Missenden Road
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC/14/RPAH/394</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Fuller</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute
Charles Perkins Centre D17
Johns Hopkins Drive
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 86271932</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>nick.fuller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Fuller</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute
Charles Perkins Centre D17
Johns Hopkins Drive
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 86271932</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>nick.fuller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Fuller</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute
Charles Perkins Centre D17
Johns Hopkins Drive
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 86271932</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>nick.fuller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Mackenzie Fong</name>
      <address>The Boden Institute
Charles Perkins Centre D17
Johns Hopkins Drive
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 86271931</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 86270141</fax>
      <email>mackenzie.fong@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>