<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367972">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000191594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Oxandrolone and Progressive Resistance Training in Older Women with Early Frailty</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effect of Oxandrolone in Combination with Progressive Resistance Training on Improving Physical Function, Muscle Strength and Power, and Body Composition in Older Women with Early Frailty: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Pfizer Protocol Number: A9001008</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Frailty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Progressive Resistance Training combined with Oxandrolone.

Participants will be instructed to take 2 x 2.5mg oxandrolone tablets, orally, twice per day (10mg), for the duration of the study (12 weeks).  Adherence will be monitored by self-report and the returning of empty packaging by the participants.  

The progressive resistance training will be performed on Keiser pneumatic resistance equipment  3 days per week for 12 weeks.  Training will be fully supervised, one-on-one, by a Nurse and Exercise Physiologist or certified Recreational Therapist.  

Participants will exercise at a minimum of 80% of their previously determined one-repetition maximum (1RM).  Sessions will last approximately 45 minutes.  Participants will perform 3 sets of 8 repetitions on the leg press, knee extension, knee flexion, triceps pushdown, plantar flexion and chest press.  1RM testing will be carried out every two weeks to ensure participants are progressed appropriately.  Borg rating scales will be used to further titrate the intensity of training by maintaining the resistance between ratings of 15 and 17 at each session. Resistance will be adjusted accordingly if participants develop any musculoskeletal complaints that could be exacerbated with PRT.

Participants will undergo both interventions simultaneously.
 </interventions>
    <comparator>Progressive Resistance Training with Placebo

The placebo tablet will be identical in in appearance, packaging, taste and texture.  Participants will be given identical instructions (2 x 2.5mg tablets, twice per day), and adherence will be monitored by self-report and the returning of empty packaging.

The progressive resistance training program will be identical in both groups.

Participants will undergo both interventions simultaneously. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Fiber Cross-sectional Area assessed using muscle biopsies obtained from the Vastus Lateralis</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Composition assessed using DEXA scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Strength (1RM) on the Leg Press, Knee Extension, Knee Flexion, Chest Press and Triceps Pushdown. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 Weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Performance assessed using 
* Habitual Gait Speed
* Maximal Gait Speed
* 6 minute walk test
* Chair rise
* Stair climb
* Static Balance assessed using half-tandem, tandem and one-leg
* Dynamic balance assessed using forward and backward tandem walk over 6 meters (20 feet).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 Weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Power on the Leg Press and Chest Press</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Evidence of a frail or pre-frail condition by demonstration of one of the following: 
*gait speed between 0.5m/s-0.9m/s 
*chair rise time &gt;12 seconds
*one or more limitation of Nagys instrumental activities of daily living
*self-reported limitation of the physical component section of the Short Form 36 Health Survey (SF-36), categories B through J inclusive
*a loss of 10lb (5kg) or more in the 5 years preceding screening, and a BMI &lt; 24
*one fall within the previous six months, or 2 or more falls within the previous 2 years.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Mini-Mental State Examination score &lt; 24

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization was performed by Pfizer central office, and randomization sequence was kept offsite. Randomization occurred at the completion of the entire baseline assessment via email to pharmacy staff who prepared study medications for each participant, distributed by research staff identified as “A” or “B” only.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size estimates were based on the adaptive response of muscle as determined by muscle fiber cross sectional area. The change in subjects receiving resistance training with oxandrolone is difficult to hypothesize based on the absence of comparable data in the literature.  However, Fiatarone et al showed that the combination of nutrition and progressive resistance training (PRT) increased type II fiber diameter by 21.6% compared to resistance training alone (1).  Thus, with an alpha of 0.05 and a power of 0.8, a sample size of 32 (16 in each group) was required to detect a significant change in type II fiber area in participants receiving oxandrolone compared to those receiving placebo.  

Sequential linear mixed-effects models with repeated measures will be used to determine the effects of group assignment over time for all dependent variables, using an intention-to-treat analytic strategy without regard to adherence or dropout. 

1. Fiatarone Singh, M.A., et al., Insulin-like growth factor I in skeletal muscle after weight-lifting exercise in frail elders. Vol. 277. 1999. E135-E143.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/01/2001</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/02/2001</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/01/2002</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>29</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>29</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pfizer Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Easters Point Road, Groton, Connecticut 06340</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pfizer Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Eastern Point Road, Groton, Connecticut 06340</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this investigation is to study the effects of 12 weeks of progressive resistance training (PRT) in combination with 20 mg/day oxandrolone or placebo in older women with early frailty.  We hypothesize that PRT plus oxandrolone would show significantly greater increases in lean tissue and reduction in adipose tissue compared to PRT plus placebo.  Furthermore, we hypothesize that PRT plus oxandrolone would result in increases in physical function, peak muscle strength [one-repetition maximum (1RM)] as well as muscle peak power compared to participants receiving PRT plus placebo.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Mavros, Y., ONeill, E., Connerty, M., Bean, JF., Broe, K., Kiel, DP., MacLean, D., Taylor, A., Fielding, RA., Fiatarone Singh, MA. Oxandrolone augmentation of resistance training in older women: A randomized trial. Medicine and Science in Sport and Exercise. 2015, 47(11):2257-2267. DOI: 10.1249/MSS.0000000000000690</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hebrew Rehabilitation Center for Aged</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1200 Centre Street, Boston, MA 02131</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/08/2000</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>00-011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Maria Fiatarone Singh</name>
      <address>University of Sydney, 
Faculty of Health Sciences
75 East Street
Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61293519755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maria.fataronesingh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Maria Fiatarone Singh</name>
      <address>University of Sydney, 
Faculty of Health Sciences
75 East Street
Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61293519755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maria.fataronesingh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Maria Fiatarone Singh</name>
      <address>University of Sydney, 
Faculty of Health Sciences
75 East Street
Lidcombe NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61293519755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maria.fataronesingh@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>