<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368088">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000317594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot Study: Evaluation of a silicone gel adhesive hydrocellular foam dressing for the prevention of sacral pressure injuries in hospitalised elderly patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a silicone gel adhesive hydrocellular foam dressing in comparison to standard care for the use in sacral pressure injuries in hospitalised elderly patients'

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-7188 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pressure injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pressure ulcer/decubitus ulcer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bedsores</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group patients will have the Allevyn Life Sacrum foam dressing applied to their sacrum for a maximum of 4 weeks.  These dressings will be lifted and the skin beneath inspected daily by nursing staff, then the same dressing will be reapplied, unless the integrity of the dressing is compromised in which case it will be replaced. A new dressing will be applied in all cases, after 7 days in situ. Dressing changes will be monitored daily and recorded on a standardised data collection form.</interventions>
    <comparator>All patients will receive standard pressure injury prevention strategies from the multidisciplinary hospital team, which includes (but are not limited to) ongoing risk assessment, regular repositioning (self encouraged or staff assist) and skin care. As well as appropriate pressure redistribution devices based on patient needs and risk. patients will be monitored by nursing staff for a duration of 4 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients who develop sacral pressure injury, as assessed by diagnosis of specialist wound care nurses. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline data will be collected on recruitment to the study.  This will then be followed up with daily assessments by the ward research nurses until participants are discharged from the unit (or up to a maximum of 4 weeks). data will be recorded on standardised data collection forms</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dressing comfort from the patients perspective</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline data will be collected on recruitment to the study.  This will then be followed up with daily assessments by the ward research nurses until participants are discharged from the unit (or up to a maximum of 4 weeks). Data will be collected by a 5 point likert scale, assessing patient comfort for: new dressing/dressing inspection, sleeping, sitting, mobilising and hygiene.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate dressing utility from the nurses perspective</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline data will be collected on recruitment to the study.  This will then be followed up with daily assessments by the ward research nurses until participants are discharged from the unit (or up to a maximum of 4 weeks). Data will be collected using a likert type scale</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To quantify the direct costs associated with use of the foam dressing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline data will be collected on recruitment to the study.  This will then be followed up with daily assessments by the ward research nurses until participants are discharge from the unit (or up to a maximum of 4 weeks). Resources to be costed include: PI interventions (e.g. mattresses, dressings etc.); length of hospital stay; Treatment for PI where this occurs (e.g. dressings, medications, surgery etc.). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) &gt;/= 65 years of age.
2) Patients assessed to be at risk of pressure injury development i.e. Waterlow Score &gt; 10.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Pre-existing sacral pressure injury.
2) Evidence of incontinence associated dermatitis (IAD).
3) Skin disease or trauma/skin damage to sacral region.
4) Documented allergy to adhesives.
5) Patients previously recruited to the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients admitted to the Geriatric Evaluation and Management (GEM) unit will be screened by the research nurse to determine if they meet the inclusion criteria.  Each potential participant will then be provided with an information letter explaining the study. Those who agree to participate will be required to provide written consent.</concealment>
    <sequence>An online random number generator will be used to allocate participants (1:1) to either the intervention or control group. Allocation will initially be concealed by using sealed opaque envelopes.
1) Intervention group: application of foam dressing.
2) Control group: standard care.



</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All data will be entered into SPSS Version 22 for analysis. Descriptive statistics will be used to describe the sample and inferential statistics will be used to analyse differences and relationships in the data. Significance is set at p &lt; 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>126</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nursing Research and Practice Development centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside Queensland 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Smith &amp; Nephew Pty Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 225 Montague Road

West End
Queensland 4101
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Catholic University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>1100 Nudgee Road Banyo Queensland 4014

Postal: PO Box 456 Virginia Queensland 4014 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to gather information about the effectiveness of a foam dressing to prevent the development of sacral pressure injuries (PI). Currently, preventative dressings are not used routinely. In this study,of adult patients who are at high risk of developing a PI, half of the sample of 126 patients will be randomly allocated to receive the sacral foam dressing and half will receive standard care i.e. no sacral dressing. The dressing will remain in place for the duration of each participant's hospital stay. It will be replaced routinely after 7 days, or before if needed. In all patients, the sacral skin will be inspected on a daily basis to observe for the presence of PI, for a maximum period of 4 weeks. The main outcome measure will be the occurrence of sacral PI. Dressing comfort will be evaluated from the patient's perspective, and its utility will be evaluated by nurses. A cost analysis will also be undertaken.

It is anticipated that patients treated with the foam dressing will have a lower incidence of pressure injuries than those receiving standard care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication>none</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>none</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research, Ethics and Governance Unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside Queensland 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QPCH/256</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fulbrook</name>
      <address>Nursing Research and Practice Development Centre
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside Queensland 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4087</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3139 6017</fax>
      <email>paul.fulbrook@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Damian Williams</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside Queensland 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 5646</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>damian.williams@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Lord</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
PO Box 456 Virginia Queensland 4014 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7240</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>roger.lord@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Petra Lawrence</name>
      <address>Nursing Research and Practice Development Centre
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside Queensland 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 6282</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3139 6017</fax>
      <email>petra.lawrence@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>