<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367127">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001110673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Diabetes and Eye Health project: increasing eye examinations for adults newly diagnosed with type 2 diabetes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Development and evaluation of a psycho-educational leaflet to increase the rate of eye examinations for adults newly diagnosed with type 2 diabetes from the following two groups: 
1. early onset type 2 diabetes (aged 18-39 years), or 
2. who live in rural and regional Victoria
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1161-9803 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>yourSAY</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic retinopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: printed materials (leaflet) containing persuasive behaviour change messages designed to raise awareness of the importance of maintaining optimal blood glucose and blood pressure levels to minimise the risk of diabetic retinopathy, increase intentions to engage in regular eye examinations and increase self-reported eye examinations.
Delivery: the leaflet will be mailed on a single occasion to study participants.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome is increase/decrease in self-reported eye health examinations assessed via response to a single questionnaire item ("Since you were diagnosed with diabetes, have you had your eye health checked?").

In order to minimise social desirability bias and any potential confounding influence of question-behaviour effect, the question will be embedded within a suite of standard self-management questions based on information already provided to all new NDSS registrants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome is increase/decrease in intention to seek eye health examinations assessed via summed response to three intention items designed specifically for this purpose. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome is increase/decrease in knowledge of modifiable risk factors associated with diabetic retinopathy assessed using a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosed with type 2 diabetes in the past three years
2. Australian residents
3. Able to read English
4. Registered with the National Diabetes Services Scheme (NDSS)
5. One of either:
- young adult (aged 18-39 years), or
- live in rural/regional locations of Victoria, Australia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Other diabetes types (e.g. Type 1, gestational, MODY)
Impaired cognitive ability</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subject enrolment: all eligible NDSS registrants who have agreed to be contacted for research will receive an invitation to participate in the Diabetes and Eye Health (Phase 2) study.  If interested, they can enter the study website (www.yoursay.org.au) where they will be asked to confirm eligibility status and will be asked to read the Plain Language Statement.  At this point, they can consent to continue with the study.  Participants will only be identified by their computer's IP address and will be randomly allocated using the method outlined below where treatment allocation is concealed from those administering the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized to one of two treatment arms (intervention vs no intervention).  Group allocation will be managed by an independent third party using an online random number generator.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The randomized controlled trail is a Solomon four group design, a rigorous design which allows for control of potential question behaviour effect (QBE) which was detected in an earlier, qualitative phase of the project.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Minimum sample size: an a priori power analysis was conducted using G*Power  and population effect size of 0.3 was estimated using meta-analytic and systematic reviews.  Based on 80% power and significance level of 0.05 a final sample size was calculated at 721 (388 for rural/regional and 333 for adults with early-onset type 2 diabetes).  This estimate also takes into consideration high cohort-specific attrition rates for adults with early-onset type 2 diabetes, reported by other RCT studies and assumed a loss to follow-up of 40%.  

Statistical analyses: discriminant function analysis will be conducted to assess differences between conditions (ie. eye examinations) on demographic characteristics and baseline outcome measures.  Binomial logistic regression analyses will be conducted on pre-intervention data to determine which modifiable cognitions are most strongly correlated with having had an eye exam.  They will be rank ordered in terms of discriminant capacity and highest ranking messages retained for inclusion in psycho-educational leaflet.

Upon completion of follow-up data collection, an algorithm outlined by Braver and Braver (1988) will be utilised which recommends 2 x 2 between group ANOVA on the post-intervention scores to determine existence of main and interaction effects of pre-intervention questionnaire.  Subsequent analyses are determined by presence or otherwise of pre-measurement effect.

All analyses will be performed on an intention-to-treat basis in the first instance although per protocol analyses may also be conducted to further explore the pattern of results.  Effect sizes will be calculated and reported as odds ratios (OR) with 95% CI and missing covariate values will be imputed using multiple imputation (MI) methods.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>721</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University (The Australian Centre for Behavioural Research in Diabetes)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>206 Queensberry Street
Melbourne
VIC 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Vision 2020 Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/174-176 Queen St, Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Diabetes - Australia (Victoria)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>570 Elizabeth Street
Melbourne
VIC 3000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with diabetes are vulnerable to diabetic retinopathy (DR); a common complication that damages the blood vessels at the back of the eye. The early stages of DR are asymptomatic; early detection via eye examination and timely treatment are important in reducing the risk of vision loss. National Health and Medical Research Council recommend eye examinations at diabetes diagnosis and minimum every two years thereafter. Some at-risk groups have unacceptably low eye examination rates, including adults with type 2 diabetes (T2DM) who are i) 18-39 years or ii) from rural/regional Victoria (eye exam rates are 50% and 65% respectively).  

The aim of this project is to develop communication messages designed to increase eye examination rates for people from the two at-risk groups. Presented in leaflet format, the messages will be mailed to eligible registrants on the National Diabetes Services Scheme (NDSS). It is hypothesized that participants who have not previously had an eye examination and who receive a psycho-educational leaflet intervention containing theoretically derived messages demonstrated to correlate with the target behaviour will report:
a. Increased intentions to seek eye examinations, and 
b. Higher rate of eye examinations than control group participants, at follow up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.yoursay.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The research design (Solomon 4-group design) was chosen because it both allows identification of key communication messages and controls for a potential confounding variable; question-behaviour effect (QBE) which was identified in an earlier exploratory study (DUHREC 2013-157). See participant flow diagram, which is attached to the original ANZCTR registration record.

QBE is a recognized phenomenon whereby asking questions and measuring intentions about a specific behaviour influences the performance of that behaviour. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Deakin Research Integrity
Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood Victoria 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-156</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367127-RCT participant flow diagram.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Speight</name>
      <address>The Australian Centre for Behavioural Research in Diabetes
206 Queensberry Street
Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 8648 1844</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)3 9667 1778</fax>
      <email>jspeight@acbrd.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amelia Lake</name>
      <address>The Australian Centre for Behavioural Research in Diabetes
206 Queensberry Street
Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 9251 7363</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)3 9667 1778</fax>
      <email>alake@acbrd.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Speight</name>
      <address>The Australian Centre for Behavioural Research in Diabetes
206 Queensberry Street
Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 8648 1844</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)3 9667 1778 </fax>
      <email>jspeight@acbrd.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amelia Lake</name>
      <address>The Australian Centre for Behavioural Research in Diabetes
206 Queensberry Street
Melbourne
VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)3 9251 7363</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)3 9667 1778  </fax>
      <email>alake@acbrd.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>