<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366318">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000523606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of mindfulness training on maternal stress, depressive symptoms and awareness of present moment experience: A pilot randomised trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In pregnant women, does mindfulness training, compared to pregnancy support, reduce maternal stress and depressive symptoms, and increase awareness of present moment experience?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1156-7824</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mindfulness group training. The Mindfulness in Pregnancy Program (MiPP) drew on the theoretical constructs of mindfulness and cognitive behavioural therapy adapted for a pregnant population and was informed by the work of Cassandra Vietens Mindful Motherhood program (Vieten, 2009; Vieten and Astin, 2008) and Nancy Bardackes Mindfulness-Based Childbirth and Parenting program (MBCP) (Bardacke, 2012). Content included experiential learning to enhance awareness, acceptance, compassion, connection and mindfulness in everyday life. The co-emergence model of behaviour reinforcement was built into the MiPP (Cayoun, 2015). This MiPP consisted of 2-hour, weekly sessions, for 8 weeks, using mindfulness of thoughts and feelings through breath awareness, mindfulness of body through guided body scanning and movement practices, and observing self, being present to self and baby, Small groups sessions with a total of 12 were conducted by a registered nurse/midwife trained with a Graduate Diploma in Mindfulness-integrated CBT,  experienced in conducting mindfulness programs.</interventions>
    <comparator>Pregnancy Support Group (PSP) consisted of an 8-week support group of 2-hour, weekly sessions. Following limited direction from the facilitator, women were encouraged to put forward issues that they would like to have supported. The PSP utilised a generalised midwifery approach to the topics without the mindfulness concepts or practices. PSP topics included: communication, empathy, body image, pain relief options, breastfeeding, caring for the newborn, and mental health and postnatal depression. Class activities included: identification and discussion of stressors (including finances), active listening, identifying own strengths, wants versus needs, self-portrait highlighting physical changes, emotional response to birthing, and breastfeeding images; envisaging support networks, brainstorming resources and childcare options.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Perceived Stress Scale; mean difference in pre-, post-, and 6-week post-intervention scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and 6 weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale; ; mean difference in pre-, post-, and 6-week post-intervention scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and 6 weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 3: Mindfulness Attention Awareness Scale; mean difference in pre-, post-, and 6-week post-intervention scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and 6 weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A program satisfaction questionnaire prepared specifically for this study was administered immediately following the program, in paper format; identifying participants' perceptions of what they learnt, impact of the program, what they liked most and least, whether they would recommend the intervention, and other comments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed immediately following the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Low risk pregnancy in the second trimester at the start of the intervention; 18 years or older; able to read and speak English; having a planned hospital birth; and those who commit to attending all eight sessions. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of mental illness; known inability to attend more than four sessions; a score 13 or higher on the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale, and who answer in the affirmative to question 10 indicating that they have considered self-harm.  
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once women show an interest in participation and meet the inclusion criteria, they will be given the participant information sheet and consent form to read and given the opportunity to ask questions. If they consent to participate in the study, randomisation will proceed by the researcher taking a concealed, opaque envelope and allocating the intervention group accordingly. Allocation of intervention groups has have been done by an off-site researcher.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated block randomisation was used and the block size is concealed from the recruiting researchers.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 24 women in each group would replicate the mean difference of 3.5 between pre- and post-intervention Perceived Stress Scale scores found by Vietan and Austin *, with 80% power, p=0.05, 2-tailed and allowing for attrition of 30%. (*Vieten, C. and J. Astin, Effects of a mindfulness-based intervention during pregnancy on prenatal stress and mood: Results of a pilot study. Archives of Women's Mental Health, 2008. 11(1): p. 67-74.)
Quantitative data will be analysed using descriptive statistics. Repeated measures MANOVA will be used to analyse between- and within-group differences in the survey scores. Content analysis of qualitative data will be conducted.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/08/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>48</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>2/12/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Casey Hospital - Berwick</hospital>
    <postcode>3806 - Berwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Jill Beattie</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Monash University
PO Box 527
Frankston  Vic  3165
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nurses Board of Victoria Legacy Limited (NBVLL)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NBVLL Secretariat
PO Box 327
Wenouree, Vic, 3355</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Christine East</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash University / Monash Health
c/- Birth Suite
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton VIC 3168
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Helen Hall</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Monash University
PO Box 527
Frankston, Victoria, 3199
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Rosalind Lau</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery
Monash University, Clayton Campus
Wellington Rd
Clayton, Victoria 3800
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mary Anne Biro</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery 
Building G, Peninsula Campus 
Monash University 
McMahons Road, Frankston VIC 3199 
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomised pilot study measured the effects of a group Mindfulness in Pregnancy Program (MiPP) on stress, depressive symptoms, and awareness of present moment experience, compared to an active control Pregnancy Support Group. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Beattie, J., Hall, H., Biro, M., East, C., &amp; Lau, R. (2017). Effects of mindfulness on maternal stress, depressive symptoms and awareness of present moment experience: A pilot randomised trial. Midwifery, 50, 174-183. doi:http://doi.org/10.1016/j.midw.2017.04.006.

Hall, H., Beattie, J., Lau, R., East, C., &amp; Biro, M. A. (2016). Mindfulness and perinatal mental health: A systematic review. Women and Birth, 29, 62-71.  doi:http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.wombi.2015.08.006.

Beattie, J., Hall, H., Biro, M., Lau, R., &amp; East, C. (2014). Does mindfulness training reduce the stress of pregnancy? Australian Nursing and Midwifery Journal, 22(1), 39. 

Beattie, J., Hall, H., Biro, M., Lau, R., &amp; East, C. (19-22 April 2015). The effects of mindfulness training compared to pregnancy support on maternal stress and depressions: A pilot randomised trial. Paper presented at the 19th Annual Meeting of The Perinatal Society of Australia and New Zealand, Melbourne, Australia.

Beattie, J., Hall, H., Lau, R., Biro, M., &amp; East, C. (2015). Managing pregnancy-related stress: Reported impact of the Mindfulness in Pregnancy Program (MiPP) and the
Pregnancy Support Program (PSP) Paper presented at the Australasian Marce Society for Perinatal Mental Health 2015 Conference, Adelaide, South Australia. 

Hall, H., Beattie, J., Lau, R., East, C., &amp; Biro, M. A. (2015). The effectiveness of mindfulness training on perinatal mental health; a systematic review. (Poster presentation) Paper presented at the 10th International Congress on Complementary Medicine Research, Jeju, Sth Korea.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate
Monash Health
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton road
Clayton, VIC, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14103B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University
Building 3E, Room 111
Clayton Campus
Wellington Road
Clayton, VIC, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF14/1361 - 2014000636</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jill Beattie</name>
      <address>Monash University, 
PO Box 527
Frankston
VIC, 3165</address>
      <phone>+61 0414835408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jill.beattie@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jill Beattie</name>
      <address>Monash University, 
PO Box 527
Frankston
VIC, 3165</address>
      <phone>+61 0414835408</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jill.beattie@monash.edu;  jbeatti@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jill Beattie</name>
      <address>Monash University, 
PO Box 527
Frankston
VIC, 3165</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9904 4653</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jill.beattie@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jill Beattie</name>
      <address>Monash University, 
PO Box 527
Frankston
VIC, 3165</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9904 4653</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jill.beattie@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>