<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365504">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000116628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Keeping Active using Exercise-based Video Games:  a physical activity programme for older people living in rest homes </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Among older people living in long term care facilities does a supervised programme of exercise-based video games improve measures of physical performance and activity when compared to usual activities? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Loss of mobility</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical performance in older people living in long term care facilities</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity levels of older people living in long term care facilities</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in the intervention group will undertake interactive exercise video games using the Xbox Kinect platform, selected and supervised by a study investigator. Sessions will be offered over 8 weeks for approximately 45-60 minutes, twice weekly.  Exercise activities will be chosen by a physiotherapist based on the residents baseline physical performance measures Activities will include balance and lower limb exercise and also upper limb activities. Activities maybe progressed or varied each session, depending on the individual skill levels. 
Although the video games are generally designed for play by 1-2 people, residents of similar ability may be able to join in the activity at one time. Residents may also be able to rest while others do an activity, before joining in again.   The group size and precise way the exercise program will be conducted will be dependent on the spread of participants abilities as well as the facilitys schedule and physical environment. Participants will be reminded about each session but attendance remains voluntary. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in control facilities will continue usual activities including participation in any activity sessions that they would normally attend.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The De Morton Mobility Index (DEMMI). The DEMMI is a 15 item test battery measuring physical performance, completed under supervision, which includes transfers, walking and balance tasks scored on a 100-point scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Timed Up and Go (TUG). The TUG is a commonly used measure of agility, scored in seconds, which involves rising from a chair, walking 3m at usual pace, turning, walking back and sitting back down.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual activity. Measured using a triaxial accelerometer. The duration of time spent active (in ambulation and standing) and sedentary (sitting and lying down) measured over the waking day, over a 4 day period</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Older people living in rest homes who can communicate, transfer and walk independently with or without a walking aid, regardless of cognitive ability, will be eligible to participate. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Insufficient vision to see a television screen; and any unstable medical, orthopaedic or neurological condition that would contraindicate participation in an exercise program e.g. acute febrile illness, unstable or acute heart failure. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A cluster randomised controlled study design will be used, with rest home facilities that consent to participate randomised to either the intervention or the control group. Residents in enrolled facilities will be invited to participate.
After completion of baseline measures of all enrolled residents , the recruitment investigator will telephone the independent investigator holding the randomisation schedule.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be via a computerised central randomisation service. An independent investigator in a distant site will hold a computer-generated randomisation schedule. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size estimates for this study have been calculated based on the DEMMI outcome measure. Based on existing research, estimated from a baseline mean score on the DEMMI of 42 +/- 15, and an expected minimal clinically important difference of 10 (power = 0.80; 2tailed with alpha set at 0.05), the sample size required is 72 ( 36 per group). Adjusting for the cluster design effect (cluster size 8, ICC 0.2), 82 would be required. At 20% attrition, the sample size would be 102. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to examine whether a supervised programme of exercise-based video games can improve measures of physical performance and increase habitual activity, when compared to usual activities, and can be implemented in a long  term care (rest home) setting. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lynne Taylor</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation (NIHI) 
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lm.taylor@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lynne Taylor</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation (NIHI) 
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lm.taylor@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lynne Taylor</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation (NIHI) 
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lm.taylor@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>