<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364312">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000593730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Operating room throughput after total intravenous anesthesia with propofol compared with desflurane anesthesia in ophthalmology surgery: A retrospective comparative study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A retrospective comparative study to compare the anesthesia-related times that comprise a patients hospital stay and postoperative nausea and vomiting following ophthalmology surgery in adult patients who received different anesthesia techniques, TIVA with propofol or desflurane anesthesia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Efficiency of operation room following ophthalmology surgery in adult patients who received TIVA with propofol anesthesia versus desflurane anesthesia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This retrospective comparative study was compared the anesthesia-related times that comprise a patients hospital stay and postoperative nausea and vomiting following ophthalmology surgery in adult patients who received different anesthesia techniques, TIVA with propofol or desflurane anesthesia at Tri-Service General Hospital.
Electronic/paper medical records of all the patients were collected and reviewed from Jan. 2010 to Dec. 2011. </interventions>
    <comparator>Electronic/paper medical records of all the patients who underwent ophthalmology surgery were collected and reviewed from Jan. 2010 to Dec. 2011.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The various perioperative time intervals</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Anesthesia time: start of anesthesia to patient leaves operating room.
2. Surgical time: incision to surgical complete.
3. Emergence time: surgery complete to patient leaves operating room.
4. PAR stay time: the beginning of care in the PAR to discharge to the general ward. 
5. Total time in operating room: start of anesthesia to discharge to the general ward. (via electronic medical records)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) and rescue for PONV</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 24 hours after surgery (via paper medical records)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>postoperative recovery outcomes: days in hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>at least 14 days after surgery (via electronic/paper medical records)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All adult patients who underwent ophthalmology surgery at Tri-Service General Hospital and received TIVA with propofol or desflurane anesthesia from Jan. 2010 to Dec. 2011.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients were excluded if they met any of the following criteria: data missing, pediatric patients and patients receiving sevoflurane or propofol combined inhalation anesthesia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/12/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1405</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Chueng-He Lu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anesthesiology , Tri-Service General Hospital, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Chueng-He Lu</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anesthesiology , Tri-Service General Hospital, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>For surgical cases with general anesthesia, components of nonsurgical operating room (OR) time include induction (arrival of patient in the OR until the start of positioning), extubation (dressing on patient to extubation), and OR exit. The interval between the end of surgery and extubation (emergence time) is of special interest to anesthesia care providers and companies because it is affected by anesthetic agents. In Taiwan, a new system of Diagnosis Related Groups (DRG) has taken its part in hospital billing service since 2010. This means that the previous billing system will not be valid for current anesthesia cost in the OR any more. Instead, one sum payment one case, selection of the anesthetic technique has to be determined: cheaper agents and least possible anesthesia-controlled time to remain competitive in the operating field.
Total intravenous anesthesia (TIVA) via target controlled infusion (TCI) system incorporating the combined use of propofol and remifentanil has indeed been shown to provide more rapid emergence than other anesthesia techniques. In our previous study, we found patients undergoing prolonged procedure recover faster after TIVA than after volatile anesthesia. To evaluate potential resources for reducing time in the OR, we performed a retrospective study to compare anesthesia-related times following ophthalmology (OPH) surgery in adult patients who received different anesthesia techniques, TIVA with propofol or desflurane anesthesia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board of Tri-Service General Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>#325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>100-05-168</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chueng-He Lu</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology , Tri-Service General Hospital, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886-2-87927128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>box.lu@msa.hinet.net</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chueng-He Lu</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology , Tri-Service General Hospital, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886-2-87927128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>box.lu@msa.hinet.net</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chueng-He Lu</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology , Tri-Service General Hospital, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886-2-87927128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>box.lu@msa.hinet.net</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>