<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372219">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000178347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the efficacy and feasibility of a university-based high intensity interval training
program (Uni HIIT) on health and well-being in young adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating the efficacy and feasibility of a university-based high intensity interval training
program (Uni HIIT) on health and well-being in young adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Uni HIIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular health
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mental Health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>* Project summary:
The overarching aim of this study is to investigate the impact of a unique HIIT program (Uni
HIIT) on cardiorespiratory fitness (primary outcome), physical activity, body composition,
stress,executive function, well-being and psycho-social health outcomes in low active young adults when implemented in university settings. Using a randomised controlled trial (RCT) the Uni HIIT program will be implemented
Phase 1: single site RCT at the UoN (n=60)

The proposed study design is a randomised controlled trial with a wait-list control investigating the effects of an 8-week high intensity university-based interval training intervention.
Assessments will be conducted at baseline (March 2017) and repeated immediately
post-intervention (July 2017) and follow-up (November 2017) . Ethics approval for the study has been gained from the UoN Human Research Ethics Committee and study participants will provide written informed consent to take part in the study.
Uni HIIT Intervention Uni HIIT will be an 8-week intervention for university students focusing on improving fitness and psycho-social outcomes via the provision of short intense interval training sessions 3 times per week (total of 24 sessions). Sessions will be run by a member of the research team (qualified physical educators) and last 10 minutes in duration, with a work to rest ratio of 30 secs: 30 secs. Exercise will include a combination of 8 core aerobic exercises and 8 core strength exercises (e.g., running skipping, side stepping, push ups, squats, lunges); and combinations of these exercises using a ball (e.g. dribbling the ball while running, lunges holding a ball above the head). Baseline assessments will be completed one week prior to the intervention beginning, Follow-up assessments will be conducted in the week following intervention completion and 4-months.
Students will be randomised to either the:
i. High Intensity Interval Training plus body weight resistance training exercises (Uni HIIT )
conditions: which will combine cardio-based exercises and muscular fitness exercises; OR
ii. Wait-list Control group (CON): students randomised to CON will receive the HIIT Uni program once the intervention and all follow-up assessments have been completed by all groups.
To ensure appropriate exercise intensity is maintained throughout each session (target 85% HRMmax), participants will wear heart rate monitors (Polar H7) which connect to a central iPad application (Polar Team) monitored by a staff member. Minimum, maximum and average heart rate for the session will be recorded. Participants will have access to this information during sessions.
Based on the success of our previous HIITT study, and our studies investigating the effectiveness of variety in PA, program sessions will be designed to be enjoyable and include a variety of exercises to promote adherence. In addition, sessions will promote peer support and encouragement, and will be completed in pairs (participant choice); with one participant undertaking the work phase while their partner rests (and vice-versa). As the intervention progresses participants will also be provided with additional elements of choice including: music(playlists), exercise choice during a workout, and choice of workout.
Note: Adherence to the program will be monitored via HR monitor data
</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list Control group (CON): students randomised to CON will receive the HIIT Uni program once the intervention and all follow-up assessments have been completed by all groups (6months).
 They will continue with their normal daily rountine during the intervention period</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular Fitness (20 m shuttle run test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at baseline (March 2017) and repeated immediate post-intervention (week after intervention completion) (July 2017) and 4-month follow-up (November 2017) follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscular fitness (90 degree push-up test &amp; the standing long jump)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at baseline (March 2017) and repeated immediate post-intervention (week after intervention completion) (July 2017) and 4-month follow-up (November 2017) follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Composition (BMI BMI Z) and body fat distribution (DEXA / INBODY) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at baseline (March 2017) and repeated immediately
post-intervention (July 2017) and 4 m0nth follow-up (November 2017) follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological well-being
Global Physical Self-Concept (Physical Self-Description)
Psychological health: Strength and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ)
Exercise related wellbeing (Feelings Scale: The Flourishing Scale and The Scale of Positive and Negative Experience) 
Psychological well-being: Diener psychological flourishing scale 
Stress: Perceived Stress Scale
Anxiety: Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) (short form) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at baseline (March 2017) and repeated immediately
post-intervention (July 2017) and 4- month follow-up (November 2017) follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Executive function (The Trail Making Test (TMT) )</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at baseline (March 2017) and repeated immediately
post-intervention (July 2017) and 4 month follow-up (November 2017) follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels will be measured using 7 day pedometery. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments will be conducted at baseline (March 2017) and repeated immediately
post-intervention (July 2017) and  4-month follow-up (November 2017) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motivation to engage in PA (Behavioural Regulations in Exercise Questionnaire-2 (BREQ-2)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After each HIIT session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male and female students from the UoN will be recruited to participate in the intervention and eligible study participants will be aged 18-25 years and have no existing medical conditions or injuries preventing participation is assessments or the Uni HIIT sessions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Injury or illness preventing physical participation  and / or age outside the 18-25 range</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Group allocation will be performed using a computer-based alogorithm performed by a researcher not involved in the study. Researchers performing assessments at baseline will also be blinded to group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Group allocation will be performed using a computer-based alogorithm performed by a researcher not involved in the study</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All outcomes will be assessed using linear mixed models in IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows (Version 20) (SPSS, INC 2010, IBM Company, Armonk, NY) and alpha levels set to 0.05. These models will be used to assess the impact of treatment (Uni HITT or control group), time (treated as categorical with levels that include baseline and follow-up) and group by time interaction.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>14/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive,
Callaghan NSW
Australia 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The overarching aim of this study is to investigate the impact of a unique HIIT program (Uni
HIIT) on cardiorespiratory fitness (primary outcome), physical activity, body composition,
stress,executive function, well-being and psycho-social health outcomes in low active young adults when implemented in university settings. Using a randomised controlled trial (RCT) the Uni HIIT program will be implemented
Phase 1: single site RCT at the UoN (n=60)</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2016-0407</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Narelle Eather</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
HPE310
University Drive
Callaghan, NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61249216232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Narelle Eather</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
HPE310
University Drive
Callaghan, NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61249216232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Narelle Eather </name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
HPE310
University Drive
Callaghan, NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61249216232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Narelle Eather </name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
HPE310
University Drive
Callaghan, NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61249216232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>narelle.eather@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>