<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371155">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001086459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and feasibility of Immediate Cooling and Emergency Decompression (ICED) for cervical spinal cord injuries</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Immediate Cooling and Emergency Decompression (ICED) in Traumatic Cervical Spinal Cord Injury - A Safety and Feasibility study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ICED- Immediate Cooling and Emergency Decompression</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic Cervical Spinal Cord Injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic Central Cord Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with cervical spinal cord injury (SCI) will be cooled by paramedics using ice-cold intravenous saline to a target core temperature of 33-34 degrees Celsius. Cooling will be continued in hospital using an intravascular cooling catheter (or surface temperature management system) set to maintain the target temperature of 33-34 degrees Celsius. The cooling method selected in hospital will be chosen at the discretion of the treating physician.

Patients will be maintained at the target temperature (33.0-34.0 degrees Celsius) for 24 hours post-treatment initiation and then slowly rewarmed to 36 degrees Celsius  over 12 hours. Controlled temperature management (36-37 degrees Celsius) will be continued for a further 72 hours. Patients enrolled in the trial will be admitted to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) and core temperature recorded hourly across the period of therapy. Measures to control core temperature will be documented, including volume and duration of ice-cold saline infused, temperature management system selected, intensity and duration of temperature control and use of passive surface cooling measures. 

Patients will also undergo decompression surgery as appropriate within 8 hours of injury for cervical fracture and/or dislocation injuries, and within 18 hours of injury for acute central cord syndrome. The aim of decompression will be to restore the spinal canal diameter to normal by reducing the dislocated vertebrae and removal of bone fragments, disc and other material.  decision of whether surgery is required,  Specifics including the number of levels decompressed, approach (anterior vs. posterior) and use of instrumentation will be left to the treating orthopaedic surgeons and/or neurosurgeons. Procedure duration averages between 2 and 4 hours and varies depending upon the extent of injury.</interventions>
    <comparator>Study data will be compared to historical injuries and concurrent patients with cervical SCI treated at the Alfred Hospital since 2010. Control patient information will be collected by retrospective medical record review.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with vertebral fracture and/or dislocation injuries undergoing decompression within 8 hours following acute cervical SCI, will be assessed by medical record review.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours post-injury</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with acute central cord syndrome undergoing decompression within 18 hours following injury, will be assessed by medical record review. </outcome>
      <timepoint>18 hours post-injury</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients achieving decompression within target time frames and hypothermia as per protocol will be assessed by medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post-injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients achieving target core temperature 33-34 degrees Celsius will be assessed by medical record review. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time patient temperature reaches 33-34 degrees Celsius</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time from injury to 35.0 degrees Celsius or below will be assessed by medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time patient temperature reaches 35.0 degrees Celsius or below</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time from injury to the target core temperature of 33-34 degrees Celsius will be assessed by medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time patient reaches target core temperature of 33-34 degrees Celsius</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Temperature profile over the period of cooling and temperature management. Core temperature will be monitored by a thermistor within the intravascular catheter. If cooling is performed using a surface temperature management system, a bladder thermometer will be used to monitor core temperature.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hourly measurements of temperature from initiation of cooling through to the end of temperature controlled management </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Temperature reduction achieved by paramedics will be assessed by medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of paramedic initiation of cooling until patient admission to hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time of initiation of cooling by paramedics will be assessed by medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of paramedic initiation of cooling until patient admission to hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of moderate and severe pneumonia within 14 days of injury will be assessed by medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of cooling until 14 days post-injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of other respiratory complications, for example pulmonary oedema (fluid accumulation in the lungs), and atelectasis (partial lung collapse), will be assessed clinically using defined criteria and by imaging including chest X-ray and chest CT where necessary. The incidence of adverse events such as urinary tract infection or surgical site infection will be assessed clinically using defined criteria and pathology testing of blood/urine/sputum samples. </outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of cooling until 6 months post-injury (+/- 1 month)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of shivering and need for anti-shivering measures will be assessed by medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>From initiation of cooling until the end of temperature controlled management </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of administration of Fresh Frozen Plasma, Cryoprecipitate or Prothrombin X will be assessed by medical record review. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Period of hospital admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of intubation will be assessed by medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>Period from intubation until extubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU length of stay will be assessed by medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>Period of ICU admission until discharge </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> International Standards for Neurological Classification of Spinal Cord Injury (ISNCSCI) grading of injury and motor score will be performed by a trained assessor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-injury  (+/- 1 month)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spinal Cord Independence Measure (SCIM) questionnaire (self-care and mobility sections only) </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-injury  (+/- 1 month)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Graded Redefined Assessment of Strength, Sensibility and Prehension (GRASSP) test of grip strength and prehension</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-injury  (+/- 1 month)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower limb motor function will be assessed using the 10-meter walk test </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-injury  (+/- 1 month)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grip strength (myometry)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post-injury  (+/- 1 month)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The volume of fluid infused by paramedics will be assessed by medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of paramedic initiation of cooling until patient admission to hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Cervical vertebral column trauma
Less than 2 hours post-injury
Able to participate in the Spinal Emergency Evaluation of Deficits (SPEED) neurological assessment
Neurological deficits in all 4 limbs: Flicker or no ankle or toe movement bilaterally (SPEED motor score of 0-2) and weak or no hand grip on SPEED neurological assessment 
Planned transport to the participating study hospital

Additional criterion for potential central cord syndrome patients: Less than 4 hours post-injury with definite foot movement (SPEED motor of 2-4), weak or no hand movement and American Spinal Injury Association Impairment Scale (AIS) motor examination score less than or equal to 50/100</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to commence induction of hypothermia within 2 hours post-injury (or within 4 hours post-injury for central cord syndrome patients)
Unable to follow commands due to significant head injury, drug or alcohol intoxication, mental or hearing impairment 
Glasgow coma score &lt;13
Suspected multiple traumatic injuries with significant blood loss (due to likely trauma to the chest, abdomen, pelvis or long bone fractures)
Known or obvious pregnancy
Cardiac arrest at scene 
Pre-injury major neurological deficit (e.g. stroke, Parkinsons disease or dementia)

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Fishers exact test will be used to analyse the primary outcome and to detect differences in the proportion of hypothermic patients. Fishers exact test will also be used to detect differences in the proportion of patients experiencing respiratory and other complications. Continuous measures will be compared by analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey HSD (honestly significant difference) post-hoc error correction. Six-month outcomes will be compared by ANOVA with Tukey HSD post-hoc error correction for continuous measures and the Kruskal-Wallis test for ranked data.

Sample size was calculated using historical data of 8% of patients with vertebral fracture and/or dislocation injuries undergo decompression within 8 hours following injury, while 6% of patients with acute central cord syndrome undergo decompression within 18 hours following injury (Victorian data). To determine the feasibility of undertaking early surgery in 80% of patients within these time frames, 9 patients with cervical spinal cord injury as a result vertebral fracture and/or dislocation injuries and 9 patients with acute central cord injuries will be required for adequate statistical power (using Fishers exact test to detect a difference in proportion between 8% and 80%, a=0.05 and beta=0.2). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/11/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>1</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parkville, VIC 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street, 
Canberra City, ACT 2600
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Safety, Compensation and Recovery Research (ISCRR)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>222 Exhibition Street
Melbourne, VIC 3000
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In young patients, traumatic injury to the cervical spinal cord generally results from vertebral fracture and dislocation of vertebra, with injury to the spinal cord occurring not just at the time of impact, but also from compression of the spinal cord as a consequence of the displaced vertebra. Traumatic central cord syndrome differs from traumatic SCI in that the general mechanism is hyper-extension of the spine, causing acute severe canal restriction, in a patient with pre-existing narrowing of the cervical canal.  Compression of the spinal cord as a result of canal stenosis and cord swelling usually occurs soon after injury. 
Animal and preliminary human data demonstrate that urgent relief of compression appears to greatly improve outcome. However, urgent decompression in humans is difficult to achieve because of the time occupied by transportation, investigation, and stabilisation of the patient as well as the organisation of surgery. Pre-clinical data demonstrate that hypothermia can suspend the progressive damage caused to the spinal cord by compression thereby allowing decompressive surgery to be performed in a clinically achievable time frame (Batchelor et al. 2010). 

The primary purpose of the ICED study is to determine whether the combination of hypothermia and early decompression is able to improve outcomes in patients with severe spinal cord injuries of the neck. Selected patients will be cooled by paramedics or emergency physicians immediately following injury and then rapidly transported to theatre to undergo surgical decompression and stabilisation of the spinal cord. Cooling will be maintained for 24 hours and then patients will be slowly rewarmed and monitored over the next 72 hours.

The ICED safety and feasibility study will determine whether it is possible to cool patients with spinal cord injuries resulting from vertebral trauma in the neck in the first hours after injury. This study will also determine whether it is feasible to operate on patients very early after injury. As well as determining whether these interventions can be performed, the incidence and severity of complications will be monitored to determine whether these interventions are safe. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne, VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Batchelor</name>
      <address>Level 4, Clinical Sciences Building 
Royal Parade (via Melbourne Private Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville VIC 3050
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 7958</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.batch@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Camila Battistuzzo</name>
      <address>Level 4, Clinical Sciences Building 
Royal Parade (via Melbourne Private Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>camilab@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Batchelor </name>
      <address>Level 4, Clinical Sciences Building 
Royal Parade (via Melbourne Private Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville VIC 3050
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 7958</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.batch@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Camila Battistuzzo</name>
      <address>Level 4, Clinical Sciences Building 
Royal Parade (via Melbourne Private Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>