<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368802">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001304527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sedation Practice in Paediatric Intensive Care Cardiac Patients: Cardiac Baby SPICE -pilot randomised trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In children requiring surgical repair of congenital cardiac defects, does the use of Dexmedetomidine as the primary sedative agent compared to Midazolam reduce the length of mechanical ventilation and PICU length of stay.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Cardiac Baby SPICE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Congenital cardiac defects requiring surgical repair</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intravenous infusion of Dexmedetomidine 1mcg/kg/hr commenced at sternotomy for the duration of the surgical procedure and during mechanical ventilation in the paediatric intensive care.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intravenous infusion of Midazolam 80mcg/kg/hr commenced at sternotomy for the duration of the surgical procedure and during mechanical ventilation in the paediatric intensive care.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the feasibility of screening and recruiting patients prior to cardiac surgery, Assessed of feasibility by proportion of screened and eligible patients who were recruited, protocol fidelity, proportion of enrolled patients who were intubated for longer than 24 hours, duration from time of intubation to time of randomisation and time from randomisation to time of commencement of study medications, retention of subjects to 90 day follow-up
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of 12mth patient study period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the process of delivering an intervention that uses dexmedetomidine as the primary sedative agent prior to placement on cardiopulmonary bypass, and early in the ICU admission, and that minimises the use of benzodiazepines. This will be assessed via daily calculation of total use dexmedetomidine</outcome>
      <timepoint>After all participants have been recruited</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure separation between the midazolam group and the demedetomidine group with respect to administered doses of sedative and analgesic drugs. The total cumulative and total daily dose of dexmedetomidine, midazolam, propofol, clonidine, ketamine, fentanyl, morphine and other sedatives assessed by review of hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from PICU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To further assess the safety of delivering an intervention that uses dexmedetomidine as the primary sedative agent prior to placement on cardiopulmonary bypass, and early in the ICU admission assessed via adverse events reported on case report forms. It is recognised that the paediatric intensive care patient population will experience a number of common aberrations in laboratory values, signs and symptoms due to the severity of the underlying disease and the impact of standard therapies. These will not necessarily constitute an adverse event unless they require significant intervention or are considered to be of concern in the investigators clinical judgement.

Adverse events
Unplanned extubation assessed by review of hospital chart
Unplanned removal of vascular lines  assessed by review of hospital chart
Re-intubation  assessed by review of hospital chart

Adverse drug effects
Bradycardia (&lt; 2 standard deviations below mean for age) assessed by EEG
Hypotension (&lt; 2 standard deviations below mean for age) assessed by IAL BP or non-invasive BP
Drug withdrawal syndromes assessed by WAT-1 assessment </outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety will be monitored throughout admission to PICU and assessed at discharge from PICU.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of mechanical ventilation during PICU admission assessed by review of hospital records.  .

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At PICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare level of sedation achieved between intervention and control groups using the State Behavioural Scale. 2.	The proportion of patients in SBS categories -2 to -3 (deep sedation), -1 to +1 (light sedation) and +2, assessed every day in ventilated patients still receiving sedative infusions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed a 6 time intervals per day during PICU admission until PICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of unplanned extubation assessed by review of hospital record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at discharge from PICU </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay in PICU assessed by review of hospital record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At PICU discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare incidence of neurodevelopmental delay using Bayley III </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 and 12 months post PICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare incidence of new morbidities using FSS</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 &amp; 12 months post PICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare incidence of Health Related Quality of Life using the PEDS-Qual</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 and 12 month post PICU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Incidence of  unplanned removal of vascular lines assessed by review of hospital record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at discharge from PICU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.   The patient is undergoing surgical repair of a congenital heart defect requiring cardiopulmonary bypass and will require mechanical ventilation via an endotracheal tube post-operatively, and the treating clinician believes that:
2.	The patient will require immediate post-operative AND ongoing sedative medication for comfort, safety, and to facilitate the delivery of life support measures.
3.	The patient is expected to remain intubated post-operatively.	
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Age &gt; 6 months
2.	Proven or suspected acute primary brain lesion that may result in global impairment of conscious level or cognition, such as traumatic brain injury, intracranial haemorrhage, intracranial infection or hypoxic brain injury.
3.	Allergy to dexmedetomidine
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomised prior to theatre using paper randomisation envelope concealment </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be done in permuted blocks </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a feasibility trial of 2 randomised sedative interventions used in critically ill patients, with the primary outcome being the difference in the proportion of time patients successfully achieve light sedation in the first 48 hours of sedation in intensive care in each arm. A sample size of 60 subjects will be sufficient to show a reduction of at least 25% in the cumulative sedation score in the intervention arm as compared to the standard arm, in the first 48 hours, and allow meaningful assessment of important secondary outcomes. The cumulative sedation score will be a continuous variable between 0 and 12 and a t-test to compare the mean cumulative sedation score in each group. Means with standard deviation for normally distributed variables and medians with interquartile ranges for non-normally distributed continuous variables, and proportions with 95% confidence limits, will be reported. If feasible, a logistic regression analysis will be used to identify factors such as site or patient characteristics that are associated with a particular pattern of sedation or clinical practice, such as deviation from the targeted level of sedation or inappropriate deep sedation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Paediatic Critical Care Research Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PCCRG
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lady CIlento Children's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>501 Stanley Street
South Brisbane, Queensland 4101</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Intravenous sedatives and analgesics are commonly administered to mechanically ventilated children post cardiac surgery, however there is substantial variability in sedation practices in different intensive care units and in different countries around the world. The Cardiac BabySPICE pilot study will evaluate the hypothesis that early light sedation with dexmedetomidine reduces length of mechanical ventilation and length of stay in PICU compared to standard practice (midazolam). In addition we will follow up the neurodevelopment (at 6 and 12 months) of the included subjects; infants undergoing cardiac surgery on bypass &lt;6 months of age. The purpose of the Cardiac BabySPICE Pilot RCT is to obtain preliminary data on the feasibility and safety of conducting a study that tests this hypothesis. 

This is a pilot prospective randomised controlled trial that will be conducted in the Lady Cilento Children's Hospital paediatric intensive care unit in Australia and will recruit 60 patients. The study will recruit patients undergoing repair of congenital heart disease who require a breathing tube at least 24 hours after enrolment AND need immediate and ongoing sedation. Patients will be recruited into one of 2 study groups. The study drug will commence whilst the child is in surgery. The intervention arm will receive dexmedetomidine as the primary agent, with the addition of secondline sedatives as required by infusion, boluses or both. The use of benzodiazepines in this arm will be minimized and clonidine will not be used concurrently with dexmedetomidine. The control arm will have midazolam according to usual practice.In both groups, the default sedation level in PICU is light sedation, as defined by a target State Behaviour Scale (SBS) of 1 to +1, unless otherwise specified by the treating clinician. The primary outcome measure for the pilot study is to demonstrate separation between the intervention group (Dex) and the control group (Mid) with respect to the proportion of patients achieving light sedation (SBS 1 to +1) in the first 48 hours of sedation in intensive care.WE will also examine length of veniltation, PICU length of stay and long term outcomes. Information from the Pilot RCT will be used to design a subsequent phase III trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Queensland Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Childrens Health Queensland  Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRCH/119</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Debbie Long</name>
      <address>PCCRG
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101
</address>
      <phone>+61(0)730681474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>debbie.long2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Debbie Long</name>
      <address>PCCRG
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101</address>
      <phone>+61(0)730681474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>debbie.long2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Debbie Long</name>
      <address>PCCRG
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101</address>
      <phone>+61(0)730681474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>debbie.long2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Debbie Long</name>
      <address>PCCRG
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101</address>
      <phone>+61(0)730681474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>debbie.long2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>