<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369652">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001365550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility study looking at the effects of Gut microbiota on adult immune response to the seasonal influenza vaccine</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility study assessing the association between gut microbiota in healthy adults and antibody response to seasonal influenza vaccination</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1174-2870</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>MRINZ/16/01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Immune response to trivalent influenza vaccine</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be vaccinated with a Medsafe approved trivalent influenza vaccine. Participants will be given one dose of the vaccine by intramuscular or deep subcutaneous injection by trained study investigators. The mode of administration will be determined at the discretion of the trained study investigators.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number needed to participate in the proposed RCT to see a 10% increase in responsiveness to the Medsafe approved annual influenza vaccine in the treated group versus the control group with 90% power and an alpha of 5%. This outcome will be assessed using regression analysis of the immune response rates (which will be analysed using Hemagglutination assays and ELISA testing) and compared to stool community type along with the withdrawal rate calculated at 28 days after Day Zero.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who fail to complete the feasibility study to Day 28. This is defined by failure to attend the Day 28 visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who fail to complete the feasibility study in its entirety.
This is defined by failure to attend the Week 26 visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who can be mapped to any of the four pre-specified Stool Community Type at Day Zero. Stool Community type will be determined by 16s rRNA analysis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who map to Stool Community Types A, B, C and D respectively at Day Zero using 16s rRNA analysis of stool sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who can be mapped to any of the four pre-specified Stool Community Type at Day 28. Stool Community type will be determined by 16s rRNA analysis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who map to Stool Community Types A, B, C and D respectively at Day 28 using 16s rRNA analysis of stool sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who have the same Stool Community Type at Day 28 versus Day Zero using 16s rRNA analysis of stool sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identification of proposed supplemental intervention. assessed using observed trends in macro-molecule diet data obtained from the 7-day food diaries, and by assesssment of Day Zero, 3, 7 and 28 blood tests.. </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who take systemic antibiotics within 28 days before Day Zero. Assessed using data obtained from the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who take systemic antibiotics between Day Zero and the 26 week visit Assessed using data obtained from participant self reporting between Day Zero and Week 26.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks after Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who take systemic corticosteroids within 28 days before Day Zero. Assessed using data obtained from the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who take systemic corticosteroids between Day Zero and the 26 week visit. Assessed using data obtained from participant self reporting between Day Zero and Week 26.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks after Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who ingest alcohol (in any quantity  as documented in the 7-day food diary) in the 24 hour period prior to supplying faecal samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who have had an influenza vaccine in the previous 2 years. Assessed using data obtained from the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who are pregnant at Day Zero, or become pregnant during the study. Assessed using data obtained the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study and self reporting by participants between Day Zero and week 26.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who complete a minimum of 5 days of the first 7-day diary AND whose reported intake for each day is greater than 1.2 x Basal Metabolic Rate (BMR), using predicted BMR based on sex, age, height and weight. Assessed by the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study and the 7-day food diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who complete a minimum of 5 days of the second 7-day diary AND whose reported intake for each day is greater than 1.2 x Basal Metabolic Rate (BMR), using predicted BMR based on sex, age, height and weight. Assessed by the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study and the 7-day food diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who complete all of the first 3 days of the first 7-day diary AND whose reported intake for each day is greater than 1.2 x Basal Metabolic Rate (BMR), using predicted BMR based on sex, age, height and weight. Assessed by the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study and the 7-day food diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who complete all of the first 3 days of the second 7-day diary AND whose reported intake for each day is greater than 1.2 x Basal Metabolic Rate (BMR), using predicted BMR based on sex, age, height and weight. Assessed by the lifestyle questionnaire created specifically for this study and the 7-day food diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who complete a minimum of 90% of the questions in the Lifestyle Questionnaire created specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who provide a faecal sample at Day Zero.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of Day Zero faecal samples that are adequately dated and time stamped by participants (i.e. can be related back to the food diary).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of participants (95% CI) who provide a faecal sample at Day 28.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of Day 28 faecal samples that are adequately dated and time stamped by participants (i.e. can be related back to the food diary).</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of blood samples obtained versus plan, and proportion (95% CI) of analysable samples at Day Zero.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of blood samples obtained versus plan, and proportion (95% CI) of analysable samples at Day Three.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of blood samples obtained versus plan, and proportion (95% CI) of analysable samples at Day Seven.</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of blood samples obtained versus plan, and proportion (95% CI) of analysable samples at Day 28.</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of blood samples obtained versus plan, and proportion (95% CI) of analysable samples at 26 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who seroconvert (pre-vaccination antiviral antibody titre less than 1:10 and a post-vaccination antiviral antibody titre equal to 1:40, OR pre-vaccination antiviral antibody titre  equal to 1:10 AND a minimum four-fold increase on post-vaccination antiviral antibody titre) to ALL arms of the influenza vaccine at Day 28 . Assessed by Hemagglutination assay and ELISA. </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants that seroconvert (pre-vaccination antiviral antibody titre less than 1:10 and a post-vaccination antiviral antibody titre equal to 1:40, OR pre-vaccination antiviral antibody titre  equal to 1:10 AND a minimum four-fold increase on post-vaccination antiviral antibody titre) to EACH arm of the influenza vaccine at Day 28. Assessed by Hemagglutination assay and ELISA. </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who undergo a 2.5-fold increase in Geometric Mean Titre to ALL arms of the influenza vaccine at Day 28. Assessed by Hemagglutination assay and ELISA. </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 Days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who undergo a 2.5-fold increase in Geometric Mean Titre to EACH arm of the influenza vaccine at Day 28. Assessed by Hemagglutination assay and ELISA.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who achieve seroprotection (antiviral antibody titre greater than 1:10)  to ALL arms of the influenza vaccine at Day 28. Assessed by Hemagglutination assay and ELISA.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion (95% CI) of participants who achieve seroprotection (antiviral antibody titre greater than 1:10)  to EACH arm of the influenza vaccine at Day 28. Assessed by Hemagglutination assay and ELISA.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after Day Zero.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the trial.
Male or Female, aged 18-64 years
In the investigators' opinion, is able and willing to comply with all trial requirements
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>They have had a known severe reaction or allergy to any components of the influenza vaccine.
They have any contra-indications to vaccination per recommendations of vaccine manufacturer.
They have a history of Guillain-Barre Syndrome within 6 weeks of receiving a previous influenza vaccine.
They have an impaired immune system that may confound immune response testing; i.e. any condition that impairs participant immune response through either the condition itself or through the treatment of the condition.
They have already received the 2016 seasonal influenza vaccine.
They have any other clinical condition which the investigator deems relevant for exclusion from the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is an open label trial, there is no allocation concealment</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The following table shows the sample size required in the main study to test for the difference between responsiveness to the influenza vaccine between the treated and the untreated group, exclusive of drop-out rates: (Please refer to appendix 1 in the attachments section for these figures)

The sample size will then be adjusted to account for the drop-out rate calculated at Day 28.
For this feasibility study the distribution of the rise of titre of antiviral antibodies against influenza vaccine is not well reported in the literature although we anticipate that it might be logarithm normal distributed. We will explore the distribution of this outcome variable in the feasibility study by ANOVA (a general linear model) of titre against community stool type with residual analysis with an appropriate transformation. If the distributional assumptions are best met on the logarithm normal scale then the difference in titres will be reported as ratio of geometric means. 
We will also estimate the proportions of participants with different stool types who have a four-fold titre rise as this is the accepted way of reporting whether seroconversion as has occurred.
For the sample size for the feasibility study having 15 to 20 participants with each stool type should be appropriate to have reasonable precision in the regression estimates.
A sample size of 100 in the Feasibility study gives a margin of error for a proportion of +/- 10%, thus a seroconversion rate in the Feasibility study of 50% will be estimated at 40 to 60%. 

Since this study is quite intense in the first week and takes place over a long period we are expecting a withdrawal rate of around 20%. Even though we only need 100 participants for the statistical analysis plan, we will be recruiting 125 participants in order to take into account potential withdrawals. Recruiting 125 participants should leave us with at least 100 participants finishing the study in its entirety ( attendance of week 26 visit). 

SAS 9.3 will be used.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>125</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>125</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Malaghan Institute of Medical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Malaghan Institute of Medical Research
PO Box 7060
Newtown
Wellington 6242
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Malaghan Institute of Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Malaghan Institute of Medical Research
PO Box 7060
Newtown
Wellington 6242
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a feasibility study that is looking at the effect of gut bacteria on immune response. Participants will be categorised into one of 4 "stool community types" based on their gut bacteria populations. 
Participants will be given a Medsafe approved influenza vaccine which is being used as a proxy for a respiratory tract infection. During the study participants will need to attend 6 visits spread out over 6 months. Participants will attend an information seminar which will explain the study and answer any questions. They will then attend Visit 1. During this visit they will be given a stool sample collection kit, a lifestyle questionnaire and a 7-day food diary. These must be completed and returned to the study investigators for Visit 2. The lifestyle questionnaire can be done online instead of on paper. 
Visit 2 will occur 7-14 days after Visit 1. Visit 2 will consist of a blood test, a temperature and general health check and vaccination with the influenza vaccine. 
Visit 3 will occur 3 days after vaccination. Visit 3 will just consist of a blood test. 
Visit 4 will occur 7 days after vaccination and will be the same format as Visit 3. At the end of Visit 4 participants will be given another stool sample collection kit and another 7-day food diary. These need to be completed and returned during Visit 5. 
Visit 5 will occur 28 days after vaccination. Visit 5 will be the same as Visit 3 and 4 with the added step of collecting the stool sample and food diary. 
The final visit (Visit 6) will occur 6 months after vaccination and will just consist of a blood test. Participants will also have the option to sign an optional consent form for future unspecified research, 
If they choose to sign this form the samples that remain after testing will be stored for future research at the Malaghan Institute of Medical research.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369652(v07-12-2015-08-46-34)-Malaghan Study Protocol V1.3 TC accept.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369652-Appendix 1.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242
New Zealand

Level 7, CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford St, Newtown
Wellington 6021
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0245</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nick Shortt</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242
New Zealand

Level 7, CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford St, Newtown
Wellington 6021
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0236</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.shortt@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nick Shortt</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242
New Zealand

Level 7, CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford St, Newtown
Wellington 6021
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0236</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.shortt@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nick Shortt</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242
Level 7, CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford St, Newtown
Wellington 6021
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0236</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.shortt@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>