<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366555">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000727640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Haemodynamic effects of Milrinone in patients with heart failure and preserved ejection fraction (HFPEF)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Haemodynamic effects of Milrinone in patients with heart failure and preserved ejection fraction (HFPEF)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following initial rest and exercise evaluation during Right Heart Catheterization (RHC), patients will be randomly allocated (by envelope) to receive either a standard loading dose of Intravenous (IV) milrinone (50mcg/kg over 10 mins) or placebo. This will be a single dose.
Rest and exercise haemodynamic and echocardiographic studies (as above) will be repeated after a further 10 minutes following the administration of the IV Milrinone.

Following baseline measures, subjects will supine perform symptom-limited supine cycling at incremental levels of 0.3, 0.6, 1.0 and 1.5Watt/kg each for 3 minutes (exercise will not be performed if the resting RHC unexpectedly demonstrates severe pulmonary hypertension PA systolic&gt;60mmHg). The test will be stopped when the patient experiences limiting dyspnoea or other limiting symptoms.</interventions>
    <comparator>Randomized study with normal Saline as the placebo.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Invasively measure haemodynamics (right heart catheterization and arterial line) at rest and during exercise in patients with presumed HFPEF and to repeat these measures after random allocation to milrinone or placebo.  Arterial and mixed venous blood gas samples will be taken at rest and peak exercise
The primary end-point will be the change in pulmonary capillary wedge pressure during exercise.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arterial and mixed venous blood gas samples will be taken at rest and peak exercise during Right Heart Catheterization (RHC), 10 minutes following the administration of IV Milrinone.

This will also be assessed following the administration of placebo
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary end-points will include:  pulmonary artery pressures taken via RHC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pulmonary Artery Pressures will be taken 10 minutes post administration of IV Milrinone at rest and during exercise.
This outcome will also be assessed following the administration of placebo</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults greater than or equal to 18 years of age, AND
Symptoms of HF (NYHA II-III) AND
Normal ejection fraction (LVEF equal to and more than 45%) with evidence of diastolic dysfunction as prescribed by ESC Working Group 15 (resting PCWP more than 12; E/e more than 15 or Eand e prime more than 8 and 
and NT-BNP more than 220)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Other cause for dyspnoea including moderate or severe valvular HD and pulmonary hypertension with PVR more than 4 Wood Units
Body mass index (BMI)  more than 35 kg/m2
History of stress-induced syncope or ventricular tachycardia during exercise
Unstable coronary artery disease
Symptoms and signs of congestive heart failure at rest (NYHA IV)
Unable to perform exercise test
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Calculations and statistics will be performed using SPSS v19.  Variables that approximated a normal distribution will be summarised as mean plus and minus standard deviation, and groups compared using T-Tests or RM-ANOVA as appropriate. Non-normal variables will be summarised as median and first and third quartiles (Q1, Q3), and groups compared using Mann-Whitney Rank sum tests with exact inference. 
 
In recent studies in HFPEF patients show that during low level exercise the PCWP rises from 14 plus or minus 6 to 32 plus or minus 6mmHg. We hypothesize that milrinone will reduce the exercise PCWP by 30%. In order to test this hypothesis with power=0.8 and significance level of p&lt;0.05 we will require n=7 per group. To account for study drop-out (in particular due to the identification of unexpected severe PHTn) we aim to recruit a total of 20 patients.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>14</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Alfred Health
Commercial Road 
Melbourne
3004
Victoria
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alfred Health
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Alfred Health
Commercial Road 
Melbourne
3004
Victoria
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Invasively measure haemodynamics (right heart catheterization and arterial line) at rest and during exercise (Ex 1) in patients with presumed HFPEF and to repeat these measures after random allocation to milrinone or placebo</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics and research committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Health
Commercial Road 
Melbourne
3004
Victoria
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>248/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Kaye</name>
      <address>Alfred Health
Commerical Road 
Melbourne
3004
Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61,3,90763263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.kaye@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fiona Tweedley</name>
      <address>Alfred Health
Commerical Road 
Melbourne
3004
Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61,3,90762978</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.tweedley@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Kaye</name>
      <address>Alfred Health
Commerical Road 
Melbourne
3004
Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61,3,90763263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.kaye@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fiona Tweedley</name>
      <address>Alfred Health
Commerical Road 
Melbourne
3004
Victoria
</address>
      <phone>+61,3,90762978</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.tweedley@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>