<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82034">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000290493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of a high intensity functional exercise program on physical performance in older adults at discharge from in-patient rehabilitation  A feasibility study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a high intensity functional exercise program on physical performance in older adults at discharge from in-patient rehabilitation  A feasibility study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>mobility in older adults</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly allocated to the intervention or control group. Participants in the control group will receciver usual in-patient rehabilitation therapy.  The intervention group will receive usual in-patient rehabilitation physiotherapy plus participate in the HIFE exercise (progressive resistane and balance exercise) program 3x/wk for 45 minutes. The intervention period will run from the time of recruitment, until they are discharged from the inpatient rehabilition service. Please note that 'usual rehabilitation' involves daily physiotherapy treatment and exercises up to one hour per day performining activites to restore mobility and function post injury or trauma. The high intensity functional exercise (HIFE) program is a standardised program of lower-limb strength and balance exercises performed in functional weight bearing positions (sit to stand, step ups, lunges etc). The program is stratified into five categories from A (high level strength/balance) to E (unable to stand unsupported) . High intensity is achieved by performing strengthening exercises at a 10-12 repetition maximum, and balance exercises perform at the limits of postural stability individually prescribed to match a participants functional level.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group - 20 subjects: usual inpatient rehabilitation only up to 60mins 5 days per week (weekdays).  Participants in the control group will not be participating in the HIFE exercise program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Performance Test score</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitaion program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed up and go test time</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>10 m walk time and stride length</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grip strength on hand held dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 minute walk test time</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reach distance</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls efficacy scale score</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>On admission and discharge from inpatient rehabilitation program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be an inpatient in a sub-acute rehabilitation ward. Participants will be aged 65 years or over, be medically stable, have current rehabilitation goals documented in their history and will be able to give informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded from this study if they have significant cardiac or respiratory disease or any other medical illness that interferes with their ability to take part in a rehabilitation program, or requires palliative care.  Patients that are non-weight bearing through their lower-limbs, or who have post-operative orders that contraindicate participation in the exercises included in the intervention program will also be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients being admitted to 2 sub-acute rehabilitation wards will be screened for eligibility for this project by the ward physiotherapists, based on the inclusion/exclusion criteria.  If a patient is interested, the ward physiotherapist will refer the patient to the lead investigator.  At this time the lead investigator will formally assess the eligibility of the potential participant by checking if they meet the eligibility criteria and do not demonstrate any of the items listed as exclusion criteria. If the participant is eligible, they will be taken through the consent process by the study therapist. Once the participant has given informed consent, the participant will be randomised into the control or intervention group.  The following procedure will be used:
1)Prior to the commencement of recruiting, and independent therapist not located on any wards associated with the study will generate a computerized random number sequence and hold this in secret.
2)The researchers will contact this therapist to say they have a participant recruited.
3)The pre-arranged independent therapist will then look at the randomized number sequence to inform the researchers if the next number on the table is an odd number or even number. 
4)Subjects who are allocated an odd number will be placed in the control group; those allocated an even number will be placed in the intervention group.  
5)This process will be repeated for each participant recruited.</concealment>
    <sequence>A random number sequence will be generate on a computer using the Excel program to generate a random number sequence</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The physiotherapist assessing participant outcome measures pre- and post-intervention trial will be blinded to group allocation</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/12/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd 
Clayton Vic 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd 
Clayton Vic 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to look at how feasible it is to (1) conduct a functional exercise program in addition to a usual rehabilitation program, and (2) to explore how effective an outcome measure (Physical Performance Test) is at measuring the physical function of people being admitted and discharged from an in-patient rehabilitation program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd 
Clayton Vic 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07086B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Melanie Farlie, Physiotherapist</name>
      <address>Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
Cheltenham VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92651000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92651574</fax>
      <email>melanie.farlie@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Melanie Farlie, Physiotherapist</name>
      <address>Kingston Centre
Warrigal Rd
Cheltenham VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92651000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92651574</fax>
      <email>melanie.farlie@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Melanie Farlie</name>
      <address>Kingston Centre Warrigal Rd Cheltenham VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92651000 pager 8364</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92651574</fax>
      <email>melanie.farlie@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>