<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364330">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001241729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of an interdisciplinary, student clinic on the functioning, disability, health and economic outcomes of people with chronic disease in regional Australia.   </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of an interdisciplinary, student clinic on the functioning, disability, health and economic outcomes of people with chronic disease in regional Australia compared to an oral health student clinic for people with chronic disease.   </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>People with chronic disease (e.g., diabetes, arthritis, heart disease, COPD, asthma, low back pain)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Assessment and treatment at a student-led interdisciplinary clinic program including medication management, interdisciplinary care, case management, functional ability assessment and treatment for chronic disease in addition to usual medical magagement and hospital intervention (if applicable).

A diverse range of individualised, interdisciplinary education and exercise therapy programs such as Back School, a Healthy Lifestyle program, and pain management programs; and individualised discipline specific consultations are provided. Sessions vary from 10-15 minutes in length to several hours depending on the clients requirements. The duration of intervention is less than 12-months but varies from one patient to another. </interventions>
    <comparator>Assessment and treatment at a student-led oral health clinic in addition to usual medical management and hospital intervention (if applicable).


A range of interventions are provided by oral health students under the supervision of a qualified oral health therapist including hygiene instruction, preventative treatment (e.g., fissure sealing), and treating demineralised areas, mild to moderate periodontitis, and gingivitis. Each appointment is for up to 90 minutes with each course of care usually involving up to 4 appointments.  Patients may be recalled on a 3, 6 or 12 month basis depending on the needs of the patient.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health measured using the SF-36  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-months, and 6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital utilisation including number of days of hospitalisation and length of hospitalisation measured using a review of patient health records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-months, and 6-months post-baseline </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health care costs including PBS and Medicare data</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-months, and 6-months post-baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health literacy as measured using the Health Literacy Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3-months, and 6-months post-baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Presence of two or more chronic diseases; 
Patients aged 18 years or older;
Patients referred to the interdisciplinary student clinic (intervention group only);   
Patients referred to the oral health student clinic (control group only)  
Attendance at a minimum of four sessions of intervention at the interdisciplinary student clinic within 6-months of the intake interview (intervention group only); 
Attendance at a minimum of one or more sessions of intervention at the student-led oral health clinic within 6-months of their initial appointment (control group only); and,
Provision of informed consent to participate.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Clients younger than 18 years;
Severe communication disability or behavioural changes that would compromise the ability to participate in the intervention program or complete the questionnaires;  
A cognitive deficit that impairs the ability to read or write or be interviewed.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>intention-to-treat analysis
matching of subjects in the intervention and control group</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics will be used to describe the outcome variables and covariates.  Confidence intervals will also be presented for outcome variables and predictors.  

Regression models for repeated measures will be used to examine the effect of time, group and predictor variables (including intervention variables) on the outcome variables.  The importance of the observed change in outcome measures will be determined by comparing the minimal detectable change to the minimally clinical important difference.  Individual growth curves will also be used to examine changes in the outcome measures. 

 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>260</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4701 - Central Queensland University</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Queensland Hospital and Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2-8 Canning St, Rockhampton, QLD 4700.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Central Queensland Hospital and Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, Allied Health Services, Canning St, Rockhampton, QLD 4700</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Metro South Hospital and Health Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 4043, Eight Mile Plains QLD 4113 Australia
 

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Metro North Hospital and Health Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress> PO Box 150 RBWH Post Office, Herston QLD 4029 Australia
 

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Catholic University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo, QLD 4014</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to investigate the effectiveness of an interdisciplinary student clinic program for people with chronic disease compared to people who receive an oral health student-led clinic intervention.  It is expected that people who receive the interdisciplinary clinic program will have better health and functioning, less disability, fewer hospitalisations, shorter lengths of stay, less ambulance usage and lower health costs than people who attend the oral health program; when people in the groups are matched using similar characteristics such as age, gender and number of comorbidities.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health Service District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research
Level 2 Building 35, Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba  Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QPAH/497</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zephanie tyack</name>
      <address>Level 3, School of Allied and Public Health, Australian Catholic University, 1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo, QLD 4014.</address>
      <phone>+61 427462286</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zephanie.tyack@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zephanie Tyack</name>
      <address>Level 3, School of Allied and Public Health, Australian Catholic University, 1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo, QLD 4014.</address>
      <phone>+61 427462286</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zephanie.tyack@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zephanie Tyack</name>
      <address>Level 3, School of Allied and Public Health, Australian Catholic University, 1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo, QLD 4014.</address>
      <phone>+61 427462286</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zephanie.tyack@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zephanie Tyack</name>
      <address>Level 3, School of Allied and Public Health, Australian Catholic University, 1100 Nudgee Road, Banyo, QLD 4014.</address>
      <phone>+61 427462286</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>zephanie.tyack@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>