<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336531">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000777998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Results of serial assessment of eye movement recovery in patients with acute vertigo (labyrinthitis)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Serial assessment of the hypoactive Vestibular ocular reflex in patients with  acute labyrinthine dysfunction</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>The Universal Trial Number (UTN) is U1111-1119-4479</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute labyrinthitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Measurement of the hypoactive vestibular ocular reflex (VOR) by videooculography

Patients with clinical features of acute labyrinthitis will be seen in casualty within 24hrs of their symptom onset of acute vertigo.  The head impulse test measures the eye movement response of a hypoactive VOR  to a high acceleration head impulse when the examiner moves the subjects head with brief random head thrusts in the angular plane. It is hoped that approximately 12 random head impulse tests will be able to be assessed to the  ipsilateral and contralateral side, depending on patient compliance and acceptability. The abnormal VOR will be monitored serially with videooculography with repeat testing in a 20 minute session to assess recovery on six occasions over a period of up to 3 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Normal controls

A normal historical  control group (including age matched subjects from 20 to 80 years) without vestibular symptoms will be used as a baseline to establish both a normal quantitative  value of the VOR gain (peak eye velocity/peak head velcoity)during the head impulse test as well as assessing what proportion of such subjects use catchup saccades. Such subjects will be seen on one occasion only in a 20 minute session. Five subjects for each decade will be recorded. Again approximately 12 random head impulse tests will be  assessed to the  ipsilateral and contralateral side, depending on patient compliance and acceptability.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the hypoactive  VOR with serial video oculography.

This will be assessed on the basis of measurement of the gain of eye velocity/head velocity at 40 and 80 ms after the onset of head rotation. Interruption of the VOR  by catch up saccades will also be noted when these occur during the head impulse test (covert saccades) as well as those occurring after the  head impulse test has been completed (overt saccades). The primary  aspect of the serial study will be to observe how quickly patients utilise the two different forms of catchup  saccades to improve their function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 24hrs of presentation of the labyrinthitis and serially at 48-72 hours, 7 days, 14 days and 90 days. .</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Affected patients may have an easily elictable abnormality of the head impulse acutely that may not be readily detected when the same test is performed two weeks later . This may reflect an acute partial lesion with recovery or  a complete lesion with recovery over time or the presence of covert saccades which give the appearance of a false negative result with the head impulse test. Serial assessment of the recovery of the head impulse test over time will distinguish these different possibilities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serial studies will be done at the time of presentation (within 24 hours), 48-72 hours, 7 days, 14 days and 90 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Usefulness of education to casualty staff in the accuracy of diagnosis of acute labyrinitis. This will be assessed on the basis of the the referring physician committing on the electronic  clinical record to their diagnosis and management - with and without specialist  neurological input.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On completion of the study with the expected accrual of 12 patients</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation of  the oculomotor abnormalities of the VOR noted on  the head impulse test with measurements of clinical recovery as assessed by tests of perceptual function and a dizziness behavioural inventory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serial studies will be done at the time of presentation (within 24 hours), 48-72 hours, 7 days, 14 days and 90 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The  sensitivity of the head impulse test performed at 72hours  to a caloric test measured in the standard manner.</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours when acute dizziness has settled.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with the clinical picture of acute labyrinthitis</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are too ill to be examined by video oculography</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 0</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Capital and Coast health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 7902
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6242</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Capital and Coast health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 7902
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6242</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Nick Cutfield</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dept Neurology Dunedin Hospital Dunedin 9054</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study is to observe the  compensatory strategies that the brain uses to recover from acute labyrinthitis.

It is proposed that in patients with a partial labyrinthitis there may be a complete and early recovery of their eye movements generated by the inner ear. That is, the normal eye velocity generated by balance receptors in the inner ear should match the head  velocity signal in a short period of time of seven days. Secondly it is proposed that the compensatory brain mechanisms used following acute labyrinthitis with rapid catch up eye movements (covert saccades) will occur within the first 24-48 hours of presentation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>MOSSMAN S. HALMAGYI GM. 
Partial ocular tilt reaction due to unilateral cerebellar lesion. 
Neurology. 49(2):491-3, 1997 Aug. 

WESTWATER H. MCDOWALL J. SIEGERT R. MOSSMAN S. ABERNETHY D. Implicit learning in Parkinson's disease: evidence from a verbal version of the serial reaction time task. [Clinical Trial. Journal Article] Journal of Clinical &amp; Experimental Neuropsychology: Official Journal of the International Neuropsychological Society. 20(3):413-8, 1998 Jun.

ROSEMERGY I, MOSSMAN S Brainstem lesions presenting with nausea and vomiting  New Zealand Medical Journal Vol 120 No 1254;1-4 May 2007

Presentations

MOSSMAN S, LAWN N, LAI M, BHARA A, LAWSON C,  CORBETT M A randomised controlled trial of a canal repositioning procedure in the treatment of BPPV World Congress of Neurology London 2001 (Poster P0654)  J of the Neurological Sciences vol 187 S1, June 15 2001

MOSSMAN S, FITZJOHN T Asymptomatic cerebellar infarcts World Congress of Neurology London 2001 (Poster P0663)  J of the Neurological Sciences vol 187 S1, June 15 2001

ANDERSON T, MacASKILL M, MOSSMAN S, BRONSTEIN A Saccadic downpulsion and cerebellar disease   Paper presented at the Xth European Conference on Eye Movements, Utrecht, Holland

MOSSMAN S MEURS L Hypoactive VOR gain with infrared oculography  P4-11Barany Society Kyoto Japan 2008

MOSSMAN S  Covert short latency saccades in combined vestibular and cerebellar failure
Barany Soc Meeting J Vestibular Research  PC-90 Vol 20, numbers 3,4 2010

SCHMULEWICZ D et al.,  Neuropathy is an intergral component of the cerebellar ataxia neuropathy vestibular areflexia syndrome (CANVAS)  C3-6 J Vestibular Research  Vol 20, numbers 3,4 2010</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Multi-region Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Ethics Red MEC/11/05/051

Or 336531   ANZTR no</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO BOx 5013 Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stuart Mossman</name>
      <address>Capital Coast health
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902
Newtown
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6443855999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stuart.mossman@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stuart Mossman</name>
      <address>Capital Coast health
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902
Newtown
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6443855999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stuart.mossman@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stuart Mossman</name>
      <address>Capital Coast health
Wellington Hospital
Private Bag 7902
Newtown
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+6443855999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stuart.mossman@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>