<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364909">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001120763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Application of the Strengths Model of Case Management in Hong Kong Mental Health Services</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A controlled before-and-after study on the effectiveness and impact of the Strengths Model of Case Management on people with severe psychiatric illnesses and their caseworkers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SMCM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>severe psychiatric disabilities</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Strengths Model of Case Management (SMCM) is the intervention used in the current trial.  The SMCM consists of three primary tools that are used during session between the case manager and the client.  The Strengths Assessment appraises the current personal and environmental assets (strengths) of the client. The Personal Medicine Worksheet are first-person accounts of activities that give rise to purpose and meaning to the client's life; they are also believed to be activities that could counteract the symptoms that a client has.  The Personal Recovery Plan, on the other hand, utilizes information from the aforementioned two assessment tools to derive a recovery plan that is meaningful for the client, and its implementation.

The intervention will consist of weekly session, each lasting for 45 to 60 minutes.  This intervention model is to be run for the entire course of 6 months.  A typical session consists of natural conversations between the client and the case manager.  During the conversation, the case manager has a responsibility to gauge, as well as elicit contents with an underlying goal to review and revise the Strengths Assessment.

Sometimes, the caseworker will also have a conversation with the clients with an aim to create an agenda for recovery.  This involves identifying elements that are meaningful for the clients in their own recovery, and assisting them to achieve the recovery goal by breaking the goal down to small, achievable steps, and monitor the progress periodically.

In addition to the actual sessions, the intervention is also characterized by adoptions of new practices in the settings, such as weekly group supervision sessions amongst teams of case workers, a lower client-to-worker ratio, and field mentoring.  Adherence to these standards (i.e. safeguarding of fidelity) will be monitored through the Fidelity checklist developed by the University of Kansas.  Fidelity check will be conducted at the three settings prior to commencement of the trial.  The pre-requisite scores are: an average of 4 for the structural items; an average of 4 for the supervision/supervisors items; and an average score of 3.5 for the clinical/service items is set.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control participants will receive standard care provided for them in thier respective agencies.  We do not dictate the control treatment, as it differ by settings.  General content of standard care including regular sessions with the client, medical appointments, community activities.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery of clients, measured using the Maryland Assessment of Recovery in People with Serious Mental Illness (MARS; Drapalski et al., 2012).</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective wellbeing, or satisfaction with life, is measured using the Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS; Diener, Emmons, Larsen &amp; Griffin, 1985).</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychiatric symptoms are measured with Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (Overall &amp; Gorham, 1962).</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapeutic alliance: The Working Alliance Inventory (WAI; (Horvath &amp; Greenberg, 1989)) is used to measure three components of therapeutic alliance: the bond between the therapist and the client, the agreement on goals and the agreement on tasks.  The client form will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The perceived degree to which intervention and the setting is recovery oriented is measured using the Recovery Self Assessment (RSA, OConnell et al., 2007).  The person-in-recovery form wll be used.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other outcomes such as educational / vocational outcomes, occurrence of hospitalization will be drawn from individual case records, documented periodically by the case managers.  These will be measured using a questionnaire designed for this purpose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3, and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Job burnout will be measured using the The Maslach Burnout Inventory (Maslach &amp; Jackson, 1986), the most widely used measure of burnout and has previously been used in mental health services research (Prosser et al., 1999).</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Utrecht Work Engagement Scale (UWES) (Schaufeli, Bakker, &amp; Salanova, 2006) will be used to measure work engagement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapeutic alliance: The Working Alliance Inventory (WAI; (Horvath &amp; Greenberg, 1989)) is used to measure three components of therapeutic alliance: the bond between the therapist and the client, the agreement on goals and the agreement on tasks.  The therapist form will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The perceived degree to which intervention and the setting is recovery oriented is measured using the Recovery Self Assessment (RSA, OConnell et al., 2007).  The service provider form will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be taken at baseline, month 3 and month 6 (endpoint).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. At least 18 years of age
2. Consent to participation
3. Is able to read, and comprehend Chinese
4. Is currently a user of mental health services from one of the three participating NGOs</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Clients who are currently experience a crisis, have serious physical or mental impairments thus have difficulty participating in the research in any way, as determined by their case managers.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size:
Assuming a small effect size (0.25) with a power of 0.8, using a 2X2 ANOVA design with one between subject factor (control vs. intervention) and one within-subject factor (pre vs. post), the minimum required sample size is 50.

Data analysis:
The objective of the data analysis is to investigate the changes, if any, between the two groups over time.  Generalized linear mixed model will be used to model the correlations between repeated measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Hong Kong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Social Work and Social Administration, The University of Hong Kong, Pokfulam, Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Baptist Oi Kwan Social Services</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>6/F, 36 Oi Kwan Road, Wanchai, Hong Kong</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Caritas (Hong Kong) Social Work Services Division</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Caritas Hong Kong , King Hong Home, G/F, Caritas Jockey Club Lai King Rehabilitation Centre, 31 Lai Chi Ling Road, Kwai Chung, New Territories, Hong Kong </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Tung Wah Group of Hospitals, Social Residential Services</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>2 Wong Chuk Hang Path,
Wong Chuk Hang, Hong Kong</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Hong Kong</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This will be a 6 month experimental investigation on the impact and efficacy of the Strengths Model of Case Management (SMCM) in a psychiatric population.  We plan to assess the psychosocial outcomes of our target participants at baseline, 3 and 6 months.  We envision that the SMCM will be efficacious in improving the psychosocial well being of our participants, as well as beneficial to the caseworkers rendering care for them in terms of less burn out and a higher sense of work engagement.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee for Non-Clinical Faculties, University of Hong Kong</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee for Non-Clinical Faculties,
University of Hong Kong,
Pokfulam, 
Hong Kong</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tsoi Wing See Emily</name>
      <address>Dept. of Social Work and Social Administration,
The University of Hong Kong,
Pokfulam,
Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+85291588529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ewstsoi@connect.hku.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tsoi Wing See Emily</name>
      <address>Dept. of Social Work and Social Administration,
The University of Hong Kong,
Pokfulam,
Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+85291588529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ewstsoi@connect.hku.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samson Tse</name>
      <address>Dept. of Social Work and Social Administration,
The University of Hong Kong,
Pokfulam,
Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+85239171071</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samsont@hku.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tsoi Wing See Emily</name>
      <address>Dept. of Social Work and Social Administration,
The University of Hong Kong,
Pokfulam,
Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>+85291588529</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ewstsoi@connect.hku.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>