<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83316">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000128291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised double blind placebo controlled trial on the effect of intraperitoneal ropivacaine on postoperative pain and recovery after diagnostic laparoscopy and hysteroscopy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised double blind placebo controlled trial on the effect of intraperitoneal ropivacaine on postoperative pain and recovery after day case gynaecological diagnostic laparoscopy and hysteroscopy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post operative pain following day case gynaecological diagnostic laparoscopy and hysteroscopy.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Postoperative nausea and vomiting following day case gynaecological diagnostic laparoscopy and hysteroscopy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Postoperative recovery following day case gynaecological diagnostic laparoscopy and hysterocopy.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is using the local anaesthetic, ropivacaine, intraperitoneally, at the end of the diagnostic hysteroscopy and laparoscopy. The dose used is 20mls of 0.25% (100mg) of ropivacaine. It will take less than two minutes to administer. The intervention treatment will only be administered once.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control is 20mls of normal saline to be administered intraperitoneally at the end of the diagnostic hysteroscopy and laparoscopy. It will take less than two minutes to administer. The control treatment will only be administered once.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount of analgesia used postoperatively as indicated from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30min, 60min, 120min, 240min after return to the recovery room.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain score which will be assessed by asking the participant to rate their pain on a visual analogue score on a zero to ten scale line.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 min, 60min, 120min, 240min and 8 hours after return to the recovery room.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative recovery generally, measured by how quickly the patient achieves certain milestones - which are - time to first sit up, time to first eating, and time to discharge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time to first sit up, time to first eating and time to discharge. These will be measured every 5 minutes in the recovery room and then every 15 minutes once the patient has moved to the waiting room.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Two port diagnostic laparoscopy and hysteroscopy  for any gynaecological reason, age 18-50 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Age &lt;18 years or &gt;50 years, 
- non-English speaking 
- weight &lt;50kg 
- patient refusal 
- operative laparoscopy, laparoscopic sterilization
- pregnancy
- 3rd port required intraoperatively 
- use of regular narcotic analgesia for pain preoperatively
- contraindications or allergies to any drugs used in the study (including renal disease, diabetes, Non-Steroidal Anti Inflammatory Drug (NSAID) sensitive asthma)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by number system, using a randomisation table from a statistical book.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3977</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Natasha Frawley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC, 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC, 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Beverley Vollenhoven</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Head of Gynaecology Department, Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC, 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BRIEF SUMMARY:
Laparoscopy and hysteroscopy is a common day case gynaecological procedure. This operation involves keyhole surgery, inserting a small telescope-like device or fibreoptic lens into the abdomen via a 10mm port. This enables direct visualisation of inside the abdomen. There is also one other cut on the abdomen of 5mm, where a thin metal probe is inserted. Finally, a second fibreoptic device, is inserted inside the womb via the vagina and cervix, and the inside of the womb is visualised. A scraping of the womb tissue is taken and sent to the pathology laboratory to be analysed under a microscope. Patients usually go home the same day, unless there have been complications.

Pain relief for this procedure has not been studied in any recent large trials. Current pain management involves use of pain relief tablets after the operation, and intravenous analgesics during the operation, including ropivacaine, depending on the anaesthetist. 

We aim to evaluate the use of intraperitoneal Ropivacaine. This is a local anaesthetic medication that can be squirted inside the abdomen at the areas that have been manipulated including the womb and fallopian tubes and injected at port sites, which are the two small incisions on the abdomen. 

HYPOTHESIS:
We hypothesise that the use of ropivacaine at the end of the procedure will reduce post operative pain and hasten recovery after a diagnostic laparoscopy and hysteroscopy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Unit, Level 4 Main block, Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/12/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Natasha Frawley</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC, 3168 
Or:
Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Box Hill Hospital, Nelson Rd, Box Hill, VIC, 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natasha.frawley@trainee.ranzcog.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Natasha Frawley</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC, 3168 
Or:
Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Box Hill Hospital, Nelson Rd, Box Hill, VIC, 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natasha.frawley@trainee.ranzcog.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Natasha Frawley</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC, 3168 
Or:
Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Box Hill Hospital, Nelson Rd, Box Hill, VIC, 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9895 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natasha.frawley@trainee.ranzcog.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>