<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370338">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000903482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of sleep apnoea (OSA) therapy for the reduction of atrial fibrilliation (AF) burden and morbidity in adults with OSA and AF

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Obstructive Sleep apnoea Intervention in AF (OSI-AF) randomised trial: 
Obstructive sleep apnoea treatment to reduce atrial fibrillation burden and morbidity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OSI-AF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial Fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Obstructive sleep apnoea treatment (CPAP or Mandibular advancement splints (MAS) if unable to tolerate CPAP).
Participants allocated to OSA intervention group will have CPAP education and mask fitting session with an experienced sleep technician to fit the CPAP mask followed by an overnight pressure determination study (with measures of sleep and respiration whilst using CPAP) - this is a standard of care test.   In the morning the CPAP machine will be set to the pressure that was shown to abolish obstructive apnoeas and hypopneas as verified by the sleep physician. 
Participants will be given instructions on how to use a CPAP machine at home and will be encouraged to use their treatment every night for as long as they are able to tolerate its use during the 2 year treatment period..
Regular follow-up during the study at 3-monthly visits will check compliance with the CPAP.  If a participant experiences ongoing problems tolerating the CPAP they will be referred to a dentist who will assess whether they are suitable for treatment with MAS. This is a dental splint worn in the mouth every night during sleep to keep the airway open. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment for patients with Atrial Fibrillation as determined by the treating clinician</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total AF arrhythmia count (cumulative duration of all episodes greater than 30s) quantified using subcutaneous injectable loop recorders (Reveal Linq, Medtronic Inc.) in patients receiving OSA treatment (CPAP or MAS) compared to those receiving no OSA treatment.   </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous monitoring for 2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(ii) cardiovascular outcomes in patients receiving OSA treatment (CPAP or MAS) compared to those receiving no OSA treatment.   
Cardiovascular adverse outcomes will be compared in the two treatment groups.
Cardiovascular outcomes will include a composite of cardiac death, MI, stroke, TIA, ACS and any other events deemed as cardiovascular by masked adjudicators.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Details of cardiovascular outcomes will be collected from patients and medical records at 3 monthly follow-up visits during the 2 years of follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> (iii) health related quality of life in patients receiving OSA treatment (CPAP or MAS) compared to those receiving no OSA treatment.   
HRQOL will be reported by participants using the EuroQoL (EQ-5D 5L), Short Form 36 questionnaire (SF-36), and UBQ-H and the FOSQ (Functional Outcomes of Sleep Weaver 1996) questionnaires. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>HRQOL will be collected at baseline, 3-months and then 6 monthly during the 2 years of follow=up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(iv) Composite of AF related hospitalisations and healthcare utilisation in patients receiving OSA treatment (CPAP or MAS) compared to those receiving no OSA treatment (collected directly from patients or via medical records).   
- Hospitalization for AF symptoms (palpitations, dyspnea, chest discomfort, syncope, pre-syncope) or its complications (exacerbation of cardiac failure, acute coronary syndrome, acute cerebral episode), 
- scheduled or emergent external cardioversion, 
- emergent ambulatory consultation for AF symptoms or related complications, 
- anti-arrhythmic (AAM) drug prescription, hospitalization for AAM initiation,
- titration or monitoring, referral for catheter ablation for AF, 
- referral for catheter ablation of AV node and pacemaker implantation, 
- complications related to systemic anticoagulation therapy. 
AF related healthcare utilisation will be formulated and applied by adjudicators blinded to the patient treatment.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Details of AF related healthcare utilisation will be collected at 3 monthly follow-up visit during the 2 years of follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(v) Cost-effectiveness of OSA treatment, assessed using data linkage to hospital records for: 1) Number of hospital admissions related to AF; 2) Average hospital length of stay and home time a patient-centred outcome meaning institutional free time; 3) Quality-adjusted survival.
Total resource use and costs for the intervention and control group will be estimated. Total health outcomes for the intervention and control group will also be estimated.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years (end of study)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(vi) serum markers potentially predictive of atrial structural remodelling, pro-arrhythmia and inflammation in patients receiving OSA treatment (CPAP or MAS) compared to those receiving no OSA treatment.   
Details of markers to be analysed will be determined prior to database lock and analysis and ANZCTR updated

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Samples will be  collected at baseline, 3-months, 6-months and then annually  during the 2 years of follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Males and females with a history of paroxysmal (at least 2 prior attacks) or persistent AF (&lt;12 months duration [in sinus rhythm at study entry]);
2) Age 18-75;
3) Polysomnography diagnosed OSA of at least moderate severity (AHI &gt;=15); 
4) Ability to provide informed consent.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Severe OSA related hypoxemia (&gt;10% sleep time with oxygen saturation &lt;80%) and/or awake oxygen saturation less than 92%%
2) Severe respiratory disease (eg Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease or (COPD)
3) Current or prior mechanical treatment for OSA with CPAP or MAS 
4)  &gt;50% of apnoeas and/or hyponeas associated with Cheyne-Stokes Respiration (CSR) or Central Sleep Apnoea (CSA)
5) Increased risk of sleep-related accident and / or excessive sleepiness defined by any of:
     * Severe sleepiness as defined by Epworth Sleepiness Scale (&gt;15) 
     *	Driver occupation (eg taxi, courier or truck driver)
     *	Sleepiness-related motor vehicle accident, or near accident, within last 12 months prior to enrolment  
6) Any relative or absolute contra-indication to CPAP or MAS therapy including chronic cranial injury; recurrent pneumothorax; indication for oral-pharyngeal surgery, edentulous, or loose teeth 
7) Any severe other cardiac disease likely to impact ability to comply:

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by phone/fax/computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be by stratified minimisation at the NMHRC CTC according to source of referral, age, gender, AF type (paroxysmal or persistent &lt;12 months), and OSA severity.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A  sample size of 200 subjects will offer 95% power at 2P=0.05 to detect a 50% reduction in cumulative AF burden from 2000 hrs total over 2 years to 1000 hr s, SD 1500 hrs. This sample size allows for up to 40% non-compliance by 2 years with adequate OSA treatment (CPAP or MAS), and 10% drop-ins.
Outcome differences will be determined within groups and between groups on an intention-to-treat basis. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, Locked bag 77, Camperdown NSW 1450</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Not yet funded - grant application submitted</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Not yet funded - grant application submitted</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is estimated to affect at least 0.25 million adult Australians and is the commonest cardiac arrhythmia world-wide. It accounts for an estimated $1.8 billion in annual direct ($1.25B) and indirect ($0.55B) healthcare costs locally. Annual hospital admissions have risen exponentially over the last 15 years, with costs for AF arrhythmia episodes alone in 2008-9 amounting to $430 million. AF causes a substantial lifetime socio-economic burden, as it causes 7,500 ischaemic strokes in Australia each year. Because the risk of stroke is determined largely by the quantitative burden of arrhythmia, treatments to lower arrhythmia burden are critically important. Obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) is an independent risk factor for AF and more than triples the risk of stroke in AF, over and above other established risk predictors. Up to 80% of patients with AF have OSA. Current AF treatment strategies are ineffective in &gt;50% of cases overall, particularly among individuals with OSA. Observational studies suggest that treatment of OSA may reduce arrhythmia recurrence, but no large RCTs have directly addressed this question. Reducing the &gt;50% arrhythmia recurrence rate may only be possible when combined with structured OSA treatment.  This randomised clinical trial is assessing whether routine OSA treatment in addition to a weight management program reduces AF arrhythmia burden.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Ethics and Governance Office (REGO)
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Tony Keech</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown
NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rebecca Mister</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown
NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>osi-af@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Tony Keech</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown
NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tony@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rebecca Mister</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown
NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rmister@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>