<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335866">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000762055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Single Site, Randomized, Single-Blind, Parallel-group, Placebo-Controlled Study to investigate reduction of inflammation using Intravenous Sodium Ascorbate in patients with Cellulitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single Site, Randomized, Single-Blind, Parallel-group, Placebo-Controlled Study to investigate reduction of inflammation using Intravenous Sodium Ascorbate in patients with Cellulitis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-6339</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Cellulitis Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cellulitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intravenous Sodium Ascorbate supplied as 30g in 200mL bag which is administered at a rate of 100 mLs/hr daily for 5 days or until discharge whichever occurs first.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intravenous matching placebo supplied as 200mL bag half-normal saline which is administered at a rate of 100 mLs/hr daily for 5 days or until discharge whichever occurs first.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine if adding high-dose intravenous antioxidant therapy (sodium ascorbate) to standard therapy will reduce a patient?s inflammatory conditions using max C-reactive protein (CRP) as the surrogate marker. A blood sample will taken at baseline and then daily to obtain the Max CRP value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days' following admission to the hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine if adding high-dose intravenous antioxidant therapy (sodium ascorbate) to standard therapy will improve the Cellulitis Visual Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days' following admission to the hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objective is to determine if adding high-dose intravenous antioxidant therapy (sodium ascorbate) to standard therapy will reduce a patient's length of stay in hospital. This will be determined from the patient's hospital notes which document the time and date of admission to the hospital until the date and time of discharge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days' following admission to the hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objective is to determine if adding high-dose intravenous antioxidant therapy (sodium ascorbate) to standard therapy is safe and tolerable. This will be assessed using the results from daily Full Blood Count data and reporting of adverse events. Expected events are: Skin ulceration, Serous exudate, Abscess formation, steomyelitis &amp; Discomfort in the vein during infusion. Daily trial nurse assessment and review of the patient's medical record will be used to assess all adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days' following admission to the hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be eligible for the study: 1. Age 18 or over. 2. Cellulitis deemed on grounds of severity to require admission for intravenous antibiotics. 3. Capable of understanding and willing to give written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The following will exclude patients from randomisation: 1. Dementia or mental state preventing informed consent 2. Refusal to give informed consent 3. Chronic heart failure requiring fluid restriction &lt; 1000ml 4. Acute oliguric renal failure 5. Pulmonary oedema 6. Supplemental ingestion of Vitamin C 7. Known Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency 8. Any pregnant patients will be excluded (urine pregnancy test to be performed as per hospital protocol prior to randomisation. Negative result must be documented prior to randomisation).9. Patients taking any prohibited medication. 10. Diabetic patients currently on insulin.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The site staff who have been trained on the protocol will contact the Coordinating Centre (GLCC) via telephone when they are ready to perform a randomisation. The required details will be given over the phone and repeated to confirm they are correct. Then the randomisation will be performed by a trained GLCC emplyee using an Oracle database module specifically designed and tested for randomisations. The allocation of study kits to patients will be based on a random list supplied to the GLCC programmer by the independent statistician for use in the randomisation module. When a randomisation has been performed the site staff will receive an email confirming the details so that they can obtain the correct kit number for the patient. Only the statistician and GLCC programmer will be aware of the randomisation schedule in New Zealand.</concealment>
    <sequence>Then the randomisation will be performed by a trained GLCC emplyee using an Oracle database module specifically designed and tested for randomisations. The allocation of study kits to patients will be based on a random list supplied to the GLCC programmer by the independent statistician for use in the randomisation module.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Single site</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/08/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/07/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>3/07/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>16</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Whangarei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Biological Therapies</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Division of Orthomolecular Medisearch Laboratories Pty Ltd.
5/20-30 Malcolm Rd
Braeside VIC 3195</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Whangarei Hospital, General Medical Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Northland District Health Board, Maunu Rd, PO Box 742
Whangarei, 0110</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>this study is being performed because patients are admitted to hospital for the treatment of Cellulitis. Cellulitis is a skin infection usually caused by a type of bacteria entering the skin, usually by way of a cut, abrasion, or break in the skin. This break does not need to be visible. The typical symptoms of Cellulitis are an area which is red, hot and is inflamed. While in hospital, patients diagnosed with lower limb Cellulitis are usually treated with antibiotics, rest and pain-killers, as well as receiving normal standard hospital care. The duration of a patients stay in hospital varies, but averages 5 days in hospital. Cellulitis is a skin infection and is associated with inflammation. Many infections, if caught early, respond to antibiotic therapy. However there is no specific therapy targeting the inflammatory component of Cellulitis. Systemic inflammation associated with Cellulitis generates large amounts of free-radicals and oxidative damage (stress to certain cells in your body). The ability of the body to fight such oxidative stress is dependent on your anti-oxidant system (protection of body cells from damaging effects). Vitamin C is an anti-oxidant, and it protects the body against oxidative stress. Vitamin C levels are reduced in the presence of low or high-grade systemic inflammation, such as Cellulitis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The protocol stated a sample size of 140 was required for a clear result. Our initial assessment based on previous admission rates indicated the site should be able to achieve this within 2 years. Unfortunately, an unforeseen change in the way treatment for cellulitis was delivered, with the sudden move away from hospital admission for treatment meant that after recruitment started the trial the numbers admitted fell dramatically. As a consequence, after 2 years the site only managed to recruit 16 patients. The PI decided to terminate the trial prematurely as a consequence.

The results obtained from the 16 patients suggested a possible positive impact of the treatment, but unfortunately the numbers were too few to make a clear judgement on whether using this as a treatment is worthwhile.
</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3rd floor, Unisys building 
650 Great South Rd
Penrose 1061
Auckland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/11/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Wendy Coleman</name>
      <address>CCU Department
Whangarei Hospital
Maunu Road
WHANGAREI, 0110</address>
      <phone>+64 9 430 4100</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 430 4117</fax>
      <email>wendy.coleman@northlanddhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wendy Coleman</name>
      <address>CCU Department
Whangarei Hospital
Maunu Road
WHANGAREI, 0110</address>
      <phone>+64 9 430 4100 ext 7662</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 430 4117</fax>
      <email>wendy.coleman@northlanddhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Caroline Alsweiler</name>
      <address>Level 1, 2163 Great North Rd, Avondale, Auckland</address>
      <phone>+6498202051</phone>
      <fax>+6498202059</fax>
      <email>carolinea@glcc.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nigel Harrison  </name>
      <address>CCU Department Whangarei Hospital Maunu Road WHANGAREI, 0110</address>
      <phone>+64 9 430 4100 ext 7662</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 430 4117</fax>
      <email>nigel.harrison@northlanddhb.org.nz  </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>