<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82365">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/11/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000616471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A double blind, placebo controlled study of diltiazem hydrocholoride 2% cream in the treatment of fissure in ano.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double blind, placebo controlled study of diltiazem hydrocholoride 2% cream in the treatment of fissure in ano.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anal Fissure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>A study to determine the effect of diltiazem hydrochloride cream in patients with anal fissure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Diltiazem hydrochloride cream 2.5cm (approximately 0.5g) three times per day versus placebo 2.5cm three times per day placed around the anus for a period of up to 8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - cream base as for active composed of liquid paraffin, cetomacragol emulsifying wax, glyceryl monostearate, propylene glycol, phenoxyethanol and water</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This study seeks to address the following question:
Does topical application of diltiazem hydrochloride 2% cream provide greater relief of pain on defaecation than placebo in subjects with chronic anal fissure (as measured on a Likert scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Randomisation
Week 2, Week 4 &amp; Week 8</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numbers of subjects achieving predetermined changes in Likert score for pain on defaecation from baseline to Week 4.
Health outcome measure at 8 weeks compared to baseline 
Fissure healing status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 4 &amp; 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Symptomatic, anal fissure (pain on or following defecation) present for &gt;4 weeks and presenting with notable fissure-related pain.
-Evidence of circumscribed fissure, with induration at the edges, with or without a sentinel tag, confirmed on physical examination. 
-Female subjects of childbearing potential must have negative urine pregnancy test on entry and be using adequate contraception</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subject with acute fissure (symptoms of duration &lt;4 weeks, no induration at edges). Previous surgical treatment for anal fissure. Other previous surgery involving the anal canal or perianal region. Score of &lt;Moderate at baseline on a Likert 7-point Scale for anal pain on defaecation and a score of &lt;4 on the Numerical Rating Scale for anal pain on defaecation (baseline pain score is the average anal pain on defaecation for the 3 defaecations prior to randomisation). Medical treatment of anal fissure during the past 4 weeks with botulinum toxin or topical steroid containing creams (e.g. Xyloproct cream, Anusol HC etc.), diltiazem or other calcium channel blocker topical or oral preparations or have used glyceryl trinitrate cream (GTN ointment, Rectogesic) for &gt;1 week in the past 4 weeks prior to the screening visit. (NB all topical preparations to the perianal region must be stopped prior to the screening phase). Subjects who have previously failed to respond to topical diltiazem therapy. Subjects who have previously failed to respond to topical GTN therapy. Subjects currently using any drugs which, in the opinion of the investigator, may influence anal sphincter tone or blood supply (e.g. alpha- or beta-adrenoceptor agonists [other than inhaled ß-agonists] or antagonists, sympathomimetics, anti-hypertensive agents, medical treatments for irritable bowel syndrome, phosphodiesterase-5 inhibitors (PDE V inhibitors) Subjects on antibiotic therapy. Subjects with a history of inflammatory bowel disease. Subjects with anal fissure associated with other conditions such as human immunodeficientcy virus (HIV) infection, fistula-in-ano, perianal sepsis, malignancy or as a result of traumatic childbirth. History or evidence on examination of pre-existing cardiac disease, including severe bradycardia, arrhythmias and conduction abnormalities. Coexisting gastrointestinal disease or previous gut resection. Known hypersensitivity to diltiazem.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>S.L.A. Pharma (UK) Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Elite House
Hill Farm Industrial Estate
Leavesden
Watford
WD25 7SA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>S.L.A. Pharma (UK) Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Elite House
Hill Farm Industrial Estate
Leavesden
Watford
WD25 7SA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>S.L.A. Pharma (UK) Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Elite House
Hill Farm Industrial Estate
Leavesden
Watford
WD25 7SA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Anal fissure is a split in the lining of the back passage and is the source of intense pain on defaecation.  The underlying cause is thought to be excessive contraction and poor blood flow in the muscle (anal sphincter) that is responsible for maintaining continence.  Diltiazem hydrochloride, applied locally as a cream, reduces contractions and improves blood flow in the sphincter so helping to reduce pain on defaecation and increase the chances of healing of the fissure.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ABN 77 054 038 872
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/11/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07/SVH/58</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Chris Jordan</name>
      <address>S.L.A. Pharma (UK)
Elite Hourse
Hill Farm Industrial Estate
Leavesden
Watford WD25 7SA</address>
      <phone>+44 1923681001</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cjordan@slapharma.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Darren Gold</name>
      <address>Surgical Professorial Unit
St Vincent's Hospital
Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83821111</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83822794</fax>
      <email>dandjgold@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sue Huntley</name>
      <address>188 Murray Farm Road
Beecroft NSW 2119</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>shuntley@slapharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>