<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365884">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000520437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of glyceryl trinitrate ointment as treatment for leg ulcers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double blind (pilot) trial of the application of 0.2% glyceryl trinitrate ointment for the healing of chronic venous leg ulcers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-9849</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Trial Number:2014/0114 CTN Scheme (Drugs)
Schedule 5A of Regulation 12 of the Therapeutic Goods Administration</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic venous leg ulcers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Connective tissue diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The proposed research plans to examine the application of an ointment containing glyceryl trinitrate (GTN) [Rectogesic 0.2% GTN], a pharmaceutical agent approved for human use, on venous leg ulcers. GTN ointment works in part by releasing nitric oxide (NO) into the wound, which acts to improve blood flow to the area and has the capacity to kill unwanted bacteria in the wound. The product to date has not been used routinely for the treatment of venous leg ulcers. A previous study by the chief investigator demonstrated the enzyme (iNOS), which drives the production of NO, was elevated in patients with faster healing leg ulcers, suggesting that application of a topical GTN donor (the ointment) might accelerate this healing process. 
The trial will be double blinded with half of the recruited patients (n=20) receiving a placebo ointment and the other half receiving the GTN donor ointment (n=20). Neither the patients nor the research nurse involved in treatment will know if the product used is the placebo or the GTN donor ointment. Participants will receive 4 x weekly dressings (weekly for 4 weeks) for the ulcer, which will include an application of the randomised ointment (5-10mL depending on the size of the ulcer) and standardised usual care of compression bandaging with foam dressing as needed. All dressings will be undertaken by the research nurse in the hospital setting, with participants as inpatients in a hospital ward, or if discharged, as outpatients in a clinic setting. Participants will be referred to their GP for usual treatment at the completion of the 4 weekly treatments if their ulcer is not healed.

Rates of healing will be determined by planimetry (ulcer tracing) using computer software for the purpose (Pictzar) since complete healing of the ulcer will most likely not be achieved in the time frame being examined. If a statistically significant difference exists between the two groups the treatment will deemed successful. It is hoped that a subsequent larger trial will be planned based on the findings from this study.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo ointment is the base ointment that is identical to the intervention ointment without the active ingredient (glyceryl trinitrate).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The trial will run only for 4 weeks so rates of healing will be determined by planimetry (ulcer tracing) using computer software for this purpose (PicZar).Complete healing of the ulcer will most likely not be achieved in the time frame being examined. If a statistically significant difference exists between the two groups the treatment will deemed successful. It is hoped that a subsequent larger trial will be planned based on the findings from this pilot clinical trial. The trial is therefore a "proof of concept" trial before larger Phase 2 trials begin.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after treatment (i.e. Each participant will be treated weekly for 4 weeks).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This investigation seeks to recruit consenting patients with venous leg ulceration from the internal medicine wards of the Prince Charles Hospital (TPCH). Venous ulceration will be confirmed by the use of transdermal oxygen sensors in conjunction with equipment provided by Podiatry (TPCH).  This is to rule out ulceration by other aetiologies (i.e. arterial, pressure, diabetic) which have been shown in earlier studies to not benefit from GTN application (data not published).

Patients recruited into this study will be informed that their participation in this trial is entirely voluntary and no financial payment will be given. If patients decide to not take part in this study, there will be no prejudice against their future care and are free to withdraw at any time. Consenting patients will then be randomly allocated to one of two groups (placebo versus GTN treatment).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients must have venous ulceration. Additionally, patients with malignant ulcers or have other forms of malignancy will be excluded from the study together with any patient who has active autoimmune disease or have had organ transplantation. Patients who have any form of cardiac disease will also be excluded from treatment with GTN as the product may lower blood pressure.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A set of 40 opaque sealed envelopes will be prepared according to the randomisation allocation list described in sequence generation. Only one researcher will have access to the randomisation list and will prepare the envelopes. All patients who meet the inclusion criteria will be asked by the research nurse to participate in the study. Once a patient consents to participate, the next envelope in the numerical sequence will be opened and the product with the corresponding number will be used for treatment for that participant. </concealment>
    <sequence>A random number generator will be used to randomise control (placebo) and experiment (GTN) allocation 1:1 across a set of numbers from 1 - 40 (40 patients in study). A set of numbered labels for 40 bottles of product (20 GTN and 20 placebo) will be prepared using the randomised allocation. Only one researcher will label the products with numbers according to the prepared randomisation list. All other researchers involved in preparation of product and data collection and analysis processes will be blinded to randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a pilot study so size of sample for power for this phenomenon is not known. A previous related study has shown some effect in a very small sample size.
The primary outcome measure is rate of healing. 
Data will be entered manually into  SPSS (version 23) for analysis. Descriptive statistics will be used to summarise the data e.g. means and percentages. Parametric tests (provided data assumptions are met) will be used to analyse differences and relationships between variables. Significance will be set at p &lt; 0.05. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>0</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rode Road
Chermside QLD 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1100 Nudgee Road
Banyo QLD 4104</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Care Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1674
Bondi Junction NSW 1355</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>3M Australia Pty. Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 9, 23 Breene Place
Morningside Qld 417o</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Radiometer Pacific</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>43/49 Butterfield St, 
Herston QLD 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Catholic University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>40 Edward St
North Sydney NSW 2060</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed research plans to examine the application of an ointment (Rectogesic 0.2% GTN), a pharmaceutical agent approved for human use, on venous leg ulcers. GTN ointment works in part by releasing nitric oxide (NO) into the wound, which acts to improve blood flow to the area and has the capacity to kill unwanted bacteria in the wound. The product to date has not been used routinely for the treatment of venous leg ulcers. A previous study by the chief investigator demonstrated the enzyme (iNOS), which drives the production of NO, was elevated in patients with faster healing leg ulcers, suggesting that application of a topical GTN donor (the ointment) might accelerate this healing process. 

The trial will be double blinded with half of the recruited patients receiving a placebo and the other half receiving the GTN donor. Neither the patients nor the research nurse involved in treatment will know if the product is the placebo or the GTN donor. The trial will run only for 4 weeks for each patient so rates of healing will be determined by planimetry (ulcer tracing) as complete healing of the ulcer will most likely not be achieved in the time frame being examined. If a statistically significant difference exists between the two groups the treatment will deemed successful. It is hoped that a subsequent larger trial will be planned based on the findings from this study.

Hypothesis: 
Participants receiving the Rectogesic (GTN donor) will have a statistically higher linear healing rate (LHR) compared to patients that receive only the placebo. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>none</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee Metro North Hospital and Health Services, The Prince Charles Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office
Building 14
Rode Road
Chermside QLD 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QPCH/68</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/365884-Research_Protocol_GTNlegulcertrial_Version_2_170715_finalised.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Lord</name>
      <address>School of Science, Brisbane
Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road
Banyo QLD 4014</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7240</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3623 7242</fax>
      <email>roger.lord@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Damian Williams</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 5646</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Damian.Williams@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Lord</name>
      <address>School of Science, Brisbane
Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road
Banyo QLD 4014</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7240</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>roger.lord@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sandra Miles</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Midwifery and Paramedicine, Brisbane
Australian Catholic University
1100 Nudgee Road
Banyo QLD 4014</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3623 7293</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sandra.miles@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>