<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373122">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001134314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating a Physical Activity Promotion Intervention for Community-Dwelling Wheelchair Users with Spinal Cord Injury.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating a Physical Activity Promotion Intervention for Community-Dwelling Wheelchair Users with Spinal Cord Injury.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>N/A</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Cord Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant will participate in the study for a total of 40 weeks.  The study will be conducted in the home and community environment of the participant. During the 40-week study, participant will be asked to wear two physical activity monitors: the wheelchair mounted device (Wheeleri) and a wrist worn accelerometer. The Wheeleri will attached to the wheelchair the whole 40-week period and the ActiGraph will be worn minimum of 15 to maximum of 17 four-day monitoring periods (60-68 days), during the whole 40-week period. These monitors will be used to measure the participants physical activity during daily activities like wheelchair propulsion and stationary upper body activities. Participants will also be asked to complete four questionnaires measuring mediators of physical activity participation (including self-efficacy, social support and decisional balance) and measures of health related quality of life at 7 time points spread equally over the 40 week study protocol. At the conclusion of the intervention, participants will be asked to participate in a semi-structured interview regarding their perceptions of the intervention program. The study protocol comprises 3 phases: baseline phase (8 weeks); intervention phase (16 weeks); and post intervention phase (16 weeks).
Phase A: No intervention (Baseline) 
During the 8-week baseline phase, participants physical activity will be monitored while they continue with their normal behaviour in order to determine their baseline level of physical activity. 
Phase B: Intervention
The baseline phase will be followed by a 16-week intervention. The intervention will be delivered using a community-based rehabilitation model which aims to enhance the natural support systems within the participants home and community environment.
During the 16-week intervention period, participants will receive 12 face to face visits of a one hour duration in their own home or local community. In between these sessions they will also receive phone/online support as required.  Session frequency will diminish over the 16-week period, with a reduced number of sessions as a result of an increased emphasis on maintenance of physical activity participation including fostering independence and self-management. 
This intervention implementation comprises of 4 Steps: 
1. Step. Pre-participation assessment: participant will have one 2 hour session at their home with primary investigator where they will have to answer different questionnaires including
1)  an assessment of physiological, personal and environmental factors that  may influence on physical activity participation such as
- the functional abilities and limitations related to disability and functioning such as ability to do wheelchair propulsion, body lifts and exercise movements with and without the chair
- the personal abilities, interests and skills to carry out physical activities and personal history and experiences in physical activity such as gardening, outdoor activities, water activities, ball games, gym work out, dance. 
-  the accessibility level of participant's home and local community to carry out physical activities such as free space at home and garden, transportation to local community activities and accessibility at the community venues and facilities. 
 2) assessment of stage of change  where participant's motivational readiness for being physically active will be evaluated. 
Pre-assessment also includes information sharing activities including the matrial (video, paper and oral material) related to the definition and benefits of physical activity participation. 
Step 2. A In lifestyle PA intervention sessions:  participant will have 12 1 hour sessions during 16 weeks intervention period at their home with primary investigator. During these sessions they will be using different stage-matched behavior change strategies; (e.g. including but not limited to information sharing, personal time auditing, value identification and barrier identification and resolution);
Step 3. Structured exercise prescription: during the 16 weeks intervention period participant will be encouraged to do different physical activities including structured exercise prescription (in terms of frequency, intensity, time and type) and/or and community based physical activity participation (e.g. going to the local pool or gym or attending an art class); 
Step 4. Tailored relapse prevention: during the Lifestyle PA sessions primary investigator will go through together with the participant tailored relapse prevention strategies to foster physical activity maintenance following the withdrawal of the intervention. 
The intervention aims to help participants to find activities that they can complete which are enjoyable, effective for improving their health and which they will be able to maintain at the conclusion of the intervention. The activities selected will be the choice of their participant and will work within their resources (e.g., access, time and money). This intervention has been demonstrated to successfully increase physical activity adoption in adults with brain impairment.  
The intervention will be delivered by the primary investigator Kati Karinharju, who has experience in exercise prescription for individuals with a disability and the use of behaviour change strategies for increasing PA. The principal investigator has a Master degree in both sport sciences and adapted physical activities and she has been working as Senior lecturer (In Finland) in the field of adapted physical activity. She has extensive experience (over 15 years) working in the area of physical activities for the populations included in this research, including high care participants. She is also experienced using devices and protocols used with used with the populations included in this project. This project also includes co-project workers with high experience and competence in these relevant areas. Given the project team's considerable experience, plus additional training as needed, will assure quality research processes and assure the comfort and safety of the project participants.
Phase A2: No Intervention (Post intervention)
The intervention phase will be followed by a 16-week non-contact post intervention period during which physical activity will be monitored in order to determine the extent to which any increases in physically active behaviour achieved during the intervention are maintained.  </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group' </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wheelchair movement (time) during the daily living using a the measure Wheeleri
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data from the primary outcome measure Wheeleri ( the time the wheelchair is moving) will be collected over the complete study duration (40 weeks including 8 week baseline phase, 16 weeks intervention phase and 16 weeks post-intervention phase). The Average daily activity (time) during the 8 baseline weeks will be compared to the average daily activity during the 16 weeks intervention (adoption) and to the last 16 weeks of post-intervention phase (maintenance). 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wheelchair movement (distance) during the daily living using a the measure Wheeleri.



</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data from the primary outcome measure Wheeleri ( the distance the wheelchair is moving) will be collected over the complete study duration (40 weeks including 8 week baseline phase, 16 weeks intervention phase and 16 weeks post-intervention phase). The average daily activity (distance) during the 8 baseline weeks will be compared to the average daily activity during the 16 weeks intervention (adoption) and to the last 16 weeks of post-intervention phase (maintenance). 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels assessed using data from ActiGpraph GT9X  ( the mean counts during the daily activities using the machine learning algorithm) to identify periods of manual wheelchair propulsion,</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data from the primary outcome measure ActiGraphGT9X ( the mean counts during the daily activities using a machine learning algorithm) will be collected with minimum of 15 to maximum of 17 four-day monitoring periods (multiple baseline design): Baseline A: 5-7 monitoring periods, Internvetion B: 5 monitoring periods and Post intervention A2: 5 monitoring periods. The average daily counts during the 8 baseline weeks  will be compared to the average daily counts during the 16 weeks intervention (adoption) and to the last 16 weeks of post-intervention phase (maintenance). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy assessed using Exercise self-efficacy questionnaire. Exercise Self-Efficacy Scale (ESES) is a self-report measure which includes 10 questions of how confident the person is with regard to carrying out regular physical activities and exercise. The SCI Exercise Self-Efficacy Scale (ESES) has 4-point Likert scale: 1 = not at all true, 2 = rarely true, 3 = moderately true, 4 = always true. This questionnaire has been validated in people with spinal cord injuries. The reliability of this instrument is very high with satisfactory validity (Kroll et al. 2007). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data for secondary outcome measure self-efficacy will be collected during 7 data collection points during:  the beginning and middle of the baseline phase (week 1 &amp; 4),  the beginning, middle and end of the intervention phase ( week 9, 17, 24); and the middle and end of the post intervention phase (32 &amp; 40). The score results during the 8 week baseline will be compared to the average score results during the 16 weeks intervention and to the last 16 weeks of post-intervention phase. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social support assessed using social support queationnaire with 13 items that are designed to measure perceptions of social support and satisfaction with that social support (e.g. offering company or help to do physical activities, or encouraging to do physical activities). The answers are rated on social support from family and friends to perform physical activities and the scale of this measure is 1 to 5, starting of none to very often (Sallis, Grossman et al. 1987). The total score for each question will be added together to get overall social support score. Higher score indicates higher perceived social support (score range 13-130). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The data for secondary outcome measure sosial support will be collected during 7 data collection points during:  the beginning and middle of the baseline phase (week 1 &amp; 4),  the beginning, middle and end of the intervention phase ( week 9, 17, 24); and the middle and end of the post intervention phase (32 &amp; 40). The score results during the 8 week baseline will be compared to the average score results during the 16 weeks intervention and to the last 16 weeks of post-intervention phase. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decisional balance assessed using questionnaire with 16 items that concentrates on the positive and negative aspects of being physically active (e.g. influences on tiredness, sleep and body image).  The psychometric properties of this measure are barriers and benefits of being physically active and the scale of this measure is 1 to 5, starting from not important to extremely important (Nigg, Rossi, Norman &amp; Benisovich 1998). The answers of decisional balance are divided in pro and con statements. The decisional balance score will be summed con statement score subtracted from summed pro score. Numbers greater than 1 indicate benefits outweigh negatives and numbers lower than 1 indicate negatives outweigh the positives.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data for secondary outcome measure decisional balance will be collected during 7 data collection points during:  the beginning and middle of the baseline phase (week 1 &amp; 4),  the beginning, middle and end of the intervention phase ( week 9, 17, 24); and the middle and end of the post intervention phase (32 &amp; 40). The score results during the 8 week baseline will be compared to the average score results during the 16 weeks intervention and to the last 16 weeks of post-intervention phase. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life (HRQL) assessed using the questionnaire SF-12, which provides quantitative information about the impact of disease on HRQL. It is a multipurpose questionnaire with 12 items that are selected from the  original SF-36 Health Survey (Ware, Kosinski, and Keller, 1996). The questions concentrates on persons health are combined, scored, and weighted to create two scales that provide glimpses into mental and physical functioning and overall health-related-quality of life (e.g. does the current health limit daily activities or does the pain influence on daily activities) (Ware, Kosinski, and Keller, 1996).  The total score is the sum of recorded physical component summary (PCS) and mental component summary (MCS). Higher scores indicate higher perceived health related quality of life</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data for secondary outcome measure healt-related quality of life will be collected during 7 data collection points during:  the beginning and middle of the baseline phase (week 1 &amp; 4),  the beginning, middle and end of the intervention phase ( week 9, 17, 24); and the middle and end of the post intervention phase (32 &amp; 40). The score results during the 8 week baseline will be compared to the average score results during the 16 weeks intervention and to the last 16 weeks of post-intervention phase. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This study aims to recruit 6 participants with spinal cord injuries.
This study will include male and female adults who at the time of enrolment:
-	have a spinal cord injury;
-	are aged 18-55;
-	use a manual wheelchair or power-assisted manual wheelchair for daily activities at least some of the time. They may use power chairs or other mobility devices at other times;
-	are insufficiently physically active for health at time of recruitment; and
-	are medically fit to undertake at least moderate intensity physical activity, as determined by the Adult Pre-exercise Screening System (APSS) (Exercise and Sport Science Australia (ESSA) 2016).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>This study will exclude individuals who have a diagnosed cognitive impairment, intellectual disability or mental illness that restricts their ability to participate in the behaviour change activities integral to the intervention.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>In this study, objective data for each participant will be recorded in real time and at the end of the each data collection period will be downloaded on a personal computer, opened in Microsoft Excel and then imported into SPSS (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive statistics will be generated using PASW Statistics 22 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive statistics will be reported as mean and standard deviation. The outcome measures of the study, will be plotted against time. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>6</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>0</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland, Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences (HMNS).</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Human Movement Studies
St Lucia campus, University of QLD, 4072
Australia

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Motor Accident Insurance Commission, Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 William St, Brisbane City QLD 4001, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland, Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences (HMNS).</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Human Movement Studies
St Lucia campus, University of QLD, 4072
Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Motor Accident Insurance Commission, Australia </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>1 William St, Brisbane City QLD 4001, 
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Individuals with a spinal cord injury do not participate in sufficient physical activity to meet the recommended guidelines for good health.  To promote physical activity, physical activity interventions are needed. The aim of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of a physical activity promotion intervention for community-dwelling adults with a spinal cord injury who use a wheelchair as their primary means of locomotion. The aim of the intervention is increase physical activity participation. Primary outcomes of this study will be increased amount of physical activity that the participants are conducting during their daily living. The secondary outcomes will be self-efficacy, social support and decisional balance in physical activity and health-related quality of life. The study design will be based on the single-subject research design guidelines for determining sample size and protocol for sampling behaviour (Romeiser Logan, Hickman et al. 2008). Each participant will participate in the study for a total of 40 weeks. The study will be conducted in the home and community environment of the participant. During the 40-week study, participant will be asked to wear two physical activity monitors: the wheelchair mounted device (Wheeleri) and a wrist worn accelerometer which has the look and feel of a wristwatch (ActiGraph GT9X). Participants will also be asked to complete four questionnaires measuring mediators of physical activity participation (including self-efficacy, social support and decisional balance) and measures of health related quality of life. The study protocol comprises 3 phases: baseline phase (8 weeks); intervention phase (16 weeks); and post intervention phase (16 weeks). During the 8-week baseline phase, participants physical activity will be monitored while they continue with their normal behaviour in order to determine their baseline level of physical activity. The baseline phase will be followed by a 16-week intervention. The intervention combines a stage-matched lifestyle physical activity intervention, structured exercise prescription and community integration delivered utilising a community-based rehabilitation. During the 16-week intervention period, participants will receive 12 face to face visits of a one hour duration in their own home or local community. In between these sessions they will also receive phone/online support as required (Dunn, Andersen et al. 1998). Session frequency will diminish over the 16-week period, with a reduced number of sessions as a result of an increased emphasis on maintenance of physical activity participation including fostering independence and self-management. The intervention phase will be followed by a 16-week non-contact post intervention period during which physical activity will be monitored in order to determine the extent to which any increases in physically active behaviour achieved during the intervention are maintained.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Human Research Ethics committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Kati Susanna Karinharju</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
St Lucia campus, University of QLD, 4072
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33654998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.karinharju@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Kati Susanna Karinharju</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
St Lucia campus, University of QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33654998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.karinharju@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Kati Susanna Karinharju</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
St Lucia campus, University of QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33654998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.karinharju@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Kati Susanna Karinharju</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement Studies
St Lucia campus, University of QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33654998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.karinharju@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>