<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364961">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001041741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Short term effects of palm-tocotrienols and palm-carotenes on vascular function and cardiovascular disease risk in individuals at increased risk of impaired vascular function. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Will short-term supplementation with palm-tocotrienols and palm-carotenes improve endothelial function as measured by brachial artery flow mediated dilation in participants with increased risk of impaired vascular function compared to control? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease risk</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Impaired fasting glucose</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Abdominal obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will consume one of the following two interventions for a duration of 8 weeks:

* 500mg/d palm tocotrienols in the form of two palm olein capsules/d to be consumed orally with the main meal.

OR

* 21mg/d palm carotenes in the form of three palm olein capsules to be consumed orally with the main meal.

Compliance will be monitored by counting of returned capsules and by measuring plasma tocotrienol and carotenoid concentrations using HPLC. </interventions>
    <comparator>800mg/d palm olein in the form of two capsules to be consumed orally with the main meal. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelial function measured by brachial artery flow mediated dilation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure using automated oscillometry
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucose metabolism
* Insulin and glucose using plama assays
* Insulin resistance by calculating HOMA2-IR
* HbA1c using HPLC
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipid profiles (total cholesterol, HDL-C, LDL-C, triglycerides) using plasma assays</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma inflammatory markers (hs-CRP, IL-6, TNFalpha, adiponectin) using multiplex kits
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma adhesion molecules (ICAM-1, VCAM-1, E-selectin) using multiplex assays
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelium derived fibrinolytic factors:
* tPA using plasma assays
* PAI-1 using mulitplex assays
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial stiffness using pulse wave velocity and augmentation index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4 weeks, 8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Male or female
*Type 2 diabetes (previously diagnosed and taking anti-diabetic medication or HbA1c of 7.0-10.0%) or impaired fasting glucose (fasting plasma glucose of 5.6 mmol/L and greater) or abdominal obesity identified by elevated waist circumference: equal of greater than 102 cm (men); equal or greater than 88 cm (women). 
*18-70 years
* BMI: 20-45 kg/m2
* No abnormality of clinical significance on medical history
* No history of coronary artery disease or cardiac (heart) abnormalities
   </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Type 1 diabetes
* Smoking
* Known proteinuria or current malignancy
* Known kidney, respiratory, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular or peripheral vascular disease
* Known abnormal liver function tests
* Known endocrinopathy unless participants are stable on treatment (have been using thyroxine for at least 3 months prior to study commencement (no changes in type and dose) and have no intention to change during study). 
* Pregnancy or lactating
* Participated in regular vigorous physical exercise greater than 1 hour per week or greater than 2x, 30 minute sessions / week during the 3 months prior to the study
* Have taken tocotrienol or carotene supplements during the 3 months prior to study
* Taking supplements known to affect outcome measures (i.e. fish oil, vitamin C) unless supplements are ceased before trial commencement (3 months for fish oil, 2 weeks for vitamin C) or participants are stable on the supplements for at least 3 months prior to study commencement (no changes in type and dose) and have no intention to change during study. 
* Use of nitrate medication, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medication (excluding aspirin)
* Taking oral contraceptives or hormone replacement therapy during the 3 months prior to study
* History of heavy alcohol consumption (&gt; 5 STD drinks/day)
* Volunteer unable to limit alcohol consumption for study duration
* Currently on a weight reducing diet or have an eating disorder
* Unwilling to be randomized to either experimental group
* Extended absences due to travel or other commitments
* Unable to comprehend or cope with study requirements </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who are eligible will be enrolled in the project and allocated to an intervention code based on a computer generated randomization scheme. Individuals who enrol and allocate particpants to interventions will be blind to intervention codes. The coded supplements will be concealed by using identical opaque drug containers. </concealment>
    <sequence>Eligible participants will be assigned to the interventions using stratified random assignment based on diabetic/impaired fasting glucose state, age, gender, weight and medication. The randomization scheme will be computer generated. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The power for this study is based on detecting differences for the a priori hypothesis based on comparisons between the palm-carotene vs placebo and palm-tocotrienol  vs placebo for the primary outcome measure of FMD. The study will commence with 30 subjects in each group. Based our previous trials, with an anticipate dropout rate of 10% and at least 27 subjects per group completing the study we will have enough power (80%, alpha = 0.05) to detect a minimum absolute difference of 1.8% between the group comparisons for FMD. An improvement in FMD of 2% (absolute) magnitude has previously been associated with a clinically relevant reduction in CVD risk.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/05/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>90</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CSIRO Animal, Food and Health Sciences </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 10041 
Adelaide BC SA 5000 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pemandu (Prime Ministers Development of the Goverment of Malaysia) / MPOB (Malaysian Palm oil Board)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Food Technology &amp; Nutrition Unit,
Product Development &amp; Advisory Services Division,
Malaysian Palm Oil Board
P.O. Box 10620
50720 Kuala Lumpur</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to investigate the effects of short term supplementation with either palm-tocotrienol or palm-carotene on blood vessel function and cardiovascular disease risk in participants at risk of impaired vascular function.

We hypothesise that supplementation with both palm-tocotrienol and palm-carotene will improve blood vessel function and cardiovascular disease risk factors compared to a control supplement. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Human Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 10041
Adelaide BC 
SA, 5000 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mahinda Abeywardena</name>
      <address>CSIRO Animal, Food and Health Sciences
PO Box 10041
Adelaide
South Australia
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8889</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mahinda.abeywardena@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Welma Stonehouse</name>
      <address>CSIRO Animal, Food and Health Sciences
PO Box 10041
Adelaide
South Australia
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8919 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>welma.stonehouse@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Welma Stonehouse</name>
      <address>CSIRO Animal, Food and Health Sciences
PO Box 10041
Adelaide
South Australia
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8919 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>welma.stonehouse@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Welma Stonehouse</name>
      <address>CSIRO Animal, Food and Health Sciences
PO Box 10041
Adelaide
South Australia
5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8919 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>welma.stonehouse@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>