<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363699">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000184774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Transcendental Meditation for Carers of Dementia Sufferers Trial [TRANSCENDENT]</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Improving the health and wellbeing of community-dwelling carers of dementia sufferers  a randomised controlled trial of structured meditation training.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TRANSCENDENT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychological stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Transcendental Meditation [Registered Trademark] (TM): The twelve-week TM training program comprises a one-hour introductory session, four one-and-a-half-hour training sessions (over the first week), followed by three weekly one-hour classes and four fortnightly one-hour classes, held in groups, under the guidance of experienced TM instructors. The initial sessions will comprise content on the health effects of stress, the theory of TM, training of the TM technique, and assessment and refining of the technique. The weekly and fortnightly sessions will focus on assessing, refining and mastering the TM technique.</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list control: Participants assigned to wait-list control will receive twelve-weeks of no intervention, followed by four-weeks of a healthy lifestyle education program. The lifestyle program comprises four weekly ninety-minute sessions. These group sessions will be facilitated by an experienced TM instructor. Sessions will be focussed on developing skills and knowledge that foster a healthy diet and lifestyle, including yoga, preparing healthy meals, and stress management.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean health-related quality of life index score, as measured by the Assessment of Quality of Life 8-dimension (AQoL-8D) instrument</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean stress score, as measured by the depression, anxiety and stress scale within the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean emotional resilience score, as measured by the WebNeuro test battery</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean depression score, as measured by the depression, anxiety and stress scale within the WebNeuro test battery.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean anxiety score, as measured by the depression, anxiety and stress scale within the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean psychomotor response speed, as measured by the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean impulsivity score, as measured by the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean attention and concentration score, as measured by the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean information processing efficiency score, as measured by the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean working memory score, as measured by the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean executive function score, as measured by the WebNeuro test battery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed at baseline (week 0), post-intervention (week 12) and at follow-up (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) Is a non-professional, community-dwelling carer of a person with diagnosed dementia, 
(ii) Has not received previous instruction on the TM technique, 
(iii) Is able to provide written consent, 
(iv) Is able to speak, read and understand English, 
(v) Is available and willing to complete all TM / healthy lifestyle program sessions and baseline, post-intervention and follow-up assessments, and
(vi) Is able to arrange respite for the dementia sufferer when away for the TM / healthy lifestyle program sessions and assessments.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) Has a history of any condition causing moderate to severe cognitive impairment, 
(ii) Has begun or ceased psychotropic medication within the past six weeks, 
(iii) Has participated in a clinical trial within the past 30 days, where psychological outcomes and quality of life were outcomes of interest, 
(iv) Practices some form of mind-body therapy on a regular basis, 
(v) Consults a psychologist or psychiatrist at least once a week, and 
(vi) Has taken a recreational drug in the past 15 days.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation codes will be held in sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes. Each envelope will be selected in consecutive order at the time of participant enrolment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to TM or wait-list control at a ratio of 1:1. Block randomisation will be used with computer-generated randomly permuted blocks of four; this will be performed by a researcher not involved in the implementation of the project, and blinded to the identity of the participants.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>- Measures of central tendency and variability will be used for descriptive data that is normally distributed. 
- Medians and the interquartile ranges will be used to describe data that is not normally distributed. 
- Frequency distributions and percentages will be used to describe categorical data.
- Differences between groups at baseline will be examined using the t-test for independent groups. 
- Outcome differences between groups, differences over time and any differential treatment effect at different points in time will be examined using repeated measures analysis of variance.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2471, Adelaide, SA, 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alzheimer's Australia Dementia Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Frewin Place, Scullin, ACT, 2614</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Maharishi Invincibility Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>190 Greenhill Road, Parkside, SA, 5063</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>RMIT University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>200 Ballarat Road, Hamilton, VIC, 3300</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The impact of dementia on family caregivers is substantial. Building on growing clinical interest in the capacity for Transcendental Meditation [Registered Trademark] (TM; a deep relaxation technique) to reduce stress and anxiety in healthy workers, this pilot RCT will examine whether similar improvements could be experienced by dementia caregivers. Specifically, the study will explore whether a TM program can improve psychological stress, quality of life, affect and cognitive performance of dementia caregivers when compared to wait-list control.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>PUBLISHED
Leach MJ. Francis A. Ziaian T. (2014) Improving the health and wellbeing of community-dwelling carers of dementia sufferers  study protocol of a randomised controlled trial of structured meditation training. Journal of Alternative &amp; Complementary Medicine. 20(2): 136-141. 

UNDER REVIEW
Two manuscripts are currently under review; the first manuscript presents the findings of the study; the second manuscript presents the challenges in recruiting carers into clinical trials.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2471, Adelaide, SA, 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Leach</name>
      <address>School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery, Centenary Building, University of South Australia, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.leach@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Leach</name>
      <address>School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery, Centenary Building, University of South Australia, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.leach@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Leach</name>
      <address>School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery, Centenary Building, University of South Australia, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.leach@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Leach</name>
      <address>School of Nursing &amp; Midwifery, Centenary Building, University of South Australia, North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2846</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.leach@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>