<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363986">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000386730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety, tolerability, food effect and pharmacokinetics of FT011 in healthy volunteers and patients with Type 2 diabetes-associated diabetic nephropathy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, double blind, randomised, placebo-controlled, dose-escalating study of the safety, tolerability, food effect and pharmacokinetics of single and repeat doses of FT011 administered orally to healthy volunteers and patients with diabetic nephropathy associated with Type 2 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Protocol number FT011-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic nephropathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>FT011 oral capsules.

Part A:  5 sequential cohorts of healthy volunteers each receiving a single dose of 10, 30, 100, 300 or 1000mg and followed up to Day 7.

Part B:  single cohort of healthy volunteers receiving a single dose of 100mg in the fed or fasted state followed by 10 day washout then crossover to a single dose of 100mg in the alternate state.  E.g a subject may be randomised to receive the dose while fasted, then will return to receive a dose after a meal, or vice versa.  Subjects will be followed up to Day 7 after the second dose.  Part B may run concurrently with Part A, once Part A 100mg cohort is complete.

Part C:  3 cohorts of healthy volunteers followed by 2 cohorts of patients each receiving one dose per day for 14 days, and followed up to Day 21.  Dose levels to be determined after Part A is complete.  Part C will run after Part A and Part B are complete and safety and dose levels have been reviewed.

All subjects (Parts A, B and C) will be resident in clinic for dosing.  This will ensure dosing compliance.

In each cohort 75% of subjects will receive FT011 and 25% will recieve placebo </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo oral capsules containing microcrystalline cellulose.

As this is a blinded study dosing periods and times will be the same as for subjects receiving FT011.

In each cohort 25% of subjects will receive placebo and 75% will receive FT011</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of a single dose of FT011 in healthy volunteers (Part A) as assessed by vital signs, medical history, physical examination, laboratory evaluations, 12-lead ECG), evaluation of adverse events and concomitant medications.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored and recorded until 7 days post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of a single dose of FT011 in healthy volunteers in the fed and fasted state (Part B) as assessed by vital signs, medical history, physical examination, laboratory evaluations, 12-lead ECG), evaluation of adverse events and concomitant medications.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored and recorded until 7 days post dose in each state (fed or fasted)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of repeat doses of FT011 when administered to healthy volunteers and Type 2 diabetic patients with DN (Part C) as assessed by vital signs, medical history, physical examination, laboratory evaluations, 12-lead ECG), evaluation of adverse events and concomitant medications.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored and recorded until 21 days post first dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic profiles (Cmax, Tmax, T1/2, AUCt, AUCinf and clearance) of FT011 in serum and urine after single and multiple doses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single dose (Part A and Part B): At 15 and 30 mins and 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 and 48 hours post dose

Multidose (Part C):  At 15 and 30 mins and 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12 and 24 hours post dose 1, pre dose 2 and 7, and 24 hours post dose 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Part C only:  urinary ACR and eGFR measured by CKD-EPI equation in patients with diabetic nephropathy
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 1, Days 7 - 14 inclusive, and Day 21</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy volunteers (Part A, Part B, Part C):
- Male aged 18 to 45 years old inclusive
- Good general health without clinically significant medical history
- Body mass index &lt; 30

Patients (Part C):
- males aged 18 to 70 years old inclusive
- have Diabetes Mellitus Type 2
- have overt albuminuria
- have eGFR &gt;/= 30 and &lt; / = 60 mL/min
- currently taking either an ACEi or an ARB at a stable dose.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Healthy volunteers (Part A, Part B, Part C):
- Have received any investigational research agent within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose, or an investigational vaccine within 6 months, a live attenuated vaccine within 60 days or a registered vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of the Investigational Product.
- Have a history of thyroidectomy or thyroid disease that required medication within the past 12 months.
- Have had serious angioedema episodes within the previous 3 years or requiring angioedema medication in the previous two years.
- Have a bleeding disorder diagnosed by a doctor (e.g. factor deficiency, coagulopathy, or platelet disorder requiring special precautions) or significant bruising or bleeding difficulties with blood draws.
- Have any clinically significant abnormality at Screening (determined by medical history, physical examination, blood chemistry, haematology, urinalysis and a 12-lead ECG, or positive urine screen for drugs of abuse), a psychiatric condition that precludes compliance with the protocol, or any other condition which in the view of the Investigator is likely to interfere with the study or put the subject at risk.
- Have a history of or current clinically significant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, cardiovascular, respiratory, endocrine, oncological, immunodeficiency, neurological, metabolic, haematological or autoimmune disorder; or a history of or current tuberculosis, epilepsy, diabetes or glaucoma

Patients (Part C):
- Have a history of untreated or uncontrolled proliferative or pre-proliferative diabetic retinopathy
- Have evidence of hepatic dysfunction, HbA1c &gt; 11.0%, serum potassium &gt; 6 mmol/L.
- Have untreated urinary tract infection or other medical conditions that impact urinary protein values
- Have unstable angina pectoris or New York Heart Association Class III or IV congestive heart failure.
- Have a history of any major medical condition or any condition which in the view of the Investigator is likely to interfere with the study or put the subject at risk.
- Have any risk of bleeding
- Use of anticoagulant drugs including warfarin or heparin, low molecular weight heparin, danaparoid, hirudin, or others.
- Have other specific renal conditions known to be the cause of renal disease, and patients with other specific, clinically significant renal disease.
- Have a history of or current clinically significant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, cardiovascular, respiratory, endocrine, oncological, immunodeficiency, neurological, metabolic, haematological or autoimmune disorder; or a history of or current tuberculosis, epilepsy, diabetes or glaucoma.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>As this is the first time FT011 has been administered to humans, no formal samples size calculations have been performed, and statistics will be descriptive.  However, the number of subjects planned for dosing is usual for this stage of development and is adequate to provide information for further development and future studies.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fibrotech Therapeutics Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 9, 278 Collins St
Melbourne
Victoria 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fibrotech Therapeutics Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 9, 278 Collins St
Melbourne
Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will assess the safety and PK of the oral drug FT011 in healthy volunteers and in a small number of patients with diabetic nephropathy due to type 2 diabetes mellitus.  

Results from this study will help determine the development of FT011 as a treatment for diabetic nephropathy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne
Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
Level 5
Burnet Building
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8906</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ann Hamer</name>
      <address>Fibrotech Therapeutics Pty Ltd
Level 9, 278 Collins St
Melbourne
Victoria 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9657 0705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahamer@fibrotech.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ann Hamer</name>
      <address>Fibrotech Therapeutics Pty Ltd
Level 9, 278 Collins St
Melbourne
Victoria 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9657 0705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahamer@fibrotech.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>