<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371000">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001178437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Platelet Parameters in Behcet's Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Platelet Parameters in Ocular Behcet's Disease With Posterior Segment Involvement </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-8290</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Ocular BD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Behcet disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Blood sampled will be collected in patients with inactive and active stage of Behcet disease. Patients with active disease will be treated with conventional therapy. Duration of observation is 1 month.</interventions>
    <comparator>healthy adult subjects serving as controls with no history of systemic or ocular disease. Blood samples are collected once in these participants.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>At least 25 ocular BD patients with posterior segment involvement in the active period. 
Mean platelet volume count will be assessed using serum samples.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post enrolment. Serum samples collected in active BD patients at 1 month.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>platelet distribution width count will be assessed using serum samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post enrolment. Serum samples collected in active BD patients at 1 month.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Platelletcrit count will be assessed using serum samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post enrolment. Serum samples collected in active BD patients at 1 month.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We included the active ocular Behcets disease (BD) patients with posterior segment involvement.. The diagnosis of BD will reached according to the criteria of the International Study Group for Behcets Disease. Subjects with at least 2 months of lesion-free period were regarded in the inactive disease period, and subjects with any oral, skin, and/or genital lesions will regarded as in the active disease period. Patients and healthy volunteers that were matched for age and gender included in this study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients and healthy volunteers who were on any kind of medication including corticosteroid and immunosuppressive therapy, who had smoking (smoke more than 1 cigarette per day) and drinking ( &gt;1 standard drink per week) habits, or who had history of systemic and ocular disease will not included in the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>We require about at least 25 participants per three groups (Active, inactive, control). Differences among the three groups for thrombophilic parameters will evaluated using one-way ANOVA analysis, where applicable. Bonferroni test will used as post hoc test after one-way ANOVA. The level of significance was set at &lt;0.05. 

For a study power of 80%, we determined 25 subjects will enough to test all parameters. The power of the test is pathfinder to know the probability that the test will give the right result when there is a real effect. The power of the significance test is the same thing as the sensitivity of a screening test. The effect size was 0.5. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>1</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Turkey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>SB Ankara Ulucanlar Eye Education and Research Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ulucanlar Cad. No: 59 06230 ALTINDAG/ANKARA/TURKEY </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ankara Ulucanlar Eye Education and research hospital. </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ulucanlar cd. no:59 06230 Altindag/Ankara/Turkey</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose: To search platelet activation via detecting three important platelet activation parameters; Mean Platelet Volume (MPV), Platelet Distribution Width (PDW), and Plateletcrit (PCT) in patients with ocular Behcet's disease (BD) in comparison to those in healthy adults as controls.
Design: A prospective case control study
Participants and Controls: Twenty-five patients within the active period of the ocular BD with posterior segment involvement (Group 1), 25 patients within the inactive period of the ocular BD with posterior segment involvement (Group 2) and 25 age-and sex-matched healthy controls will included into the study (Group 3).
Methods: All patients and control subjects will undergo complete ophthalmologic evaluation. MPV, PDW, and PCT will measure in the studied groups.
Main Outcome Measures: Alterations in platelet activation parameters.
Results: The mean level of MPV value in Group 1, in Group 2, and in Group 3 will determined. Mean serum level of PDW in three groups will determined. Mean serum PCT value in Group 1, in Group 2, and in Group 3 will determined. MPV, PDW, and PCT levels can be significantly altered in ocular BD patients.
Conclusion: Platelet activation reflected by MPV, PDW, and PCT may have an impact on the genesis of vessel occlusion in ocular BD with posterior segment involvement. The results may be important for the clinical management of patients with ocular BD in everyday clinical practice since those platelet parameters are routinely detected in complete blood count analyses.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ankara Numune Training and Research Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hacettepe, Talatpasa Blv No:44, Altindag/Ankara</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>181175</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mehmet CITIRIK</name>
      <address>SB Ankara Ulucanlar Eye Education and Research Hospital. 
Ulucanlar Cad. No: 59 06230 ALTINDAG/ANKARA/TURKEY </address>
      <phone>+903123126261</phone>
      <fax>+903123124827</fax>
      <email>mcitirik@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ali Keles</name>
      <address>SB Ankara Ulucanlar Eye Education and Research Hospital. 
Ulucanlar Cad. No: 59 06230 ALTINDAG/ANKARA/TURKEY </address>
      <phone>+903123126261</phone>
      <fax>+903123124827</fax>
      <email>kelesali2706@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mehmet CITIRIK</name>
      <address>SB Ankara Ulucanlar Eye Education and Research Hospital. 
Ulucanlar Cad. No: 59 06230 ALTINDAG/ANKARA/TURKEY </address>
      <phone>+903123126261</phone>
      <fax>+903123124827</fax>
      <email>mcitirik@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>