<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347742">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000049875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Insomnia 100 sleep study: Profiling of Insomnia disorder in a sample of 100 participants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Profiling of Insomnia disorder in a sample of 100 participants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1125-9767</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Insomnia Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study consists of two visits to the Woolcock institute. One for screening / consent lasting an hour where the participants will be given an actiwatch and sleep diary to complete for two weeks. After this period, the participant will attend an overnight routine sleep assessment again at the Woolcock institute this will last no longer than 12 hours. After this the study will end. Actiwatch and Diaries. The actiwatch looks like a conventional wrist watch and is used to objectively assess sleep and wake activity, while the diaries contain questions relating to sleep quality, subjective sleepiness and drug accountability. Both are to be used by the patient at home for one week prior to the routine overnight visit. Questionnaires. These will be used at each visit to assess subjective sleepiness, quality of sleep, quality of life, depression and investigators overall impression of the status of the patient. These will take approximately 45 min to complete. Routine Diagnostic Polysomnographic Sleep Study. The patient will spend a night in the sleep laboratory at the Woolcock Institute for Medical Research for a routine diagnostic sleep study. This will determine the status of their sleep in general and if they suffer from any potential comorbid conditions. A small amount of blood will be taken as well to check liver function and a full blood count. This will take twelve hours. Neurocognitive test battery. A computer based battery of tests will be administered during the routine overnight sleep study. This will consist of short tests assessing attention &amp; cognitive function. All together, these tests will take approximately one hour. After the study, participants with insomnia will be offered to complete a course in cognitive behavioural therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) as a thank you for completing the study. They will have the choice of internet based CBT-I with six online sessions to address worries and anxieties about sleeping, relaxation techniques, sleep hygiene procedures, and sleep scheduling involving stimulus control and sleep restriction therapy. Each session will take approximately an hour to complete over six weeks. The website is completely interactive and moderated by a team of psychologists. Alternatively, participants may enroll into a insomnia CBT-I workshop with a psychologist that also involves 5 hour long sessions (1 hour per session over 10 weeks) to address worries and anxieties about sleeping, relaxation techniques, sleep hygiene procedures, and sleep scheduling involving stimulus control and sleep restriction therapy for insomnia. At the end of both interventions, participants will have their insomnia severity index score re-examined.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparison will be made within different subtypes of insomnia disorder sufferers (sleep onset insomnia, sleep maintenance insomnia, early morning awakenings insomnia, and mixed insomnia).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to determine whether there are observable physiological and neurocognitive differences within different subtypes of insomnia disorder sufferers (sleep onset insomnia, sleep maintenance insomnia, early morning awakenings insomnia, and mixed insomnia).</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 12 hour overnight sleep assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate potential correlations between questionnaire response data and overnight sleep study results with regards to insomnia sub-type. Allowing us to further understand the differences within subtypes of insomnia disorder.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 12 hour overnight sleep assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Predictors of treatment success: we will evaluate which subtypes of insomnia respond best to treatment by correlating their treatment outcome with their insomnia subtype.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Symptoms of Insomnia Disorder as diagnosed by the Diagnostic and
Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition criteria for insomnia
disorder (APA, 2013) specifically: Difficulty initiating or maintaining sleep or
waking up too early for at least 3 nights per week, for at least 3 months,
with adequate opportunity and circumstances for sleep
2. Stable sleep/wake schedule with no shift work
3. Able to give informed, written consent
4. Fluent speaker of English
5. Referred by a sleep physician to have a routine sleep study as part of Medicare</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Active illicit substance use or alcohol dependence
2. Psychiatric disorders, other than mild to moderate depression (on the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales)
3. Previous history of depressive episode
4. Sleep disorders (other than insomnia) 
5. Learning disabilities 
6. Dementia 
7. Neurological problems
8. Pregnancy or lactation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/02/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CIRUS 
PO BOX M77
Missenden Rd
Sydney
2050 NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>CIRUS 
PO BOX M77
Missenden Rd
Sydney
2050 NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To discover and profile the biological mechanisms within Insomnia. This will be achieved by sampling a large number of sufferers and examining them overnight through a clinical sleep study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Delwyn Bartlett</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe
Sydney
NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0460</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>delwyn.bartlett@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Miller</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe
Sydney
NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 (2) 9114 0411</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>chris.miller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christopher Miller</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe
Sydney
NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 (2) 9114 0411</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>chris.miller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Miller</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
PO Box M77, Missenden Road, NSW, 2050
Camperdown</address>
      <phone>+61291140411</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chris.miller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>