<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363795">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000259741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Outcomes of patients with paediatric onset Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) following transition into adult care what do we know?
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with paediatric onset Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) who have transitioned to adult care, what are their health outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study aims to identify the physical and psychosocial outcomes of patients with paediatric onset IBD who have transitioned to adult care, which may have been adversely influenced by their transition process. We aim to identify these outcomes and patient perspectives of the process through a questionnaire.

The questionnaire will be given once during the observational period and will look at their IBD from the time of diagnosis until the date of the questionnaire (All patients included - maximum 10years). The questionnaire does not have a specific name. The entire study will run for 1 year. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control - group of patients diagnosed with IBD as an adult who have not undergone the transition process. This control group will not be given a questionnaire. Data regarding their health outcomes has previously been collected.
Source of data - Medical records data for suitable patients 2002-2012</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health outcomes of patients with paediatric onset IBD who have transitioned to adult care. Health outcomes will be obtained through the questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients surveyed have to have transitioned to adult care. This is a once off survey and consequently this outcome will be assessed as soon as the patient has consented to participate.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient perspectives on the transition process - through the questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This is a once off survey and consequently this outcome will be assessed as soon as the patient has consented to participate.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>&gt;18years of age
Diagnosis of IBD in paediatric years
Has to have transitioned to adult care</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>28</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age&lt;17years</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Enrolling by invitation</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Womens and Childrens Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>SA Department of Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Citi Centre Building, 11 Hindmarsh Square, Adelaide SA 5000  
Postal Address:  PO Box 287, Rundle Mall, Adelaide SA 5000  
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Abbott</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>32-34 Lord St
Botany, NSW 2019
Locked Bag 5016
Botany, NSW 1455
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite multiple studies reporting outcomes separately in both adult and paediatric cohorts and existing literature about transition care, little data has been published regarding the outcomes of patients with paediatric onset Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) in the years after they have entered adult care. This is important as major changes in transition practices are currently being recommended without knowing what is actually happening to this group of IBD patients and what is needed. 

This study aims to identify the physical and psychosocial outcomes of this cohort, which may have been adversely influenced by their transition process, in addition to patient perspectives of the process. 

The project will achieve its aims by using a database from the Womens and Childrens Hospital which contains a list of patients with paediatric onset IBD that have since transitioned into adult care (defined as having turned 18 at the time of interrogating the database). Participants will be contacted and invited to participate in a survey which will collect data regarding basic demographic information, IBD-associated health outcomes, transition experiences and perceived positives and negatives from the transition process. Health outcomes of this population will then be compared to both local and published data of adult onset IBD patients of similar disease duration. Current guidelines of management of IBD in this cohort will also be compared to the study group. 

From this information, obstacles to optimal transition will be highlighted, and patients views obtained. These data will be vital to guide the successful development of new and improved transition programs which optimise patient care. This has the potential to improve disease-specific and psychological outcomes for these patients and thus also reduce the direct and indirect economic burden in this cohort.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WCHN Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide
SA
5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REC 2518/11/2015 LNR-HREC/12/WCHN/95</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Level 7
Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 4 288 30 979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alice.bennett@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Level 7
Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5207</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alice.bennett@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Level 7
Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5207</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alice.bennett@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Level 7
Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>