<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373755">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001407381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparative assessment of the absorption of a test formulation of 1 x 30 mg isotretinoin capsule against the innovator 1 x 30 mg isotretinoin capsules conducted under fasting conditions in healthy male volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single dose, randomized, open-label, pharmacokinetic study of a test formulation of 1 x 30 mg isotretinoin capsule in a 2 way crossover comparison against the innovator 1 x 30 mg isotretinoin capsules conducted under fasting conditions in healthy male volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1201-4598</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Isotretinoin is a medicine that is used to treat severe forms of acne.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single dose, crossover study design whereby each participant receives the test formulation of isotretinoin, 1 x 30 mg capsule on one occasion and the innovator formulation of isotretinoin, 1 x 30 mg capsules on one occasion with each dose separated by a two week washout period. The intervention for this trial is the test formulation of isotretinoin.

No water is allowed for 1 hour prior to dosing until 1 hour after dosing (except for the water consumed with each dose).

Participants are required not to eat for 10 hours before dosing and to fast for approximately 4 hours after each dose.

Bathroom visits will be supervised to ensure no unauthorized water or food intake and for personal safety. 

Participants will be confined at the Clinical Site for 12 hours prior to dosing to ensure compliance and for 24 hours after dosing.

Participants will be monitored for adverse events throughout the study.

Standard meals will be consumed at the Clinical Site with no additional food intake allowed. Alcohol breath testing will be performed upon each participant reporting to the Clinical Site 12 hours prior to dosing.

Pre and post study laboratory tests will be completed to assess the health of the participants along with HIV, Hepatitis and drugs of abuse testing.

Each dose will be taken orally with 240 ml of water at ambient temperature. Medication must be swallowed whole and a mouth check will be conducted to ensure that the medication has been taken as directed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Single dose, crossover study whereby each participant receives the test formulation of isotretinoin (1 x 30 mg) on one occasion and the innovator formulation of isotretinoin (1 x 30 mg) on one occasion with each dose separated by a two week washout period. The comparator/control for this trial is the innovator formulation of isotretinoin.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacokinetics (as summarised by Cmax and AUC) of the test formulation relative to that of the reference formulation. All plasma samples will be assayed for isotretinoin using one fully validated LC/MS/MS method. Validation will be conducted to comply with FDA guidelines.</outcome>
      <timepoint> -10, -2, 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 4.5, 5, 5.5, 6, 6.5, 7, 8, 10, 12, 16, 20, 24, 36, 48, 60 and 72 hours post dosing. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to maximum peak concentration (Tmax) will be determined by plasma sample analysis. Tmax will be the time where the maximum concentration occurred in the sample points.</outcome>
      <timepoint> -10, -2, 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 4.5, 5, 5.5, 6, 6.5, 7, 8, 10, 12, 16, 20, 24, 36, 48, 60 and 72 hours post dosing. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy males
Aged between 18 and 55 years
Non-smoker
BMI greater than or equal to 18.5 and less than 30 inclusive
Normal, healthy individuals as determined by medical history, physical examination, ECG, blood pressure and laboratory tests
Drug free as determined by urine drug testing
Able to comply with the study restrictions
Able to provide written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Females
History of recent recurrent attacks of bronchitis, asthma or migraine headaches
Concomitant drug therapy of any kind
Received an investigational compound or drug known to induce or inhibit liver enzymes within 60 days of the start of the study
History of depression or other mental illness, or a history of epilepsy or seizures
History of conditions that might interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism or excretion of the drug
History of alcohol or drug abuse or dependency
Sensitivities to Vitamin A or food such as liver
Participation in a drug study within 60 days of the start of the study or undertaking to donate blood within 60 days after the completion of the study
Sensitivities to isotretinoin, its excipients or any other retinoids
Contact lens wearers and individuals who have very fair skin and a strong propensity to sunburn
Individuals for whom the Clinical Investigator believes, for any reason, that participation would not be an acceptable risk</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All formulations will be labeled as Formulation A and B. The identification of each treatment will only be known to the Managing Director and Section Head - Trials and Regulatory Affairs or their delegate. </concealment>
    <sequence>Each participant will be identified by a 3 digit screening number and a 2 digit subject number. The screening number will be issued once the participant has given written consent to participate in the study and the two digit study number (randomisation number) after acceptance into the study. Randomization will be performed using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerized sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/10/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>0</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zenith Technology Corp Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 1777
Dunedin 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Douglas Pharmaceuticals Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Central Park Drive
PO Box 45-027
Auckland 0610</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this study is to evaluate the bioequivalence of the test (new) formulation of 30 mg isotretinoin capsule relative to that of the reference formulation (innovator brand of 30 mg isotreinoin capsule) following oral administration of a single dose of 30 mg in healthy male subjects under fasting conditions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
1 the Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/STH/166</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Noelyn Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corp Ltd
PO Box 1777,
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64345779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>noelyn.hung@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Linda Folland</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corp Ltd
PO Box 1777,
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>linda.folland@zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tak Hung</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corp Ltd
PO Box 1777,
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434779669</phone>
      <fax>+6434779605</fax>
      <email>tak.hung@zenithtechnoloy.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>