<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365001">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001189718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Investigation of the Extended Range of Vision (ERV) Intraocular Lenses (IOLs), Model XRA03 and Toric Series ZXT in Participants Requiring Bilateral Cataract Removal and Lens Replacement.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, Non-randomized, Multicenter, Parallel group (55-75 subjects) Clinical Investigation of Extended Range of Vision (ERV) Intraocular Lenses, XRA03 and Toric series ZXT on Best-Corrected Distance Visual Acuity in Participants Requiring Bilateral Cataract Removal and Lens Replacement Sequentially In Both Eyes 
. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>UTN1111-1148-5637</utrn>
    <trialacronym> EROV-107-ZXRT

</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bilateral Cataract  removal and replacment of crystalline lens  with an investigational extended range of vision IOL, in otherwise healthy eyes </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Investigational Toric ERV Intraocular lens (IOL).  This model series ZXT is a modification from the currently marketed Tecnis Toric IOL with the same toric options in a range of 1.50 D  4.00 D.  The spherical diffractive posterior surface of the Toric lens optic has been designed to provide an increased range of vision (far, intermediate and near) and a reduction in residual refractive cylinder. The eye will be marked preoperatively for a standard axis orientation for toric lens placement, the cataractous lens will be removed during a routine phacoemulsification procedure lasting approximately 30 mins, and the toric lens will be implanted using the preoperative marks as guidelines. Once implanted using an Abbott lens inserter/unfolder, the design benefits of the lens are intended to be permanent.</interventions>
    <comparator>Investigational non-toric ERV IOL, Model XRA03. In this model  a modification from the currently marketed multi-focal lens, the spherical diffractive posterior surface of the lens optic has been designed to provide an increased range of vision (far, intermediate and near) and to partially correct for chromatic aberrations. The cataractous lens will be removed by routine phacoemulsification procedure lasting approximately 30 mins. Once implanted  using an Abbott lens inserter/unfolder, the design benefits of the lens are intended to be permanent.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular, photopic, best-corrected distance visual acuity at six months for the ERV model series ZXT IOL compared to that for the ERV model XRA03.
Subjects will be tested monocularly per standardized visual acuity methods using ETDRS eye charts situated at a specific distance under controlled lighting conditions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular , photopic, distance-corrected intermediate visual acuity at 66 cm for the ERV series ZXT IOLs compared to that for the XRA03 lens.

Subjects will be tested monocularly per standardized visual acuity methods using ETDRS eye charts situated at a intermediate distance (66cm) under controlled lighting conditions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular, photopic, uncorrected distance visual acuity for the ERV series ZXT IOLs compared to that for the XRA03 lens.

Subjects will be tested monocularly per standardized visual acuity methods using ETDRS eye charts situated at a distance under controlled lighting conditions .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> A unique Sponsor-developed questionnaire for this study addressing spectacle independence and subject satisfaction (including dysphotopsia) will be completed by participants. (descriptive purposes only)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Bilateral cataracts for which phacoemulsification extraction and posterior chamber IOL implantation are planned
2. Visual potential of 6/7.5 Metric (20/25 Snellen) or better in each eye following cataract removal and IOL implantation
3. Clear intraocular media other than cataract in each eye
4. Normal corneal topography

5. Subjects for ERV Model Series ZXT only:
5.1 Preoperative corneal cylinder between 0.75 D and 3.62 D in both eyes and an AMO Toric calculation lens model recommendation of a ZCT lens equal to the study lens powers of ZXT150, ZXT225, ZXT300, or ZXT375, with a predicted spherical equivalent outcome of emmetropia (+/-0.25 D). 
 </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pupil abnormalities (non-reactive, fixed pupils, or abnormally shaped pupils) 
2. Recent ocular trauma or ocular surgery that is not resolved/stable or may affect visual outcomes or increase risk to the subject
3. Prior corneal refractive (LASIK, LASEK, RK, PRK, etc.) or intraocular surgery
4.Corneal abnormalities such as stromal, epithelial or endothelial dystrophies that are predicted to cause visual acuity losses 
5. Use of systemic or ocular medications that may affect vision
6. No irregular corneal astigmatism.
7. Poorly-controlled diabetes
8. Subjects with conditions associated with increased risk of zonular rupture, including capsular or zonular abnormalities that may lead to IOL decentration or tilt, such as pseudoexfoliation, trauma, or posterior capsule defects</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolment via recommendation by PI/CI surgeons based on pre surgery assessment of subject against the acceptance critieria after informed consent given. Detailed information of the potential risks and benefits to participation in this clinical study is discussed with each subject as detailed on the informed consent form. Allocation of a toric or non-toric ERV lens will depend on subject's preoperative biometry and astigmatism.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non-randomized</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the Primary (BCDVA) and Secondary Endpoints (DCIVA, UCDVA), there is more than a 89% power for equivalence testing to detect a difference in mean visual acuity between IOL groups (assume no difference in groups, standard deviation of 1.2 lines, equivalence margin of 1 line, and a two-sided significance level of 0.05) with 40 subjects in the Toric Study Lens group and 25 subjects in the Study Lens group.
For the Other endpoints, descriptive statistics including mean, standard deviation, minimum and maximum values will be reported for continuous variables.  The frequency and proportion will be reported for categorical variables.

BCDVA=   Best-corrected distance visual acuity
DCIVA =  Distance-corrected intermediate visual acuity
UCDVA=  Uncorrected distance visual acuity</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>14/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>10/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>74</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Abbott Medical Optics Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1700 East Saint Andrew Place
Santa Ana,
California 92705
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Abbott Medical Optics Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1700 East Saint Andrew Place
Santa Ana,
California 92705
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study objective is to evaluate the clinical outcomes of far, intermediate and near visual acuity and the rates of complications and adverse events in subjects implanted with the ERV Model XRA03 IOL and the ERV Toric IOL, Model Series ZXT. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disability Ehtics Committee (HDEC) New Zealand </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/- MEDSAFE, Lvl 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington 
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dean Corbett BSc MBChB, FRANZCO</name>
      <address>Auckland Eye 
8  St Mark's Road
Remuera
1050 Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 529 24780</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 529 24781</fax>
      <email>dlcorbett@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dean Corbett BSc MBChB, FRANZCO</name>
      <address>Auckland Eye 
8  St Mark's Road
Remuera
1050 Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 529 24780</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 529 24781</fax>
      <email>dlcorbett@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anne Buteyn</name>
      <address>Abbott Medical Optics Inc.
543 Ohio Ave
Oostburg, WI 53070
</address>
      <phone>+1 949-505-2029</phone>
      <fax>+1 714-247-4610</fax>
      <email>Anne.Buteyn@amo.abbott.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dale Lambert</name>
      <address>Abbott Medical Optics (AMO) Australia
299 Lane Cove Road 
Macquarie Park 2113
Sydney NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9855 0120</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9855 0190</fax>
      <email>dale.lambert@abbott.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>