<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372268">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000277347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Non-inferiority randomised controlled trial comparing wound healing with compression therapy to electric stimulation therapy (Wound ELECT Trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multi site randomised controlled trial comparing clinical effectiveness of electric stimulation therapy compared to or in combination with compression therapy in wound healing of chronic lower leg ulcers (Wound ELECT Trial)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Wound ELECT Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic venous, lymphoedema and mixed venous/lymphoedema ulcers</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lower leg oedema</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An electric stimulation therapyBodyflow (Trademark) Therapyinvolves the application of electrodes to the limb which delivers a mild transdermal electrical stimulus targeting stimulation of smooth muscle (Tunica media) to promote the stimulation of arterial, venous and lymphatic systems. 
Participants will be randomly allocated to one of three treatment groups in total n = 208 participants will be required.
1 Compression therapy (control) n=69
2 Electric Stimulation Therapy (with no compression therapy) n=69
3 Electric Stimulation Therapy and compression therapy n=69
The Bodyflow (Trademark) Electric Stimulation Device is a small portable device suitable for self-administration in the home setting. Recruits to the Bodyflow group will be given a demonstration on the use of Bodyflow by the clinician on recruitment including the placement of the electrodes, management of the battery powered unit. Written instruction are also given to the recruits to reinforce the instructions on the operation of the device. For recruits in the compression and electrical stimulation group, compression is not removed during treatment.
Guidelines for utilising the Bodyflow (Trademark) Therapy is four times daily for 20 minute sessions over 14 weeks, implemented by the participant or an informal carer in the home environment. Electrodes are attached to the lower limb around the wound (not directly over it) or above or below compression therapy if institu. The device is pre-set to a single, non-adjustable specific low frequency found between one and two Hertz, a current that specifically targets smooth muscle. Use of the device can create a pulsing or tingling sensation. There are no reported serious adverse events anticipated from the use of the Bodyflow (Trademark) Therapy.
Adherence to treatment in the Bodyflow group will be automatically logged by the machine. Continuing and ongoing data collection tools will be completed on each assessment visit and subsequent 2 week visit, 6 week visit, 10 week visit and 14 week visit.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care of compression therapy will be provided to study participants as per sections 1 and 2 of the Flow Chart for the Management of Venous Leg Ulcers (Australian and New Zealand clinical practice guideline for prevention and management of venous leg ulcer) or as outlined by the  Best Practice for the Management of Lymphoedema: International Consensus. All care will be provided by registered healthcare professionals with specialist skills in wound care. Participants randomised to the compression therapy group will be encouraged to use the highest compression possible.  Participants will be encouraged to use their compression therapy either 24/7 or from waking in the morning to going to bed at night. Financial support to encourage participants to purchase new compression stockings or to increase their level of compression bandaging will be provided. The study will require n=208 in total (69 per study group). To accommodate a 10% attrition of study participants the study will recruit a sample of n=76 per study group: N=228 overall.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Healed Study wound defined as 100% epithelization/wound closure .
Wound will be traced and measured using  ImageJ is a public domain electronic  Java image processing and analysis program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From screening and recruitment recruits will be monitored at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 10 weeks and 14 weeks. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1
Wound healing algorithms to assess- Percentage of area change (PAC) for the study wound.  (determined from wound planimetry methods and corroborated by digital image planimetry.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From screening and recruitment recruits will be monitored at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 10 weeks and 14 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2 
Limb measurements recorded by measuring the leg in centimetres from  smallest ankle measure to the  widest calf measure and the big toe distal to web space. </outcome>
      <timepoint>From screening and recruitment recruits will be monitored at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 10 weeks and 14 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3
Adherence to four daily (20 minute) treatments with Electric Stimulation Therapy as automatically recorded by the device during use. Self-reported adherence will be further recorded by participants in a log stored with the Electric Stimulation Therapy device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From screening and recruitment recruits will be monitored at 2 weeks, 6 weeks, 10 weeks and 14 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4
Indicative cost indicators will be measured over the duration of the recruits participation in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over all costs will be assessed by number of clinic visits/home visits, duration of visits, wound dressing products used over the 14 weeks the recruit is enrolled in the trail.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*A person is eligible if they are over 18 years and have a leg ulcer with a confirmed diagnosis of venous, lymphodema or venous/lymphodema ulcer.
*A person is appropriate for best practice treatment (compression therapy).
*The person or carer /guardian is able to provide informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Person is unable to or does not have an informal carer/support person able to physically implement the Electric Stimulation Therapy
*Person has an an existing diagnosis of Deep Vein Thrombosis (DVT)
*Person has an implanted cardiac device such as a permanent pace-maker or internal defibrillator.
*Pregnant women
*Person with a diagnosis of an active malignant disease
*Person with a known reaction to adhesives
*Person who is assessed by the attending clinician to be at risk of skin tears upon removal of the adhesive pads as part of the electric stimulation device due to fragile skin.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be provided by a centralised, remote randomisation system (online) once written consent has been obtained. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation lists will be generated using a random number function in Microsoft excel.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The trial includes three groups:
Compression therapy and no electric stimulation therapy
Electric stimulation therapy and no compression therapy
Compression therapy and electric stimulation therapy</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>7/08/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>228</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>7/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,TAS,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3021 - St Albans</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Dublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>La Trobe University
Address	Bundoora, Corner Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive, Victoria, Australia. 3083
Country	Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bodyflow International Pty, Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 1 297 Ingles Street
Port Melbourne VIC 3207</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The trial will consider the clinical effectiveness of electrical stimulation therapy compared to or in combination with compression therapy. People with a lower leg ulcers will be recruited into the study. Participates will be randomised to either (1) continue their current compression therapy (control). (2) to use electronic stimulation therapy (intervention) or (3) use both compression therapy and electric stimulation. Participants in the study group involving electrical stimulation therapy will use a portable stimulation device that can be self administered in the home setting 4 times a day daily for 20 minutes per session. The number of wounds that heal and the percentage of wound size change will be monitored for 14 weeks in total. Fortnightly for the first follow up visit and then monthly. The clinical effectiveness of the treatments will be considered as will cost effectiveness. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Road, Prahran, VIC 3181
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>501/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>William McGinuess</name>
      <address>La Trobe University
Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Prahran VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 94796748</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9533 2104</fax>
      <email>w.mcguiness@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Charne Miller</name>
      <address>La Trobe University
Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Prahran VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9476 5090</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9533 2104</fax>
      <email>c.miller@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Charne Miller</name>
      <address>La Trobe university
Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Prahran VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9476 5090</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9533 2104</fax>
      <email>c.miller@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Charne Miller</name>
      <address>Level 4, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Prahran VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9476 5090</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9533 2104</fax>
      <email>c.miller@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>