<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363235">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001171808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intervention Whyalla: Workplace health promotion for improving metabolic health and health awareness</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of health promotion strategies targeting physical activity, diet, sleep and smoking  in a regional Australian mining and steelmaking company on waist girth and glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) trajectories: a multiple baseline interrupted time-series study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-6167</utrn>
    <trialacronym>iWhyalla</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Abdominal obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiometabolic disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a multi-strategy intervention. Firstly, type 2 diabetes screening using HbA1c measured at point-of-care with immediate referral to general practitioners when HbA1c is 6.5% (48 mmol/mol) or greater. Secondly, Health promotion strategies delivered by peer champions (trained co-workers) to work units during normal weekly worktime meetings (2hr/week over 8 weeks). The strategies include education practical skill development; flexible goal setting; action planning and self-monitoring (attending to theoretical constructs of behaviour: knowledge; intentions, attitudes, subjective norms, perceived efficacy (Theory of Planned Behaviour);  perceived susceptibility, perceived severity, perceived benefits, perceived barriers (Health Belief Model); collective efficacy (Social Learning Theory). Behaviours focussed on are in the causal pathway to abdominal obesity, type 2 diabetes and diabetic control: physical inactivity, low fruit and vegetable consumption, high sugar sweeted beverage consumption, high alcohol consumption, short sleep and smoking.
Peer champions will be trained by an chronic disease self-management Trainer-trainer accredited in both Stanford and Flinders models. The recruitment and training of peer champions is a key component of readiness to adopt the intervention within a workgroup.
Thirdly, during the health promotion eduction and in response to process and outcomes data collected during the study, workplace environmental intervention strategies will be developed.
Although the overall duration of this intervention is not set, as the timing of adoption is not prescribed, we expect to run this study initially for 20 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator of work units who have adopted the intervention are the work units who have not yet adopted the intervention (but who would intend to once ready); similar to having multiple 'waitlist control' groups in a clinical trial. This study is a multiple baseline time-series design, so intervention groups (work units) are feely allowed to adopt the intervention as they become ready Assuming the classic Rogers theory of innovation adoption is upheld, adoption of the intervention by work groups will occur progressively across the organisation. Rather than collection of two waves of data (pre/post) as is typical in conventional randomised community trial designs, outcomes data are collected multiple times on the same schedule across all groups before, during and after the intervention. The resulting time series will be tested for changes in trends associated with the timing, nature and intensity of intervention strategies within each group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean HbA1c (% and mmol/mol) as measured at 'point-of-care' using the DCA Vantage (Siemens Healthcare Diagnostics, Deerfield, IL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 4 to 6 months over 20 months determined based on resource availability and organisational requirements.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean waist girth as measured according to International Society for the Advancement of Kinanthropometry (ISAK) standards, using Lufkin W606PM steel girth tapes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 4 to 6 months over 20 months determined based on resource availability and organisational requirements.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diabetes incidence as assessed by self reported new diagnoses of type 2 diabetes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure (systolic and diastolic) ans measured by automated sphygmomanometry (model HEM-7221, Omron Healthcare, Kyoto, Japan)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 4 to 6 months over 20 months determined based on resource availability and organisational requirements.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Steps per day as measured by pedomter-accelerometer (GSensor model GS2026)</outcome>
      <timepoint>daily over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity (total; leisure time; dometsic and gardening (yard); work-related; transport-related) as measured by the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occupational activity domains (sitting; standing; walking; sleeping/napping heavy labour/physically demanding tasks) as measured in minutes per week using a modified version of the Occpational Sitting and Physical Activity Questionnaire (Chau et al. 2012. Med. Sci. Sports Exerc.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep duration (hours) as measured by the Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daytime dysfunction as measured by the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fruit and vegetable consumptions as measured by self reported number of serves per day using standard serving size prompts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Avergage alcohol consumption (grams/day) as measured by a set of alcoholic beverage consumption questions modified from the Cancer Council of Victoria Dietary Questionnaire (Version 3.1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average sugar sweetened beverage consumption (kj of carbohydrate from beverages) as measured by a set of beverage consumption questions modified from the Cancer Council of Victoria Dietary Questionnaire (Version 3.1)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking cessation as measured by the question: Are you currently a smoker?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>habitual smoking reduction as measure by the question: how many cigarettes in a day do you now smoke? (from the Fagerstrom Test for nictine Dependence).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 months over 20 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Workplace incident rate as determined through routine organisational reporting procedures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quarterly from 2004 to 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Workplace injury rate as determined through routine organisational reporting procedures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quarterly from 2004 to 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Workplace health-related abstenteeism rate as determined through routine organisational reporting procedures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quarterly from 2004 to 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Employees of Onesteel Whyalla Steelworks and Arrium Mining in Whyalla, South Australia and surrounding mining sites.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study is a multiple baseline interrupted time-series design. This includes parallel outcome monitoring but progressively adopted intervention over time accross the groups.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1800</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Government Department of Health and Ageing (University Department of Rural Health Program)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arrium Ltd (Onesteel Whyalla Steelworks &amp; Arrium Mining)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Port Augusta Road
Whyalla SA 5600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Onesteel Whyalla Steelworks/Arrium Mining</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Port Augusta Road
Whyalla SA 5600</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to prevent the current excess of abdominal obesity from translating into an excess of diabetes in the future. We aim to begin this objective through a workplace health promotion program in the major employer in the city as working age has been shown to be the most cost-effective period of the lifecourse for behavioural interventions in obesity. Through personal and environmentl strategies we aim to promote healthful trajectories in: (a) behaviour (physical activity, sleep, diet and smoking reduction); (b) waist girth and blood sugar; (c) diabetes detection and management; (d) workplace injuries and productivity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>29326</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matthew T Haren</name>
      <address>Social Epidemiology and Evaluation Research Group
School of Population Health
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83021827</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022603</fax>
      <email>Matt.Haren@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matthew T Haren</name>
      <address>Social Epidemiology and Evaluation Research Group
School of Population Health
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83021827</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022603</fax>
      <email>Matt.Haren@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Matthew T Haren</name>
      <address>Social Epidemiology and Evaluation Research Group
School of Population Health
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83021827</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022603</fax>
      <email>Matt.Haren@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>