<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343138">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000940976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomized, Controlled, Double-Blind Study of a Single Intra-Articular Injection of the less than 5,000 MW Fraction of Human Albumin 5% (Ampion-Trademark) in Adults with Osteoarthritis of the Knee</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, Controlled, Double-Blind Study of a Single Intra-Articular Injection of the less than 5,000 MW Fraction of Human Albumin 5% (Ampion-Trademark) in Adults with Osteoarthritis of the Knee for the Reduction of Pain</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1122-5164</utrn>
    <trialacronym>AIK</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis of the knee</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The eligible patient will be randomized to receive a single 10mL intra-articular injection into the study knee of one of the following treatment:

1. Ampion (Trademark) (4mL) combined with lignocaine (4mL)/betamethasone suspension (2mL) OR

2. Ampion(Trademark) (4mL), combined with betamethasone suspension (2mL) OR

3.Saline (4mL) placebo combined with lignocaine (4mL)/betamethasone (2mL) suspension

Treatment 1 has Ampion combined with both betamethsone and lignocaine, whereas Treatment 2 a combination of Ampion with betamethasone but without lignocaine.  Treatment 3, the Ampion is replaced with saline.</interventions>
    <comparator>Saline placebo combined with lignocaine/betamethasone suspension</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the reduction in pain in subjects with knee osteoarthritis of a single intra-articular knee injection of Ampion(TM) combined with lignocaine/betamethasone suspension with Ampion (TM) combined with betamethasone suspension combined or compared with a saline placebo combined with lignocaine/betamethsone suspension.


This outcome will be assessed by the Western Ontario McMaster University Osteoarthritis (WOMAC) Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single injection to study knee on Day 1 with clinical follow up over 72 hours.
Folllow up visits on Day 2 and Day 4.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess joint function and pain subjects by WOMAC index  following injection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single injection to study knee on Day 1 with clinical follow up over 72 hours.
Folllow up visits on Day 2 and Day 4.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the requirement for rescue medications in subjects with knee osteoarthritis following injection.

This outcome will be assessed by providing each patient with a diary card to record their medications.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single injection to study knee on Day 1 with clinical follow up over 72 hours.
Folllow up visits on Day 2 and Day 4.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess effect on the range of motion and limited range of motion in the study knee due to pain and inflammation following injection.

The investigator will assess the patient's study knee will for degrees of flexion and extension using an instrument called a goniometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single injection to study knee on Day 1 with clinical follow up over 72 hours.
Folllow up visits on Day 2 and Day 4.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare safety and tolerability between treatments as assessed by reported adverse events.

This will be assessed by type of adverse events reported (if any) by patients following injection.  The adverse events will be given a diagnosis by the investigator and a severity is deemed and a resolution is recorded.  Each patient will also their blood taken for standard biochemistry and haematology pathology test on Days 2 and 4.

The investigator will assess the results of their patholoy tests and any adverse events reported for the duration of the study to assess safety and tolerability of treatments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Single injection to study knee on Day 1 with clinical follow up over 72 hours.
Folllow up visits on Day 2 and Day 4.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Male or female, 40 years to 85 years old (inclusive), fully ambulatory, willing to sign informed consent.
2.	Symptomatic index knee osteoarthritis greater/equal to 6 months prior to screening with Kellgren Lawrence Grade II or III.
3.	Symptoms in the index knee for at least 6 months preceding screening.
4.	Because of the unknown effects of AmpionTM, women should avoid becoming pregnant during the course of this study if you become pregnant you will have to withdraw from the trial and your medical progress will be carefully followed.  These precautions are necessary because the information on the effects on the unborn or new born baby of drugs like AmpionTM, is still very limited. Your own doctor, as well as the study coordinator should be able to assist you if you have any questions about the need to avoid pregnancy.
Because of the unknown effects of AmpionTM, on sperm and possibly on foetus, men should avoid any possibility of fathering a child during the course of this trial.  If your partner does become pregnant you should notify the study coordinator and their medical progress will be monitored.  These precautions are necessary because the information on the effects on the unborn or new born baby of drugs like AmpionTM, is still limited.  Your own doctor, as well as the study coordinator, should be able to assist you if you have any questions about the need to avoid emitting sperm that might result in pregnancy.
5.	Is able to provide written informed consent to participate in the study in accordance with local regulations, and is not under any guardianship provision.
6.	Is willing and able to comply with all study requirements and instructions of the site study staff.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	As a result of medical review and screening investigation (including electrocardiogram (ECG) and laboratory tests), the Principal Investigator considers the patient unfit for the study.
2.	A history of allergic reactions to albumin (reaction to non human albumin such as egg albumin is not an exclusion criteria).
3.	A history of allergic reactions to excipients in 5% human albumin (N-acetyltryptophan, sodium caprylate).
4.	Any intra-articular or local periarticular injection, injection or surgery to the index knee during the 6 months prior to screening.
5.	Operative arthroscopy within 3 months of screening.
6.	Surgical procedure to the index knee other than arthroscopy within 12 months of participation in the trial.
7.	Any investigational knee products within 12 months of participation in the trial.
8.	Kellgren Lawrence Grade I or IV (doubtful or severe) osteoarthritis of the knee.
9.	Inflammatory or crystal arthropathies, acute fractures, severe loss of bone density, bone necrosis.
10.	Isolated patella-femoral syndrome or chondromalacia.
11.	Any other disease or condition interfering with the free use and evaluation of the index knee for the duration of the trial (e.g. cancer, congenital defects, spine osteoarthritis).
12.	Major injury to the index knee within the 12 months prior to screening.
13.	Severe hip osteoarthritis ipsilateral to the index knee.
14.	Any pain that could interfere with the assessment of index knee pain (e.g. pain in any other part of the lower extremities, pain radiating to the knee).
15.	Any pharmacological or non-pharmacological treatment started or changed during the 
4 weeks prior to randomization or likely to be changed during the duration of the study.
16.	Use of the following medications:
a.	Any topical treatment on osteoarthritis knees within 48 hours prior to randomization.
b.	All analgesics and NSAIDs except paracetamol within 48 hours prior to randomization 
c.	Anticoagulant therapy for 48 hours prior to randomization
d.	Any systemic steroid treatments within 14 days prior to randomization
e.	All immunosuppressives within a period of 5 times the drugs half life prior to randomization
17.	Use of corticosteroids greater than 10 mg prednisolone equivalent per day during the 30 days prior to randomization.
18.	Any albumin treatment in the 3 months before randomization.
19.	Female subjects who are pregnant or lactating.
20.	Female subjects of childbearing potential who have a positive pregnancy test on Day 1 prior to treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential subjects will be screened to assess their eligibility.  Treatment to each subject will be allocated by randomization.  Randomization schedule will be maintained under controlled access.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be allocated to a sequentially numbered treatment in accordance with the randomization schedule following confirmation of eligibility at pre-dose.  The randomization number will be in the form of a four digit number, Rsrnn, where s is the site number, r is the replacement indicator, and nn is the subject randomization number within site e.g. R1006.  If a subject is replaced, the second digit is incremented by one, and the same treatment is administered to the replacement subject as was allocated to the original subject e.g. R1006 is replaced by R1106, and receives the treatment originally allocated for R1006. 
Each subject will be assigned to one of the three treatments, i.e. active Ampion(TM) (either combined with lidocaine/betamethasone or betamethasone suspension) or saline placebo combined with lidocaine/betamethasone.  The allocation of treatment will be performed using a block randomization algorithm.  Two sentinel subjects will be randomized to either of the treatment A (AmpionTrademark) with betamethasone/lidocaine) or the treatment C (saline with betamethasone/lidocaine).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>randomized, double-blin,placebo-controlled</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ampio Pharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5445 DTC Parkway, Suite P4
Greenwood Village CO 80111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ampio Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5445 DTC Parkway, Suite P4
Greenwood Village CO 80111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>CPR Pharma Services</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Suite C 32 West Thebarton Rd
Thebarton SA 5031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind, parallel study designed to evaluate the effect of intra-articular knee injection of Ampion (Trademark) in male or female subjects 40 years to 85 years old (inclusive) with symptomatic primary knee osteoarthritis for 6 months preceding screening.  
The study consists of a 3 week screening period and a 4 day study participation period.
Each subject will be randomized to receive a single 10 mL knee injection of one of the following:

1.	Ampion(TM) combined with lignocaine/betamethasone suspension
2.	Ampion(TM) combined with betamethasone suspension 
3.	Saline placebo combined with lignocaine/betamethasone suspension</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Calvary Health Care Adelaide Human Research &amp; Ethics Committee (CHCA-HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>89 Strangways Terrace
North Adelaide SA 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Flinders Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 2A221 
Flinders Medical Centre 
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vaughan Clift</name>
      <address>Ampio Pharmaceuticals, Inc.
5445 DTC Parkway, Suite P4
Greenwood Village CO 80111</address>
      <phone>+1 303-418-1000</phone>
      <fax>+1 303-418-1001</fax>
      <email>vclift@ampiopharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vaughan Clift</name>
      <address>Ampio Pharmaceuticals, Inc.
5445 DTC Parkway, Suite P4
Greenwood Village CO 80111</address>
      <phone>+1 303-418-1000</phone>
      <fax>+1 303-418-1001</fax>
      <email>vclift@ampiopharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vaughan Clift</name>
      <address>Ampio Pharmaceuticals, Inc.
5445 DTC Parkway, Suite P4
Greenwood Village CO 80111</address>
      <phone>+1 303-418-1000</phone>
      <fax>+1 303-418-1001</fax>
      <email>vclift@ampiopharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>