<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365532">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000788673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized controlled trial evaluating self-care among three groups of patients with heart failure educated by health educators, by volunteers and a control group</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing the efficacy of a new educational strategy involving community health volunteers on self-care in patients with chronic heart failure compared with health workers in western Iran</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Public Health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention included two stages, first training nine female volunteers by a skilled general practitioner in a few workshops.
The duration and number of workshops are depended on situation and necessity realized in the first session by obtaining feedback from participants. The materials obtained from heart failure text books and related sites such as (http://www.heartfoundation.org.au/)translated into a simple language under supervision a cardiologist, was used and provided slides of PowerPoint and pamphlets taught in workshops. Second step was performing educational program for two groups of patients with CHF randomly been allocated into group A or B. The group A was trained face to face at their homes by trained community health volunteers (CHVs) and second group divided into 3 subgroups were trained by two skilled formal health professionals (FHP)at hospital. Trainings were a single session for both groups have been considered. The training duration for each patient in group A (educated by CHVs) was about 2 hours, but the patients in the second group(FHP) taken a 3.5 hours education with half an hour break in mid time. Two months latter they were interviewed again to assess their self-care activities and behaviors.</interventions>
    <comparator>comparing two educational strategies and a control group,  patients with regular health care who are normally given a very brief medical information or even no information more than the dosage of medicines and suggesting to avoid salt consumption .Unfortunately, there is not a practical program for educating all patients with CHF as a part of regular care currently, however those patients with CHF who have gone under surgery of coronary artery bypass during a rehabilitation program are educated by nurses and general practitioner.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>self-care scales (self-care maintenance, self-care management and self-care confidence) are the outcome that are measured using pSCHFI.The pSCHFI  is comprised of three scales with 22 questions containing 10 questions for self-maintenance, 6 for self-management and 6 for self-confidence. Each scale is standardized to a possible score of zero to 100(using likert scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>outcome was assessed at 60 days from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>over 18 year
diagnosed by heart failure
signing consent form
lack of mental disorder </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>95</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>less than 18 or more than 95
cognition problems
disagreement

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>According to the information received from another study of a similar design, it was expected the mean of self-care increase about 22 unit (d=22). Hence to have a power of 90% we needed at least 67 participants for each group. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>201</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state>Kermanshah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kermanshah University of Medical Sciences</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kermanshah University of Medical Sciences, Bolvar Shahid Beheshti, Kermanshah, Iran</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kermanshah University of Medical Sciences</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kermanshah University of Medical Sciences, Bolvar Shahid Beheshti, Kermanshah, Iran</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>the university of sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Sydney  NSW  2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is an ongoing randomized control trial in which 231 patients with chronic heart failure (CHF) randomly allocated into three groups- two intervention groups and a control group, and approved by ethics committees in Iran and Australia. Two educational approaches; a face to face training by trained volunteers at home and a classic training by skilled health workers at hospital have been established. Data through interviewing before and two months after intervention have been collected using self-care of chronic heart failure index translated and validated into Persian (pSCHFI), as the primary outcome of the current study plus an investigator developed questionnaire. Data will be analysised to compare self-care in three groups, and also determine expected associations between different variables. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>the Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level6, Jane Foss Russell Building-G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14451</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>soraya siabani</name>
      <address>Victor Coppleson Building - D02  Menzies Center for Health Policy
Medical School The University of Sydney NSW 2006
 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9036 7000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 5204  </fax>
      <email>ssia5034@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>soraya siabani</name>
      <address>Victor Coppleson Building - D02 Menzies Center for Health Policy
Medical School The University of Sydney NSW 2006
 </address>
      <phone>+61478262727</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 5204  </fax>
      <email>ssia5034@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>soraya siabani</name>
      <address>Victor Coppleson Building - D02  Menzies Center for Health Policy
Medical School The University of Sydney NSW 2006
 </address>
      <phone>+61478262727</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ssia5034@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>soraya siabani</name>
      <address>128 Ryde road Pymble NSW 2073 </address>
      <phone>+61478262727</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>