<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82747">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000203358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Living Well with Diabetes - Telephone Counselling for Maintenance of Physical Activity, Weight Loss and Glycaemic Control in Type 2 diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate a telephone counselling intervention for physical activity, weight loss and glycaemic control in adult patients with type 2 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LWWD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Intervention Group: Participants receive a series of telephone calls over the 18-month intervention. Calls are delivered weekly and fortnightly for the first 6 months and monthly for the following 12 months. Calls will be tapered according to particpant needs. Participants receive a detailed workbook containing feedback on their baseline assessment, sections on physical activity, diet and weight loss, information on goal setting, problem-solving, self-monitoring and supports. Participants receive feedback following each assessment. Using the workbook during calls, participants work collaboratively with their telephone counsellor to set goals for physical activity, dietary change and weight loss. Barriers and supports are identified; confidence is assessed and problem solving is discussed as necessary. Participants are encouraged to work towards achieving overall physical activity targets of putting together at least 200 minutes a week of moderate-intensity physical activity, 3-4 sessions a week of strength training and to reduce their sedentary time; weight loss targets of a loss of 5-7% of initial body weight and diet targets of reducing energy intake by 2000kJ, total fat intake to less than 30% of energy intake and saturated fat to less than 7% of energy intake.</interventions>
    <comparator>The Control group: After each assessment, usual care participants are sent a thank you letter that includes brief feedback on their assessment. Included in this mailing are standard, off-the shelf brochures, that are suitable for persons with diabetes, on a range of health behaviours (including diet, physical activity, alcohol) and a project newsletter that updates them on how many people are participating in the study and gives general health tips.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Physical activity (exact measures to be confirmed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 12-months, 18-months and 24-months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight Loss</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 12-months, 18-months and 24-months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glycaemic Control (HbA1c)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in dietary intake (exact changes to be confirmed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood lipid level (total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, HDL-cholesterol, triglycerides)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood glucose level</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in liver function (Alanine Amino-Transferase, Aspartate Amino Transferase, Lactate Dehydrogenase, Alkaline Phosphatase and Gamma-Glutamyl Transpeptidase)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in body composition (waist circumference and body fat, using bio-electrical impedance analysis)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 12-months, 18-months and 24-months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in medication use (including diabetes, cholesterol and hypertension medications)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life, measured using the Short-Form (SF)-12 Health Survey</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6-months, 18-months and 24-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of type 2 diabetes; English speaking; minimum age: 20 years, maximum age: 75 years; both males and females.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not undergoing active treatment for cancer; not planning hip/knee replacement in next year; not using mobility aid; not with active heart disease; not with breathing problems; not undergoing dialysis; not taking warfarin; not pregnant.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/03/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>21/03/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>350</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>302</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Public Health, The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4
Public Health Building
Herston road
Herston QLD 4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This 5-year, randomised controlled trial is evaluating a telephone-delivered physical activity, weight loss and glycaemic control intervention targeting patients with type 2 diabetes, recruited from the primary care setting, and compared to usual care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Papers:

Eakin EG, Reeves MM, Marshall AL, Dunstan DW, Graves N, Healy GN, Bleier J, Barnett AG, OMoore-Sullivan T, Russell A, Wilkie K. Living Well with Diabetes: a randomized controlled trial of a telephone-delivered intervention for maintenance of weight loss, physical activity and glycaemic control in adults with type 2 diabetes. BMC Public Health, 2010:10:452.

Eakin EG, Reeves MM, Winkler E, Healy GN, Dunstan DW, Owen N, Marshall AM, Wilkie KC. Six-month outcomes from Living Well with Diabetes: A randomized trial of a telephone-delivered weight loss and physical activity intervention to improve glycemic control. Annals of Behavioral Medicine, 2013:46(2):193-203.

Winkler E, Waters L, Eakin E, Fjeldsoe B, Owen N, Reeves M. Is measurement error altered by participation in a physical activity intervention? Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise, 2013:45(5):1004-1011.

Eakin EG, Winkler EA, Dunstan DW, Healy GN, Owen N, Marshall AM, Graves N, Reeves MM. Living Well with Diabetes: 24-month outcomes from a randomized trial of telephone-delivered weight loss and physical activity intervention to improve glycemic control. Diabetes Care, 2014: 37(8): 2177-85.

Goode AD, Winkler EAH, Reeves MM, Eakin EG. Relationship between intervention dose and outcomes in Living Well with Diabetes - a randomized trial of a telephone-delivered lifestyle-based weight loss intervention. American Journal of Health Promotion. Epub ahead of print, 5 November 2014.

Presentation:

Eakin E, Reeves M, Dunstan D, Healy G, Winkler E, Marshall A, Owen N. (31 October  3 November 2012). Living Well with Diabetes: Six-month randomised trial outcomes of a telephone-delivered weight loss intervention. Paper presented at the 4th International Congress on Physical Activity and Public Health, Sydney, Australia.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008000188</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Eakin</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, School of Public Health, Cancer Prevention Research Centre, Level 4 Public Health Building, Herston road, HERSTON, QLD, 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33464692</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33655540</fax>
      <email>e.eakin@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Eakin</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, School of Public Health, Cancer Prevention Research Centre, Level 4 Public Health Building, Herston road, HERSTON, QLD, 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5505</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33655540</fax>
      <email>e.eakin@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Eakin</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, School of Public Health, Cancer Prevention Research Centre, Level 4 Public Health Building, Herston road, HERSTON, QLD, 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5505</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 5540</fax>
      <email>e.eakin@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>