<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320488">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000802202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison between perineal and anal repair of rectocele in obstructed defecation patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized Controlled Trial evaluating the effect of Perineal versus Anal Repairs of Rectocele  on functional score, symptom improvement and sexual function in  patients with Obstructed Defecation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructed defecation due to rectocele</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>multiparous females women with obstructed defecation due to rectocele will be randomly allocated into three groups: transperineal repair with levatorplasty (TPR-LP); transperineal repair without levatorplasty (TPR); and transanal repair (TAR. The study includes defecographic assessment, anal manometry, and score on a function questionnaire. Assessments will be done preoperatively and six months postoperatively.
In the transanal approach,a Hill-Ferguson retractor was inserted into the anal canal, and the anterior rectal wall was exposed. With a finger inserted in the vagina, the true borders of the rectocele were delineated. After submucosal infiltration of a 1:200000 adrenaline solution in saline, the mucosal flap in the whole area of the rectocele (starting 1 cm above the dentate line) was elevated and excised. Horizontal plication of the muscular layer was performed with 2/0 Vicryl sutures, and the continuity of the mucosa was restored with one row of interrupted 3/0 Vicryl sutures (half Delorme procedure). Rectal packing was not used, and normal feeding was allowed on the second day after the operation.
In the transperineal approach, a transverse incision was made in the perineum above the subcutaneous anal sphincter, and dissection was performed between the rectum and the vagina. Suturing of the rectal submucosal area was done with 3/0 Vicryl sutures. Then the deeper transverse or deeper perineal tissues were approximated to reinforce the rectovaginal septum, and to take tension off the first layer of sutures. 
When levatorplasty was done, tissues of the perineal body, including the puborectalis muscle, were approximated in the midline to provide an additional layer of tissue between the vaginal and rectal wall and to reinforce the closure.
Each procedure takes about 45 - 60 minutes</interventions>
    <comparator>Trans anal repair considered as control treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resumption of normal function</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after surgery by questionnaires</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>symptoms of obstruction during defecation and sexual function</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after surgery by questionnaires</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recurrence by examination at 3 months intervals</outcome>
      <timepoint>recurrence assesed once every 3 months for a year after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>multiparous females with rectocele</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with recurrent rectocele, diabetes, previous anal surgery, systemic steroid treatment, connective tissue disease, slow-transit constipation, compromised anal sphincter function, or abnormal thyroid function</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>patients presented to outpatient clinic in our institute. allocation of treatment will be done by  sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>none</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Khaled Madbouly</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mehatet el Raml, university of alexandria, faculty of medicine, department of surgery, alexandria. 21311</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mansoura University hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mansoura University, faculty of medicine, main square, mansoura, Egypt, 21326</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Egypt</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Although functional outcome of surgical rectocele repair is considered successful in 70 to 90 percent of patients, it is a matter of debate which procedure is the most effective. This study was therefore designed to evaluate functional outcome of transperineal repair with and without levatorplasty versus transrectal repair of rectocele with obstructed defecation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alexandria committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mehatet el Raml, University of Alexandria, faculty of medicine, alexandria 21311</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/01/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>khaled madbouly</name>
      <address>Mehatet el raml, Alex faculty of Medicine, university of alexandria, departement of surgery, alexandria, 21311</address>
      <phone>2034864416</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khaled.madbouly@alexmed.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Khaled madbouly</name>
      <address>Mehatet el raml, Alex faculty of Medicine, university of alexandria, departement of surgery, alexandria, 21311</address>
      <phone>2034864416</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khaled.madbouly@alexmed.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Khaled Madbouly</name>
      <address>Mehatet el raml, Alex faculty of Medicine, university of alexandria, departement of surgery, alexandria, 21311</address>
      <phone>2034864416</phone>
      <fax>2034864416</fax>
      <email>khaled.madbouly@alexmed.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>