<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369672">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001630404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Psycho-Educational Intervention For Common Mental Health Problems In Pregnant Women Exposed To Humanitarian Emergency </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating feasibility and acceptability of a Psycho-educational intervention for pregnant women with common mental disorders in rural Pakistan: a randomized controlled feasibility trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Social support</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Help seeking for Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are two arms to this trial. Arm 1: Psycho-educational sessions. Arm 2: Routine care. The intervention arm received an initial introductory session of 20 minutes duration regarding the intervention with each participant's family; for family buy in and participation in the next visit. This was followed by the main session of around one hour duration to the whole family in their home by the local community health worker. The intervention focuses attention on maternal psycho-social well-being, associating it with the optimal growth and development of the unborn child. The main areas of the intervention were empathetic listening, availability of social support, ensuring the pregnant woman regarding the circle of support that is available, domestic peace, balanced diet, rest, engagement of the pregnant woman in pleasurable activities, routine check-up during pregnancy, consulting doctor in case the distress is not relieved and maintenance of household peace and harmony throughout. These were described as steps for the health and well-being of the pregnant woman and her unborn child. Each of these steps has a maternal well-being message for the whole family. The intervention uses a simple pictorial approach of paired illustrations with one showing unwanted behaviors and the other positive actions to achieve the desired outcome of support for the mother and were designed specifically for this intervention. The duration of the study for any participant will conclude after two months follow-up assessment post intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2: Routine care was conducted by the local community health workers (LHWs) to the control arm participants as is their routine official duty. During their routine visits LHWs conduct educational sessions (awareness for prevention of common diseases) and also provide the household with routine over the counter medicine for common ailments along with iron and folic acids. The duration of the study for any participant will conclude after two months follow-up assessment after study enrollment. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Help-seeking for psychological distress by pregnant women

This was assessed at the end of the trial . This was determined through a semi-structured approach by a researcher blind to allocation status at 2 months post-intervention. The information was obtained directly from the womens LHW. The LHWs were asked whether anyone in the family of the distressed pregnant woman had contacted them for assistance with the mental health of the pregnant woman in the two months after the psycho-educational sessions. As the LHWs were the first point of contact for the women, they were considered to be the best source for this information. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment (week 1), posttreatment (week 9)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress as measured by the Self-Reporting Questionnaire (SRQ-20)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment (week 1), posttreatment (week 9)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Social Support  as measured by means scores on the Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support (MSPSS) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pretreatment (week 1), posttreatment (week 9)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>SRQ score of &gt;8 at any stage of their pregnancy were eligible for participation in the study.

All the participants were sourced from the cross sectional study that has been published and referenced as below.
Khan, M. N., Chiumento, A., Dherani, M., Bristow, K., Sikander, S., and Rahman, A (2015). Psychological distress and its associations with past events in pregnant women affected by armed conflict in Swat, Pakistan: a cross sectional study. Conflict and Health. 2015; 9(1).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a) Participants with suicidal intent
b) Severe mental or medical illness
c) Recently given birth 
d) Living with another women with an SRQ score of 9 or above.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants were pregnant women identified from a cross sectional study conducted in the earlier phase of the research in the local area, through predefined inclusion and exclusion criteria along with the baseline data. The unit of randomization was individual trial participants. Randomization was done by a researcher at the independent trial center at the Human Development Research Foundation who was not involved in intervention delivery, clinical supervision, independent assessment or other aspects of the day-to-day running of the study. The trial participants were randomized to the intervention and routine care arm, using a 1:1 allocation ratio.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization was done through a computer generated system using 1:1 allocation ratio. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/11/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>71</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/01/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state>Swat/Khyber Pakhtunkhwa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Human Development Research Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>House 06, Street 55, F-7/4 Islamabad postcode: 44000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Pakistan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Human Development Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>House 06, Street 55, F-7/4 Islamabad postcode: 44000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Pakistan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This was a feasibility trial of an intervention to raise awareness about psychological distress in pregnant women living in a post-conflict setting,  The rationale of the study was to evaluate the feasibility and acceptability of the research procedures in pregnant women in low-resources settings affected by humanitarian emergency. This study compares the relative efficacy of (a) Psycho-educational intervention and (b) Routine care. It is hypothesized that Psycho-educational intervention will lead to increase in uptake of services/help for their psychological distress than routine care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Review Committee, University of Liverpool</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>UoL000851</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>United Kingdom</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Muhammad Naseem Khan</name>
      <address>Institute of Public Health and Social Sciences, Khyber Medical University, Phase 5, Hayatabad Peshawar, postcode 25000.</address>
      <phone>+923339482238</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drnasim@kmu.edu.pk</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Muhammad Naseem Khan</name>
      <address>Institute of Public Health and Social Sciences, Khyber Medical University, Phase 5, Hayatabad Peshawar, postcode 25000.</address>
      <phone>+923339482238</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drnasim@kmu.edu.pk</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Muhammad Naseem Khan</name>
      <address>Institute of Public Health and Social Sciences, Khyber Medical University, Phase 5, Hayatabad Peshawar, postcode 25000.</address>
      <phone>+923339482238</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drnasim@kmu.edu.pk</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Muhammad Naseem Khan</name>
      <address>Institute of Public Health and Social Sciences, Khyber Medical University, Phase 5, Hayatabad Peshawar.</address>
      <phone>+923339482238</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drnasim@kmu.edu.pk</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>