<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369351">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000011381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A field survey of windfarm and traffic noise effects on sleep</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Identification of complaint levels on sleep, based on overnight noise exposure in windfarm-exposed, traffic noise-exposed and quiet rural areas: A field survey.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1191-1014</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>GNT1113571 </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Noise effects on sleep</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The survey will include key elements from a survey already developed and used in a Health Canada study. It will be brief and will specifically focus on sleep (i.e., Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, PSQI; Insomnia Severity Index, ISI; Epworth Sleepiness Scale, ESS) quality of life (EQ-5D) and Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ), with only general night-time noise questions directly relevant to sleep and proximity to noise sources within the past 3 months. Return envelopes and reminders will be used to maximise response rates. Surveys will help to describe self-reported sleep and overnight-noise outcomes in different exposure groups. 

Our aim is to recruit from stratified samples of wind farm exposed and wind farm naïve participants in order to reduce bias effects. We will recruit via postal surveys targeted to residents living close to a wind farm with known noise complaints (i.e., Waterloo, Hallett and Lake Bonney wind farms), wind farm naïve residents living adjacent to a busy road traffic corridor (i.e., a known noise problem positive control group), and residents living in a quiet rural location (i.e., no exposure controls).</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The main outcome of the survey is to identify 4 groups according to overnight noise exposure type and level of complaints into; highest complaint quartiles in wind farm and traffic noise exposure groups (WFNQ1 and TNQ1), lowest quartile complaints in the wind farm exposure group (WFNQ4) and a quiet rural exposure control group (CN). Level of complaints will be generated using a combination of scores from the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, (PSQI); Insomnia Severity Index, (ISI); Epworth Sleepiness Scale, (ESS); quality of life (EQ-5D) and Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ). In addition, responses to general night-time noise questions directly relevant to sleep and proximity to noise sources within the past 3 months will be used to identify residents who indicate high vs. low complaints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once a minimum of 400 responses to surveys are collected, or at least 200 from wind farm-exposed areas &amp; 200 responses from wind farm-naive areas.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe self-reported sleep in different exposure groups using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index, (PSQI); Insomnia Severity Index, (ISI); Epworth Sleepiness Scale, (ESS); quality of life (EQ-5D) and Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once a minimum of 400 responses to surveys are collected, or at least 200 from wind farm-exposed areas &amp; 200 responses from wind farm-naive areas.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe overnight-noise outcomes in different exposure groups using the general night-time noise questions directly relevant to sleep and proximity to noise sources.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once a minimum of 400 responses to surveys are collected, or at least 200 from wind farm-exposed areas &amp; 200 responses from wind farm-naive areas.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age: &gt; 17 years.
2. Willing and able to complete the survey. Consent will be implied on the basis of survey completion given that separate consent is not practical for online survey tools we plan to predominantly use where possible.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Language difficulties that might preclude informed consent and study questionnaire completion.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This survey is the first part of a larger project. It is designed to identify people who report being affected by wind farm noise and others who do not. Following data collection from survey responses, we will identify 4 groups according to overnight noise exposure type and level of complaints into:

- Highest complaint quartiles in wind farm and traffic noise exposure groups (WFNQ1 and TNQ1);
- Lowest quartile complaints in the wind farm exposure group (WFNQ4);
- Quiet rural exposure control group (CN).

These will be used to identify study groups for Part 2 (In-Home Study) or Part 3 (In-Lab Study) of the project. Using computerised minimisation/randomisation, individuals within these groups will be sequentially invited to participate in further in-home or in-laboratory measurement sleep studies.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Psychosocial</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sturt Rd
Bedford Park 
South Australia 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Repatriation General Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health 
216 Daws Rd
Daw Park 
South Australia 5041</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Increased sustainable green energy production has led to rapid expansion of wind farm facilities in Australia and world-wide. This has been associated with community complaints regarding noise emissions that include infra-sound (noise below average hearing threshold), and concerns that this may have negative effects on sleep and health. International studies so far remain inconclusive and none have included any direct measurements of sleep so it remains unclear how disturbing wind farm noise is to sleep. Ongoing uncertainty in this area remains a problem for communities close to wind farm facilities, government regulators, wind energy producers and the broader community.

This project is specifically designed to address knowledge gaps concerning potential wind farm noise effects on sleep using the most sensitive techniques currently available for assessing sleep disturbance. The results of this study will help to inform the potential need for improved noise regulation and abatement strategies to minimise potential sleep and health impacts.

This survey is the first part of a larger project, and is designed to identify people who report being affected by wind farm noise and others who do not, to be invited to participate in a home sleep and noise measurement study, or a later in-laboratory study at Flinders University.

This survey is largely based on that developed by Health Canada to study wind farm effects on health and is being used with permission from the Health Canada study team, but has been modified based on input from Australian noise and sleep researchers, and community representatives from areas affected by wind farm or traffic noise. The aim of the survey is to identify 4 groups according to overnight noise exposure type and level of complaints.
Individuals within these groups will be sequentially invited to participate in further field measurement and in-laboratory studies.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee (SAC HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics, Room 2A
221 Flinders Medical Centre
Level 2, Flinders Medical Centre
BEDFORD PARK SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/SAC/207 55.16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Catcheside</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health: 
A Flinders Centre for Research Excellence
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Rd, Daw Park
South Australia 5041
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1309 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.catcheside@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gorica Micic</name>
      <address>Flinders University
Sturt Rd, Bedford Park 
South Australia 5042
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 2377</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8201 2388</fax>
      <email>gorica.micic@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Catcheside</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health: 
A Flinders Centre for Research Excellence
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Rd, Daw Park
South Australia 5041
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8275 1309 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.catcheside@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gorica Micic</name>
      <address>Flinders University
Sturt Rd, Bedford Park 
South Australia 5042
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 2377</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 201 2388</fax>
      <email>gorica.micic@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>