<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83727">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000420246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Outpatient Foley catheter Vs inpatient Prostin gel for induction of labour</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An evaluation of Outpatient Foley (intracervical) catheter versus Inpatient Prostaglandin Vaginal Gel (PGE2) on the induction of labour at term.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Induction of labour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Foley catheter placed intracervically (with 30mL inflation of balloon) in women requiring cervical ripening procedure as part of induction of labour.  Catheter placement procedure takes approximately 5 minutes.  Women then return home while cervical ripening occurs (expected duration of catheter in situ 12-18 hours, maximum 24 hours) and return to hospital for induction the following day.</interventions>
    <comparator>Prostaglandin vaginal gel (PGE2: Prostin) as an inpatient for cervical ripening as part of induction of labour.  Doses 2mg at baseline then 1mg at 6 hours following commencement of treatment for nulliparous women, 1mg at baseline then 1mg at 6 hours following commencement of treatment for multiparous women.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of women delivering vaginally within 12 hours of admission to Delivery Unit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 12 hours after admission to Delivery Unit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total inpatient hours from induction to delivery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured prospectively by study researchers and correlated with medical record.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of women requiring syntocinon for induction or augmentation of labour, as assessed by actual syntocinon use during labour recorded in patient records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured post-delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mode of delivery (rate of Caesarean delivery, spontaneous vaginal delivery, and instrumental vaginal delivery)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Induction to delivery interval i.e. time from commencement of cervical ripening to delivery</outcome>
      <timepoint>At delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vaginal delivery within 24 hours of insertion of Foley Catheter or first dose PGE2 gel</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 hours post insertion of catheter or gel</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Delivery within 24 hours of insertion of Foley Catheter or first dose PGE2 gel</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 hours post insertion of catheter or gel</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for second method of cervical ripening or (in Prostin group) 3rd dose of prostaglandin, as assessed by actual use of 3rd dose Prostin in Prostin group, or crossover to use of Prostin from Foley group, recorded in patient file.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Checked post-delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction using questionnaire created for purposes of this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaire 24-48 hours post-delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to hospital (Foleys group) prior to planned readmission and not in labour</outcome>
      <timepoint>Unscheduled return to hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal febrile morbidity (temperature greater or equal to 38 degrees C on at least two occasions or greater than or equal to 38.5 degrees C on at least 1 occasion, measured using infrared thermometer to take tympanic temperature readings).</outcome>
      <timepoint>From commencement of induction to 48 hours post-delivery.  Temperature is measured at intervals as per hospital protocol (2nd hourly while in labour and immediately post-delivery in Delivery Suite/Birth Centre, then daily thereafter unless clinical symptoms/signs infection).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-reassuring fetal heart rate trace as assessed by cardiotocograph monitoring.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From induction commencement to delivery.  Cardiotocograph monitoring will occur in Foley group for 30 minutes (or until reassuring CTG obtained, whichever is longer) after initial insertion of Foley catheter, and in Prostin group for 30 minutes (or until reassurring CTG obtained, whichever is longer) after insertion of each dose of Prostin.  Fetal heart rate is continuously monitored when induced women are in active labour in Delivery Suite.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caesarean or instrumental delivery for fetal distress</outcome>
      <timepoint>delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Admission to newborn care as recorded in patient records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth to 6 weeks of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apgar scores 1 and 5 minutes</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 and 5 minutes of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resource utilization as assessed by use of resource utilization form, which has been developed for the study in order to extract data on resource utilization from patient records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From commencement of induction to 6 weeks post-partum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Epidural use as specified in patient records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From induction to delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 18 and over
Gestational age 37 weeks or greater
Booked for cervical ripening procedure as part of induction of labour</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not suitable for outpatient management on maternal or fetal grounds
Potentially unsuitable for randomisation to prostaglandin gel use (e.g. uterine scar, oligohydramnios, grand multiparity)

Bishop's score 7 or more, or cervical dilation 2cm or greater, at time of booked induction

Regular painful uterine contractions at time of booked induction

Ruptured membranes

Chorioamnionitis or suspected chorioamnionitis

Multiple pregnancy

Non-vertex presentation

Non-English speaking

Allergy/hypersensitivity to Latex or PGE2 gel</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>* Information leaflets about the trial to be made available to women in the late stages of pregnancy who may require induction of labour (IOL).
* All eligible women to be seen, enrolled and randomised on day of planned induction.  
* All women for induction to have cardiotocograph (CTG), baseline vaginal examination (VE), and recording of Bishops score at time of admission for IOL, then eligible women to be randomised.

* Sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes will be used to contain the allocation assignment.  

* Allocation assignments will be placed in envelope and envelope sealed by a person not otherwise involved in the conduct of the trial.  * Envelopes are to be kept in a locked, secure area.  * Envelopes will be opened only after participant details are written on the envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a random number table.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/12/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>101</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Hospital for Women</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Barker St
Randwick
NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Maternal Fetal Medicine
Royal Hospital for Women</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St
Randwick
NSW 2031</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims of study are
1) To compare:
a)	Clinical effectiveness
b)	Patient acceptability
c)	Safety

of the use of Foley catheter in the outpatient setting with intravaginal PGE2 (Prostin) gel in the inpatient setting for induction of labour.

2) To assess the cost-effectiveness of intracervical Foley catheter in the outpatient setting to intravaginal PGE2 (Prostin) gel in the inpatient setting for use in induction of labour.

The hypothesis is that for induction of labour in women with an unfavourable cervix, use of the catheter on an outpatient basis (women have catheter inserted, then go home until the following morning) will be at least as clinically effective and safe as use of gel as an inpatient (staying in hospital), and that outpatient catheter use will be both acceptable to women and cost-effective.

Currently, most pregnant women who need cervical ripening as part of an induction of labour stay in hospital from the time the gel or catheter is inserted until the cervix is ready for the rest of the induction.  This means many women stay 12-24 hours in hospital while they are not in labour, but are waiting for the gel or catheter to work.  Most women and their babies needing cervical ripening are otherwise very well, and could stay at home during this time if a safe and effective way to do this was available.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Peer-reviewed journal articles

1) Henry A, Madan A, Reid R, Tracy SK, Austin K, Welsh AW, Challis D.  Outpatient Foley catheter versus inpatient prostaglandin E2 gel for induction of labour: a randomised trial.  BMC Pregnancy and Childbirth 2013, 13:25

2) Madan A, Tracy S, Reid R, Henry A. Recruitment difficulties in obstetric trials: case study and review. ANZJOG 2014; 54 (6): 546-552.

3) Austin K, Chambers GM, de Abreu Lourenco R, Madan A, Susic D, Henry A. Cost-effectiveness of term induction of labour using inpatient prostaglandin gel versus outpatient Foley catheter. ANZJOG 2015; 55(4): 440-5. DOI: 10.1111/ajo.12348.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Illawarra Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC), Northern Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Edmund Blackett Building
Cnr Avoca and High Streets
RANDWICK NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/04/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/09/0007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/83727-Final article BMC Preg Childbirth.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amanda Henry</name>
      <address>School of Women's and Children's Health, University of New South Wales
Level 1, Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St (Locked Bag 2000)
Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91132315</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93826444</fax>
      <email>amanda.henry@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amanda Henry</name>
      <address>School of Women's and Children's Health, University of New South Wales
Level 1, Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St (Locked Bag 2000)
Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 91132315</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93826444</fax>
      <email>amanda.henry@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Henry</name>
      <address>School of Women's and Children's Health, University of New South Wales
Level 1, Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St (Locked Bag 2000)
Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91132315</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93826444</fax>
      <email>amanda.henry@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amanda Henry</name>
      <address>School of Women's and Children's Health, University of New South Wales
Level 1, Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St (Locked Bag 2000)
Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91132315</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amanda.henry@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>