<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83190">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000430235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A prospective, single-masked, cross-over, randomised clinical trial assessing ocular comfort and ocular changes with and without lens replacement during the day with AIR OPTIX (trademark) AQUA contact lenses worn by experienced wearers over three days</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, single-masked, cross-over, randomised clinical trial assessing ocular comfort and ocular changes with and without lens replacement during the day with AIR OPTIX (trademark) AQUA contact lenses worn by experienced wearers over three days</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contact lens wear</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ocular Comfort</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a prospective, single-masked, cross-over, randomised clinical trial, with participants wearing AIR OPTIX AQUA contact lenses bilaterally over 3 days following initial lens dispense. 
Participants will initially be fitted with contact lenses . This is followed by three days of wear with the same lens type. Each day corresponds to one stage of the study. For two of the stages, participants will insert their own study lenses and these will be removed after approximately five hours of wear. Either the same lenses will be re-inserted after a brief soak in saline or a new pair of lenses will be inserted. For the other stage, participants will insert their own study lenses and wear the same lenses for the day without removal. The order in which this occurs will be randomised for all stages and masked when lenses are removed during the day. Subjective responses will also be evaluated at regular intervals during each stage.
It is expected that most participants will have six scheduled visits, comprising the baseline visit followed by two stages with two visits per stage and one stage with one visit. 
*	Baseline visit
*	Stages where lenses removed during the day
o	Visit 1
o	Visit 2
*	Stage where lenses not removed during the day:
o	Visit 1
*	Take home questionnaires (THQ) at regular intervals during the day for all stages</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control- cross over study</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective ocular comfort with contact lenses. This will be assessed by using questionnaires which are to be completed at regular time points during the day.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 1, 2, 3</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ocular response. This will assessed with a slit lamp biomicroscope, which is a specialised micrsocope used to view the eye.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 1, 2, 3</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
Be at least 18 years old;
Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses;
Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses; 
Be an experienced contact lens wearer;</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosis. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
An active corneal infection or any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment and/or during the study;
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse manner or risk providing a false positive. 
N.B. Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial;  
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
Previous corneal refractive surgery;
Contraindications to contact lens wear;
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial;
Participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks for dispensing studies and 48 hours between in-house studies;

The Investigator may, at his/her discretion, exclude anyone else who they believe may not be able to fulfil the study requirements, or if it is believed to be in the participants best interests.

N.B. Whilst pregnant or lactating women are not excluded from the trial, they must be able to complete the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/08/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/09/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CIBA VISION</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>11460 Johns Creek Parkway
Duluth, GA 30097-1556</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Eye Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building (RMB), Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales  SYDNEY NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this trial is to assess changes in ocular comfort during the day, and whether ocular comfort is influenced by new lens replacement or re-insertion with the same lens after a brief soak in saline, during the day. The trial also aims to assess ocular changes and whether these correlate with changes in comfort.

The hypothesis for this trial is ocular comfort will decrease with lens wear during the day whether lenses are replaced, the same lens is re-inserted or the same lens is worn uninterrupted for the day.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Papas EB, Tilia D, Tomlinson D, Williams J, Chan E, Chan J, Golebiowski B.
Consequences of wear interruption for discomfort with contact lenses
Optom Vis Sci. 2014 Jan;91(1):24-31</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Vision CRC and Institute for Eye Research Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales  SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0903</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales  SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293856165</phone>
      <fax>+61293857404</fax>
      <email>d.tilia@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax>+61293857404</fax>
      <email>d.tilia@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales  SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293856165</phone>
      <fax>+61293857404</fax>
      <email>d.tilia@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5 RMB
Gate 14 Barker St
UNSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>