<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365471">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000169640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of Analgesia Nociception Index (ANI) guided analgesia administration with Standard Clinical Practice during Routine General Anaesthesia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of Analgesia Nociception Index (ANI) guided analgesia administration with Standard Clinical Practice during Routine General Anaesthesia on post-operative pain scores and post-operative opioid requirement in patients undergoing spinal surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The proposed study aims to evaluate Analgesia Nociception Index (ANI) titrated analgesia in patients undergoing spinal surgery.  The ANI Monitor examines small fluctuations in heart rate to determine the level of analgesia to nociception balance. This clinical utility study is designed to investigate the effect of ANI monitor guided fentanyl administration on post-operative events, including self-reported post-operative pain scores, analgesia administration, recovery times, and opioid-related side effects.  The monitor will be applied prior to induction of anaesthesia and removed once the patient is ready for transfer to a general nursing ward. The study will also record the incidence of unwanted intra-operative events such as tachycardia, hypertension, and the consumption of fentanyl under constant hypnotic level balanced general anaesthesia.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Clinical Practice.  This involves titrating fentanyl to traditional variables, such as heart rate, blood pressure, respiratory rate and surgical stimulus.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative pain scores using Numerical rating scales (NRS). Patients rate their pain intensity on the scale of 0 to 10 where 0 represents no pain and 10 represents worst pain
imaginable. The Verbal NRS (VNRS) is administered using a phrase such as: On ascale of 0 to 10, with 0 being no pain at all and 10 being the worst pain you could imagine, where would you rate the pain you are experiencing right now?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 hour of completion of surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative fenanyl Consumption in micrograms (total) and micrograms per hour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until ready for discharge from PACU</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intra-operative hemodynamic disturbance.
a.	Defined as a change in blood pressure &lt; or &gt; 20% of baseline as measured by a non-invasive blood pressure machine at 2.5 minutely intervals
b.	Defined as a change in heart rate &lt; or &gt; 20% of baseline as measured via Electrocardiogram
c.	Total time spent (total and %) within these limits and outside of these limits
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra-operatively every 5 minutes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative sedation scores with Ramsay Sedation Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutely within 1 hour post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative opioid side-effects:
a.	Nausea and vomiting: to measure the incidence of any nausea, emetic episodes (retching or vomiting), or both (i.e., postoperative nausea and vomiting) during the first 24 postoperative hours. Upon Discharge from PACU, and at 24 hours post surgery, patients will verbally rate their worst nausea episode since emergence on an 11-point scale, where 0 represented no nausea and 10 the most severe nausea.
b.	Respiratory depression: respiratory rate recorded at 5 minute intervals. This will be done by the PACU nurse, counting the number of breaths the patient takes over a 30 second period and multiplying by 2. Requirement for naloxone reversal of opioids will be recorded.
c.	Airway Obstruction: recorded as episodes of intervention, either manual support (jaw-thrust/chin lift) or devices used (oro-pharyngeal airway/nasopharyngeal airway)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 24 hours post-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative time to discharge from Post Anaesthesia Care Unit (PACU)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operative time to ready for discharge from Post Anaesthesia Care Unit (PACU)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients scheduled for non-emergent, spinal surgery, aged 18-75 years, American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) score 1 or 2, competent to consent to participation, able to use a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) and able to activate a patient controlled analgesia (PCA) machine post-operatively.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Emergency surgery
Inability to consent, lack of written consent or speak English fluently 
Pregnancy or lactation.  Pregnancy test will be performed in all women of child bearing potential
Cardiac morbidity
Non-regular sinus cardiac rhythym 
Cardiac disease which impacts usual daily functioning (equivalent to ASA greater than or equal to 3)
Implanted cardiac pacemaker 
Concurrent medications with a major effect affect upon the sinus node
Expected duration of surgery greater than 3 hours (180 minutes)
Extremes of weight (Body Mass Index less than or equal to 19 or  greater than or equal to 35 kg per meter squared) 
Pre-operative chronic opioid use or chronic pain, equivalent to oxycodone 20mg per oral, per day for more than 6 weeks
Allergy or intolerance to any of the study drugs 
Use of neuraxial anaesthesia 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects are enrolled once inclusion and exclusion criteria have been checked and informed consent obtained. Allocation to placebo or active arms of the trial will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation to treatment or standard clinical practice via random allocation using random permuted blocks (i.e. computerised sequence generation). Allocation to trial will be the randomisation point.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size estimation is based on the primary outcome (early post-operative pain scores). Post-operative pain will be measured by a numerical pain rating scale (NPRS) from 0-10.  If we assume that ANI guided analgesia administration reduces the post-operative pain NPRS from 5 to 3, and a Standard Deviation equal to 4, then recruitment of 25 participants in each group will result in a statistical power (1-Beta) of 0.8 at an a error level of 0.05.  The reduction of pain from a NPRS of 5 (moderate pain) to 3 (mild pain) has been chosen as a clinically significant improvement in clinical practice that would make the use of such a monitor clinically beneficial.  This is supported by evidence that reduction in pain intensity by 30% to 35% from baseline has been rated as clinically meaningful by patients with postoperative pain.  It has been shown recently in an observational study that the mean NPRS upon waking from anaesthesia was 5 following ENT and endoscopic proceedures and the standard deviation used in the sample size calculation has been taken from research examining NPRS post-operatively. 

Previous studies from other investigators looking at the effect of intraoperative drug delivery and monitoring of analgesia and have required between 40-80 subjects.  We believe that 50 subjects will be sufficient to detect a difference between the groups if one exists.  We plan to recruit 30 participants to each group (Total 60) to allow withdrawals from the study and data failures.  
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>13/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>54</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Adelaide
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Adelaide
North Terrace 
Adelaide SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Guy Ludbrook</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Professor of Anaesthesia and Intensive Care
University of Adelaide
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Jamie Sleigh</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Professor of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
22 Princes St Auckland
New Zealand 1010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed study aims to evaluate Analgesia Nociception Index (ANI) titrated analgesia in patients undergoing spinal surgery.  This clinical utility study is designed to investigate the effect of ANI guided fentanyl administration on post-operative events, including self-reported post-operative pain scores, analgesia administration, recovery times, and opioid-related side effects.  The study will also record the incidence of unwanted intra-operative events such as tachycardia, hypertension, and the consumption of fentanyl under constant hypnotic level balanced general anaesthesia.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Level 3 Hanson Building
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>130714</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Wing</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Hyperbaric Medicine
North Terrace
The Royal Adelaide Hospital
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882224000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrewwing1@netscape.net</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Wing</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Hyperbaric Medicine
North Terrace
The Royal Adelaide Hospital
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882224000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrewwing1@netscape.net</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Wing</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Hyperbaric Medicine
North Terrace
The Royal Adelaide Hospital
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882224000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrewwing1@netscape.net</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Wing</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Hyperbaric Medicine
North Terrace
The Royal Adelaide Hospital
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61882224000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrewwing1@netscape.net</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>