<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365677">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000391673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Preoperative tramadol combined with diclofenac sodium reduces intraoperative loading dose of tramadol in patients undergoing abdominal hysterectomy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Preoperative tramadol combined with diclofenac sodium reduces intraoperative loading dose of tramadol in patients undergoing abdominal hysterectomy: A randomized trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1152-4158</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postoperative pain
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>35-65 year-old, 45 ASA I and II patients, undergoing elective total abdominal hysterectomy (TAH) with or without bilateral salpingo-oopherectomy (BSO) under general anesthesia in Ankara EZH Research and Teaching Hospital, were enrolled (1:1:1) into this prospective, randomized, double-blind study. All patients received 1 mg/kg intravenous (iv) tramadol (infused in 100 ml NS over 15 minutes) and 75 mg intramuscular (im) diclofenac sodium 30 minutes before surgery. The patients were randomized into three groups (using computer-generated random numbers list with codes in sealed envelopes) to receive either placebo (Group I), 0.5 mg/kg (Group II) or 1 mg/kg (Group III) iv tramadol at the begining of the fascia closure, about 30 minutes before the end of surgery. The different doses of tramadol, prepared and labeled according to codes, were in equal volume syringes (in normal saline).  Our hypothesis was iv tramadol combined with im diclofenac sodium administered 30 minutes before the operation, reduces intraoperative loading dose. </interventions>
    <comparator>Group I received Placebo (intravenous saline) for intraoperative loading dose.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tramadol-PCA consumption in the first 24 hours postoperatively</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative 24 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergence time (time elapsed from the termination of anesthetic agents to gaining the ability of spontaneous eye opening, gripping fingers and breathing deeply on request) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>sedation score (alert,0; drowsy but rousable to voice,1; drowsy but rousable to shaking,2) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>postoperative nausea and vomiting </outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first activation of Patient Control Analgesia (PCA)(time elapsed from the administration of intraoperative loading dose) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Verbal rating scale scores (Pain: none,0; mild,1; moderate,2; strong,3; unbearable,4)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>rescue analgesic medication</outcome>
      <timepoint>postoperative 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Elective Total Abdominal Hysterctomy with or without BSO under general anesthesia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known allergy, sensitivity or contraindications to study drugs, inability to use PCA device, long-term use of opioid medications, use of any analgesic drugs in the last 24 hours, history of clinically significant cardiac, respiratory, hepatic or renal disease and history of chronic pain and previous history of postoperative nausea and vomiting. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/07/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/01/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Ankara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Turkish Ministery of Health Ankara Etlik ZH Maternity and Women’s Health Research and Teaching Hospital, Ankara, Turkey</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Asagi Eglence Mah., Yeni Etlik Cd, 06010 Etlik (Incirli)/Ankara

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>none</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>none</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Intraoperative use of loading doses of tramadol-patient control analgesia (PCA) has been recommended in previously published articles. It is recommended mostly due to its diminishing effect on the frequency of postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) at Postanesthesia Care Unit (PACU), which is immediately after surgery. There is also a recommendation on the optimal intraoperative loading dose actually by the same authors, which is 2.5 mg.kg-1.  We used this recommended optimal dose in our clinic, and we observed that emergence times of our patients prolonged to a duration of more than 40 minutes. We planned this study in order to reduce the need for intraoperative loading dose to a lower dose than 2.5 mg.kg-1. We hypothesized that preoperatively administered analgesics reduce the intraoperative loading dose. Our results revealed that this optimal dose may be reduced to a lower dose, while both providing adequate analgesia with less tramadol-PCA consumption.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>IRB of Turkish Ministery of Health Ankara Etlik ZH Maternity and Women’s Health Research and Teaching Hospital </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>IRB of Turkish Ministery of Health Ankara Etlik ZH Maternity and Womens Health Research and Teaching Hospital, Etik Kurul Asagi Eglence Mah., Yeni Etlik Cd, 06010 Etlik (Incirli)/Ankara

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Filiz Uzumcugil</name>
      <address>Hacettepe University School of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation 06100 Sihhiye-ANKARA</address>
      <phone>+903123051265</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>filizuzumcugil@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Filiz Uzumcugil</name>
      <address>Hacettepe University School of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation 06100 Sihhiye-ANKARA</address>
      <phone>+903123051265</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>filizuzumcugil@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Filiz Uzumcugil</name>
      <address>Hacettepe University School of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation 06100 Sihhiye-ANKARA</address>
      <phone>+903123051265</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>filizuzumcugil@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>