<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373021">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000936325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lactate values as a risk stratifying tool in the Adult Emergency department for the unwell and undifferentiated patient 

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The usefulness and validity of using lactate clearance and serial lactate measurements in the Emergency Department as a risk stratifying tool for the unwell and undifferentiated adult patient</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1197-0257</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Unwell and Undifferentiated patient</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Shortness of breath</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chest pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Syncope</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sepsis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will be observing lactate clearance in the emergency department patient that are undifferentiated and unwell adult patients and if this is a useful tool in identifying the deteriorating patient early and those that need to be admitted into hospital for care.  These patients will have their capillary/venous/arterial lactate recorded by a point of care device from Nova Biomedical measured at 1 hour and 3 hours of stay.  Their readings and clearance and range will be looked at and their patient disposition ie discharge point to home, hospital, critical care unit and deaths.  Their outcome will be observed for 72 hours post leaving the Emergency Department.  

These lactate measurements will be taken from different groups of patients in the emergency department at different times so that it allows for staff to focus on one group at a time eg sepsis patients, patients with shortness of breath.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality (death) </outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours post ED discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Discharge location ie home , rehabilitation or still as inpatient- will be determined by medical record review and phone call at 72 hours post discharge from hospital (as inpatient or from Emergency Department)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The time they leave emergency and at 72 hours post leaving the emergency department</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The range of lactate readings for our focus population in the emergency department using the nova lactate meter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 hour of stay and 3 hours of stay in the emergency department</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Triage number and if that was changed to a higher category number as a result of using the Statstrip lactate meter (High reading) using our medical record system in the emergency department Firstnet</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the time of entry at study and whilst in the emergency department</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>if the location of patient changed in the emergency department to a more acute setting ie acute care to resuscitation bay by using the medical record whilst they are in emergency (Firstnet)</outcome>
      <timepoint>time in ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost of running the StatStrip point of care lactate meter vs using the venous blood gas machine (Roche BL800) theoretically if used instead.  This will be calculated using excel spreadsheet per patient and the costs for the department.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Times used in the emergency department for each patient</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Person greater than or equal to 18 years of age
- Triaged for assessment in adult acute assessment
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion of persons with the following comorbidities/presentation:
1. Seizure
2. Severe hepatic failure
3. Patients that did not stay for their treatment in the department
4. Biguanide therapy (phenformin, metformin) 
5. Patients unable to give consent eg low GCS, dementia
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be recorded using statistical database software such as SPSS to analyse and store data.  We will then analyse the data to look for cut off points from a receiver operator characteristic curve to compare deterioration of a patient in the department or first 72 hours, disposition of a patient is discharge from ED location and mortality.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Louisa Ng</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal North Shore Hospital Emergency Department
Reserve Road, St Leonards 2065, NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal North Shore Hospital Emergency Department</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Reserve Road, St Leonards 2065, NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nova Biomedical</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nova Biomedical
200 Prospect Street
Waltham, MA 02454-9141 U.S.A.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mark Gillett</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal North Shore Hospital Emergency Department
Reserve Road, St Leonards 2065, NSW</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Nova Biomedical</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Nova Biomedical
200 Prospect Street
Waltham, MA 02454-9141 U.S.A.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Research Question 
Can measurements of lactate clearance with a point of care lactate measuring device (StatStripAccutrend) assist in the management and early identification of patients at higher risk of deterioration in the emergency department?    
Rationale for Current Study
In the emergency department, the undifferentiated patient presents a diagnostic and time management challenge.  Lactate is used as a surrogate marker for global hypoperfusion in sepsis, trauma and patients with surgical abdomens, but there are also other areas of developing interest where lactate measurements could be used to assist in fast tracking decisions and risk stratifying patients to decide their disposition.
Primary Objective
1. To measure serial lactate measurements in the ED within the first hour of presentation and at 3 hours of stay to monitor and predict deterioration in the department or the hospital in the first 72 hours?
STUDY DESIGN
This study is a prospective longitudinal study where data will be collected over a year.  The data will be collected with written or and verbal consent, and fact sheet given to the participant about the study.  Verbal and written consent will be obtained at the first reading and second readings taken to make sure that participants are happy to continue with the study.  Patients can withdraw at any time in the study.  Exclusion criteria of patients will include those that are &lt;18 years old, severe hepatic failure, presentation of known seizure disorders and those triaged to other areas apart from the adult acute area or self discharged from the department before completion of treatment, if they dont have a serial measurement of their lactate at 3 hours.  The lactate measurements will be recorded at a time within one hour of presentation and the second reading at 3 hours of presentation electronically on their medical records.  The data will then be extracted and de-identified for this research project and determined if the participant is to be excluded or included in the study.  .  This study to reach the sample size of 1000 participants would approximately go over the course of 6 months to a year.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nova Biomedical will be supplying equipment for no fee and will not influence the study nor access to raw data - only final data and write up and interim reports</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louisa Ng</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Emergency Department
Reserve Road
St Leonards, New South Wales
2065</address>
      <phone>+61425247862</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rnshedlactate@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mark Gillett</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Emergency Department
Reserve Road
St Leonards, New South Wales
2065</address>
      <phone>+61294632222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mark.Gillett@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mark Gillett</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Emergency Department
Reserve Road
St Leonards, New South Wales
2065</address>
      <phone>+61294632222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mark.Gillett@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Louisa Ng</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Emergency Department
Reserve Road
St Leonards, New South Wales
2065</address>
      <phone>+61425247862</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rnshedlactate@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>