<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365376">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001317785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MIART: Can melatonin improve the live birth rate in infertile couples undergoing assisted reproductive technologies?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double-blind randomised placebo-controlled dose-response trial assessing the effects of melatonin on infertility treatment (MIART)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1150-7764</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MIART</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infertility</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This trial will have four arms. All capsules will be indistinguishable from each other.
1.	Placebo capsule taken twice per day
2.	2mg melatonin capsule twice per day (4mg/d total)
3.	4mg melatonin capsule twice per day (8mg/d total)
4.	8mg melatonin capsule twice per day (16mg/d total)

The participant will commence taking the trial medication on the day that she begins ovarian stimulation injections (Day 2-3 of her natural menses) at 0800 and 2200 each day, with the last capsule being taken at 2200 the night before oocyte collection. Each participant will undergo an assisted reproductive technology as deemed appropriate by their treating clinician. Melatonin has a very short half-life. Consequently, no significant period of time is required for 'washout'. If a participant does not fall pregnant in her first trial cycle, she will be offered randomisation to a different treatment arm for her next cycle.

In order to ensure the integrity of study data, participant adherence to trial protocol will be assessed on a medication administration record updated daily by the participant. At oocyte collection, participants will return medication bottles and compliance will be confirmed by counting remaining tablets. This will be recorded on individual patient compliance forms and patient record forms.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - equivalent appearance</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Pregnancy rate - defined as the presence of a live pregnancy in the uterine cavity at a transvaginal ultrasound after approximately 7 weeks gestation</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Miscarriage rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Follicular fluid and serum levels of melatonin</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Follicular fluid and serum levels of 8-OHDG</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Live birth rate - Birth of a live baby after 24 weeks gestation</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleepiness score - based on the Karolinska sleepiness scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pregnancy complication rate - Including ovarian hyperstimulation syndrome (OHSS), multiple pregnancy, congenital or chromosomal abnormalities, stillbirth, preeclampsia, delivery before 34 weeks, delivery between 34 and 37 weeks, placenta praevia, gestational diabetes, low birthweight</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of oocytes collected</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical pregnancy rate - Presence of serum hCG level of &gt;25IU/l on Day 16 after embryo transfer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 16 after embryo transfer</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oestradiol and Progesterone levels - serum assays</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Follicular blood flow and uterine artery blood flow - pelvic Power Doppler ultrasound 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>approximately 2 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>oocyte quality - graded visually using a standardised grading chart into germinal vesicle, meiosis I or meiosis II at time of oocyte collection</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of oocyte colelction</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>total number and quality of embryos - graded visually using standardised scale into Grades 1-4</outcome>
      <timepoint>Just prior to embryo transfer (Day 3-5 post oocyte collection)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>fertilization rate - the number of oocytes that become fertilised</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3-5 post oocyte collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Utilisation rate = (number of embryos transferred or frozen)/(number of oocytes fertilised), assessed by count.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Requiring first cycle of IVF or ICSI for infertility treatment
- Age between 18 and 45
- Undergoing a GnRH antagonist cycle (without OCP scheduling)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Current untreated pelvic pathology  Stage 3 or 4 endometriosis, large submucosal uterine fibroids/polyps thought by the specialist to affect fertility, diagnosed current pelvic inflammatory disease, uterine malformations (i.e uterine didelphys, bicornuate uterus and septate uterus), Asherman's syndrome and the current diagnosis of a hydrosalpinx (not treated).
2.	Currently enrolled in another investigational trial
3.	Concurrent use of other adjuvant therapies (eg. Co Enzyme Q10, acupuncture)
4.	Current pregnancy
5.	Malignancy or other contraindication to IVF
6.	Autoimmune disorders
7.	Will not have regular blood tests with Monash IVF (because of distance from Monash IVF)
8.	Undergoing preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD)
9.	Hypersensitivity to melatonin or its metabolites
10.	Concurrent use of any of the following medications
a.	Fluvoxamine (eg. Luvox, Movox, Voxam)
b.	Cimetidine (eg. Magicul, Tagamet)
c.	Quinolones and other CYP1A2 inhibitors (Ciprofloxacin, Avalox)
d.	Carbemazepine (eg. Tegretol), rifampicin (eg.Rifadin) and other CYP1A2 inducers
e.	Zolpidem (eg Stilnox), zopiclone (eg. Imovane) and other non-benzodiazepine hypnotics
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participating clinicians will flag suitable patients to the primary investigator. The primary investigator will approach identified patients at the time of attendance for treatment with IVF and obtain informed consent for inclusion in the trial.
Each treatment arm will be randomly allocated a letter (A, B, C or D) by way of opaque sealed envelope (allocation concealment). Randomisation will be computerised and patients will be randomised at a ratio of 1:1:1:1 to one of the groups, A-D, using the minimisation method, which is a method of randomisation based on factors known to affect the outcome used in small trials to prevent selection bias. Participants will be blinded by receiving identical-appearing unmarked capsules. No trial researchers will be aware of participant allocation until after analyses are performed at the completion of the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Minimisation method. Ad hoc allocation based on characteristics of the patient and relative numbers in each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As this is a pilot dose-finding study, without precedence on which to base accurate power calculations, a power calculation has not been performed. Part of our aim is to provide clarification allowing for larger randomised trials to be designed in the future. We have chosen to recruit 160 participants, 40 in each group in order to assess biochemical and sonographic secondary outcomes as well as to provide an indication of effect size with our primary outcome, clinical pregnancy rate. Statistical analyses will be performed using Chi-square tests for categorical outcome variables. Clinical and demographic data will be analysed with parametric tests if they are normally distributed, otherwise appropriate non-parametric tests will be used. SPSS v20 (IBM, Armonk, New York 2011) will be used for data analysis. P &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant. Adjustments will be made for confounding factors where this is statistically sound.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/08/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>160</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Epworth Richmond - Richmond</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Surgical Private Hospital - Clayton</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash University
Victoria 3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash IVF Research and Education Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash Surgical Private Hospital, Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash Medical Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>246 Clayton rd
Clayton 
VIC 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to determine whether melatonin supplementation has a dose response effect on clinical pregnancy rates, together with numerous important clinical, biochemical and sonographic secondary outcome measures. This will be achieved by a series of experiments designed to investigate the effect of melatonin on follicular fluid, serum, embryo and oocyte parameters as well as assessing clinical pregnancy rates and delivery rates</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>246 Clayton rd
Clayton 
VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13402B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shavi Fernando</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Level 5
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61395946666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shavif@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shavi Fernando</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Level 5
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61395946666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shavif@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shavi Fernando</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Level 5
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61395946666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shavif@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shavi Fernando</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
Level 5
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd Clayton
3168</address>
      <phone>+61395946666</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shavif@Hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>