<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373006">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000826347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of iodine dye injected into long central venous catheter, on Thyroid Function in Premature Infants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of iodine dye injected into long line on Thyroid Function in Premature Infants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PITFALLS (Premature Infant Thyroid Function After Long Line Study)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Thyroid function</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Premature birth</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Thyroid disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The PITFALLS study is a double-blind randomised controlled trial. Infants will be randomised to receive the study agent (iodine dye or normal saline). Treatment allocation will be made by the method of stratified block randomisation using computer generated codes. Randomisation will be done by the clinical trials pharmacist soon after successful insertion of the Peripherally Inserted Central venous Catheter (PICC) line. 
Treatment arm will receive 0.2 mL water-soluble, non-ionic, iodine-containing agent iohexol [Omnipaque (Trademark) 180, GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, UK] through PICC line during X-ray. The doctor who inserts the PICC Line will administer the study agent. X-ray including antero-posterior with or without lateral view will be done in the NICU. 
Control arm will receive 0.2 mL normal saline through PICC line during X-ray.
Both these agents will be prepared in identical looking syringes in the Pharmacy and labelled as Study agent. Only the clinical trials pharmacist will be aware of the agent and will not be involved in the study. All others will be blinded as to what study agent is being administered to infants.
Intervention adherence: Dose will be documented on the medication chart as "Study agent" by the doctor who inject the agent and countersigned by the nurse assisting in PICC Line insertion. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control arm will receive 0.2 mL normal saline through PICC line during X-ray.
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thyroid function test results (Composite outcome of change in Free Thyroxine-fT4 and Thyroid Stimulating Hormone-TSH) in Control arm versus treatment arm.
Results will be assessed based on serum assay of fT4 and TSH</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Point 1 : BaselinefT4 and TSH just before insertion of PICC line (any time within 24 hours prior to insertion of PICC Line).
Time Point 2 : fT4 and TSH , 7 days after Time Point 1 (+/- 24 hours).
Time Point 3 : fT4 and TSH , 7 days after Time Point 2 (+/- 24 hours).
Time Point 4 : fT4 and TSH , 7 days after Time Point 3 (+/- 24 hours).
Time Point 5 : fT4 and TSH , 7 days after Time Point 4 (+/- 24 hours).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clearly identifiable tip position of PICC on X-ray. Assessed as categorical yes/No Outcome as judged by the clinician managing the baby.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following insertion of PICC line.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be admitted to the PITFALLS study if they fulfil the following criteria:
1. Premature infants 37 or less weeks
2. Admitted to NICU 
3. Require the insertion of a 28G PICC line.
4. Parental consent is obtained.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded from the PITFALLS study should they be:
1. Infants with diagnosed thyroid disorders
2. Born to mothers with thyroid disease with potential to influence fetal thyroid function (e.g. thyrotoxicosis)
3. Infants being given iodine iodine-containing contrast for some other reason.
4. PICC inserted for the second /subsequent times in an infant who was already enrolled once
5. Anuria
6. Severe decompensated cardiac failure
7. Major lethal congenital/chromosomal anomalies
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule (pharmacist) </concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified block randomisation using computer generated codes. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size determination:
We performed power calculations based on the results of 410 Nepean Hospital Newborn Intensive Care NBST TSH results, which gave a mean TSH of 1.94mU/L and standard deviation of 1.92. 
To estimate the effect size of iodine exposure on TSH levels, we used an estimate of a 91% rise in TSH to 3.7mU/L following iodine contrast exposure, which is similar to the 91% rise in TSH by day 7, seen in infants exposed to topical iodine in other studies (Smerdely P, Lim A, Boyages SC, et al. Topical iodine-containing antiseptics and neonatal hypothyroidism in very-low-birthweight infants. Lancet 1989; 2(8664): 661-4.). From these calculations, a sample size of 30 patients per group will give greater than 90% power to detect the change in TSH with a p-value of &lt;0.05. Allowing for a 10% non-compliance rate (e.g.: necessity to give open label iodine), there would be 88% power to detect the difference.
Each baby will be enrolled only once. Sometimes PICC may need to be inserted for the 2nd time in the same baby. In such situation the baby will not be enrolled in the study and PCVC insertion will be performed as per the standard Unit protocol.
Statistical methods:
Descriptive statistics of continuous data will be based on means (standard deviation) or median (interquartile range) depending on the statistical distribution of data normality. Categorical data will be summarised using frequency distributions.
Analyses of the primary outcome measures and endpoints will be according to treatment received, including neonates who do not complete the follow-up measurements. All p-values will be two-tailed without adjustment. A nominal significance level of 0.05 will be applied.
Univariate t-tests will be used to compare the primary outcomes between groups with placebo-assigned neonates acting as control in comparison. Mann-Whitney U-test, t-test and ANOVA will be used for comparisons of continuous outcomes. Fishers exact test will be used for categorical outcome.  Comparisons of anthropometric measurements at each time point will be analysed using repeated measures regression where the adjustments of measurements at birth will always be included in the outcome comparisons. 
All statistical analyses will be conducted with STATA (Registered Trademark) 14.0, SPSS (Registered Trademark) 23.0 or GraphPad Prism (Registered Trademark) 6.0 statistical software packages. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>6/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kiran Kumar Balegar Virupakshappa</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Neonatology, Nepean Hospital, Derby Street, Kingswood, NSW 2747</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nepean Medical Research Foundation (NMRF)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box1838, Penrith,  NSW 2751 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Premature babies admitted to neonatal intensive care units routinely undergo insertion of Peripherally Inserted Central venous Catheter (PICC) lines. It is a routine practice to perform x-ray to visualise the line tip to ensure it is in the ideal location. There is a varied practice in different NICUs in Australia, with some NICUs including Nepean Hospital NICU routinely injecting iodine containing dye to enhance visibility of PICC tip on x-ray. Exposure to high doses of iodine potentially increases the risk of hypothyroidism. Although the hypothyroidism due to iodine is likely transient, the effects during the critical period of neurological development in premature babies are potentially detrimental. There is paucity of evidence from randomised controlled study regarding the potential benefits and risks of using iodine-containing intravenous contrast in PICC insertions in premature babies. Thus, a study examining these outcomes in neonates with a placebo-controlled group is urgently required.

Design: double-blind RCT. Infants eligible for 28 G PICC line will be enrolled following parental consent. Participants will be excluded from the PITFALLS study should they be: Infants with diagnosed thyroid disorders, Born to mothers with thyroid disease with potential to influence fetal thyroid function, Infants being given iodine iodine-containing contrast for some other reason, PICC inserted for the second /subsequent times in an infant who was already enrolled once, Anuria, Severe decompensated cardiac failure, Major lethal congenital/chromosomal anomalies.

Babies will be randomised to receive the study agent(iodine dye or normal saline). Treatment allocation will be made by the method of stratified block randomisation using computer generated codes. Randomisation will be done by the clinical trials pharmacist, soon after successful insertion of the PICC. All others will be blinded.
Treatment arm will receive 0.2 mL water-soluble, non-ionic, iodine-containing agent iohexol [Omnipaque (Trademark) 180, GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, UK] through PICC line during X-ray.
Control arm will receive 0.2 mL normal saline through PICC line during X-ray.
Both these agents will be prepared in identical looking syringes in the Pharmacy and labelled as Study agent. Only the clinical trials pharmacist will be aware of the agent and will not be involved in the study. Researchers will be blinded as to what study agent is being administered to infants.
Primary outcome: fT4 and TSH in controls and exposed.
Primary end points: fT4 and TSH before PICC line insertion and subsequently on a weekly basis for next 4 weeks
Secondary outcome: Clearly identifiable tip position of PICC on X-ray
Secondary end point: Following successful insertion of PICC line
Sample size: 60
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Nepean Blue Mountains Local Health District Research Governance Office</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Nepean Hospital, Derby Street, Kingswood, NSW 2747</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SSA/15/NEPEAN/146</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kiran Kumar Balegar Virupakshappa</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatology, Nepean Hospital, Derby Street, Kingswood, NSW 2747</address>
      <phone>+61247342850</phone>
      <fax>+61247342698</fax>
      <email>Kiran.Balegarvirupakshappa@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kiran Kumar Balegar Virupakshappa</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatology, Nepean Hospital, Derby Street, Kingswood, NSW 2747</address>
      <phone>+61247342850</phone>
      <fax>+61247342698</fax>
      <email>Kiran.Balegarvirupakshappa@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kiran Kumar Balegar Virupakshappa</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatology, Nepean Hospital, Derby Street, Kingswood, NSW 2747</address>
      <phone>+61247342850</phone>
      <fax>+61247342698</fax>
      <email>Kiran.Balegarvirupakshappa@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kiran Kumar Balegar Virupakshappa</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatology, Nepean Hospital, Kingswood, NSW 2747</address>
      <phone>+61247342850</phone>
      <fax>+61247342698</fax>
      <email>Kiran.Balegarvirupakshappa@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>