<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370577">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000542493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of the use of a respiratory function monitor to teach
neonatal mask ventilation to healthcare professionals in a simulation setting</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of the use of a respiratory function monitor to teach
neonatal mask ventilation to healthcare professionals in a simulation setting</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-2232</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neonatal resuscitation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Training in mask ventilation will be conducted according to the Newborn Resuscitation (NeoResus) program with the addition of a Respiratory Function Monitor (RFM) attached to the t- piece device (Neopuff). This will provide continuous real time feedback on mask leak. Course participants will perform the mask ventilation skill station in groups of six. Neonatal mask ventilation training will last for 1 hour and 25 minutes in total. During this time period each participant will perform two episodes of mask ventilation, each lasting 90 seconds. The first episode will consist of the participant performing mask ventilation as a standalone skill. The second episode will consist of the participant performing mask ventilation as part of a simulated resuscitation scenario. Participants will be instructed on mask ventilation and on interpretation of the RFM. When performing mask ventilation, the participants will be instructed to achieve:
1. Minimal (0-10%) mask leak, and 
2. Mannequin chest rise
Both the participants and trainers will observe leak and chest rise during ventilation. Participants will adjust their technique to minimise the leak by making the following changes: 
1. Reposition airway to the neutral position, avoid neck flexion or overextension 
2. Mask adjustment: adjust face mask hold, ensure face mask is covering nose and mouth, ensure mask is pressed against mannequin face, adjust face mask position on face, reapply face mask 
Participants will be advised of additional manoeuvers (suction mouth and nose, open mouth, increase pressure, consider an alternative airway) to attempt if they are unable to obtain chest rise and improvement in heart rate/colour and saturations in the simulation setting.

Quality assurance:

Supervision;
Each training course is supervised by 3-4 Nurse educators and 1-2 medical educators (Neonatal fellow and neonatal consultant or two neonatal fellows)

Measurement of participant adherence and compliance to teaching protocol;

Compliance with the standardisation of training and instruction will be ensured by facilitator instruction pre-course, assessment of facilitators, the use of checklists to assist facilitators, intermittent reassessment of each facilitator (6 monthly) and the presence of an independent researcher at each station, who is responsible for compliance with the study protocol i.e. timing of intervention, clarity and order of instruction. Compliance with the protocol will be recorded in each participant CRF.
Significant non-compliance is defined as a participant failing to perform two episodes of mask ventilation or performed mask ventilation for under 50% of the allocated time. Facilitators and researchers will be advised to report each incidence of significant non-compliance to the PI. A high number of non-compliance incidents will trigger a protocol review.

Assessment:
Immediately after the skill session, participants will be reassessed and mask leak will be recorded for 90 seconds of mask ventilation. This timeframe was chosen because international guidelines recommend operators re-assess the airway every 30 seconds and we wish to capture at least 2 reassessment episodes. 


</interventions>
    <comparator>Training in mask ventilation will be conducted according to the Newborn Resuscitation (NeoResus) program with a T-piece device (Neopuff). Participants will perform the mask ventilation skill station in groups of six. Neonatal mask ventilation training will last for 1 hour and 25 minutes in total. During this time period each participant will perform two episodes of mask ventilation, each lasting 90 seconds. The first episode will consist of the participant performing mask ventilation as a standalone skill. The second episode will consist of the participant performing mask ventilation as part of a simulated resuscitation scenario. 
Participants will be instructed on mask ventilation. When performing mask ventilation, the participants will be instructed to achieve adequate mannequin chest rise. Both the participants and trainers will observe chest rise during ventilation. 
Participants will adjust their technique to improve chest rise by making the following changes: 
1. Reposition airway to the neutral position, avoid neck flexion or overextension
2. Mask adjustment: adjust face mask hold, ensure face mask is covering nose and mouth, ensure mask is pressed against mannequin face, adjust face mask position on face, reapply face mask 
Participants will be advised of additional manoeuvers (suction mouth and nose, open mouth, increase pressure, consider an alternative airway) to attempt if they are unable to obtain chest rise and improvement in heart rate/colour and saturations in the clinical setting. 

Assessment:
Immediately after the skill session, participants will be reassessed and mask leak will be recorded for 90 seconds of mask ventilation. This timeframe was chosen because international guidelines recommend operators re-assess the airway every 30 seconds and we wish to capture at least 2 reassessment episodes. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is difference in leak measured after neonatal mask ventilation training between the control and intervention groups. Leak between the mask and the mannequin face will be measured. The expiratory leak will be calculated from the volume of gas that does not return back through the flow sensor on expiration, expressed as a percentage of the inspired volume.
Leak (%) = (inflating tidal volume - expired tidal volume     x100) / inflating tidal volume
 A Florian Respiratory Function monitor (Acutronic Medical Systems, Zug, Switzerland) will be used to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. The monitor measures flow directly through a line connected at the T-piece. Gas flow is measured using a flow sensor placed between the mask and the Neopuff. The monitor integrates the flow signal to determine the tidal volume of gas passing through the sensor. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measure immediately after completion of 1 hour 25 minutes of training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in expired tidal volume
A Florian Respiratory Function monitor (Acutronic Medical Systems, Zug, Switzerland) will be used to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. The monitor measures flow directly through a line connected at the T-piece. Gas flow is measured using a flow sensor placed between the mask and the Neopuff. The monitor integrates the flow signal to determine the tidal volume of gas passing through the sensor. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured immediately after 1 hour 25 minutes of training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stability of tidal volume achieved ie consistency of tidal volumes in consecutive breaths.
A Florian Respiratory Function monitor (Acutronic Medical Systems, Zug, Switzerland) will be used to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. The monitor measures flow directly through a line connected at the T-piece. Gas flow is measured using a flow sensor placed between the mask and the Neopuff. The monitor integrates the flow signal to determine the tidal volume of gas passing through the sensor. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured immediately after 1 hour 25 minutes of training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of obstructed breaths
A Florian Respiratory Function monitor (Acutronic Medical Systems, Zug, Switzerland) will be used to measure inflating pressures and gas flow. The monitor measures flow directly through a line connected at the T-piece. Gas flow is measured using a flow sensor placed between the mask and the Neopuff. The monitor integrates the flow signal to determine the tidal volume of gas passing through the sensor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured immediately after 1 hour 25 minutes of training</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Each participant must meet the following criteria to be enrolled in the study:
1. Over 18 years of age
2. One of the following healthcare professionals: Doctors from any specialty, midwives, nurses, physiotherapists, occupational therapists, paramedics, or a medical, nursing or midwifery student
3. Attending the Victorian Neonatal Resuscitation training program. Attendees of both the first response program (3 hours duration) and the Advanced Resuscitation (7 hours duration) are eligible.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Unable or unwilling to provide written informed consent
2. Attendees who are not one of the healthcare professional groups or student groups listed above will not be included 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be achieved using sequentially numbered, sealed opaque envelopes. Study envelopes will be kept in the Paediatric Infant Perinatal Emergency Retrieval (PIPER) Education office, Second floor, Royal Children’s Hospital, Parkville, VIC 3052, Australia.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size Estimation

Mask leak has been reported between 14-65% in neonatal mannequin studies and 29% (interquartile range 16-63%) in preterm infant resuscitation studies. Assuming a median leak of 50% in the control group and a standard deviation of 30% a sample size of 382 (191 in each arm) would give a power of 90% to detect a 10% absolute difference in leak (50% leak versus 40% leak). Fourteen neonatal resuscitation courses are planned in the Royal Childrens Hospital, Melbourne in 2016 with 24 participants per course. We estimate that consent, equipment and availability of researchers will allow for 12 participants per course to be enrolled. We therefore expect to be able to complete recruitment in 27 months.

Statistical Analysis Plan 

Analysis will be performed on an intention-to-treat basis. Data will be analysed using Stata software (Intercooled 10, Stata Corp, College Station, Texas, USA). The data will be presented as mean (standard deviation) for normally distributed variables and median (interquartile range) when the distribution is skewed. The clinical characteristics and outcome variables will be analysed by using the Student t test for parametric and Mann-Whitney U test for nonparametric comparisons of continuous variables and Chi squared for categorical variables. Data will be clustered by operator. P values will be 2-sided and P values of less than 0.05 will be considered statistically significant</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>12/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>382</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>262</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>The Women’s at Sandringham - Sandringham</hospital>
    <hospital>Frankston Hospital - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Malvern - Malvern</hospital>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <hospital>Wimmera Health Care Group - Horsham - Horsham</hospital>
    <hospital>Latrobe Regional Hospital - Traralgon</hospital>
    <hospital>Northeast Health Wangaratta - Wangaratta</hospital>
    <hospital>Albury Wodonga Health - Wodonga campus - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Benalla Health - Benalla</hospital>
    <hospital>Djerriwarrh Health Service - Bacchus Marsh - Bacchus Marsh</hospital>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong Hospital campus - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>Castlemaine Health - Castlemaine</hospital>
    <hospital>Cohuna District Hospital - Cohuna</hospital>
    <hospital>Colac Area Health - Colac</hospital>
    <hospital>Echuca Regional Health - Echuca</hospital>
    <hospital>Epworth Freemasons - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Western District Health Service - Hamilton - Hamilton</hospital>
    <hospital>Gippsland Southern Health Service - Leongatha campus - Leongatha</hospital>
    <hospital>Maryborough Hospital - Maryborough</hospital>
    <hospital>The Bays Hospital - Mornington - Mornington</hospital>
    <hospital>West Gippsland Healthcare Group - Warragul</hospital>
    <hospital>Southwest Health Care - Warrnambool - Warrnambool</hospital>
    <hospital>Werribee Mercy Hospital - Werribee</hospital>
    <hospital>Bass Coast Regional Health - Wonthaggi</hospital>
    <hospital>Kyneton District Health Service - Kyneton</hospital>
    <postcode>3191 - Sandringham</postcode>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <postcode>3076 - Epping</postcode>
    <postcode>3400 - Horsham</postcode>
    <postcode>3844 - Traralgon</postcode>
    <postcode>3677 - Wangaratta</postcode>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <postcode>3672 - Benalla</postcode>
    <postcode>3340 - Bacchus Marsh</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3450 - Castlemaine</postcode>
    <postcode>3568 - Cohuna</postcode>
    <postcode>3250 - Colac</postcode>
    <postcode>3564 - Echuca</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3300 - Hamilton</postcode>
    <postcode>3953 - Leongatha</postcode>
    <postcode>4650 - Maryborough</postcode>
    <postcode>3931 - Mornington</postcode>
    <postcode>3820 - Warragul</postcode>
    <postcode>3280 - Warrnambool</postcode>
    <postcode>3030 - Werribee</postcode>
    <postcode>3995 - Wonthaggi</postcode>
    <postcode>3444 - Kyneton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Research Excellence and Newborn Research Centre, Royal Women's Hospital Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington rd,
Parkville
VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Women's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Flemington rd,
Parkville
VIC 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to improve how we teach doctors, nurses and midwives how to breath for babies not breathing at birth. The primary objective is to compare the leak from mask ventilation performed on a mannequin, after learning using a respiratory function monitor and after learning without using a respiratory function monitor.

The design is a single centre, randomised controlled trial. The participants will be randomised to either the intervention group (neonatal mask ventilation taught with a respiratory function monitor) or control (standard teaching of neonatal mask ventilation). 

Adult health care professionals attending the Victorian Neonatal Resuscitation training program (a structured simulation training program, NeoResus) in the Royal Childrens Hospital during the study period will be eligible to participate. 382 (191 in each arm) participants are expected, over 2 years 3 months.

The primary outcome is the difference in leak measured after neonatal mask ventilation training between the control and intervention groups. Secondary outcomes are difference in the volume of breaths, the stability of breaths and the number of obstructed breaths.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Children’s Hospital Melbourne Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>50 Flemington Rd
Parkville
Vic 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RCH HREC Reference Number: 36031A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370577-Protocol 21.03.16.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370577-36031A HREC and Governance (06.04.2016).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eoin O Currain</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Centre
20 Flemington Rd
Royal Women's Hospital
Parkville
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61, 3, 83453763</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eoin.ocurrain@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eoin O Currain</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Centre
20 Flemington Rd
Royal Women's Hospital
Parkville
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61, 3, 83453763</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eoin.ocurrain@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eoin O Currain</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Centre
20 Flemington Rd
Royal Women's Hospital
Parkville
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61, 3, 83453763</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eoin.ocurrain@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eoin O Currain</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Centre
20 Flemington Rd
Royal Women's Hospital
Parkville
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61, 3, 83453763</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eoin.ocurrain@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>