<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370690">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000634471p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mobile Mindfulness Meditation as an Adjunct to Treatment-as-usual: A Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Mobile Mindfulness Meditation as an Adjunct to Treatment-as-usual for Distressed University Students who Require Counselling: A Randomised Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-8250</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mental Health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We aim to recruit a representative sample of 360 Dunedin-based students from the University of Otago who are considered distressed (as indicated by opting in to the counselling service at Student Health Services). Participants will be guided through mindfulness meditation practice using an application (app) once daily for 10- 20 minutes for 30 days. 

Participants will be randomised into one of three conditions: 
Arm1: Mobile Mindfulness Meditation beginning before formal treatment (in the interim between initial assessment and beginning of treatment), This will be sent to participants immediately following enrolment (irrespective of when they are scheduled to begin their treatment at the Counselling Service which due to the nature of this setting could be 1 day to several weeks). 
Arm 2: Mobile Mindfulness Meditation beginning during treatment-as-usual, This will be sent to participants on the day that they begin treatment.
Arm 3: Wait-list control with Mobile Mindfulness Meditation following treatment-as-usual. This will be sent to participants on the day they end treatment.

All participants will be asked to download and integrate the mindfulness meditation app into their daily routine for 30 days. The app will be downloaded to their personal smartphone. All participants will be asked to answer surveys of psychological outcomes at the outset of app-use, and 14-28 days into app-use. Other than recruitment, all aspects of this study will occur via mobile or email. 

In order to obtain adherence data, during the information and consent process, participants will agree to allow the Mobile Mindfulness Meditation app (Headspace) to provide researchers with user data such as, number of sessions completed, and date/time of session. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 3: Wait-list control with Mobile Mindfulness Meditation following treatment-as-usual. Participants in Arm 3 will receive treatment-as-usual through Student Health Services' Counselling Service. At the end of their treatment they will be asked to download and use the mobile mindfulness meditation app for 30 days. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distress as measured by the K10 </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at beginning of intervention exposure, 14 days after access to app is made available, at beginning of treatment-as-usual, at end of treatment-as-usual.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression as measured by the Beck Depression Inventory II (BDI II)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at beginning of intervention exposure, 14 days after access to app is made available, at beginning of treatment-as-usual, at end of treatment-as-usual.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety as measured by the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at beginning of intervention exposure, 14 days after access to app is made available, at beginning of treatment-as-usual, at end of treatment-as-usual.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mindfulness as measured by the Cognitive and Affective Mindfulness Scale-Revised </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at beginning of intervention exposure, 14 days after access to app is made available, at beginning of treatment-as-usual, at end of treatment-as-usual.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological well-being as measured by the flourishing scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at beginning of intervention exposure, 14 days after access to app is made available, at beginning of treatment-as-usual, at end of treatment-as-usual.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived stress as measured by the Perceived Stress Scale 10</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at beginning of intervention exposure, 14 days after access to app is made available, at beginning of treatment-as-usual, at end of treatment-as-usual.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resilience as measured by the Brief Resilience Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at beginning of intervention exposure, 14 days after access to app is made available, at beginning of treatment-as-usual, at end of treatment-as-usual.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for this study, participants must be at least part-time University of Otago students, and own a smartphone (roughly 97% of student body; Flett et al., 2015). As this study aims to recruit distressed participants, all participants will be invited to participate by their Student Health Services Counselling clinician if the clinician deems them to need further assistance through the Counselling Service. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those with pre-existent or prodromal psychotic illness, including schizophrenia, psychosis, bipolar disorder; high and imminent risk of suicide, or post-traumatic stress disorder will not be eligible to participate in the present study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves central randomisation via computer. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation) with additional stratified allocation using gender to stratify the sample. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We aim to recruit a representative sample of 360 Dunedin-based students from the University of Otago who are considered distressed (as indicated by opting in to the counselling service at Student Health Services). A clinically interesting difference for the K10 is regarded as 5 points (equivalent to a 0.5 unit change on each of the 10 items or roughly 0.5 of a standard deviation).  In order to provide 80% power to detect such a difference in change scores between any two arms of the study using a two-sided test at the 0.0167 level (i.e., conservatively allowing for a Bonferroni adjustment over the three post-hoc comparisons), based on an SD for changes of 8 (obtained via personal communication with Prof. Sunny Collings and Dr. James Stanley who conducted semantically similar studies of this nature in similar study populations e.g., Collings et al, 2012), this would require n = 56/arm.  Allowing for around 50% dropout/unusable data, n = 120 will be recruited for each group or n = 360 overall.

Analyses will test for differences between both the intervention groups (Mobile Mindfulness before and during Treatment-as-usual) and the waitlist control group (Mobile Mindfulness after Treatment-as-usual) on changes in psychological health at each stage of treatment (initial consult, onset of treatment, end of treatment) and the beginning and mid-point of access to the intervention. The effectiveness of the time of delivery in improving psychological health will also be tested by comparing changes between these groups. We will use a combination of difference scores, reliable change indices, and crossing clinical thresholds analysis to determine clinically meaningful change. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Otago
P.O. Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Funded from the Office of the Vice-Chancellor, University of Otago. </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Otago P.O. Box 56 Dunedin 9054 New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed study is a micro-longitudinal, 3-arm randomized controlled trial (RCT) investigating the influence of mobile mindfulness meditation on psychological well-being in an adult student population who report experiencing distress. This design will allow further investigation of whether there is a relationship between mobile mindfulness meditation and improved psychological outcomes and whether this relationship is contingent upon time of delivery of intervention. 
Prior to the commencement of this intervention, a pilot study, of similar design, was conducted in a normative population to ensure that the current research program was feasible, that Headspace was a suitable tool, and that the mobile mindfulness meditation app did no harm.
The proposed project will involve innovative assessment and intervention delivery methods utilizing mobile phone technology to increase positive psychological wellbeing in naturalistic environments over time.
Overall, the goal is to understand whether our intervention increases mindfulness practice and whether that increase in mindfulness practice translates into noticeable improvements in psychological well-being (better mood, lower depression), and whether such changes in well-being are mediated by psychological expectancies or therapeutic alliance with their clinician. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington, 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tess Patterson</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, 
Dunedin School of Medicine, 
Health Sciences,
University of Otago,
P.O. Box 56,
Dunedin 9054

</address>
      <phone>+6434709451</phone>
      <fax>+6434709684</fax>
      <email>tess.patterson@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jayde Flett</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Otago,
P.O. Box 56,
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434799427</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jflett@psy.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tess Patterson</name>
      <address>Dunedin School of Medicine, 
Health Sciences,
University of Otago,
P.O. Box 56,
Dunedin 9054

</address>
      <phone>+6434709451</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tess.patterson@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jayde Flett</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Otago,
P.O. Box 56,
Dunedin 9054

</address>
      <phone>+6434799427</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jflett@psy.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>