<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371209">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001145493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of High Flow Tracheostomy Device for weaning from Mechanical Ventilation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Determination of the effect of a high flow tracheostomy device on applying positive airway pressure and increasing end expiratory lung volume in patients weaning from long term mechanical ventilation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mechanical Ventilation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Tracheostomy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is 15 minutes of high flow oxygen treatment at 50L/min (intervention) via Highflow Trachesotomy interface (Optiflow (TM) Tracheostomy interface and MR850 heated humidifier, Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare). All oxygen therapy will humidified as per standard practice. Patients will act as their own control.  The order in which the intervention is applied will be randomised. A 15 minute washout period of standard low flow treatment will occur between the intervention and standard treatment. A registered ICU nurse with over 10 years experience will apply the interventions. The study will be conducted in the ICU of The Prince Charles Hospital. Oxygen saturation will be maintained at greater than 92% or as dictated by the treating intensivist. Electrical Impedance topography (EIT) will be used to measure end expiratory lung impedance (EELI) which correlates closely with end expiratory lung volume (EELV). EIT involves placing a belt containing sensors around the patients chest patients chest. A 6Fr cannula will be placed in the tracheostomy tube to 1cm from the proximal end. This will be conducted to a pressure transducer in order to measure airway pressures.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator treatment will be as per the intervention except that  it will use a regular T-Piece weaning kit at flow rates of 15L/min. These flow rates are much lower then the intervention. All measurements will be the same  Patients act as  their own control group. Oxygen therapy in the control group was also humidified.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in tracheal airway pressure as measured by a 6Fr cannula placed in the tracheostomy tube connected to a pressure transducer


</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 15 minutes of standard treatment a 2 minute continuous reading will be undertaken. A further 2 minutes of continuous data will be collected at the end of 15 minutes of high flow therapy. A 15 minute washout period of standard treatment ( low flow) will be conducted between interventions</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in EELV as measure by EELI using EIT</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 15 minutes of standard treatment a 2 minute continuous reading will be undertaken. A further 2 minutes of continuous data will be collected at the end of 15 minutes of high flow therapy. A 15 minute washout period of standard treatment ( low flow) will be conducted between interventions</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in respiratory rate as determined by EIT


</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 15 minutes of standard treatment a 2 minute continuous reading will be undertaken. A further 2 minutes of continuous data will be collected at the end of 15 minutes of high flow therapy. A 15 minute washout period of standard treatment ( low flow) will be conducted between interventions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in oxygenation as measured on arterial blood gas (ABG)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 15 minutes of standard treatment an ABG will be taken. A further ABG will be collected at the end of 15 minutes of high flow therapy. A 15 minute washout period of standard treatment ( low flow) will be conducted between interventions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in subjective dyspnoea score (modified Borg  score)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 15 minutes of standard treatment a modified Borg score will be undertaken. A further modified Borg score will be collected at the end of 15 minutes of high flow therapy. A 15 minute washout period of standard treatment ( low flow) will be conducted between interventions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Written informed consent
Male or female over 18 years of age
Tracheostomy in situ
Mechanical ventilation time over 96hrs
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient refusal
Patients unable to tolerate low flow oxygen as deemed by treating doctor 
Pneumothorax
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed Opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple Randomisation using random nature of non study staff placing allocations in envelopes</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients will be placed on normal T-Piece weaning device for 15 minutes to establish baseline measurements and then randomly allocated to either  a further 15 minutes on normal T-Piece device or 15 minutes on the  high flow device. At the end of 15 minutes a 15 minute washout period will occur (on normal T-Piece device) followed by 15 minutes on the opposite treatment arm</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be reported using simple descriptive statistics and compared using either a paired t-test or Wilcoxon signed rank test as appropriate. The study will recruit 20 patients, No power calculation was performed for this study and this number is based on previous work we have carried out in post op cardiac surgical patients using high flow nasal prongs which showed statistically significant improved changes of similar parameters. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>2/03/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Prince Charles Hospital, 627 Rode Road, Chermside Qld 4320</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Prince Charles Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 Administration Building
The Prince Charles Hospital, 627 Rode Road, Chermside</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The weaning of long term tracheostomised ICU patients from prolonged mechanical ventilation can be difficult, challenging and at a great financial cost to the health care institution. Humidified oxygen can be delivered via a humidified t-piece at up to 15 litres a minute but this is unlikely to offer any benefit in terms of generating positive airway pressure and increasing end expiratory lung volume.The High flow tracheostomy device (HFT) allows the delivery of warmed, humidified oxygen at a prescribed fraction of inspired oxygen (FiO2) at flow rates much higher than previously allowable with other delivery systems. The use of this method of oxygen and flow delivery in weaning off mechanical ventilation is becoming more common in our ICU and there is a real need to determine if this therapy generates positive airway pressure and increases end expiratory lung volume; to quantify these changes; and also to determine if this treatment has any clinically relevant benefit which will lead to improved outcomes for these patients.

Electrical Impedance Topography (EIT) is a relatively new non-invasive radiation-free imaging technique which can be used easily and safely at the bedside to provide real-time dynamic images of regional lung ventilation. Changes in end-expiratory lung impedance (EELI) as measured by EIT have been shown to have a strong linear correlation with changes in end-expiratory lung volume (EELV). Therefore, it will be possible to assess both pressure and volume simultaneously within the lung.

This study aims to determine if HFT has any clinically relevant benefit in weaning patients from mechanical ventilation by assessing whether this treatment provides positive airway pressure and an increase in EELV, in addition to assessing their effects on oxygenation, respiratory rate and subjective scoring of dyspnoea</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Human Research Ethics Comitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital 
Rode Road
Chermisde
Qld
4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/QPCH/179</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Corley</name>
      <address>Level 5 Clinical Sciences Building 
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Rode
Chermside
Qld
4320</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 5772</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amand.corley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Corley</name>
      <address>Level 5 Clinical Sciences Building 
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Rode
Chermside
Qld
4320</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 5772</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amand.corley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda Corley</name>
      <address>Level 5 Clinical Sciences Building 
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Rode
Chermside
Qld
4320</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 5772</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amand.corley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>