<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363624">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000130763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dietary prebiotic supplementation in adults with prediabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of dietary prebiotic supplementation versus maltodextrin on advanced glycation, insulin resistance and inflammatory biomarkers in adults with pre-diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1139-1544</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pre-diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>10 grams inulin powder taken orally once daily, for 24 weeks</interventions>
    <comparator>3.7 grams maltodextrin powder taken orally once daily, for 24 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean skin autofluorescence (which correlates with tissue accumulation of advanced glycation endproducts), measured by an AGE Reader, pre and post intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks after commencement of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary levels of 8-isoprostanes (corrected for urinary Creatinine)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HOMA-IR (This is an estimate of an individual's insulin resistance based on their fasting blood glucose and insulin levels)
HOMA-IR = Homeostasis Model Assessment - Insulin Resistance</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum adiponectin</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum myeloperoxidase</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum methylglyoxal concentration, as measured by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay) of blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feacal concentration of Branched Chain Fatty acids (proprionate, acetate and butyrate)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum lipopolysaccharide (LPS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and after 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c (glycated hemoglobin) measured in blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals diagnosed with prediabetes (Impaired Fasting Glucose or Impaired Glucose Tolerance) within the previous 12 months. Diagnosis will have been made at each individuals local GP clinic after undertaking an Oral Glucose Tolerance Test. Prediabetes was defined as a fasting plasma glucose concentration greater than or equal to 6.1 and less than 7.0 mmol/L followed by a 2-hour post glucose load glucose concentration less than 7.8 mmol/L, or a fasting plasma glucose less than 7.0 mmol/L followed by a 2-hour post glucose load glucose concentration greater than or equal to 7.8 and less than 11.1 mmol/L.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals previously diagnosed with type 1, type 2 diabetes or impaired renal function, individuals with any gastrointestinal pathology (coeliac disease, inflammatory bowel disease), cigarette smokers, pregnant women, individuals already taking antibiotics or dietary prebiotic or probiotic nutritional supplements, individuals taking aspirin or Vitamin B, individuals who have made major dietary or lifestyle changes in the previous three months, individuals who are unwilling to provide blood, urine and stool samples or are unable to attend their local pathology collection centre.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Doctors at local general practice clinics will provide all patients fulfilling the inclusion criteria with information about the study. Patients who are interested in undergoing further assessment for eligibility will contact one of the researchers by telephone, who will determine whether inclusion/exclusion criteria are met and provide further information about the trial. Potential trial participants will attend the general practice clinics to sign paperwork and undergo initial assessment by this researcher. At this time the participant will select an envelope from a collection of 40 sealed, opaque envelopes which details the participant's treatment allocation. The researcher will make a note of the treatment allocation and will ensure that each participant receives supplies of their correct treatment or placebo. This researcher will then have no further involvement in the collection of results or data analysis of this trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>When 40 participants have been recruited, the order that each participant attends the general practice clinic for initial assessment and treatment allocation will be determined using random number generation (Microsoft Excel)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intention-to-treat analysis will be performed. Data will be presented as means +/- SD. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov goodness-of-fit test will be used to test for normal distribution. Differences of means between groups will be analysed by the Student t-test or the non-parametric equivalent. Correlation analyses will be performed using the Pearson correlation coefficient. Significance of changes during the study will be assessed by comparing 1) change of means between baseline and end of study within each group by paired t test, 2) percentage of change from baseline to the end of the study between the intervention and the control groups by the Mann-Whitney U test, and 3) differences between the means of both groups at the end of the study by unpaired t test. Significant differences will be defined as a value of P&lt;0.05 based on two-sided tests. Effect sizes including 95% confidence intervals will be calculated for all significant outcomes. Data analysis will be performed using SPSS 20.0 software (SPSS, Chicago, IL).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/06/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3995 - Wonthaggi</postcode>
    <postcode>3953 - Leongatha</postcode>
    <postcode>3950 - Korumburra</postcode>
    <postcode>3960 - Foster</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Rural &amp; Indigenous Health 
PO Box 973
Moe
Victoria 3825</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Rural &amp; Indigenous Health
PO Box 973
Moe 
Victoria 3825</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Advanced glycation endproducts (AGEs) are formed within the human body as a normal consequence of metabolism, but their formation is accelerated in people with elevated blood glucose levels such as those with diabetes. Excessive AGEs are known to have negative effects within the body including contributing to kidney damage, stimulating inflammation and promoting changes in blood vessels which lead to heart disease. AGEs have been shown to contribute to the development of the complications of diabetes and more recently it has been hypothesised that AGEs may play a major role in the development of type 2 diabetes. Simple therapies aimed at reducing the progression of inflammation and insulin resistance are urgently needed to prevent or slow type 2 diabetes development in susceptible individuals. Dietary supplements (called prebiotics) which promote the growth of beneficial bacteria in the human bowel have been shown to reduce inflammation and improve insulin resistance, but their effect on AGEs is unknown. Taking a daily prebiotic dietary supplement which stimulates the growth of beneficial bacteria in the human bowel might offer protection against AGE-related pathology in people at risk of developing type 2 diabetes. This study aims to determine the effect of 24-week consumption of a prebiotic dietary supplement on tissue AGE (advanced glycation endproduct) levels, insulin resistance and inflammatory biomarkers in adults with pre-diabetes in comparison to those receiving a placebo supplement. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University
Clayton Campus
Wellington Road
Clayton
Victoria 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF12/2690 - 2012001452: Dietary prebiotic supplementation in adults with prediabetes</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gayle Savige</name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Rural Health
PO Box 973, Moe, Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5128 1027</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5128 1080</fax>
      <email>gayle.savige@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gayle Savige</name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Rural Health
PO Box 973, Moe, Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5128 1027</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5128 1080</fax>
      <email>gayle.savige@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Nicole Kellow</name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Rural Health
PO Box 973, Moe, Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)488 488 808</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5128 1080</fax>
      <email>nicole.kellow@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Nicole Kellow</name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Rural Health
PO Box 973, Moe, Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)488 488 808</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5128 1080</fax>
      <email>nicole.kellow@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>