<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364123">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000501741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of carbohydrates of differing molecular-size on diarrhoea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome (IBS-D)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of carbohydrates of differing molecular-size on faecal water content, gastrointestinal symptoms and breath hydrogen in patients with IBS-D</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Irritable bowel syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will ingest the following single dose solutions fasted (on waking) in a random order with a minimum of three day washout period before crossing over to all of the other solutions:  
Arm 1 - 20g Lactulose in 100mL solution
Arm 2 - 20g Fructo-oligosaccharide in 100mL solution
Arm 3 - 20g Inulin in 100mL solution
Arm 4 - 20g Glucose in 100mL solution</interventions>
    <comparator>Glucose is the negative control and lactulose is the positive control.  15g is usually given as a dose for a positive control for symptoms and breath hydrogen production.  20g is given in this study to ensure the participants get symptoms on the lactulose positive control.  The other sugars provided are of the same dose for comparison.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Faecal water content after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions.  This will be determined via comparing weight of faecal sample before and after freeze-drying, which will remove water from the sample.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of overall gut symptoms and specific symptoms of bloating, pain and loose bowel motions after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions as measured by a 100 mm visual analogue scale.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Rated at the end of the day after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consistency of bowel motions after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions as rated by the Bristol Stool Chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each bowel motion for 24 hours after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breath hydrogen after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions.  Participants will collect breath samples at 15 minute intervals for four hours after ingestion of the sugars in supplied breath-collection bags.  The stored breath will be measured for hydrogen content using a 'breathtracker' instrument.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected for 4 hours after ingestion of lactulose, fructo-oligosaccharide, inulin and glucose solutions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with diarrhoea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome with reported good symptom control while following a low FODMAP diet</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Organic disease or condition predisposing the patient to diarrhoea (e.g. coeliac disease, inflammatory bowel disease, bowel resection)
2.	Use of antidiarrhoeal medications for one week prior to study commencement
3.	Probiotic or prebiotic use for two weeks prior to study commencement
4.	Antibiotic use for two weeks prior to study commencement
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited from a private dietetics practice.  The director and dietitian of the company will email patients diarrhoea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome previously seen at the practice for a low FODMAP diet as therapy.  Patients interested in the study will contact a study investigator for assessment of eligibility.  If eligible, the participant will be randomly allocated the order of which sugar solutions they will receive.  The allocation will be determined by a computer-generated order for the participant to receive 'Solution A', 'Solution B', 'Solution C' and 'Solution D' in random order.  The study investigators will administer the solutions to the participants but the labeling of solutions will be conducted by one persion who  is not a study investigator.  This way, both the participant and study investigators will be blinded to the sugar solutions.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated randomisation will be used.  The cross-over study design means all participants will ingests all four sugar solutions.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Appropriate ANOVA testing to compare multiple observations.  

There is no known previously published data investigating the primary endpoint of faecal water content in patients with IBS-D.  Sample size was therefore based on the secondary endpoint of gastrointestinal symptoms.  Based on published data in IBS patients ingesting both fructan and glucose solutions, 18 patients will detect a 63% increase in reported adequately controlled symptoms on the glucose solution, assuming 77% of IBS patients will not have reported adequately controlled symptoms on similar dose of fructan ingestion.  This sample size is based on 80% power and p-value of 0.05.  Allowing a drop-out rate of 20%, then 25 participants will need to be recruited for the study.  Interim analysis for the primary endpoint will be completed on 25 participants to determine require of more participants.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Gastroenterology, Central Clinical School, Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University

</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The low FODMAP diet is effective in managing symptoms in many patients with irritable bowel syndrome.  To assess if liberalisation of the diet is possible while still maintaining good symptom control, it is hypothesised that longer-chain FODMAP sugars (inulin) is less fermentable and less osmotic in the large intestine and will therefore not contribute to symptoms as much as shorter-chain FODMAPs (fructo-oligosaccharides and lactulose).  Glucose is not a FODMAP, but a sugar that is well absorbed and it is hypothesised that glucose will not contribute to symptoms.  
Diarrhoea-predominant patients with reported good symptom control on a low FODMAP diet will be recruited for easier measuring of symptom change, bowel motions and faecal water content specifically.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Clayton Campus
Wellington Rd
Clayton VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF13/477 - 2013000207</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jane Muir</name>
      <address>Head of Translational Nutrition Science
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0147</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jane.Muir@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Frances Burns</name>
      <address>Honours Student
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0396</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fsbur1@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Emma Halmos</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Emma.Halmos@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Emma Halmos</name>
      <address>Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Emma.Halmos@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>