<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371780">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000088347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Listening to preferred music to reduce risky wandering: A feasibility study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Listening to preferred music to reduce risky wandering in people with severe dementia in residential aged care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-5507 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil other</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Wandering</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Non-drug trial
Participants with severe dementia living in long term care with a history of wandering will listen to a selection of preferred music as selected by the participants next of kin. The music will be downloaded on to an iPod shuffle and listened to through head phones or speakers depending on preference. There are 2 conditions (2 participating facilities):
Condition 1: Each participant will listen to their selection of music in a quiet area for 20 mins, 5 days per week (Mon-Fri), for 3 weeks, 30 minutes before an individuals unique peak activity period.
Condition 2: Each participant will listen to their selection of music in a quiet area for 20 mins, 5 days per week (Mon-Fri), for 3 weeks, at a randomized time not including 30 minutes before an individuals unique peak activity period. Participants will be randomised to any 20 minute time period not 30 mins prior to peak activity periods or during scheduled meal times between 8am-6.30pm Mon-Fri.
Cluster randomization at the level of the facility was used to assign conditions - Facility 1 assigned condition 1; Facility 2 assigned condition 2. Condition assignment was chosen by a colleague not associated with the project. Participants only received 1 condition
The intervention will be delivered by trained research assistants who will remain with the participant during the intervention to observe reaction to the music (duration of time listening to music) and mood using Lawton's Modified Behavior Stream. To measure protocol fidelity, the person conducting the music session completed a checklist of essential protocol items (pre music session checklist (asked participant if they would like to listen to music, wearing appropriate clothing, elimination needs attended to, offered a drink), time music session commenced, duration of music session, mood that participant listen to music (headphones/speaker), location that music session was conducted, and comments about deviations from protocol). 10% of all interventions were observed by the principle investigator or project manager for inter rater reliability.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparisons will be made between the two conditions as well between weeks (Baseline (1 week before intervention), weekly during the 3 week intervention, week after the 3 week intervention)
Pre and post measures of wandering behaviour (steps taken, intrusion into private space, pattern of ambulation) by direct observation 2 x 2hr/week/participant, agitation, mood (Lawton's Modified Behavior Stream - collected during each intervention and pre or post wandering observations)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of following the intervention protocol through checklist completed at the end of each intervention session and congruence with a second observer of 10% of all interventions delivered</outcome>
      <timepoint>During each listening to music session the RA will observe the participant's mood to assess acceptability . At the end of each listening to music session the RA will complete a checklist of items included in the protocol</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcomes
Characteristics of wandering: frequency of ambulation (steps taken using Actigraph activity monitor), boundary transgression (frequency and duration of entry into private space collected by direct observation), pattern of ambulation (lapping, pacing, random, direct collected using direct observation). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre intervention - Week 1), during intervention (Week 2-4) and post intervention (week 5). 
RA observe each participant for 2 hours 2 x per week - 1 x in peak activity periods, 1 x outside peak activity periods. For IRR 10% of all observations have 2 observers - aim for 95% congruence. re training to occur if not acheived</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agitation - Cohen Mansfield Agitation Inventory - Short Form (CMAI-SF)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (pre intervention - start Week 1), during intervention (Start Weeks 2-4) and post intervention (start week 5). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff and family perceptions of benefits and acceptability of music program: Composite secondary outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>Interviews conducted in the weeks after the 3 week  listening to music program is completed with staff present during the listen ting to music program.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the use of headphones or speakers (mode of listening to music directed by person with dementia or family member) to listen to music</outcome>
      <timepoint>The duration of time that the participant listen s to music will be recorded at the end of each listening to music session by the RA observing the session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Are participants able to listen to music for a period of 20 minutes per day five times per week for 3 weeks?</outcome>
      <timepoint>During each listening to music session, the participant will be observed by the research assistant who will note when the session is ended and why it ends i.e. by participant or research assistant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Do participants enjoy listening to music?</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each listening to music session, participants will be asked if they enjoyed the music session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immediate pleasure</outcome>
      <timepoint>During each listening to music session the RA will observe the participant and collect data related to positive (pleasure, interest), neutral and negative (sadness, worry/anxiety, anger) affect will be collected (Lawton's Modified Behavior Stream)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reliability of staff to identify residents with dementia who wander and exhibit BT at an intensity that is observable</outcome>
      <timepoint>Congruence between identified potential participants with inclusion criteria</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>&gt; 55 years
Severe dementia as documented in medical history and confirmed with Global Deterioration Scale
Positive history of wandering as reported by care staff and confirmed using Revised Algase Wandering Scale
Independently ambulant (wheelie walker and walking stick acceptable
Not  experiencing an acute mental illness
Able to listen to music
Enjoys listening to music
Walks &gt; 5000 step per day</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not severe dementia
Not independently ambulant
Does not walk &gt; 5000 steps per day
Experiencing an acute psychotic episode
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealed </concealment>
    <sequence>A colleague not associated with the project chose one of two folded pieces of paper with condition 1 and condition 2 written on them. The first one chosen was allocated to Facility 1 and Facility 2 received the other.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To compare effect of intervention, repeated measures ANOVA will be used to compare mean frequency of CMAI scores and wandering observations across the 5 weeks of the program</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4022 - Rothwell</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove, Qld 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>QUT
Level 6 N Block
Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove, Qld 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the absence of effective alternatives, residential aged care (RAC) still resort to using pharmacological interventions, such as antipsychotic and sedating medications, to manage behaviours of dementia despite there being strong evidence that these are ineffective and are associated with severe adverse outcomes for the person with dementia. Non-pharmacological interventions are recommended as best practice to mitigate adverse outcomes associated with behaviours of dementia. There is considerable evidence that listening to preferred music reduces agitation in dementia. However, there is also robust evidence that dementia-related wandering and agitation are distinct phenomenon. Therefore we cannot assume that an intervention effective in reducing agitation will also reduce aspects of wandering that incur risk or result in negative outcomes for the person with dementia. There have been no known trials of music based interventions for people with dementia who wander, despite the pressing need for non-pharmacological interventions in this area. The goal of this applied research is to test the feasibility of using an intervention protocol, previously found to be effective in reducing agitation for people with dementia, to determine if it can be used with people who wander.
Therefore the aims of this feasibility study are:
1) For people with dementia who wander and exhibit boundary transgression (BT) (entry into out of bounds and hazardous areas) in residential aged care (RAC):
a. Is listening to music for a period of 20 minutes five times per week for 3 weeks tolerated?
b. Is listening to the music via ear bud head phones tolerated?
c. Do participants enjoy listening to the music?
2) Does listening to preferred music daily for 20 minutes under two conditions:
a) Reduce risky aspects of wandering including frequent ambulation and boundary transgression (BT)?
b) Reduce participant agitation?
c) Provide immediate pleasure to the participant?
3) Are facility care staff able to reliably identify residents with dementia who wander and exhibit BT at an intensity that is observable?
4) Do care staff and family members perceive the music intervention to be beneficial for resident with dementia who wander?

This feasibility study will use cluster randomisation (Facility 1 and Facility 2) to trial two intervention conditions:
Condition 1: Daily (Mon-Fri) session of listening to preferred music for 20 minutes, 30 minutes before unique peak activity period 
Condition 2: Daily (Mon-Fri) session of listening to preferred music for 20 minutes at a randomly selected time between 10 am-7pm not including 30 mins prior to individual peak activity periods.
Pre, during and post intervention measures of wandering characterisitics (frequency, boundary transgression, pattern), mood and agitation will be collected.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Participating nursing homes
Beaumont Care Rothwell and Seabrae Manor Rothwell</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove, Qld 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1600000627</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Margaret MacAndrew</name>
      <address>QUT
Victoria Park Rd
Level 3 N Block
Kelvin Grove, Qld 4059
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31385956</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>margaret.macandrew@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Margaret MacAndrew</name>
      <address>QUT
Victoria Park Rd
Level 3 N Block
Kelvin Grove, Qld 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31385956</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>margaret.macandrew@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Margaret MacAndrew</name>
      <address>QUT
Victoria Park Rd
Level 3 N Block
Kelvin Grove, Qld 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31385956</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>margaret.macandrew@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Margaret MacAndrew</name>
      <address>QUT
Victoria Park Rd
Level 3 N Block
Kelvin Grove, Qld 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31385956</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>margaret.macandrew@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>