<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="361990">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000470897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Decreasing screen-based entertainment in young children: The Family@play study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Decreasing screen-based entertainment in young children: The Family@play study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-5205</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Family@play</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Screen-based entertainment (SBE)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Time spent in screen-based entertainment (SBE) has been shown to be associated with adverse health and cognitive outcomes even in young children. This project therefore aims to examine the feasibility, acceptability and potential efficacy of a program to reduce screen-based entertainment in young children. Twenty-thirty families will be recruited into the study and the intervention will be delivered to parents in intact groups over a 6-week period. That is, existing groups such as parents attending a particular swimming lesson class or local playgroup, will be approached to participate in the program to ensure a familiar support base amongst parent group. 

The intervention consists of six weekly one hour group-based sessions. In each session, participants will set a goal aimed to reduce their young childs screen-based entertainment which they will implement during the week following the session. Each family will provide data (child height/weight, parent survey, objectively assessed physical activity) three times (baseline, completion of program, 10 weeks post intervention). Each data collection meeting will take approximately 15 minutes and will occur at a time and location convenient to the participant (such as their home, during or adjacent to their playgroup/lesson, or other time/location convenient). During the data collection visits, children will be weighed and measured following standardised protocols. Activity monitors to measure overall physical activity (accelerometer) and time in different postures such as sitting and standing (inclinometer) will be fitted to participating children. Parents will be provided with an information sheet about the monitors and a log sheet to complete during the time their child wears the monitors. Six sessions will be delivered across the intervention period at the physical location where each group was recruited. Intervention sessions will be scheduled either immediately before or after the groups' usual attendance time. Following baseline data collection, a computer generated program will be used to randomly select two of the four groups to participate in the program from August to September 2012. The remaining two groups will participate in an enhanced program (following feedback on the program from the first two groups) in February to March 2013.

Sessions will focus on three primary components: a) non-selectively decreasing SBE by use of budgeting, removing SBE options from children's bedrooms; b) selectively reducing SBE by setting rules/boundaries around use, and limiting participation based on context (only when child is not eating); and c) displacing SBE with other activities such as reading, imaginary games, etc. Content for group sessions will include: clarification of parents' values regarding their! child's health and well being; factors which influence children's development/well-being/health; changing and influencing children's behaviours; review of baseline results of current SBE use in their child; consequences of excessive SBE use to health and other outcomes; benefits of lower levels of SBE, such as social interaction, language development; building motivation and skills to reduce SBE including self-monitoring, goal setting, outcome and efficacy expectancies; awareness of good/bad SBE content; self-efficacy (barrier identification and goal-setting to overcome barriers); and support strategies within each group. Group sessions will also discuss the home-based activities to be undertaken by families and will use an anticipatory guidance approach (where expected challenges are identified and options to manage these are discussed prior to them being encountered) to facilitate group-based problem solving to possible challenges. By peer-based problem solving, participant! s may be more open in discussing challenges and more willing to accept advice from their peers. SMS messaging will be used between group sessions to support adherence to goals. A weekly internet blog site will also be available to support adherence and allow participants to post comments. A healthy afternoon tea and childcare for children and siblings will be provided during the group session.</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list Control. In the initial phase of the intervention, two groups will receive the treatment while two groups act as controls. Once post-intervention (immediately following the conclusion of the program) and follow-up measures (10 weeks post program completion) are taken, the control group will participate in the program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Screen-based entertainment is assessed by detailed time use diary on four days</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate conclusion of the program (June 2012) and 10 weeks post intervention (late August).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objectively measured postural position (sitting, lying, standing, walking) will be assessed using activPAL accelerometers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate conclusion of the program (June 2012) and 10 weeks post intervention (late August).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family functioning/parenting strategies for supporting healthy behaviors in their child as assessed by a parent survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate conclusion of the program (June 2012) and 10 weeks post intervention (late August).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adiposity (height and weight, body mass index) will be assessed. Height and weight will be objectively measured using a calibrated set of electronic scales and portable stadiometer. Body mass index will be calculated from measured height and weight.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate conclusion of the program (June 2012) and 10 weeks post intervention (late August).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent self efficacy for supporting healthy behaviors in their child as assessed by a parent survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate conclusion of the program (June 2012) and 10 weeks post intervention (late August).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participating families will have one child aged two or three years who exceeds the Australian recommendation for SBE of one hour or less per day. Participating parents will be willing, able and available to attend the group sessions when scheduled, and be willing to be randomised into either the intervention or control group. Intact groups will have five or more families willing to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>24</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>47</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants are excluded from this study according to age (&lt;2 or &gt;3.999) and if they meet Australian screen-based entertainment recommendations (&lt;1h/d).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants in this intervention will be 20-32, two- to three-year-old children and their parents. Participants will be recruited through intact groups. That is, existing groups such as parents attending a particular swimming lesson class or local playgroup, will be approached to participate in the program. In total, four groups of five to eight participants each will be recruited. Once baseline measures are complete, two of the four groups will be randomly selected to receive the treatment from August – September 2012. A computer generated program will be used to randomly assign the groups to either intervention or control conditions. The remaining two groups will act as controls and will receive the program once all measures (post-intervention, follow-up) are completed. The control group will participate in an enhanced program from February to March 2013. The program will be enhanced following feedback from the intervention group at the end of their participation in the program.

The allocation will be concealed as it will be done by central randomization by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be completed following baseline measurements to minimise withdrawal. Participant groups will be randomised using a computer-based random number-producing algorithm to either the intervention group (two intact groups, 10-16 participant families) or the wait list control group (two intact groups, 10-16 participant families). To prevent allocation bias, staff taking measurements, will be kept blind to the allocation sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Wait list control - both control and intervention groups will receive the intervention; controls will receive the intervention once all data has been collected (post-intervention, follow-up) and no further data will be collected once they have participated in the program.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/03/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/07/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>26</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2500</postcode>
    <postcode>2519</postcode>
    <postcode>2516</postcode>
    <postcode>2518</postcode>
    <postcode>2525</postcode>
    <postcode>2505</postcode>
    <postcode>2517</postcode>
    <postcode>2518</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trina Hinkley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Wollongong (Faculty of Education)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Northfields Avenue 
Wollongong
New South Wales 2522</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Tony Okely</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Northfields Avenue 
Wollongong
New South Wales 2522</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dylan Cliff</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Northfields Avenue 
Wollongong
New South Wales 2522</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Time spent in screen-based entertainment has been shown to be associated with adverse health and cognitive outcomes even in young children. Recent evidence suggests that a large proportion of young children exceed recommendations for screen-based entertainment.  This project therefore aims to examine the feasibility, acceptability and potential efficacy of a program to reduce screen-based entertainment in young children. The intervention will be delivered to parents in intact groups over a 10-week period.

Both the intervention and control groups will participate in the program and therefore we hypothesise that all participants will see improvements in the targeted outcomes. These include but are not limited to decreased screen-based entertainment, easier application of rules to support healthy behaviours and increased parental self-efficacy. Children may also display increases in physical activity and decreased sitting time. Participants results concerning their height and weight and time in screen-based entertainment will be forwarded to parents upon completion of analysis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Hinkley T, Cliff DP, Okely AD. Reducing electronic media use in 2-3 year-old children: the Family@play pilot randomised controlled trial. BMC Public Health. 2015; 15(779).</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Wollongong/South Eastern Sydney &amp; Illawarra Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Wollongong
Northfields Avenue
Wollongong NSW 2500</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE11/474</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+613 9251 7723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+613 9251 7723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+613 9251 7723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+613 9251 7723</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>