<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363725">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001156774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of mental health training for managers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of mental health training for managers working in Fire and Rescue NSW on knowledge, attitudes, confidence and behaviour.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>RESPECT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The proposed study seeks to test the effectiveness of a combined program of mental health literacy and sickness absence management for Duty Commanders within Fire and Rescue NSW. Specifically, the study will examine the effectiveness of the combined program in increasing mental health literacy, reducing stigma around mental illness, increasing manager knowledge of their role in sickness absence management as well as increasing confidence and encouraging early communication with employees on sickness absence leave. Importantly, we will also investigate the potential impact of the training in reducing overall sickness absence rates within Fire and Rescue NSW.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A new type of manager training, which combines mental health literacy with sickness absence management is soon to be rolled out across Fire and Rescue NSW. This single session training will be delivered by the Black Dog Institute to groups of 8 to 12 managers over a 4 hour period. The training is designed to be very interactive and to focus on the enhancing of confidence and skills rather than didactic lectures. Following the face to face training, there will also be two follow up phone contacts to provide additional support and evaluation.  The first of these phone calls (which will be made by an EAP Manager Support Service) will be between 3 and 4 weeks after the training, while the second will occur between 6 to 8 weeks after the training.

</interventions>
    <comparator>All Duty Commanders within Fire and Rescue NSW will be asked to attend this training. It is planned that the new training will be rolled out across Sydney Metropolitan NSW Fire and Rescue over a period of six months. In order to facilitate evaluation of the program, Fire NSW have agreed to randomly allocate the order in which Duty Commanders receive this training, with half receiving the training in the first wave of teaching and the half receiving the training in a second wave of teaching which will occur six months later (wait-list control group). This will allow those receiving the training in the second wave to act as a comparison group over a six month follow up period following the first wave of teaching.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of interest in this study is the rate of sickness absence. This is calculated as the total number of hours of sickness absence divided by the sum of the total number of hours of sickness absence and hours of attendance. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6 months after training intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health literacy questionnaire developed by the researchers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after training, and 6 months after training intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attitudes towards mental illness (Stigma) using modified versions of measures of personal stigma towards depression, anxiety and PTSD (Griffiths, Christensen, Jorm, Evans and Groves, 2004; Griffiths et al. 2011, Greenberg, Gould, Langston and Brayne, 2009)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after training, and 6 months after training intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confidence in communicating with employees who might have mental illness. The measure was developed by the researchers and will be assessed using a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after training, and 6 months after training intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge on manager's role in managing employees on sickness absence leave. The measure was developed by the researchers and will be assessed using a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after training, and 6 months after training intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Early communication with employees on sickness absence leave possibly due to mental illness. The measure was developed by the researchers and will be assessed using a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after training, and 6 months after training intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Duty Commander (or equivalent or higher level of seniority) in Fire and Rescue NSW, Metropolitan region
Good English comprehension</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to provide informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited as part of the ongoing standard training for Duty Commanders within Fire and Rescue NSW. It is planned that the new training will be rolled out to all Duty Commanders within Fire and Rescue NSW over a period of six months. Allocation will be concealed so the researchers would be unable to which group the subject would be allocated during the decision to determine eligibility.

In order to facilitate evaluation of the program, Fire NSW have agreed to randomly allocate the order in which Duty Commanders receive this training, with half receiving the training in the first wave of teaching and the half receiving the training in a second wave of teaching after a 6 month delay. An email/memo from Fire NSW to all Duty Commanders will be sent notifying them of the upcoming training and the associated research study. Following this memo, all Duty Commanders will then be approached and provided with the Participant Information Sheet and Consent Form. As outlined in the information sheet, it will be made clear to all potential participants that participation in the research study is entirely voluntary and that they can still receive the training without participating in the evaluation. Duty Commanders who are to receive the new training during the second wave of teaching (six months after the first wave) will be sent a letter in November informing them that will be receiving their training at a later date and introducing the associated research project. This letter will include the Participant Information Sheet and Consent Form . As outlined above, they will have previously received a memo from NSW Fire and Rescue informing them of this research study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Each participant will be given a participant number.  Randomisation computer software will be used to provide a random assignment of participants to each group.  Block randomisation according to shift patterns will be used to aid the logistics of providing the training</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The statistical analysis for this project will be conducted using STATA statistical software. The primary outcome will be comparison of the mean number of hours sickness absence between the intervention and control groups, which will be tested for using multivariate linear regression with appropriate controls for clustered data. Currently, the average number of hours of sickness absence taken by Fire and Rescue NSW staff is 118 hours per year. An average reduction of 10 hours per annum in the intervention group would be considered a meaningful and important effect. As the intervention is being delivered at the level of duty commanders, the potential clustering of sickness absence within staff groups needs to be accounted for in the power calculations. Based on an average of 25 staff members per group, a standard deviation in the number of hours of sickness absence of 60 and an intragroup correlation of 0.05, a total of 98 duty commanders would need to be recruited to this study to achieve 0.8 power with an alpha of 0.05 (two sided). A total of 130 duty commanders within the metropolitan NSW Fire and Rescue service will be required to undertake this new training. Assuming at least 75% agree to participate with the training evaluation, adequate power should be achieved.

Differences in other outcome measures, such as levels of mental health literacy, stigma, awareness of a managers role, confidence in communicating with ill staff and self-reported levels of communication will also be tested.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/11/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>88</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/05/2014</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>29/10/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychiatry
Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Employers Mutual</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Employers Mutual
acting as the agent for NSW Self Insurance Corporation (NSW Treasury Managed Fund No 2)
Level 12, 175 Pitt Street Sydney NSW 2000
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Black Dog Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hospital Road, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Fire and Rescue New South Wales
Health and Safety</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Health and Safety
Fire and Rescue New South Wales
Level 8, 227 Elizabeth Street, 
Sydney, NSW 2000 </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Managers and supervisors play a key role in the welfare of the workforce and in the prevention of long-term disability. There is evidence that managers within the emergency services feel under-skilled in dealing with sickness absence, particularly when absence is due to mental illness. We seek to test the effectiveness of a novel program of manager education which combines mental health literacy and sickness absence management training within Fire and Rescue NSW. The program will be rolled out over a six month period to all Duty Commanders as part of a NSW Fire and Rescue training initiative. We aim to evaluate the effectiveness of the program in increasing mental health literacy, reducing stigma around mental illness, increasing manager knowledge of their role in sickness absence management as well as increasing confidence and encouraging early communication with employees on sickness absence leave. Importantly, we will also investigate the potential impact of the training in reducing overall sickness absence rates within Fire and Rescue NSW.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>No publications yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Secretariat
UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3, South Wing
The University of New South Wales 
SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC12562</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Harvey</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry, UNSW
G06, Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 8356</phone>
      <fax>+612 9382 8151</fax>
      <email>s.harvey@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Harvey</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry, UNSW
G06, Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 8356</phone>
      <fax>+612 9382 8151</fax>
      <email>s.harvey@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Harvey</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry, UNSW
G06, Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 8356</phone>
      <fax>+612 9382 8151</fax>
      <email>s.harvey@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Josie Milligan-Saville</name>
      <address>School of Psychiatry, UNSW
G03, Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road, Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 4517</phone>
      <fax>+612 9382 8151</fax>
      <email>j.milligan-saville@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>