<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372177">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000158369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing the results of different skin closure techniques in children after elective surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective Randomised Controlled Trial Comparing Parental Satisfaction and
Clinical Outcome Measures for Paediatric Skin Closure Techniques</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PST Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Skin closure following surgical incision</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Wound outcomes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention Arm 1 - skin closure of surgical wound incision with adhesive glue (DERMABOND)

Patients randomised to this intervention group will have have skin closure of the surgical wound incisions with DERMABOND adhesive glue once the wound has been closed with sutures. There will be no alteration to the surgery itself. The skin incision will be closed using the DERMABOND adhesive glue by the paediatric surgeon/paediatric surgical registrar performing the operation. The DERMABOND adhesive glue is a liquid glue packaged in a ready-to-use small plastic vial with an applicator at the tip. The liquid glue is applied at the wound edge to bring the two wound edges together and hold it in place and is then left to dry for a minute or two. The approximate volume used for closing the wound incision will be determined by the treating surgeon. There is no follow-up treatment required to remove the glue itself; it will fall off after a few days. Children participating in the study as well as their parents/guardians will be told that the skin was closed with DERMABOND adhesive glue at the completion of the operation.

Intervention Arm 2 - skin closure of surgical wound incision with adhesive tape (SteriStrips)

Patients randomised to this intervention group will have have skin closure of the surgical wound incisions with adhesive tape (SteriStrips) once the wound has been closed with sutures. There will be no alteration to the surgery itself. The skin incision will be closed using the adhesive tape (SteriStrips) by the paediatric surgeon/paediatric surgical registrar performing the operation. SteriStrips are small strips of adhesive tape. The adhesive tape is applied to bring the two wound edges together and hold them in place. They are applied to the skin after the wound has been closed. The number of strips of adhesive tape required for the wound incision will be determined by the treating surgeon. There is no follow-up required to remove the SteriStrips themselves; they will fall off after a few days. Children participating in the study as well as their parents/guardians will be told that the skin was closed with adhesive tape (SteriStrips) at the completion of the operation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intervention Arm 3 - skin closure of surgical wound incision with occlusive dressing used over the top

Patients randomised to this  group will have have an occlusive dressing applied over the surgical wound incisions after the wound has been closed with sutures. There will be no alteration to the surgery itself. The skin incision will be closed with sutures and the occlusive dressing placed over the top by the paediatric surgeon/paediatric surgical registrar performing the operation in order to protect and cover the wound as it heals. This dressing will be a normal waterproof occlusive dressing applied over the surgical site after the wound has been closed with stitches. For the purposes of the study, a standardised wound dressing will be used for all patients. There is no follow-up required to remove the dressing; it will come off itself after a few days. Children participating in the study as well as their parents/guardians will be told that the skin was closed with sutures and a dressing was placed over the top at the completion of the operation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental satisfaction with the skin closure technique used at 2 and 6 weeks

Parents/guardians will be asked a question similar to a Likert scale where they will be asked how satisfied they were with the adhesive tape/skin glue used to close the skin incision/s. They will be given the options of 'Very Satisfied', 'Satisfied', 'Neutral', 'Dissatisfied' and 'Very Dissatisfied'.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 6 weeks after the surgery and application of the skin closure technique</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cosmetic outcome as evaluated by the child and their parents/guardians as well as a paediatric surgeon after the procedure This outcome is assessed using a visual analogue scale completed at 2 weeks and 6 weeks after the operation completed by the child and their parents/guardians. A de-identified photograph taken of the wound at the 6 week follow-up will be used by the paediatric surgeon and the cosmetic outcome assessed using the Hollander Wound Evaluation Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cosmetic outcome at 2 weeks and 6 weeks after the surgery and application of the skin closure technique as rated by the child and their parents/guardians

Cosmetic outcome at 6 weeks after the surgery and application of the skin closure technique as rated by a paediatric surgeon blinded to the skin closure technique used</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of wound infection</outcome>
      <timepoint>Wound infection as reported by the child's parents/guardians at 2 weeks after the operation and application of the skin closure technique</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of wound dehiscence</outcome>
      <timepoint>Wound dehiscence as reported by the child's parents/guardians at 2 weeks after the operation and application of the skin closure technique</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of requirement to see a healthcare practitioner due to a problem with the adhesive tape or adhesive glue
</outcome>
      <timepoint>As reported by the child and their parents/guardians at the 2 week follow-up after the surgery and application of the skin closure technique</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental concerns raised regarding the skin closure technique used</outcome>
      <timepoint>As reported by the child's parents/guardians at the 2 week follow-up after the surgery and application of the skin closure technique</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time taken for the skin closure technique to come off</outcome>
      <timepoint>As reported by the child's parents/guardians at the 2 week follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Paediatric patients (0-18 years) presenting for an elective paediatric surgical
procedure at Monash Children's Hospital</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Repeat elective operations</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be achieved using identical opaque envelopes which will be used to randomise participating patients into one of the two intervention arms.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/03/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1089</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>13/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Casey Hospital - Berwick</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3806 - Berwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Paediatric Surgery, Monash Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Paediatric Surgery
Monash Children's Hospital, Monash Health
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Paediatric Surgery, Monash Children's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Paediatric Surgery
Monash Children's Hospital, Monash Health
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A prospective randomised controlled trial comparing skin closure of surgical incisions in children using either a wound dressing only, adhesive tape (SteriStrips) or adhesive glue (Dermabond). The choice of which of these techniques is used is usually dependent upon the surgeons preference and there is little evidence to show which of the three is better. This study will help to determine which of these three techniques, if any, is better and will help paediatric surgeons choose the best skin closure technique for their patients.

Parents of children presenting for elective surgical procedures will be approached for enrolment. Participating children will then be randomised to have surgical incision skin closure with sutures and then either adhesive tape, adhesive glue or a simple wound dressing.

Postoperatively, children will be followed up at 2 weeks via telephone survey where a parental satisfaction survey in terms of the wounds will be performed. Parents will also be asked questions related to:
1. Wound healing
2. The presence of any complications such as wound infection
3. Requirement to see a doctor regarding the wound postoperatively,
4. Time taken for each skin closure type to come off
5. Any parental concerns regarding the type of skin closure used.
Parents will also be asked to fill out an online survey in which they will rate the cosmetic outcome of the wound. Parents unable to be reached via telephone will have a link emailed to their email address to complete the entire survey online.

There will be a second followup at 6 weeks postoperatively where children will be reviewed by a paediatric surgeon in the Outpatients Clinic to assess the cosmetic outcome of the surgical wound and parents will be asked to complete a survey in hard-copy or on an iPad about the cosmetic outcome of the wound and overall parental satisfaction with the skin closure technique. Data collected will then be used to assess for differences between the three patient groups including blinded photographic assessment of the surgical wounds.

This project will aim to look for differences between the three groups in terms of cosmetic outcome (as rated by the parents and a blinded paediatric surgeon assessor), differences in wound infection and wound breakdown rates and a comparison of parental satisfaction with the skin closure technique.

It is hypothesised that, as all three wound closure techniques are used in clinical practice, it is likely that there will be minimal difference between the three groups. However these techniques have not been compared in a controlled trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Any costs associated with this study will be met through departmental funds.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Services
Monash Health
Level 2, I Block
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Reference Number: HREC/16/MonH/401</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ramesh Nataraja</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatric Surgery
Monash Children's Hospital
246 Clayton Road
Clayton 3168, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9594 6998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ram.Nataraja@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ramesh Nataraja</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatric Surgery
Monash Children's Hospital
246 Clayton Road
Clayton 3168, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9594 6998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ram.Nataraja@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ramesh Nataraja</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatric Surgery
Monash Children's Hospital
246 Clayton Road
Clayton 3168, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9594 6998</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ram.Nataraja@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>