<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82987">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000412336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Part 3 of a study to evaluate the safety of a single dose of increasing amounts of INO-4885 given via a vein to healthy adult male volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Single-Center, Randomized, Single-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Single-Dose, Dose-Escalation Study to Evaluate the Tolerability, Safety, and Pharmacokinetics of an Intravenous Infusion of INO-4885 Administered to Healthy Adult Male Volunteers  Part 3</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>No specific health condition being studied - the study is being conducted for safety reasons in healthy male volunteers that do not belong to any target population for the given intervention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In the completed Parts 1 and 2 of this trial, the tolerability and safety of intravenous doses of INO-4885 ranging from 1-600 mcg/kg administered to healthy adult volunteers was established . Based upon these findings and animals toxicology (safety ) studies, 1200 mcg/kg of INO-4885 will be administered intravenously to healthy adult volunteers in this trial (Part 3) at a rate of 15 mL/min.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo is standard 0.9% normal saline (salt water) to be administered intravenously at 15 mL per minute.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability and Safety: results of physical examinations, vital signs, clinical laboratory tests, electrocardiogram (ECG) tracings, drug exposure, concomitant medications, withdrawals/termination, renal safety biomarkers, and adverse events (AEs) will be used to assess tolerability and safety. Adverse events such as clinically significant abnormal findings on safety tests reported by the investigators and events reported by enrolled subjects will be recorded, listed, and reviewed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Physical examinations at Screening and Days 0, 1, 2, and 7; vital signs at Screening, Day 0, Day 1 (pre-dose and immediately following conclusion of the study drug infusion, every half hour for 1 hour, every hour for 3 hours, and then every 4 hours for 8 hours), Day 2, Day 3, and Day 7; clinical laboratory tests at Screening and Days 2,3, and 7; electrocardiogram (ECG) tracings at Screening, Days 0, Day 1 (pre-dose and at 0, 20, 60, 120, and 180 min post-dose), and on Days 2, 3, and 7; blood samples for INO-4885 levels and/or kidney safety markers on Day 1 at pre-dose and at 0, 20 and 40 minutes, and at 1, 2, 4, 7, 10, 24, 30, 48, and 54 hours post administration of INO-4885; urine collected for 48 hours on Days 1-3 for levels of INO-4885; and documentation at Screening and on Days 0, 1, 2, 3, and 7 of concomitant medications, withdrawals, terminations, and adverse events (AEs) will be used to assess tolerability and safety.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetic profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood for INO-4885 levels will be sampled on Day 1 at pre-dose and at 0, 20 and 40 minutes, and at 1, 2, 4, 7, 10, 24, 30, 48, and 54 hours post administration of INO-4885.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subject's body weight between 65 and 100 kg and Body Mass Index between 18 and 29, inclusive.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subject received treatment or participated in a study with any investigational product within 30 days prior to study drug administration; subject used tobacco, alcohol, caffeine, vitamins, or herbal medications within 48 hours prior to study drug administration; subject used or required any prescription medications during the 4 weeks prior to study drug administration</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation was concealed using sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation to intervention is randomized controlled trial. Randomisation was accomplished using simple random generation code generated by software purched from Statistical Analysis Software (SAS). Code was written and executed by an outsourced vendor, Medistat, located in Kiryat Atidim, Israel.  The vendor also prepared the opaque envelopes and randomisation lists.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Inotek Pharmaceuticals Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Cummings Center, Suite 419E
Beverly, Massachusetts 01915</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Inotek Pharmaceuticals Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>100 Cummings Center, Suite 419E,
Beverly, Massachusetts</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The goal of this study is to evaluate the safety of increasing doses of an experimental drug called INO-4885. In the earlier, completed parts (Parts 1 and 2) of this study, a single dose on INO-4885 at 1-600 micrograms per kilogram body weight was given to healthy male volunteers via a catheter placed in an arm vein. In Part 3 of this study, one dose of 1200 micrograms per kilogram body weight will be given to healthy male volunteers. Safety assessments will include physical examinations, routine blood and urine tests, electrocardiograms, blood and urine levels of INO-4885, and other indicators of safety will be recorded and analyzed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital
Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chaim Brickman</name>
      <address>100 Cummings Center, suite 419E
Beverly, Massachusetts 01915</address>
      <phone>+1-978-232-9660, ext 8805</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbrickman@inotekcorp.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chaim Brickman</name>
      <address>100 Cummings Center, suite 419E
Beverly, Massachusetts 01915</address>
      <phone>+1-978-232-9660, ext 8805</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbrickman@inotekcorp.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chaim Brickman</name>
      <address>100 Cummings Center, suite 419E
Beverly, Massachusetts 01915</address>
      <phone>+1-978-232-9660, ext 8805</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbrickman@inotekcorp.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>