<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336721">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000344998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparatve study between self catheterisation with a silicone catheter and a stainless steel catheter assessing bladder infection rate in female patients who are self catheterising.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparative Multicentre trial assessing the incidence of urinary tract infections using the conventional silicone catheter with a stainless steel catheter for intermittent self catheterising in patients who have a neurogenic bladder and a post void residual volume of &gt;100mls</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-3101</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>This study has not been previously registered with another registry</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neurogenic bladder with post void residual volumes of greater than 100mls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an extenson of a previous study registration number:
ACTRN12610000637044. The previous study was titled "A comparative study between the use of the conventional silicone catheter and the surgical stainless steel catheter". The previous study only enrolled 10 participants to trial the catheter. The participants who were involved in the study reported that the surgical stainless steel catheter improved bladder emtpying, reduced time to void, did not need lubrication and it was easier to carry around. 

This present study has been designed to further evaluate incidence of infection, ease of use and continence specific quality of life in 50 female pateints comparing a conventional silicone catheter with a surgical stainless steel catheter. Patients wil be asked to catheterise for 3 months using the silicone catheter followed by 3 months with the stainless steel catheter, catheterising at their usual frequency ie 3-4 times per day</interventions>
    <comparator>No control due to sample numbers</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of urinary tract infection. Any patient developing symptoms during the trial period will be investigated for urinary tract infection with microscopy and culture to confirm infection and treated accordingly</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any time during the 6 months study period if the patient is symptomatic</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparing Ease of use using a questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessing continence specific quality of life changes usng a questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate effectiveness simplified cleaning techniques compared to costly replacement of silicone catheters using a questionnaire and performing urinalysis if symptomatic with UTI</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Female patients aged 16 - 75.
(2) The patient must have a neurogenic bladder and a post void residual volume &gt; 100mls.
(3) The patient must be able to self-catheterise without assistance from a carer.
(4) There must be a history of recurrent urinary tract infections associated with self-catheterisation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) History of urethral trauma/stricture.
(2) Inadequate upper limb dexterity to be able to self-catheterise.
(3) No history of infections in the preceding 14 days.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Approaching all patients who are self catheterising and are the supervision of continence services in New Zealand</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr LJ (Vic) du Plessis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>ISIS Centre
Private Bag 1921
Dunedin</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr Dave Solomon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>82 Glenpark Ave
Mornington
Dunedin</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study has been designed is to compare the incidence of urinary tract infections (UTI) in 50 female patients who need to self catheterise to properly empty their bladders.
Participants in this study will be monitored for a 3 month period for frequency of  UTIs, ease of use and continence specific quality of life while using the Nelaton silicone catheter, followed by a 3 month study period using a surgical stainless steel catheter assessing the same parameters for intermittent self catheterising.
During the 6 month study peroid, participants will be asked to keep a urinary diary and they will be monitored closely for urinary tract infection (UTI). If a participant develops symptoms of UTI, a urine sample will be obtained and sent for urinalysis. If positive they will be commenced on appriopriate antibiotics and a decision will be made whether the patient needs to be withdrawn from the study.
At the end of the study, each participant will be asked to complete a patient satisfaction survery and continence specific quality of life questionnaire.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Multi-region Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 5013
Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr LJ (Vic) du Plessis</name>
      <address>ISIS Centre
Private Bag 1921
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>0064 212531148</phone>
      <fax>0064 3 4766046</fax>
      <email>Vic.DuPlessis@southerndhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr LJ (Vic) du Plessis</name>
      <address>ISIS Centre
Private Bag 1921
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>0064 212531148</phone>
      <fax>0064 3 4766046</fax>
      <email>Vic.DuPlessis@southerndhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr LJ (Vic) du Plessis</name>
      <address>ISIS Centre
Private Bag 1921
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>0064 212531148</phone>
      <fax>0064 3 4766046</fax>
      <email>Vic.DuPlessis@southerndhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>