<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363011">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001136897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Obstructive sleep apnoea and related symptoms study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In participants with Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA) and depression, is Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) effective in reducing the symptoms associated with depression?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Therapeutic Continuous Positive Airway Pressure plus humidification for 12 weeks. 

Treatment Arm 1 - Diagnosed depression* + obstructive sleep apnoea
Treatment Arm 2 - No diagnosed depression* + obstructive sleep apnoea

*Depression or no depression will be based on DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for mood disorders as assessed by the SCID Mood Episodes module A.

CPAP involves the use of a machine during sleep that pumps air under gentle pressure, via a tube, to a mask that covers the nose (or mouth and nose).  The air pressure acts to hold the upper airway open so that it does not collapse during sleep.

Therapeutic CPAP therapy will involve the use of a CPAP device with variable pressure setting for the first week.  After 1 week, a fixed-pressure CPAP will be prescribed, based on the pressure required to control 95% of periods of apnoea or hypopnoea.  Participants will receive the prescribed pressure for 11 weeks.   Participants will be encouraged to use the therapeutic CPAP device during periods of sleep each night.  Hours of use, and days used will be recorded.</interventions>
    <comparator>Sham (sub-therapeutic) Continuous Positive Airway Pressure  plus humidificiation for 12 weeks.

Treatment Arm 3 - Diagnosed depression* + obstructive sleep apnoea
Treatment Arm 4 - No diagnosed depression* + obstructive sleep apnoea

*Depression or no depression will be based on DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for mood disorders as assessed by the SCID Mood Episodes module A.

Sham CPAP is a modified CPAP device that provides a sub-therapeutic pressure at the mask (less than 1cm H20).  The Sham CPAP device will be indistinguishable from the therapeutic CPAP device.  Participants will receive the sub-therapeutic pressure weeks 1-12.  Participants will be encouraged to use the sham CPAP device during periods of sleep each night.  Hours of use, and days used will be recorded.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in Hamilton Depression Scale of 4 or more.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinician-rated moderate or marked improvement in overall well-being from baseline as per the Clinical Global Impression scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of anxiety as per the Generalised Anxiety Disorder Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8, 12 weeks following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Epworth Sleepiness Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12 weeks following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep Apnoea Quality of Lilfe Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 6, 8, 12 weeks following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Apnoea/hypopnoea index (AHI) greater than 15</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Central (non-obstructive) sleep apnoea.
Current or prior treatment for OSA, including: mandibular advancement splint; CPAP therapy; upper airway surgery; Provent Nasal Device (microvalve technology that provides expiratory positive airway pressure).
Participants who meet the DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for psychotic symptoms as assessed by the SCID Psychotic Screen modules B/C; or participants who meet the DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for substance abuse or co-morbid alcohol use as diagnosed by the SCID Substance Use Disorders module E, 
 within the 12 months prior to enrolment.
Participants who are actively suicidal as assessed by the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited entirely from the Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Sleep Disorders Clinic with stratification for sex and diagnosed depression to ensure equal numbers of males and females, and depressed and non-depressed participants in each treatment arm.
Recruitment will occur in two stages:
Stage 1	100% of females and 50% of males will be invited to be screened.  Males born in months 1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11 will be invited to be screened.
Stage 2	Following written informed consent, and determination of depression status, 100% of depressed females; 42% of not depressed females (those born in months 1, 4, 7, 10, 12);  67% of depressed males (those born in months 3,5,7,9); and 50% of not depressed males (those born in months 1,7,11)  will be randomised.
Recruitment across the strata will be reviewed following randomisation of 90 participants.  In the event that proportions of males and females, depressed and not depressed are unequal, the recruitment process will be adjusted by varying the number of birth months used for recruitment.
In order to allow for possible seasonal effects on depression, it is aimed to recruit each of the above strata at a similar rate over the study period.
Based upon depression status, sex and birth month, participants will be allocated to a treatment group using a computer program, in accordance with a predetermined random computer-generated algorithm.  The researcher who will conduct assessments at each visit will remain blinded as to the treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Within each stratum, a random computer-generated list of sequences will determine the randomisation sequence.   
This will ensure balance in Therapeutic CPAP vs sham CPAP after each block.  The randomisation sequence will be generated by off-site chief investigators.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Health and Medical Research Council Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Depression is one of the most frequent psychiatric disorders in obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA) and is associated with more severe OSA, reduced engagement with ontinuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy, reduced quality of life and social functioning.  CPAP therapy may be an effective option for treating depression in OSA.
Hypotheses: 
1.  OSA participants with depression who receive CPAP will show a significant reduction in depression scores at 3 months follow-up compared with participants treated with Sham CPAP; and
2.  The persistence of depression in OSA, despite CPAP treatment, will have a negative impact upon OSA outcomes including symptoms and compliance with therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, A Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
WA     6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-042</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Clinical Professor David Hillman</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology and Sleep Medicine
Level 5, G Block Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
WA    6009</address>
      <phone>61 8 9346 2222</phone>
      <fax>61 8 9346 2034</fax>
      <email>David.Hillman@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Peta Grayson</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology and Sleep Medicine
Level 5, G Block Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
WA    6009</address>
      <phone>61 8 9346 2888</phone>
      <fax>61 8 9346 2034</fax>
      <email>Peta.Grayson@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Peta Grayson</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology and Sleep Medicine
Level 5, G Block Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
WA    6009</address>
      <phone>61 8 9346 2888</phone>
      <fax>61 8 9346 2034</fax>
      <email>Peta.Grayson@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Hillman</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology and Sleep Medicine Level 5, G Block Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Hospital Avenue Nedlands WA 6009  </address>
      <phone>61 (08) 9346 2222</phone>
      <fax>61 (0)8 9346 2034</fax>
      <email>David.Hillman@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>