<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368908">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000753550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle> Home-based, tailored intervention for reducing falls after stroke: the Falls After Stroke Trial (FAST) Feasibility Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle> Home-based, tailored intervention for reducing falls after stroke: the Falls After Stroke Trial (FAST) Feasibility Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FAST Feasibility </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Falls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Community dwelling-stroke survivors will be assigned to the experimental group to test the feasibility of the intervention. The experimental group will receive a home-based, tailored intervention consisting of habit forming exercise and/or safety training depending on their level of disability. For example, the faster walkers (&gt; 0.8 m/s) will have most emphasis on habit-forming exercise, the slower walkers (&lt; 0.4 m/s) will have most emphasis on safety training, while the middle group (0.4-0.8
m/s) will have a combination of both habit-forming exercise and safety training. Habit-forming exercise will be based on the successful Lifestyle integrated Functional Exercise program (Clemson et al., 2012). This program encourages participants to look for ways of doing more physical
activity. Activities which challenge their balance and strength will be incorporated into specific daily tasks. They will be performed intentionally and consciously until they become habitual and embedded in daily occupation. Feedback, monitoring and positive reinforcement will be used to enhance the performance of these activities and the self-efficacy of the participants. The safety intervention will focus on environmental adaptations to reduce fall hazards and protective behaviours to reduce risk. The
Westmead Home Safety Assessment (Clemson et al 1999), and the Falls Behavioural Scale for Older People, validated by Clemson and colleagues (Clemson et al., 2008a), will be used to identify environmental hazards, as well as risks, so that the participants and therapist can generate
solutions. The home-based tailored intervention will be delivered through 7 weekly home visits followed by three booster sessions at Weeks 9, 13, 19 with two phone calls during Week 15 and 23. All home visits will be pproximately 1 hour duration and all home visits and phone calls will be
delivered by a physiotherapists or an occupational therapist with experience in neurological rehabilitation. The  herapists delivering the intervention and participants will keep exercise logs to monitor adherence and adverse events.</interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure will be falls defined according to a recent consensus statements and Cochrane review recommendations as an unexpected event in which the participant comes to rest on the ground, floor, or lower level (Lamb et al., 2005). Participants will self report using monthly falls calendars
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance will be measured using the Berg Balance Scale (Berg et al 1992). It has demonstrate good test-retest reliability and validity in measuring balance after stroke (Berg et al 1995).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance will also be measured using the Step Test (Hill et al 1996). The test has demonstrate good test-retest reliability and validity in measuring balance after stroke ( Hill et al 1996, Blennerhasset et al
2009)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy will be measured using the Activities Specific Balance
Confidence Scale It has demonstrated good test-retest reliability and
adequate internal consistency (Powell and Myers, 1995; ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy will also be measured using the Modified Falls Efficacy Scale to measure confidence in performing daily activity without risk of falling. It has demonstrated good test-retest reliability and adequate internal consistency (Lamb et al., 2005).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility will be assessed using the 6-min walk test (6MWT) The 6MWT will be conducted according to the recently updated guidelines (Holland et al, 2014). It is commonly used as a functional submaximal measure of oxygen uptake and exercise capacity (Solway et al., 2001) and is a valid and reliable clinical measure of walking ability in stroke survivors (Fulk et al., 2008).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility will also be assessed using the 10-m walk test (self-selected and fast speed: step length, and cadence). The 10-m walk test will be  conducted with a moving start and finish to take into account any acceleration and deceleration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual physical activity will be assessed using the Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire (IPEQ) which has been validated and which provide estimates of the frequency and duration of planned and casual day-to-day activities (Delbare et al 2010) </outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual physical activity will also be assessed using the ActivPALTM, an accelerometer-based monitor to measure physical activity for 7 days. Time on feet, time in sitting and lying and steps per day will be analysed (Grant et al., 2008).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Community participation will be measured using the Late-Life Function and Disability Instrument which measures limitation and frequency of participation in life tasks across personal, social and community domains
(Sayers et al., 2004).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life will be measured using the EuroQual-5D (EQ-5D) (Kind et al 2005), which provides a measure of overall health using a visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to Intervention schedule measured as percentage of home visits and telephone calls delivered</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 mths</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People with stroke will be screened and invited to participate if they:
a) are within 2 years of their first stroke (either ischaemic or haemorrhagic)
b) have been discharged from formal rehabilitation and are communitydwelling
c) can walk, defined as being able to walk 10 m across flat ground with or
without a gait aid
d)are adults capable of providing consent (ie, score greater than or equal
to 20 on Mini-Mental State Examination score, Folstein et al 1975)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>They will be excluded if they:
a) have moderate to severe receptive aphasia as determined by a score of less than 25/30 on the Frenchay Screening Aphasia Test (Enderby et al., 1987).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited via professional networks and all will be assigned to the experimental intervention for the feasibility trial</concealment>
    <sequence>not relevant</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Adherence to the intervention protocol and number of falls and proportion of fallers will be analysed descriptively as well as pre-post changes in outcomes in this feasibility trial.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Catherine dean</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept of Health Professions
Macquarie university
Ground Floor
75 Talavera Rd
Macquarie Park
NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Dept of Health Professions
Macquarie university
Ground Floor
75 Talavera Rd
Macquarie Park
NSW 2109
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Macquarie University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dept of Health Professions
Macquarie university
Ground Floor
75 Talavera Rd
Macquarie Park
NSW 2109</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the Falls After Stroke Trial (FAST) is to test the effect of homebased, tailored intervention to reduce falls. A sample of communitydwelling stroke survivors who have finished formal rehabilitation, and therefore are at a high risk of falling again will assigned to an experimental group (habit-forming exercise and safety training) to test the feasibility of the intervention.
The primary hypothesis is that the home-based, tailored intervention will be safe and reduce both the proportion of people falling and rate of falls over a one-year period in stroke survivors living in the community.
The secondary hypotheses are:
2. That home-based, tailored intervention will also be associated with improvements in improving: balance, self-efficacy, mobility, physical activity, community participation, and health-related quality of life.

This feasibility trial will test the experimental intervention over 6 months and evaluate feasibility of recruitment, intervention and assessment protocols as well as monitoring outcomes and adverse events. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC Medical Sciences)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Building C5C East
Macquarie University
NSW 2109 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201500456</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Dean</name>
      <address>Ground Floor
 75 Talavera Road
 Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.dean@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>catherine Dean</name>
      <address>Ground Floor
 75 Talavera Road
 Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.dean@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Dean</name>
      <address>Ground Floor
 75 Talavera Road
 Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.dean@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Catherine Dean</name>
      <address>Ground Floor
 75 Talavera Road
 Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.dean@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>