<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365163">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001173785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Kinesiology Taping in breast cancer-related lymphedema</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Kinesiology Taping on breast cancer-related lymphedema: a randomized single blind controlled pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Kinesiology Taping</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>breast cancer-related lymphedema</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of the study is to assess the efficacy of Kinesiology Taping (KT) for treating breast cancer-related lymphedema. The endpoints are the reduction of limb volume and percentage edema size after a month therapy.

Intervention:
Subjects from all three groups receive a routine treatment, including skin care, 45-min pneumatic compression therapy (at 90 mmHg, 12 chambers), 1-h manual lymphatic drainage, application of a multi-layered short-stretch bandages (50-60 mmHg). The tape groups (KT and Quasi KT groups also receive standard therapy - only skin care, pneumatic compression and manual drainage - the same as in MCT group), but K or Quasi tapes are used instead of a bandages. Each groups are treated 3 times weekly (bandages or K-tapes are applied and changed on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays) for in the 4-week intervention period. One physical therapist (PTs) provides treatment. The program is standardized, following the same protocol for lymphatic drainage to the anterior trunk, posterior trunk and affected arm, always moving fluid from the affected side toward the unimpaired side. After lymphatic drainage and before either the short-stretch bandages or the K-tape are applied by the physical therapist. In KT group the fan tape anchor starts at the anterior aspect of the hand with no tension. The tails of the tape are applied to the anterior, medial and posterior aspects of the forearm and arm with 5  15% tension, and then on anterior part of chest. The tapes are left on the patients skin for the next three days. In Quasi KT group we use tapes without therapeutic effects (tapes were apllied without any tension) with the same methodology as in KT group (anatomical placement of tapes on upper limb was the same in both groups). In MCT group we use 4-layered compression bandaging. The first layer is applied to the skin directly with Tubula orthopedic sleeve. Then a supporting bandage Matoplast is applied to the fingers and on hand. Another layer is cotton RoltaSoft covering whole limb. The external layer consists of short  stretch Hartmann bandages. 

Measurements:
To assess the volume of limb we use an optoelectronic Perometer 400 T, co - operating with a personal computer. This method allows to estimate the volume of the measuring error for only 0.5%. The assessment technique is based on a special ring, equipped with a system of 378 LED diodes (emitting the infrared radiation). Within the ring are also the optical sensors that receive electromagnetic stimuli. In the course of measuring the limb is located inside the ring on the diode - sensor lines. The registered light pulses on the detectors is turned into electronic signals. The ring moves during measurement to cover the entire limb. Measurements of the limb volume (both affected and healthy upper limb) are made for all three groups of patients before and after therapy 
</interventions>
    <comparator>patients treated in use of quasi-KT and multi-layered bandaging</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction of limb volume

Tests/methods: perometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>after 1 month therapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage edema size 

Tests/methods: perometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 1 month therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) unilateral breast cancer-related lymphedema for at least one year, (2) moderate to severe lymphedema (stage II and III of upper limb edema, the volume difference between affected and healthy extremity more than 20%), (3) lack of chemo- or radiation therapy for at least 6 months, (4) good compliance and willingness to sign the written consent form. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) active cancer or disease that might lead to swelling and presently taking diuretic therapy or other lymphedema-influencing drugs, (2) skin disease, (3) irremovable bracelet or ring, (4) marked restriction of active range of motion in the affected upper extremity, (5) the presence of a pacemaker, heart disease, pregnancy, metallic devices in the limb to be treated, infectious disease, epilepsy, cartilage growth, thrombophlebitis, arterial hypertension or metastases, which are the treatment contraindications, and (6) the presence of mental, sensorial or language problems, which could make cooperation difficult. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants are randomly allocated to the groups. Computer-generated random numbers were sealed in sequentially numbered envelopes, and the group allocation was independent of the time and person delivering the treatment. The physician (main coordinator) who allocated the patients to groups had envelopes, each containing a piece of paper marked with either group KT, Quasi KT, or MCT. The physician would select and open an envelope in the presence of a physiotherapist to see the symbol and would then direct the patient to the corresponding group. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer and numbered envelopes</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis and evaluation of the results are be based on the comparison of intra- and intergroup results. Statistical analysis of these results is performed by means of the Statistica 10 software, manufactured by StatSoft (licence of Academy School of Physical Education). 

To compare the individual parameters that characterized the study groups, the non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis test for countable variables and the chi-squared test for categorical variables is used (75 patients in three groups are not enough for parametric analysis and comparing to normal distribution Gauss curve). The nonparametric matched pair Wilcoxon test is used to compare the within-group results before and after therapy. The Kruskal-Wallis analysis of variance (post hoc Tukeys test) is used to evaluate differences in the changes between the groups in the limb volume and edema values. Two-sided results (p&lt;0.05) are considered to be statistically significant.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/12/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/08/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/08/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Silesia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Academy School of Physical Education</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mikolowska Street 72 40-065 Katowice</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Academy School of Physical Education
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mikolowska Street 72 40-065 Katowice</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Kinesiology Taping (KT) for lymphatic drainage is a new choice in the field of physical and alternative therapy. The material used for the Kinesio tape and the original concept of the taping technique was introduced by Dr. Kenso Kase in 1973. K-tape had been designed to allow 30-40% longitudinal stretch. It is composed of 100% cotton fibers and acrylic heat sensitive glue. Development of the technique for its administration is still ongoing. Dr. Kase claimed that applying K-tape would have physiological effects including decreasing pain or abnormal sensation, supporting the movement of muscles, removing congestion of lymphatic fluid or hemorrhages under the skin, and correcting misalignment of joints. After applying K-tape, the taped area will form convolutions to increase the space between the skin and muscles. Once the skin is lifted, the flow of blood and lymphatic fluid is promoted. Other advantages are that a patient can take a shower without taking the tape off since it is waterproof. Patients can wear it 1 to 4 days and even longer if it is applied on the back or buttock area. Many practitioners use it in clinical practice in European countries, and it has a beneficial effect. However, there is insufficient evidence for its clinical effects on lymphedematic limbs. The aim of the study is to assess the efficacy of Kinesiology Taping (KT) for treating breast cancer-related lymphedema. The endpoints are the reduction of limb volume and percentage edema size after a month therapy.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Research Ethics Committee from the Academy School of Physical Education in Katowice, Poland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mikolowska Street 72 40-065 Katowice</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1605/12/2012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jakub Taradaj</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy Basics 
Academy School of Physical Education 
Mikolowska 72 Street 40-065 Katowice</address>
      <phone>+48668613945</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.taradaj@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jakub Taradaj</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy Basics 
Academy School of Physical Education 
Mikolowska 72 Street 40-065 Katowice</address>
      <phone>+48668613945</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.taradaj@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jakub Taradaj</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy Basics 
Academy School of Physical Education 
Mikolowska 72 Street 40-065 Katowice</address>
      <phone>+48668613945</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.taradaj@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jakub Taradaj</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy Basics 
Academy School of Physical Education 
Mikolowska 72 Street 40-065 Katowice</address>
      <phone>+48668613945</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.taradaj@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>