<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1225">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/04/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000155594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) weaning trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) weaning trial to determine the most efficient method in weaning babies less than 30 weeks gestational age "OFF" CPAP.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CPAP weaning trial follow up phase</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Babies who are on constant continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) support need to have the CPAP weaned in order to allow the babies to breathe without support.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This trial will look at 3 methods of weaning CPAP.
Method 1. When the baby has reached the stability criteria they will be taken OFF CPAP.
Method 2.  When the baby has reached the stability criteria they will be gradually taken OFF CPAP from 30 minutes to completely OFF .
Method 3. When the baby has reached the stability criteria they will be gradually taken OFF CPAP from 30 minutes to completely OFF as in method 2, but when the baby is having time OFF CPAP  they will have supplemental air or oxygen via a nasal cannula at 0.5 L/min</interventions>
    <comparator>No control groups, 3 treament groups.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in time of respiratory support.  For methods 1 and 2 this will be 24 hours "OFF" CPAP and for those in method 3, this will be 24 hours "OFF" nasal cannula. So the time on CPAP will be from the time commenced CPAP to "OFF" support.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days after OFF CPAP.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in Chronic Lung Disease (CLD) rate defined as requiring oxygen at 36 weeks post conceptional age</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 Weeks post conceptional age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in admission time</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge to home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.All babies &lt;30 weeks gestational age 2.On CPAP for &gt;24 hours 3.Babies either extubated to CPAP or as a primary treatment for respiratory distress Criteria for commencing weaning: Babies must have all of the following for the past 12 hours:- 1.CPAP &lt;6 cm H2O 2.Oxygen requirement less than 26% and not increasing 3.RR less than 60 4.No significant chest recession 5.Less than 3 episodes of mild self reverting apnoeas and/or bradycardias and/or desaturations in 1 hour for the previous 6 hours 6.Average saturation above 87% most of the time and/or transcutaneous (TcPO2)/arterial PaO2 &gt;50 mm Hg. 7.Tolerates nose rests well during nursing cares 8.Not treated for patent ductus arteriosus (PDA) or sepsis Criteria for failed trial OFF at least 2 of the following:- 1.Increase work of breathing (Intercostal recession and accessory muscles contributing for respiration) with RR &gt;75 for &gt;1 hour 2.Increased apnoeas and/or bradycardias and/or desaturations &gt;2 in previous 1 hour 3.Major apnoea or bradycardia requiring more sustained stimulation/ resuscitation 4.Increased O2 requirement &gt;25% with average saturation &lt;85% and/or TcPO2/PaO2 &lt;45mmHg 5.pH of &lt;7.2 6.PaCO2 of &gt; 65 mmHg. The babies will be put back on CPAP if failed trial OFF CPAP. If a baby has a major apnoea and/or bradycardia requiring resuscitation they may require intubation and ventilation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. If congenital respiratory abnormality including central and anatomical.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The randomisation will now be web based where investigators will log into the CPAP weaning trial web site (TREONIC WEB SITE) and once logged in will be able to randomise babies to a specific group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation. The babies will be stratified into 2 gestational age (GA) categories.  One category will be babies &lt; 27 weeks GA and the second category will be babies 27-29 weeks GA.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>If the babies fail time OFF CPAP they will return to the same CPAP weaning group.  We will review the data after 90 babies have been enrolled.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Random sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/03/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr David Todd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Neonatal Unit 
The Canberra hospital
Woden
ACT
2606</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Canberra Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ACT, 2606</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many small babies &lt;30 weeks gestational age have a very immature respiratory system and require respiratory support for a limited period of time until they mature and can breath by themselves. Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) is one such method by which support can be given to these immature babies to allow them to breath without being put on a ventilator or breathing machine. When these babies have matured a little the CPAP is weaned in order to allow the babies to breath without support.  This trial will look at 3 methods of weaning CPAP to see which method is most efficient in allowing the babies to breath on their own. The trial has started at Westmead Hospital and we hope to include other Hospitals to increase our numbers in the trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Westmead Hospital, Sydney West Area Health Service The Canberra Hospital, Woden ACT 2606 
Royal Brisbane and Womens' Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2005/8/4.27(2087)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mrs Margaret Broom</name>
      <address>Newborn Intensive Care Unit (NICU) The Canberra Hospital PO Box 11 Woden ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61 2 62444056</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 62443112</fax>
      <email>Margaret.Broom@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr David Todd</name>
      <address>Newborn Intensive Care Unit (NICU)
The Canberra Hospital
PO Box 11
Woden ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61 2 62444056</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 62443112</fax>
      <email>david.todd@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>