<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369041">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000893505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of artesunate+ampdiaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated malaria in district hospital of Massakory, Hadjer Lamis region, Chad</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of artesunate+ampdiaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated malaria in district hospital of Massakory, Hadjer Lamis region, Chad</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NIL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To assess the efficacy and safety of artesunate+amodiaquine
(artesunate 4 mg/kg body weight + amodiaquine 10mg/kg body weight once daily for 3 consecutive days) for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum infection. The treatment will be taken orally under direct supervision by the health worker. Eligibile subjects will be treated for three days and followed up for 28 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable.

This is a surveillance study of one-arm.
</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of treatment failures (early treatment failure + late clinical failure +late parasitological failure). This is composite primary outcome.

Enrolled patients will be assessed for parasitological (using microscopy), clinical responses during the 28 days follow-up and treatment outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 28 following initiation of artesunate+amodiaquine</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of adverse event will be documented. The known adverse events of artesunate+amodiaquineare Asthenia, cough, diarrhoea, fever, loss of appetite, nausea, vomiting.

Parents or guardians of all enrolled patients will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be evaluated and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 28 following initiation of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of artemisinin resistance molecular markers (K13).

Parasite DNA extracted from the dried blood spots will be analyzed by PCR and sequencing for the presence of K13 (molecular marker for artemisinin resistance).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Day 0 (prior initiation of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. age between six months and 5 years;
2. mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy;
3. parasitaemia of 1000100,000/microliter asexual forms;
4. presence of axillary temperature greater or equal to 37.5 degrees C or history of fever during the past 24 h
5. ability to swallow oral medication;
6. ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule;
7.informed consent from the parent or guardian in the case of children
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO;
2. weight under 5 kg;
3. mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
4. presence of severe malnutrition defined as a child aged 6-60 months has a mid-upper arm circumference belo 115 mm)
5. presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS);
6. regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial
pharmacokinetics;
7. history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s);
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients aged between 6 month and 5 years with uncomplicated malaria who meet the study inclusion criteria will be enrolled, treated on site with artesunate+amodiaquine and monitored for 28 days. The follow-up will consist of a fixed schedule of check-up visits and corresponding clinical and laboratory examinations.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable.

This surveillance study is a one-arm prospective evaluation of clinical and parasitological responses to directly observed treatment for uncomplicated malaria with artesunate+amodiaquine.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Currently the treatment failure rate to 
artesunate+amodiaquine in the study area is assumed unknown and assumed to be &lt;50%. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 10%, a minimum of 96 patients must be included per drug test. With a 20% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the 28-day follow-up period, 103 patients should be included in the study.

Excel WHO tailored database will be used for data management and analysis. Data will be analysed by two methods: the Kaplan-Meier method and per-protocol analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>103</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>105</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>29/12/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Chad</country>
      <state>Hadjer-Lamis Region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health of Chad</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>N'djamena 
B.P. 440 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Chad</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health of Chad</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>N'djamena 
B.P. 440 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Chad</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of artesunate+amodiaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in district hospital of Massakory, Hadier Lamis region of Chad

Purpose: To assess the efficacy and safety of the first-line treatment.

Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety of artesunate+amodiaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria infections.

Study Sites: District hospital of Massakory, Hadier Lamis region of Chad.

Study Period: The study will be conducted from 1 August to 1st October 2015.

Study Design: A one arm prospective study.

Patient population: Febrile patients aged between 6 months and 5 years 
with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum infection will be enrolled.

Sample Size: A total of 103 patients will be enrolled.

Treatments and follow-up: artesunate+amodiaquine given daily dose for
3 days. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 28-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy and safety.

Primary endpoints: The proportion of patients with early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response as indicators of efficacy. Recrudescence will be distinguished from re-infection by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis. Day 3 malaria positivity rate will determined.

Secondary endpoints: The frequency of adverse events and polymorphism of molecular markers for artemisinin resistance.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National EThical board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>B.P. 440 
N'djamena </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2192/PR/PM/MSP/SE/SG</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Chad</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WHO ERC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Av. Appia,
1211 Geneva 27 Switzerland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ERC.0002631</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Clement Kerah Hinzoumbe</name>
      <address>BP 759 Njamena</address>
      <phone>+23566282431</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerah_clement@yahoo.fr</email>
      <country>Chad</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Clement Kerah Hinzoumbe</name>
      <address>BP 759 Njamena</address>
      <phone>+23566282431</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerah_clement@yahoo.fr</email>
      <country>Chad</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Clement Kerah Hinzoumbe</name>
      <address>BP 759 Njamena</address>
      <phone>+23566282431</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerah_clement@yahoo.fr</email>
      <country>Chad</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marian Warsame</name>
      <address>Global Malaria Programme, World health Organization 20 Av. Appia, 1211
Geneva 27 Switzerland</address>
      <phone>+41 22 791 5076</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>warsamem@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>