<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347948">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000072819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Stand@Work Pilot Study. A randomised controlled trial to see if using sit-stand workstations reduces sitting time in office workers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In office workers, does using a sit-stand workstation lead to reductions in sitting time?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Stand@Work</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prolonged sitting during work and outside of work</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention involves giving office workers a sit-stand workstation to use for 4 weeks for all workdays each week (3 to 5 workdays per week depending on full-time or part-time employment status). The sit-stand workstation allows office workers to vary their posture throughout the workday between sitting and standing. Prior to receiving the sit-stand workstation, participants will receive brief training on how to use the sit-stand workstations, including how to adjust workstation height and the correct ergonomic set ups while sitting or standing.

Participants will complete a workday sitting and total sitting questionnaire at 4 weeks pre-intervention (baseline), 2 weeks pre-intervention (pre-intervention), and 2 weeks mid-intervention (intervention). At each measurement timepoint, participants will wear activity monitors for that week (7 days).

After the intervention, each participant will attend one focus group faciliated by two members of the research team. Each focus group will involve 5 to 6 participants and will run for approximately 45 minutes. Participants will provide their views on a range of issues relate to their time using the sit-stand workstation (e.g., effects on productivity, physical discomfort, ease of use, enjoyable, feasibility in the office)</interventions>
    <comparator>This study has a randomised controlled trial design (waitlist control) with crossover and rolling recruitment. Control participants will be on the waiting list for 4 weeks before they receive the sit-stand workstations.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported time spent sitting, standing, walking or doing physically demanding tasks at work. (Occupational Sitting and Physical Activity Questionnaire, OSPAQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks pre-intervention (baseline)
2 weeks pre-intervention (pre-intervention)
2 weeks mid-intervention (intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported sitting time in different domains (e.g., at work, for transport, using the computer) by work and nonworkdays. (Workforce Sitting Questionnaire, WSQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks pre-intervention (baseline)
2 weeks pre-intervention (pre-intervention)
2 weeks mid-intervention (intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objectively measured sedentary and activity time. The Actigraph accelerometer will assess time in different activity intensity levels (i.e., sedentary, light, moderate-to-vigorous). The ActivPAL will measure time spent in different postures (i.e., sitting, standing)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks pre-intervention (baseline)
2 weeks pre-intervention (pre-intervention)
2 weeks mid-intervention (intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative focus group data on perceptions and attitudes about using the sit-stand workstations. E.g., ease of use, any discomfort, impact on productivity, feasibility in the workplace, enjoyableness</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Staff working at the Heart Foundation Sydney and Newcastle offices. Participants must be over the age of 18 years, work at least 3 days per week, and have sufficient English language proficiency to take part in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Working less than 3 days per week</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This study has a randomised controlled trial design (waitlist control group) with crossover and rolling recruitment. Eligible staff members who express interest in being involved will be randomly drawn from a ballot and assigned to the intervention or control condition after completing a consent form to participate in the study. Participants allocated to the intervention will use a sit-stand workstation for 4 weeks, while control participants will be on the waiting list for 4 weeks before they receive the sit-stand workstations. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation via ballot draw</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cluster for Physical Activity and Health, Prevention Research Collaboration</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cluster for Physical Activity and Health, Prevention Research Collaboration
Sydney School of Public Health
Level 2, Medical Foundation Building (K25)
University of Sydney NSW 2006

Street address:
Level 2 Medical Foundation Building
94 Parramatta Rd, Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Foundation New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Heart Foundation New South Wales
Level 3, 80 William Street
East Sydney NSW 2011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Heart Foundation New South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Heart Foundation New South Wales
Level 3, 80 William Street
East Sydney NSW 2011</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sitting is recognised as a new risk factor for developing chronic illnesses that is independent of physical activity. Current knowledge is limited regarding effective strategies for reducing sitting in the workplace. This study will evaluate whether using sit-stand workstations in the office changes office workers sitting time at work and outside of work. Sit-stand workstations allow office staff to switch between sitting and standing while they are working at their desks. Participants (n=50) will trial the sit-stand workstations for 4 weeks and complete questionnaires about their sitting time before and during the trial. They will also wear activity monitors which will objectively measure their sitting time at each measurement time point. After the trial, participants will have a debrief session where they will give feedback about the sit-stand workstations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building - G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/08/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08-2011 / 14067</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hidde van der Ploeg or Josephine Chau</name>
      <address>Cluster for Physical Activity and Health, Prevention Research Collaboration
Level 2 Medical Foundation Building K25
University of Sydney NSW 2006

Street address:
Level 2 Medical Foundation Building
94 Parramatta Rd, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9036 3288  or +61 2 9036 3337</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hidde.vanderploeg@sydney.edu.au or josephine.chau@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michelle Daley or Scott Dunn</name>
      <address>Heart Foundation New South Wales
Level 3, 80 William Street
East Sydney NSW 2011</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9219 2459 or +61 2 9219 2458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Michelle.Daley@heartfoundation.org.au or 
scott@actevate.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Josephine Chau</name>
      <address>Cluster for Physical Activity and Health, Prevention Research Collaboration
Level 2 Medical Foundation Building K25
University of Sydney NSW 2006

Street address:
Level 2 Medical Foundation Building
94 Parramatta Rd, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9036 3337</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>josephine.chau@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>