<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373531">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001261303p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Physical Activity Promotion in Community-Dwelling Adults with Whiplash Associated Disorders</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a Physical Activity Intervention for Adults With Brain
Impairment: A Multiple-Baseline, Single Case Experimental Study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>n/a</utrn>
    <trialacronym>n/a</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Whiplash Associated Disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Adapted Physical Activity (APA) model is a theory-based PA promotion intervention for people with chronic and complex conditions delivered in the participants home and community. The APA model is comprised of four steps; 
Step 1: comprised of a preparticipation evaluation of physiological, personal and environmental factors that influence physical activity participation (Step 1a); a stage of change assessment (Step 1b); and information sharing activity (Step 1c);
Step 2: comprised of a lifestyle PA intervention comprised of tailored evidence based PA promotion strategies;
Step 3: comprised of structured exercise prescription (Step 3a) and community integration (Step 3b); and 
Step 4: tailored relapse prevention strategies. 
All participants receive Step 1, 2, 3 and 4 of the intervention program. Based on the stage of change assessment conducted in Step 1b, participants strategies in Step 2 will be tailored as per the participants motivational readiness. Depending on the outcomes of the discussions undertaken during Step 2 participants will undertake an individually tailored combination of  structured exercise (Step 3a) or community based activities that promote PA participation (Step 3b). Structured exercise prescription, as per Step 3a, includes goal oriented PA prescribed in terms of frequency, intensity, time and type targeted towards improving one or more components of health and/or physical fitness. Exercise prescription will be tailored based on the participants physical functioning and goals, with activity intensity in the first instance being light and progressing to moderate intensity. Community integration (Step 3b) includes the promotion of PA achieved through participation in activities of daily living, outdoor recreational activities or sport. Step 4 of the intervention entails the delivery of individually tailored relapse prevention strategies designed to help participants identify potential situations in which their PA routine may be disrupted or stopped (e.g., illness, reduction in social support, weather changes) and to formulate appropriate strategies to restart or continue with their PA program [1]. A previous controlled clinical trial conducted by the study investigators demonstrated that this intervention can be successfully used to promote PA adoption in adults with brain impairment [2]. 

The design  will require simultaneous commencement of 3-5 participants who will complete 8 weeks of baseline data collection (minimum), 16 weeks of an intervention program and 8 weeks of follow-up data collection. Participants in the PA intervention will participate in 10 face to face one hour sessions over a 16-week period conducted in their home environment. The intervention will be delivered by an accredited exercise physiologist with experience in exercise prescription for individuals with a disability and behaviour change strategies associated with increasing PA. The features of the APA model are well situated to help promote PA in adults with chronic whiplash associated disorder (WAD). The intervention program fosters self-management with the activities undertaken being directly tailored towards the participants goals relating to independence and function with an emphasis on integrating the participant to pre-existing services within their local community [3]. Step 3a relates to active exercise that can involve functional exercises (stretching and isometric), range of motion exercises and general strengthening exercises which have been determined to be an important component of rehabilitation for patients with WAD. The exercise program incorporates a slow progression of duration and intensity with a focus on increasing general physical fitness and reducing fear of movement [4, 5]. Step 3b promotes the adoption and maintenance of normal recreational and occupational activities with a focus on improving function and community integration. 

Tailoring of the intervention model will be undertaken to include strategies identified to be associated with increased PA participation and effective self-management in adults with chronic WAD including setting specific, realistic and relevant goals, use of positive encouragement, promoting pacing of activities, barrier identification and resolution, promoting self-efficacy and addressing fear-avoidance [3, 6]. 

Intervention fidelity and equivalent contact will be monitored by researchers associated with the study during case management meetings. 

1.	Blair, S.N., et al., Active Living Every Day. 2001, Champaign, IL: Human Kinetics.
2.	Clanchy, K., S.M. Tweedy, and S.G. Trost, Evaluation of a Physical Activity Intervention for Adults With Brain Impairment: A Controlled Clinical Trial. Neurorehabilitation and Neural Repair, 2016. 30(9): p. 854-865.
3.	Motor Accident Commission and South Australian Centre for Trauma and Injury Recovery, Clinical Guidelines for Best Practice Management of Acute and Chronic Whiplash Associated Disorders: Clinical Resource Guide. 2008, South Australia: TRACsa: Trauma and Injury Recovery.
4.	Gill, J.R. and C.A. Brown, A Structured Review of the Evidence for Pacing as a Chronic Pain Intervention. European Journal of Pain, 2009. 13(2): p. 214-216.
5.	Wallman, K.E., et al., Randomised Controlled Trial of Graded Exercise in Chronic Fatigue Syndrome. Medical Journal of Australia, 2004. 180(9): p. 444-448.
6.	Soderlund, A. and P. Lindberg, Cognitive Behavioural Components in Physiotherapy Management of Chronic Whiplash Associated Disorders (WAD)- A Randomised Group Study. Supplemento A, Psicologia, 2007. 29(1): p. A5-A11.


</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Participation: The primary outcome measure will be habitual PA measured by the ActiGraph GT9X Link accelerometer. The ActiGraph is a triaxial accelerometer that measures vertical acceleration 25 times each second, and these data are integrated over a user defined period, or epoch, to give a number of counts. ActiGraph counts provide a real-time indication of the intensity of physical activity performed by an individual  the higher the counts, the greater the activity intensity. It is small, unobtrusive, lightweight, non-reactive and because it collects activity data in real time is capable of assessing the pattern and intensity of activity, as well as total accumulated activity.  The ActiGraph link is a wrist worn accelerometer which improves client comfort and compliance. The monitor can be programmed to display the time and date only or to provide participants with feedback regarding their activity participation. 

An epoch of 1 minute will be used in this study [1]. On completion of the 3-day monitoring period, the accelerometer data will be downloaded, and a customized Visual Basic Excel Macro will be used to determine daily wear time, daily average counts per minute (cpm), and daily time spent in MVPA. Counts will be classified as either MVPA or light/sedentary using the Freedson et al [2] cut-point. For a monitoring day to be considered valid and included for analysis, 600 minutes of wear time will be required [3]. Non-wear time is classified as consecutive 0 counts for at least 60 consecutive minutes, allowing for up to 2 consecutive 1-minute epochs with nonzero counts less than or equal to 100 counts. Daily wear time will be calculated by subtracting the estimated non-wear time from the total monitoring time. 

1.	Trost, S.G., K.L. McIver, and R.R. Pate, Conducting Accelerometer Based Activity Assessments in Field-Based Research. Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise, 2005. 37: p. s531-s543.
2.	Freedson, P.S., E. Melanson, and J. Sirad, Calibration of the Computer Science and Applications, Inc. Accelerometer. Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise, 1998. 30: p. 777-781.
3.	Choi, L., et al., Validation of Accelerometer Wear and Nonwear Time Classification Algorithm. Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise, 2011. 43(357-364).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will wear the device for 5 x 3 day data collection periods in each stage of the research program (e.g., baseline-during the intervention-follow up) for 15 data collection points in total. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 3; Week 5; Week 7; and Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 9; Week 13; Week 17; Week 20; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 25; Week 27; Week 29; Week 31; Week 32</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck Disability Index (NDI): The NDI is a valid, reliable and responsive measure of neck pain related disability [1, 2]. The questionnaire has 10 items concerning pain and activities of daily living including personal care, lifting, reading, headaches, concentration, work status, driving, sleeping and recreation. An overall score (out of 100) will be calculated by totaling responses to 10 questions, each with 6 potential Likert-type responses (e.g., 0 indicating no disability to 5 indicating total disability), and multiplying the sum by 2 to yield a percentage.

1.	MacDermid, J.C., et al., Measurement Properties of the Neck Disability Index: A Systematic Review. Journal of Orthopaedic and Sports Physical Therapy, 2009. 39(5): p. 400-412.
2.	Vernon, H. and S. Moir, The Neck Disability Index: A Study of Reliability and Validity. Journal of Manipulative Physiological Therapeutics, 1991. 14(7): p. 409-415.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete this measure 5 times during each stage of the research program (e.g., baseline-during the intervention-follow up) for 15 data collection points in total. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 3; Week 5; Week 7; and Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 9; Week 13; Week 17; Week 20; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 25; Week 27; Week 29; Week 31; Week 32
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Self-Efficacy: Self-efficacy will be measured using the 5-item scale developed by Marcus et al. [1]. A 5-point Likert-type scale is used to rate each item, with 1 indicating not at all confident, and 5 very confident.

1.	Marcus, B.H., et al., Self-Efficacy and the Stages of Exercise Behaviour Change. Research Quarterly for Exercise and Sport, 1992. 63: p. 60-66.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Support for Physical Activity Participation: Social support will be measured using the 13-item scale developed by Sallis et al. [1]. A 5-point Likert type scale will be used to rate the frequency of support received from family and friends in the 3-months prior, with 1 indicating none, and 5 indicating very often. Social support scores will be calculated for family and friends separately by computing the sum of the items on the measure [39].

1.	Sallis, J., et al., The Development of Scales to Measure Social Support for Diet and Exercise Behaviours. Preventative Medicine, 1987. 16: p. 825-836.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decisional Balance for Physical Activity Participation: Decisional balance will be measured using the 16-item scale developed by Marcus et al [1] which included 6 items representing the avoidance of exercise (cons) and 10 items representing the positive perceptions of exercise (pros). A 5-point Likert-type scale will be used to rate how important each statement is, with 1 indicating not at all important, and 5 indicating extremely important. The average of the 10 pro items and the 6 con items will be computed. The difference in the averages (i.e., average pro score - average con score) will be taken as the decisional balance score.

1.	Marcus, B.H., W. Rakowski, and J.S. Rossi, Assessing Motivational Readiness and Decision Making For Exercise. Health Psychology, 1992. 11: p. 257-261.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: Participants health related quality of life will be assessed using The Medical Outcomes Survey Short Form (SF-12) measure. The SF-12 contains 12 questions relating to domains including: physical functioning; role limitations because of physical health problems; bodily pain; general health perceptions; vitality (energy/fatigue); social functioning; role limitations because of emotional problems; and general mental health (psychological distress and psychological well-being) [1, 2]. The 12 items will be used to calculate a physical and mental component summary score [3]. The SF-12 has demonstrated evidence of validity and reliability for use in individuals with chronic disease including cervical spine disorders [4]. 

1.	Cheak-Zamora, N.C. and K.W. Wyrwich, Reliability and Validity of the SF-12v2 in the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey. Quality of Life Research, 2009. 18(6): p. 727-735.
2.	Jakobsson, U. and A. Westergren, Construct Validity of the SF-12 in Three Different Samples. Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice, 2012. 18(3): p. 560-566.
3.	Ware J, K.M., Keller S. A SF-12: How to Score the SF-12 Physical and Mental Health Summary Scales. Vol. Second Edition. 1995, Boston, MA.: The Health Istitute, New England Medical Center.
4.	Lee, C. and D. Jones, Measuring Health of Patients with Cervical Spinal Disorder: Is the SF-12 Health Survey a Valid Alternative for the SF-36. The Journal of Pain, 2007. 8(4): p. s22.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numeric Pain Rating Scale: Participants will be asked to rate their current, best and worst pain using a Numeric Pain Rating Scale [1]. Participants will be asked to select the number that best represents their pain during the previous 24-hours on a scale of 0 to 10; with 0 indicating no pain and 10 indicating worst possible pain. Scores will be categorised as mild (score ranging 13), moderate (score ranging 46), or severe pain (score ranging 710) [2]. Evidence indicates that Numeric Pain Rating Scales can provide sufficient discriminative power for chronic pain patients to describe their pain intensity [3].
1.	McCaffery, M. and A. Beebe, Pain: Clinical Manual for Nursing Practice. 1989, St. Louis, MO: Mosby.
2.	Fejer, R., A. Jordan, and J. Hartvigsen, Categorising the Severity of Neck Pain: Establishment of Cut Points for Use in Clinical and Epidemiological Research. Pain, 2005. 119: p. 176182.
3.	Jensen, M.P., J.A. Turner, and J.M. Romano, What is the Maximum Number of Levels Needed in Pain Intensity Measurement? Pain, 1994. 58: p. 387-392.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.   </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS): Catastrophizing is defined as an exaggerated negative mental set brought to bear during an actual or anticipated painful experience [1]. The PCS is a 13-item instrument relating to the degree to which participants experienced 13 thoughts or feelings when experiencing pain on a 5-point scale with 0 indicating not at all and 4 indicating all the time. The measure provides a total pain catastrophizing score and a scale for three subscales including rumination, magnification and helplessness. The sum of responses yields a score out of 52 with higher scores indicating greater pain catastrophizing. A PCS total score &gt;24 indicates a high level of pain catastrophizing. The PCS has been shown to have adequate internal consistency (coefficient alphas: total PCS= .87, rumination= .87, magnification= .66, and helplessness= .78) [2].

1.	Sullivan, M.J.L., et al., Theoretical Perspectives on the Relation Between Catastrophizing and Pain. The Clinical Journal of Pain, 2001. 17: p. 52-64.
2.	Sullivan, M.J.L., S. Bishop, and J. Pivik, The Pain Catastrophizing Scale: Development and Validation. Psychological Assessment, 1995. 7: p. 524-532.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-Efficacy Scale: The Pain Self-Efficacy Questionnaire (PSEQ) is a self-administered, 10 item questionnaire survey that was developed to assess an individuals confidence to perform specific tasks in the presence of pain.  Confidence in performing each of 10 activities/tasks despite current pain is rated from 0 (not at all confident) to 6 (completely confident) [1]. Responses are totalled to provide a score out of 60 with higher scores reflecting stronger self-efficacy beliefs.

1.	Nicholas, M., The Pain Self-Efficacy Questionnaire: Taking Pain into Account. European Journal of Pain, 2007. 11: p. 153163.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and Anxiety: The Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale short version (DASS21) is a widely used, valid and reliable self-administered tool that is designed to assess symptoms of three negative emotional states: depression, anxiety and stress [1]. The 21-item self-administered survey contains three subscales: depression, anxiety and stress. Each subscale contains 7-items.  There are 4 response options for each item with 0 indicating did not apply to me at all, never and 3 indicating applied to me very much or most of the time, almost always.  Scores are totalled for each subscale [2]. Higher scores on each subscale indicate increased symptom severity. 

1.	Parkitny, L. and J. McAuley, The Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS). Journal of Physiotherapy, 2010. 56: p. 204.
2.	Lovibond, S. and P. Lovibond, Manual for the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales. 1995, Sydney: Psychology Foundation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Posttraumatic Stress Symptoms: The Impact of Event Scale-Revised (IES-R) is a self-administered, 22-item survey developed to assess an individuals subjective distress to a specific traumatic event. The IES-R comprises 3 subscales: intrusion, avoidance and hyperarousal [1]. The client is asked to report the degree of distress experienced for each item over the past 7 days. Each question has 5 response options with 0 indicating not at all and 4 indicating extremely. The scores therefore range from 0-4 for each subscale and 0-12 for the total, with higher scores indicating greater distress.

1.	Weiss, D., et al., The Impact of Event Scale-Revised, in Assessing Psychological Trauma and PTSD: a Practitioner's Handbook. 1999, Guilford Press: New York. p. 399-411.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 of the baseline period; at the conclusion of the baseline period; at the midpoint of the intervention; at the end point of the intervention; and at the end of the follow-up period. 
Baseline (8 weeks total- weeks 1-8): Week 1; Week 8
Intervention (16 weeks total- weeks 9-24): Week 17; Week 24
Follow Up (8 weeks total- weeks 25-32): Week 32
Secondary outcome measures will administered using an online survey medium.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Process Evaluation: At the conclusion of the intervention participants will be asked to participate in a semi-structured interview regarding their perceptions of the intervention efficacy and acceptability. </outcome>
      <timepoint>An interview will be conducted with the participant immediately post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants and Recruitment: Five participants aged 18-50 years will be recruited for this study. 

Participants meeting the following inclusion criteria are eligible to participate: 
	Grade II whiplash of at least 3 months duration; 
	Living in a community setting in the Brisbane, Gold Coast or Northern NSW region; 
	A neck disability index score &gt;30% (e.g., indicative of a moderate disability) as per the Neck Disability Index (NDI) Scale [1, 2]; 
	Deemed medically safe to participate in moderate intensity PA as per Exercise and Sports Science Australias Adult Pre-Exercise Screening System [3] and the American College of Sports Medicine Guidelines; and
	Currently not enrolled in structured sport or training for physical fitness; and not completing 30 minutes of moderate PA on 5 or more days per week. 

1.	MacDermid, J.C., et al., Measurement Properties of the Neck Disability Index: A Systematic Review. Journal of Orthopaedic and Sports Physical Therapy, 2009. 39(5): p. 400-412.
2.	Vernon, H. and S. Moir, The Neck Disability Index: A Study of Reliability and Validity. Journal of Manipulative Physiological Therapeutics, 1991. 14(7): p. 409-415.
3.	Exercise and Sports Science Australia, Adult Pre-Exercise Screening Tool. 2001: Version 1.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for the study includes:
	Known or suspected serious spinal pathology (e.g. metastatic disease of the spine); 
	Confirmed fracture or dislocation at time of injury  WAD Grade IV;
	Nerve root compromise  WAD Grade III; and
	Spinal surgery in the past 12 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>No allocation concealment will occur.</concealment>
    <sequence>There is no randomisation sequence required.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Study Design: The efficacy of the intervention program will be evaluated using a Multiple Baseline Single Subject Experimental Design to determine the optimal intervention for an individual using an objective data-driven criteria [1, 2]. The single subject design, includes within-subject methods, repeated measures designs, and intra-subject replication designs [2]. Within-subjects methods are advantageous for example in the context of disability research where the sample being investigated is frequently heterogeneous or when there are only few eligible subjects available [3]. Within this design the subjects can be exposed to both the treatment and control conditions as it also allows them to act as their own controls [3]. In the ranking system of evidence-based practice single subject study design are ranked as Level I Evidence by the Oxford Centre for Evidence Based Medicine yielding evidence of an equivalent strength to randomized controlled trials [3, 4]. 

This study will utilise an A1-B-A2 in which the use of different behavioural change strategies varied across the three phases: a baseline (A1 no intervention); intervention phase (B); and a no intervention (A2 follow up). 
Baseline: The participants will complete an 8-week baseline phase (minimum) undertaking their usual behaviour. The timeline of the baseline phase will vary across the participants in order to allow the intervention start point to be randomised.
Intervention Phase: The baseline phase will be followed by a 16-week intervention period. Participants in the PA intervention will participate in 10 one hour sessions over a 16-week period. The intervention will be delivered by an accredited exercise physiologist with experience in exercise prescription for individuals with a disability and behaviour change strategies associated with increasing PA.  
No Intervention (Follow-Up) Phase: The intervention phase will be followed by an 8-week follow-up phase where participants will have no contact with the intervention personnel. 

The study will be conducted and reported as per the Single Case Reporting Guidelines In BEhavioural Interventions (SCRIBE) 2016 Statement [5]. In the context of sample size and measuring sampling behaviour, the study design will be based on single-subject research design guidelines [3]. In order to evaluate the efficacy of the intervention it is recommend that a minimum of three participants and five data collection points in each phase are included in the study design [3]. 

Data collection will be completed by a researcher independent of the intervention delivery.

1.	Nikles, J., What are N-of-1 Trials?, in The Essential Guide to N-of-1 Trials in Health, J. Nikles and G. Mitchell, Editors. 2015, Springer Netherlands: Dordrecht. p. 9-17.
2.	Lillie, E.O., et al., The n-of-1 Clinical Trial: The Ultimate Strategy for Individualizing Medicine? Per Med, 2011. 8(2): p. 161-173.
3.	Romeiser Logan, L., et al., Single-Subject Research Design: Recommendations for Levels of Evidence and Quality Rating. Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology, 2008. 50(2): p. 99-103.
4.	OCEBM Levels of Evidence Working Group - Howick, J., Chalmers, I., Glasziou, P., Greenhalgh, T., Heneghan, C., Liberati, A., Moschetti, I., Phillips, B., Thornton, H., Goddard, O., and Hodgkinson, M. The Oxford 2011 Levels of Evidence Table (Introductory Document). 2011  [cited 2016; Available from: Available from: http://www.cebm.net/index.aspx?o=5653.
5.	Tate, R.L., et al., The Single-Case Reporting Guideline In BEhavioural Interventions (SCRIBE) 2016 Statement. Evidence-Based Communication Assessment and Intervention, 2016. 10(1): p. 44-58.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Main outcome measures will be plotted against time and visually examined for: (1) level; (2) trend; (3) variability; (4) immediacy of the effect; (5) overlap; and (6) consistency of data patterns in similar phases. More consistency, separation between phases, and strong patterns suggest a real effect. Once each phase is assessed, results from successive phases are compared to determine if the intervention had an effect by changing the outcome from phase to phase [1].

1.	Kratochwill, T.R., et al. Single-case designs technical documentation. . What Works Clearinghouse 2010  [cited 2016 30/8/2016]; Available from: Retrieved from website: http://ies.ed.gov/ncee/wwc/pdf/wwc_scd.pdf.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>5</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4217 - Gold Coast</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Allied Health Sciences
Clinical Science 1 (G02) Room 1.04
Gold Coast Campus
Griffith University, Southport
Queensland 4222 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Griffith University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Allied Health Sciences
Clinical Science 1 (G02) Room 1.04
Gold Coast Campus
Griffith University, Southport
Queensland 4222 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>n/a</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>n/a</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Whiplash associated disorders (WAD) account for approximately 75% of all survivable road traffic crash injuries with a socioeconomic costs relating to pain and disability exceeding $350 million in Queensland [1]. The overall aim of this project is to increase physical activity (PA) participation in adults with WAD. This will be achieved through the novel application of a tailored PA intervention that combines evidence-based PA promotion strategies, structured exercise prescription and community integration (APA model). The features of the APA model are well situated to help promote PA in adults with chronic WAD. The intervention program fosters self-management with the activities undertaken being directly tailored towards the participants goals relating to independence and function with an emphasis on integrating the participant to pre-existing services within their local community [2]. Our hypotheses are that the PA intervention will: (a) result in clinically significant increases in total PA participation and time spent in moderate intensity PA which has a demonstrated influence on reducing secondary disease and disability; (b) improve health related quality of life and psychological variables including anxiety, depression and pain catastrophizing; and c) reduce pain, perceived neck disability and fear of movement.

Five participants aged 18-50 years will be recruited for this study. Inclusion criteria includes: grade II whiplash of at least 3 months duration; living in a community setting; a neck disability index score &gt;32% [3]; deemed medically safe to participate in moderate intensity PA; and currently insufficiently physically active for good health. Exclusion criteria includes: known or suspected serious spinal pathology; confirmed fracture or dislocation at time of injury  WAD Grade IV; nerve root compromise; and spinal surgery in the past 12 months. 

This study will utilise Multiple Baseline Single Subject Experimental Design with three phases: 8-week baseline; a 16-week intervention comprised of 10 one hour sessions; and an 8-week no intervention withdraw. Participants will wear an accelerometer for 5 x 3 day periods in each stage of the research program for 15 data collection points in total. Secondary outcome measures will be collected during 5 data collection periods. Data collection will be completed by a researcher independent of the intervention delivery. 

1.	Motor Accident Insurance Commission, Motor Accident Insurance Commission Annual Report 2011-2012, 2012: Brisbane, Queensland.
2.	Motor Accident Commission and South Australian Centre for Trauma and Injury Recovery, Clinical Guidelines for Best Practice Management of Acute and Chronic Whiplash Associated Disorders: Clinical Resource Guide. 2008, South Australia: TRACsa: Trauma and Injury Recovery.
3.	MacDermid, J.C., et al., Measurement Properties of the Neck Disability Index: A Systematic Review. Journal of Orthopaedic and Sports Physical Therapy, 2009. 39(5): p. 400-412.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>n/a</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Level 0, Bray Centre (N54)
Griffith University
170 Kessels Road
Nathan Qld 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>Pending</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Clanchy</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Clinical Science 1 (G02) Room 1.04
Gold Coast Campus
Griffith University, Southport
Queensland 4222 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552-7006</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.clanchy@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Clanchy</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Clinical Science 1 (G02) Room 1.04
Gold Coast Campus
Griffith University, Southport
Queensland 4222 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552-7006</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.clanchy@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Clanchy</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Clinical Science 1 (G02) Room 1.04
Gold Coast Campus
Griffith University, Southport
Queensland 4222 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552-7006</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.clanchy@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Clanchy</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Clinical Science 1 (G02) Room 1.04
Gold Coast Campus
Griffith University, Southport
Queensland 4222 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5552-7006</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.clanchy@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>