<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365096">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001220752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Usability and initial efficacy testing of a website-delivered behaviour change intervention designed to promote physical activity among post-treatment breast cancer survivors. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Usability and initial efficacy testing of a website-delivered behaviour change intervention designed to promote physical activity among post-treatment breast cancer survivors. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>physical activity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to receive one of the following interventions:
(1) a computer-tailored single module intervention (participants are assessed and provided with a single round of feedback and advice); (2) a computer-tailored three module intervention delivered weekly (participants are assessed each week for two weeks and provided with iterative tailored feedback after each weekly assessment); and (3) a computer-tailored three module intervention delivered monthly (participants are assessed each month for two months and provided with iterative feedback after each monthly assessment).

For participants in the single module group - The advice participants receive will be delivered in a single module and will be tailored using information derived from individual assessments at baseline.  Completion of the module will take approximately half an hour. 

The advice will include information on the Australian physical activity (PA) guidelines for cancer survivors (non-tailored), tailored feedback on PA behaviour (aerobic, resistance) relative to the guidelines, information about the beneficial outcomes of PA, safety advice, expert advice from a behaviour change expert (non-tailored), a testimonial illustrating success, advice on eliciting social support, expert advice from an exercise physiologist (non-tailored), advice on restructuring the physical environment, information about available support services and an action planning activity. 

For participants in the three module arms advice will be 
tailored using information derived from individual assessments at baseline, and short assessments (assessing physical activity and goal setting behaviour) completed at the start of module 2 and 3. Each module will take 15-20 minutes to complete.

Participants will receive similar information to participants in the single module group but information will be provided over three separate modules (instead of all at once) and also contain some feedback on progress over time.

For this group, module 1 will include information on the Australian PA guidelines for cancer survivors (non-tailored), tailored feedback on PA behaviour (aerobic, resistance and sitting time) relative to the guidelines, information about the beneficial outcomes of PA, safety advice and an action planning activity. Module 2 will include expert advice from a behaviour change expert (non-tailored), feedback on PA performance (aerobic, resistance and sitting time) relative to N1, a testimonial illustrating success, advice on eliciting social support and an action planning activity. Module 3 will include expert advice from an exercise physiologist (non-tailored), tailored feedback on PA performance (aerobic, resistance and sitting time) relative to N2 and N1, advice on restructuring the physical environment, information about available support services and an action planning activity. 

Feedback in all modules is tailored primarily on demographic  social-cognitive, behavioural and health status variables collected at baseline. 


</interventions>
    <comparator>Single module intervention arm 

This group receives a single module 

The advice will include information on the Australian physical activity (PA) guidelines for cancer survivors (non-tailored), tailored feedback on PA behaviour (aerobic, resistance) relative to the guidelines, information about the beneficial outcomes of PA, safety advice, expert advice from a behaviour change expert (non-tailored), a testimonial illustrating success, advice on eliciting social support, expert advice from an exercise physiologist (non-tailored), advice on restructuring the physical environment, information about available support services and an action planning activity.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome, change in physical activity (Moderate-Vigorous mins/week) at 3 months post baseline, will be assessed using an adapted version of the leisure score index (LSI) of the validated Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (GLTEQ). The adapted version of the LSI contains three items assessing participants average participation (frequency and duration) in mild, moderate and strenuous aerobic physical activity in a typical week over the past month. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post-baseline </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical activity at other time points 

(change in physical activity at other time points will be assessed using an adapted version of the leisure score index (LSI) of the validated Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (GLTEQ). The adapted version of the LSI contains three items assessing participants average participation (frequency and duration) in mild, moderate and strenuous aerobic physical activity in a typical week over the past month). </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life  (FACT-B)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months, 6 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in resistance training activity 

Resistance-training will be assessed using an adapted version of the leisure score index (LSI) of the validated Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (GLTEQ). The adapted version of the LSI contains a resistance training item that asks participants to report the frequency (times per week) and duration (average exercises and repetitions per session) of resistance training activities (i.e., lifting, pushing, pulling, and/or controlled lowering using machine weights, free weights, body weight or therabands) on average over the past month. </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 3 months, and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible participants must: 
Have previously been diagnosed with breast cancer (at any time point). 
Have completed active cancer treatment (i.e., chemotherapy, radiotherapy, surgery). 
Be proficient in the English Language in order to read content of the website and complete surveys. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>To be eligible participants must not:
Have contraindications to exercise. 
Participate in moderate-vigorous physical activity for 150 minutes or more per week. 
Have previously participated in the Move More for Life Study (i.e., research project previously conducted by the research team). 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participant will be asked to register for the study online, and complete a consent and eligibility form. Once this is completed the computer software supporting the website will automatically randomise participants into one of the three groups and direct them to the appropriate website. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>PA data, socio-cognitive and QOL measures will be analysed using Linear-mixed model (LMM) analyses. The primary analysis will be conducted using all observed data (i.e., a completers analysis) and sensitivity analyses (accounting for all randomised participants) using the baseline observations carried forward approach will be conducted to explore the impact of missing data. 

To detect a medium standardized effect (d = 0.50) on our primary outcome (i.e., self-reported PA) with a power of 0.80 and a two-tailored alpha less than .05, we will need 63 survivors per group.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>190</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Queensland University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bruce Highway 
Central Queensland University 
Rockhampton QLD 4702</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to examine the usability and initial feasibility of a low cost distance-based intervention delivered via the internet for promoting physical activity among post-treatment breast cancer survivors. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are a woman aged 18 years or above who has been previously diagnosed with breast cancer (at any time point). To be eligible, you must have completed active cancer treatment and be proficient in the English language. Study details All participants in this study will receive a website-delivered tailored behaviour change intervention designed to promote physical activity. Participants will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of three groups. Those in group 1 will receive a single module intervention only, whereas groups 2 and 3 will receive a three module intervention delivered over 3 weeks in group 2 and 3 months in group 3. All participants will be assessed at 1, 3, and 6 months post baseline in order to determine any changes in physical activity and quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Under development </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CQ University's HUman Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CQU
Bruce Highway, 
Rockampton QLD 4702
Australia </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>H13/07-126</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Camille Short </name>
      <address>Building 18, room 1.30 
Bruce Highway
CQU University 
Rockhampton, QLD 4702 </address>
      <phone>61749232689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.short@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Camille Short </name>
      <address>Building 18, room 1.30 
Bruce Highway
CQU University 
Rockhampton, QLD 4702 </address>
      <phone>61749232689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.short@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Camille Short </name>
      <address>Building 18, room 1.30 
Bruce Highway
CQU University 
Rockhampton, QLD 4702 </address>
      <phone>61749232689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.short@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Camille Short </name>
      <address>Building 18, room 1.30 
Bruce Highway
CQU University 
Rockhampton, QLD 4702 </address>
      <phone>61749232689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.short@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>