<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367251">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001290684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ambu AuraGain versus LMA Supreme Second Seal:
oropharyngeal leak pressures and gastric drain functionality in spontaneously breathing patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ambu AuraGain versus LMA Supreme Second Seal: comparing
oropharyngeal leak pressures and gastric drain functionality in spontaneously breathing patients under general anaesthesia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Supraglottic device use in spontaneously breathing patients under general anaesthesia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Insertion of Ambu Auragain supraglottic device by an experienced anaesthesiologist (&gt;10 year working experience).

The Ambu Auragain differs from the LMA Supreme (control device) in which it has the added feature of intubation capability.
After the placement of the Ambu Auragain, it can be used as a conduit for direct endotracheal intubation assisted by a flexible scope.


Patient is not premedicated. He/she will be positioned supine, and pre-oxygenated for 3 minutes.
Standardised induction of anaesthesia with intravenous fentanyl 1-2 mcg/kg and propofol 2-3mg/kg.
Ambu Auragain will be inserted when the patient's jaw is sufficiently slack.
The duration of an insertion attempt is no longer than 120 seconds.
The appearance of the first square end-tidal CO2 trace denotes successful establishment of effective ventilation.
Otherwise, the device will be completely removed for another insertion attempt. (up to 3 attempts allowed)

Once in place, the Ambu Auragain will be secured with surgical tape.
A prelubricated 14 French gauge gastric tube will then be inserted into the gastric drain outlet, and ease &amp; time taken for insertion will be assessed.
Gastric decompression will be done and total amount of gastric fluid aspirated to be recorded.

Oropharyngeal leak pressure will be measured after closing the adjustable pressure limiting valve with a fresh gas flow of 3 L/min, noting the airway pressure at equilibrium or when there is audible air leak from the throat.
Maximum pressure allowed is 40 cm H2O.

The patient's heart rate and blood pressure will be recorded every minute for the first 5 minutes from induction of anaesthesia.
Anaesthesia will be maintained with sevoflurane 1-2 MAC.

Upon end of the surgery, the Ambu Auragain will be removed (upon return of spontaneous breathing &amp; eye opening)

45 minutes later, a blinded, independent observer will assess the patient for post operative sore throat, dysphonia and dysphagia.</interventions>
    <comparator>The Laryngeal Mask Airway Supreme (Second Seal) will be used for  the control group (50 separate subjects). Induction of anaesthesia,  checking of oropharyngeal leak pressure, gastric drain functionality and other complications will be exactly the same as for the Intervention group (Ambu Auragain)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of oropharyngeal leak pressure (in cm H2O) of the satisfactorily placed supraglottic airway device, using a handheld aneroid manometer (Portex Pressure Gauge)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After insertion of supraglottic airway device</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of insertion of gastric tube through the supraglottic airway device's gastric drain outlet.
Ease of insertion will be graded on a scale of 1 (easy), 2 (acceptable), 3 (difficult), and recorded in the data collection sheet.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After insertion of supraglottic airway device</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of supraglottic airway device insertion and number of attempts required.
Ease of insertion will be graded on a scale of 1 (easy), 2 (acceptable), 3 (difficult), and recorded in the data collection sheet.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During insertion of supraglottic airway device</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Haemodynamic response to insertion of supraglottic airway device
(Systolic/diastolic/mean arterial blood pressure, heart rate)
-measured using automatic sphyngomanometer and ECG</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of supraglottic airway device insertion, up to 5 minutes post insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Manouvres required to optimise ventilation after supraglottic airway device insertion:
-Head/neck position adjustment
-Change of depth of device insertion
-Application of jaw lift
-Change of device size
-Reinsertion of device</outcome>
      <timepoint>After insertion of supraglottic airway device</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications of supraglottic airway device insertion, will be assessed by an unblinded independent observer who is not involved in this study.
Any complications noted will be recorded on the data collection sheet.
(Desaturation SpO2 &lt; 95%, gross regurgitation/aspiration, tongue trauma, lip injury, difficulty in ventilation, bronchospasm, mucosal injury, post operative sore throat, dysphonia, dysphagia, dental injury)</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of supraglottic airway device insertion up to 45 minutes after supraglottic device removal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult surgical patients above 18 years of age, undergoing surgery under general anaesthesia (appropriate to be done with a supraglottic airway device)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>ASA IV;
morbidly obese BMI &gt; 40kg/m2;
high risk or regurgitation/aspiration e.g.: symptomatic gastro-oesophageal reflux, hiatus hernia;
respiratory tract pathology e.g.: preoperative sore throat
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer generated random number table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Teoh WH, Anaes 2010 conducted a study involving LMA Supreme insertions that demonstrated a mean (SD) oropharyngeal leak pressure of 26 (5) cm H2O.
In order to detect a difference of 10%, prospective power analysis at 80% power and 0.05 level of significance (two tailed) showed that a sample size of 47 patients would be required.
Therefore, we recruited 50 patients per group to account for dropouts and protocol breaches.

Insertion times and other parametric data will be analyzed using the Student's t-test.
Mallampati scores and other non-parametric data will be analyzed using the Mann-Whitney U test.
Comparison of side effects will be analyzed using the Fisher'sw exact test.
Repeated measures of haemodynamic variables will be analyzed using the general linear model.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Anaesthesiology, Universiti Malaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesiology,
Universiti Malaya
50603 Kuala Lumpur</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Postgraduate Research Fund, Universiti Malaya</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Universiti Malaya
50603 Kuala Lumpur</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The supraglottic airway device may substitute the invasive procedure of endotracheal intubation in selected patients/surgeries under general anaesthesia.

The Ambu AuraGain is a new phthalate-free, anatomically curved, single use supraglottic airway device launced in June 2014. It features an intergrated gastric access port.

We would like to compare the Ambu Auragain with the Lanyngeal Mask Airway Supreme (Second Seal), in terms of oropharyngeal leak pressure, ease of insertion, gastric drain functionality and haemodynamic response.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Malaya Research Ethics (UMREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai , 59100, Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20148-425</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ina Ismiarti Shariffuddin</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology,
Universiti Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60379492052</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>inashariffuddin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ina Ismiarti Shariffuddin</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology,
Universiti Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60379492052</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>inashariffuddin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ina Ismiarti Shariffuddin</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology,
Universiti Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60379492052</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>inashariffuddin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eric Tang Boon Kiat</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology,
Universiti Malaya,
50603 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60125943394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aerikh@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>