<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372475">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000670370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>What are the effects on carbohydrate digestion and absorption of variations in the salivary amylase gene in healthy adults? </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Physiological significance of AMY1 gene copy number variation in healthy individuals after consumption of high carbohydrate meals</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1193-7666</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SAMY study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will compare the rate and extent of digestion of starchy meals and sugary meals in healthy adults. There will be a variable number of acute meal tests, dependent on the person's actual AMY1 gene copy number (minimum 4 sessions and maximum 20 sessions).    Individuals with either low AMY1 copy number (5 or fewer copies of the AMY1 gene) or high AMY1 copy number (9 or more copies of the AMY1 gene) will complete up to the maximum 20 sessions (or until consent is withdrawn).  Participants with either low or high AMY1 copy number will be randomly allocated to receive one treatment at each visit, including 2 control reference sessions (25 g or 50 g glucose in solution) and any combination of 25/50/75 g carbohydrate (containing starch, sugar or both starch and sugar), and any of the listed food types or a mixed meal. Carbohydrate foods tested include white bread, pasta, rice, breakfast cereals, potatoes, oats, fruit and dairy products.  The mixed meals contain egg, toast and orange juice or rice with soy sauce.  Individuals with 6 - 8 AMY1 gene copies will complete the minimum of 4 sessions ((2 control sessions containing glucose in solution and 2 test food sessions containing white bread, pasta, rice, potatoes, oats, fruit or dairy products (randomly allocated)). There will be washout period of at least one day between sessions. 

Fingerprick blood and breath samples will be taken at regular intervals (15-60 mins) over for minimum of 2 hours and maximum of 8 hours.  The participants will complete a questionnaire about feelings of fullness and gastrointestinal symptoms.  All sessions will be conducted on the main campus of the University of Sydney.  A qualified dietitian (APD accredited practising dietitian) will conduct all sessions.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Each subject acts as their own control, ie. their postprandial responses are compared relative to their response to the control food (glucose in solution).  A control reference food (25 or 50 g of glucose in solution) will be consumed by every participant on 2 occasions.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial plasma glucose responses</outcome>
      <timepoint>Relative postprandial glucose concentration assessed as incremental area under curve over 120 mins (0, 15, 30, 45, 60 ,90, 120 min) to the test food versus the reference food. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial plasma insulin responses</outcome>
      <timepoint>Relative postprandial insulin concentration assessed as incremental area under curve over 120 mins (0, 15, 30, 45, 60 ,90, 120 min) to the test food versus the reference food. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial breath hydrogen and methane responses over 8 hours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Breath hydrogen and methane concentration assessed as area under curve over 8 hours (0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240, 300, 360, 420, 480 min) to two starchy meals containing rice with and without a source of resistant starch (HiMaize).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional composition of usual diet, including proportion of energy as starch.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diet assessed by a 3-day written food record at baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial satiety (feeling of fullness) assessed over 120 mins</outcome>
      <timepoint>Satiety assessed at as incremental area under the curve (0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90 and 120 mins)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salivary amylase activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in fasting state only or in the case of the breath studies at hourly intervals for 8 hours. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy, non-smoker, good comprehension of English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Smoking, food allergy or intolerance, diagnosed diabetes, taking medications known to influence glucose metabolism</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated randomisation to order of meals</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Unpaired and pair t tests to compare mean difference in 2 groups
Linear regression analysis to determine linear trends</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>30/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Science
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Science
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to identify the variation of the salivary amylase (AMY1) gene copy number in the Australian population and to investigate the effect of AMY1 copy number on carbohydrate digestion, acute metabolic and satiety responses, and potential associations with obesity and diabetes risk.  

This project will screen Australian adults for their number of copies of the AMY1 gene.  This gene produces a protein, salivary amylase, which is secreted in the mouth and begins starch breakdown.  Individuals with varying AMY1 copy numbers will be asked to perform a series of starch challenge tests during which they will consume different high carbohydrate foods.  Fingerprick blood samples will be taken at regular intervals over 2 hours to measure their metabolic responses to starchy foods.  To assess the efficiency of starch digestion, salivary amylase activity, breath hydrogen and methane responses, and postprandial glucose and insulin responses will also be assessed over an 8 hour period following the consumption of different high carbohydrate meals.  Information on how AMY1 copy number influences carbohydrate metabolism and usual dietary intake may have important implications for the dietary management of diabetes and obesity and/or identify those at greater risk of developing these conditions.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009/11871</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics and Governace Office, Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown
NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X16-0161</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennie Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre
Johns Hopkins Drive
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+ 61 417 658 695</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennie.brandmiller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fiona Atkinson</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre
Johns Hopkins Drive
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 6018</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fiona.atkinson@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fiona Atkinson</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre
Johns Hopkins Drive
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 6018</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fiona.atkinson@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>