<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370484">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001013459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Structured Home-Based Exercise Program for Ambulant Cerebral Palsy in Improving Ambulation Function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Structured Home-Based Exercise Program for Ambulant Cerebral Palsy in Improving Ambulation Function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Palsy </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Structured home-based exercise program which comprises flexibility, aerobic and strengthening therapy. 

Information on structured home-based exercise program: 

Familiarization - 4 sessions of  home-based exercise taught at the physiotherapist gym to parents/caregiver and participants supervised by physiotherapist. This is done one month prior to the start of intervention. 
a) duration of each session is 30 minutes up to 1 hr
b) frequency of sessions, once weekly 
c) format - one to one session 

Intervention duration - 8 weeks , structured home-based program delivered at home supervised by parents, using the provided logbook which has all details with pictures of exercises and timetable as guidance. Investigators will follow up and check on logbook timetable during every visits for assessment. 

A. Materials &amp; equipments during familiarization (training of exercise for 1 month before intervention started) and intervention ( 8 weeks home-based exercise program)
1) structured home-based exercise booklet which comprises flexibility, aerobic and strengthening therapy for both upper and lower limbs: 

a. flexibility - stretching of muscles that crossed two joints of both upper and lower limb example; biceps, wrist flexors, hamstrings, gastrocnemius
b. Aerobic - for lower limb; moving up and down with ankle weights using stepping stool until achieved OMNI-RPE scale 6-7, for upper limb; throwing and playing balls until OMNI-RPE 6-7. 
c. strengthening - Using free weights to move upper and lower limbs repetitively until achieve OMNI-RPE 6-7

2) A timetable of frequency gradually increase from twice to 4 times a week included in the booklet for parents to monitor the exercises done for total of 8 weeks - participants will alternate sessions between flexibility and aerobic, and flexibility and strengthening for every. All session need to be supervised by parents or caregiver. 

3) Intensity of exercise is monitored by parents using the OMNI-RPE scale (laminated), up to OMNI-RPE 6-7 (moderate intensity)

4) Equipments provided for participants, playground ball and step stool to perform aerobic exercises for upper and lower limbs respectively. Ankle &amp; wrist weights (of 500g, 1 kg per pair) for performing strengthening exercise for upper and lower limbs respectively. 

5) Exercise schedule: 
Frequency of exercise - alternate combination of flexibility and aerobic AND flexibility and strengthening. Week 1&amp;2 (2 days per week). Week 3&amp;4 (3 times per week). Week 5,6,7 &amp; 8 (4 times per week). 
Duration- determines by how they achieve targeted intensity based on OMNI-RPE scale (6-7) for aerobic &amp; strengthening exercises. Maximum aerobic exercise per session for both upper and lower limbs are 20 mins and maximum repetition of strengthening exercise is 8 repetitions each.  For flexibility component, stretching of each specified areas of upper and lower limbs is advised for 15-30 seconds. 

B. Personnel involve in delivering intervention 
1) Physiotherapists - 2 physiotherapists involve in training participants and parents during familiarisation of home-based exercise and monitoring outcome using 6-minute walking test and GMFM-66 (component D&amp;E). They are experienced in handling cerebral palsy children in Paediatric Rehabilitation service for at least 3 years. 
2) Occupational therapist (OT) - 2 OTs are involved to monitor outcome in activities of daily living using Paediatric Evaluation Disability Inventory (PEDI). OT involve are experienced in paediatric rehabilitation service at least minimum of 3 years. 
3) Investigators &amp; Research assistant - involve in the planning of intervention program and monitoring the whole participation of participants in the assessment schedule and help with keeping records and tabulating research's data. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>no comparator treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6-minute walk test (6MWT) to assess walking speed and calculate the physiological cost index (PCI) which derived by walking HR-resting HR	/ walking speed 

*HR is monitored during 6MWT by using a polar watch for paediatric population. 	

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome measure will be assessed: 

1) Every week for 1 month (4 weeks) before start of intervention as baseline measures 
2) 3 times during intervention period (8 weeks) on 3rd, 6th and 9th week
3) 2 times post intervention at 1st month and 3rd month post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) Gross Motor Function Measure GMFM-66 (component D&amp;E) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome measure will be assessed: 

1) Every week for 1 month (4 weeks) before start of intervention as baseline measures 
2) 3 times during intervention period (8 weeks) on 3rd, 6th and 9th week
3) 2 times post intervention at 1st month and 3rd month post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Activities of daily living in ambulation and hand function using Paediatric Evaluation of Disability Inventory (PEDI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PEDI will be assessed during the:
1) 3 times during intervention period (8 weeks) on 3rd, 6th and 9th week
2) 2 times post intervention at 1st month and 3rd month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children Assessment of Participation and Enjoyment (CAPE) questionnaire 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Children Assessment of Participation and Enjoyment (CAPE) questionnaire will be assessed: 

1) Once at baseline before intervention 
2) Once post intervention at week 9th
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1- Children with CP
2- Age 7-18 years old
3- GMFCS I-III
4- Received standard rehabilitation therapy 
5- Able to follow at least 2 steps command
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1-	Unable to comprehend even 2 steps command 
2-	Not undergoing any rehabilitation therapy 
3-	Does not agree for participation in study
4-	Received any surgical intervention or botulinum toxin injection last 3 months before study participation 
5-	Received home based private physiotherapy service
6-	Staying far, outside Klang Valley
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Time series analysis will be performed to evaluate outcome pre and post intervention over time, using one-way repeated measures ANOVA
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>8/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>19</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur, Federal Territory</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute of Research Management &amp; Monitoring (IPPP), University of Malaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute of Research Management &amp; Monitoring (IPPP)
Level 7, Research Management &amp; Innovation Complex
University Malaya
50603 Kuala Lumpur
Federal Territory
Malaysia </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Malaya Research Fund Assistance </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Centre of Research Grant Management
Level 4, Research Management &amp; Innovation Complex
University Malaya
50603 Kuala Lumpur
Federal Territory
Malaysia </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>none</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Introduction
Deterioration in ambulation function as the children with CP grow needs to be addressed, as this may lead to other medical problems related to lack of physical activities. Low muscle strength, has been found to cause the greatest limitations in motor function in children with CP. Therefore, in the rehabilitation management of children with CP, emphasis on exercise as well as physical activity is pertinent in improving motor function. Based on previous studies and literatures, exercise training may provide positive and significant effects on physical function of children with CP. Exercise interventions are varied which can be deployed at regular rehabilitation therapy site, school as well as home-based. In view of the limitation of rehabilitation service utilization in our local context, in which time constraint, accessibility and transportation are among the main barriers to rehabilitation at hospital, we would like to explore on a structured home-based exercise program intervention.

Main objective or aim of the present study is to demonstrate that structured home-based exercise may produce important improvements in ambulation function of ambulant children with Cerebral Palsy in terms of walking speed and better endurance level. This study involves children with Cerebral Palsy aged 7-18 years old who are walking with or without walking aids and needs parents or caregiver supervision at home when children are doing the structured home-based exercise program. 




</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Center</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Malaya Medical Centre
Lembah Pantai, 59100
Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MECID.NO: 201581543</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aishah Ahmad Fauzi</name>
      <address>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine
Level 12, South Tower, 
University Malaya Medical Centre,
50603 Kuala Lumpur, Federal Territory </address>
      <phone>+60133417577</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aishahaf@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aishah Ahmad Fauzi</name>
      <address>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine
Level 12, South Tower, 
University Malaya Medical Centre,
50603 Kuala Lumpur, Federal Territory </address>
      <phone>+60133417577</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aishahaf@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Masyitah Mohd Khayat</name>
      <address>Department of Rehabilitation Medicine
Level 12, South Tower 
University Malaya Medical Centre
50603 Federal Territory, Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60126304290</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>masyitahmkhayat@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>