<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364314">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000596707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Helping smokers to quit through increasing their appreciation of health risks information</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Reducing the burden of lung disease: Using self-affirmation to reduce defensiveness towards health risk information among smokers with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1143-5613 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>SACO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>tobacco smoking</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Materials: The proposed study will be administered entirely via computer surveys and procedures, either using a study laptop or online for participants wishing to complete the study on a personal computer from home. Self-affirmation manipulation, threat message (smoking risk information), and survey questions will be compiled into a survey battery accessed via laptop or a secured web address. Participants will be asked to fill out the questionnaire once only (which includes self-affirmation task and warning message) and should take approximately 40 minutes.

Randomization: Participants will be randomised to either the self-affirmation or control condition. The study will utilise a cross-over design, where by at the conclusion of their participation, both control and treatment group participants would have been self-affirmed; the treatment group before health risk information, and control group after health risk information. After screening for eligibility, participants will be provided with the online survey website address, a unique subject identification number and unique password to access the study survey. This unique password will also randomly allocate the participant to one of the two conditions. 

Self-affirmation manipulation: The present study will use the Classification of Character Strengths to manipulate self-affirmation in participants. This measure has been shown to reliably manipulate self-affirmation and is well suited to computer/online administered questionnaire forms. For the treatment group, self-affirmation manipulation will be presented prior to the threat message to ensure greatest effect. To check if self-affirmation manipulation has occurred, participants will be asked to rate their overall feeling from very bad to very good. By situating this question at the end of the questionnaire any theoretical possibility such a check could annul the self-affirmation effect will be avoided. Subjects in the control group will be asked to complete a time matched non-self-referent task before the health risk information where instead of rating themselves, they will be asked to rate a well-known personality on the same attributes. Control and treatment groups will conclude their respective questionnaire with the alternative forms of the Classification of Character Strengths (self-affirmation questionnaire). 

Smoking risk information: Health risk information will be provided to participants in the form of a short government sponsored quit smoking/anti-smoking advertisement (for example; http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sjrnaHInUHM). It is anticipated that a visual and auditory presentation of risk information will elicit a more threatening response than text or picture alone. Smoking risk information is presented to both groups, embedded approximately midway through the questionnaire.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group will not receive self-affirmation manipulation prior to being presented with the health risk information (will instead do a non self-referent task prior to health risk information; self affirmation task will be done after risk information/at conclusion of questionnaire) and it is anticipated that as a result they will be more defensive towards the presented health information, and less likely to intend to quit smoking.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>It is hypothesised that participants in the treatment group (self-affirmed) will report a greater intention to quit smoking (How certain are you that you will actually quit smoking in the future? 1-Very certain - 7-Not at all certain) compared to participants in the control group who have not been affirmed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measures will be measured as part of questionnaire.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>It is hypothesised that participants in the treatment group (self-affirmed) will report higher message acceptance (as measured by How important do you think it is that people stop smoking in order to avoid the problems mentioned in the video? 1-Not important  7-very important).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measures will be measured as part of questionnaire.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants in the treatment group are expected to report higher risk perception (How likely do you think you will be to get cancer as a result of your smoking?  7-point scale  impossible [1]  extremely likely [7]) compared to participants in the control group who have not been affirmed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measures will be measured as part of questionnaire.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants in the treatment group are anticipated to report higher self-efficacy (as measured by If I wanted to, I could easily cut down the number of cigarettes I smoke in the next 7 days 1-Totally agree  7-totally disagree) compared to control group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome measures will be measured as part of questionnaire.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible to participate subjects must be current smokers with or without a diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease with a minimum of 20 pack years, be aged 40 years and older and be referred for lung function testing. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Younger than 40, less than 20 cigarette pack years.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Smokers will be recruited through the Northern Lung Function Service (NLFS) which provides respiratory diagnostic and monitoring services to the medical community in the North and North West of Tasmania. Participants will be 40 years and older, with a minimum smoking history of 20 pack years. The lung function results of patients of the NLFS will be used by NLFS staff to identify or confirm the presence of COPD. Staff of the NLFS will then provide eligible patients with a study information sheet, including researcher contact details. Patients can then choose to contact (phone or email) the researchers for further information about the study and/or enrol for participation. Upon contacting the researchers, potential participants will be provided with additional study information, have any questions answered, be screened for eligibility, and if eligible, enrolled in the study. After screening for eligibility, participants will be provided with the online survey website address, a unique subject identification number and unique password to access the study survey. This unique password will also randomly allocate the participant to one of the two conditions.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be assigned to one of two conditions by electronic random number generation. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The proposed study will adopt a crossover 2 by 2 between subjects design: (Group: COPD smokers vs. non COPD smokers) x (Condition: self-affirmation vs. control). Analysis of variance will be conducted to determine if there is an interaction between group and condition.

A previous, self-affirmation study into message acceptance of smoking information (Griffin &amp; Harris, 2011) found a medium to large effect of d = .60 with a power of beta = .80. Based on the difference in message acceptance in that study, a 15% increase in acceptance with self-affirmation, and to obtain an interaction effect with 80% power to detect an effect 10% larger in affirmed smokers with COPD, we will require 90 participants completing the study. We will over-recruit by 15% to allow for an unequal ratio of participants with or without COPD and attrition, giving a target of N = 114 recruited participants.

[Griffin, D. W., &amp; Harris, P. R. (2011). Calibrating the response to health warnings: Limiting both overreaction and underreaction with self-affirmation. Psychological Science, 22(5), 572-578. doi: 10.1177/0956797611405678]</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>26/09/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>114</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>7250 - Launceston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Mai Frandsen</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Pharmacy
C/O Locked Bag 1320
University of Tasmania
Launceston, Tasmania, 7250</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P.O. Box 1963
Launceston, Tasmania 7250</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Julia Walters</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Medicine
Locked Bag 23
University of Tasmania
Hobart, Tasmania, 7000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study seeks to determine whether self-affirmation (boosting self-image) is effective at reducing defensiveness towards smoking risk information in smokers with and without chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. This can lead to increased acceptance of health warnings and increased quitting in smokers at high risk.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Tasmania Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>H0013242</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mai Frandsen</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
C/O Locked Bag 1320
University of Tasmania
Launceston, Tasmania, 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6324 3137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mai.Frandsen@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mai Frandsen</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
C/O Locked Bag 1320
University of Tasmania
Launceston, Tasmania, 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6324 3137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mai.Frandsen@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mai Frandsen</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
C/O Locked Bag 1320
University of Tasmania
Launceston, Tasmania, 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6324 3137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mai.Frandsen@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mai Frandsen</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
C/O Locked Bag 1320
University of Tasmania
Launceston, Tasmania, 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6324 3137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mai.Frandsen@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>