<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370594">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000865415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does A Retropulsion Prevention Device Equalize The Surgical Success of Ho:YAG Laser and Pneumatic Lithotripters for Upper Ureteral Stones?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does A Retropulsion Prevention Device Equalize The Surgical Success of Ho:YAG Laser and Pneumatic Lithotripters for Upper Ureteral Stones? A Prospective Randomized Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-3895</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Upper ureteral stones</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients were treated with pneumatic(comparator) and Ho:YAG laser(intervention) lithotripters in group-1 and group-2, respectively. Pneumatic lithotripsy was performed in 130 patients and laser lithotripsy was performed in 130 patients. Two patients in group-2 were excluded due to inappropriate follow-up.
Ureteroscopy and lithotripsy were performed under spinal anesthesia for all patients.  The surgeries were performed by the same surgical team (consultant urologist). Semi-rigid 7.5 or 9.5 Fr ureterorenoscopes (Richard Wolf, Knittlingen, Germany) were used for ureteroscopy under lithotomy position. Initially, a hydrophilic guidewire for safety was inserted into the ureter under fluoroscopy or direct vision. After that, a Stone-coneTM Nitinol Retrieval Coin (Boston Scientific, Marlborough, MA, USA) was placed for retropulsion prevention  but not activated. Thereafter, the stone cone was opened under direct vision or fluoroscopy and lithotripsy was performed with  Ho:YAG laser (Sphinx 30 Minimally Invasive Surgical Laser, LISA laser, Pleasanton, CA, USA) lithotripter for group-2.  For group-2, 365 microm laser fibers were used and lithotripsy was performed with 1.0-2.0 Joule 5-10 Hz (5-20 Watt) settings. Treating surgeon decided the adjustments of energy setting on the basis of stone characteristics during the surgery. At the end of efficient fragmentation, extraction of the stone fragments was performed with stone forceps and the Stone-coneTM was closed and withdrawn. Approximate duration of surgery was 48 minutes. Flexible ureterorenoscopy was not performed in any of patients simultaneously. A doubleJ stent was inserted for two weeks in patients with residual stone fragments, bleeding and ureteral edema.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Patients were treated with pneumatic(comparator) and Ho:YAG laser(intervention) lithotripters in group-1 and group-2, respectively. Pneumatic lithotripsy was performed in 130 patients and laser lithotripsy was performed in 130 patients. Two patients in group-2 were excluded due to inappropriate follow-up.
Ureteroscopy and lithotripsy were performed under spinal anesthesia for all patients.  The surgeries were performed by the same surgical team (consultant urologist). Semi-rigid 7.5 or 9.5 Fr ureterorenoscopes (Richard Wolf, Knittlingen, Germany) were used for ureteroscopy under lithotomy position. Initially, a hydrophilic guidewire for safety was inserted into the ureter under fluoroscopy or direct vision. After that, a Stone-coneTM Nitinol Retrieval Coin (Boston Scientific, Marlborough, MA, USA) was placed for retropulsion prevention  but not activated. Thereafter, the stone cone was opened under direct vision or fluoroscopy and lithotripsy was performed with pneumatic (Vibrolith Pneumatic Lithotripter, ELMED, Turkey)  lithotripter for group-1.  For group-1, lithotripsy was started with 4-5 bars and then the frequency of the lithotripter was increased if necessary. The frequency settings were 50-500 pulse/minute. Treating surgeon decided the adjustments of  power setting on the basis of stone characteristics during the surgery. At the end of efficient fragmentation, extraction of the stone fragments was performed with stone forceps and the Stone-coneTM was closed and withdrawn. Approximate duration of surgery was 46 minutes. Flexible ureterorenoscopy was not performed in any of patients simultaneously. A doubleJ stent was inserted for two weeks in patients with residual stone fragments, bleeding and ureteral edema.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients were evaluated on the first postoperative day before discharge with plain x-ray and ultrasonography for residual stone fragments and hydronephrosis. Patients with residual fragments greater than or equal to 4mm were accepted as surgical failures. Patients with stone-free status or with residual fragments &lt;4mm were accepted as surgical success.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative first day.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for auxiliary procedures one month after surgery, assessed by x-ray and ultrasonography. A decision was made one month after surgery for auxiliary procedures. </outcome>
      <timepoint>One month after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients between  18 and 82 with obstructive, radioopaque and primary unilateral upper ureteral stones were included in this study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>82</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criterias were abnormal coagulation profile, previous SWL, bilateral ureteral stones, radiolucent stones, likelihood of spontaneous stone passage, and presence of a non-functioning kidney. Patients with narrow ureters that required stenting and with push-back of the stone before activation of the stone cone were excluded. Stone localization in the fluoroscopic stone immediately prior to the surgery was compared with preoperative stone localizations. Patients with changing stone localizations were excluded from the study.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization was arranged with “=Rand( )” formula in Microsoft Office Excel 2007 (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, USA) software. Patients were randomly allocated with the use of a computer-generated schedule to receive pneumatic or Ho:YAG laser lithotripsy. Single-blinding was used for this study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>For calculating a priori sample size, we could not find a similar study comparing two different energy sources with the use of a retropulsion prevention device for upper ureteral stones in the literature and decided to perform post hoc analysis. Power value was 96.4% for an effect size value (0.2343563) that was calculated for a surgical success rate of 81.5% in the pneumatic group and 90.6% in the laser group. With this power value it was found that the sample size was sufficient.
The normal distribution assumption was tested with Kolmogorov-Smirnov and Shapiro-Wilk tests. Kurtosis and skewness values were also examined. It was found that the data were normally distributed for both groups. Data are expressed as mean+/-SD for continuous variables and number and/or percentage for categorical variables.
In this study, Pearsons Chi-square test was used for the categorical variables and independent t-test was used for continuous variables. In all tests, p&lt;0.05 was considered to indicate statistical significance.
Statistical Package for Social Sciences version 21.0 Software for Windows (IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 21.0. Armonk, NY: IBM Corp. USA) was used for descriptive statistics, independent t-test and Chi-Square tests. G-power 3.1 (Department of Psychology, University of Düsseldorf, Germany) was used for post hoc power analysis. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>258</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>8/03/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Kirsehir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ahi Evran University, Academical Researches Supporting Unit</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ahi Evran University, Academical Researches Supporting Unit, Bagbasi Campus, 40100, Kirsehir/TURKEY</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ahi Evran University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ahi Evran University, Academical Researches Supporting Unit, Bagbasi Campus, 40100, Kirsehir/TURKEY
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose: To establish if a retropulsion prevention device for ureteral stones equalizes surgical success and push-back rates of Ho:YAG laser and pneumatic lithotripters for upper ureteral stones.   
Materials and Methods: Patients with upper ureteral stones (n=267) were treated endoscopically at the Department of Urology between April 2014 and December 2015.  Patients were randomly assigned to pneumatic and Ho:YAG laser lithotripters as group-1 and group-2, respectively.  Among the 267 patients three and four patients were excluded due to changing stone localizations in group-1 and group-2, respectively. Pneumatic lithotripsy was performed in 130 patients and laser lithotripsy was performed in 130 patients. Two patients in group-2 were excluded due to inappropriate follow-up.Lithotripsy was performed with Stone-coneTM in both groups. 

Results: The surgical success rate on the first postoperative day was 81.5% (n=106) and 90.6% (n=116) for group-1 and group-2, respectively, and the difference between the groups was statistically significant (p&lt;0.05). The relation between stone size and surgical success was statistically significant for both groups (p&lt;0.01). Surgical success for the stones closer than 2cm to the UPJ was 23.1% for the pneumatic group versus 64% for the laser group (p&lt;0.01). Lithotripsy time was significantly longer in group-2 (16.48+/-4.74 min.) than group-1 (12.24+/-3.95 min.) (p&lt;0.01).

Conclusions: Ho:YAG laser can fragment the stone in place in the low-power settings and this provides high success rates with the use of a push-back prevention device, especially for very high level upper ureteral stones. Many clinics may not have unlimited access to flexible ureteroscopy. Ho:YAG laser lithotripsy is more successful than pneumatic lithotripsy for upper ureteral stones, and a retropulsion prevention device does not equalize the surgical success of  Ho:YAG laser and pneumatic lithotripters for upper ureteral stones. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Kirikkale University Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kirikkale University Medicine Faculty, Ethics Committee, Ankara Street, 71100. Kirikkale/TURKEY.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/02-11.03.2013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sahin Bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Faculty of Medicine, Ahi Evran University, Bagbasi Campus, 40100. Kirsehir/TURKEY.</address>
      <phone>+903862134517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahin.bagbanci@ahievran.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sahin Bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Faculty of Medicine, Ahi Evran University, Bagbasi Campus, 40100. Kirsehir/TURKEY.</address>
      <phone>+903862134517</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahiin1980@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sahin Bagbanci</name>
      <address>Department of Urology, Faculty of Medicine, Ahi Evran University, Bagbasi Campus, 40100. Kirsehir/TURKEY.</address>
      <phone>+90 505 445 00 75</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sahin.bagbanci@ahievran.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>