<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371097">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000959471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A multicentre study of the dose concentration response of febuxostat in patients with chronic gout.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multicentre, prospective, open-label, pharmacokinetic pharmacodynamic (PKPD) study of febuxostat in patients with chronic gout.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gout</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study aims at exploring a) the dose-concentrations-response relationships of febuxostat in patients with chronic gout b) the influence of renal function on the plasma concentrations of febuxostat and response of urate to febuxostat.
A number of blood samples (up to 4 blood samples per dose level) will be collected at least one week after the initiation and/or dose adjustment for the determination of the plasma concentrations of febuxostat and urate.  In this open-label observational study, the dose of febuxostat, dose adjustment, duration of administration and the target treatment serum urate are judged by the treating rheumatologist as part of usual management of gout. Some data will be collected including; baseline and steady-state treatment concentrations of serum urate and creatinine, age, sex, height, weight, medical history and current co-morbidities and concomitant therapies (including change in co-therapies during enrollment). Some information pertaining to gout (duration of gout, frequency of gout attacks and past gout treatments, if any) will also be collected. 
Patients will be asked to complete The ARMS (Adherence to Refills and Medications Scale) questionnaire in order to assess their general adherence behaviour. A Febuxostat adherence Questionnaire will also be completed before each blood collection in order to capture the extent of adherence to treatment with febuxostat over the week prior to collecting a blood sample. Patients will also be offered a participant's diary to monitor their adherence to febuxostat. 
Patients will be followed up for up to 6 months from recruitment.  After the follow up period ends, patients with chronic gout will continue to take febuxostat to maintain their serum urate concentrations below the target concentrations, as part of their chronic gout management, treating doctors will continue following up patients as per usual care.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group.  </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The PD parameter to be assessed is the change in serum urate concentrations. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline serum urate (not during an acute attack) and change in serum urate post treatment (at least 1 week after the initiation and/or dose change). 

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pharmacokinetic parameters to be assessed include; the plasma area under the concentration time curve, apparent clearance, and peak and trough concentrations of febuxostat. The relationship of an individuals pharmacokinetic parameters with the reduction in serum urate concentrations will be explored and reported as mathematical equations. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 4 blood samples (10 mL each) will be collected at least one week after intervention commencement and/or dose adjustment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients for whom febuxostat is, or has been, clinically indicated for the treatment of chronic gout. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Any patient with a past history of febuxostat hypersensitivity.
2) Patients taking xanthine oxidoreductase substrates such as mercaptopurine/azathioprine or theophylline (no studies to substantiate the combination with febuxostat).* 
3) Women lactating, pregnant or of childbearing potential who are not willing to avoid becoming pregnant during the study.
4) Patients with a history of a psychological illness or condition such as to interfere with the patient's ability to understand the requirements of the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Non applicable. </concealment>
    <sequence>Non applicable. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>There is no established method for calculating a sample size for PKPD open-label studies. A sample size of up to 120 patients was chosen on the basis of previous studies of similar medicines and to provide sufficient data to assess the dose-concentration-response relationship of febuxostat in patients with gout.

A population pharmacokinetic model for febuxostat will be developed using existing data from the literature. This model, together with plasma concentrations determined in our study, will be used to estimate individual pharmacokinetic parameters of febuxostat (PK analysis) for each patient with gout. The relationships of the pharmacokinetic parameters, notably the plasma area under the concentration time curve, apparent clearance, and peak and trough concentrations will be correlated with the reduction in plasma urate. The influence of renal function (creatinine clearance) on the pharmacokinetics or response to febuxostat will be examined. The significance of other patient characteristics (e.g. body weight, sex and age) will also be investigated. The febuxostat dose-concentration-response relationships will be fitted using modelling techniques. The clinical relevance of the results will be examined and reported.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>10/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <hospital>Camden Hospital - Camden</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Private Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
    <postcode>2570 - Camden</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2134 - Burwood</postcode>
    <postcode>2042 - Newtown</postcode>
    <postcode>2228 - Miranda</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St, Darlingurst, Australia, NSW 2010.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clinical Pharmacology Lexy Davies Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Australia, NSW 2010. </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objectives of the study are: 
1) Explore the dose-concentration-response relationship of febuxostat in patients with chronic gout.
2) Gain insights into optimisation of febuxostat therapy to achieve target plasma urate concentrations.
3) Understand inter-patient variations in the pharmacokinetic parameters of the drug and their impact on the serum urate concentration. 
4) Explore factors that may affect the pharmacokinetics and/or the response of urate to febuxostat. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>97-105 Boundary St, Darlinghurst, Australia, NSW 2010.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/SVH/22</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard O Day</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology and Toxicology, 
Level 2 Xavier Building, 
St Vincent's Hospital, 
390 Victoria St,
Darlinghurst, Australia, NSW 2010.
</address>
      <phone>+61, 2, 8382 2331</phone>
      <fax>+61, 2, 8382 2724</fax>
      <email>r.day@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Bishoy Kamel</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology and Toxicology, 
Level 2 Xavier Building, 
St Vincent's Hospital, 
390 Victoria St,
Darlinghurst, Australia, NSW 2010.</address>
      <phone>+61, 2, 8382 2051</phone>
      <fax>+61, 2, 8382 2724</fax>
      <email>b.kamel@unswalumni.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard O Day</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology and Toxicology, 
Level 2 Xavier Building, 
St Vincent's Hospital, 
390 Victoria St,
Darlinghurst, Australia, NSW 2010.</address>
      <phone>+61, 2, 8382 2331</phone>
      <fax>+61, 2, 8382 2724</fax>
      <email>r.day@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Bishoy Kamel</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology and Toxicology, 
Level 2 Xavier Building, 
St Vincent's Hospital, 
390 Victoria St,
Darlinghurst, Australia, NSW 2010.</address>
      <phone>+61, 2, 8382 2051</phone>
      <fax>+61, 2, 8382 2724</fax>
      <email>b.kamel@unswalumni.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>