<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363443">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001062718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Preterm Infant Functional and Clinical Outcomes (PIFCO): Understanding Complex Factors That Influence Long Term Outcomes After Preterm Birth</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Observational Study of Physiological and Etiological Markers of Long Term Cardiorespiratory and Developmental Outcomes After Preterm Birth Prior to 32 Weeks Gestation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PIFCO Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Very Preterm Birth</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bronchopulmonary Dysplasia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diaphragm Dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational study of very preterm infants with intermittent physiological evaluation of:
- immunological function (birth, 1 d, 7 d, 36 w PMA, 1 yr corrected age)
- cardiorespiratory and diaphragm function (primary measurement at 36 w PMA and 1 yr corrected age, with other intermittent measurements as able to be collected)
- neurodevelopmental outcome (1 yr)

Observations will be correlated with data pertaining to antenatal and postnatal exposures including demographic variables, gestation, ventilation, oxygen, steroids, infection, and nutrition </interventions>
    <comparator>Term born healthy infants will be included as comparators for the 1 year outcomes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thoracic Dysfunction Index derived as a composite function of Lung, Heart and Diaphragm Dysfunction determined using the following techniques at 1 year corrected postnatal age:
a) Multiple Breath Washout (Functional Residual Capacity,  Lung Clearance Index)
b) Tidal breathing Flow Volume Loop Analysis (RR, Vt/kg, Vd/kg)
c) Ventilation Perfusion Imbalance (derived from Shunt and Shift assessed on SpO2/FiO2 curves)
d) Pulmonary hypertension determined from R ventricular contractility, pulmonary artery pressures and pulmonary blood flow on echocardiography)
e)transdiaphragmatic pressure generated after magnetic stimulation of the phrenic nerve </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year Corrected Postnatal Age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thoracic Dysfunction Index derived as a composite function of Lung, Heart and Diaphragm Dysfunction determined using the following techniques at 36 w postmenstrual age:
a) Multiple Breath Washout (Functional Residual Capacity,  Lung Clearance Index)
b) Tidal breathing Flow Volume Loop Analysis (RR, Vt/kg, Vd/kg)
c) Ventilation Perfusion Imbalance (derived from Shunt and Shift assessed on SpO2/FiO2 curves)
d) Pulmonary hypertension determined from R ventricular contractility, pulmonary artery pressures and pulmonary blood flow on echocardiography)
e)transdiaphragmatic pressure generated after magnetic stimulation of the phrenic nerve </outcome>
      <timepoint>36 w postmenstrual age (PMA)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurodevelopmental Outcome (Griffith's Test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year corrected postnatal age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inpatient at King Edward Memorial Hospital
Born at &lt; 32 w gestation (postmenstrual age)

Term comparison group - healthy uncomplicated deliveries between 37 and 42 w postmenstrual age</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Hours</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Informed consent unable to be obtained
Major congenital abnormalities likely to impact cardiorespiratory function</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>We will use multivariable logistic regression to predict the development and severity of BPD taking into account primary antecedent adverse perinatal exposures and function of the lungs, heart, pulmonary circulation and the diaphragm. Based on an incidence of NICHD defined BPD of 25% in very preterm infants at KEMH, a cohort of 400 infants evaluated at 1 year of age used in the logistic regression analysis will attain &gt;80% power to detect odds ratios (OR) of 1.6-1.8 associated with change in the independent continuous predictors from their mean by one standard deviation (i.e. risk increase 6-10%), and ORs of 2.0-3.0 associated with categorical predictors (i.e. risk increase 12-16%) while controlling of other simultaneous covariates with partial R2=0.15 (PASS 2008 Power and Sample Size Program For Windows, Kaysville, Utah). Linear regression analysis will be used to investigate factors associated with lung, heart and pulmonary circulation, chest wall and diaphragm. All linear multiple regression analyses will attain =90% power to detect R2=0.05 attributable to a given risk factor while simultaneously controlling for up to 12 additional covariates in the model. 
A cohort size of 400 infants at 1 year of age requires recruitment of 500 neonates, as our past experience indicates 20% attrition at 1 year of age (illness, failure to sleep, technical difficulties and withdrawn consent). Assuming 25% of these will have BPD (mild, moderate or severe) and ~ 12% will have moderate to severe BPD, we will target recruitment for neonatal studies of a total of 125 &lt;32 w GA infants with BPD, including 60 infants with moderate-severe BPD out of the total cohort of 500 infants.  Approximately 300 very preterm (&lt; 32 w GA) are born at KEMH each year. The factor determining the required recruitment duration is the incidence of BPD: With 25% of &lt; 32 w GA infants developing BPD, we expect approximately 75 eligible preterm infants with BPD (any severity) each year. Our recent experience is that we are able to obtain consent for lung and diaphragm function studies prior to discharge in at least 50-60 % of this pool (40-45 BPD infants/year) and echocardiographic studies in close to 100 % of infants. We obtain acceptable and repeatable lung function data in at least 80% of infants tested providing us with comprehensive functional information within the neonatal period on ~35 infants with BPD each year, requiring ~3.6 years for recruitment of the full cohort. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>1</followup>
    <followuptype>Years</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>King Edward Memorial Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Stirling Highway,
Crawley, 6009
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>King Edward Memorial Hospital
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>374 Bagot Rd, Subiaco, 6008
Western Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Roberts Rd,
Subiaco, 6008
Western Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Breathing problems persisting into infancy and later life is an important complication of premature birth with lifelong consequences. Breathing problems often occur together with lung disease, but prematurity can also affect heart and blood vessel development, and weakness of the main breathing muscle (the diaphragm). We will find out how much the heart, lung and muscles each contribute to breathing problems, as well as identify factors such as infection, nutrition and treatments that influence these and other long-term outcomes of very preterm birth.  This knowledge will help us to better predict, diagnose, treat  and prevent adverse outcomes after preterm birth. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women and Newborn Health Service Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>374 Bagot Rd
Subiaco, 6008
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-091 EW</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Pillow</name>
      <address>c/- School of Human Sciences and UWA Centre for Neonatal Research and Education,
M309, The University of Western Australia,
35 Stirling Highway, 
Crawley, 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6488 3318</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 6488 1051</fax>
      <email>jane.pillow@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Diane Arnott</name>
      <address>c/- UWA Centre for Neonatal Research and Education
1st Floor, King Edward Memorial Hospital,
374 Bagot Rd,
Subiaco, 6008
Western Australia</address>
      <phone> 61 8 9340 1260</phone>
      <fax> 61 8 9340 1266</fax>
      <email>diane.arnott@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Pillow</name>
      <address>c/- School of Human Sciences and UWA Centre for Neonatal Research and Education,
M309, The University of Western Australia,
35 Stirling Highway, 
Crawley, 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6488 3318</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 6488 1051</fax>
      <email>jane.pillow@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Pillow</name>
      <address>c/- School of Human Sciences and UWA Centre for Neonatal Research and Education,
M309, The University of Western Australia,
35 Stirling Highway, 
Crawley, 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6488 3318</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 6488 1051</fax>
      <email>jane.pillow@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>