<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368383">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000859583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Healing pressure ulcers/injuries: Efficacy and cost effectiveness of nutrition interventions in the treatment of pressure ulcer/injuries </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Do specific nutrition interventions improve healing of pressure ulcer/injuries compared to standard nutritional care in hospital inpatients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NIPIHR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pressure ulcer/injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be randomized to one of the following groups: a. Standard nutritional care by clinical team that may or may not include dietetic intervention, high protein/energy diet and/or nutritional supplement.  
b. intensive individualised nutritional intervention provided by an associate investigator site dietitian aimed to meet estimated nutritional requirements of patients on a daily basis, which will likely include a high protein/energy diet and supplements (but not including wound healing supplements).  Estimated nutritional requirements will be determined at 1.2g protein/kg and 30 KCal/kg per day. Patient will be reviewed by a dietitian for appox 20-30 minutes 3-4 times per week to assess intake and modify nutritional care plan if required.
c. standard care as described above, plus the provision of a nutritional supplements developed specifically to enhance wound healing ie complete oral liquid nutritional formulas enriched with Arginine, Vitamin C and Zinc. Supplements will be prescribed based on manufacturers recommendations ie 2 or 3 200-250ml tetrapaks daily.  Patients will be given a choice of two different brands of supplements based on their preferences.  

Supplement A contains per 200ml bottle: 20g protein (of which arginine is 3.0g), 250 KCal, 9 mg Zinc,  250 mg Vitamin C Recommended dose is 3 200ml bottles per day.
Supplement B contains per 250ml tetrapak: 21 g protein (of which arginine is 4.5g), 250 KCal, 15 mg Zinc, 250 mg Vitamin C. Recommended dose is 2 250 ml tetrapaks per day.

Duration of interventions will be for the duration of patient hospital stay.

Compliance with interventions will be monitored through data collection of food and fluid (including supplement) intake. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard nutritional care: standard clinical team based nutritional care that may include a dietetic or nutrition intervention such as high protein/energy diet and/or nutritional supplements. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in pressure injury measured in 2 different way: 1. surface area - measured using Visitrak wound measurement system by trained Research Assistant
2. severity score - measured using Pressure Ulcer Scale for Healing PUSH Score - by trained Research Assistant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days to healing - measured as number of days from randomization into study until full wound closure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness of nutritional interventions in pressure ulcer healing. This will be measured by incremental cost-effectiveness ratio of alternate nutrition interventions compared to other forms of treatment of pressure ulcer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of pressure ulcers healed between groups - measured by number of pressure ulcers in each study group healed until full wound closure</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability and adherence to nutritional interventions between groups. This will be measured by determining quantifying nutritional intake from 24 hour food and supplement records; patient complications eg. gastrointestinal side effects and patient satisfaction feedback. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inpatients (adults) of 5 acute hospitals with pressure ulcer/injury stage 2 or greater. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Stage 1 of deep tissue pressure injury
Patients unable to receive nutrition via enteral route
Patients inappropriate for intensive nutrition support ie palliative care
Patients unable to follow nutrition support advise ie cognitively impaired
Pregnancy
Previously recruited to study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible patients in consecutive order as identified by clinical staff will be approach for consent to participate in study.
Consenting patients will be randomly assigned to treatment groups by independent researcher.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation, stratified by severity of pressure ulcer based on PUSH score</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>285</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>131</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Butterfield St
HERSTON 4029 QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sir Fred Schonnel Drive 
St Lucia 4067  QLD</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Multi-centre study investigating whether specific nutritional interventions improve pressure injury healing compared to standard care. Consenting eligible patients with pressure injuries stage 2 or greater at 5 south East Queensland hospitals will be randomized to receive standard ward based nutrition, intensive dietetic nutrition intervention or prescription of a wound healing formula. Data will be collected at baseline and weekly including a range of relevant demographic, nutritional and pressure ulcer measurements. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Butterfield St
HERSTON 4029 QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/QRBW/125</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Merrilyn Banks</name>
      <address>Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Butterfield St
HERSTON 4029 QLD</address>
      <phone>617 36467994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>merrilyn.banks@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Merrilyn Banks</name>
      <address>Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Butterfield St
HERSTON 4029 QLD</address>
      <phone>617 36467994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>merrilyn.banks@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Merrilyn Banks</name>
      <address>Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Butterfield St
HERSTON 4029 QLD</address>
      <phone>617 36467994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>merrilyn.banks@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Merrilyn Banks</name>
      <address>Nutrition &amp; Dietetics
Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital
Butterfield St
HERSTON 4029 QLD</address>
      <phone>617 36467994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>merrilyn.banks@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>