<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372053">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000321347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Parenting from the start: Evaluating a preventative intervention to improve outcomes for first-time mothers and their babies</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Parenting from the start: Evaluating a preventative intervention
to improve attachment and health outcomes for first-time mothers and their babies</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111111840331</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Maternal sensitivity and responsiveness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Infant attachment security </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Birth outcomes / interventions (including instrumental and surgical birth)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Infant feeding / breastfeeding</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Infant sleep practices </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Social support / alloparenting</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Brief name: Antenatal parenting intervention

Evidence-based parenting workshop plus a gifted resource to assist with early parenting.  The full-day workshop will provide first-time mothers and their whanau with evidence-based information to facilitate informed decision making. The workshop does not involve giving advice or telling people how to parent.

The mode of delivery is face-to-face, and the workshops will take place at a variety of community venues around the Manawatu region such as health hubs and wananga (Maori tertiary education institutions). Each workshop is intended to include approximately 10 women, plus their partners, support people, and/or family/whanau members, although the number of participants may need to be adjusted to fit the demand at each locality.
 
The presenter, a registered clinical psychologist, is expected to be sensitive to the needs of the people in each group and flexible in her presentation style  providing extra explanation or hands-on demonstration as appropriate. 

Intervention adherence / fidelity will be assessed. At the conclusion of each workshop, a checklist will be completed by the presenter to indicate whether key topics were covered, and key process issues adhered to. Participants will complete a Workshop Feedback Form at the end of the workshop, providing the presenter with information about what is working and/or not working so that the workshop can be adjusted as appropriate. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The experiences of control group participants will differ in terms of timing and the resources received. They will be invited to attend a workshop at a different stage to intervention group participants. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal sensitivity and responsiveness (composite score or classification based on 3 measures, all involving expert ratings based on a 60-90 minute home observation). Two established observational measures will be used: the Maternal Behavior Q-Sort (MBQS-mini) and Ainsworth Sensitivity Scales, plus another observational / interview measure purpose-designed for this study: Observational Measure of Sensitivity and Responsiveness (OMOSAR). All measures will be completed by the lead researcher &amp;/or a trained research assistant. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At home visit 4-6 months post birth.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of infants securely attached to their mother on the Strange Situation Procedure (SSP). The SSP will be scored by a trained research assistant who is blind to group allocation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At lab assessment 12 to 15 months post birth. Note: timing of lab assessment will be delayed for infants born prematurely.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting intentions as measured by maternal responses to likert scales on purpose-designed questionnaire: Parenting Intentions Questionnaire (PIQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered twice as a pre-test and post-test immediately before and after workshop (same day). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Workshop feedback as measured by maternal responses to likert scales on purpose-designed Workshop Feedback Form. The feedback form also invites qualitative responses (comments, feedback).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the workshop (same day)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of infants admitted to the newborn intensive care unit as measured by maternal report on purpose-designed questionnaire: Parenting Strategies Questionnaire (PSQ). </outcome>
      <timepoint>4-6 months post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of mothers reporting particular birth interventions (e.g. medication, forceps, caesarian sections) as measured by maternal report on purpose-designed questionnaire: Parenting Strategies Questionnaire (PSQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>4-6 months post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of infants who are partially / fully / exclusively breastfed at various ages according to mothers report on purpose-designed questionnaires: Parenting Strategies Questionnaire (PSQ) and Evolved Developmental Niche Scale (EDN Scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At home visit 4-6 months post birth (PSQ), and during lab assessment 12-15 months post birth (EDN Scale).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of mothers with scores over 13 on the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS). Mean depression score on EPDS. This screening test is OPTIONAL, so may not be completed by all participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At home visit 4-6 months post birth. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of mothers employing particular parenting strategies as measured by maternal responses to purpose-designed questionnaire: Parenting Strategies Questionnaire (PIQ), which includes 60 multi-choice and likert-type items. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At home visit 4-6 months post birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on the purpose-designed Evolved Developmental Niche Scale (EDN Scale), measuring evolved parenting practices.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At lab assessment 12-15 months post birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Maternal Behavior Q-Sort (MBQS-mini). This measure will be completed by the lead researcher &amp;/or a trained research assistant based on a 60-90 minute home observation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At home visit 4-6 months post-birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Ainsworth Sensitivity Scales. This measure will be completed by the lead researcher &amp;/or a trained research assistant based on a 60-90 minute home observation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At home visit 4-6 months post-birth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on the Observational Measure of Sensitivity and Responsiveness (OMOSAR), which was developed for this study. This measure will be completed by the lead researcher &amp;/or a trained research assistant based on a 60-90 minute home observation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At home visit 4-6 months post-birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This research will be conducted in the Manawatu region of Aotearoa New Zealand. Participants will be first-time mothers who enter the study during pregnancy and are happy for their baby to participate alongside them during their first year of life. Additional criteria for participation include being able to read and write well in English (in order to complete the questionnaires), a permanent resident living within 60 minutes drive of Palmerston North, able to remain involved in the study until their baby is 12-18 months old, and anticipating a normal pregnancy and birth. The Screening Questionnaire outlines the inclusion/ exclusion criteria.

People who report serious or chronic health conditions on the Screening Questionnaire will be allowed to enter the study on a case-by-case basis if the research team decides the condition will not seriously interfere with their ability to benefit from the parenting intervention being trialed. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People will not be able to take part if they are expecting a multiple birth (e.g. twins), are planning to adopt or foster a baby, or have serious health conditions likely to affect their pregnancy, birth, and/or parenting choices (in the view of the research team). Fathers and other partners or family members will be able to attend the workshop, but will not be able to enrol in the study.

The Screening Questionnaire includes follow-up questions asking for a description of the health condition affecting the mother and/or baby. The purpose of these questions is to gain sufficient information to make a judgement about the appropriateness of study participation. People will not be able to participate if they have serious mental or physical health issues or addictions that are likely to limit their ability to make use of the information and resources presented in the workshop. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Yes. Potential participants will be given an Information Sheet once they have completed a Screening Questionnaire and met study criteria. Each Information Sheet will be placed in a sealed opaque envelope and numbered by a research assistant, and the envelopes will be handed out in pre-arranged random order by the lead researcher as people express interest in entering the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Yes. Potential participants will be given an Information Sheet once they have completed a Screening Questionnaire and met study criteria. Each Information Sheet will be placed in a sealed opaque envelope and numbered by a research assistant, and the envelopes will be handed out in pre-arranged random order by the lead researcher as people express interest in entering the study.

Simple randomisation. There will be two versions of the Information Sheet, which will be given out in (pre-arranged) random order: One for the intervention group and one for the control group. Randomisation will be accomplished using a list of random numbers generated by www.randomizer.org, with even numbers indicating assignment to the intervention group (Group B) and odd numbers indicating assignment to the control group (Group A). This ‘allocation concealment’ prevents bias from influencing the recruitment process.
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is the first study of its kind. We are aiming to recruit up to 200 mother-infant dyads (approximately 100 per group). A sample of even one quarter this size (50 dyads) is likely to produce useful findings in telling us what strategies local parents are utilising during their first year, but may not provide sufficient power for significance testing.

We intend to use a combination of descriptive statistics to describe the tools and strategies parents in our region are using and significance testing (e.g. t tests) to compare the intervention and control groups on each measure. We also plan to use linear regression to assess the predictive validity of our maternal sensitivity measures. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Leith Anna Pugmire</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Massey University Manawatu Campus
Private Bag 11 222 
Palmerston North 4442 
New Zealand
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Massey University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Massey University Manawatu Campus
Private Bag 11 222 
Palmerston North 4442 
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Te Hahi Tuhauwiri / Aotearoa New Zealand Religious Society of Friends (Quakers)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Te Hahi Tuhauwiri / Aotearoa New Zealand Religious Society of Friends (Quakers) 
c/o Friends Settlement
76 Virginia Road, Otamatea
Whanganui 4500</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Jaycee Trust </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Palmeston North Jaycee Trust 
c/o Palmerston North City Council 
Private Bag 11034
PALMERSTON NORTH 4442
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Shane Harvey (Primary PhD Supervisor)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Psychology Clinic
Massey University Manawatu Campus
Private Bag 11 222 
Palmerston North 4442 
New Zealand
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study evaluates an evidence-based parenting intervention and collects information about what New Zealand parents are doing when it comes to parenting during the first year of life. Up to 200 first-time mothers in the Manawatu region of New Zealand will be followed from pregnancy until their babies are 12 to 15 months old, and assessed using a range of outcome measures. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NA</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health &amp; Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Health and Disability Ethics Committees
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6140
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/STH/186</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372053-Screening Questionnaire (1).pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372053-Advertising Poster (v3.2).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Leith Anna Pugmire</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Massey University Manawatu Campus
Private Bag 11 222 
Palmerston North 4442 
New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>+64212548812</phone>
      <fax>NA</fax>
      <email>l.pugmire@netmail.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Leith Anna Pugmire</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Massey University Manawatu Campus
Private Bag 11 222 
Palmerston North 4442 
New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>+64212548812</phone>
      <fax>NA</fax>
      <email>l.pugmire@netmail.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Leith Anna Pugmire</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Massey University Manawatu Campus
Private Bag 11 222 
Palmerston North 4442 
New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>+64212548812</phone>
      <fax>NA</fax>
      <email>l.pugmire@netmail.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Leith Anna Pugmire</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Massey University Manawatu Campus
Private Bag 11 222 
Palmerston North 4442 
New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>+64212548812</phone>
      <fax>NA</fax>
      <email>l.pugmire@netmail.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>