<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320888">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000058077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Corneal nerve microstructure in Diabetes Mellitus</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Correlation of corneal nerve microstructure and function with peripheral neuropathy in Type I Diabetes Mellitus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type I Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational study. The changes in corneal innervation, thickness, epithelium, keratocyte density and endothelium will be observed in 100 participants with diabetic cornea and 40 age matched participants with normal cornea without any history of diabetes or corneal disorders. These will be correlated with the severity of peripheral diabetic neuropathy and retinopathy. The corneal nerve pattern will also be  observed in both normal and diabetic cornea. The duration of the project is 3 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To quantify changes in corneal innervation, thickness, epithelium, keratocyte density and endothelium, and correlate these with the severity of peripheral diabetic neuropathy and retinopathy.

Techniques will include in vivo confocal microscopy of the cornea to measure epithelium, keratocyte  and endothelium density, corneal thickness measurement by computerised corneal topography, assessment of corneal sensation by aesthesiometry. Corneal data will be compared with a cohort of 40 age-matched controls, who have no history of corneal disease, diabetes, or neurological disease. Within the diabetic group, data will be correlated with the stage of peripheral neuropathy as characterised by a standardised neuropathy questionnaire and clinical examination graded by the Neuropathy Disability Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>140 participants will be assessed within a period of 24 months. Each participant will  require only one visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To qualitatively compare corneal nerve pattern in the normal, Type I diabetic cornea.
Technique will include in vivo confocal microscopy of the cornea to obtain images of corneal nerves. The images will be arranged to form a contiguous montage of corneal nerve pattern.</outcome>
      <timepoint>20 participants will undergo this assessment within a period of 6 months. Each participant will  require only one visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate tear film abnormalities in the diabetic eye.
Tear film Symptomatology will be assessed by McMonnies Dry Eye Questionnaire, Tear film stability by Tearscope Plus (Keeler) and Tear production by phenol red thread test.
The tear film data will be compared with a cohort of 40 age-matched controls, who have no history of corneal disease, diabetes, or neurological disease. Within the diabetic group, data will be correlated with the stage of peripheral neuropathy as characterised by a standardised neuropathy questionnaire and clinical examination graded by the Neuropathy Disability Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>140 participants will be assessed within a period of 24 months. Each participant will  require only one visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Type I Diabetes Mellitus</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of contact lens wear ocular disease or ocular surgery
use of preservative topical medications
Any other known cause of neuropathy 
Any clinical evidence of significant corneal abnormality.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019,
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland Doctoral Scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Auckland,
Private Bag 92019,
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Diabetic neuropathy involves changes to peripheral somatic and autonomic innervation, as well as quantifiable changes to cranial nerves and the central nervous system. Corneal innervation provides important protective and trophic functions and its interruption may result in impaired cell attachment, altered epithelial structure, decreased mitotic rate, increased permeability, poor tear film and delayed wound healing. Reduced corneal sensation, observed in 70% of diabetics compared with 10% of controls, has been shown to be associated with duration of diabetic disease and correlates strongly with stage of peripheral neuropathy. We hypothesise that changes in corneal innervation, as imaged by in vivo confocal microscopy and assessed by aesthesiometry, will correlate with the stage of peripheral diabetic neuropathy, offering future potential for assessing nerve structure in vivo, without the need for nerve biopsy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Committees
Health &amp; Disability Services Policy Group
Population Health Directorate
Ministry of Health
09 580 9105
09 580 9001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>NTX/09/12/122</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jennifer Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology, 
Faculty of Medical &amp; Health Science
University of Auckland,
Private bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 8173</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 367 7173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stuti Misra</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology, 
Faculty of Medical &amp; Health Science
University of Auckland,
Private bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6582</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 367 7173</fax>
      <email>s.misra@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Stuti Misra</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology, 
Faculty of Medical &amp; Health Science
University of Auckland,
Private bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6582</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 367 7173</fax>
      <email>s.misra@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>