<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370286">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000401459p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Probiotics and Orotic Acid  for treatment resistant depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Project title: A randomised placebo controlled clinical trial investigating the role of orotate and probiotics co-administered with antidepressant medications for the management of treatment resistant depression. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Treatment resistant depression with high risk of relapse</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mental Health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The project intervention will consist of n=250 using a randomised parallel treatment trial to test the efficacy of the oral administration of specific strain probiotics and orotic acid administered in conjunction with selective serotonin uptake inhibiters (SSRI) for treatment resistant depression. 
The project time line will consist of rolling recruitment and block allocation to conditions.  All participants will be inducted into a 2 week precondition where they will receive  2x placebo capsules daily to identify placebo responders. Placebo capsules (microcellulose) will be identical the probiotic and the Mg orotate tablets used in the experimental phase of the study. All participants are then allocated to a 2 week probiotic run in period and receive 2 probiotic capsules daily followed by random allocation to either 1. probiotic + orotic acid (Magnesium form: Mg orotate) and 2., probiotic and placebo groups for 8 weeks with a 4 week follow up assessment. Total study duration is 16 weeks for participants with repeated recruitments over a minimum of 24 months. .
Probiotic: A daily dose of 2 probiotic capsules taken orally, 1 x morning and 1 x evening with a meal. Each capsule contains 50 billion colony-forming units (CFU) of live organisms (Lactobacillus acidophilus +Lactobacillus casei +Lactobacillus rhamnosus JB-1.)
Orotic acid: A daily oral dose of 4 x Mg orotate taken 2 x morning and 2 x evening with a meal, yielding 1600mg of orotate.
Each participant will be taking SSRI medication prescribed by their own medical practitioner  as part of the selection criteria, and they will continue taking their medication throughout the study.  
Supplement and SSRI compliance will be monitored by fortnightly contact with each participant by a research assistant and a dosage log book that must be completed by participants on a daily basis throughout the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control is conducted in 2 phases, firstly the placebo responder screening (2 weeks).
The experimental control consists of administering a placebo in place of Mg orotate in parallel group 2, while continuing to take the probiotic.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beck Depression Inventory Score will provide primary symptom response data. Outcome 1 consists of evaluating BDI during and after treatment. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>BDI scores will be administered at study intake, end of placebo screen condition, end of 2 week run in phase, and end point of experimental phase at 8 weeks and at 4 week follow up. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysbiosis is assessed using fecal sequencing and analysis from samples provided by each participant. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Fecal sequence at intake week -1 and study endpoint, week 8 and follow up week 4. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipopolysacharide levels (LPS) will be assessed using blood tests provided by individual participants as a marker of systemic inflammation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>LPS blood samples drawn at week 1, 8 and follow up, week 4, </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The outcome questionnaire (OQ45) will be administered to assesses functional symptom and distress. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Intake, placebo screen at -2 weeks, weekly during run in probiotic phase 2 weeks, weekly during experimental phase 8 weeks, and at a single point follow up, 4 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood cytokine levels as an inflammation marker </outcome>
      <timepoint>Samples provided at experimental phase allocation, endpoint 8 weeks and follow up 4weeks.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Be depressed,, with depression as primary diagnosis, while taking SSRI antidepressant medication as prescribed by a doctor 
2. Currently be under the management of a medical practitioner e.g. family doctor or a psychiatrist
3. Have a history of depression that has not responded well to medication, with at least 2 previous episodes
4. Be over 18 years of age and have the capacity to provide informed consent
5. Have the willingness and ability to comply with assessment protocols of the study

 





</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Resistant depression not being the primary diagnosis
2. Current substance misuse
3. Other psychiatric disorder as primary diagnosis
4. Active suicidality
5. Not able to understand or conform to study requirements 
6. Subject to a mental health or guardianship order
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly allocated to conditions. Randomisation will be conducted by a person not involved with the selection and assessment of participants. </concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted randomisation carried out by a research assistant who was not involved with selection or assessment of participants, to 1 = probiotic + mg orotate and SSRI or 2 = probiotic + placebo and SSRI. Rolling allocation will occur during recruitment until n=250. 

</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>2 x pre experimental conditions, being placebo screen x 2 weeks, and probiotic run in phase x 2 weeks, then experimental conditions begin. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power calculations were based on effect sizes achieved from our pilot data using adjuvant treatments. We assume the standard deviation of the difference in responses between treatments for the same patient is 21 units, and that alpha=0.05. To identify a clinically important between-treatment difference of 5 units or greater, with 80% power, we need to obtain complete outcome data on 140 individual patients. Assuming a notional 30% of participants who enrol for the study do not complete all intervals of measurement, as a sample validity measure, the recruitment target will be expanded to n=200 participants for this study. Further, it is possible that 20% of the sample will be placebo responders in the screen condition, therefore an additional n=50 participants will be recruited resulting in a total of n=250 participants. 

Data will be analysed using SPSS statistical software package version 17.0. For the BDI, QOL, OQ45 scores repeated measures analyses of variance [ANOVA] will be conducted to investigate the relationship between matched differences between the 2 treatments on pre-post- and follow up and weekly symptom change scores. T-tests will be conducted for significant and marginally significant within group effects. Regression tests will be employed to examine measures of association between variables. Non-parametric tests will be employed if data is skewed from normality. Biological test data will be reported in full and entered as either scored variables or categorical data for the different analyses. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Luis Vitetta</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Medical School
Edward Ford Building A27
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to evaluate the role of dysbiosis and probiotics and orotic acid as a treatment for depressive illness that does not respond to standard medication treatment. 
The mechanisms of probiotics in the treatment of dysbiosis and systemic inflammation and orotic acid as a treatment for resistant depression will also be evaluated. Significance: Developing effective and safe treatments for resistant depression is essential as this group presents a significant burden of care to the health system and generally have poorer vocational and quality of life outcomes and are at increased risk of morbidity and mortality. Dysbiosis and ensuing systemic inflammation has been strongly implicated in depression that has a poor treatment response. Orotic acid rapidly metabolises into uridine which has proven antidepressant effects through mechanisms different to antidepressant medication. Orotic acid demonstrated efficacy in our previous pilot work. The expected outcome of this study is to provide preliminary efficacy and safety data, and elucidate the mechanism of probiotics and orotoic acid as an adjuvant therapy with one class of standard medication.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee (MREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UQ Research &amp; Innovation
Cumbrae-Stewart Building (72)
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND QLD 4072
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Luis Vitetta</name>
      <address>Sydney Medical School
Edward Ford Building A27
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 402263316</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luis.vitetta@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Bambling </name>
      <address>School of Medicine 
Mayne Medical School
288 Herston Road
 Herston QLD 4006
 Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+61 466532314</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.bambling@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Bambling</name>
      <address>School of Medicine 
Mayne Medical School
288 Herston Road
 Herston QLD 4006
 Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+61 466532314</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.bambling@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Bambling</name>
      <address>School of Medicine 
Mayne Medical School
288 Herston Road
 Herston QLD 4006
 Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+61 466532314</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.bambling@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>