<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365984">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000405617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparative study of orotracheal intubation through Air Q laryngeal mask airway: Blind versus fiberoptic guided during general anesthesia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparative study of orotracheal intubation through Air Q laryngeal mask airway: Blind versus fiberoptic guided during general anesthesia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-5889</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>orotracheal intubation </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>pressor response</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition> arousable response</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study was conducted at Beni- Suef University Hospital,Egypt. 100 adult patients ASA I and II undergoing elective surgeries under general anesthesia with orotracheal intubation were divided into two groups according to the technique of intubation through Air-Q ILA. Group I (n= 50) patients intubated blindly using air Q intubating laryngeal airway (Air-Q ILA): the cuff of the Air-Q ILA was deflated until two dimples appear at the back of Air-Q ILA as described by manufacturer and was lubricated with xylocain gel 2% , the Air-Q ILA was inserted into the patients mouth with the upper incisor of the patient opposite the lower landmark on the tube of the air Q ILA to prevent epiglottic folding with the cuff of the Air-Q ILA, the cuff then inflated with 10-15 ml air and connected to the circle system.After confirmation of ventilation by capnography, bilateral chest expansion , and bilateral auscultation of breath sounds the air Q ILA mask adaptor was disconnected, a well lubricated PVC endotracheal tube (ID 7mm in females,7.5 in males)was advanced through its shaft blindly then connected to the circle system, successful endotracheal intubation and ventilation was confirmed with capnography, then the cuffs of the Air-Q ILA and endotracheal tube were deflated, the ETT connector was removed then the Air-Q ILA was removed over a special stylet, Then, the ETT connector was placed into its position ,the cuff reinflated and the ETT was connected to the circle system, any blood visible on the device indicative of trauma to the upper airway or bronchospasm were recorded If first attempt of intubation failed, the second attempt was done by maximal head extension and mandibular lift,If the second attempt failed, the third attempt was done by fiberoptic bronchooscope through Air-Q ILA.).</interventions>
    <comparator>In Group II(n=50) patients were intubated through the Air-Q ILA from the start guided by flexible fiberoptic bronchoscpe( KARL STORZ- Endoscope 5.2 x 65): a reusable Air-Q ILA use was lubricated with xylocain gel 2% and inserted into the patient mouth, the cuff then inflated with 10-15 ml and the Air-Q ILAwas connected to the circle system, after confirmation of ventilation, a well lubricated fiberoptic bronchoscope loaded with a proper size well lubricated PVC ETT (ID 7mm in females and 7.5 in males) was advanced through the Air-Q ILA shaft till visualization of the glottic area of the larynx and advancing into the trachea until visualization of the carina then the ETT was advanced into the trachea . The scope then was removed and the ETT cuff was inflated and connected to the circle system, successful endotracheal intubation was confirmed with capnography , adequate chest expansion and bilateral auscultation of breath sounds. The cuff of the Air-Q ILA was deflated then it was removed over a special stylet. Any blood visible on the device, indicative of trauma to the upper airway or bronchospasm was reported</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time of insertion of the air q ila: stop watch</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of insertion of the endotracheal tube</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	
Number  of attempts of insertion of Air-Q ILA</outcome>
      <timepoint>	Number  of attempts of  intubation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients who failed to be intubated with the device </outcome>
      <timepoint>	Number of patients who failed to be intubated with the device (after 3 attempts) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Airway complications: injury to the gums or teeth damage.hoarseness of the voice , bleeding, sore throat. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Before leaving the PACU the patients was  asked about  sore throat and hoarseness. If noted, assessment for 48 hours was done</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bispectral Index (BIS) values </outcome>
      <timepoint> measured before induction of anesthesia,  after induction,  immediately after intubation and after 5 minutes of endotracheal intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Arterial oxygen saturation (SpO2); by pulse oximetry</outcome>
      <timepoint> before, during and after intubation.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systolic arterial blood pressure : by noninvasive blood pressure monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint> preinduction, after induction of anesthesia, then at 1 and 5 minutes after intubation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> diastolic  arterial blood pressure :
 by noninvasive blood pressure monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint> preinduction, after induction of anesthesia, then at 1 and 5 minutes after intubation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> mean arterial blood pressure: by noninvasive blood pressure monitoring</outcome>
      <timepoint>  preinduction, after induction of anesthesia, then at 1 and 5 minutes after intubation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ASA (III) planned for elective surgical operations under general  anesthesia  with oral endotracheal intubation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>hypertension, neurological, cardiovascular, endocrine disease, risk of regurgitation  and pulmonary aspiration, cervical  spine lesion, patients undergoing  cardiac and neurosurgical procedures, risk index of El-Ganzouri for difficult tracheal intubation more than or eqaul 4, BMI &gt; 35 kg/m2, oropharyngeal mass, respiratory pathology, or any history of allergy to drugs used  in the protocol</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis and data handling
Data are presented  as mean+/-  SD, number and percentage ,median  and rang as  appropriate. Unpaired Student t- test was used for comparison between means of the two groups. Mann-Whitney U test was used for comparison of nonparametric data. Chi-square test or Fisher's exact test were  used for comparing categorical data. P values = 0.05 were considered  statistically significant. Statistical package for social science (SPSS) software version 17 was used."Sample size was calculated based on a previous study (El-Ganzouri AR, Marzouk S, Abdelalem N and Yousef M: Blind versus fiberopticlaryngoscopic intubation through air Q laryngeal mask airway, Egypt J Anesth,2011; 27: 2138.) which included 40 patients in each group, we increased the size to 50 patient per group to compensate if any case excluded due to failure or difficult technique.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/03/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>benisuef</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>faculty of medicine benisuef university</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>egypt,benisuef governerate
 -,mokbel, 62511
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>benisuef university hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>egypt benisuef governerate
 -,mokbel, 62511
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>personal</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>egypt</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background:Tracheal intubation is the gold standard for securing the airway, laryngoscopy and endotracheal intubation induce pressor response which is of concern in patients with  cardiac diseases and patients with cerebrovascular lesions, not only laryngoscopy and tracheal intubation cause cardiovascular responses but also induce an arousal response on the EEG .The AIR-Q intubating Laryngeal Mask (Air-Q ILA Cookgas LLC; distributed by Mercury Medical)is a new supraglottic device with the following advantages: ease of insertion, reliable alignment of the glottis opening, ability for continuous oxygenation and ventilation .
Methods:
This study was conducted at Beni- Suef  University Hospital,Egypt, 100 adult patients ASA I and II undergoing elective surgeries under general anesthesia with orotracheal intubation  were divided into two groups according to the technique of intubation through Air-Q ILA 
Group I (n= 50)patients intubated   blindly through Air-Q ILA
Group II (n=50) patients intubated  through Air-Q ILA guided by flexible fiberoptic bronchoscope.
The following parameters were recorded: Heart rate,systolic, diastolic and mean arterial blood pressure  and Bispectral Index (BIS) values: preinduction, after induction of anesthesia, then at 1 and 5 minutes after intubation ,arterial oxygen saturation (SpO2): before, during and after intubation,time of insertion(in seconds) and number of attempts of insertion  of the Air-Q ILA and  endotracheal tube and airway complications; injury to the gums or teeth damage, hoarseness of the voice , bleeding, sore throat.
Results:
Systolic and mean arterial blood pressures were statistically significant lower in the fiberoptic group than blind group. There was no statistically significant difference between the two groups in the heart rate and diastolic blood pressure. Time and number of attempts of insertion of Air-Q ILA were statistically significant lower in fiberoptic group than in blind group. There was statistically significant lower time of intubation and less number of attempts in fiberoptic group than in blind group and success rate of intubation in the fiberoptic group was 100% compared  to 76% in blind group. There was statistically significant lower BIS value in the fiberoptic group 1 minute after intubation than in the blind group
Conclusion: endotracheal intubationthrough the Air-Q ILA guided by  flexible fiberoptic bronchoscope is associated with less hemodynamic pressor response and arousal response than blind endotracheal intubation through the Air-Q ILA,the number of attempt and time of successful intubation were statistically significantly lower in the fiberoptic group than the blind group
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>research ethical comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>benisuef governerate
 -,mokbel, 62511
 benisuef faculty of medicine
(FMBUS)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Reham  Mohammed Mohammed essawy</name>
      <address>Reham  Mohammed Mohammed essawy 
egypt,benisuef governerate
benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511
</address>
      <phone>+2020822318605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Re_esawy@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>doaa rashwan</name>
      <address>doaa rashwan  egypt,

benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511


</address>
      <phone>+20822318605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doaa_rashwan2007@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>doaa rashwan</name>
      <address>doaa rashwan  egypt,

benisuef university,faculty of medicine

 -,mokbel,mohamad anwar hassan street, 62511

</address>
      <phone>+20822318605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doaa_rashwan@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>doaa rashwan</name>
      <address>egypt,benisuef governerate
 -,mokbel, 62511</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>doaa_rashwan2007@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>