<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347714">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001195943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Immediate effect of a global pelvic manipulation technique on lumbar pain in patients with primary dysmenorrhea: a randomized controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Immediate effect of a global pelvic manipulation technique versus a placebo technique on lumbar pain measured with a visual analogue scale, the pressure pain threshold in sacroiliac joints and the body's response to pain following a catecholamine and serotonine release in 40 patients with primary dismenorrhea: a double blind randomized controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pressure pain treshold in sacroiliac joints</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Self-perceived pain in lumbo-pelvic area</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The experimental group will receive a global pelvic manipulation (gpm) technique.

The patient will lie in lateral position. The therapist stands in front of the patient. The therapist will then flex the top leg until there is movement at the selected segment interspace (L5 fifth lumbar vertebrae -S1 first sacral segment)  and place the patient's foot in the popliteal fossa of the bottom leg. Next the therapist grasps the patient's bottom shoulder and arm and introduces left trunk sidebending and right rotation until motion is felt at the selected interspace. This interspace will be controlled by therapist's both hands adding a small traction.
Finally the therapist will apply a high velocity, low amplitude thrust of the pelvis in an anterior direction.

the whole technique lasts for two minutes and will be performed just once. The technique is harmless and painless</interventions>
    <comparator>the control group will be placed in a similar position but with no intended manipulation or thrust technique for the same estimated period of time.

A sham procedure will take place, so the technique will appear to happen, but with no real pressure</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- To quantitatively assess the effect of global pelvic manipulation (GPM) on lumbo-pelvic self-perceived pain using VAS scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and After the intervention procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- To explore differences in Pressure pain threshold (PPT) in sacroiliac joints (SIJ) with an algometer (FXP 25, Wagner Instruments), predicting an improvent in mechanosensibility in at least a 10%</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and  After the intervention procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- To assess body's endogenous response to pain following a catecholamine and serotonin release. A blood test will be done to measure the catecholamine / serotonin levels with an expected variability of 15%</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and After the intervention procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) age between 18 and 60 years old
(ii) regular menstruation intervals
(iii) willing to participate in the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) to wear a intrauterine device (IUD)
(ii) to suffer from secondary dysmenorrhea
(iii) previous gynecologic surgeries
(iv) Any contraindication to a spinal manipulation technique
(v) to have received any kind of manipulative treatment in the two months prior to the inclusion in the study
(vi) to show any fear to blood test or manipulative techniques</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone

Subjects have been selected from one hundred clinical histories from one of the researcher's clinical practice. The subjects should have shown low back pain and medical diagnosis of primary dysmenorrhea.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by a computer


(http://www.randomized.com/)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidad de Sevilla</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avicena s/n 41009 Sevilla (Spain)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidad de Sevilla</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avicena s/n 41009 Sevilla (Spain)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Primary dysmenorrhea (PD) is a gynecological disorder common in women of childbearing age.  The premenstrual symptoms are the following: the most common is pain in the lower abdomen, followed by lumbo-pelvic pain together with other less frequent symptoms. Due to the high frequency of women suffering from PD, it could be considered as a problem of public health. With manipulative techniques we can deal with pain of visceral origin, so our hypothesis is to provide an objective view of how lumbo-pelvic pain improves after applying a manual therapy technique. 

The main goal of the study is to quantitatively assess the effect of global pelvic manipulation technique on lumbar pain in patients with primary dysmenorrhea. The following parameters will be measured pre / post intervention in both, control and experimental groups, trough several parameters: (i) lumbo-pelvic pain using Visual Analogue Scale scores, (ii) the pressure pain threshold in sacroiliac joints and (iii) the bodys endogenous response to pain following a catecholamine and serotonin release.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Molins-Cubero, S., Rodriguez-Blanco, C., Oliva-Pascual-Vaca, A., Heredia-Rizo, A. M., Bosca-Gandia, J. J. and Ricard, F. (2014), Changes in Pain Perception after Pelvis Manipulation in Women with Primary Dysmenorrhea: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Pain Medicine. doi: 10.1111/pme.12404</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite Etico de Experimentacion de la Universidad de Sevilla</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Paseo de las Delicias s/n 41013 Sevilla (Spain)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NONE</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ALBERTO MARCOS HEREDIA RIZO</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy. Faculty of Nursing, Physiotherapy and Podiatrics. Universidad de Sevilla

C/ Avicena s/n 41009 Sevilla</address>
      <phone>(+34)687823894</phone>
      <fax>(+34)954486527</fax>
      <email>amheredia@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>ALBERTO MARCOS HEREDIA RIZO</name>
      <address>DEPARTMENT OF PHYSIOTHERAPY. FACULTY OF NURSING, PHYSIOTHERAPY AND PODIATRICS. UNIVERSIDAD DE SEVILLA

C/ Avicena s/n 41009 Sevilla</address>
      <phone>(+34)687823894</phone>
      <fax>(+34)954486527</fax>
      <email>amheredia@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>ALBERTO MARCOS HEREDIA RIZO</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy. Faculty of Nursing, Physiotherapy and Podiatrics. Universidad de Sevilla

C/ Avicena s/n 41009 Sevilla</address>
      <phone>(+34)687823894</phone>
      <fax>(+34)954486527</fax>
      <email>amheredia@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cleofas Rodriguez-Blanco</name>
      <address>C/ Avicena s/n 41009, Sevilla, University of Sevilla</address>
      <phone>(+34 954486528)</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cleofas@us.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>