<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82378">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/10/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/10/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000553471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Targeted strength training to improve functional walking capacity of adolescents and young adults with cerebral palsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to find out if targeted strength training can improve the functional walking capacity of adolescents and young adults with diplegic cerebral palsy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cerebral palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Progressive resistance strength training (PRST) in a community gymnasium, twice a week for 12 weeks targeting the major muscles in the lower limbs contributing to limited walking ability. Participants will complete 2 to 3 sets of 10 to 12 repetitions of each exercise, with a 2 minute break between each set, at an intensity of 10-12 repetition maximum and exercise under the supervision of a physiotherapist.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants allocated to the control group will continue usual care during the 12-weeks between baseline and testing including their usual recreation and physiotherapy provided that these do not include progressive resistance trength training (PRST).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6 minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcome measurements will be taken three times: at baseline, after 12 weeks, and after a further 12 weeks (24 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activity levels:  
will be measured with an accelerometer-based activity monitor, monitoring step counts and time spent in sitting/lying, standing, and walking over a 3-day period</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcome measurements will be taken three times: at baseline, after 12 weeks, and after a further 12 weeks (24 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait kinematics: 
The Gillette Gait Index, formerly known as the Normalcy Index, will be used to document the effect of PRST on gait kinematics.  Derived from principal component analysis of 16 kinematic variables the Gillette Gait Index produces a dimensionless unit that indicates how much walking deviates from normal</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcome measurements will be taken three times: at baseline, after 12 weeks, and after a further 12 weeks (24 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength:
Dynamic strength will be assessed using one repetition maximum of a leg press (using the major antigravity support muscles of hip extensors, knee extensors and plantar flexors) and a reverse leg press (using the major lift-off muscles of hip flexors, knee flexors and ankle dorsiflexors). 
A hand held dynamometer will be used to assess isometric strength of the specific muscles targeted for each participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcome measurements will be taken three times: at baseline, after 12 weeks, and after a further 12 weeks (24 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) Diplegic cerebral palsy aged between 14 and 22 years  
(ii) Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) level II or III. 
(iii) Approval from a medical practitioner to participate in PRST.
(iv) Ability to follow simple instructions so that the participant can complete the prescribed exercise program.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>22</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) Single event multi-level orthopaedic surgery within the previous 2 years 
(ii) Participation in a PRST program in the 6 months prior to the start of the trial 
(iii) Contractures of more than 10ยบ at the hip and knee</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed sequentially numbered opaque envelopes administered by a researcher independent of the project</concealment>
    <sequence>Block allocation sequence will be generated using a random numbers table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/08/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>49</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3052</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>La Trobe University
Victoria 3086
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council (NHMRC) project grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Children's Hospital, Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville  Victoria  3052
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main aim is to find out if targeted strength training for the lower limbs can improve walking ability of adolescents and young adults with cerebral palsy (CP).
CP is the most common cause of childhood disability in Australia.  Difficulty with walking is the major issue affecting the independence of many young people with CP.  Preliminary data suggests that strengthening weak muscles of young people with CP can improve functional activities like walking. In addition, pilot data indicates that strength training works best for adolescents and young adults with CP after other managements like surgery and rehabilitation have been completed.A randomised controlled trial will compare strength training against a control group receiving usual care.This will be the first fully powered randomised controlled trial to find out if strength training can help the walking ability of young people with CP, the major issue affecting their independence. If successful strength training could be an important treatment option for young people with CP as they make the transition to adulthood and sustained independence.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Taylor NF, Dodd KJ, Baker RJ, Willoughby K, Thomason P, Graham HK. 2013. Progressive resistance training and mobility-related function in young people with cerebral palsy: a randomized controlled trial.  Developmental Medicine and Child Neurology 55(9): 806-812.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Childrens Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Childrens Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville Victoria 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/04/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Royal Childrens Hospital 28006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/11/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health, La Trobe University Victoria 3086</address>
      <phone>61 3 9479 5860</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health, La Trobe University Victoria 3086</address>
      <phone>61 3 9479 5860</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health, La Trobe University, Victoria 3086.</address>
      <phone>61 3 94795860</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>