<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365899">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000255684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of the health care needs of people with serious lung disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the efficacy and cost-effectiveness of targeted advance care planning interventions among patients with severe respiratory disease in a tertiary hospital and in a rural setting</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>End-of-life care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Life sustaining treatments</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Advance care planning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a nurse-led advance care planning (ACP) discussion, in collaboration with the primary treating doctor and usual health care team.  The nurse will facilitate the doctor and broader health care team to initiate ACP discussions with eligible patients, and will assist in the documentation, distribution and storage of ACP documents for the duration of the trial.  They will also be a 'point of contact' for patients who are recruited to trial, and will be available for further discussion about advance care planning if necessary.

ACP discussions will include the following elements: eliciting patient/carer understanding of current health state, providing information about patient prognosis (if possible and appropriate), eliciting patient/carer perspectives on 'living well', eliciting patient/carer understanding of potential future medical treatments, values and goals of care, cultural/spiritual beliefs, preferences for future medical treatments, understanding of 'medical futility', understanding of 'time limited trials of treatment'.  The ACP discussion will also include a discussion about who would be an appropriate person to contact if the patient was unable to communicate.

The ACP discussion intervention is provided at least once, and participants will be assured that if they ever wish to revisit this discussion, they can do so by contacting the research nurse and/or usual healthcare provider.  ACP discussions will probably take between 30 minutes and 60 minutes, and may occur over multiple consultations.  Follow up ACP discussions with the research nurse will be available from the time of recruitment into the study, through until the completion of follow-up (18 months later after commencement of recruitment phase). </interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition is an "active control" condition, in which usual care is monitored for the duration of recruitment (12 months) and follow up (6 months).  Usual care involves standard evidence-based medical and nursing care, provided by participating hospitals, general practices and residential aged care facilities.

An additional historical control group (decedents treated at Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Respiratory Unit or Albany Health Campus) is included in this trial, to ensure that the overall management of patients with respiratory disease has not changed during the time of recruitment of intervention and control participants.  The historical data will be collected during 2014, and will include the medical records of patients who were deceased post 2010.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost of healthcare utilisation for each patient recruited into the study, (measured by costing hospital admissions, emergency department admissions, outpatient consultations, domicillary care visits and [in rural setting only] general practitioner and residential aged care facility care).  This will be costed against the resources associated with delivering the ACP intervention, as compared to usual care.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Healthcare utilisation is measured from the time of recruitment into the study, until the end of the study or time of death.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction with care, as measured by a validated questionnaire (Patient Satisfaction Index, Guyatt et al. 1995).  There are versions of the Patient Satisfaction Index that can be completed by  a family member (if the patient is deceased or has become incompetent).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of recruitment, 3 months following recruitment, 6 months following recruitment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Uptake of advance care planning as assessed by the number of patients who have undertaken formal or informal advance care planning at follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 month follow up, 6 month follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Place of death, as assessed by the match between preferred and actual place of death, for those patients who die during the course of the trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concordance between preferred and actual end-of-life care among those with ACP (decedents from historical control condition compared to recruited patients who die during the course of the trial).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Cognitively competent to provide consent and undertake ACP
English speaking
Severe respiratory disease
Treated at participating healthcare settings
Identified as high risk, based on fulfilling one or more general triggers or 'disease specific' triggers</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Lack of capacity to provide informed consent or participate in ACP
Non-English speaking patient
Patient expected to die within 48 hours
Formal advance care planning already in place
Currently on an end-of-life care pathway</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consenting subjects will be asked to state their preference for receiving or not receiving the ACP intervention.  Those who strongly prefer to receive ACP, or not receive ACP, will not be randomised, but will receive their preference.  Those with ambivalent preferences will be randomised, on a 2:1 schedule favouring the intervention.  Random allocation will be achieved by asking subjects to select an opaque, sealed envelope, from a box.  </concealment>
    <sequence>The box will initially be stocked with 21 sealed, opaque envelopes (14 specifying intervention, 7 specifying control).  Each subject who is randomly allocated will select their own envelope from the box.  When the box has only 4 envelopes left, the researcher will add a new set of 21 envelopes to the remaining 4 envelopes, and continue the process of allocating newly consented subjects by selection of envelopes from the box.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients are recruited into the trial in two distinct geographical regions (with little prospect of cross-over).
In addition to the random allocation process, the recruitment procedure also includes a patient preference component.  This means that those patients with strong preferences can be allocated directly into their preferred condition, while those with ambivalent preferences can be randomly allocated.
Collection of data from a sample of historical control patients (decedents with respiratory disease from Albany Health Campus or Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital) will be used to ensure that there have been no changes to the normal management of patients with respiratory disease.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We have designed a study protocol with 80% power to detect a 75% ratio of geometric means between the intervention and usual care conditions, assuming a coefficient of variation equal to or less than 0.4.  This would require 40 participants to be randomly allocated into the intervention condition, and uptake ACP.  We expect that 50% of those offered ACP will uptake ACP, hence this requires 120 participants to be recruited with a 2:1 randomisation schedule favouring the intervention.  Hence a sample of 150 patients in each study setting will enable sufficient power to answer the primary research questions.

Data analysis to test the research hypotheses will be done on an intention to treat basis, with the metropolitan and rural samples being treated separately.  Covariates will be tested for balance between groups.  Data analysis techniques are chi squared (for categorical variables), t test (for numerical variables) and Kruskal Wallis for ordinal variables.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Albany Hospital - Albany</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Crawley</postcode>
    <postcode>6330 - Albany</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Rural Clinical School of WA, University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rural Clinical School of WA (Albany)
UWA Albany Centre
31 Stirling Terrace
Albany, WA
6330</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>State Health Research Advisory Committee</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>State Health Research Advisory Committee
Research Development Unit
Level 2, C Block
189 Royal Street
East Perth, WA
6004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital (Lung Institute of WA)
</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>B Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands, WA
6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>WA Cancer &amp; Palliative Care Network
</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>189 Royal Street
East Perth, WA
6004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to better understand the healthcare needs of people with severe lung disease.  In particular we will investigate whether 'advance care planning' (a process of discussion between patients, family/carers and health professionals, about values and goals for treatment) can result in increased patient satisfaction with care and/or a better match between preferred and actual medical treatments. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 2 A Block
Hospital Ave
Nedlands
WA, 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2013-173</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Craig Sinclair</name>
      <address>Rural Clinical School of WA
UWA Albany Centre
31 Stirling Terrace
Albany, WA, 6330</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9842 0829</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9842 0879</fax>
      <email>craig.sinclair@rcswa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Craig Sinclair</name>
      <address>Rural Clinical School of WA
UWA Albany Centre
31 Stirling Terrace
Albany, WA, 6330</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9842 0829</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9842 0879</fax>
      <email>craig.sinclair@rcswa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Craig Sinclair</name>
      <address>Rural Clinical School of WA
UWA Albany Centre
31 Stirling Terrace
Albany, WA, 6330</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9842 0829</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9842 0879</fax>
      <email>craig.sinclair@rcswa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Craig Sinclair</name>
      <address>Rural Clinical School of WA
UWA Albany Centre
31 Stirling Terrace
Albany, WA, 6330</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9842 0829</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9842 0879</fax>
      <email>craig.sinclair@rcswa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>