<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366829">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001147673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Smoke-Free Recovery from trauma surgery: A pilot trial of an online smoking cessation programme for trauma surgery patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot trial of an online smoking cessation program investigating uptake and usage of an online smoking cessation programme.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1159-9492</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SFR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tobacco smoking cessation among orthopaedic trauma patients requiring surgical intervention </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in will receive access to an online tailored smoking cessation program to help them quit smoking whilst they are in hospital and after discharge. Duration of participant enrolment will be up to two month post discharge from hospital. The program will provide easily accessible, interactive, tailored smoking cessation information and support in hospital without over-burdening the hospital staff. This smoking cessation intervention can be continued at home, with the individuals able to navigate freely through the program. The program will feature a low reading age, graphics and visuals where possible and will be available to participants indefinitely. 
The program will be structured with seven modules to guide participants through the quit smoking process. These modules will include barriers to smoking cessation, tips on how to quit and stay quit as well as information on how to overcome relapse. The program will also feature interactive games, information about stop smoking medication, a discussion forum and a section for the individuals to track their progress. Participant will be able to access the program for the duration of their study enrolment, as the program is designed to be as close as possible to a real world interactive website which is available 24 hours a day on the internet. 
Participants will have the opportunity to use the intervention program multiple times during their hospital stay, accessing it either on their own internet enabled device or on one of the study iPads. After the participants are discharged from hospital, they will continue to access the online program using their own internet enabled devices. 
The program content will incorporate behaviour change techniques, tailoring and motivational interviewing to increase likelihood of effectiveness.
Participants will be followed up with one month after hospital discharge to determine their thoughts and rates of usage of the programme. Phone interviews will be conducted with participants lasting approximately five minutes 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator group used. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported programme usage during and after hospital admission. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: At least one week after discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported smoking status- patient self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: At least one week after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Receipt of smoking cessation care during hospital admission- patient self-report at follow-up call. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: At least one week after discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibility criteria:
1. aged 18- 80 years old
2. Smokes tobacco cigarettes
3. Can read English
4. Has recently been admitted to the John Hunter or Liverpool Hospital for a fracture requiring surgery</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals will be excluded from participating in this study if the individual is an elective surgical patient.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A two step recruitment process was used.
Step 1: Consent to health behaviour survey 
A Research Assistant (RA) on the ward will approach all fractures patients to complete an online health behaviours survey. Results from this survey will indicate to the RA that the individual may be eligible to take part in the study. 
Step 2: Consent to Smoke-Free Recovery trial
The RA will screen individuals for eligibility using a Case Report Form which lists the eligibility and ineligibility criteria for Smoke-Free Recovery. If an individual is deemed eligible by the RA, they will be given the Participant Information Statement outlining the requirements of the study and a Consent Form which will need to be signed and returned before they are able to participate. Individuals will be given up to 72 hours (3 days) after their initial admission to hospital to return a signed Consent Form and complete the baseline survey. 
Individuals will be allowed to use the iPad to access the online program at their own free will whilst in hospital.
Participants are contacted at least one week after discharge for a follow-up telephone call. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation was removed during study recruitment due to difficulties finding eligible individuals. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>No sub-group analysis was conducted. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis:
From the results of follow-up phone calls, qualitative analysis will be used to determine themes based on rates of usage, changes in tobacco smoking and receipt of smoking cessation care following hospital discharge. A full statistical analysis plan will be developed at a later date. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>22/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>710</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>31</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital Royal Newcastle Centre - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Dr, Callaghan NSW 2308
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Partnership</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Postal address: 
National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hunter New England Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lookout Rd, New Lambton NSW 2305</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>South West Sydney Local Area Health </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Eastern Campus Of Liverpool Hospital/Elizabeth St, Liverpool NSW 2170</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Smoke-Free Recovery from trauma surgery is a trial taking place at the John Hunter and Liverpool Hospital, NSW. The study will investigate the uptake and usage of an online smoking cessation programme following an orthopaedic trauma. 
Smoke-Free Recovery will be developed to provide help for patients recovery from orthopaedic trauma surgery while successfully quitting smoking. The program will be specifically tailored to the individuals smoking profile and will provide information about the effects of smoking on their specific wound recovery.
This study aims to determine if it is feasible to provide patients with an online smoking cessation programme to promote smoking cessation during and following hospitalisation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Health Human Research Ethic Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lookout Rd, New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/HNE/46</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Billie Bonevski</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
1 University Drive
Callaghan 
NSW 2308
</address>
      <phone>+612 40335710</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Billie.Bonevski@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sam McCrabb</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
1 University Drive
Callaghan 
NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>61240335713</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.mccrabb@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sam McCrabb</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
1 University Drive
Callaghan 
NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61240335713</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sam.mccrabb@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>