<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1360">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/08/2003</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2003</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000518561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Transfer of preterm infants from incubator to open cot at a lower body weight (1600g) versus a higher body weight (1800g)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of transferring preterm infants born less than 1600g, from incubator to open cot at lower (1600g) versus higher (1800g) body weight to determine the effects on weight gain, temperature stability and length of hospital stay</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TIC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Perinatal Trials Registry: PTR427</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Premature infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>intervention group- will remain in the incubator until the weight reaches greater than or equal to 1600 grams at which time they will be transferred to and nursed in an open cot until discharge</interventions>
    <comparator>control group- will remain in the incubator until the weight reaches greater than or equal to 1800 grams at which time they will be transferred to and nursed in an open cot until discharge</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infants temperature stability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at one hour post transfer to an open cot and then third hourly for the first 72 hours and then eighth hourly until discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average daily weight gain over the first 14 days following transfer to an open cot.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the first 14 days following transfer to an open cot</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of infants requiring an overhead heater for temperature maintenance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at one hour post transfer to an open cot then third hourly for the first 72 hours and then eighth hourly until discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of infants requiring to be returned to an incubator for temperature maintenance.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at one hour post transfer to an open cot then third hourly for the first 72 hours and then eighth hourly until discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to discharge from Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital and referral hospital (from time of group allocation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured as date of discharge from the Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Age at discharge home</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured as gestational age in weeks and days at the time of discharge from a hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight at discharge home</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured as weight in grams at the time of discharge home from a hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Preterm infants, both male and female, with a birthweight of less than 1600 grams - weight &lt;1600 grams at enrolment- &gt;=48 hours age,- &gt;= 48 hours without requiring assisted ventilation or Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP)- medically stable- receiving enteral calorie intake of at least 60 mls/kg/day, and- at least one parent who can understand written or spoken English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Requiring assisted ventilation or CPAP,- medically unstable,- oxygen via cot or sub nasal prongs,- major congenital abnormality.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>An independent statistician managed sequence generation, using a computer generated random number sequence. Stratified allocation by birth weight (BW) (&lt;1000g or &gt;=1000g) and gestational age (GA) at birth (&lt;34 weeks or &gt;=34 weeks) have been used. Therefore each preterm infant will belong to one of the four following strata: &lt;1000g and &lt;34 weeks; &gt;=1000g and &lt;34 weeks; &lt;1000g and &gt;=34 weeks; &gt;=1000g and &lt;34 weeks and will be randomly allocated to the control vs intervention group within each stratum.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/06/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/07/2003</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2005</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>13/02/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>182</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Division of neonatology, Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Butterfield Street
Herston Q 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Division of neonatology, Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Butterfield Street
Herston Q 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One of the key criteria for discharging preterm infants from nurseries is their ability to maintain their temperature once transferred from an incubator to an open cot. This practice varies widely between neonatal units; however it seems that a weight mark of 1800g is preferred, which appears to be based on tradition or the personal experience of clinicians, as the scientific evidence of when and at what weight this should occur is limited. By delaying transition to an open cot on the basis that the infant has not reached a certain weight may result in longer hospitalisation than necessary, thus increasing cost of care and prolonging parental separation resulting in parental anxiety. However, transferring infants too soon may also result in extended hospitalisation and again add to cost of care. This study will determine the effects of transferring preterm infants from incubators to open cots at a lower weight of 1600 grams on the outcomes of temperature stability, weight gain and length of hospital stay.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>New K, Flenady V, Davies MW. Transfer of preterm infants from incubator to open cot at lower versus higher body weight. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 2012, Issue 9. Art. No.: CD004214. DOI: 10.1002/14651858.CD004214.pub2. 
New K, Flint A, Bogossian F, East C, Davies MW (2012). Transferring preterm infants from incubators to open cots at 1600 g: a multicentre randomised controlled trial. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed 97, F88-92.
New K, Bogossian F, East C, Flint A, Davies M (2010). Transferring preterm infants from incubators to open cots at 1600 g: a multicentre randomised controlled trial. 7th International Neonatal Nurses Conference, Durban, South Africa, 26 October.
New K, Bogossian, East C, Davies MW (2012). Does early transfer from isolette to open cot decrease length of stay for premature neonates? 21st Annual RBWH Healthcare Symposium, Brisbane, QLD, 11 October.
New K, Bogossian F, East C, Davies MW (2010). The effect of nursing premature infants in open cots on weight gain and rate of growth. Australian College of Neonatal Nurses Annual National Conference, Canberra, ACT, 21 May.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/04/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2003/001</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Redcliffe &amp; Caboolture Hospitals</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/11/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>04/Dec/05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Toowoomba Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/05/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>042/2004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen New</name>
      <address>UQ School of Nursing, Midwifery and Social Work 
Room 337, Level 3, Chamberlain Building, The University of Queensland QLD 4072
</address>
      <phone>+61733467041</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36365259</fax>
      <email>k.new@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen New</name>
      <address>UQ School of Nursing, Midwifery and Social Work 
Room 337, Level 3, Chamberlain Building, The University of Queensland QLD 4072
</address>
      <phone>+61733467041</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36365259</fax>
      <email>k.new@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen New</name>
      <address>UQ School of Nursing, Midwifery and Social Work 
Room 337, Level 3, Chamberlain Building, The University of Queensland QLD 4072
</address>
      <phone>+61733467041</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.new@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>