<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362278">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000387820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of a 'Brief Behavioural Activation' Programme on Treatment Adherence for Chronic Pain Management.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Additional Effects of a Brief Behavioural Activation Programme on Treatment Adherence for People Undergoing the STEPS and PUMP programmes for Chronic Pain Management.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1129-3255</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Brief Behavioural Activation:
A structured 12 week programme in which participants receive positive consequences for healthy behaviours/activities.  This increases the likelihood that these behaviours will reoccur in the future. The programme works at increasing the behaviours/activities someone does that result in a positive consequence so the person is more likely to be involved in that behaviour/activity again. It includes goal setting, activity monitoring (24 hr monitoring) and activity scheduling. Involves a 1 hour weekly appointment to recieve instructions for goal seeting, activity monitoring and activity scheduling and to complete outcome measures. The Brief Behavioural Activation programme is administered in one-to-one, face-to-face appointments with a student psychologist, under the supervision of a registered psychologist. 
 
Self-Training Educative Pain Sessions (STEPS) Programme:
An 8 hour course (4 hours on a tuesday 9-1pm and 4 hours on a thursday 9-1pm) provided by the Pain Medine Unit at Fremantle Hospital, giving patients with chronic pain a broad overview of options, current research, knowledge and skills for the management of persistent pain. Participants are offered the PUMP programme and it is up to them if they choose to attend the PUMP programme. 

Pain Understanding and Management Programme (PUMP):
An intensive four week (Every morning from 9-1pm for a four week period) multidisciplinary pain management programmeme provided by the Pain Medicine Unit at Fremantle Hospital, designed to improve patients physical function and coping capacity when dealing with ongoing pain. Participants must complete the STEPS programme before attending the PUMP programme. Only participants who participate in the PUMP programme will be recieving the Brief Behavioural Activation programme. Participants who recieve the Brief Behavioural Activation programme will begin at the same time as starting the PUMP programme. Their appointment for the Brief Behavioural Activation will occur after the PUMP programme, so participants dont have to make an extra trip.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual (No Brief Behavioural Activation, just STEPS and PUMP)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and duration of increases in activities engaged (including treatment adherence). This is assessed through obtaining information on a patient 24 hour daily diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, during treatment (weekly), end of treatment and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in  Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS) scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, during treatment (weekly), end of treatment and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be over 18 years of age, speak and understand English fluently, agree to have Brief Behavioural Activation Programme sessions audio recorded for assessment of treatment integrity, have a diagnosis of chronic pain,  have been given individually specialised treatment instructions from medical practitioners ( e.g. medication, physiotherapy, psychology appointments, exercise; treatment adherence will vary between participants), be willing to communicate treatment instructions, not be receiving standardised treatment from other health professionals regarding treatment adherence and do not have any other diagnosed medical conditions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under 18 years of age. Do not speak or understand english fluently. Do not agree to have sessions audio taped for treatment integrity. Do not have a diagnosis of Chronic Pain. Do not have treatment instructions. Are receiving a standardised treatment for treatment adherence.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After attending the STEPS programme, participants who are selected for the PUMP programme are allocated to either just the PUMP programme or PUMP + Brief Behavioural Activation programmes.

Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software - through Excel.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>South Street campus
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch
Western Australia 6150</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>South Street campus
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch
Western Australia 6150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Pain Medicine Unit, Fremantle Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dalgety Street,
East Fremantle,
WA
6158</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to:
1. Investigate the effects of adding a Brief Behavioural Activation Programme to the STEPS (Self-Training Educative Pain Sessions) and PUMP (Pain Understanding and Management Programme) programmes for patients with chronic pain. 
2. Investigate the effects of adding a Brief Behavioural Activation Programme to the STEPS and PUMP programme on patients adherence to their own particular treatment instructions. 
3. Identifying the effects of STEPS and PUMP programmes in combination. It is hoped that this research will provide an opportunity to work collaboratively with patients with the ultimate aim of establishing improved self-management strategies for patients coping with pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jacqueline Le Mesurier</name>
      <address>South Street campus
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch
Western Australia 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 0420939109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.LeMesurier@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jacqueline Le Mesurier</name>
      <address>South Street campus
Murdoch University
90 South Street
Murdoch
Western Australia 6150</address>
      <phone>+61 0420939109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.LeMesurier@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>