<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364802">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001080718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 2, Randomized, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the
Safety and Efficacy of GS-4774 for the Treatment of
Virally-Suppressed Subjects with Chronic Hepatitis B</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 2, Randomized, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of GS-4774 for the Treatment of Virally-Suppressed Subjects with Chronic Hepatitis B</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1147-8339 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Virally-Suppressed Subjects with Chronic Hepatitis B</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment Arm A: 25 subjects continue Oral Antiviral alone
Treatment Arm B: 50 subjects OAV + GS-4774 2 YU (Yeast Units)subcutaneous injection every four weeks for 6 doses
Treatment Arm C: 50 subjects OAV + GS-4774 10 YU
subcutaneous injection every four weeks for 6 doses
Treatment Arm D: 50 subjects OAV + GS-4774 40 YU
subcutaneous injection every four weeks for 6 doses
a) the dose of GS-4774 administered is GS 4774 2YU (Yeast Units) or 10YU or 40YU or Oral antiviral alone
b) Administered every 4 weeks for 6 doses
c) Mode of administration, Oral antirvial and GS 4774 subcutaneous injection
d) We will be collecting patient reported adherence to OAV at each study visit on the Electronic Data Base.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment Arm A is the control Group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of GS-4774 in subjects
with chronic hepatitis B infection (CHB)
We will assess safety parameters including adverse events, laboratory changes, serious adverse events as well as discontinuations of study drug due to AEs to help determine the safety and tolerability of the GS-4774 treatments.
Injection site reactions comprised the majority of adverse events seen in the Phase 1 study of GS-4774 in healthy volunteers.  These reactions included pain, warmth, erythema, swelling or induration over the injection site.  Over 99% of these injection site reactions were mild and all resolved with only two requiring treatment (one requiring ice, the other paracetamol).    Headache, seen in 27% of subjects, was the only other adverse event seen in &gt;10% of subjects.   
</outcome>
      <timepoint>We are collecting safety data for the entirety of the study that we will reviewat safety and tolerability until Week 48 in the first instance</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the efficacy of GS-4774 at week 24 as measured by
the change from Baseline in serum Hepatitis B surface Antigen
(HBsAg) (log10 IU/mL) titers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.To evaluate the rates of HBsAg loss and seroconversion at Weeks 24 and 48
Evaluated with serum tests of presence of HBsAg and HBsAb</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Weeks 24 and 48
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. To evaluate the rates of HBeAg loss and seroconversion at Weeks 24 and 48
Evaluated with serum tests of presence of HBeAg and HBeAb
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 24 and 48
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3.To evaluate the change in log10 IU/mL serum HBsAg from Baseline to Weeks 12 and 48
Evaluated with serum tests of quantitative HBsAg levels (Abbott Architect Assay)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Weeks 12 and 48
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4.To evaluate the proportion of subjects with a 1-log decline in HBsAg at Weeks 12, 24 and 48
Evaluated with serum tests of quantitative HBsAg levels (Abbott Architect Assay)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 12, 24 and
48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Documented evidence of chronic HBV infection (e.g., HBsAg positive for more than
6 months)
2. Virally-suppressed (screening HBV DNA &lt;29 IU/mL) with HBV DNA below the lower
limit of quantification 
3. Ability to understand and sign a writtent informed consent form, which must be obtained prior to initiation of study procedures
4. Currently taking an HBV oral antiviral medication

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Cirrhosis 
2. Co-infection with HCV, HIV or HDV
3. Evidence of hepatocellular carcinoma (e.g., as evidenced by recent imaging)
4. Significant cardiovascular, pulmonary, or neurological disease
5. Received solid organ or bone marrow transplant
6. Received prolonged therapy with immunomodulators (e.g., corticosteroids) or biologics
(e.g., monoclonal Ab, interferon) within 3 months of screening
7. Use of another investigational agents within 3 months of screening
8. Current alcohol or substance abuse judged by the investigator to potentially interfere with
subject compliance
9. Receipt of immunoglobulin or other blood products within 3 months of screening
10. Known hypersensitivity to study drug, metabolites or formulation excipients
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>It is the responsibility of the investigator to ensure that subjects are eligible to participate in
the study prior to enrollment. Each study candidate must sign an Informed Consent Form
prior to the conduct of any screening procedures, in accordance with regulatory and local
Ethics Committee requirements. Once consent has been obtained, all screening tests and
procedures have been completed, and study eligibility has been confirmed, subjects will be
randomized using an Interactive Voice Randomisation System (IVRS) or Interactive Web Randomisation System (IWRS). </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomization will be performed via an Interactive Voice Response System (IVRS) or
Interactive Web Response System (IWRS)
Randomization list was generated by the IWRS vendor (Bracket).  
The vendor’s statistician prepared a randomization program in SAS.  A dummy list was also generated using a random seed.  A Gilead’s statistician reviewed the program and the output for accuracy.  The vendor’s statistician then generated the final list using a different seed than the seed used in the dummy list.  This is a stratified randomization using a randomization table created by computer software (SAS).  Treatments were randomly assigned .  Two stratification factors were employed:  HBeAg status (Positive vs Negative) and HBsAg level (&gt; 1000 IU/mL vs &lt;= 1000 IU/mL).  </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis will be performed when the last subject
reaches Week 24. The analysis will compare the OAV only arm to
the OAV + 2 YU GS-4774 arm, the OAV + 10 YU GS-4774 arm
and the OAV + 40YU GS-4774 arm, respectively.
With respect to the primary efficacy endpoint, the change from Baseline to Week 24 in HBsAg (log10Iu/ml), a sample size of 25 in the OAV only arm and 50 in an OAV=GS-4774 arm will have at least 80% power to detect a difference of 0.15 log 10 HBsAg (IU/ml) between the OAV only arm and each of the OAV+GS-4774 arm. This sample size calculation assumes a change from Baseline to week 24 in the OAV only arm of -0.12 log 10IU/ml, with a common standard deviation of 0.179 log10 IU/ml, and an alpha level of 0.016 (adjusting for 3 test arms). These assumptions were derived from studies GS-US-174-0102 and GS-US-174-0103.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>175</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gilead Sciences, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gilead Sciences, Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>PRA: Pharmaceutical Research Associates</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Suite 1701, Central Square, 323 Castlereagh St
Sydney N.S.W. Australia 2000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>GS-4774 is an experimental (investigational) vaccine being tested as a possible treatment of chronic Hepatitis B and is not yet approved by the United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA). GS-4774 has been designed to stimulate your immune system, the system that your body uses to defend itself from infections. GS-4774 is produced from bakers yeast which has been changed to include the substance found in the Hepatitis B virus. This yeast has been heat inactivated and you will not be receiving live yeast. Studies in healthy subjects have shown that GS-4774 stimulated the immune system to help block the spread of Hepatitis B virus. 

The purpose of this study is to determine how well your body tolerates GS-4774 and how it affects the HBV infection in your body in addition to the oral antiviral treatment regimen you are currently receiving.  The study is for research purposes only and is not intended or expected to cure any medical conditions. As this is a research study,      GS-4774 will only be given to you during your participation of the trial. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Not applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Not applicable</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Chesapeake Research Review, Inc.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>7063 Columbia Gateway Drive, Suite 110
Columbia, MD 21046
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Edward Gane</name>
      <address>Auckland Clinical Studies
3 Ferncroft Street
Ground Floor ECOM Building
Grafton
AUCKLAND 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9307 4949</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 3479</fax>
      <email>edgane@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Allison Fidelholtz</name>
      <address>Clinical Program Manager, Clinical Operations
Gilead Sciences, Inc.  
333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</address>
      <phone>+1 650-577-6585</phone>
      <fax>+1 650-524-9418</fax>
      <email>Allison.Fidelholtz@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anuj Gaggar, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Associate Director, Clinical Research, Medical Monitor
Gilead Sciences, Inc.  
333 Lakeside Drive
Foster City, CA 94404</address>
      <phone>+1  650-358-1090 </phone>
      <fax>+1  650-524-9272</fax>
      <email>Anuj.Gaggar@gilead.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anne Howard</name>
      <address>Pharmaceutical Research Associates
Suite 1701, Central Square
323 Castelreagh Stree, Sydney NSW 2000</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9289 8574</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9289 8501</fax>
      <email>HowardAnne@praintl.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>