<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370321">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000762459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised comparison of AMBU (Registered Trademark) AuraGainTM &amp; LMA Supreme TM in patients undergoing laparoscopic surgery under general anaesthesia. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised comparison of AMBU(Registered Trademark) AuraGainTM &amp; LMA Supreme TM in patients undergoing laparoscopic surgery under general anaesthesia. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>difficult airway</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Use of the AMBU AuraGain laryngeal mask in patients undergoing laparoscopic surgery under general anaesthesia

The AMBU AuraGain laryngeal mask is a new phthalate-free, laryngeal mask device launched in June 2014. Both devices are similar in their fundamental design ie. anatomically curved airway tube, single-use disposable product, with a built-in gastric access port where an orogastric catheter can be inserted to suck out gastric contents and secretions, thereby enhancing patient safety when they undergo positive pressure ventilation. Laryngeal mask airways are inserted routinely for short surgeries as a means to maintain a patent airway to allow the patient to remain ventilated and oxygenated by an anaesthetic ventilator during surgery.

Insertion of device will be performed by 1 specialist anaesthetists (Principal Investigators) and 2 senior anaesthesia residents with at least 3 years experience, and at least 10 LMA Supreme &amp; 10 AuraGain insertions in patients with normal airways before trial commencement; supervised by the Principal Investigator. 

A maximum of 3 attempts at insertion of the laryngeal mask device is allowed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Use of the control device LMA Supreme in patients undergoing laparoscopic surgery under general anaesthesia

 Laryngeal mask airways are inserted routinely for short surgeries as a means to maintain a patent airway to allow the patient to remain ventilated and oxygenated by an anaesthetic ventilator during surgery. The Supreme laryngeal mask (control device) is made of PVC and is similar to the AuraGain laryngeal mask (intervention device) in their fundamental design. The AuraGain has a further advantage of direct intubating capability, and may be suitable as a rescue device in a difficult airway situation. Inherent differences in materials may affect performance characteristics. 

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>oropharyngeal leak pressure (OLP)
The oropharyngeal leak pressure is measured by closing the Adjustable Pressure Limiting valve of the circle system (of the anaesthesia machine) at a fixed gas flow of 3 L/min in manual ventilation mode. The oropharyngeal leak pressure is the pressure in the circuit when an audible noise was heard over the mouth. For safety concerns, the maximal allowable oropharyngeal leak pressure was 40cmH2O and auscultation over epigastrium is done at the same time to rule out air leak into stomach during measurement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After succesful LMA insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of attempts at device insertion

Each attempt is defined as the re-insertion of the laryngeal mask device into the mouth. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During device insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to successful device placement 

from insertion of airway device into mouth till presence of 1st end-tidal CO2 tracing on capnography</outcome>
      <timepoint>from insertion of airway device into mouth till presence of 1st end-tidal CO2 tracing on capnography</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective ease of device insertion on a 5 point scale

5 point scale: Easy, Fair, Difficult, Very Difficult, Impossible</outcome>
      <timepoint>During LMA insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Additional manoeuvres required for insertion
(adjustment of head and neck position, jaw thrust, change of device size, change of depth insertion) will be recorded in our data collection sheet</outcome>
      <timepoint>During LMA insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of insertion of lubricated NG tube on a 3 point scale: easy, difficult, impossible</outcome>
      <timepoint>During NG tube insertion through the LMA device</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak inspiratory pressure (PIP) as measured by the spirometry analyser in the anaesthesia machine</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the entire surgical procedure at fixed intervals, i.e. before pneumoperitoneum creation, after pneumoperitoneum creation and then at 30 minutes interval thereafter</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leak volume, defined as the difference between inspiratory and expiratory volume, as measured by the spirometry analyser in the anaesthesia machine</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the entire surgical procedure at fixed intervals, i.e. before pneumoperitoneum creation, after pneumoperitoneum creation and then at 30 minutes interval thereafter</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cuff pressure measured with a cuff pressure gauge (VBM Medizintechnik GmbH, Germany).</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured after device insertion, and then during the entire surgical procedure at fixed intervals i.e. before pneumoperitoneum creation, after pneumoperitoneum creation and then at 30 minutes interval thereafter</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intra-abdominal pressure as measured by the CO2 insufflation machine used by the surgical team for laparoscopic surgery. Ths machine measures and displays the intra-abdominal pressure achieved.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the entire duration of pneumoperitoneum maintanence, measured at regular intervals, i.e. before pneumoperitoneum creation, after pneumoperitoneum creation and then at 30 minutes interval thereafter.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative hemodynamic parameters of Heart rate as analysed by ECG module of the anaesthesia monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured every minute from induction of general anaesthesia, up till 3 minutes after successful LMA placement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>intraoperative Complication of desaturation below 95% as analysed by the pulse oximetry of the anaesthesia monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured during LMA insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>non-invasive blood pressure monitoring as analysed by non-inviasve blood pressure module of the anaesthesia monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured every minute from induction of general anaesthesia, up till 3 minutes after successful LMA placement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>oxygen saturation as measured by pulse oximetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured every minute from induction of general anaesthesia, up till 3 minutes after successful LMA placement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>intraoperative complication of bronchospasm as evident by upsloping of the capnography, high peak airway pressure and presence of rhonchi upon auscultation of lungs</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured during and immediately after LMA insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>intraoperative complication of aspiration/gross regurgitation as evident by the presence of gastric fluid in the gastric and/or airway port of the laryngeal mask device</outcome>
      <timepoint>observed during LMA insertion and throughout surgical procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>oral cavity injury upon visual inspection by anaesthesiologist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured after LMA insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>intraoperative complication of gastric distension as reported by the surgeons during laparoscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>during laparoscopic surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>blood on laryngeal mask device after removal as evident by the presence of blood upon examining the device after removal, observed by the anaesthetists</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured after surgery and after removal of laryngeal mask device</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>postoperative sorethroat self-reported by patients when questioned by the nurses in the recovery unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured postop in recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>postoperative dysphonia self-reported by patients when questioned by the nurses in the recovery unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured postop in recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>postoperative dysphagia (difficulty in swallowing) self-reported by patients when questioned by the nurses in the recovery unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured postop in recovery unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status Class I-III
2. between age 21 to 80, 
3. who require general anaesthesia for laparoscopic surgeries eg. cholecystectomy, inguinal herniorraphy..</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients of age  less than 21 or more than 80 years old, 
2. BMI more than 35 kg/m2 or body weight less than 30kg, 
3. patients with a predicted difficult airway (based on history of difficult airway, inter-incisor distance less than 20mm, cervical spine pathology, modified Mallampati class 4, thyromental distance less than 60mm), 
4. where laryngeal mask devices are contraindicated: high risk of regurgitation or aspiration (GERD, hiatus hernia), respiratory tract pathology e.g. restrictive lung disease/active upper respiratory tract infection, 
5. patients who decline to participate in the study or are unable to give informed consent. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>computer-generated random number table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Teoh WH et al (Anaesthesia 2010) demonstrated that the mean oropharyngeal leak pressure with LMA Supreme was 26 +/- 5 cm H2O. 
A difference of 10% in mean OLP between AG &amp; LS is likely to be clinically relevant. Using a desired power of 80% and two-sided significance level of 5%, a sample size of 59 patients in each group (total of 118 patients) is estimated to be adequate for each supraglottic device(Stata v13.1). We will therefore recruit 60 per group to account for drop-outs. 

Continuous variables will be presented as mean (standard deviation) or median (interquartile range) after assessing normality. Categorical variables will be summarised using frequency (percentage). Depending on the normality of continuous outcome variables, independent students t-test or Mann-Whitney U test will be conducted to compare means or medians between two groups. The chi-square test or Fishers exact test will be used for comparison of categorical variables when appropriate. General linear model for repeated measures will be used for analysis of hemodynamic variables.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Singapore</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Tan Tock Seng Hospital
11 Jalan Tan Tock Seng
Singapore 308433</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Singapore</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>11 Jalan Tan Tock Seng
Singapore 308433</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Singapore</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Supraglottic airway devices are useful in situations where the expected time of surgery &amp; general anaesthesia is short &amp; are effective yet easy to insert. The AuraGain resembles the LMA Supreme in terms of anatomical curvature &amp; availability of gastric access; and also allows passage of a tracheal tube which is not possible in a LMA Supreme, thus increasing its utility as a disposable supraglottic device with added functionality. The AMBU AuraGain may be useful as an alternative to the LMA Supreme as a disposable supraglottic device, and coupled with its intubating capability, may be suitable as a rescue device in a difficult airway situation. The study's null hypothesis is the the AuraGain is as efficacious and the LMA Supreme in paralysed patients receiving controlled ventilation. We aim to recruit and randomise 118 patients between 21-80 years old, of ASA status I to III to receive either the AuraGain or the LMA Supreme during general anaesthesia with controlled ventilation for laparoscopic procedures. The primary outcome of the study is oropharyngeal leak pressure, and secondary outcomes include success of device insertion, time to successful device placement, leak volume, peak inspiratory pressure and complications. Risks to participants are related that of general anaesthesia and LMA insertion, such as dental trauma, post-operative nausea and vomiting and sorethroat. Such side effects are very mild in severity and of short duration (less than 1 day). Rare adverse effects include regurgitation and aspiration. Upon completion, the study investigators can better advise local institutions if the AMBU AuraGain can be considered as an alternative airway device, especially for controlled ventilation. If the AuraGain (AMBU, Singapore) is shown to be similar or better in efficacy over the LMA Supreme, it may be useful as an alternative to the LMA Supreme in laparoscopic surgeries, with the added advantage of use as a rescue device in a difficult airway situation allowing direct intubation through the AuraGain via a flexible scope</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Domain Specific Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Domain Specific Review Board (DSRB)
c/o National Healthcare Group, Research &amp; Development Office (RDO)
Nexus @One-North (South Tower), No. 3 Fusionopolis Link, #03-08, Singapore 138543</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/00989</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Singapore</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370321-NHG DSRB Ref 2015 00989 Approval Letter.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zhang Jinbin</name>
      <address>Tan Tock Seng Hospital
11 Jalan Tan Tock Seng
Singapore 308433</address>
      <phone>+6596542881</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jinbin_zhang@ttsh.com.sg</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zhang Jinbin</name>
      <address>Tan Tock Seng Hospital
11 Jalan Tan Tock Seng
Singapore 308433</address>
      <phone>+6596542881</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jinbin_zhang@ttsh.com.sg</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zhang Jinbin</name>
      <address>Tan Tock Seng Hospital
11 Jalan Tan Tock Seng
Singapore 308433</address>
      <phone>+6596542881</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jinbin_zhang@ttsh.com.sg</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zhang Jinbin</name>
      <address>Tan Tock Seng Hospital
11 Jalan Tan Tock Seng
Singapore 308433</address>
      <phone>+6596542881</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jinbin_zhang@ttsh.com.sg</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>