<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83347">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000172202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Equivalency of two concentrations of fentanyl administered by the intranasal route for acute analgesia in children in a paediatric emergency department</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Equivalency of two concentrations of fentanyl administered by the intranasal route for acute analgesia in children in a paediatric emergency department</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>acute pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Fentanyl is an opiate analgeisa used for relief of strong pain. Total dosage for both groups is the same; ie 1.5 mics/kg, however the concentration for the intervention group will be 50micrograms/ml and for the control group will be 300micrograms/ml. The dose will be administered and then repeated according to effect after 10minutes. If requied may have 2-3 doses during study period. Study period is 30 minutes after which time child's care will be taken over by usual medical and nursing staff. Administration of fentnayl takes seconds. Observation time is 30 minutes. Drug is administered intranasally</interventions>
    <comparator>Intranasal Fentanyl (INF) will be administered 2-3 times as required - in general most patients will need only one dose (from previous studies). The drug will be admisnitered as soon as possible after arrival in the Emergency Department (ED) - after baseline observations and consent has been obtained. Participant's pain will be reassessed after 10 minutes and additional drugs admisnitered if necessary. An active drug is being given to all patients - the control group being the highly concetrated fentnayl (300micrograms/ml) have treatment for the same time as the standrard concentration (50micrograms/m). Observations and pain scores will be recorded prior to first administration of intranasal fentanyl (INF) and at 10, 20 and 30 minutes post administration. The fentanyl will be adminstered intranasally.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This study aims to illustrate the comparative effectiveness of a standard concentration intranasal fentanyl (INF) to the gold standard of highly concentrated INF. If equivalency can be proven, then standard solution can be recommended for intranasal use. This will reduce the cost of using INF for analgesia as standard concentration fentanyl is cheaper and more available than the highly concentrated fentanyl.
Outcome measurement is pain scores at 10,20,30 minutes</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 10, 20 and 30 minutes post administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any significant side effects (such as nausea, sedation, swelling, vomiting, itch and other) will be documented on the data collection sheet by the attending nurse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 minutes post administration of first dose of intranasal fentanyl (INF)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children aged 3 to 15 years presenting to the emergency department with clinically deformed closed long bone fractures would be included.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Administration of an opiate analgesic (excluding codeine) within 4 hours of arrival in ED, Head injury resulting in impaired judgement, Known allergies to opiate analgesics, Significantly blocked or traumatised nose preventing nasal administration, Inability to perform pain scoring, Compound fracture</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation via a sealed envelope in the study pack.</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will be stratified into block according to age and then randomised according to simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by a computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children (PMH)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Roberts Road
Subiaco, Perth
Western Australia 
Australia 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Fentanyl is a pain-relieving agent that is commonly used to provide short term analgesia for painful procedures. This study aims to compare the effectiveness of two concentrations of intranasal fentanyl (INF) in children aged between 3 and 15 years presenting to the Emergency Department with clinically fractured long bones (arms or legs). These patients will be given either a highly concentrated solution or a standard concentration. Their pain scores and other observations will be recorded before they are given INF and at 10, 20 and 30 minutes after.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>PMH Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Roberts Road
Subiaco, Perth
Western Australia 
Australia 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Meredith Borland</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital 
Emergency Department
GPO Box D184
Perth WA 6840</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93408222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meredith.borland@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Meredith Borland</name>
      <address>PMH ED
GPO Box D184
Perth WA 6840</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93408222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meredith.borland@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Meredith Borland</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital 
Emergency Department
GPO Box D184
Perth WA 6840</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93408222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meredith.borland@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>