<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372176">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000111370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Influence of the Disease Label 'Polycystic Ovary Syndrome' on Intention to have an Ultrasound and Psychosocial Outcomes: A Randomised Online Study in Young Women 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Influence of the Disease Label 'Polycystic Ovary Syndrome' on Intention to have an Ultrasound and Psychosocial Outcomes: A Randomised Online Study in Young Women 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The effect of the disease label 'Polycystic Ovary Syndrome'</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is delivered online and takes approximately 15-30 minutes to complete.

Time 1 intervention: Hypothetical scenarios are used to test the impact of the disease label 'polycystic ovary syndrome' on outcome measures. The text scenarios are presented online using Qualtrics survey software. 

Intervention materials: A hypothetical scenario of a doctors visit- Participants are asked to imagine that for the past six months they have had unusually irregular periods, a few more pimples than usual and an increase of body hair in certain areas, so they visit their general practitioner to see if this is of any concern. 

Disease label intervention: In the intervention group, the doctor provides the disease label polycystic ovary syndrome for the symptoms described. The control group receives no disease label (symptoms are just described as an hormonal imbalance)
Information about ultrasounds variable: the doctor briefly mentions that ultrasounds are unreliable in clarifying a diagnosis or identifying the cause of absent periods vs. the doctor mentions no information about ultrasound unreliability. 

Participants are randomised to receive one of four hypothetical scenarios, where the disease label provided and information about ultrasounds given is varied: 
1)	PCOS disease label + no information about ultrasound reliability
2)	No disease label + no information about ultrasound reliability
3)	PCOS disease label + information about ultrasound reliability
4)	No disease label + information about ultrasound reliability

Time 2 intervention: Second hypothetical scenario highlighting issue of overdiagnosis of PCOS.
After completing the outcome measures after viewing the first hypothetical scenario, all participants are presented with another scenario asking them to imagine they get a second opinion. In this second scenario, the new doctor says: I believe your symptoms are often overdiagnosed as polycystic ovary syndrome. Because of the increased sensitivity of ultrasounds, screening can lead to finding abnormalities that are not harmful or unusual, resulting in unnecessary stress, anxiety and medication. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group is provided the same explanation and summary of associated risks in the hypothetical scenario of a doctor's visit, but does not receive a specific disease label for their hypothetical condition, the doctor instead referring to the condition as a hormonal imbalance throughout the scenario. The words 'polycystic ovary syndrome' are never mentioned prior to post-intervention measures or during the hypothetical scenario. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intention to have an ultrasound: a single item on a 10-point scale assessing hypothetical intention to have an ultrasound, adapted from previous research (Fisher et al., 2012) (1=Definitely will not to 10=Definitely will).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-esteem, measured using the validated Rosenberg self-esteem scale (Strongly disagree to Strongly agree) (Rosenberg, 1965). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Negative affect, measured using the validated Positive and Negative affect schedule (PANAS) questionnaire, which consists of 20 items that each describe a mood, measured on a 5-point scale (Very slightly or not at all to Extremely) (Watson et al., 1988).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1.  
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived severity of the (hypothetical) diagnosis: 
The validated Perceived Severity Scale, which measured 5 items on a 5-point scale (Strongly disagree to Strongly agree) (Bish, 2000). 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intention to have an ultrasound, after information about overdiagnosis is presented, measured by a single item on a 10-point scale, adapted from previous research (Fisher et al., 2012) (1=Definitely will not to 10=Definitely will).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured immediately after participants are presented with the second hypothetical scenario, where a second doctor mentions the possibility of overdiagnosis of PCOS at Time 2.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived seriousness was measured using a single item on a 7-point scale (Strongly disagree to Strongly agree) (Courneya, 2001).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1.

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived seriousness of diagnosis, after information about overdiagnosis is presented, measured using a single item on a 7-point scale (Strongly disagree to Strongly agree).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured immediately after participants are presented with the second hypothetical scenario, where a second doctor mentions the possibility of overdiagnosis of PCOS at Time 2.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Credibility of the doctor, measured using the validated five item Credibility Index, measured on a 5-point scale (Longman et al., 2012, Meyer, 1988).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interest in obtaining a second opinion: One item on a 7-point scale.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response efficacy of having the ultrasound: 4 items on a 7-point scale, adapted from previous research (Courneya &amp; Hellsten)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response costs of having the ultrasound (4 items on a 7-point scale; Courneya &amp; Hellsten, 2001).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after participants have read their respective hypothetical scenarios of the doctors visit at Time 1.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female and fluent in written English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Male and not fluent in written English. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants were sent an email link to access the Qualtrics survey by the researcher. The link directed participants to complete the online consent form. After completing the consent form participants were then randomised to one of the four hypothetical scenarios using Qualtrics survey software. The recruiting researcher was unaware of which condition participants would be randomised to, as randomisation occurred after participants had clicked on the link to complete the online intervention. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using Qualtrics survey software. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) version 22.0 was used, with an alpha level of .05 set for all statistical tests. A power analysis using Cohen's d formula was conducted, and results indicated a sample size of N = 160 was sufficient to detect a medium effect size (f=.30) with power at .95 and significance level of .05. However, to be able to detect effects in the secondary outcomes it is worthwhile recruiting more participants. 

To control for previous experience of the syndrome and its associated symptoms, a composite variable was computed by combining a personal diagnosis and/ or a family history of PCOS to include as a covariate in further analyses. Prior to analyses, data was examined for missing values, outliers and accuracy, and to establish homogeneity of variance. A few outliers were identified, however, as they had no effect on results, they were retained to provide a complete report of the data.

To analyse the effect of the disease label and ultrasound reliability information on participants intention and psychosocial outcomes, six 2 (disease label: PCOS versus no label) x2 (ultrasound reliability: unreliable versus no information) between-participant analyses of covariance (ANCOVAS), were conducted, controlling for previous history of PCOS (personal diagnosis and/or family history). Two 2x2x(2) mixed-design ANCOVAS were also conducted to investigate the impact of the two experimental factors on intention and perceived severity after overdiagnosis information was presented. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>204</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/08/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2006 - The University Of Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Public Health, University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Program Grant 633003</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street, Canberra City ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Widening diagnostic criteria and improved imaging sensitivity have increased the number of reproductive-aged women diagnosed with PCOS from 4-8% to up to 21%. Given the increase in prevalence, the uncertain clinical benefit of knowing this diagnosis needs to be weighed against the potential for poor psychological outcomes in women labelled with PCOS. The purpose of this experimental study was to investigate the impact of the disease label PCOS on interest in medical interventions and on psychosocial outcomes. 
181 young women were randomised online to receive one of four hypothetical scenarios of a doctors visit in a 2 (PCOS disease label vs. no disease label) x 2 (information about unreliability of ultrasounds in clarifying diagnosis vs. no information) design. Participants were university students (mean age: 19.4). After presenting the scenario, intention to have an ultrasound, negative affect, self-esteem, perceived severity of condition, credibility of the doctor, interest in a second opinion and response efficacy and costs of having the ultrasound were measured. Participants were then presented with a second scenario, where the possibility of PCOS overdiagnosis was mentioned. Change in intention and perceived severity were then assessed.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office 
Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/335</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jesse Jansen</name>
      <address>226a Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 5178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jesse.jansen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jesse Jansen</name>
      <address>226a Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 5178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jesse.jansen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jesse Jansen</name>
      <address>226a Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 5178</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jesse.jansen@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tessa Copp </name>
      <address>127A Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9351 3137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tcop6073@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>