<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367950">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000216516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An audit of the impact of a change in the blood glucose targets protocol on intensive care mortality for diabetic patients admitted to the intensive care unit</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An audit of the impact of a change in the blood glucose targets protocol on intensive care mortality for diabetic patients admitted to the intensive care unit</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>From March 2015 to March 2017 adult patients admitted to the intensive care unit with a medical history of having diabetes will have their blood glucose level target as being between 10.0 to 14.0 mmol per litre.</interventions>
    <comparator>For the 14-month period preceeding the introduction of the change in the blood glucose target protocol for diabetic patients. The target blood glucose level for both non-diabetic and diabetic patients in the intenisve care was clinician preference. </comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality - intensive care</outcome>
      <timepoint>Survival status of diabetic patients at the time of their discharge from the intensive care unit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality - hospital</outcome>
      <timepoint>Survival status of diabetic patients at the time of their discharge from the hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of intensive care unit admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of days the patient is admitted to the intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of hospital admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of days the patient is admitted to the hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mechanical ventilation - intensive care unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration in hours of mechanical ventilation received by each patient while admitted to the intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute kidney injury - intensive care unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Development of acute kidney injury as defined by the Risk, Injury Failure, Loss of function, End-stage renal disease (RIFLE) or Kidney Disease Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) criteria while the patient is admitted hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Delirium - requiring anti-psychotic medication - intensive care unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patient requirement for anti-psychotic medication while admitted to the intensive care unit </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum troponin levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely reported for the duration of the patients admission to hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypoglycaemic event - mild (blood glucose equal to or greater than 4.0 to &lt; 6.0 mmol/L) for both assessment periods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of hypoglycaemic events - mild - occuring in the intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypoglycaemic event - moderate (blood glucose &gt;2.3 to less than or equal to 3.9 mmol/L) for both assessment periods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of hypoglycaemic events - moderate -  event occurring in the intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypoglycaemic event - severe (blood glucose equal to or less than 2.2 mmol/L)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Number of hypoglycaemic events - severe - occuring in the intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean blood glucose concentrations in mmol/L - all diabetic patients admitted to the intensive care unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>24-month period following the introduction of the protocol change of blood glucose target.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum ketone levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely reported for the duration of the patient's admission to the intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum C-peptide levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely reported for the duration of the patient's admission to the intensive care unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin administration assessed via medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely documented for the duration of the patient's admission to the intensive care unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Empagliflozin administration assessed via medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely recorded for the duration of the patient's admission to hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anti-delirium medicine (e.g. quetiapine, haloperidol, demedetomidine, clonidine) administration assessed via medical record review</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely recorded for the duration of hte patient's admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Microbiology positive result from all of the following together, blood culture sample, trachael aspirate via an endotrachael tube, urinary sample obtained from an indwelling urinary catheter, cerebrospinal fluid sample and pleural effusion drainage sample assessed via medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely recorded for the duration of the patients' admission to hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of episodes of "relative hypoglycemia" defined as a blood glucose level 30% below the patient's premorbid estimated average glucose concentration determined via analysis of the blood glucose results via medical record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily as routinely reported for the duration of the patient's admission to hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patients admitted to the intensive care unit with a medical diagnosis of diabetes</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Convenience sampling</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>With 350 patients in each group We have a&gt;95% power to see an increase in glucose levels of 2mmmol/L with liberal glucose control, assuming a control (before) level of 9 mmol/L with a standard deviation of 5 mmol/L at an alpha of 0.05.

Baseline comparisons will be performed using Fishers exact tests and reported as n (%). Continuous normally distributed variables will be compared using Student t-tests and reported as means (standard deviation), while non-normally distributed data will be compared using Wilcoxon rank-sum tests and reported as medians [interquartile range]. Changes over time will be determined using repeated measures mixed linear modeling with each patient treated as a random effect, and therapy group, time and the interaction of therapy group and time as effect fixed effects. All analysis will be performed by using SPSS version 19.0 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL, USA).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>700</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>350</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Rinaldo Bellomo
Director, Intensive Care Research</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people with type-1 and type-2 diabetes develop critical illness, which inevitably leads to deterioration in glycaemic control.  However, most critically ill patients with hyperglycaemia are not diabetic, but develop disordered glucose metabolism that normalises once the acute illness resolves  so-called critical-illness induced hyperglycaemia (CIIH).  While a number of studies have evaluated the effects of modulating glycaemia, using insulin, on outcomes in the critically ill, a major limitation of these studies, given recent information, is that critically ill patients with hyperglycaemia have been considered a homogenous cohort, rather than classifying hyperglycaemia in the critically ill according to pre-morbid glycaemia or presence of diabetes.

Recent data indicate that a paradigm shift is required, and that patients with CIIH should be considered separately to those critically ill patients known to have diabetes, particularly those patients with chronic hyperglycaemia, or poorly controlled diabetes.  Given these data (and that it intuitively makes sense) the medical staff at Austin Hospital Intensive Care Unit believe we should be personalising blood glucose targets and that, in diabetic patients, the target glucose level in ICU should simulate the sort of glycemic levels these patients are likely to commonly experience in their daily lives, especially during situations of physiological stress (between 10-14 mmol/L).  Such target glucose level would also be expected to prevent any episodes of even mild hypoglycaemia, which have been associated with increased risk of death.

However, allowing slightly increased blood glucose concentrations in critically ill patients known to have diabetes is a slight change from current practice, and evidence to support this change, although logical and strong, is from observational studies only. 

Accordingly, we wish to collect data after the implementation of the new protocol to audit the effects of glycaemia on outcomes and ensure that this protocol proves safe and does indeed prevent hypoglycemic episodes as expected.

This audit represents a formal assessment of a quality improvement initiative dedicated at increasing the quality of glycaemic care in critically ill diabetic patients.


</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LNR/14/Austin/487</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367950-LNR14Austin487(full approval)5's LNRR application single site - APPROVED after changes template v2 July 2014.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367950(v25-08-2016-14-44-44)-LNR14Austin487(full approval)5's LNRR application single site - APPROVED after changes template v2 July 2014.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367950-20160817 LETTER LNR14Austin487 Ethics Amendment Approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367950-20170512 LETTER LNR14Austin487 Ethics Amendment Approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road 
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road 
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>glenn.eastwood@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road 
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road 
Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>glenn.eastwood@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>