<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368668">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001380583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Brain Computer Interface (BCI) driven Paired Associative Stimulation (PAS) protocol: A rehabilitation intervention for people with stroke.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Brain Computer Interface (BCI) driven Paired Associative Stimulation (PAS) protocol: An investigation of the effects of a 4-week BCI-PAS intervention on cortical excitability and walking performance in people with stroke.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The BCI-PAS intervention will be delivered three times per week for 4 weeks. 

In the first session of each week, electroencephalography (EEG) will be recorded using an electrode cap, while subjects perform active ankle dorsiflexion of their affected leg, in time with a visual cue. The EEG is then analysed and the peak negativity of the movement related cortical potential (MRCP) is determined. This timing is then used to inform the timing of the BCI-PAS intervention for that week. 

The BCI-PAS is delivered three times each week for 4 weeks, by a trained Research Assistant. During each intervention session, the subject completes 50 repetitions of cued active ankle dorsiflexion of the affected leg. During each repetition of ankle dorsiflexion, a single pulse of electrical stimulation (pulse width 1ms) is delivered to the deep branch of the common peroneal nerve at the intensity required to produce a palpable twitch in the tibialis anterior tendon. Each pulse of electrical stimulation is timed to arrive in the motor cortex at the point of peak negativity of the MRCP. The BCI-PAS intervention takes approximately 15 minutes, with additional time required for setting up the electrical stimulation. </interventions>
    <comparator>BCI-PAS will be delivered three times per week for four weeks, with a lower intensity of electrical stimulation than that used in the intervention group. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Corticomotor excitability using Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 days post completion of the 4-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3D gait analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days post completion of the 4-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking speed (6m walk test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days post completion of the 4-week intervention.
12 days post completion of the 4-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic balance assessed using the Step test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days post completion of the 4-week intervention.
12 days post completion of the 4-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum voluntary contraction of the ankle dorsiflexors. Measured with force plate. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 days post completion of the 4-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interviews to determine acceptability of the intervention to people with stroke.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety monitored by recording any medical/physical changes at the beginning of each session, and any changes during the session. Unrelated events such as illness will be recorded and may result in a session being missed. Possible related events include superficial skin irritation related to electrode placement, or transient effects associated with transcranial magnetic stimulation such as headache, discomfort, hearing changes, or syncope. Risk of seizure related to transcranial magnetic stimulation is considered very low, and subjects at increased risk of seizure are excluded from the study during screening processes. Any adverse events requiring the participant to seek medical attention from a health professional will be recorded on an adverse events form. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the beginning and during each session, throughout the duration of the study. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence monitored by register of attendance at sessions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the duration of the study. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stroke with hemiparesis affecting ability to walk. 
&gt;6 months post stroke. 
Gait speed 0.05-1.2m/s.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant cognitive, perceptual or communication deficits.
Presence of another medical condition that may impact the results. 
Contra-indications to Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each subject is screened for inclusion in the study. After providing informed written consent at their first session, subjects are randomly allocated via a computer-generated randomisation plan which is held by a third party. </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence was generated using https://www.random.org/</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Unbiased variance estimates for all outcomes will be produced under identity and log transformation. The sample size should enable reasonably precise estimates of variance in functional outcomes that will be primary outcome candidates for a future trial. 

An ANCOVA model will be used to estimate the effect of BCI-PAS on cortical excitability and functional outcomes, adjusting for baseline values. If necessary, logarithmic transformations will be applied to improve the normality of the data. As a pilot, this study will not be powered to detect statistically significant differences between intervention and control groups with high power at a low significance level.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>6</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>7/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Physiotherapy New Zealand</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 27 386, Wellington 6141, New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neurological Foundation of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 110022, Auckland City Hospital, Auckland 1148
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Auckland University of Technology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Private Bag 92006
Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Aalborg University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>P.O. Box 159
DK - 9100 Aalborg
Denmark</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Denmark</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to explore the feasibility of the BCI-PAS protocol as an intervention to improve walking performance in people with stroke. This pilot randomised controlled trial will investigate the effect of a 4-week BCI-PAS intervention on cortical excitability and walking performance. The study will provide estimates of variance and effect size for measures of physical function, which will be used to inform a large randomised controlled trial powered for changes in clinical outcomes. Other issues of feasibility will be addressed including safety, adherence and acceptability of the intervention to people with stroke.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Auckland University of Technology Ethics Committee (AUTEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Wellesley Street East, Auckland 1010.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Denise Taylor</name>
      <address>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University, Private Bag 92006, 
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9680</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>denise.taylor@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nada Signal</name>
      <address>Health &amp; Rehabilitation Research Institute, School of Rehabilitation and Occupation Studies, AUT University, Private Bag 92006, Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999 x7062</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nada.signal@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Denise Taylor</name>
      <address>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University, Private Bag 92006, 
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9680</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>denise.taylor@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sharon Olsen</name>
      <address>C/o Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University, Private Bag 92006, Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>solsen@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>