<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362966">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000729729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MiYoga: Mindfulness Yoga for Children with Cerebral Palsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>MiYoga: A Randomised Controlled Trial of a Mindfulness Yoga Program for enhancing sustained attention in Children with Cerebral Palsy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MiYoga</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will use a randomised waitlist control design.  

Participants in both groups will receive the Mindfulness Yoga (MiYoga) intervention which aims to teach both children and parent/guardians mindfulness skills (ability to focus attention on the present moment without judgement).  Through mindfulness practices, this MiYoga aims to enhance attention, physical and behavioural outcomes in children with cerebral palsy while at the same time aiming to improve parent's psychological flexibility, parent-child relationship and reduce stress.  This program will be conducted as a group program with 5-8 child-parent diads per group. 6 group sessions running for 90 minutes each will be offered once weekly for six weeks, with an additional 20 minutes daily home practice with a MiYoga DVD in between group sessions.  The total length of the program is 25+ hours (including 20 minutes daily home practice) over 8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>The treatment group will be compared to a wait-list control group, who will receive the MiYoga intervention once the treatment group has completed their intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sustained attention: Conners Continuous Performance Test (CPT; Conners, 2000)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child and Adolescent Mindfulness Measure (CAMM; Greco, Baer &amp; Smith, 2011)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mindfulness Attention Awareness Scale (MASS; Brown and Ryan 2003) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symbol Search from the WISC-IV (Wechsler, 2004). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Digit Span Backward from the WISC-IV (Wechsler, 2004) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trail Making Test (D-KEFS; Delis et al., 2001) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Colour-Word Interference (D-KEFS; Delis et al., 2001)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sit and reach test (reach distance)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lateral Step-up (Verschuren et al., 2008)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Half kneel to stand (Verschuren et al., 2008)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6-minute walk test (6MWT) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CP QOL-Child (Waters et al., 2006)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MobQues47</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function (BRIEF; Gioia et al., 2000)  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptance and Action Questionnaire (AAQ-II, Bond et al., 2011) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS) (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal Wellbeing Index  Adult (PWI-A; International Wellbeing Group, 2006) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ChildParent Relationship Scale (CPRS; Driscoll &amp; Pianta, 2001) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention and follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants are children (aged between 8 and 16 at the point of recruitment) with a diagnosis of CP with spastic motor type, diplegia motor distribution and a GMFCS I-III.  Children must also have sufficient co-operation and cognitive understanding to follow simple instructions.  The primary caregiver of eligible children will participate alongside their child.  Children with comorbid diagnoses to CP are included. 

Diagnosis of CP must be confirmed by the treating paediatrician or clinician and in accordance with published recommendations.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children will be excluded if they have (i) received upper-limb or lower-limb surgery in the previous 6 months; (ii) unstable epilepsy (i.e. frequent seizures not controlled by medication); (iii) spinal instability or other spinal problems that would prevent them from participating safely in the MiYoga program; (iv) have a medical condition that would prevent them from participating safely in the MiYoga program; or (v) parents/guardians who are pregnant as a safety precaution.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A waitlist randomised control trial, where Children with mild to moderate CP are randomised via a computergenerated random number table to either receive MiYoga immediately or be waitlisted for a 8 week period and then commence MiYoga. Allocations will be placed in concealed envelopes, held and opened after initial baseline measurement to either
Immediate intervention group or the delayed intervention group (waitlist control).</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomization sequence will be computer-generated.  Treatment allocations will be recorded on pieces of paper, which will be folded and placed inside sealed, numbered, opaque envelopes by a staff member not involved in the study.  Envelopes will be opened by the study coordinator in order as each participant returns their questionnaires. Given the nature of the study, no parties will be blinded to group assignment. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Waitlist Control</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>It was documented that the reaction time of children with CP was two standard deviations below healthy controls on the Continuous Performance Test (CPT) (Lemay et al., 2012). This study is interested in detecting a difference of one standard deviation between the treatment and control group at Time 2 (post-intervention) to determine the clinical significance of the MiYoga program. Based on Lehr's equation with alpha set at 0.05 and power set at 0.80, to detect a difference of one standard deviation between groups, a sample size of 16 participants per group would be needed (Lehr, 1992). If a retention rate of 90% is assumed, a total of 36 children will need to be recruited. 

Analysis will follow standard principles for RCTs, using two-group comparisons on all participants on an intention-to-treat basis. External and internal validity of results will be checked using baseline and general descriptive information available for all eligible families; comparing the characteristics of families who completed the study with those who enrolled in the study but did not complete, and those who did not enroll. The primary comparison immediately post intervention (8 weeks) will be scores from the Continuous Performance Test.

Analysis will follow standard methods for randomised controlled trials using comparisons between the two groups (MiYoga and wait-list control). The protocol of intention-to-treat analysis will be followed in order to minimise inflation of treatment effects consistent with CONSORT guidelines. The experimental unit will be the child and their participating primary caregiver. Attrition analysis will be conducted. Data will be analysed using SPSS and Stata. 

The hypotheses relating to intervention efficacy will be tested using general linear models, specifically via ANCOVA. In addition, predictors of treatment outcome will be explored using regression analyses. In particular, which child or parent benefited from MiYoga. It is hypothesized that children with the most difficulties regulating their attention as measured on CPT, and WISC-IV and D-KEFS subtests and parents experiencing low levels of mindfulness as measured by the MAAS and high levels of psychological symptoms as measured on the DASS will benefit most from MiYoga. 

Non-parametric methods will be used for simple comparisons in cases where continuous data exhibit substantial skewness not overcome by transformation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>45</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>24/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland - School of Psychology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sir Fred Schonell Dr,  St Lucia, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sir Fred Schonell Dr,  St Lucia, QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland - School of Medicine, Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Herston Road, Herston, Brisbane, QLD 4029</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>MiYoga has the potential to assist children with CP, training them to focus their attention on the present moment so that they can fully focus on activities in school, in therapy or when interacting with peers.  At the same time, hatha yoga postures may provide additional physical benefits to complement the on-going therapy for children with CP. 

It is hypothesized that the MiYoga program will lead to improvement in the following child outcomes: 1) enhance sustained attention; 2) increase physical functioning  strength, balance and flexibility; 3) enhance present-moment awareness (mindfulness); 4) enhance in parent-reported child executive functioning in everyday life; and 5) decrease in parent-reported child behavioural and emotional problems; and 6) enhance parent-reported (if &lt;9 years old) or child self-reported (if &gt;9 years old) child quality of life.  In addition, it is predicted that there will be improvements in the following parent outcomes: 1) decrease parents stress levels; 2) enhance child-parent relationship; and 3) enhance parent's psychological flexibility.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://qcprrc.centre.uq.edu.au/miyoga-0</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children’s Health Queensland  Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
Lady Cilento Children's Hospital Precinct
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane  QLD  4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/QRCH/120</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/07/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Behavioural &amp; Social Sciences Ethical Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UQ Research and Innovation
Cumbrae Stewart Building (72)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012000993</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Catherine Mak</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre (QCPRRC)
Level 6, Centre for Childrens Health Research
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane, QLD 4101 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 73560</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.mak@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Catherine Mak</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre (QCPRRC)
Level 6, Centre for Childrens Health Research
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane, QLD 4101 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 73560</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.mak@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Catherine Mak</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre (QCPRRC)
Level 6, Centre for Childrens Health Research
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane, QLD 4101 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 73560</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.mak@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Catherine Mak</name>
      <address>Queensland Cerebral Palsy and Rehabilitation Research Centre (QCPRRC)
Level 6, Centre for Childrens Health Research
62 Graham Street, South Brisbane, QLD 4101 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3069 73560</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.mak@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>