<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368639">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000599572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>SMART CF - A smartphone application for reporting symptoms in adults with cystic fibrosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adults with cystic fibrosis, what is the effect of a smartphone application used to report symptoms versus usual care on exacerbations requiring intravenous antibiotics, healthcare utilisation, lung function, quality of life, anxiety and depression, nutritional status, medication adherence and absenteeism and presenteeism. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-6087 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>SMART CF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Smartphone application. Participants will use their own smartphone to answer 10 questions relating to their respiratory symptoms and 2 questions relating to their emotional wellbeing on a weekly basis (or sooner if they choose) for a 12 month period. Answers will be emailed securely to the CF team and contact will be made with the participant if the responses indicate a potential exacerbation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care. Participants will attend routine CF clinic visits, with the ability to contact the CF team at any time if an earlier review is required. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of exacerbations requiring intravenous antibiotics (IVABs). This will be collected from the participants medical record. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary timepoint will be 12 months (end of the intervention period). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of intravenous antibiotic days. This will be collected from the participants medical record. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary timepoint will be 12 months (end of the intervention period).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung Function measured via spirometry (according to ATS/ERS criteria)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months (from commencement of intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire - Revised</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months (from commencement of intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months (from commencement of intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutional status measured via body mass index</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months (from commencement of intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment Adherence Questionnaire - CF</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months (from commencement of intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absenteeism and Presenteeism</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months (from commencement of intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>System Usability measured via the System Usability Scale, and application data including frequency/day/time of use</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months (from commencement of intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time (in days from baseline) to first exacerbation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected from participants medical record at 12 months (from commencement of  intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>If lung function returned to baseline following each exacerbation requiring IVABs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected from participants medical record at 12 months (from commencement of  intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of hospital admissions and admission days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected from participants medical record at 12 months (from commencement of  intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of courses and days of oral and inhaled antibiotics. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected from participants medical record at 12 months (from commencement of  intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of CF clinic visits and clinical phone calls.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected from participants medical record at 12 months (from commencement of  intervention period).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost of antibiotic treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected from participants medical record at 12 months (from commencement of  intervention period), and verified with hospital phramacy and finance departments. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost of hospital admissions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected from participants medical record at 12 months (from commencement of  intervention period), and verified with hospital phramacy and finance departments. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of CF; aged 18 years or older; under the care of the Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital (SCGH) CF team; clinically stable at time of recruitment; exacerbation requiring IVABs in the preceding 12 months. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Lung transplantation or currently listed for lung transplantation; current pregnancy; inability to provide informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Individuals will be identified from those who are under the care of the SCGH CF team and meet the inclusion criteria. Individuals will be provided with the Participant Information Sheet and contacted 1 week later to determine whether or not they would like to participate. 

Partcipants will attend a baseline visit and the relevant outcome measures will be collected. They will then be randomised to either the smartphone application group or the control (usual care) group. The NHMRC randomisation system will be used in this trial. </concealment>
    <sequence>The NHMRC randomisation system will be used in this trial.  The randomisation sequence will be stratified according to gender and location (metropolitan or rural and remote), as well as use of ivacaftor.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Intention to treat analysis</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To investigate the difference in the number of IVAB courses between the two groups, assuming a within group standard deviation of 1.21 (based on IVAB usage at the SCGH CF centre during 2013 and 2014), a sample size of 23 in each group will be required to detect a difference of one exacerbation requiring IVABs per participant, with 80% power and a significance level of p &lt; 0.05. To account for any loss to follow up or drop out, we will recruit an additional seven individuals per group for a total sample size of 60. 

Between-group analysis will be performed using an independent t-test (parametric data) or Mann Whitney U test (non-parametric data). Within group changes in outcome measures collected at each visit will be assessed using one-way repeated measures analysis of variance (parametric data) or Friedmans test (non-parametric data). Time to first pulmonary exacerbation will be analysed using a KaplanMeier survival analysis. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hospital Avenue, Nedlands, WA, 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Research Advisory Committee</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hospital Avenue, Nedlands, WA, 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Curtin University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Kent Street, Bentley, Perth
Western Australia, 6102.
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Telemedicine, Burke Rehabilitation and Research Institute, Cornell University.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>785 Mamaroneck Ave, White Plains, NY 10605</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cystic fibrosis (CF) is the most common Caucasian genetic disease and has a reduced life expectancy of approximately 40 years of age. The decline in lung function in CF is accelerated by exacerbations. Severe exacerbations require treatment with intravenous antibiotics (IVABs), but of concern many do not regain the lung function they have lost following treatment. One of the major factors in this failure to regain lung function is the delay in time it takes for the individual with CF to present to the CF centre to report symptoms and commence treatment. 

In collaboration with Curtin University and the Burke Rehabilitation and Research Institute in New York, USA, we have developed a smartphone application that can be used by participants to report their symptoms to the CF team at Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital on a weekly basis or sooner if they feel they need to.  We will now aim to complete a 12 month randomised controlled trial in 60 participants, investigating the impact of using this smartphone application on the number of exacerbations requiring IVABs per participant, as well as other health outcomes and measures of healthcare utilisation.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hospital Avenue, Nedlands, WA, 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-030</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jamie Wood</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
A Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamie.wood@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jamie Wood</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
A Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamie.wood@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jamie Wood</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
A Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamie.wood@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jamie Wood</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
A Block
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands, WA, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamie.wood@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>