<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364019">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000416796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Wrist acupressure for post-operative nausea and vomiting: A feasibility study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Wrist acupressure for post-operative nausea and vomiting: a comparison of PC 6 acupoint stimulation versus placebo for reducing postoperative nausea and vomiting in cardiac surgery patients (WRAP Trial)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-7495</utrn>
    <trialacronym>WRAP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>post-operative nausea and vomiting in cardiac surgery patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The PC6 acupoint is the meridian point in the pericardium channel and located on the inner forearm between the extensor carpi radialis and palmaris longus tendons one sixth of the distance from PC7 on the medial wrist crease to PC 3 in the cubital fossa (WHO, 2008). Participants in the intervention group (acupressure wristband) will have the Seaband (Registered Trademark) wristbands applied to both wrists ensuring the bead stimulates the Neiguan (PC 6) after establishment of IV access and invasive monitoring in the operating theatre. The wristbands will be covered with opaque bandaging to ensure blinding. The wristbands will be removed at 36 hours from admission time to ICU after final outcome measurement.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the placebo (sham) wristband group will have a sham (without bead) Seaband (Registered Trademark) wristbands applied to both wrists at the position of the Neiguan (PC6) acupoint after establishment of IV access and invasive monitoring in the operating theatre. The wristbands will be covered with opaque bandaging to ensure blinding. The wristbands will be removed at 36 hours from admission time to ICU after final outcome measurement.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the feasibility of launching a full-scale multisite efficacy trial, using pre-defined feasibility criteria for recruitment, retention, protocol fidelity and use the pilot data to refine the protocol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome assessed when the whole trial is completed, that is when the last participant has completed the final nausea and vomiting outcomes measures at 36 hours and the morning of day 3 Quality of Recovery outcome measure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients in the acupressure group will experience less nausea and vomiting postoperatively compared with patients in the sham group. This will be assessed 6 hours from arrival to the ICU, at 8 hours post arrival, 4 hourly up to 24 hours and then at 36 hours on a bedside Case Report Form. Nausea will be assessed on a 10 point scale (0 = no nausea to 10 = severe nausea). For vomiting, all episodes of retching or vomiting in the 36 hour time period will be recorded on the bedside Case Report Form.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be assessed 6 hours from arrival to the ICU, at 8 hours post arrival, 4 hourly up to 24 hours and then at 36 hours. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Costs associated with PC 6 stimulation device, costs of antiemetic medication and hospital length of stay in the two groups will be assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The cost evaluation of the 2 groups will be assessed at the completion of the trial - ie, when the final participant has completed the last outcome measures for nausea and vomiting at 36 hours post-operatively and Quality of Recovery at day 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients in the acupressure group will have a greater quality of recovery at morning of day 3 than patients in the sham group. Participants will self assess the quality of the recovery on the morning of the 3rd postoperative day using a 15 item questionnaire (QOR15; Stark et al., in press).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Morning of day 3 post-operative.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore the different treatment arms in relation to dose effect at 8, 24 and 36 hours post application of the wristbands.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be assessed at the completion of the trial when the last participant has completed all nausea and vomiting outcome measures to 36 hours post-operatively.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore the different treatment arms in relation to the effect on severe nausea</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be assessed at the completion of the trial when the last participant has completed all post-operative nausea and vomiting outcome measures to 36 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore the different arms in relation to the need for rescue drug therapy. Participants need for rescue medication will be recorded on the bedside Case Report Form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be assessed at the completion of the trial when the last participant's need for rescue medication has bee recorded at 36 hours post-operative. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Elective and urgent primary cardiac surgery (CABG; valve and double valve replacement; CABG + single valve replacement 
- Able to understand, speak, read and write  English
- Over 18 years of age and able to give informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Add in wrist circumference&gt;21cm.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Computer generated allocation provided by independent automated service at the Griffith University Clinical Trials Coordination Centre (CTCC). Allocation is concealed until the patient is randomised</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Placebo device will be used</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data analysis will be conducted using Stata/SPSS. The Intention To Treat (ITT) principle will be used for all analyses. Descriptive statistics will be reported using appropriate measures of spread and locations to answer the feasibility questions. Differences between study groups of incidence of nausea and vomiting, measured regularly over the first 36 hours, will be analysed using repeated measures logistic regression with either generalized linear models (GenLin) or generalized estimating equations (GEE). Potential confounders (mixed effects) will be identified and differences adjusted for within the models. Nausea severity will use repeated measures general linear models (GLM), whilst other nontemporal outcomes (e.g., usage of rescue therapy and quality of recovery) will use multivariate logistic regression and linear regression models. Due to the sample size (N = 80 - 100), statistical significance is not expected to be found, yet general trends will provide preliminary data to provide support for a large scale RCT. For all statistical comparisons, a significance level of p=0.05 will be employed.). The aim is to establish protocol fidelity and data will be recorded at each assessment of nausea regarding whether wristbands are correctly positioned; and data will be collected in relation to patients lost to follow up and missing data. The feasibility of placing the wristbands on patients after establishment of IV access and invasive monitoring in the operating theatre will be established through interviews with staff.

As sample size of 40 per group (n = 80 in total) has been determined. As this is a feasibility study the sample size was based on Hertzog's (Considerations in Determining
Sample Size for Pilot Studies, Research in Nursing &amp; Health, 2008, 31, 180191) estimations for efficacy studies that argues that a sample size of 40 per group will  provide appropriate power for a pilot study.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>80</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Nathan Campus, 170 Kessels Road, Nathan QLD 4111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Griffith University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nathan Campus, 170 Kessels Road, Nathan QLD 4111</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rode Road, Chermside, Brisbane, QLD, 4032</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Post-operative nausea and vomiting (PONV) are unwanted complications following anaesthesia and surgery. The occurrence of PONV ranges from 20% to 80%, despite optimal pharmacologic interventions. The burden of caring for patients post cardiac surgery in healthcare system world-wide is immense. In 2009-2010, In Australia alone, over 230,000 cardiac procedures were performed, and the number and rate of cardiac procedures are increasing. Similar to many countries world-wide, cardiovascular disease (CVD) remains the most expensive disease group in Australia, costing about $5.9 billion in 200405 with just over half of this money spent on patients admitted to hospital. As part of their illness treatment and recovery, cardiac surgery patients experience varying rates of PONV; studies across various populations have reported rates ranging from 22% to 50%. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>In press Journal article
Cooke M, et al. Wrist acupressure for post-operative nausea and vomiting (WrAP): A pilot study. Complement Ther Med (2015), http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ctim.2015.03.007</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rode Road, Chermside, Brisbane, QLD, 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Marie Cooke</name>
      <address>Griffith University 170 Kessels Road, Nathan Qld 4111</address>
      <phone>+61  37355253 </phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3735 3560</fax>
      <email>m.cooke@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Marie Cooke</name>
      <address>Griffith University  170 Kessels Road, Nathan Qld 4111</address>
      <phone>+61 7 37355253</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3735 3560</fax>
      <email>m.cooke@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Marie Cooke</name>
      <address>Griffith Universtiy 170 Kessels Road, Nathan QLD 4111</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3735 7985</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3735 3560</fax>
      <email>m.cooke@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>